<act><tid>1001891</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN COPPER CORPORATION (ACQUISITION OF UNDERTAKING) ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 58 OF <year>1972</year>
[ 21st September, <year>1972</year>.]

An Act to provide for the acquisition of the undertaking of the Indian 
Copper Corporation Limited for the purpose of enabling the Central 
Government to conserve and exploit, in a scientific and rational 
manner, to the maximum advantage of the nation, the copper deposits in 
the Singhbhum belt in the State of Bihar, to utilise the copper 
deposits in such manner as to subserve the common good, in the context 
to the requirements of cooper in the country, and for 
matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>92552</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Indian Copper 
Corporation (Acquisition of Undertaking) Act, <year>1972</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>387628</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to the policy of the State. It is hereby 
declared that this Act is for giving effect to the policy of the State 
towards securing the principles specified in clause (b) of article 39 
of the Constitution.
Explanation.-- In this section," State" has the same meaning as in 
article 12 of the Constitution.



</article>



<article><tid>249335</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definations. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>256439</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this 
Act:

</section>

<section><tid>1739067</tid>
<number>b</number>" company" means the Indian Copper Corporation Limited, 
being a company incorporated in England and having its 
principal place of business, in India, at Gillander 
House, Netaji Subhas Road, Calcutta- 1;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>230</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1588693</tid>
<number>c</number>" Hindustan Copper" means the Hindustan Copper Limited, 
being a Government company as defined in section 617 of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and having its 
registered office at Khetri Nagar in the State of 
Rajasthan;

</section>

<section><tid>389186</tid>
<number>d</number>" undertaking of the company" means the undertaking of 
the company in India.
CHAP

ACQUISITION OF THE UNDERTAKING OF THE INDIAN CORPORATION LIMITED

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION OF THE UNDERTAKING OF THE INDIAN COPPER CORPORATION 
LIMITED




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>995394</tid>
<number>4</number>Undertaking of the company to vest in Central Government. On 
the appointed day, the undertaking of the company shall, by virtue of 
this Act, stand transferred to, and vested in, the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>702839</tid>
<number> 5</number> General effect of vesting under section 4.
<section><tid>52546</tid>
<number>1</number>The undertaking  
of the company shall be deemed to include all assets, rights, 
leaseholds (including mining leases, if any); powers, authorities and 
privileges; and all property, movable and immovable, including lands, 
buildings, works, mines, workshops, projects, smelters, refineries, 
stores, instruments, machinery, locomotives, automobiles and other 
vehicles; mined or extracted copper and other ores, concentrates and 
metals, in process or in stock or in transit; cash balances, cash on 
hand, reserve fund, investments and book debts; and all other rights 
and interests arising out of such property as were immediately before 
the appointed day in the ownership, possession, power or control of 
the company in relation to its undertaking in India; and all books of 
account, registers, maps, plans, sections, drawings, records of survey 
and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto; and shall 
also be deemed to include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations 
of whatever kind then subsisting of the company in relation to its 
undertaking in India.

</section>

<section><tid>488512</tid>
<number>2</number>All property included as aforesaid in the undertaking of the 
company which has vested in the Central Government under section 4 
shall, by force of such vesting, be freed and discharged from any 
trusts, obligations, mortgages, charges, liens and other encumbrances 
affecting it, and any attachment, injunction or any decree or order of 
any court restricting the use of such property in any manner shall be 
deemed to have been withdrawn.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>231</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1110704</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, all 
contracts and working arrangements which are subsisting immediately 
before the appointed day and affecting the company shall, in so far as 
they relate to the undertaking of the company, cease to have effect or 
be enforceable against the company or any person who was surety, or 
had guaranteed the performance thereof, and shall be of as full force 
and effect against or in favour of the Central Government and 
enforceable as fully and effectually as if instead of the company, the 
Central Government had been named therein or had been a party thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>495069</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, any 
proceeding or cause of action pending or existing immediately before 
the appointed day by or against the company in relation to its 
undertaking in India may, as from such commencement, be continued and 
enforced by or against the Central Government as it might have been 
enforced by or against the company if this Act had not been passed, 
and shall cease to be enforceable by or against the company, its 
surety or guarantor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>172968</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power of Central Government to direct vesting of the 
undertaking in Hindustan Copper.
<section><tid>1617445</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in sections 4 and 5, the Central Government may, by order in 
writing, direct that the undertaking of the company together with all 
its properties, assets, liabilities and obligations specified in sub- 
section (1) of section 5 shall, instead of continuing to vest in the 
Central Government, vest in Hindustan Copper either on the date of 
publication of the direction or on such earlier or later date (not  
  being a date earlier than the appointed day) as may be specified in 
that direction.

</section>

<section><tid>1798708</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an order vesting the undertaking of the company in 
Hindustan Copper is made under sub- section (1), all the rights, 
liabilities and obligations of the Central Government in relation to 
the undertaking of the company shall, on and from the date of such 
vesting, be deemed to have become the rights, liabilities and 
obligations, respectively of Hindustan Copper.

</section>

<section><tid>770424</tid>
<number>3</number>Hindustan Copper shall, in the management and administration 
of the undertaking of the company, act in accordance with such 
directions, if any, as may be issued by the Central Government in this 
behalf.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>232</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>794915</tid>
<number>4</number>Hindustan Copper may also apply to the Central Government at 
any time for instructions as to the manner in which the management of 
the under taking of the company or in relation to any matter arising 
in the course of such management shall be conducted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1779421</tid>
<number> 7</number> Duty to deliver possession of property acquired and documents 
relating thereto.
<section><tid>450775</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any property has vested in the Central  
Government or Hindustan Copper under this Act, every person in whose 
possession or custody or under whose control the property may be, 
shall deliver the property to the Central Government or Hindustan 
Copper, as the case may be, forthwith.

</section>

<section><tid>1093264</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who, on the appointed day, has in his possession 
or under his control, any books, documents or other papers relating to 
the undertaking of the company, which have vested in the Central 
Government or Hindustan Copper under this Act and which belong to the 
company or would have so belonged if the undertaking of the company 
had not vested in the Central Government or Hindustan Copper, shall be 
liable to account for the said books, documents and papers to the 
Central Government or Hindustan Copper, as the case may be, and shall 
deliver them up to the Central Government or Hindustan Copper.

</section>

<section><tid>982247</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government or Hindustan Copper may take, or cause 
to be taken, all necessary steps for securing possession of all 
properties which have vested in that Government or Hindustan Copper 
under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>622567</tid>
<number> 8</number> Duty to furnish particulars. The company shall, within one 
month from the appointed day or such further period as the Central 
Government may allow in this behalf, furnish, in respect of the 
undertaking of the company, as on the appointed day, a complete 
inventory of--
<section><tid>1551933</tid>
<number>i</number>all the properties and assets;

</section>

<section><tid>670442</tid>
<number>ii</number>all the liabilities and obligations; and

</section>

<section><tid>303403</tid>
<number>iii</number>all agreements entered into by the company and in force 
on that day (including agreements, whether express or  
implied, relating to leave, pension, gratuity and other 
terms of service of any officer or other employee of 
  the company), under which, by virtue of this Act, the 
Central Government or Hindustan Copper has, or will 
have, or may have, liabilities or obligations,
and for this purpose, the Central Government or Hindustan Copper shall 
afford the company all reasonable facilities.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>233</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>334858</tid>
<number> 9</number> Transfer of service of existing employees.
<section><tid>233154</tid>
<number>1</number>Every officer  
or other employee employed, immediately before the appointed day, in 
connection with the affairs of the undertaking of the company, shall, 
as from that day, become an officer or other employee of the Central 
Government and shall, as from the date of publication of the direction 
made under sub- section (1) of section 6 or the date specified therein, 
become an officer or other employee of Hindustan Copper and shall hold 
his office by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the 
same terms and conditions and with the same rights and privileges as 
to pension, gratuity and other matters as he would have held under the 
company, if this Act had not been passed, and shall continue to do so, 
unless and until his employment in the Central Government or, as the 
case may be, in Hindustan Copper, is terminated or until his 
remuneration, terms and conditions are duly altered by the Central 
Government or Hindustan Copper:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply 
to any officer or other employee, who has, by notice in writing given 
to the Central Government within thirty days from the appointed day, 
intimated his intention of becoming an officer or other employee of 
the Central Government or Hindustan Copper.


</section>

<section><tid>808568</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law for the time being in 
force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other employee 
of the company to the Central Government or Hindustan Copper by reason 
of the provisions of this Act shall not entitle any such officer or 
other employee to any compensation under that Act or other law, and no 
such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other 
authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>309991</tid>
<number> 10</number> Provident, superannuation, welfare and other funds.
<section><tid>896710</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
the company has established a provident, superannuation, welfare or 
any other fund for the benefit of its officers or other employees and 
constituted a trust in respect thereof, the moneys relatable to the 
officers or other employees, whose services have become transferred, 
by or under this Act, to the Central Government or Hindustan Copper, 
shall, out of the moneys standing on the appointed day, to the credit 
of such provident, superannuation, welfare or other fund, stand 
transferred to, and vested in, the Central Government or Hindustan 
Copper, as the case may be, free from any such trust.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>234</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>331256</tid>
<number>2</number>The moneys which stand transferred under sub- section (1) to 
the Central Government or Hindustan Copper shall be dealt with by that 
Government or Hindustan Copper, as the case may be, in such manner as 
may be prescribed by rules made under this Act.
CHAP

PAYMENT OF AMOUNT

CHAPTER III

PAYMENT OF AMOUNT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>180482</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amount to be paid for transfer and vesting of the undertaking 
of the company.
<section><tid>1562485</tid>
<number>1</number>The company shall be given by the Central  
Government, in cash, an amount of rupees seven and a half crores, for 
vesting in it, under section 4, of the undertaking of the company.

</section>

<section><tid>179612</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount payable under sub- section (1) shall carry simple 
interest at the rate of four per cent. per annum from the appointed 
day.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1859341</tid>
<number> 12</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>378789</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person, who-- 

<subsection><tid>1824102</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control any 
property forming part of the undertaking of the 
company, wrongfully withholds such property from the 
Central Government or Hindustan Copper; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1093137</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of any property forming 
part of the undertaking of the company which has vested 
in the Central Government or Hindustan Copper under 
this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>674858</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Central 
Government or Hindustan Copper, as required by sub- 
section (2) of section 7, any document which may be in 
his possession, custody or control; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1076697</tid>
<number>d</number>wilfully fails to furnish an inventory as required under 
section 8; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>93953</tid>
<number>e</number>when required to furnish such inventory furnishes any 
particulars therein which are false and which he either

<pagefootnote><pagenum>235</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

knows or believes to be false, or does not believe to 
be true,

shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine, or with both:

Provided that the court trying any offence under clause (a) or 
clause (b) or clause (c) of this sub- section may, at the time of 
convicting the accused person, order him to deliver up or refund, 
within a time to be fixed by the court, any property or cash 
wrongfully withheld or obtained or any document wilfully withheld or 
not furnished.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1965155</tid>
<number>2</number>No court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under 
this section except with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government or of an officer authorised by that Government in this 
behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1070685</tid>
<number> 13</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1647805</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1538379</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1583457</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1366978</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>236</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>653759</tid>
<number>14</number>Receiver not to be appointed in relation to the business of 
the company. No proceeding for the appointment of a Receiver in 
respect of the business of the company in so far as it relates to its 
undertaking in India, shall lie in any court except with the consent 
of the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1273335</tid>
<number>15</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any law other than this Act or in any instrument having 
effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or in any decree or 
order of any court, tribunal or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>1990577</tid>
<number> 16</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>470417</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or Hindustan Copper or any of its officers or other 
employees for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>29720</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or Hindustan Copper or any of its officers or other 
employees for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>878621</tid>
<number> 17</number> Contracts in bad faith may be ceancelled or varied.
<section><tid>1147078</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
the Central Government is satisfied, after such inquiry as it may 
think fit, that any contract or agreement entered into at any time 
within twelve months immediately preceding the 10th day of March, 
<year>1972</year>, between the company or the managing agents of the company or any 
other person, in so far as such contract or agreement relates to the 
undertaking of the company, has been entered into in bad faith or is 
detrimental to the interests of the undertaking of the company, it may 
make an order cancelling or varying (either unconditionally or subject  
  to such conditions as it may think fit to impose) such contract or 
agreement and thereafter the contract or agreement shall have effect 
accordingly:
Provided that no contract or agreement shall be cancelled or 
varied except after giving to the parties to the contract or agreement 
reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>472699</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person aggrieved by an order under sub- section (1) may 
make an application to the High Court within the local limits of whose 
jurisdiction the principal place of business of the company in India 
is situated, for the variation or reversal of such order and thereupon 
such court may confirm, modify or reverse such order.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>237</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>953346</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power to make rule.
<section><tid>318890</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>486137</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1524348</tid>
<number>19</number>[ Repeal of Act 11 of <year>1972</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1978</year> (38 of <year>1978</year>), s. 2 and First Sch.

</article>



 </act>