<act><tid>1005016</tid>
<title>THE INTEREST ON DELAYED PAYMENTS TO SMALL SCALE AND 
ANCILLARYINDUSTRIAL UNDERTAKINGS ACT, <year>1993</year></title>

ACT NO. 32 OF <year>1993</year> 
[ 2nd April, <year>1993</year>.]
An Act to provide for and regulate the payment of interest on delayed 
payments to small scale and ancillary industrial undertakings and for 
matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-




<article><tid>491119</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>606614</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Interest on Delayed Payments to Small Scale and Ancillary 
Industrial Undertakings Act, <year>1993</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1143482</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>1401149</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 23rd day of 
September, <year>1992</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1331037</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1586917</tid>
<number>a</number>" ancillary industrial undertaking" has the meaning assigned to it 
by clause (aa) of section 3 of the Industries (Development and  
  Regulation) Act, <year>1951</year> (65 of <year>1951</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1009595</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the day following immediately after the 
expiry of the period of thirty days from the day of acceptance or the 
day of deemed acceptance of any goods or any services by a buyer from 
a supplier.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause,-


<subsection><tid>1156112</tid>
<number>i</number>" the day of acceptance" means,-

<subsubsection><tid>1238197</tid>
<number>a</number>the day of the actual delivery of goods or the rendering of 
services; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1117875</tid>
<number>b</number>where any objection is made in writing by the buyer regarding 
acceptance of goods or services within thirty days from the day of the 
delivery of goods or the rendering of services, the day on which such 
objection is removed by the supplier;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1477161</tid>
<number>ii</number>" the day of deemed acceptance" means, where no objection is made 
in writing by the buyer regarding acceptance of goods or services 
within thirty days from the day of the delivery of goods or the 
rendering of services, the day of the actual delivery of goods or the 
rendering of services;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1989696</tid>
<number>c</number>" buyer" means whoever buys any goods or receives any services from 
a supplier for consideration;

</section>

<section><tid>1319731</tid>
<number>d</number>" goods" means every kind of movable property other than actionable 
claims and money;

</section>

<section><tid>278891</tid>
<number>e</number>" small scale industrial undertaking" has the meaning assigned to 
it by clause (j) of section 3 of the Industries (Development and  
  Regulation) Act, <year>1951</year> (65 of <year>1951</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1254035</tid>
<number>f</number>" supplier" means an ancillary industrial undertaking or a small 
scale industrial undertaking holding a permanent registration 
certificate issued by the Directorate of Industries of a State <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or 
Union territory and includes,-

<subsection><tid>1570968</tid>
<number>i</number>the National Small Industries Corporation, being a company, 
registered under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>978710</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Small Industries Development Corporation of a State or a 
Union territory, by whatever name called, being a company registered 
under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>)].


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1342238</tid>
<number>3</number>Liability of buyer to make payment.- Where any supplier supplies 
any goods or renders any services to any buyer, the buyer shall make 
payment therefor on or before the date agreed upon between him and the 
supplier in writing or, where there is no agreement in this behalf, 
before the appointed day:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that in no case the period agreed upon between the 
supplier and the buyer in writing shall exceed one hundred and twenty 
days from the day of acceptance or the day of deemed acceptance.]


</article>



<article><tid>546282</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Date from which and rate at which interest is payable.- Where 
any buyer fails to make payment of the amount to the supplier, as 
required under section 3, the buyer shall, notwithstanding anything 
contained in any agreement between the buyer and the supplier or in 
any law for the time being in force, be liable to pay interest to the 
supplier on that amount from the appointed day or, as the case may be, 
from the date immediately following the date agreed upon, at one and 
half time of prime Lending Rate charged by the State Bank of India.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," Prime Lending Rate" 
means the Prime Lending Rate of the State Bank of India which is 
available to the best borrowers of the bank.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 23 of <year>1998</year>, s 2 for certain words. 
2. Ins. by s. 3, ibid. 
3. Subs. by s. 4, for s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1175070</tid>
<number>5</number>Liability of buyer to pay compound interest.- Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any agreement between a supplier and a buyer or 
in any law for the time being in force, the buyer shall be liable to 
pay compound interest (with monthly interests) at the rate mentioned 
in section 4 on the amount due to the supplier.

</article>



<article><tid>1062463</tid>
<number> 6</number> Recovery of amount due.- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>326306</tid>
<number>1</number>The amount due from a buyer,  
together with the amount of interest calculated in accordance with the 
provisions of sections 4 and 5, shall be recoverable by the supplier 
from the buyer by way of a suit or other proceeding under any law for 
the time being in force.]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[ (2) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), any 
party to a dispute may make a reference to the Industry Faciliation 
Council for acting as an arbitrator or conciliator in respect of the 
matters referred to in that sub- section and the provisions of the 
Arbitration and Conciliation Act, <year>1996</year> (26 of <year>1996</year>) shall apply to 
such dispute as if the arbitration or conciliation were pursuant to an 
arbitration agreement referred to in sub- section (1) of section 7 of 
that Act.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>445423</tid>
<number>7</number>Appeal.- No appeal against any decree, award or other order shall 
be entertained by any court or other authority unless the appellant 
 (not being a supplier) has deposited with it seventy- five per cent. 
of the amount in terms of the decree, award or, as the case may be, 
other order in the manner directed by such court or, as the case may 
be, such authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> S. 6 renumbered as sub- section (1) thereof by Act 23 of <year>1998</year>, s. 52. Ins. by s. 5, 
i


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>106187</tid>
<number>7A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Establishment of Industry Facilitation Council.- The State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish one 
or more Industry Facilitation Councils at such places exercising such 
jurisdiction and for such areas, as may be specified in the 
notification.]

</article>



<article><tid>339018</tid>
<number> 7B</number> Composition of Industry Facilitation Council.-
<section><tid>65313</tid>
<number>1</number>The Industry  
Facilitation Council shall consist of one or more members to be 
appointed from amongst the following categories:-

<subsection><tid>506632</tid>
<number>i</number>Director of Industries by whatever name called or any other 
officer not below the rank of such Director, of the State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1666723</tid>
<number>ii</number>representatives of banks and financial institutions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>460715</tid>
<number>iii</number>office- bearers or representatives of State Industry 
Associations; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1819932</tid>
<number>iv</number>persons having special knowledge in the field of Industry, 
Finance, Law, Trade and Commerce.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>282963</tid>
<number>2</number>The person appointed under clause (i) of sub- section (1) shall be 
the Chairperson of the Industry Facilitation Council.

</section>

<section><tid>458192</tid>
<number>3</number>The composition of the Industry Facilitation Council, the manner 
of filling vacancies among, and the procedure to be followed in the 
discharge of their functions by, the members shall be such as may be 
prescribed by rules by the State Government.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>625786</tid>
<number>7C</number>Laying of rules before State Legislature.- Every notification 
issued and every rule made by the State Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it issued or made, before the 
State Legislature.]

</article>



<article><tid>883430</tid>
<number>8</number>Requirement to specify unpaid amount with interest in the annual 
statement of accounts.- Where any buyer is required to get his annual 
accounts audited under any law for the time being in force, such buyer 
shall specify the amount together with the interest in his annual 
statement of accounts as remains unpaid to any supplier at the end of 
each accounting year.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. byu s. 6, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>812630</tid>
<number>9</number>Interest not to be allowed as deduction from income.- 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>), the amount of interest payable or paid by any buyer, under or in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act, shall not, for the 
purposes of computation of income under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, be 
allowed as deduction.

</article>



<article><tid>23788</tid>
<number>10</number>Overriding effect.- The provisions of this Act shall have 
effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in 
any other law for the time being in force.

</article>



<article><tid>129299</tid>
<number> 11</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>234298</tid>
<number>1</number>The Interest on Delayed Payments to Small  
Scale and Ancillary Industrial Undertakings Ordinance, <year>1993</year> (Ord. 4  
  of <year>1993</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1066917</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the Ordinance so repealed shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>