<act><tid>1017644</tid>
<title>THE WORKS OF DEFENCE ACT, <year>1903</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 7 OF <year>1903</year>
[ 20th March, <year>1903</year>.]

An Act to provide for imposing restrictions upon the use and enjoyment 
of land in the vicinity of works of defence in order that such land 
may be kept free from buildings and other obstructions, and for 
determining the amount of compensation to be made on account of such 
imposition.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for imposing restrictions upon 
the use and enjoyment of land in the vicinity of works of defence in 
order that such land may be kept free from buildings and other 
obstructions, and for determining the amount of compensation to be 
made on account of such imposition; It is hereby enacted as follows:-

PART

PRELIMINARY.

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>105265</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1339921</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>  
Works of Defence Act, <year>1903</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>534550</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>766525</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is something repugnant 
in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1897963</tid>
<number>a</number>the expression" land" includes benefits to arise out 
of land, and things attached to the earth or permanently 
fastened to anything attached to the earth;

</section>

<section><tid>808594</tid>
<number>b</number>the expression" person interested" includes all 
persons claiming an interest in compensation to be made on 
account of the imposition of restrictions upon the use and 
enjoyment of land under this Act; and a person shall be 
deemed to be interested in land if he is interested in an 
easement affecting the land:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 8 and sch. and to Pondichery (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>) by Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The word" Indian" omitted by Act 50 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 39 of <year>1965</year>, s. 2, for the former sub- section (2).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1317187</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the expression" District" means one of the Districts 
into which India is, for military purposes for the time 
being, divided; it includes a Brigade area which does not 
form part of any District, and any area which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
declare to be a District for all or any of the purposes of 
this Act:

</section>

<section><tid>1062656</tid>
<number>d</number>the expression" General Officer Commanding the 
District" means the officer for the time being in command of 
the forces in a District:]

</section>

<section><tid>1089804</tid>
<number>e</number>the expression" Commanding Officer" means the officer 
for the time being in command of a work of defence:

</section>

<section><tid>928286</tid>
<number>f</number>the expression" Collector" includes any officer specially 
appointed by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] to perform the 
functions of a Collector under this Act:

</section>

<section><tid>544665</tid>
<number>g</number>the expression" Court" means a principal Civil Court of 
original jurisdiction, unless the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] has 
appointed (as it is hereby empowered to do) a special 
judicial officer within any specified local limits to perform 
the functions of the Court under this Act:

</section>

<section><tid>1594955</tid>
<number>h</number>" maintain", with its grammatical variations and cognate 
expressions, does not, when used in relation to a house or 
other construction, include the doing of any act necessary 
for keeping such house or construction, until the making of 
the award referred to in section 12 or until the exercise, 
prior to the making of the award, of the powers of demolition 
conferred, in case of emergency, by section 6, sub- sections 
 (1) and (3), in the state in which it was at the time of the 
publication of the notice referred to in section 3, sub- 
section (2):

</section>

<section><tid>1029208</tid>
<number>i</number>the following persons shall be deemed" entitled to act" 
as and to the extent hereinafter provided, that is to say,-
trustees for other persons beneficially interested shall be 
deemed the persons entitled to act with reference to any 
case. and that to the same extent as the


<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>subs. by Act 11 of <year>1921</year>, s. 2 for the former cls. (c) and 
 (d).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

persons beneficially interested could have acted if free from 
disability:

a married woman, in cases to which the English law is 
applicable, shall be deemed the person so entitled to act, 
and, whether of full age or not, to the same extent as if she 
were unmarried and of full age: and

the guardians, of minors and the committees or managers of 
lunatics or idiots shall be deemed respectively the persons 
so entitled to act, to the same extent as the minors, 
lunatics or idiots themselves, if free from disability, could 
have acted:

Provided that-


<subsection><tid>1087568</tid>
<number>i</number>no person shall be deemed" entitled to act" whose 
interest in the subject- matter is shown to the satisfaction 
of the Collector or Court to be adverse to the interest of 
the person interested for whom he would otherwise be entitled 
to act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>10429</tid>
<number>ii</number>in every case the person interested may appear by a 
next friend or, in default of his appearance by a next 
friend, the Collector or Court, as the case may be, shall 
appoint a guardian for the case to act on his behalf in the 
conduct thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>701253</tid>
<number>iii</number>the provisions of Chapter XXXI of the Code of Civil 
Procedure (14 of <year>1882</year>) 1 shall, mutatis mutandis, apply in the 
case of persons, interested appearing before a Collector or 
Court by a next friend, or by a guardian for the case, in 
proceedings under this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>643952</tid>
<number>iv</number>no person" entitled to act" shall be competent to 
receive the compensation- money payable to the person for whom 
he is entitled to act, unless he would have been competent to 
alienate the land upon the use and enjoyment of which 
restrictions are to be imposed and receive and give a good 
discharge for the purchase- money on a voluntary sale.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>462320</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Construction of references to laws not in force, or any 
functionary not in existence, in any area. Any reference in this Act 
to any law which is not in force in any area or any reference therein 
to any functionary not in existence in any area shall, in relation to 
that

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), Sch. I, 
Order XXXII.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 39 of <year>1965</year>. S. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

area, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if any, 
in force, or to the corresponding functionary, if any, in existence, 
in that area.]

PART

IMPOSITION OF RESTRICTIONS.

PART II

IMPOSITION OF RESTRICTIONS



</article>



<article><tid>103114</tid>
<number> 3</number> Declaration and notice that restrictions will be imposed.
<section><tid>1417112</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever it appears to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] that it Is necessary 
to impose restrictions upon the use and enjoyment of land in the 
vicinity of any work of defence or of any site intended to be used or 
to be acquired for any such work, in order that such land may be kept 
free from buildings and other obstructions, a declaration shall be 
made to that effect under the signature of a Secretary to such 
Government or of some officer duly authorised to certify its orders.

</section>

<section><tid>108034</tid>
<number>2</number>The said- declaration shall be published in the Official 
Gazette and shall state the district or other territorial division in 
which the land is situate and the place where a sketch plan of the 
land, which shall be prepared on a scale not smaller than six inches 
to the mile and shall distinguish the boundaries referred to in 
section 7, may be inspected; and the Collector shall cause public 
notice of the substance of the said declaration to be given at 
convenient places in the locality.

</section>

<section><tid>448352</tid>
<number>3</number>The said declaration shall be conclusive proof that it is 
necessary to keep the land free from buildings and other obstructions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1945144</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to do preliminary acts after publication of notice under 
section 3, sub- section (2). It shall be lawful for such officer as 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] may, by general or special order, authorise 
in this behalf, and for his servants and workmen, at any time after 
publication of the notice mentioned in section 3, sub- section (2), to 
enter upon and survey and take levels of any land in such locality, 
to dig or bore into the sub- soil, to do all other acts necessary to 
ascertain whether any and, if so, what restrictions should be imposed 
on the use and enjoyment of the land, to set out the boundaries of 
the land upon the use and enjoyment of which restrictions are to be 
imposed, or of any part of such land, to mark such levels, boundaries 
and line by placing marks and cutting trenches, and, where otherwise 
the survey cannot be completed and the levels taken and the boundaries 
and line marked, to cut down and clear away any part of any standing 
crop, fence or jungle:
Provided that no person shall enter into any building or upon any 
enclosed court or garden attached to a dwelling- house (unless with 


<pagefootnote><pagenum>16A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G,",






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

  the consent of the occupier thereof) without previously giving such 
occupier at least seven days' notice in writing of his intention to do 
so.



</article>



<article><tid>1984904</tid>
<number>5</number>Payment for damage. The officer so authorised shall at the time 
of such entry pay or tender payment for all necessary damage to be 
done as aforesaid, and, in case of dispute as to the sufficiency of 
the amount so paid or tendered, he shall at once refer the dispute to 
the decision of the Collector or other chief revenue- officer of the 
district, and such decision shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1580414</tid>
<number> 6</number> Further powers exercisable after publication of notice under 
section 3, sub- section (2).
<section><tid>190903</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever a declaration has been made 
and public notice thereof has been given under section 3, it shall, 
subject to the provisions of sub- sections (2) to (4), be lawful for 
such officer as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] may, by general or special 
order, authorise in this behalf, and for his servants and workmen, to 
enter and demolish any buildings or other constructions on the 
surface, to cut down or grub up all or any of the trees, to remove or 
alter all or any of the banks, fences, hedges and ditches, to make 
underground and other

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

drains, to fill up all excavations, and demolish all buildings and 
other constructions below the surface, and generally to level and 
clear the said land and do all such acts for levelling and clearing 
the same as he may deem necessary or proper, but in such manner 
nevertheless that evidence of the boundaries of the lands held by 
different owners may be preserved.


</section>

<section><tid>1780219</tid>
<number>2</number>The powers conferred by sub- section (1) shall not be exer- 
cised,-

<subsection><tid>1417618</tid>
<number>a</number>save as otherwise provided by sub- section (3), before 
the making of the award hereinafter referred to in section 
12, nor

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>396722</tid>
<number>b</number>save as otherwise provided by sub- section (4), after 
the expiration of six months from the making of the said 
award, or any shorter period on the expiration of which the 
officer exercising such powers gives notice to the Collector 
that there will be no further exercise of them.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>643324</tid>
<number>3</number>In case of emergency, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare that all or any powers 
conferred by sub- section (1) may be exercised at any time within six 
months after the publication of the notice referred to in section 3, 
sub- section (2), and such powers may be exercised accordingly, and the 
said notification shall be conclusive proof of emergency.

</section>

<section><tid>1397902</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall be deemed to preclude any 
such officer or his servants or workmen from exercising at any time 
the said powers for the purpose of removing, wholly or in part, any 
building or other obstruction maintained, created, added to, altered, 
planted, stacked, stored or otherwise accumulated in contravention of 
this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder or of any condition 
prescribed in accordance therewith.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1553206</tid>
<number> 7</number> Restrictions. From and after the publication of the notice 
mentioned in section 3, sub- section (2), such of the following 
restrictions as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] may in its discretion 
declare therein shall attach with reference to such land, namely:-
<section><tid>223708</tid>
<number>a</number>Within an outer boundary which, except so far as is 
otherwise provided in section 39, sub- section (4), may extend 
to a distance of two thousand yards from the crest of the 
outer parapet of the work,-

<subsection><tid>891152</tid>
<number>i</number>no variation shall be made in the ground- level, and 
no building, wall, bank or other construction above

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." 
rep.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

the ground shall be maintained, erected, added to or 
altered otherwise than with the written approval of the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> General Officer Commanding the District], and on such 
conditions as he may prescribe;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>896516</tid>
<number>ii</number>no wood, earth, stone, brick, gravel, sand or other 
material shall be stacked, stored or otherwise 
accumulated:
Provided that, with the written approval of the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> General Officer Commanding the District] and on such 
conditions as he may prescribe, road- ballast, manure and 
agricultural produce may be exempted from the 
prohibition:

Provided also that any person having control of the land 
as owner, lessee or occupier shall be bound forthwith to 
remove such road- ballast, manure or agricultural 
produce, without compensation, on the requisition of the 
Commanding Officer;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1306200</tid>
<number>iii</number>no surveying operation shall be conducted otherwise 
than by or under the personal supervision of a public 
servant duly authorised in this behalf, in the case of 
land under the control of military authority, by the 
Commanding Officer and, in other cases, by the Collector 
with the concurrence of the Commanding Officer; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1755718</tid>
<number>iv</number>where any building, wall, bank or other con- 
struction above the ground has been permitted under 
clause (i) of this sub- section to be maintained, 
erected, added to or altered, repairs shall not, without 
the written approval of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> General Officer Commanding 
the District], be made with materials different in kind 
from those employed in the original building, wall, bank 
or other construction.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>178205</tid>
<number>b</number>Within a second boundary which may extend to a distance 
of one thousand yards from the crest of the outer parapet of 
the work, the restrictions enumerated in clause (a) shall 
apply with the following additional limitations, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1606095</tid>
<number>i</number>no building, wall, bank or other construction of 
permanent materials above the ground shall be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1921</year>, s. 3, for" General Officer Commanding 
the Division".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" General Officer Commanding the 
Division, District or Brigade".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 28 of <year>1940</year>, s. 2, for the original words.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

maintained otherwise than with the written approval of 
the General Officer Commanding the District and on such 
conditions as he may prescribe, and no such building, 
wall, bank or other construction shall be erected:]

Provided that, with the written approval of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> General 
Officer Commanding the District] and on such conditions 
as he may prescribe, huts, fences or other constructions 
of wood or other materials, easily destroyed or removed, 
may be maintained, erected, added to or altered:

Provided, also, that any person having control of the 
land as owner, lessee or occupier shall be bound 
forthwith to destroy or remove such huts, fences or 
other constructions, without compensation, upon an order 
in writing signed by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> General Officer Commanding 
the District]; and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>135455</tid>
<number>ii</number>live hedges, rows or clumps of trees or orchards 
shall not be maintained, planted, added to or altered 
otherwise than with the written approval of the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> General Officer Commanding the District] and on such 
conditions as he may prescribe.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1736023</tid>
<number>c</number>Within a third boundary which may extend to a distance 
of five hundred yards from the crest of the outer parapet of 
the work, the restrictions enumerated in clauses (a) and (b) 
shall apply with the following additional limitation, namely:
no building or other construction on the surface, and no 
excavation, building or other construction below the surface, 
shall be maintained or erected:

Provided that, with the written approval of the Commanding 
Officer and on such conditions as he may, prescribe, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a 
building or other construction on the surface may be 
maintained and] open railings and dry brush- wood fences may 
be exempted from this prohibition.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>418616</tid>
<number>8</number>Land to be marked out measured, registered and planned. As 
soon as may be after the publication of the declaration aforesaid, the 
Collector shall cause the land to be marked out and measured, and 
shall also prepare a register and a detailed plan, which shall

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1921</year>, s. 3, for" General Officer Commanding 
the Division".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1921</year>, s. 3, for" General Officer Commanding 
the Division, District or Brigade".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 28 of <year>1940</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

be on a scale not smaller than six inches to the mile, showing 
accurately every building, tree and other obstruction.



</article>



<article><tid>1525985</tid>
<number> 9</number> Notice to persons interested.
<section><tid>996731</tid>
<number>1</number>At any time before the  
expiration of-

<subsection><tid>1384613</tid>
<number>a</number>the period of eighteen months from the publication of 
the declaration referred to in section 3, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>725747</tid>
<number>b</number>such other period not exceeding three years from the 
said publication as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct in this behalf,
the Collector shall cause public notice to be given at convenient 
places on or near the land, stating the effect of the said declaration 
and that claims to compensation for all interests in such land 
affected by anything done or ordered in pursuance of such declaration 
may be made to him:

Provided that, where anything has been done in exercise of the 
powers conferred, in case of emergency, by section 6, sub- section (3), 
the notice prescribed by this section shall be given as soon as may be 
thereafter.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1970914</tid>
<number>2</number>Such notice shall state the particulars of any damage, 
ordered to be done or, in the case referred to in section 6, sub- 
section (3), done in exercise of any of the powers conferred by the 
said section, and the particulars of any restrictions attaching to the 
land under section 7, and shall require all persons interested in the 
land to appear personally or by agent before the Collector at a time 
and place therein mentioned (such time not being earlier than fifteen  
  days after the date of publication of the notice), and to state the 
nature of their respective interests in the land and the amount and 
particulars of their claims to compensation for damage to such 
interests and their objections (if any) to the measurements made under 
section 8. The Collector may in any case require such statement to be 
made in writing and signed by the party or his agent.

</section>

<section><tid>1395104</tid>
<number>3</number>The Collector shall also serve notice to the same effect on 
the occupier (if any) of such land and on all such persons known or 
believed to be interested therein, or to be entitled to act for 
persons so interested, as reside or have agents authorised to receive 
service on their behalf, within the revenue- district in which the land 
is situate.

</section>

<section><tid>898633</tid>
<number>4</number>In case any person so interested resides elsewhere, and has 
no such agent, the notice shall be sent to him by post in a letter 
addressed to him at his last known residence, address or place of 
business.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C.", 
rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1678734</tid>
<number>10</number>Power to require and enforce the making of statements as to 
names and interests. The Collector may also require any such person to 
make or deliver to him, at a time and place mentioned (such time not  
  being earlier than fifteen days after the date of the requisition), a 
statement containing, so far as may be practicable, the name of every 
other person possessing any interest in the land or any part thereof 
as co- proprietor, sub- proprietor, mortgagee, tenant or otherwise, and 
of the nature of such interest, and of the rents and profits (if any) 
received or receivable on account thereof for three years next pre- 
ceding the date of the statement.


</article>



<article><tid>1561602</tid>
<number>11</number>Application of certain sections of the Indian Penal Code. 
Every person required to make or deliver a statement under section 9 
or section 10 shall be deemed to be legally bound to do so within the 
meaning of sections 175 and 176 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>63169</tid>
<number> 12</number> Inquiry and award by Collector. On the day fixed under 
section 9 or on any other day to which the inquiry has been adjourned, 
the Collector shall proceed to inquire into the objections (if any) 
which any person interested has stated pursuant to a notice given 
under the said section to the measurements made under section 8, and 
into the decrease in the value of the land, and into the respective 
interests of the persons claiming the compensation, and shall make an 
award under his hand of-
<section><tid>233120</tid>
<number>a</number>the true area of the land and the nature of the 
obstructions from which the land is to be kept free;

</section>

<section><tid>404679</tid>
<number>b</number>the compensation which in his opinion should be allowed 
for any damage caused or to be caused under section 6 and for 
any restrictions imposed under section 7; and

</section>

<section><tid>1464784</tid>
<number>c</number>the apportionment of the said compensation among all the 
persons known or believed to be interested in the land, of 
whom or of whose claims he has information, whether they have 
respectively appeared before him or not.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1944332</tid>
<number> 13</number> Award of Collector when to be final.
<section><tid>1376620</tid>
<number>1</number>Such award shall be  
filed in the Collector' s office and shall, except as hereinafter 
provided, be final and conclusive evidence, as between the Collector 
and the persons interested, whether they have respectively appeared 
before the Collector or not, of the true area of the land, the nature 
of the said obstructions from which the land is to be kept free, the 
damage caused or to be caused under section 6, the value of the rights 
restricted under section 7, and the apportionment of the compensation 
among the persons interested.

</section>

<section><tid>536570</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector shall give immediate notice of his award to 
such of the persons interested as are not present personally or by 
their representatives when the award is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>549668</tid>
<number>14</number>Adjournment of inquiry. The Collector may, for any cause he 
thinks fit, from time to time adjourn the inquiry to a day to be fixed 
by him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1827348</tid>
<number>15</number>Power to summon and enforce attendance of witnesses and 
production of documents. For the purpose of inquiries under this Act 
the Collector shall have power to summon and enforce the attendance of 
witnesses, including the parties interested or any of them, and to 
compel the production of documents, by the same means, and (so far as  
  may be) in the same manner, as is provided in the case of a Civil 
Court under the Code of Civil Procedure (14 of <year>1882</year>) 1.


</article>



<article><tid>666065</tid>
<number>16</number>Matters to be considered and neglected. In determining the 
amount of compensation, the Collector shall be guided by the 
provisions contained in sections 23 and 24.


</article>



<article><tid>624675</tid>
<number> 17</number> Supplementary proceedings. Whenever the officer exercising 
powers conferred by section 6 considers it necessary that anything in 
respect of which any person is or may be entitled to compensation but 
of which no notice has been given or compensation awarded, under 
sections 9 and 12, respectively, should be done in pursuance of the 
said powers, the collector shall cause supplementary notice to be 
given, as nearly as may be, in the manner prescribed by section 9 and 
subject to the limit of time imposed by sub- section
<section><tid>1172643</tid>
<number>1</number>of that  
section, and the provisions of sections 10 to 16 shall, so far as they 
are applicable, be deemed to apply to any further inquiry and award 
which may be held or made in consequence of such supplementary notice.
PART

REFERENCE TO COURT AND PROCEDURE THEREON.

PART III

REFERENCE TO COURT AND PROCEDURE THEREON




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>142734</tid>
<number> 18</number> Reference to Court.
<section><tid>1771291</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person interested who has not  
accepted the award may, by written application to the Collector, 
require that the matter be referred by the Collector. for the 
determination of the Court, whether his objection be to the 
measurement of the land, the amount of the compensation, the persons 
to whom it is payable, or the apportionment of the compensation among 
the persons interested:
Provided that every such application shall be made,-


<subsection><tid>1696729</tid>
<number>a</number>if the person making it was present or represented before 
the Collector at the time when he made his award, within six 
weeks from the date of the Collector' s award;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>956491</tid>
<number>b</number>in other cases, within six weeks of the receipt of the 
notice from the Collector under section 13, sub- section (2), 
or within six months from the date of the Collector' s award, 
whichever period shall first expire.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>370714</tid>
<number>2</number>The application shall state the grounds on which objection to 
the award is taken.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (Act 5 of <year>1908</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>407323</tid>
<number> 19</number> Collector' s statement to the Court.
<section><tid>917948</tid>
<number>1</number>In making the  
reference the Collector shall state, for the information of the Court, 
in writing under his hand,-

<subsection><tid>1914000</tid>
<number>a</number>the situation and extent of the land with particulars 
of any damage caused under section 6 or of restrictions 
imposed under section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1319644</tid>
<number>b</number>the names of the persons whom he has reason to think 
interested in such land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>627406</tid>
<number>c</number>the amount of compensation awarded under section 12 
and,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1996093</tid>
<number>d</number>if the objection be to the amount of the compensation, 
the grounds on which the amount of compensation was 
determined.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>301528</tid>
<number>2</number>To the said statement shall be attached a schedule giving 
the particulars of the notices served upon, and of the statements in 
writing made or delivered by, the parties interested respectively.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>295945</tid>
<number> 20</number> Service of notice. The Court shall thereupon cause a notice 
specifying the day on which the Court will proceed to determine the 
objection, and directing their appearance before the Court on that 
day, to be served on the following persons, namely:-
<section><tid>610131</tid>
<number>a</number>the applicant;

</section>

<section><tid>701504</tid>
<number>b</number>all persons interested in the objection, except such 
 (if any) of them as have consented without protest to receive 
payment of the compensation awarded; and

</section>

<section><tid>1452200</tid>
<number>c</number>if the objection is in regard to the area of the land, 
the nature of the obstructions or the amount of the compen- 
sation, the Collector.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>662837</tid>
<number>21</number>Restriction on scope of proceedings. The scope of the 
inquiry in every such proceeding shall be restricted to a 
consideration of the interests of the persons affected by the 
objection.


</article>



<article><tid>1455499</tid>
<number>22</number>Proceedings to be in open Court. Every such proceeding shall 
take place in open Court, and all persons entitled to practise in any 
Civil Court in the State shall be entitled to appear, plead and act, 
as the case may be, in such proceeding.


</article>



<article><tid>94058</tid>
<number> 23</number> Matters to be considered in determining compensation.
<section><tid>1052171</tid>
<number>1</number>In determining the amount of compensation to be awarded for damage 
caused, or to be caused, or for restrictions imposed under this Act, 
the Court shall take into consideration-

<subsection><tid>1090473</tid>
<number>a</number>the actual decrease in market- value of the land owing 
to the publication of the declaration relating thereto under 
section 3 and any damage caused or to be caused under section 
 6;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>809065</tid>
<number>b</number>the damage sustained by the person interested, by 
reason of the removal of any standing crops in the exercise 
of any power conferred by section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>269405</tid>
<number>c</number>the damage (if any) sustained by the person interested, 
by reason of ceasing to be able to use such land conjointly 
with his other land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>913824</tid>
<number>d</number>the damage (if any) sustained by the person interested, 
by anything done or ordered under sections 6 and 7 injuri- 
ously affecting his other property, movable or immovable, 
in any other manner, or his earnings; and,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1283897</tid>
<number>e</number>if, in consequence of the imposition of restrictions, 
the person interested is compelled to change his residence or 
place of business, the reasonable expenses (if. any) 
incidental to such change.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>885413</tid>
<number>2</number>In addition to the amount representing the actual decrease in the 
market- value of the land as above provided, the Court shall in 
every case award a further sum of fifteen per centum on such amount.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1336932</tid>
<number> 24</number> Matters not to be considered in determining compensation. 
In determining the amount of compensation to be awarded for damage 
caused, or to be caused, or for restrictions imposed under this Act, 
the Court shall not take into consideration-
<section><tid>1035249</tid>
<number>a</number>the degree of urgency which has led to the damage or 
the imposition of restrictions;

</section>

<section><tid>1272752</tid>
<number>b</number>any disinclination of the person interested to submit 
to damage or restrictions;

</section>

<section><tid>1417071</tid>
<number>c</number>any damage sustained by him, which, if caused by a 
private person, would not render such person liable to a 
suit;

</section>

<section><tid>1995992</tid>
<number>d</number>any increase to the value of the other land of the 
person interested, accruing or likely to accrue from anything 
done under this Act; or

</section>

<section><tid>1023308</tid>
<number>e</number>any outlay or improvements on, or disposal of, the land 
commenced, made or effected without the sanction of the 
Collector after the date of the publication of the 
declaration under section 3.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>719911</tid>
<number> 25</number> Rules as to amount of compensation.
<section><tid>206128</tid>
<number>1</number>When the applicant  
has made a claim to compensation, pursuant to any notice given under 
section 9, the amount awarded to him by the Court shall not exceed the 
amount so claimed or be less than the amount awarded by the Collector 
under section 12.

</section>

<section><tid>1982596</tid>
<number>2</number>When the applicant has refused to make such claim or has 
omitted without sufficient reason (to be allowed by the Judge) to make 
such claim, the amount awarded by the Court shall in no case exceed 
the amount awarded by the Collector.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>324364</tid>
<number>3</number>When the applicant has omitted for a sufficient reason (to  
  be allowed by the Judge) to make such claim, the amount awarded to him 
by the Court shall not be less than, and may exceed, the amount 
awarded by the Collector.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1742311</tid>
<number>26</number>Form of awards. Every award under this Part shall be in 
writing signed by the Judge, and shall specify the amount awarded 
under section 23, sub- section (1), clause (a), and also the amounts (if  
  any) respectively awarded under each of the other clauses of the same 
sub- section, together with the grounds of awarding each of the said 
amounts.


</article>



<article><tid>379829</tid>
<number> 27</number> Costs.
<section><tid>1081861</tid>
<number>1</number>Every such award shall also state the amount of  
costs incurred in the proceedings under this Part, and by what persons 
and in what proportion they are to be paid.

</section>

<section><tid>95992</tid>
<number>2</number>When the award of the Collector is not upheld, the costs 
shall ordinarily be paid by the Collector, unless the Court is of 
opinion that the claim of the applicant was so extravagant or that he 
was so negligent in putting his case before the Collector that some 
deduction from his costs should be made or that he should pay a part 
of the Collector' s costs.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>868665</tid>
<number>28</number>Collector may be directed to pay interest on excess 
compensation. If the sum which, in the opinion of the Court, the 
Collector ought to have awarded as compensation is in excess of the 
sum which the Collector did award as compensation, the Court may 
direct that the Collector shall pay interest on such excess at the 
rate of six per centum per annum from the date of his award to the 
date of payment of such excess into Court.
PART IV.

PART IV

APPORTIONMENT OF COMPENSATION



</article>



<article><tid>245715</tid>
<number>29</number>Particulars of apportionment to be specified. Where there 
are several persons interested, if such persons agree in the 
apportionment of the compensation, the particulars of such 
apportionment shall be specified in the award, and as between such 
persons the award shall be conclusive evidence of the correctness of 
the apportionment.


</article>



<article><tid>363206</tid>
<number>30</number>Dispute as to apportionment. When the amount of 
compensation has been settled under section 12, if any dispute arises 
as to the apportionment of the same or any part thereof, or as to the 
persons to whom the same or any part thereof is payable, the Collector 
may refer such dispute to the decision of the Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

PAYMENT.

PART V

PAYMENT



</article>



<article><tid>881210</tid>
<number> 31</number> Payment of compensation or deposit of same in Court.
<section><tid>1669843</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
making an award under section 12, the Collector shall tender payment 
of the compensation awarded by him to the persons interested entitled 
thereto according to the award, and shall pay it to them unless 
prevented by some one or more of the contingencies mentioned in sub- 
section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>216743</tid>
<number>2</number>If they do not consent to receive it, or if there is no 
person competent to alienate the land, or if there is any dispute as 
to the title to receive the compensation or as to the apportionment of 
it, the Collector shall deposit the amount of the compensation in 
the Court to which a reference under section 18 would be submitted:
Provided, first, that any person admitted to be interested may 
receive such payment under protest as to the sufficiency of the 
amount:

Provided, secondly, that no person who has received the amount 
otherwise than under protest shall be entitled to make any application 
under section 18:

Provided, thirdly, that nothing herein contained shall affect the 
liability of any person, who may receive the whole or any part of any 
compensation awarded under this Act, to pay the same to the person 
lawfully entitled thereto.


</section>

<section><tid>1554792</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything in this section, the Collector may, 
with the sanction of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government], instead of awarding a 
money- compensation in respect of any land, make any arrangement with a 
person having a limited interest in such land, either by the grant of 
other lands in exchange, or by the remission of land- revenue on the 
same or on other lands held under the same title, or in such other way 
as may be equitable having regard to the interests of the parties 
concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>495144</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in sub- section (3) shall be construed to interfere 
with or limit the power of the Collector to enter into any arrangement 
with any person interested in the land and competent to contract in 
respect thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1003640</tid>
<number> 32</number> Investment of money deposited in respect of lands belonging 
to persons incompetent to alienate.
<section><tid>848347</tid>
<number>1</number>If any money is deposited in 
Court under section 31, sub- section (2), and it appears that the land 
in respect of which the same was awarded belonged to any person who 
had no power to alienate the same, the Court shall order the money to 
be invested-

<subsection><tid>1071244</tid>
<number>a</number>in the purchase of other lands to be held under the 
like title and conditions of ownership as the land in respect 
of which such money was deposited is held, or,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630380</tid>
<number>b</number>if such purchase cannot be effected forthwith, then in 
such Government or other approved securities as it thinks 
fit;
and shall direct the payment of the interest or other proceeds arising 
from such investment to the person or persons who would for the time 
being have been entitled to the possession of the said land, and such 
moneys shall remain so deposited and invested until the same are 
applied-


<subsubsection><tid>261499</tid>
<number>i</number>in the purchase of such other lands as aforesaid; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1768846</tid>
<number>ii</number>in payment to any person or persons becoming absolutely 
entitled thereto.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>223623</tid>
<number>2</number>In all cases of moneys deposited to which this section 
applies, the Court shall order the cost of the following matters, 
including therein all reasonable charges and expenses incident 
thereto, to be paid by the Collector, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1646352</tid>
<number>a</number>the costs of such investments as aforesaid;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1697321</tid>
<number>b</number>the costs of the orders for the payment of the interest 
or other proceeds of the securities in which such moneys are 
for the time being invested, and for the payment out of Court 
of the principal of such moneys and the costs of all 
proceedings relating thereto, except such as may be 
occasioned by litigation between adverse claimants.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>275492</tid>
<number>33</number>Investment of money deposited in other cases. If any money 
is deposited in Court under this Act for any cause other than that 
mentioned in section 32, the Court may, on the application of any 
party interested or claiming an interest in such money, order the same 
to be invested in such Government or other approved securities as it 
thinks fit, and may direct the interest or other proceeds of any such 
investment to be accumulated and paid in such manner as well, in its 
opinion, give the parties interested therein the same benefit 
therefrom as they might have had from the land in respect of which 
such money was deposited or as near thereto as may be.


</article>



<article><tid>253361</tid>
<number>34</number>Payment of interest. When the amount of any compensation 
awarded under this Act is not paid or deposited within fifteen days of 
making the award, the Collector shall pay the amount awarded with 
interest thereon at the rate of six per centum per annum from the date 
of the award until it is so paid or deposited.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>13560</tid>
<number> 35</number> Service of notices.
<section><tid>1074600</tid>
<number>1</number>Service of any notice under this  
Act shall be made by delivering or tendering a copy thereof signed, in 
the case of a notice under section 3, sub- section (2), by the officer 
therein mentioned, and, in the case of any other notice, by or by 
order of the Collector or the Judge.

</section>

<section><tid>485897</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever it may be practicable, the service of the notice 
shall be made on the person therein named.

</section>

<section><tid>1334917</tid>
<number>3</number>When such person cannot be found, the service may be made on 
any adult male member of his family residing with him; and, if no such 
adult male member can be found, the notice may be served by fixing the 
copy on the outer door of the house in which the person therein named 
ordinarily dwells or carries on business, or by fixing a copy thereof 
in some conspicuous place in the office of the officer aforesaid or of 
the Collector or in the court- house and also in some conspicuous part 
of the land upon which restrictions are to be imposed:
Provided that, if the Collector or Judge so directs, a notice may 
be sent by post in a letter addressed to the person named therein at 
his last known residence, address or place of business and service of 
it may be proved by the production of the addressee' s receipt.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1593093</tid>
<number> 36</number> Penalties. Whoever wilfully-
<section><tid>1635680</tid>
<number>a</number>obstructs any person in doing any of the acts 
authorised by section 4, section 6 or section 8, or

</section>

<section><tid>435938</tid>
<number>b</number>destroys, damages, alters or otherwise interferes with 
the ground- level or any work done under section 6, or

</section>

<section><tid>1449268</tid>
<number>c</number>contravenes any of the provisions of section 7 or any 
condition prescribed thereunder,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
one month, or with fine which may extend to fifty rupees, or with 
both, and, in the case of a continuing offence, with an additional 
fine which may extend to five rupees for every day after the 
first in regard to which he is convicted of having persisted 
in the offence; and any expenses incurred in removing the 
effects of his offence may be recovered from him in the 
manner provided by the law for the time being in force for 
the recovery of fines.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>756944</tid>
<number>37</number>Magistrate to enforce the terms of the Act. If the 
Collector or officer authorised under section 6 is opposed or impeded 
in doing anything directed or permitted by this Act, he shall, if a 
Magistrate, enforce compliance, and, if not a Magistrate,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

he shall apply to a Magistrate <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or (within any area for which a  
  Commissioner of Police has been appointed) to the Commissioner of 
Police], and such Magistrate or Commissioner (as the case may be) shall 
enforce compliance.



</article>



<article><tid>241917</tid>
<number> 38</number> Completion of imposition of restrictions no compulsory but 
compensation to be awarded when not completed.
<section><tid>1949261</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central 
Government] shall be at liberty to withdraw from the imposition of any 
declared restrictions before any of the measures authorised by section 
 6 have been taken.

</section>

<section><tid>305349</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] withdraws the imposition 
of any declared restrictions, the Collector shall determine the amount 
of compensation due for the damage suffered by the owner in 
consequence of the notice or of any proceedings thereunder, and shall 
pay such amount to the person interested, together with all costs 
reasonably incurred by him in the prosecution of the proceedings under 
this Act relating to the said restrictions.

</section>

<section><tid>411868</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of Part III shall apply, so far as may be, to 
the determination of the compensation payable under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>279230</tid>
<number> 39</number> Demolition of part of house or building and imposition of 
restrictions on part of land.
<section><tid>115448</tid>
<number>1</number>The Provisions of this Act shall 
not be put in force for the purpose of demolishing or acquiring the 
right to demolish a part only of any house, manufactory or other 
building, if the owner desires that the whole of such house, 
manufactory or building shall be demolished or that the right to 
demolish the whole of it shall be acquired:
Provided that the owner may at any time before the Collector has 
made his award under section 12, by notice in writing, withdraw or 
modify his expressed desire that the whole of such house, manufactory 
or building shall be demolished, or that the right to demolish the 
whole of it shall be acquired:

Provided, also, that, if any question shall arise as to whether 
any building or other construction proposed to be demolished under 
this Act does or does not form part of a house, manufactory or 
building within the meaning of this section, the Collector shall 
refer the determination of such question to the Court, and such 
building or other construction shall not be demolished until after the 
question has been determined.

In deciding on such a reference the Court shall have regard to 
the question whether the building or other construction proposed to be 
demolished is reasonably required for the full and unimpaired use of 
the house, manufactory or building.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1974</year>, s. 3, for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" L. G.".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>840807</tid>
<number>2</number>If, in the case of any claim of the kind referred to in 
section 23, sub- section (1), clause (c), by a person interested, on 
account of ceasing to be able to use the land, upon the use and 
enjoyment of which restrictions are to be imposed conjointly with his 
other land, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] is of opinion that the claim is 
unreasonable or excessive, it may, at any time before the Collector 
has made his award, order the imposition of restrictions upon the 
whole of the land of which the land upon the use and enjoyment of 
which it was first sought to impose restrictions forms a part.

</section>

<section><tid>1131314</tid>
<number>3</number>In the case provided for by sub- section (2) no fresh 
declaration or other proceeding under sections 3 to 10 shall be 
necessary; but the Collector shall without delay furnish a copy of the 
order of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Central Government] to the person interested, and shall 
thereafter proceed to make his award under section 12.

</section>

<section><tid>1981191</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, clause (a), 
any land, upon the use and enjoyment of which restrictions are imposed 
under this section, may be included in the outer boundary, even though 
its distance from the crest of the outer parapet of the work exceeds 
two thousand yards.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1400789</tid>
<number>40</number>Exemption from stamp- duty and fees. No award or agreement 
made under this Act shall be chargeable with stamp- duty, and no 
person claiming under any such award or agreement shall be liable to 
pay any fee for a copy of the same.


</article>



<article><tid>1272484</tid>
<number>41</number>Notice in case of suits for anything done in pursuance of 
Act. No suit or other proceeding shall be commenced or prosecuted 
against any person for anything done in pursuance of this Act, without 
giving to such person a month' s previous notice in writing of the 
intended proceeding, and of the cause thereof, nor after tender of 
sufficient amends.


</article>



<article><tid>1338154</tid>
<number>42</number>Code of Civil Procedure to apply to proceedings before 
Court. Save in so far as they may be inconsistent with anything con- 
tained in this Act, the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure 2 (14  
  of <year>1882</year>) shall apply to all proceedings before the Court under this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>406538</tid>
<number>43</number>Appeals in proceedings before Court. Subject to the 
provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure 2 (14 of <year>1882</year>) applicable to 
appeals from original decrees, an appeal shall lie to the High Court 
from the award or from any part of the award of the Court in any 
proceeding under this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>30A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>936050</tid>
<number> 44</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1911038</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] for the guidance of 
officers in all matters connected with the enforcement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1190987</tid>
<number>2</number>The power to make rules under sub- section (1) shall be 
subject to the condition of the rules being made after previous 
publication.

</section>

<section><tid>21913</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be com- 
prised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1974</year>, s. 4, for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for sub- section (3).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>