<act> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Standards of Weights and Measures (Enforcement) Act, 
1985.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into force in a State on such date as the State Government 
may, by notification, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for 
different provisions thereof, in or in relation to, different—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> areas in the State; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> classes of 
undertakings in the State; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> classes of goods 
produced, sold, distributed, marketed or transferred in the state; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number> classes of services 
rendered in the State; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number> classes of weights 
and measures manufactured, sold, distributed, marketed, transferred, repaired 
or used in the State; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number> classes of users 
of weights and measures in the State,
 and any reference in any such 
provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to 
the coming into force of this Act, or, as the case may be, of that provision, 
in such areas or in respect of such classes of undertakings, goods, services, 
classes of weights and measures or classes of users of weights and measures, in 
relation to which, or whom, this Act has been brought into force.
</subsection></section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>2</number> 
Act not to apply to inter-State trade or commerce.—Nothing in this Act shall apply to any inter-State 
trade or commerce in,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> any weight 
or measure, or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> any other 
goods which are sold, delivered or distributed by weights, measure or 
number.</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> “Additional Controller” includes a Joint 
Controller, Deputy Controller and an Assistant Controller appointed under 
section 5;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> “authorised seal or stamp” means a seal or stamp 
under, and in accordance with, the provisions of this Act;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> “Controller” means the Controller of Legal 
Metrology appointed under section 5;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> “counterfeit”, in relation to a seal or stamp, 
means a seal or stamp which is so made as to resemble an authorised seal or 
stamp, as the case may be, intending by that resemblance to practise deception, 
or knowing it to be likely that deception will thereby be practised;
  Explanation I.—It is not 
essential that the resemblance of the counterfeit seal or stamp to the 
authorised seal or stamp should be exact.
  Explanation II.—When a 
person caused a counterfeit seal or stamp to resemble an authorised seal or 
stamp and the resemblance is such that if a person relies on such seal or 
stamp, he might be deceived thereby, it shall be presumed, until the contrary 
is proved, that the person so causing the seal or stamp to resemble the 
authorised seal or stamp intended by means of that resemblance to practise 
deception or knew it to be likely that deception would thereby be pactised;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  “heap” means any unit of a commodity for sale 
where such sale is intended to be made without any weighment or measurement or, 
where the sale is made by number, without counting the number;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  “Inspector” means a person who is appointed as 
such under section 5, by whatever name called;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  “mint” means a mint of the Central Government;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  “notification” means a notification published 
in the Official Gazette;
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made 
under this Act;
 </section><section>        <number>j</number>  “protection” means the utilisation of any 
weight or measure, or any reading obtained with the help of any weight or 
measure, for the purpose of determining whether or not any step is required to 
be taken to safeguard the well-being of any human being or animal, or to 
protect any commodity, vegetation or thing. whether individually or 
collectively;
 </section><section>       <number>k</number>  “Standards Act” means the Standards of Weights 
and Measures Act, 1976 (60 of 1976);
 </section><section>        <number>l</number>  “standard weight or measure” means a weight, 
measure or number which conforms to the standards established in relation 
thereto by or under the Standards Act;
 </section><section>       <number>m</number>  “State Act” means the Act enacted by the 
Legislature of a State for the enforcement of the standards established by or 
under the Standards of Weights and Measures Act, 1956 (89 of 1956);
 </section><section>       <number>n</number>  “State Government”, in relation to Union 
territory, means the Administrator thereof;
 </section><section>       <number>o</number>  words and expressions used in this Act and not 
defined but defined in the Standards Act shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in that Act.
</section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>4</number> Provisions of this Act to 
override the provisions of any other law except the Standards 
Act.—The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any 
enactment other than this Act and the Standards Act or in any instrument having 
effect by virtue of any enactment other than this Act or the Standards 
Act.</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>5</number> Appointment of 
Controllers, Inspectors and other officers and staff.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification, appoint a Controller of Legal 
Metrology for the State and as many Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant 
Controllers, Inspectors, and other officers and staff as may be necessary for 
exercising the powers, and efficiently discharging the duties, conferred or 
imposed on them by or under this Act or the Standards Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every Additional 
Controller, Inspector or other officer, appointed under sub-section (1), shall 
exercise such powers and discharge such functions of the Controller as the 
State Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Controller may, by 
general or special order, define the local limits within which each Additional 
Controller, Inspector or other officer, appointed under sub-section (1) shall 
exercise his powers and discharge the duties conferred or imposed on him by or 
under this Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Subject to the provisions 
of this Act, every Additional Controller, Inspector and other officer appointed 
under sub-section (1) shall exercise his powers and discharge the duties of his 
office under the general superintendence, direction and control of the 
Controller and shall exercise those powers and discharge those duties in the 
same manner and with the same effect as if they had been conferred or imposed 
on him directly by or under this Act and not by way of authorisation.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Controller and every 
Additional Controller and other officer authorised by or under this Act may 
also—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> perform all or any of the functions of, and 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> exercise all or any of the powers conferred by 
this Act or any rule or order made thereunder, on,
 an Inspector.


</subsection></section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>6</number> Power to authorise 
Inspector to adjust weights or measures.—Where 
the Controller is of opinion that it is necessary so to do, he may, by an order 
in writing, authorise any officer not below the rank of an Inspector, to adjust 
any weight or measure in any area within the local limits of his jurisdiction.
</article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>7</number> Controller and officers 
appointed under this Act to be public servants.—
<section><number>a</number> The Controller and every Additional Controller, 
and every Inspector, and
 </section><section><number>b</number> every other officer authorised 
by or under this Act to perform any duty,
 shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 
21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>8</number> Protection of action 
taken in good faith.—No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Controller, any 
Additional Controller, Inspector or any other person authorised by or under 
this Act to exercise any power or to perform any duty in respect of anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the 
Standards Act or any rule or order made under either of the Act aforesaid.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>9</number> Prohibition of use of 
weights and measures other than standard weights and measures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding any custom, usage or method of whatever nature, no weight or 
measure, other than the standard weight or measure, shall be used or kept in 
any premises in such circumstances as to indicate that such weight or measure 
is intended, or is likely to be used, for any weighment or measurement.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On and from the 
commencement of this Act, no weight, measure or number, other than the standard 
weight or measure shall be used in, or form the basis of any contract or other 
agreement in relation to any trade, commerce, production or protection.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any contract or other 
agreement, which contravenes the provisions of sub-section (2) shall be void.





</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>10</number> Use of weights only or 
measures only in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may by rules made in this behalf, direct that in respect 
of the classes of goods, services or undertakings or users specified therein.-
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> no transaction, dealing or contract shall be 
made or had, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  no industrial production shall be undertaken, 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  no use for protection shall be made,
 except by such weight, measure or number as may be specified 
therein.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any rule made under 
sub-section (1) shall taken effect in such area, from such future date and 
subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified therein.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>11</number> Prohibition of 
quotations, etc., otherwise than in terms of standard weight or measure.—Except 
where he is permitted under the Standards Act so to do, no person shall, in 
relation to any goods or things which are sold, transferred, distributed or 
delivered, or any service rendered—
 <section>       <number>a</number> quote, or make announcement of, whether by word 
of mouth or otherwise, any price or charge, or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> issue or exhibit any price list, invoice, cash 
memo or other document, or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> mention any weight or measure in any 
advertisement poster or other document, or
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> indicate the weight, measure or number of the 
net contents of any package on the package itself or on any label, carton or 
other thing, or
 </section><section>       <number>e</number> express, in relation to any transaction, 
industrial production or protection, any quantity or dimension,
 otherwise than in accordance with the standard weight or measure.


</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>12</number> Custody and verification 
of reference standards.—Every 
reference standard shall be kept at such place and in such custody as may be 
prescribed, and no such reference standard shall be deemed to be a reference 
standard and shall be used as such unless it has been verified authenticated 
and maintained in accordance with the rules made under the Standards Act.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>13</number> Preparation of secondary 
and working standards.—The State 
Government may cause to be prepared at the metrological wing of the mint at 
Bombay, as many sets of secondary standards or working standards as it may 
think necessary:
 Provided that where the mint 
intimates the State Government in writing that it is unable to prepare any 
secondary standard or working standard, that Government may cause such 
secondary standard or working standard to be prepared by such organisation as 
the Central Government may, on a reference made to it by the State Government, 
by notification, specify in this behalf.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>14</number> Verification, stamping 
and custody of secondary or working standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every secondary standard or working standard referred to in section 13, shall 
conform to the standards established by or under the Standards Act and shall be 
verified—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> in the case of a secondary standard, at any one 
of the places where reference standards are maintained, against the appropriate 
reference standard;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> in the case of a working standard, at any one of 
the places where secondary standards are maintained, against the appropriate 
secondary standard,
 in such manner and at such periodical intervals as may be 
specified by or under the Standards Act and shall, if found on such 
verification to conform to the standards established by or under that Act, be 
stamped.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where any secondary 
standard or working standard is stamped under sub-section (1), a certificate 
shall be separately issued showing the date on which such weight or measure was 
stamped.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every verification and 
stamping referred to in sub-section (1) shall be made by such person or 
authority as may be specified by or under the Standards Act.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A secondary standard or 
working standard which is not verified and stamped in accordance with the 
provisions of sub-section (1) and sub-section (3) shall not be deemed to be a 
secondary standard or working standard, as the case may be, and shall not be 
used for the verification of any working standard or, as the case may be, for 
the verification of any weight or measure.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every verified secondary 
standard and every verified working standard shall be kept at such place and in 
such custody as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>15</number> Secondary or working 
standard which may not be stamped.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the State Government is of opinion that by reason of the size or nature 
of any secondary standard or working standard, it is not desirable or 
practicable to put a stamp thereon, it may direct that instead of putting a 
stamp on such secondary standard or working standard, a certificate may be 
issued to the effect that such secondary standard or working standard conforms 
to the standards established by or under the Standards Act and every secondary 
standard or working standard so certified shall be deemed to have been duly 
stamped under this Act on the date on which such certificate was issued.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every certificate referred 
to in sub-section (1) shall be in such form as may be prescribed and shall 
contain such details as to enable a clear identification of the weight or 
measure to which it relates.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>16</number> Persons using weights or 
measures for transactions or industrial production or for protection to get 
themselves registered.—No person, 
not being an itinerant vendor, shall use any weight or measure in any 
transaction or for industrial production or for protection unless he is 
registered in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>17</number> Procedure of 
registration.—
<section><number>1</number> Every person, who 
intends to commence, or carry on, the use of any weight or measure in any 
transaction or for industrial production or for protection, shall make, within 
such time and containing such particulars as may be prescribed, an application 
for the inclusion of his name in a register to be maintained for the purpose 
(hereinafter in this section referred to as the “Register of Users”).
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Register of Users shall 
be maintained in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The application referred to 
in sub-section (1) shall be made to the Controller or to such other person as 
the Controller may, by general or special order in writing, authorise in this 
behalf and every such application shall be made in such form, in such manner 
and on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of the 
application referred to in sub-section (1) the Controller or the person 
authorised by him shall include the name or such person in the Register of 
Users and issue to the applicant a certificate to the effect that his name has 
been so included.
 </section><section><number>5</number> A certificate issued under 
sub- section (4) shall be valid for the period specified therein and may be 
renewed from time to time for such further period and on payment of such fee as 
may be prescribed.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>18</number> Punishment for 
non-registration.—Whoever uses, 
after the expiry of the period prescribed under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 17, 
any weight or measure in any transaction or for industrial production or for 
protection shall, unless he is registered in accordance with the provisions of 
this Chapter, be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, 
and for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to six months, or with fine, or with both.
</section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>19</number> Prohibition on the 
manufacture, repair or sale of weights or measures without 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall make, 
manufacture, repair or sell, or offer, expose or possess for repair or sale, any 
weight or measure unless he holds a valid licence issued in this behalf by the 
Controller authorising such person to do so:
 Provided that a person who bona 
fide repairs any weight or measure owned and possessed by him shall not be 
required to take out a licence referred to in this sub-section.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every licence issued under 
this section—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> shall be—
 <subsubsection>             
<number>i</number>  is such form,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>ii</number>  issued on payment of such fees, and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>iii</number> valid for such period.
 as may be prescribed.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> may be renewed from 
time to time, and 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  may contain 
such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every licence issued under the 
State Act shall, if in force immediately before the commencement of this Act, 
continue to be in force until the expiry of the period of its validity, or until 
the cancellation thereof, whichever is earlier, and may be renewed under this 
Act after the expiry of the period of its validity, if an application for such 
renewal is made in the prescribed form at least one month before the expiry of 
the period of validity of the licence.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every person who intends to 
commence business, after the commencement of this Act, as a maker, manufacturer, 
repairer or seller or any weight or measure, shall make an application in such 
form and on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, for the issue of a 
licence to him, and every licence so issued may be renewed if an application for 
its renewal, accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed, is made by such 
person in the prescribed form at least one month before the expiry of the period 
of its validity.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Controller may, if he is 
satisfied that the maker, manufacturer, repairer or seller, as the case may be, 
of any weight or measure was prevented by sufficient cause from making an 
application for the renewal of his licence before the expiry of the period of 
the validity thereof, permit him to make the application within a further period 
of one month from the date of expiry of the period of such validity, on payment 
by him of such further fee, not exceeding the fee which is payable for the issue 
of the licence.
 </section><section><number>6</number> No application for the issue 
or renewal of a licence shall be rejected unless—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> the applicant or, as 
the case may be, the holder of the licence has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against the proposed action, and 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> the Controller is 
satisfied that—
 <subsubsection>             
<number>i</number> the application has not been made within the time specified in this section, 
or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>ii</number> the applicant has made any statement in, or in relation to, the application 
for the issue or renewal of the licence which is incorrect or false in material 
particulars, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>iii</number>  the applicant has contravened any provision of the Standards Act or 
of any State Act or of this Act or of any rule or order made under the Standards 
Act, State Act or this Act.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>7</number> The Controller may require 
every repairer licensed under this Act to furnish to the State Government 
security for such sum, not exceeding two hundred rupees, as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section><number>8</number> Nothing contained in this 
section shall apply to the sale by a user (who is not a maker, manufacturer, 
dealer or repairer) or any weight or measure:
 Provided that no sale of any 
weight or measure of the prescribed description shall be made except with the 
written permission of the Controller.
 </section><section><number>9</number> Every licence issued or 
renewed under this Act shall be displayed in a conspicuous place in the premises 
where the licensee carries on his business.

</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>20</number> Suspension and 
cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Controller may, if he has any reasonable cause to believe that the holder of 
any licence issued, renewed or continued under this Act has made any statement 
in, or in relation to, any application for the issue, renewal or continuance of 
the licence, which is incorrect or false in any material particular or has 
contravened any provision of the Standards Act or any State Act or this Act or 
any rule or order made thereunder, suspend such licence, pending the completion 
of any inquiry or trial against the holder of such licence:
 Provided that no such licence 
shall be suspended unless the holder thereof has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against the proposed action:
 Provided further that where the 
inquiry or trial referred to in this sub-section is not completed within a 
period of three months from the date of suspension of a licence, such 
suspension shall, on the expiry of the period aforesaid, stand vacated.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Controller may, if he 
is satisfied, after making such inquiry as he may think fit, that the holder of 
a licence has made a false or incorrect statement of the nature referred to in 
sub-section (1) or has contravened any law or order referred to in that 
sub-section, cancel such licence:
 Provided that no such licence 
shall be cancelled unless the holder thereof has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause against the proposed action.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every person whose licence 
has been suspended shall, immediately after such suspension, stop functioning 
as such licensee and shall not resume business as such licensee until the order 
of such suspension has been or stands, vacated.
 </section><section><number>4</number>. Every licensee whose 
licence has been suspended or cancelled shall, after such suspension or 
cancellation, as the case may be, surrender such licence to the authority by 
which such licence was issued.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every licensee whose 
licence has been cancelled shall, within a period of thirty days from the date 
of such cancellation, or within such further period, not exceeding three months 
from such date, as the Controller may, on sufficient cause being shown, allow, 
dispose of the weights or measures which were in his possession, custody or 
control on the date of such cancellation, and in the event of his failure to do 
so, the Controller or any other officer authorised by him, in writing, in this 
behalf, may seize and dispose of the same and distribute the proceeds thereof 
in such manner as may be prescribed.


</section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>21</number> Manufacture of weights or 
measures.—Save as otherwise provided 
in the Standards Act, no person shall—
 <section>       <number>a</number> make or manufacture 
any weight or measure unless such weight or measure conforms to the standards 
established by or under the Standards Act;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> make or manufacture 
any weight or measure with indications thereon of any weights or measures in 
accordance with unit other than the units of weights or measure specified by or 
under the Standards Act.</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>22</number> Prohibition of sale or 
use of unstamped weights or measures.—No 
weight or measure shall be sold, or offered, exposed or possessed for sale, or 
used or kept for use in any transaction or for industrial production or for 
protection unless it has been verified and stamped:
 Provided that nothing in this 
section shall apply to any weight or measure which has been initially verified 
and stamped with a special seal referred to in sub-section (3) of section 41 of 
the Standards Act.
</article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>23</number> Manufacturer, etc., 
to maintain records and registers.—
<section><number>1</number> Every maker, manufacturer, repairer or dealer and 
every person using any weight or measure in any transaction or for industrial 
production or for protection shall maintain such records and registers as may be 
prescribed and if required so to do by an Inspector, shall produce such records 
and registers before the Inspector for inspection.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), if the Controller is of opinion that having regard 
to the nature or volume of the business carried on by any maker, manufacturer, 
dealer, repairer or user of any weight or measure, it is necessary so to do, he 
may, by order, exempt maker, manufacturere, dealer, repairer or user from the 
operation of sub-section (1).</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>24</number> Verification and 
stamping of weights or measures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person having any weight or measure in his possession, custody or control 
in circumstances indicating that such weight or measure is being, or is 
intended or likely to be, used by him in any transaction or for industrial 
production or for protection, shall, before putting such weight or measure into 
such use, have such weight or measure verified at such place and during such 
hours as the Controller may, by general or special order, specify in this 
behalf (hereinafter referred to as the specified place or specified time), on 
payment of such fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every weight or measure 
referred to in sub-section (1) shall be re-verified at such periodical 
intervals as may be prescribed.
 Explanation.—For 
the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that no periodical re-verification 
shall be necessary is relation to any weight or measure which is used 
exclusively for domestic purposes.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every Inspector shall, for 
the purpose of verification of any weight or measure attend the specified place 
(with the local limit of his jurisdiction) at the specified time and verify 
every weight or measure which is brought to him at such place and within such 
time and shall, if he is satisfied that such weight or measure conforms to the 
standards established by or under the Standards Act, put his stamp thereon:
 Provided that where any weight 
or measure is such that it cannot, or should not, be moved from its location, 
the Inspector shall take such steps for the verification of such weight or 
measure at the place of its location as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where any verification has 
been made under sub-section (3) the Inspector shall grant to the person 
referred to in sub-section (1) a certificate in the prescribed form indicating 
therein the particulars of the weight or measure verified and stamped by him.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where the Controller is of 
opinion that by reason of the size or nature of any weight or measure, it is 
not desirable or practicable to put a stamp thereon, he may, by an order in 
writing, direct that instead of putting a stamp on such weight or measure, a 
certificate may be issued to the effect that such weight or measure conforms to 
the standards established by or under the Standards Act and every weight or 
measure so certified shall be deemed to have been duly verified and stamped 
under this Act on the date on which such certificate was issued.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Every certificate referred 
to in sub-section (5) shall be in such form as may be prescribed and shall 
contain such details as to enable a clear identification of the weight or 
measure to which it relates.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>25</number> Display of certificate 
of verification.—Every certification 
of verification granted under this Act shall be displayed in a conspicuous 
place in the premises where such weight or measure is being, or is intended or 
likely to be, used in any transaction or for industrial production or for 
protection.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>26</number> Validity or weights or 
measures duly stamped.—
<section><number>1</number> A weight 
or measure which is, or is deemed to be, duly verified and stamped under this 
Act shall be deemed to conform to the standards established by or under the 
Standards Act at every place within the State in which it is stamped unless it 
is found on inspection or verification that such weight or measure has ceased 
to conform to the standards established by or under the Standards Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No weight or measure which 
is, or is deemed to be, duly verified and stamped under this Act shall require 
to be re-stamped merely by reason of the fact that it is being used at any 
place within the State other than the place at which it was originally verified 
and stamped:
 Provided that where a verified 
weight or measure, installed at one place, is dismantled and re-installed at a 
different place, such weight or measure shall not be put into use unless it has 
been duly re-verified and stamped, notwithstanding that periodical 
re-verification of such weight or measure has not become due.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a verified weight or 
measure has been repaired, whether by a licensed repairer or by the person 
owning and possessing the same, such weight or measure shall not be put into 
use unless it has been duly re-verified and stamped, notwithstanding that 
periodical re-verification of such weight or measure has not become due.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>27</number> Power to inspect.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An Inspector may, within the local limits of his  
jurisdiction, inspect and test at all reasonable times, any weight or measure 
which—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> is in the possession, custody or control of any 
person, or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> is in or on any premises,
 in such circumstances as to indicate that such weight or measure 
is being, or is intended or likely to be, used in any transaction or for 
industrial production or for protection, and may also verify whether such 
weight or measure is in conformity with the standards established by or under 
the Standards Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> For the purpose of 
ascertaining the correctness of any weight or measure use in any transaction, 
an Inspector may also test the weight or measure of the article sold or 
delivered to any person in the course of such transaction.


</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>28</number> Power of Inspector to 
require production of weight or measure or records for inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An Inspector may, if he has any reasonable cause to believe that an offence 
punishable under this Act has been or is likely to be, committed in respect of 
any weight or measure or that any weight or measure does not conform to the 
standards established by or under the Standards Act, require, at all reasonable 
times, the person having the custody or control of such weight or measure to 
produce before him for inspection every such weight or measure which,—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> is used by such person or is caused by such 
person to be used by any other person, or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> is in the possession, custody or control of 
such person for use, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number> is kept in or on any premises for use, in any 
transaction or for industrial production or for protection.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Inspector may also 
require the production of every document or other record relating to the weight 
or measure referred to in sub-section (1) and the person having the custody of 
such weight or measure shall comply with such requisition.
 </section><section><number>3</number> On inspection, whether 
under section 27 or under this section, the Inspector shall obliterate the 
stamp on—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  any weight or measure which, being due for 
verification, has not been submitted for such verification;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> any weight or measure which, since the last 
verification and stamping, has been repaired or re-adjusted, and does not, 
after such repair or re-adjustment, conform to the standards established by or 
under the Standards Act;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> any weight or measure which does not admit of 
proper adjustment by reason of its being broken, indented or otherwise 
defective;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number> any weight or measure other than those specified 
in clause (b) or clause (c) which does not, or cannot be made to, conform to 
the standards established by or under the Standards Act:
 Provided that where the 
Inspector is of opinion that the defect or error in such weight or measure is 
not such as to require immediate obliteration of the stamp, he shall serve a 
notice on the user of such weight or measure informing him of the defect or 
error found in the weight or measure and calling upon him to remove the defect 
or error within such time, not exceeding eight days, as he may specify, and 
shall—
 <subsubsection>        <number>i</number>  if the user fails to remove the defect or 
error within that period, obliterate the stamp, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>ii</number> if the defect or error is so removed as to 
make the weight or measure conform to the standards established by or under the 
Standards Act, verify such weight or measure and put his stamp thereon.
 Explanation.—The 
obliteration of the stamp on any weight or measure shall not take away or 
abridge the power of the Inspector to seize such weight or measure in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>29</number> Power of Inspector to 
enter premises.—An Inspector may, if 
he has any reason to believe, whether from any information given to him by any 
person and taken down by him in writing or from personal knowledge or 
otherwise, that an offence punishable under this Act has been, or is likely to 
be, committed in relation to any weight, measure or other goods which are sold, 
delivered or distributed by weight, measure or number, enter, at all reasonable 
times, into any premises—
 <section>        <number>i</number> where such weight or measure is—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number> made manufactured, repaired, or sold, or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number> used, or kept or believed to be kept for 
use, in any transaction or for industrial production or for protection;
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>ii</number> where such goods are manufactured, packed, 
distributed or sold or kept or offered for sale in packaged form,
 and inspet or verify any weight or measure or the net contents, by 
weight, measure or number, or any package, and may also examine any document or 
other record relating thereto.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>30</number> Power to search.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Controller has reason to believe that any weight or measure, liable 
to be seized under this Act, or any document or thing in relation to any weight 
or measure, will be, in his opinion, useful for or relevant to, any proceeding 
under this Act, is secreted in any place, he may search or authorise any 
officer, not below the rank of an Inspector, to search for and seize, such 
weight or measure, document or thing, and the provisions of sections 100 and 
102 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), shall apply to every 
such search.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every authorisation made by 
the Controller under sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be a warrant referred 
to in section 93 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).




















</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Power of Inspector to seize any weight or 
measure.—
<section><number>1</number> An Inspector may seize 
and detain any weight or measure in relation to which an offence under this Act 
is being, or appears to have been, committed, or which is intended or likely to 
be used in the commission of such offence, and may also seize and detain any 
goods sold or delivered, or cause to be sold or delivered, by such weight or 
measure:
 
Provided that where any goods seized under this sub-section are subject to 
speedy or natural decay, the Inspector may dispose of such goods in such manner 
as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any weight, measure or any article is seized and detained under 
sub-section (1), the Inspector may also seize and detain any document or other 
record relating to such weight, measure or article.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of section 102 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974), shall apply to every seizure made under this section.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Forfeiture.—Every 
false or unverified weight or measure (other than those referred to in section 
30 of the Standards Act) seized under the provisions of this Act shall be 
liable to be forfeited to Government:
 Provided that such unverified 
weight or measure shall not be forfeited to the Government if the person from 
whom such weight or measure was seized gets the same verified and stamped 
within such time as may be prescribed.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>33</number> Provisions of the 
Standards Act and the rules made thereunder relating to commodities in packaged 
form to apply to commodities in packaged form sold or distributed within the 
State.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of the 
Standards Act and the rules made thereunder, as in force immediately before the 
commencement of this Act, with regard to commodities in packaged form shall, as 
far as may be, apply to every commodity in packaged form which is distributed, 
sold, or kept, offered or exposed for sale, in the State as if the provisions 
aforesaid were enacted by, or made under, this Act subject to the modification 
that any reference therein to the “Central Government”, “Standards Act” and the 
“Director” shall be construed as references respectively, to the “State 
Government”, “this Act” and the “Controller”.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government may 
make rules, not inconsistent with the Standards Act or any rule made thereunder, 
to regulate the packaging of any commodity intended to be sold or distributed, 
within the State in packaged form, or to regulate the sale or distribution, 
within the State, of any commodity in packaged form.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section, “commodity in packaged form” shall have the 
meaning assigned to it in the Standards Act and shall include a pre-packed 
commodity.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>34</number> Custom or usage 
requiring delivery of additional quantities to cease.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any custom, usage, practice or method of whatever nature which permits a person 
to demand, receive, or cause to be demanded or received, any quantity of 
article, thing or service in excess of; or less than the quantity specified by 
weight, measure or number in any contract or other agreement in relation to the 
said article, thing or service, shall be void.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where in relation to any 
commodity sold by number there is a custom or usage of delivering a fixed 
number of such commodity in addition to the number of commodities paid for, 
such custom or usage shall, on and from the commencement of this Act, cease.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>35</number> Sale by heaps.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any commodity is sold by heaps, the approximate weight, measure or number 
of the commodity contained in each heap shall be conspicuously announced by the 
seller or his agent, if any, either by word of mouth or by a written notice 
placed on each heap:
 Provided that no such 
announcement shall be necessary in the case of a heap where the total price of 
the commodity contained in such heap does not exceed two rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where, or weighment, measurement or counting of any commodity sold by heap, 
it is found that the weight, measure or number, determined by such weighment, 
measurement or counting, is less than the approximate weight, measure or number 
announced by the seller or his agent and the deficiency is more than five per 
cent of such announced weight, measure or number, the seller shall be deemed to 
have used a false weight or measure.
</section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>36</number> 
Penalty for manufacturing, etc., of non-standard weights or 
measures.—Whoever,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> makes or 
manufactures, or causes to be made or manufactured (except where he is permitted 
under the Standards Act so to do), any weight or measure in accordance with any 
standards other than the standards established by or under the Standards Act, 
or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  (i) 
sells or otherwise transfers, or causes to be sold or otherwise transferred, 
or
 <subsection>            
<number>ii</number> lets, or causes to be let, on hire, 
 any weight or measure which has been 
manufactured in accordance with any standards other than the standards 
established by or under the Standards Act, 1[shall be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months but which 
may extend to one year, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six months, but which may 
extend to three years, and also with fine.]


</subsection></section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Penalty for counter-feiting of seals, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever,—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> counterfeits any 
seal specified by or under this Act or the Standards Act, or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> sells or 
otherwise disposes of any counterfeit seal, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number> possesses any 
counterfeit seal, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number> counterfeits any 
stamp, specified by or under this Act or the Standards Act or any rule made 
under either of those Acts, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number> removes any stamp 
made, whether under this Act or the Standards Act or any rule made under either 
of those Act, or tampers with any stamp so made, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number> removes any stamp 
made, whether under this Act or the Standards Act or any rule made under either 
of those Acts, and affixes the stamp so removed on, or inserts the same into, 
any other weight or measure, or
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>vii</number> increases or 
diminishes or alters in any way any weight or measure with a view to deceiving 
any person or knowing or having reason to believe that any person is likely to 
be deceived thereby,
 

1[shall be punished with imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to two 
years, and for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than one year but which may extend to five years and 
also with fine.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Whoever obtains, by 
unlawful means, possession of any seal specified by or under this Act or the 
Standards Act and uses, or causes to be used, any such seal for making any 
stamp on any weight or measure with a view to representing that the stamp made 
by such seal is authorised by or under this Act or the Standards Act,1[shall 
be punished with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six 
months but which may extend to who years, and, for the second or subsequent 
offence, with imprison­ment for a term which shall not be less than one year 
but which may extend to five years and also with fine.]
 </section><section><number>3</number> Whoever, being in lawful 
possession of a seal specified by or under this Act or the Standards Act uses, 
or causes to be used, such seal without any lawful authority for such use,


1[shall be punished with imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to two 
years, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than one year but which may extend to five years and 
also with fine.]
 </section><section><number>4</number> Whoever sells, or offers or 
exposes for sale or otherwise disposes of any weight or measure which, he knows 
or has reason to believe, bears thereon a counterfeit stamp, 

1[shall be punished with imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to two 
years, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than one year but which may extend to five years and 
also with fine.]



</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>38</number> Penalty for sale or 
delivery of commodities, etc., by non-standard weight or measure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Except where he is permitted under the Standards Act so to do, whoever sells, 
or causes to be sold, delivers, or causes to be delivered, any commodity, 
article or thing by any weight, measure or number other than the standard 
weight or measure 

1[shall be punished with fine which 
shall not be less than five hundred rupees but which may extend to two thousand 
rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than three months but which may extend to one year and 
also with fine.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever renders, or causes 
to be rendered, any service in terms of any weight, measure or number other 
than the standard weight or measure 

1[shall be punished with fine which 
shall not be less than five hundred rupees but which may extend to two thousand 
rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than three months but which may extend to one year and 
also with fine.]



</section></article> 
  
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>39</number> Penalty for keeping 
non-standard weights or measures for use and for other contravention.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever keeps any weight or measure other than the standard weight or measure 
in any premises in such circumstances as to indicate that such weight or 
measure is being, or is likely to be, used for any—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> weighment or measurement, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> transaction or for industrial production or for 
protection,
 shall be punished with fine which may extend to two thousand 
rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to one year and also with fine.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Whoever,—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number> in selling any article or thing by weight, 
measure or number, delivers or causes to be delivered to the purchaser any 
quantity or number of that article or thing less than the quantity or number 
contracted for and paid for, or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number> in rendering any service by weight, measure or 
number, renders that service less than the service contracted for and paid for, 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number> in buying any article or thing by weight, 
measure or number, fraudulently receives, or causes to be received any quantity 
or number of that article or thing in excess of the quantity or number 
contracted for and paid for, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number> in obtaining any service by weight, measure or 
number, obtains that service in excess of the service contracted for and paid 
for,
 shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand 
rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to five years and also with fine.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Whoever enters, after the 
commencement of this Act, into any contract or other agreement (not being a 
contract or other agreement for export) in which any weight, measure or number 
is expressed in terms of any standard other than the standard weight or 
measure, shall be punished with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, 
and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to one year and also with fine.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>40</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 10.—Whoever, 
in relation to any specified class of goods, services, undertakings or users of 
weights or measures, uses in any transaction or for industrial production or 
for protection, any weight, measure or number, other than the weight, measure 
or number specified by rules made under section 10, shall be punished with fine 
which may extend to two thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent 
offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and also 
with fine.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>41</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 11.—Except 
where he is permitted under the Standards Act so to do, whoever, in relation to 
any goods or things which are sold, transferred, distributed or delivered, or 
any service rendered,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> quotes any price or charge, or makes any 
announcement with regard to the price or charge, or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> issues or exhibits any price list, invoice, cash 
memo, or other document, or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  mentions any weight or measure in any 
advertisement, poster or other document, or
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> indicates the weight, measure or number of the 
net contents of any package or on any label, carton or other thing, or
 </section><section>       <number>e</number> expresses, in relation to any transaction, 
industrial production or protection, any quantity or dimension,
 otherwise than in accordance with the standard weight or measure, 
shall be punished with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, and, for 
the second or subsequent offence, with imprison­ment for a term which may 
extend to one year and also with fine.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>42</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 19.—Whoever, 
being required to obtain a licence under this Act makes, manufactures, repairs 
or sells or offers, exposes or possesses for repair or sale, any weight or 
measure, without being in possession of a valid licence empowering him to do 
so, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one 
year, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both, and, 
for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to three years and also with fine.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>43</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 20.—A 
licensee who after the suspension of cancellation of the licence issued to him 
or renewed or continued under this Act, omits or fails to stop functioning as a 
licensee under this Act, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to one year.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>44</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 21.—Except 
where he is permitted under the Standards Act so to do, whoever makes or 
manufactures any weight or measure which,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> though ostensibly purports to conform to the 
standards established by or under that Act, does not actually to the said 
standards, or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> bears thereon any indication of weight or 
measure which is not in conformity with the standards of weight or measure 
established by or under that Act, whether such indication is or is not in 
addition to the indication of weight or measure in accordance with the said 
standards, 
 shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
one year, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both 
and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to three years and also with fine.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>45</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 22.—Whoever,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> sells, offers, exposes or possesses for sale, 
any weight or measure which has not been verified and stamped under this Act, 
or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> uses, or keeps for use, any weight or measure 
which, being required to be verified and stamped uner this Act, has not been so 
verified and stamped, 
 shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both, 
and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to one year and also with fine:
 Provided that nothing in clause 
(b) shall apply, in relation to any weight or measure which is used for 
domestic purposes.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>46</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 23.—Whoever, 
being required by section 23 to maintain any record or register, omits or fails 
to do so, or being required by an Inspector to produced any records or 
registers for his inspection, omits or fails to do so, shall be punished with 
fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent 
offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and also 
with fine.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>47</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 24.—Whoever, 
being required by section 24 to present any weight or measure for verification 
or re-verification, omits or fails, without any reasonable cause to do so, 
shall be punished with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and, for 
the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to one year and also with fine.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>48</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 28.—Whoever, 
being required by an Inspector, or any person authorised by or under this Act 
to exercise the powers of an Inspector, to produce before him for inspection 
any weight or measure or any document or other record relating thereto, omits 
or fails, without any reasonable cause, to do so, shall be punished with fine 
which may extend to one thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent 
offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and also 
with fine.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>49</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 29.—Whoever 
obstructs the entry of an Inspector, or any person authorised by or under this 
Act to exercise the powers of an Inspector, into any premises for the 
inspection and verification of any weight or measure or any document or other 
record relating thereto or the net contents of any packaged commodity or for 
any other prescribed purpose, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to two years, and for the second and subsequent offence, with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>50</number> Penalty for 
contravention of sections 30 and 31.—Whoever 
prevents the Controller or any officer authorised by the Controller in this 
behalf, from searching any premises or prevents an Inspector from making any 
seizure of any weight, measure, packaged commodity, goods, document, record or 
label, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two 
years, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to five years and also with fine. 
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>51</number> Penalty for 
contravention of section 33.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever manufactures, distributes, packs, sells or keeps for sale or offers or 
exposes for sale, or has in his possession for sale, any commodity in packaged 
form, shall, unless each such package conforms to the provisions of the 
Standards Act and the rules made thereunder, read with section 33, be punished 
with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, and, for the second or 
subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years 
and also with fine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever manufactures, packs, distributes or sells, or causes to be 
manufactured, packed, distributed or sold, any commodity in packaged form, 
knowing or having reason to believe that the commodity contained in such 
package is lesser in weight, measure or number than the weight, measure or 
number, as the case may be, stated on the package or label thereon, shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, or with 
fine which may extend to three thousand rupees, or with both, and, for the 
second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
five years and also with fine.
 
Explanation.—In 
determining, for the purpose of this sub-section, whether the quantity 
contained in a package is lesser than the quantity declared on the package or 
label thereon, the maximum permissible error specified under the Standards Act 
in relation to the commodity contained in such package, shall be taken into 
account.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Penalty for contravention of section 35.—Whoever 
sells any commodity by heaps without complying with the provisions of section 
35, shall be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and, 
for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
with both.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> Penalty for tampering with licence.—Whoever 
alters or otherwise tampers with any licence issued or renewed under this Act 
or any rule made thereunder, otherwise than in accordance with any 
authorisation made by the Controller in this behalf, shall be punished with 
fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to one year, or with both.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> Penalty for selling or delivering rejected 
weights and measures.—Whoever sells, 
delivers or disposes of, or causes to be sold, delivered or disposed of, and 
weight or measure which has been rejected on verification under this Act or the 
Standards Act, or any rule made under either of the said Act, shall be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which 
may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both:
 
Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to the sale, as scrap, or any 
rejected weight or measure which has been defaced in the prescribed manner.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> Penalty for personation of officials.—Whoever 
personates in any way the Controller, Additional Controller or an Inspector or 
any other officer authorised by the Controller, shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> Penalty for giving false information or 
maintaining false records or registers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever gives information to a Controller, Additional Controller or an 
Inspector or any other officer authorised by the Controller, which he may 
require or ask for in the course of his duty and which such person either knows 
or has reason to believe to be false or does not believe to be true, shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with 
fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever, being required by 
or under this Act so to do, submits a return or maintains any record or 
register which is false in any material particular, shall be punished with fine 
which may extend to two thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent 
offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year and also 
with fine.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>57</number> Wilful verification or 
disclosure in contravention of Law.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any  
Inspector or any other officer exercising powers under this Act or any rule 
made  
thereunder wilfully verifies or stamps any weight or measure in contravention 
of the provisions of this Act or of any rule made thereunder, he shall, for 
every such offence, be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to one year, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with 
both.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any Inspector or other 
officer who enters into any premises in the course of his duty wilfully 
discloses, except in the performance of such duty, to any person any 
information obtained by him from such premises with regard to any trade secret 
or any secret in relation to any manufacturing process, he shall be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which 
may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>58</number> Vexatious search.—An 
Inspector or any other officer exercising powers under this Act or any rule or 
order made thereunder who knows that there are no reasonable grounds for so 
doing, and yet—
 <section>       <number>a</number> searches, or causes to be searched, any house, 
conveyance or place, or 
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> searches any person, or
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> seizes any weight, measure or other movable 
property,
 shall, for every such offence, be punished with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to one year or with fine which may extend to two thousand 
rupees, or with both.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>59</number> Penalty for 
contravention not separately provided for.—Whoever 
contravenes any provision of this Act for the contravention of which no 
punishment has been separately provided for in this Act, shall be punished with 
fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>60</number> Presumption to be made 
in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
person,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> makes or manufactures, or causes to be made or 
manufactured, any false weight or measure, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> uses, or causes to be used, any false or 
unverified weight or measure in any transaction or for industrial production or 
for protection, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> sells, distributes, delivers or otherwise 
transfers, or causes to be sold, distributed, delivered or otherwise 
transferred, any false or unverified weight or measure,
 it shall be presumed, until the contrary is proved, that he had 
done so with the knowledge that the weight or measure was a false or unverified 
weight or measure, as the case may be.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If any person has in his 
possession custody or control any false or unverified weight or measure in such 
circumstances as to indicate that such weight or measure is likely to be used 
in any transaction or for industrial production or for protection, it shall be 
presumed, until the contrary is proved, that such false or unverified weight or 
measure was possessed, held or controlled by such person with the intention of 
using the same in any transaction or for industrial production or for 
protection.


</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>61</number> When employer to be 
deemed to have abetted an offence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any  
employer, who knows or has reason to believe that any person employed by him 
has, in the course of such employment, contravened any provision of this Act or 
any rule made thereunder, shall be deemed to have abetted an offence against 
this Act:
 Provided that no such abetment 
shall be deemed to have taken place if such employer has, before the expiry of 
seven days from the date on which,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> he comes to know of the contravention, or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> he has reason to believe that such contravention 
has been made,
 intimated, in writing, to the Controller the name of the person by 
whom such contravention was made and the date and other particulars of such 
contravention.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Whoever is deemed under 
sub-section (1) to have abetted an offence against this Act shall be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which 
may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both, and, for the second or 
subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years 
and also with fine.
 Explanation.—Dismissal 
or termination of service of an employee after the expiry of the period 
specified in the proviso to sub-section (1) shall not absolve any employer of 
his liability under this sub-section.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>62</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the person committing an offence under this Act is a company, every person 
who, at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was 
responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as 
well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 Provided that nothing contained 
in this sub-section shall render any person liable to punishment if he proves 
that the offence was committed without his knowledge, or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), where any offence under this Act has been 
committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed 
with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect or the 
part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty 
of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> “company” means any body corporate and includes 
a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> “director”, in relation to a firm, means partner 
in the firm.


</subsection></section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>63</number> Cognizance of offences.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974),—
 
        1[
<section><number>a</number> 
no court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act except 
upon a complaint, in writing, made by—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number> the Controller;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number> any other officer authorised in this 
behalf by the Controller by general or special order;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number> any person aggrieved; or
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number> a recognised consumer association whether 
the person aggrieved is a member of such association or not.
               Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
clause “recognised consumer association” means a voluntary consumer association 
registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or any other law for the 
time being in force.]
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>b</number> no court inferior to that of a Metropolitan 
Magistrate or Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence 
punishable under this Act.








</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>64</number> Summary trial of certain 
offences.—Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), an offence 
punishable under section 36, section 38, section 39, section 40, section 41, 
section 42, section 45, section 52 or sub-section (3) of section 72 may be 
tried summarily.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>65</number> Compounding of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any offence punishable under section 39, section 40, section 41, section 42, 
section 44, section 45, section 46, section 47, section 48, section 51, section 
52, section 54 or section 59 or any rule made under sub-section (3) of section 
72, may either before or after the institution of the prosecution, be 
compounded, by the Controller or such other officer as may be authorised in 
this behalf by the Controller, on payment, for credit to the State Government, 
of such sum as the Controller or such other officer may specify:
 Provided that such sum shall 
not, in any case, exceed the maximum amount of the fine which may be imposed 
under this Act for the offence so compounded.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
sub-section (1) shall apply to a person who commits the same or similar offence 
within a period of three years from the date on which the first offence, 
committed by him, was compounded.
 Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this sub-section, any second or subsequent offence committed 
after the expiry of a period of three years from the date on which the offence 
was previously compounded, shall be deemed to be a first offence.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an offence has been 
compounded under sub-section (1), no proceeding or further proceeding, as the 
case may be, shall be taken against the offender, in respect of the offence so 
compounded, and the offender, if in custody, shall be discharged forthwith.
 </section><section><number>4</number> No offence punishable under 
this Act shall be compounded except as provided by this section.


</section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>66</number> Provisions of Indian Penal 
Code not to apply to any offence under this Act.—The provisions of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) 
in so far as such provisions relate to offences with regard to weights or 
measures, shall not apply to any offence which is punishable under this 
Act</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>67</number> Transfer or transmission 
of business.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the business 
of a person licensed under this Act is transmitted by succession, intestate or 
testamentary, the heir or legatee, as the case may be, of such person shall not 
carry on the business of such licensee either in his own name or in any other 
name, unless the heir or legatee has, before the expiry of sixty days after the 
date of such transmission, made to the Controller an application for the issue 
of a licence in accordance with the provisions of this Act:
 Provided that nothing in this 
section shall be deemed to prohibit the heir or legatee from carrying on 
business as such licensee for the aforesaid period of sixty days, and, if he 
has applied for such licence, until he is granted the licence or is, by a 
notice in writing informed by the Controller that such licence cannot be 
granted to him.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the business of any 
person licensed under this Act is transferred by sale, gift, lease or 
otherwise, the transferee or lessee, as the case may be, shall not carry on 
such business either in his own name or in any other name, unless he has 
obtained a licence to carry on such business.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>68</number> Licences neither 
saleable nor transferable.—A licence 
issued or renewed under this Act shall not be saleable or otherwise 
transferable.
</article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>69</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), an appeal shall lie,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> from every decision given or order made under 
Chapter V, Chapter VI, Chapter VII, Chapter VIII, Chapter IX or Chapter X of 
this Act, by—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> an Inspector, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> an Additional Controller,
      to the Controller; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> from every decision given or order made by the 
Controller under Chapter V, Chapter VI, Chapter VII, Chapter VIII, Chapter IX 
or Chapter X of this Act, not being a decision made in appeal under clause (a),
 to the State Government or any officer specially authorised in 
this behalf by that Government.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Every such appeal shall be 
preferred within sixty days from the date of the decision or order appealed 
against:
 Provided that the appellate 
authority may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by 
sufficient cause from preferring the appeal within the said period of sixty 
days, permit the appellant to prefer the appeal within a further period of 
sixty days.
 </section><section><number>3</number> On receipt of any such 
appeal, the appellate authority shall, after giving the parties to the appeal, 
a reasonable opportunity of being heard and after making such inquiry as it 
deems proper, makes such order, as it may think fit, confirming, modifying or 
reversing the decision or order appealed against, or may send back the case 
with such direction as it may think fit for a fresh decision of order after 
taking additional evidence, if necessary.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every appeal shall be 
preferred on payment of such fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The State Government may, 
on its own motion or otherwise, call for and examine the record of any 
proceeding (including a proceeding in appeal) in which any decision or order 
has been made, for the purpose of satisfying itself as to the correctness, 
legality or propriety of such decision or order and may pass such orders 
thereon as it may think fit:
 Provided that no decision or 
order shall be varied under this sub-section so as to prejudicially affect any 
person unless such person has been given a reasonably opportunity of showing 
cause against the proposed action.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>70</number> Levy of fees.—The 
State Government may, by rules made under section 72, levy such fees, not 
exceeding:—
 <section>       <number>a</number> five hundred rupees, for the application for the 
issue or renewal of a licence for making or manufacturing of any weight or 
measure,
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> one hundred rupees, for the issue of a licence 
for repairing or selling of any weight or measure,
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> fifty rupees for 
the alteration of any licence,
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> five thousand 
rupees, on a graded scale, for the verification of any weight or measure, 
having regard to the time and labour which may be involved in making such 
verification,
 </section><section>       <number>e</number> ten rupees, for 
the adjustment of any weight or measure,
 </section><section>        <number>f</number> ten rupees, for 
the issue of a duplicate licence or certificate of verification,
 </section><section>       <number>g</number> one rupee, for 
every hundred words or less, for the grant of copies of any document, not being 
a document of a confidential nature,
 </section><section>       <number>h</number> twenty-five 
rupees, for any appeal preferred under this Act,
 </section><section>        <number>i</number> five rupees, for 
application for registration or renewal of registration under section 17.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> Delegation of powers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification, direct that any power exercisable by 
it under this Act or rule made thereunder, not being a power conferred by 
section 69 (relating to appeal) or section 70 (power to lay down scale of fee) 
or section 72 (power to make rules), in relation to such matters and subject to 
such conditions as may be specified, may be exercised also by such officer 
subordinate to it as may be specified in the notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to any general or special direction or condition imposed by the 
State Government, any person authorised by the State Government to exercise any 
powers may exercise those powers in the same manner and to the same extent as 
if they had been conferred on that person directly by this Act and not by way 
of delegation.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification and after consultation with the 
Central Government, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any or the following matters, namely.—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> the class of 
goods, services, undertakings or users in relation to which no transaction, 
dealing or contract, or industrial production or use for protection shall be 
made or had or undertaken except by such weight, measure or number as required 
by section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> the places at 
which, and the custody in which, the following standards shall be kept, 
namely:—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> reference 
standards,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> secondary 
standards,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number> working 
standards,
 
     as required by section 12 and sub-section (5) of section 14;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the form and 
details of particulars for identification of weight or measure referred to in 
sub-section (2) of section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number> the time within 
which an application referred to in sub-section (1) of section 17 shall be 
made, the particulars which such application shall contain and the form and 
manner in which such application shall be made;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number> the form and 
manner in which the register referred to in sub-section (2) of section 17 shall 
be maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number> the form and 
manner in which an application shall be made under sub-section (3) of section 
17;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number> the form in which 
an application shall be made for the issue or renewal of a licence to carry on 
business as a maker, manufacturer, repairer or dealer of any weight or measure, 
as required by sub-section (4) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number> the form in which 
and the conditions, limitation and restrictions subject to which any licence 
may be issued and the period of validity of such licence, as required by 
sub-section (2) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number> the sum to be 
furnished by a repairer as security as required by sub-section (7) of section 
19;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number> the description 
of weight or measure which may not be sold by a user except with the written 
permission of the Controller as required by sub-section (8) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number> the manner of 
disposal of weights or measures after cancellation of licence and the 
distribution of proceeds thereof as required by sub-section (5) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number> the records and 
registers relating to weights or measures to be maintained in pursuance of the 
provisions of sub-section (1) of section 23;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>m</number> the period within 
which weights or measures shall be verified or re-verified as required by 
sub-section (2) of section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number> the steps to be 
taken for verifying any weight or measure which cannot, or should not, be moved 
from its location, as required by the provision to sub-section (3) of section 
24;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>o</number> the form in which 
a certificate of verification of any weight or measure shall be granted as 
required by sub-section (4) of section 24 and the form in which the certificate 
referred to in sub-section (5) of section 24 shall be issued and the details 
which such certificate shall contain, as required by sub-section (6) of section 
24;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>p</number> the manner of 
disposal of seized articles which are subject to speedy or natural decay, as 
required by the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 31;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>q</number> the time within 
which an unverified weight or measure seized under this Act may be permitted 
under the proviso to section 32 to be verified and stamped;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>r</number> the manner in 
which, and the conditions, restrictions and limitations subject to which,—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> any 
commodity intended to be sold or distributed, within the State, shall be 
packaged, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> the sale or 
distribution of any commodity in packaged form shall be made within the State,
 
     as required by sub-section (2) of section 33;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>s</number> the manner of 
obliteration of stamps on rejected weights or measures, as required by the 
proviso to section 54;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>t</number> the form in 
which appeals may be preferred under section 69 and the procedure for the 
hearing of appeals;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>u</number> the amount of 
fees which may be levied and collected for each of the matters specified in 
section 70;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number> any other matter 
which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In making any rule under this section, the State Government may provide 
that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The power to make rules under this section shall be subject to the 
condition of the rule being made after previous publication in the Official 
Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every rule made under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is 
made, be laid before each House of the State Legislature where there are two 
Houses, and where there is one House of the State Legislature, before that 
House.
</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> Power of State Government to make 
provisions of the Standards Act  
relating to approval of models applicable to models of weights or measures 
intended to be used exclusively within the State.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any type of weight or measure manufactured by a licensed manufacturer is 
such that all the weights or measures of that type manufactured by him within 
the State is intended to be sold, distributed or delivered therein, the State 
Government may, by notification, direct that the model of every such type of 
weight or measure shall be submitted for approval in accordance with the 
provisions of sections 36, 37 and 38 of the Standards Act, and thereupon, the 
provisions of the said sections 36, 37 and 38 shall become applicable to such 
model, and references in those sections to the Central Government and to the 
Standards Act shall be construed as references, respectively, to the State 
Government and this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the State Government makes a direction under sub-section (1) in 
relation to any type of weight or measure, any contravention of the provisions 
of section 39, section 40 or section 41 of the Standards Act in relation to 
that type of weight or measure shall be an offence punishable under this Act 
and the punishment provided therefore in the Standards Act shall be deemed to 
be the punishment provided therefore in this Act as if the said provisions 
relating to punishment were enacted by this Act.
</section></article> 
 THE STANDARDS OF 
WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article><number>74</number> 
Act not to apply in certain cases.—The provisions of this Act, in so far as they relate 
to the verification and stamping of weight and measures, shall not apply to any 
weight or measure,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> used in any 
factory exclusively engaged in the manufacture of any arms, or ammunition, or 
both, for the use of the Armed Forces of the Union;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> used for 
scientific investigation or for research;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> manufactured 
exclusively for export.</section></article> 
 THE 
STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES (ENFORCEMENT) ACT, 1985
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On the commencement of any provisions of this Act in a State, the corresponding 
provisions of any law in force for the time being in that State shall stand 
repealed, and on such repeal, the provisions of section 6 of the General 
Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall apply as if the provisions so repealed 
were the provisions of a Central Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, any appointment, notification, rule, order, 
registration, licence, certificate, notice, decision, approval, authorisation 
or consent made, issued or given under such law shall, if in force at the 
commencement of this Act, continue to be in force and have effect as if it were 
made, issued or given under the corresponding provisions of this Act. 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>