<act><title>

The
Protection of Civil Rights Rules,
19771</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>  

<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Protection of Civil Rights Rules, 1977. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions— In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number> “Act” means the Protection of Civil Rights Act, 1955 (22 of 1955). 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>  “section” means a section of the Act. 
 

  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Manner of inquiry under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number>
of section 10A.—(1) The State Government may appoint an officer not below
the rank of a Sub-divisional Magistrate for the purpose of making an inquiry
referred to in sub-section (1) of section 10A.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The officer appointed under sub-rule (1) (hereinafter in this rule referred to
as the inquiry officer) shall issue a public notice specifying the date, time,
place and the purpose of such inquiry
and calling upon all the residents of the area in respect
of which the inquiry is to be held to furnish such information and
materials, including documents in their posses­sion, as may be relevant for the
purposes of the inquiry.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The public notice referred to in sub-rule (2) shall be in the local language or
languages of the area and the same shall be,—
 


 <subsection><number>i</number> published on the notice board in the offices of the District Magistrate,
the District Superintendent of Police, the Village Panchayat or Municipal
Committee of the area and such other places as the inquiry officer deems fit and
at least in one daily newspaper circulating in the area; and 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> proclaimed in the area by beat of drum or in such other manner as the
inquiry officer may think best in the circum­stances to bring the contents of
the public notice to the notice of the inhabitants of the area. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
The inquiry officer, while making such inquiry shall follow as nearly as
practicable, the procedure for summary trials in­cluding the recording of
evidence as laid down in Chapter XXI of Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
1974).
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
The inquiry officer shall complete the inquiry as expedi­tiously as possible
and submit his report to the State Government within such period, not exceeding
six weeks, as may be specified by the State Government in the order appointing
the inquiry officer:
 


 Provided
that the State Government may, having regard to the nature of the inquiry,
extend the period of submission of the report by such period not exceeding two
months in total as it may consider necessary.
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Period for filing a petition under sub-section (3) of section 10A.—Any
person aggrieved by the imposition of a collective fine under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of
section 10A or by the order of apportionment, may within a period of thirty days
from the date of proclamation of the notification under sub-section (2) of
that section file a petition before the State Government or the authority
specified by it:
 


 Provided
that where the State Government or the authority, as the case may be, may
entertain the petition after the expiry of the said period if it is satisfied
that the petitioner was prevented
by sufficient cause from filing the
petition in time.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The State Government or the authority before which the peti­tion is filed shall
dispose of the petition as expeditiously as possible.
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Report by the State Government.—Every
State Government shall, for the purpose of enabling the Central Government,
place the report referred to in sub-section (4) of section 15A, on the Table of
each House of Parliament, furnish to the Government before the 15th day of
February each year, a summary of the measures taken by it under sub-sections 
<section><number>1</number>
and (2) of that section during the preceding calendar year and shall also
furnish such other information as may be required by the Central Govern­ment
from time to time.
 


  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>