<act><tid>1028936</tid>
<title>THE CRIMINAL LAW AMENDMENT ACT, <year>1938</year></title>

ACT NO. 20 OF <year>1938</year>
[ 14th September, <year>1938</year>.]

An Act to amend the criminal law.

WHEREAS it is expedient to supplement the criminal law by provid- 
ing for the punishment of certain acts prejudicial to the recruitment 
of persons to serve in, and to the discipline of, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Armed Forces 
of the Union]; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>816142</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1110783</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1938</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1815824</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>189638</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force in a State on such date <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as the 
State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
in his behalf for such State.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>692254</tid>
<number> 2</number> Dissuasion from enlistment and instigation to mutiny 
or insubordination after enlistment. Whoever-
<section><tid>993027</tid>
<number>a</number>with intent to affect adversely the recruitment of 
persons to serve in the Military, Naval or Air Forces of 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Union], wilfully dissuades or attempts to dissuade the 
public or any person from entering any such Forces, or

</section>

<section><tid>1846500</tid>
<number>b</number>without dissuading or attempting to dissuade any person 
from entering such Forces, instigates the public or any 
person to do, after entering any such Force, any thing which 
is an offence punishable as mutiny or insubordination under 
section 27 of the Indian Army Act 5, <year>1911</year> (8 of <year>1911</year>), or 
sections 10 to 12 and 14 to 17 inclusive of <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the 
Indian Navy (Discipline) Act, <year>1934</year> (34 of <year>1934</year>), or sections 
 35 to 37 inclusive of the Indian Air Force Act 7, <year>1932</year> (14 of  
  <year>1932</year>), as the case may be,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>663A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" His Majesty' s Forces".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" except Part B States" were omitted by Act 3 of 
<year>1951</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Came into force in the States of Delhi, Ajmer and Coorg on the 
1st August, <year>1954</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1954</year>, Pt. 11, see. 3, p. <year>1806</year>; 
in Uttar Pradesh on the 20th August, <year>1954</year>, see U. P. Gazette, Pt. 
I, p. 1041 and in Assam on the 25th August, <year>1954</year>, see Assam Gazette, 
<year>1954</year>, Pt. IIA, p. <year>1809</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" His Majesty".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Now see the Army Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of <year>1950</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>The words" the Naval Discipline Act as applied to the Indian 
Navy by" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Now see the Air Force Act, <year>1950</year> (45 of <year>1950</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f. 1-  
  10- <year>1957</year>): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>663B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 
of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>663C</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli 
 (w. e. f. 1. 7. 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>664</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
one year, or with fine, or with both.

No person shall be prosecuted for any offence under this Act 
except with the previous sanction of the State Government.

Exception 1.- The provisions of clause (a) of this section do not 
extend to comments on or criticism of the policy of Government in 
connection with the Military, Naval or Air Forces, made in good faith 
without any intention of dissuading from enlistment.

Exception 1.- The provisions of clause (a) of this section do not 
extend to the case in which advice is given in good faith for the 
benefit of the individual to whom it is given, or for the benefit of 
any member of his family or of any of his dependents.



</section>

</article>



 </act>