<act><tid>103056</tid>
<title>THE HACKNEY- CARRIAGE ACT, <year>1879</year></title>

ACT NO. 14 OF <year>1879</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 5th September, <year>1879</year>.]

An Act for the regulation and control of hackney- carriages 
in 
certain Municipalities and Cantonments.

Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the 
regulation 
and control of hackney- carriages in certain municipalities 
and 
cantonments; It is hereby enacted as follows





<article><tid>1650327</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Hackaey- carriage 
Act, <year>1879</year>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

Saving.- Nothing herein contained shall affect any power conferred 
by any law relating to municipalities, or any rule made in exercise of 
any such power.



</article>



<article><tid>81145</tid>
<number>2</number>Interpretation- clause.- In this Act-
" hackney- carriage" means any wheeled vehicle drawn by animals and 
used for the conveyance of passengers which is kept or offered or 
plies for hire; and

" committee" means a municipal committee, or a body of municipal 
commissioners, constituted under the provisions of any enactment for 
the time being in force.



</article>



<article><tid>444268</tid>
<number>3</number>Application of Act to municipalities.- <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The State Government 
concerned may, by notification in the Official Gazette, apply this Act 
to any municipalities in Uttar Pradesh, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Punjab as it existed 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>], the Central Provinces, 
Assam, Ajmer or Coorg.]
Power of committees to make rules.- When this Act has been so 
applied to any municipality, the committee of such municipality may, 
from time to time, make rules for the regulation and control of 
hackney- carriages within the limits of such municipality, in the 
manner in which, under the law for the time being in force, it makes 
rules or bye- laws for the regulation and control of other matters 
within such limits.

Confirmation and publication of rules.- Every rule made under this 
section shall, when confirmed by the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Commissioner] and published for 
such time and in such, manner as the[ Commissioner] may, from time to 
time, prescribe, have the force of law:

Power of Commissioner to rescind rules. Provided that the 5 
[ Commissioner] may at anytime, rescind any such rule.



</article>



<article><tid>130064</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Power to make rules for cantonments.] Rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1727373</tid>
<number>5</number>Power to extent operation of rules beyond limits of 
municipality or cantonment.- The authority making any rules under this 
Act may'[ with the sanction of the Commissioner] extend their 
operation to any railway station, or specified part of a road, not 
more than six miles from the local limits of the municipality <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> 
concerned.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>348</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been amended in-

Coorg by Coorg Act 6 of <year>1940</year>; and

Ajmer- Merwara by Act 6 of <year>1945</year>.

C. P. by C. P. and Berar Act 15 of <year>1941</year>.

The Act has been repealed in Punjab by Punjab Act 16 of 
196O.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" and it shall come into force at once; but" rep. by Act 1 
1 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 11.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The original paragraph has been successively amended by the A. O. 
<year>1937</year>, the A. O. <year>1948</year> and the A. O. <year>1950</year> to read as above.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Punjab".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Sub 3. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Part 1, for" L. G.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
7, The words, or cantonment" omitted, Ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>The second paragraph (Proviso) and third paragraph omitted, ibid.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1054775</tid>
<number> 6</number> What rules under section 3 may provide for.-- The rules to be 
made under section 3 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> may, among other matters,-
<section><tid>709943</tid>
<number>a</number>direct that no hackney- carriage, or no hackney- 
carriage of a particular description, shall be let to 
hire, or taken to ply, or offered for hire, except under 
a license granted in that behalf;

</section>

<section><tid>816882</tid>
<number>b</number>direct that no person shall act as driver of a 
hackney- carriage except under a license granted in that 
behalf;

</section>

<section><tid>1824351</tid>
<number>c</number>provide for the issue of the licenses referred to 
in clauses (a) and (b), prescribe the conditions (if  
  any) on which such licenses shall be granted, and fix 
the fees (if any) to be paid therefore;

</section>

<section><tid>1235742</tid>
<number>d</number>regulate the description of animals, harness and 
other things to be used with licensed carriages, and the 
condition in which such carriages, and the animals, 
harness and other things used therewith, shall be kept, 
and the lights (if any) to be carried after sun set and 
before sunrise;

</section>

<section><tid>1917116</tid>
<number>e</number>provide for the inspection of the premises on which 
any such carriages, animals, harness and other, things 
are kept;

</section>

<section><tid>1818751</tid>
<number>f</number>fix the time for which such licenses shall continue 
in force, and the events (if any) upon which within such 
time they shall be subject to revocation or suspension;

</section>

<section><tid>898643</tid>
<number>g</number>provide for the numbering of such carriages;

</section>

<section><tid>1180654</tid>
<number>h</number>determine the times at which, and the 
circumstances under which, any person keeping a hackney- 
carriage shall be bound to let or refuse to let such 
carriage to any person requiring the same;

</section>

<section><tid>151200</tid>
<number>i</number>appoint places as stands for hackney- carriages, and prohibit 
such carriages waiting for hire except at such places;

</section>

<section><tid>1977371</tid>
<number>j</number>limit the rates or fares, as well for time as distance, 
which may be demanded for the hire of any hackney- 
carriage; and prescribe the minimum speed at which such 
carriages when hired by time shall be driven;

</section>

<section><tid>111424</tid>
<number>k</number>limit the number of persons, and the weight of 
property, which may be conveyed by any such carriage;

</section>

<section><tid>117161</tid>
<number>l</number>require the owner or person in charge of any such 
carriage to keep a printed list of fares, in English and 
such other language as may be prescribed, affixed 
inside such carriage in such place as may be determined 
by the rules, and prohibit the destruction or defacement 
of such list;

</section>

<section><tid>1436894</tid>
<number>m</number>require drivers to wear a numbered badge or ticket, 
and to produce their licenses when required by a 
Magistrate or other person authorized by the rules in 
this, behalf, and prohibit the transfer or lending of 
such licenses and badges; and

</section>

<section><tid>235002</tid>
<number>n</number>provide for the deposit of property found in such 
carriages, and the payment of a fee by the owner of such 
property on the delivery thereof to him.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>349071</tid>
<number>7</number>Penalty for breach of rules.- Any person breaking any rule made 
under this Act shall be punished with fine which may extend to fifty 
rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1625578</tid>
<number>8</number>Disposal of fees and payment of expenses.- The amount of any 
fees received and the amount of any expenses incurred in giving effect 
to this Act shall <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> be credited and debited respectively to the 
municipal fund <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.


</article>



<article><tid>1972855</tid>
<number>9</number>Power of Magistrate to decide disputes regarding fares.- If any 
dispute arises between the hirer of any hackney- carriage and the owner 
or driver of such carriage as to the amount of the fare payable by 
such hirer under any rule made under this Act, such dispute shall, 
upon application made in that behalf by either of the disputing 
parties, be hear and determined by any Magistrate or Bench of 
Magistrates within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such dispute 
has arisen; and such Magistrate or Bench may, besides determining the 
amount so in dispute, direct that either party shall pay to the other 
such sum as compensation for loss of time as such Magistrate or Bench 
thinks fit.
Any sum determined to be due or directed to be paid under this 
section shall be recoverable as if it were a fine. 4

The decision of any Magistrate or Bench in any case under this 
section shall be final.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>349</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words and figure" or section 4" omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" in any municipality" omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" and in any cantonment where there is a cantonment- fund, 
to such fund" omitted, ibid,

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>As to recovery of fines, see the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of  
  <year>1897</year>). s. 25.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

When any such case is heard by a Bench, any difference of opinion 
arising between the members of such Bench shall be settled in the same 
manner as differences of opinion arising between such members in the 
trial of criminal cases.



</article>



<article><tid>554038</tid>
<number>10</number>In case of dispute, hirer may require driver to take him to 
Court.- If, at the time any dispute mentioned in section 9 arises, any 
Magistrate or Bench of Magistrates having jurisdiction in respect of 
such dispute is sitting within the local limits to which the rules 
apply, the hirer of the carriage may require the driver thereof to 
take him in the same to the Court of such Magistrate or Bench for the 
purpose of making an application under that section.
Any driver neglecting or refusing to comply with such requisition 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one 
month, or with fine not exceeding fifty rupees, or with both.


</article>



 </act>