<act><tid>1036666</tid>
<title>THE RED CROSS SOCIETY (ALLOCATION OF  
  PROPERTY) ACT, <year>1936</year></title>

ACT NO. 18 OF <year>1936</year>
[ 27th October, <year>1936</year>.]

An Act to provide out of the property of the Indian Red Cross 
Society a fund to be administered in Burma by a Burma Red Cross 
Society, and to terminate in Burma the existing functions of the 
Indian Red Cross Society.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide out of the property of the 
Indian Red Cross Society a Fund to be administered in Burma by a Burma 
Red Cross Society, and to terminate in Burma the existing functions of 
the Indian Red Cross Society; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1935567</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>213913</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the Red  
Cross Society (Allocation of Property) Act, <year>1936</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>257661</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>692319</tid>
<number>2</number>Apportionment of corpus of property of Indian Red Cross 
Society. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Red Cross 
Society Act, <year>1920</year>, (15 of <year>1920</year>) an amount equal to seven per cent of 
the corpus of the property vested by the said Act in the Indian Red 
Cross Society (which amount is in this Act referred to as the Fund) 
shall be set apart to be administered in the Province of Burma as a 
trust by such body of trustees as the High Court of Judicature at 
Rangoon may appoint, and in accordance with, and for such of the 
purposes referred to in section 7 of the said Act as may be contained 
in, any scheme settled by the said High Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Transfer of apportioned property to trustees and dissolution of BurmaBranch 
Committee of Indian Red Cross Society.

</article>



<article><tid>394237</tid>
<number>3</number>Transfer of apportioned property to trustees and dissolution of 
Burma Branch Committee of Indian Red Cross Society. As soon as the 
High Court of Judicature at Rangoon has settled a scheme and made an 
order vesting the Fund in the body of trustees referred to in section 
 2 the Managing Body of the Indian Red Cross Society shall transfer the 
Fund to the said body of trustees and thereupon the Burma Provincial 
Committee of the Indian Red Cross Society, known as the Indian Red 
Cross Society, Burma Branch, shall be dissolved and all property of or 
belonging to that Committee,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>100</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section (2).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for Part 
B States".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

including the unexpended balance, if any, of any moneys distributed to 
that Committee under section 8 of the Indian Red Cross Society Act, 
 <year>1920</year> (15 of <year>1920</year>), shall be transferred to and shall vest in the said 
body of trustees to be held by them in the same manner and, subject to 
the scheme settled by the said High Court, for the same purposes as 
such property was held by that Committee.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Cesser of provisions of Indian Red Cross Society Act, <year>1920</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>36005</tid>
<number>4</number>Cesser of provisions of Indian Red Cross Society Act, <year>1920</year>. On 
the making of the vesting order referred to in section 3 the 
provisions of the Indian Red Cross Society Act, <year>1920</year> (15 of <year>1920</year>), and 
of any rules made thereunder relating to Branch Committees in the Sta- 
tes, their constitution, powers or functions, their representation on 
the Managing Body of the Indian Red Cross Society, and their right to 
receive a proportion of the income of property vested in the Society, 
shall cease to have effect in respect of the Province of Burma and of 
the Indian Red Cross Society, Burma Branch Committee.
</article>



 </act>