<act><title>


    The Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Rules, 19761</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Rules, 1976.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the 
      Bonded Labour System (Abolition) Act, 1976 (19 of 1976);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  “District 
      Vigilance Committee” means a Vigilance Committee constituted for a 
      district under sub-section (1) of section 13;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  “Section” means a 
      section of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>  “Sub-Divisional 
      Vigilance Committee” means a Vigilance Com­mittee constituted for a 
      sub-division under sub-section (1) of section 13.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Term of Office, and vacation of seat, of members of District Vigilance 
    Committee.—<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every member of a District Vigilance Committee, nominated under clauses (b), 
    (c), (d) and (e) of sub-section (2 of section 13) shall hold office for a 
    period of two years from the date on which his nomination is notified in the 
    Official Gazette and shall, on the expiry of the said period, continue to 
    hold office until his successor is nominated and shall also be eligible for 
    re-nomination.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every member referred to in sub-rule (1)—
 
 <subsection>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>  
      may, by giving notice in writing of not less than 30 days to the authority 
      which nominated him, resign his office and, on such resignation being 
      accepted or on the expiry of the notice period of 30 days, whichever is 
      earlier, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  Shall be deemed to 
      have vacated his office—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  if he fails to 
        attend three consecutive meetings of the District Committee without 
        obtaining leave of the Chairman of such absence:
 
Provided that the 
        authority, which nominated him may, if it is satisfied that such member 
        was prevented by sufficient cause from attending the three consecutive 
        meetings of the Committee, re­store him to membership;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>  if he becomes 
        subject to any of the following disqualifica­tions, namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>1</number> is adjudged 
        involvement;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>2</number> is declared to be 
        of unsound mind by a competent court;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>3</number> is convicted of 
        an offence which, in the opinion of the authority, which nominated him, 
        involves moral turpitude;
</subsubsubsection></subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  may be removed 
      from office, if the authority, which nominated such member, is of the 
      opinion that such member has ceased to represent the interest to represent 
      which he was nominated:
 

      Provided that a member shall not be removed from office under this Clause 
      unless a reasonable opportunity is given to him for showing cause against 
      such removal.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    member, nominated to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for the 
    unexpired portion of the term of his predecessor.






 
 <subsection>

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>  
      may, be giving notice in writing of not less than 30 days, to the 
      authority which nominated him, resign his office and, on such resignation 
      being accepted or on the expiry of the notice period of 30 days, whichever 
      is earlier, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  shall be deemed to 
      have vacated his office—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  if he fails to 
        attend three consecutive meetings of the Sub-Divisional Vigilance 
        Committee without obtaining leave of the Chairman of such Committee for 
        such absence:
 
Provided that the 
        authority which nominated him may, if it is satisfied that such member 
        was prevented by sufficient cause from attending three consecutive 
        meetings of the committee restore him to membership;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> if he becomes 
        subject to any of the following disqualific­ations namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>1</number>  is adjudged 
        insolvent;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>2</number>  is declared to 
        be of unsound mind by a competent court;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>3</number>  is convicted of 
        an offence which, in the opinion of the authority which nominated him, 
        involves moral turpitude;
</subsubsubsection></subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> may be removed from 
      office, if the authority which nominated such member is of the opinion 
      that such member has ceased to represent the interest to represent which 
      he was nominated:
 

      Provided that a member shall not be removed from officer under this clause 
      unless a reasonable opportunity is given to him for showing cause against 
      such removal.
</subsection>






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Term of office, and vacation of seat, of members of Sub-Divisional Vigilance 
    Committee.—<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every member of a Sub-Divisional Vigilance Committee, nominated under 
    clauses (b), (c), (d) and (e) of sub-section (3) of section 13 shall hold 
    office for a period of two years from the date on which his nomination is 
    notified in the Official Gazette and shall, on the expiry of the said 
    period, continue to hold office until his successor is nominated and shall 
    also be eligible for re-nomination.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every member referred to in sub-rule (1)—
 
 <subsection>

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>  
      may, be giving notice in writing of not less than 30 days, to the 
      authority which nominated him, resign his office and, on such resignation 
      being accepted or on the expiry of the notice period of 30 days, whichever 
      is earlier, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  shall be 
      deemed to have vacated his office—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  if he fails 
        to attend three consecutive meetings of the Sub-Divisional Vigilance 
        Committee without obtaining leave of the Chairman of such Committee for 
        such absence:
 
Provided that the 
        authority which nominated him may, if it is satisfied that such member 
        was prevented by sufficient cause from attending three consecutive 
        meetings of the committee restore him to membership;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> if he becomes 
        subject to any of the following disqualific­ations namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>1</number>  is adjudged 
        insolvent;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>2</number>  is declared 
        to be of unsound mind by a competent court;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>3</number>  is 
        convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the authority which 
        nominated him, involves moral turpitude;
</subsubsubsection></subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> may be removed from 
      office, if the authority which nominated such member is of the opinion 
      that such member has ceased to represent the interest to represent which 
      he was nominated:
 

      Provided that a member shall not be removed from officer under this clause 
      unless a reasonable opportunity is given to him for showing cause against 
      such removal.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    member nominated to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for the 
    unexpired portion of the term of his predecessor.





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Prescribed authority under sub-section (6) of section 6.—An 
    application under sub-section (6) of section 6 for restoration of possession 
    of any property referred to in sub-section (4) or sub-section (5) of that 
    section shall be made to the Executive Magis­trate, on whom the powers of a 
    Judicial Magistrate of the first class or of the second class have been 
    conferred under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 21, and within the local limits 
    of whose jurisdiction the said property is, or the applicant has reason to 
    believe is, situated at the time of making the application:
 

    Provided that where there are two Executive Magistrates, on one of whom the 
    powers of a Judicial Magistrate of the first class and on the other the 
    powers of a Judicial Magistrate of the second class have been conferred 
    under sub-section (1), of sec­tion 21 having jurisdiction to entertain the 
    application for restoration of possession of property referred to in 
    sub-rule (1), the application shall be made to the Executive Magistrate on 
    whom the powers of a Judicial Magistrate of the second class have been 
    conferred.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Time within which an application under sub-section (6) of section 6 is to be 
    made.—An 
    application under sub-section (6) of section 6 for restoration of possession 
    of any property re­ferred to in sub-section (4) or sub-section (5) of that 
    section shall be made within a period of ninety days from the date on which 
    these rules come into force.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Records to be maintained by District Vigilance Committees to ensure the 
    implementation of the provisions of the Act and Rules.—In 
    order to ensure the implementation of the Act and the Rules, every District 
    Vigilance Committee shall maintain the following registers in respect of 
    freed bonded labour within the local limits of its jurisdiction, namely:—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>  a register 
      containing the names and addresses of freed bonded labour;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  a register 
      containing statistics relating to the vocation, occupation and income of 
      every freed bonded labour;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  a register 
      containing details of the benefits which the freed bonded labour are 
      receiving, including benefits in the form of land, inputs for agriculture, 
      training in handicrafts and allied occupations, loans at different rates 
      of interest or employment in urban or non-urban area;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>  a register 
      containing details of cases under sub-section (6) of section (6) 
      sub-section (2) of section 8, sub-section (2) of section 9, section 16, 
      section 17, section 18, section 19 and section 20.
</section>

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
 Subs. by S.O. 1755, 
    dated 12th March, 1983.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Subs. by G.S.R. 
    1455, dated 16th November, 1978.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 Subs. by S.O.1755, 
    dated 12th March, 1983.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
 Subs. by G.S.R. 
    1455, dated 16th November, 1978.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> 
 Subs. by S.O.1755, 
    dated 12th March, 1983.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> 
 Subs. by G.S.R. 
    1455, dated 16th November, 1978.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>