<act><tid>1055865</tid>
<title>THE MIZORAM UNIVERSITY ACT, <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 8 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 25th April, <year>2000</year>]

An Act to establish and incorporate a teaching and affiliating 
University in the State of Mizoram and to provide for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>440134</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>618257</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Mizoram University Act, <year>2000</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>351281</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1150382</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder, 
unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1444191</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1098447</tid>
<number>b</number>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are designated 
as academic staff by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>299924</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1173503</tid>
<number>d</number>" College Development Council" means the College Development 
Council of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>395062</tid>
<number>e</number>" College" means a College maintained by, or admitted to the 
privileges of, the University;

</section>

<section><tid>39095</tid>
<number>f</number>" Court" means the Court of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1862081</tid>
<number>g</number>" Department" means a Department of Studies and includes a Centre 
of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>1703923</tid>
<number>h</number>" distance education system" means the system of imparting 
education through any means of communication, such as broadcasting, 
telecasting, correspondence courses, seminars, contact programmes or 
the combination of any two or more such means;

</section>

<section><tid>310298</tid>
<number>i</number>" employee" means any person appointed by the University and 
includes teachers and other staff of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>921634</tid>
<number>j</number>" Executive Council" means the Executive Council of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>834180</tid>
<number>k</number>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life for the 
students of the University, or of a College or an Institution, 
maintained by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1759426</tid>
<number>l</number>" Institution" means an academic institution, not being a College, 
maintained by, or admitted to the privileges of, the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1709799</tid>
<number>m</number>" North- Eastern Hill University" means the University established 
under section 3 of the North- Eastern Hill University Act, <year>1973</year> (24 of  
  <year>1973</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1247796</tid>
<number>n</number>" Principal" means the Head of a College or an Institution 
maintained by the University and includes, where there is no 
Principal, the person for the time being duly appointed to act as 
Principal, and in the absence of the Principal, or the acting Pri 
cipal, a Vice- Principal duly appointed as such;

</section>

<section><tid>854725</tid>
<number>o</number>" recognised Institution" means an institution of higher learning 
recognised by the University within the State of Mizoram;

</section>

<section><tid>1421787</tid>
<number>p</number>" recognised teachers" means such persons as may be recognised by 
the University for the purpose of imparting instructions in a College 
or an Institution admitted to the privileges of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1301462</tid>
<number>q</number>" Regulations" means the Regulations made by any authority of the 
University under this Act for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>259793</tid>
<number>r</number>" School" means a School of Studies of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1875329</tid>
<number>s</number>" Statutes" and" Ordinances" mean, respectively, the Statutes and 
the Ordinances of the University for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>793304</tid>
<number>t</number>" teachers of the University" means Professors, Readers, Lecturers 
and such other persons as may be appointed for imparting instruction 
or conducting research in the University or in any College or 
Institution maintained by the University and are desi nated as 
teachers by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>214304</tid>
<number>u</number>" University" means the Mizoram University established and 
incorporated as a University under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1479953</tid>
<number>v</number>" Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice- Chancellor" mean, respectively, 
the Vice- Chancellor and Pro- Vice- Chancellor of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1723330</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of the University.-
<section><tid>823686</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established a  
University by the name of" Mizoram University".

</section>

<section><tid>888268</tid>
<number>2</number>The headquarters of the University shall be at Aizawl.

</section>

<section><tid>1787353</tid>
<number>3</number>The first Vice- Chancellor and the first members of the Court, the 
Executive Council, the Academic Council and all persons who may 
hereafter become such officers or members, so long as they continue to 
hold such office or membership, are hereby consti uted a body 
corporate by the name of" Mizoram University".

</section>

<section><tid>1640645</tid>
<number>4</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common seal 
and shall sue and be sued by the said name.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1553509</tid>
<number>4</number>Objects of the University.- The objects of the University shall be 
to disseminate and advance knowledge by providing instructional and 
research facilities in such branches of learning as it may deem fit; 
to make provisions for integrated courses in hum nities, natural and 
physical sciences, social sciences, forestry and other allied 
disciplines in the educational programmes of the University; to take 
appropriate measures for promoting innovations in teaching- learning 
process, inter- disciplinary studies and research; to educate and 
train manpower for the development of the State of Mizoram; and to 
pay special attention to the improvement of the social and economic 
conditions and welfare of the people of that State, their 
intellectual, academic and cultu al development.


</article>



<article><tid>294595</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of the University.- The University shall have the following 
powers, namely:-
<section><tid>1482084</tid>
<number>i</number>to provide for instructions in such branches of learning as the 
University may, from time to time, determine and to make provisions 
for research and for the advancement and dissemination of knowledge;

</section>

<section><tid>561579</tid>
<number>ii</number>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University may 
determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or other 
academic distinctions on the basis of examinations, evaluation or any 
other method of testing, on persons, and to withdraw any such 
diplomas, certificates, degrees or other academic distinctions for 
good and sufficient cause;

</section>

<section><tid>127441</tid>
<number>iii</number>to organise and to undertake extramural studies, training and 
extension services;

</section>

<section><tid>112891</tid>
<number>iv</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the manner 
prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>1048815</tid>
<number>v</number>to provide facilities through the distance education system to 
such persons as it may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1717348</tid>
<number>vi</number>to institute Principalships, Professorships, Readerships, 
Lecturerships and other teaching or academic positions, required by 
the University and to appoint persons to such Principalships, 
Professorships, Readerships, Lecturerships or other teaching or 
academic positions;

</section>

<section><tid>1392436</tid>
<number>vii</number>to recognise an institution of higher learning for such purposes 
as the University may determine and to withdraw such recognition;

</section>

<section><tid>600629</tid>
<number>viii</number>to recognise persons for imparting instructions in any College 
or Institution admitted to the privileges of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>800098</tid>
<number>ix</number>to appoint persons working in any other University or 
organisation as teachers of the University for a specified period;

</section>

<section><tid>573908</tid>
<number>x</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts and to make 
appointments thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>194980</tid>
<number>xi</number>to co- operate or collaborate or associate with any other 
University or authority or institution of higher learning in such 
manner and for such purposes as the University may determine;

<subsection><tid>493158</tid>
<number>xii</number>to establish, with the prior approval of the Central Government, 
such Centres and specialised laboratories or other units for research 
and instruction as are, in the opinion of the University necessary for 
the furtherance of its objects;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1921377</tid>
<number>xiii</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, studentships, 
medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1594994</tid>
<number>xiv</number>to establish and maintain Colleges, Institutions and Halls;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1959140</tid>
<number>xv</number>to make provision for research and advisory services and for that 
purpose to enter into such arrangements with other institutions, 
industrial or other organisations, as the University may deem 
necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1310385</tid>
<number>xvi</number>to organise and conduct refresher courses, workshops, seminars 
and other programmes for teachers, evaluators and other academic 
staff;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1274765</tid>
<number>xvii</number>to admit to its privileges colleges and institutions within the 
State of Mizoram not maintained by the University; to withdraw all or 
any of those privileges in accordance with such conditions as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes; to recognise, gu de, supervise, and 
control Halls not maintained by the University and other accommodation 
for students, and to withdraw any such recognition;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1011460</tid>
<number>xviii</number>to appoint on contract or otherwise visiting Professors, 
Emeritus Professors, Consultants, Scholars and such other persons who 
may contribute to the advancement of the objects of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1821524</tid>
<number>xix</number>to confer autonomous status on a College or an Institution or a 
Department, as the case may be, in accordance with the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>632902</tid>
<number>xx</number>to determine standards of admission to the University, which may 
include examination, evaluation or any other method of testing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>6975</tid>
<number>xxi</number>to demand and receive payment of fees and other charges;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>322668</tid>
<number>xxii</number>to supervise the residences of the students of the University 
and to make arrangements for promoting their health and general 
welfare;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1466016</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>to lay down conditions of service of all categories of 
employees, including their code of conduct;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1670089</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among the students and the 
employees, and to take such disciplinary measures in this regard as 
may be deemed by the University to be necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>841557</tid>
<number>xxv</number>to make arrangements for promoting the health and general 
welfare of the employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1841746</tid>
<number>xxvi</number>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts and to acquire, 
hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable or immovable, 
including trust and endowment properties for the purposes of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>269307</tid>
<number>xxvii</number>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government, on the 
security of the property of the University, money for the purposes of 
the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1039248</tid>
<number>xxviii</number>to do all such other acts and things as may be necessary, 
incidental or conducive to the attainment of all or any of its 
objects.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1275740</tid>
<number>6</number>Transfer of properties of North- Eastern Hill University.- On and 
from the commencement of this Act, all properties of the North- Eastern 
Hill University in the State of Mizoram shall stand transferred to, 
and vest in, the University and shall be applied to the objects for 
which the University is established.


</article>



<article><tid>1646867</tid>
<number> 7</number> Jurisdiction.-
<section><tid>1988906</tid>
<number>1</number>The jurisdiction of the University shall extend  
to the whole of the State of Mizoram.

</section>

<section><tid>194214</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the commencement of this Act, all Colleges, 
Institutions, Schools and Departments affiliated to, or admitted to 
the privileges of, or maintained by, the North- Eastern Hill University 
shall stand affiliated to, or admitted to the privilege of, or 
maintained by, the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1104784</tid>
<number>3</number>On and from the date of commencement of this Act, the 
North- Eastern Hill University shall cease to exercise its jurisdiction 
in the State of Mizoram.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1628123</tid>
<number>8</number>University open to all classes, castes and creed.- The University 
shall be open to persons of either sex and of whatever caste, creed, 
race or class, and it shall not be lawful for the University to adopt 
or impose on any person, any test whatsoever of religious belief or 
profession in order to entitle him to be appointed as a teacher of the 
University or to hold any other office therein or be admitted as a 
student in the University or to graduate thereat or to enjoy or 
exercise any privilege thereof:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent the 
University from making special provisions for the employment or 
admission of women, physically handicapped or of persons belonging to 
the weaker sections of the society and, in particul r, of the 
Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes.



</article>



<article><tid>152224</tid>
<number> 9</number> The Visitor.-
<section><tid>1198135</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor of  
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1685273</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor may, from time to time, appoint one or more persons to 
review the work and progress of the University, including Colleges and 
Institutions maintained by it, and to submit a report thereon; and 
upon receipt of that report, the Visitor may, after obtaining the 
views of the Executive Council thereon through the Vice- Chancellor, 
take such action and issue such directions as he considers necessary 
in respect of any of the matters dealt within the report and the 
University shall be bound to com ly with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>1880060</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be made 
by such person or persons as he may direct, of the University, its 
buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any College or 
Institution maintained by the University or admitted to its 
privileges; and also of the examinations, teaching and other work 
conducted or done by the University and to cause an inquiry to be made 
in like manner in respect of any matter connected with the 
administration or finances of the University, Colleges or 
Institutions.

</section>

<section><tid>1083544</tid>
<number>4</number>The Visitor shall, in every matter referred to in sub- section (2), 
give notice of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be 
made,-

<subsection><tid>496644</tid>
<number>a</number>to the University, if such inspection or inquiry is to be made in 
respect of the University or any College or Institution maintained by 
it, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1640166</tid>
<number>b</number>to the management of the College or Institution, if the inspection 
or inquiry is to be made in respect of College or Institution admitted 
to the privileges of the University, and the University or the 
management, as the case may be, shall have the right to make such 
representations to the Visitor, as it may consider necessary.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1496916</tid>
<number>5</number>After considering the representations, if any, made by the 
University or the management, as the case may be, the Visitor may 
cause to be made such inspection or inquiry as is referred to in 
sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>60053</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by the 
Visitor, the University or the management shall be entitled to appoint 
a representative, who shall have the right to be present and be heard 
at such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>1974739</tid>
<number>7</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in respect 
of the University or any College or Institution maintained by it, 
address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such 
inspection or inquiry together with such views and adv ce with regard 
to the action to be taken thereon, as the Visitor may be pleased to 
offer, and on receipt of address made by the Visitor, the 
Vice- Chancellor shall communicate, to the Executive Council, the views 
of the Visitor with such advice as the Vis tor may offer upon the 
action to be taken thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1128492</tid>
<number>8</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in respect 
of any College or Institution admitted to the privileges of the 
University, address the management concerned through the 
Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such inspection r 
inquiry, his views thereon and such advice as he may be pleased to 
offer upon the action to be taken thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1607636</tid>
<number>9</number>The Executive Council or the management, as the case may be, shall 
communicate, through the Vice- Chancellor to the Visitor such action, 
if any, as it proposes to take or has been taken upon the result of 
such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>945615</tid>
<number>10</number>Where, the Executive Council or the management, does not, within 
a reasonable time, take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the 
Visitor may, after considering any explanation furnished or 
representation made by the Executive Council or the m nagement, issue 
such directions as he may think fit and the Executive Council or the 
management, as the case may be, shall comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>905704</tid>
<number>11</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this section, 
the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of the 
University which is not in conformity with the Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances:
Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon the 
Registrar to show cause why such an order should not be made, and, if 
any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the 
same.


</section>

<section><tid>929603</tid>
<number>12</number>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be prescribed by 
the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1116223</tid>
<number> 10</number> Officers of the University.- The following shall be the officers 
of the University:-
<section><tid>712763</tid>
<number>1</number>the Vice- Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>24112</tid>
<number>2</number>the Pro- Vice- Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>238052</tid>
<number>3</number>the Deans of Schools;

</section>

<section><tid>1895159</tid>
<number>4</number>the Registrar;

</section>

<section><tid>67221</tid>
<number>5</number>the Finance Officer;

</section>

<section><tid>1887839</tid>
<number>6</number>the Librarian; and

</section>

<section><tid>1074823</tid>
<number>7</number>such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes to be 
officers of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>952035</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Vice- Chancellor.-
<section><tid>1773476</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed  
by the Visitor in such manner and on such terms and conditions of 
service as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1364653</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and academic 
officer of the University and shall exercise general supervision and 
control over the affairs of the University and give effect to the 
decisions of all the authorities of the Universi y.

</section>

<section><tid>1061802</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate action 
is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any 
authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to 
such authority the action taken by him on such ma ter:
Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such 
action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the 
Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that any person in the service of the University who 
is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this 
sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action to the 
Executive Council within three months from the date on which decision 
on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the Executive 
Council may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by the 
Vice- Chancellor.


</section>

<section><tid>211181</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor, if he is of the opinion that any decision of 
any authority of the University is beyond the powers of the authority 
conferred by the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or the 
Ordinances or that any decision taken is not in the nterest of the 
University, may ask the authority concerned to review its decision 
within sixty days of such decision and if the authority refuses to 
review the decision either in whole or in part or no decision is taken 
by it within the said period of si ty days, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>313047</tid>
<number>5</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and perform 
such other duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes or the 
Ordinances.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Pro- Vice- Chancellor.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>58596</tid>
<number>12</number>The Pro- Vice- Chancellor.- The Pro- Vice- Chancellor shall be 
appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform 
such duties, as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Deans of Schools.

</article>



<article><tid>1807171</tid>
<number>13</number>The Deans of Schools.- Every Dean of a School shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Registrar.

</article>



<article><tid>547424</tid>
<number> 14</number> The Registrar.-
<section><tid>758302</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  
manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1905931</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreement, sign 
documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University and 
shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Finance Officer.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1340002</tid>
<number>15</number>The Finance Officer.- The Finance Officer shall be appointed in 
such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as 
may be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Librarian.

</article>



<article><tid>1034436</tid>
<number>16</number>The Librarian.- The Librarian shall be appointed in such manner 
and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Other Officers.

</article>



<article><tid>290892</tid>
<number>17</number>Other officers.- The manner of appointment and powers and duties 
of the other officers of the University shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Authorities of the University.

</article>



<article><tid>119959</tid>
<number> 18</number> Authorities of the University.- The following shall be the 
authorities of the University:-
<section><tid>1306509</tid>
<number>1</number>the Court;

</section>

<section><tid>1223037</tid>
<number>2</number>the Executive Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1827491</tid>
<number>3</number>the Academic Council;

</section>

<section><tid>385583</tid>
<number>4</number>the College Development Council;

</section>

<section><tid>389395</tid>
<number>5</number>the Board of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>632266</tid>
<number>6</number>the Finance Committee; and

</section>

<section><tid>1801125</tid>
<number>7</number>such other authorities as may be declared by the Statutes to be 
the authorities of the University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Court.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>890019</tid>
<number> 19</number> The Court.-
<section><tid>988400</tid>
<number>1</number>The constitution of the Court and the term of  
office of its members shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1183353</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have the 
following powers and functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1704714</tid>
<number>a</number>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and programmes of 
the University and to suggest measures for the improvement and 
development of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1309721</tid>
<number>b</number>to consider and pass resolutions on the annual report and the 
annual accounts of the University and the audit report on such 
accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>992211</tid>
<number>c</number>to advise the Visitor in respect of any matter which may be 
referred to it for advice; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>382759</tid>
<number>d</number>to perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

TheExecutive Council.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>594011</tid>
<number> 20</number> The Executive Council.-
<section><tid>1128547</tid>
<number>1</number>The Executive Council shall be the  
principal executive body of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>97424</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Executive Council, the term of office of 
its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Academic Council.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>498598</tid>
<number> 21</number> The Academic Council.-
<section><tid>1842333</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Council shall be the  
principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, co- ordinate 
and exercise general supervision over the academic po icies of the 
University.

</section>

<section><tid>357026</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Academic Council, the term of office of 
its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The College Development Council.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>844521</tid>
<number> 22</number> The College Development Council.-
<section><tid>775856</tid>
<number>1</number>The College Development  
Council shall be responsible for admitting Colleges to the privileges 
of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1118394</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the College Development Council, the term of 
office of its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed 
by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Boards of Studies.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>391646</tid>
<number>23</number>The Boards of Studies.- The constitution, powers and functions of 
the Boards of Studies shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

The Finance Committee.

</article>



<article><tid>1724120</tid>
<number>24</number>The Finance Committee.- The constitution, powers and functions of 
the Finance Committee shall be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Other authorities.

</article>



<article><tid>953560</tid>
<number>25</number>Other authorities of the University.- The constitution, powers and 
functions of other authorities, as may be declared by the Statutes to 
be the authorities of the University, shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Power to make Statutes.

</article>



<article><tid>666002</tid>
<number> 26</number> Powers to make Statutes.- Subject to the provisions of this Act, 
the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:-
<section><tid>332010</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, powers and functions of authorities and other 
bodies of the University, as may be constituted from time to time;

</section>

<section><tid>1275215</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment and continuance in office of the members of the 
said authorities and bodies, the filling up of vacancies of members, 
and all other matters relating to those authorities and other bodies 
for which it may be necessary or desirable to pr vide;

</section>

<section><tid>1650420</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of the 
University and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>551479</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of teachers, academic staff and other employees of 
the University, their emoluments and conditions of service;

</section>

<section><tid>201132</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of teachers, academic staff working in any other 
University or organisation for a specific period for undertaking a 
joint project;

</section>

<section><tid>1158663</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of service of employees including provisions 
pension, insurance and provident fund, the manner of termination of 
service and disciplinary action relating to employees of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>990192</tid>
<number>g</number>the principles governing the seniority of service of the employees 
of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>969140</tid>
<number>h</number>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute between 
employees or students and the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1518280</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for appeal to the Executive Council by any employee 
or student against the action of any officer or authority of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>579651</tid>
<number>j</number>the conferment of autonomous status on a College or an Institution 
or a Department;

</section>

<section><tid>93400</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment and abolition of Schools, Departments, Centres, 
Halls, Colleges and Institutions;

</section>

<section><tid>275181</tid>
<number>l</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>1202238</tid>
<number>m</number>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other 
academic distinctions;

</section>

<section><tid>444936</tid>
<number>n</number>the conditions under which Colleges and Institutions may be 
admitted to the privileges of the University and the withdrawal of 
such privileges;

</section>

<section><tid>149656</tid>
<number>o</number>the management of Colleges and Institutions established by the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>868264</tid>
<number>p</number>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or officers of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1041865</tid>
<number>q</number>the maintenance of discipline among the employees and students;

</section>

<section><tid>249753</tid>
<number>r</number>all other matters which by this Act are to be or may be provided 
for by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Statutes how to be made.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1200232</tid>
<number> 27</number> Statutes how to be made.-
<section><tid>1239570</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes are those set out  
in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>630956</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Council may, from time to time, make new or 
additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in 
sub- section (1):
Provided that the Executive Council shall not make, amend or repeal 
any Statutes affecting the status, powers or constitution of any 
authority of the University until such authority has been given an 
opportunity of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed 
changes, and any opinion so expressed shall be considered by the 
Executive Council.


</section>

<section><tid>237101</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statute or addition to the Statutes or any amendment or 
repeal of a Statute shall require the assent of the Visitor who may 
assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the Executive Council 
for re- consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1742387</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>927127</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- sections, 
the Visitor may make new or additional Statutes or amend or repeal the 
Statutes referred to in sub- section (1), during the period of three 
years immediately after the commencement of t is Act:
Provided that the Visitor may, on the expiry of the said period of 
three years, make, within one year from the date of such expiry, such 
detailed Statutes as he may consider necessary and such detailed 
Statutes shall be laid before both Houses of Parliam nt.


</section>

<section><tid>1468146</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- sections, 
the Visitor may direct the University to make provisions in the 
Statutes in respect of any matter specified by him and if the 
Executive Council is unable to implement such direction wi hin sixty 
days of its receipt, the Visitor may, after considering the reasons, 
if any, communicated by the Executive Council for its inability to 
comply with such direction, make or amend the Statutes suitably.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Power to make Ordinances.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1177389</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to make Ordinances.-
<section><tid>778001</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this  
Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>11391</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their enrolment as 
such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>33745</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, diplomas and 
certificates of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>169447</tid>
<number>c</number>the medium of instruction and examination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>98364</tid>
<number>d</number>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic 
distinctions, qualifications for the same and the means to be taken 
relating to the granting and obtaining of the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>407935</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the University and 
for admission to the examinations, degrees and diplomas of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1741471</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions for award of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>39073</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of examinations, including the term of office and 
manner of appointment and the duties of examining bodies, examiners 
and moderators;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>630149</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of the students of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>389031</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for the 
residence, discipline and teaching of women students and the 
prescribing of special courses of studies for them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1144895</tid>
<number>j</number>the establishment of Centres of Studies, Boards of Studies, 
Specialised Laboratories and other Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1158213</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other 
Universities, institutions and other agencies including learned bodies 
or associations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1291307</tid>
<number>l</number>the creation, composition and functions of any other body which is 
considered necessary for improving the academic life of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1295508</tid>
<number>m</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, studentships, medals 
and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>388011</tid>
<number>n</number>the supervision of management of Colleges and Institutions 
admitted to the privileges of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1695549</tid>
<number>o</number>the setting up of a machinery for redressal of grievances of 
employees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1680710</tid>
<number>p</number>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes, are to be or 
may be, provided for by the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>552739</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor with the 
previous approval of the Central Government and the Ordinances so made 
may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by the Executive 
Council in the manner prescribed by the Statut s.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Regulations.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>604740</tid>
<number>29</number>Regulations.- The authorities of the University may make 
Regulations, consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances 
for the conduct of their own business and that of the Committees, if 
any, appointed by them and not provided for by this Ac, the Statutes 
or the Ordinances, in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Annual Report.

</article>



<article><tid>459715</tid>
<number> 30</number> Annual report.-
<section><tid>1105070</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University shall be  
prepared under the direction of the Executive Council, which shall 
include, among other matters, the steps taken by the University 
towards the fulfilment of its objects and shall be subm tted to the 
Court on or after such date as may be prescribed by the Statutes and 
the Court shall consider the report in its annual meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1832958</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court shall submit the annual report to the Visitor along with 
its comments, if any.

</section>

<section><tid>988046</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the annual report, as prepared under sub- section (1), 
shall also be submitted to the Central Government, which shall, as 
soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both Houses of 
Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Annual accounts.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1067064</tid>
<number> 31</number> Annual accounts.-
<section><tid>493745</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of the  
University shall be prepared under the directions of the Executive 
Council and shall, once at least every year and at intervals of not 
more than fifteen months, be audited by the Compt oller and 
Auditor- General of India or by such persons as he may authorise in 
this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1918915</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report 
thereon shall be submitted to the Court and the Visitor along with the 
observations of the Executive Council.

</section>

<section><tid>835968</tid>
<number>3</number>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts shall 
be brought to the notice of the Court and the observations of the 
Court, if any, shall, after being considered by the Executive Council, 
be submitted to the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1771937</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report as 
submitted to the Visitor, shall also be submitted to the Central 
Government, which shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid 
before both Houses of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1675207</tid>
<number>5</number>The audited annual accounts after having been laid before both 
Houses of Parliament shall be published in the Gazette of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Returns and information.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>820945</tid>
<number>32</number>Returns and information.- The University shall furnish to the 
Central Government such returns or other information with respect to 
its property or activities as the Central Government may, from time to 
time, require.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Transfer of services of certain employees of the North- Eastern HillUniversity.

</article>



<article><tid>212930</tid>
<number> 33</number> Transfer of services of certain employees of the North- Eastern 
Hill University.-
<section><tid>748966</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who, immediately before the  
commencement of this Act, is holding or discharging the duties of any 
post or office in connection with the affairs of the No th- Eastern 
Hill University in any area which on that date falls within the State 
of Mizoram shall be deemed to have been transferred to the services of 
the Mizoram University on the same terms and conditions and to the 
same rights and privileges as to p nsion, gratuity, provident fund and 
other matters as he would have been had under the North- Eastern Hill 
University Act, <year>1973</year> (24 of <year>1973</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1665771</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute between a person referred to in sub- section (1) and 
the University shall, at the request of such person, be referred to a 
Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions of sub- sections (2), (3), 
 (4) and (5) of section 34 shall, as far as may e, apply to a reference 
made under this sub- section.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Conditions of service.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1170184</tid>
<number> 34</number> Conditions of service.-
<section><tid>1547713</tid>
<number>1</number>Every employee of the University shall  
be appointed under a written contract, which shall be lodged with the 
University and a copy of which shall be furnished to the employee 
concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>421632</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of the contract between the University and 
any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be referred to a 
Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member appointed by the 
Executive Council, one member nominated by the e ployee concerned and 
an umpire appointed by the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>249874</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Tribunal shall be final, and no suit shall lie 
in any civil court in respect of the matters decided by the Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>1152642</tid>
<number>4</number>Every request made by the employee under sub- section (2), shall be 
deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of this 
section within the meaning of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 
 <year>1996</year> (26 of <year>1996</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1228142</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure for regulating the work of the Tribunal shall be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases againststudents.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>609519</tid>
<number> 35</number> Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases against 
students.-
<section><tid>749160</tid>
<number>1</number>Any student or candidate for an examination whose name  
has been removed from the rolls of the University by the orders or 
resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Co mittee or Examination 
Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred from 
appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one 
year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or 
copy of such resolution by him, appe l to the Executive Council and 
the Executive Council may confirm, modify or reverse the decision of 
the Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>70762</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by the 
University against a student shall, at the request of such student, be 
referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions of 
sub- sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of section 34 shall, as far as may 
be, apply to a reference made under this sub- section.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Right to appeal.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>822509</tid>
<number>36</number>Right to appeal.- Every employee or student of the University or 
of a College or Institution maintained by the University or admitted 
to its privileges shall, notwithstanding anything contained in this 
Act, have a right to appeal within such time as m y be prescribed by 
the Statutes, to the Executive Council against the decision of any 
officer or authority of the University or of the Principal or the 
management of any College or an Institution, as the case may be, and 
thereupon the Executive Council m y confirm, modify or reverse the 
decision appealed against.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provident and pension funds.

</article>



<article><tid>1135866</tid>
<number> 37</number> Provident and pension funds.-
<section><tid>115777</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall constitute  
for the benefit of its employees such provident or pension fund or 
provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such manner and 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed b the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>403840</tid>
<number>2</number>Where such provident fund or pension fund has been so constituted, 
the Central Government may declare that the provisions of the 
Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (28 of <year>1925</year>), shall apply to such fund, as 
if it were a Government provident fund.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and bodies.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1625228</tid>
<number>38</number>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and 
bodies.- If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly 
elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any 
authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Filling of casual vacancies.

</article>



<article><tid>1509817</tid>
<number>39</number>Filling of casual vacancies.- All casual vacancies among the 
members (other than ex officio members) of any authority or other body 
of the University shall be filled, as soon as may be, by the person or 
body who appoints, elects or co- opts the member hose place has become 
vacant and person appointed, elected or co- opted to a casual vacancy 
shall be a member of such authority or body for the residue of the 
term for which the person whose place he fills would have been a 
member.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not invalidated byvacancies.

</article>



<article><tid>1312166</tid>
<number>40</number>Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not invalidated 
by vacancies.- No act or proceedings of any authority or other body of 
the University shall be invalid merely by reason of the existence of a 
vacancy or vacancies among its members.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Protection of action taken in good faith.

</article>



<article><tid>146493</tid>
<number>41</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit or other legal 
proceedings shall lie against any officer or other employee of the 
University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done in pursuance of any of the provisions of th s Act, the Statutes 
or the Ordinances.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Mode of proof of University record.

</article>



<article><tid>419110</tid>
<number>42</number>Mode of proof of University record.- A copy of any receipt, 
application, notice, order, proceeding, resolution of any authority or 
Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the 
University, or any entry in any register duly maint ined by the 
University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima 
facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, 
proceeding, resolution, or documents or the existence of entry in the 
register and shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and 
transactions therein where the original thereof would, if produced, 
have been admissible in evidence, notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>) or in any other law for 
the time being in force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Power to remove difficulties.

</article>



<article><tid>487506</tid>
<number> 43</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>498819</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made under this section after the 
expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>199428</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Transitional provisions.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1439494</tid>
<number> 44</number> Transitional provisions.- Notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act and the Statutes,-
<section><tid>1682630</tid>
<number>a</number>the first Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed by the Visitor in 
such manner and on such conditions as may be deemed fit and each of 
the said officer shall hold office for such term, not exceeding five 
years as may be specified by the Visitor;

</section>

<section><tid>1058204</tid>
<number>b</number>the first Registrar and the first Finance Officer shall be 
appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers shall hold 
office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>1838923</tid>
<number>c</number>the first Court and the first Executive Council shall consist of 
not more than thirty members and eleven members, respectively, who 
shall be nominated by the Visitor and shall hold office for a term of 
three years;

</section>

<section><tid>1266578</tid>
<number>d</number>the first College Development Council shall consist of not more 
than ten members, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and they shall 
hold office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>235513</tid>
<number>e</number>the first Academic Council shall consist of not more than 
twenty- one members, who shall be nominated by the Visitor and they 
shall hold office for a term of three years:
Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or 
authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as 
the case may be, by the Visitor, and the person so appointed or 
nominated shall hold office for so long as the officer or m mber in 
whose place he is appointed or nominated would have held office, if 
such vacancy had not occurred.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Completion of coures of studueis in Colleges or Insitutionsaffiliated to the 
University.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>894239</tid>
<number>45</number>Completion of courses of studies in Colleges or Institutions 
affiliated to the University.- Notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, or in the Statutes or the Ordinances, any student of a 
College, Institution, School or Department, who, immedia ely before 
the admission of such College, Institution, School or Department, to 
the privileges of the University, was studying for a degree, diploma 
or certificate of the North- Eastern Hill University, shall be 
permitted by the University, to complete hi course for that degree, 
diploma or certificate, as the case may be, and the Mizoram University 
and such College, Institution, School or Department, shall provide for 
the instructions and examination of such student in accordance with 
the syllabus of stu ies of the North- Eastern Hill University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>46</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the OfficialGazette and 
to be laid before Parliament.

</article>



<article><tid>1935802</tid>
<number> 46</number> Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the 
Official Gazette and to be laid before Parliament.-
<section><tid>625045</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Statute,  
Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall be published in the 
Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>152189</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Statute, Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall 
be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
ollowing the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
agree in making any modification in the Statute, Ordinance or 
Regulation or both Houses agree that the Statute, Ordinance or 
Regulation should not be made, the Statute, Ordinance or R gulation 
shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification 
or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that Statute, Ordin nce or Regulation.

</section>

<section><tid>273112</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to make Statutes, Ordinances or Regulations shall 
include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier 
than the date of commencement of this Act, to the Statutes, Ordinances 
or Regulations or any of them but no retrospecti e effect shall be 
given to any Statute, Ordinance or Regulation so as to prejudicially 
affect the interests of any person to whom such Statute, Ordinance or 
Regulation may be applicable.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>47</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Amendment of Act 24 of <year>1973</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>288152</tid>
<number> 47</number> Amendment of Act 24 of <year>1973</year>.- In the North- Eastern Hill University 
Act, <year>1973</year>,-
<section><tid>1245234</tid>
<number>i</number>in section 1, in sub- section (2), for the words" Union territories 
of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram", the words" State of Arunachal 
Pradesh" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>145592</tid>
<number>ii</number>in section 2, in clause (l), for the words" Union territories of 
Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram", the words" State of Arunachal Pradesh" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1796430</tid>
<number>iii</number>in section 6, in sub- section (1), for the words" Union 
territories of Arunachal Pradesh and Mizoram", the words" State of 
Arunachal Pradesh" shall be substituted.


</section>

</article>



 </act>