<act> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Mines) Rules, 19891
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, 
application and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Payment of Undisbursed Wages (Mines) Rules, 1989.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules apply in 
respect of the payment of undisbursed wages to persons employed, either by the 
owner in any mine to which the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952), applies or in any 
oil-field.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They shall extend to 
the whole of India.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Mines) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Payment of Wages 
Act, 1936 (4 of 1936);
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “Chief Labour Commissioner 
(Central)” means an Officer appointed as such by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “employer” means the owner of 
the mine and includes a contractor, agent, manager or any other person 
responsible under section 3 of the Act for payment of wages and includes in the 
case of a deceased employer, his legal representative;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “family” means,—
 <subsection>
              <number>i</number>  in case of a male 
employee, his wife or wives and children, whether married or unmarried, his 
dependent parents and widow and children of his deceased son;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  in case of a female 
employee, her husband, her children, whether married or unmarried, her dependent 
parents, her husband’s dependent parents and widows and children of her deceased 
sons;
 </subsection></section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “Form” means a Form appended to 
these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “mine” means a mine as defined 
in clause (j) of section 2 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  “person employed” or “employed 
person” or “employee” means a person employed in a mine or an oilfield to whom 
the Act applies and includes, in the case of a deceased employed person, his 
legal representative;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  “prescribed authority” means, in 
case of—
 </section><section>
              <number>i</number>  mines covered under the 
provisions of the Mica Mines Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1946, the Limestone and 
Dolomite Labour Welfare Fund Act, 1972 and the Iron Ore Mines, Manganese Ore 
Mines and Chrome Ore Mines Welfare Fund Act, 1976, the Welfare Commissioner 
appointed under the provisions of the aforementioned Acts;
 <subsection>
             <number>ii</number>  mines other than those 
covered under clause (i), but owned or operated by the public sector 
undertakings of the Central Government or the State Government, the Chief 
Executive of the concerned public sector undertaking;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number>  all other mines not 
covered under clauses (i) and (ii) the concerned Regional Labour Commissioner 
(Central);
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  “section” means a section of 
the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  “undisbursed wages” means 
amounts payable to an employed person as wage which could not or cannot be paid 
on account of his death before payment or on account of his whereabouts not 
being known;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  words and expressions used in 
these rules and not defined herein shall have the same meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Act.
  
</subsection></section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Mines) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Nomination.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person who is already in employment on the date of the Payment of Undisbursed 
Wages (Mines) Rules, 1989, ordinarily within six months from such date, and a 
person who has been employed after the date of the commencement of the said 
rules, ordinarily within three months from the date he is employed, shall 
nominate a person conferring on him the right to receive all amounts payable to 
him as undisbursed wages, and such nomination shall be in Form I and submitted 
in duplicate by the employed person by personal service, after taking proper 
receipt thereof or by sending through registered post with acknowledgement due 
to the employer:
 
Provided that any 
nomination may be accepted after the expiry of the specified period, if the 
person satisfies the employer that he had sufficient grounds for not filing the 
nomination within such period and no nomination so accepted shall become invalid 
on the ground that it was filed after the expiry of the specified period.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Within thirty days 
from the receipt of the nomination under sub-rule (1), the employer shall get 
the service particulars of the employed person as mentioned in the form of 
nomination verified with reference to records of the mines and a duly attested 
copy of the Form I by the employer shall be given to the employed person.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, at the time of 
making a nomination an employed person has a family, the nomination shall not be 
in favour of a person other than the members of his family.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If at the time of 
making the nomination, the employed person has no family, the nomination may be 
made in favour of any person but as soon as the employed person subsequently 
acquires a family, such nomination shall become invalid forthwith and the 
employed person shall, within thirty days of acquiring a family, submit a fresh 
nomination in duplicate in Form II to the employer and thereafter the provisions 
of sub-rule (2) shall apply mutatis mutandis, as if it was made under 
sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the nominee 
predeceases an employed person, the interest of the nominee shall revert to the 
employed person who shall within a period of thirty days from the death of 
nominee make a fresh nomination in the manner hereinafter provided for.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A notice of 
modification of a nomination including cases where a nominee predeceases an 
employed person shall be submitted in duplicate in Form III to the employer in 
the manner specified in sub-rule (1) and thereafter the provisions of sub-rule 
(2) shall apply mutatis mutandis as if it was made under sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A nomination or a 
fresh nomination or a notice of modification of nomination shall be signed by 
the employed person or if illiterate, bear his thumb impression in the presence 
of two witnesses who shall also sign a declaration to that effect in the 
nomination/fresh nomination or a notice of modification of nomination as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A nomination or a 
fresh nomination or a notice of modification of nomination shall take effect 
from the date of receipt thereof by the employer.
 
 
</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Mines) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Register of 
nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer shall record and file all nominations, fresh nominations and 
notices of modification of nominations, as the case may be, in the register of 
nominations which shall be maintained chronologically by him in Form IV.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The register of 
nominations shall be maintained by the employer up-to-date and kept permanently 
at the work-spot or where the employer experiences difficulty in keeping them at 
the work-spot, at any other suitable place as may be approved by the prescribed 
authority in this behalf.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Mines) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Deposit of amounts of 
undisbursed wages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where all amounts payable as wages to a person employed in an establishment in 
relation to mines remain undisbursed because either no nomination has been made 
by the employed person or for any reasons, such amounts could not be paid to the 
nominee of the employed person until the expiry of three years from the date of 
same had become payable, all such amounts shall be deposited by the employer 
with the prescribed authority before the expiry of the fifteenth day after the 
last day of the said period of three years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The amounts referred 
to in sub-rule (1) shall be deposited by the employer through crossed demand 
draft obtained from any scheduled bank in India drawn in favour of the 
prescribed authority, and such demand draft shall be submitted by the employer 
to the prescribed authority together with relevant details in Form V by 
Registered Post.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Undisbursed Wages (Mines) Rules, 1989
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Manner of dealing with 
the undisbursed wages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The amount deposited with the prescribed authority shall remain with the 
prescribed authority for four years and be invested in the Central or State 
Government Securities or deposited in the nationalised banks.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As soon as possible, 
the prescribed authority will exhibit at least for fifteen days on the notice 
board of the mine(s) and shall also publish in any two newspapers circulating in 
the language commonly understood in the area of the mine(s) in which undisbursed 
wages were earned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The prescribed 
authority shall release the money to the nominee or to that person who has 
claims to this money and which has been decided by the competent 
authority/court.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The amount deposited 
shall, after a lapse of four years from the date the amount is deposited with 
the prescribed authority by the employer, be applied by the prescribed authority 
to meet the expenditure incurred in connection with the measures which in his 
opinion are expedient to promote the welfare of persons employed in mines and in 
particular to defray the cost of measures for the benefit of persons employed in 
the mines directed towards—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  the provision and improvement 
of educational facilities;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the provision and improvement 
of recreational facilities;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  the provision and improvement 
of family welfare including family planning;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  the provision and improvement of 
vocational training, rehabilitation of disabled and handicapped persons; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>v</number>  the provision and improvement of 
transport facilities.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The expenditure 
incurred in connection with the measures referred to in sub-rule (4) either by 
an employer in relation to a mine or a trade union registered under the Trade 
Unions Act, 1926 of persons employed in a mine may be reimbursed to the person 
concerned by the Prescribed Authority either wholly or partly at his discretion, 
provided he is satisfied that the expenditure has been actually incurred by that 
person for bona fide purpose as specified in sub-rule (4).
 
 
  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>