<act><tid>106388</tid>
<title>THE TAXATION LAWS (AMENDMENT AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1965</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1965</year>
[ 4th December, <year>1965</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, the Estate Duty 
Act, <year>1953</year>, the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year>, the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year> and to 
provide for exemption from tax in certain cases of undisclosed income 
invested in National Defence Gold Bonds, <year>1980</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>560886</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Taxation Laws 
 (Amendment and Miscellaneous Provisions)' Act, <year>1965</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>238152</tid>
<number> 8</number> Exemption from tax in certain cases of undisclosed income 
invested in National Defence Gold Bonds, <year>1980</year>.
<section><tid>1497486</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a person  
who hag acquired any gold out of his income which has not been 
disclosed by him, for the purposes of the 192. Indian income- tax 
Act, <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>) or the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>, (43 of <year>1961</year>) or 
the Excess Profits Tax Act, <year>1940</year>, (15 of <year>1940</year>) or the Business Profits 
Tax Act, <year>1947</year>, (21 of <year>1947</year>) or the Super Profits Tax Act, <year>1963</year>, (14 of  
  <year>1963</year>) or the Companies (Profits) Surtax 193 Act, <year>1964</year>, (7 of <year>1964</year>). 
tenders such gold as subscription for the National Defence Gold Bonds, 
<year>1980</year>, prior to the detection of such income by the Income- tax Officer 
or the seizure of such gold under any law for the time being in force, 
such income shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the said 
Acts, not be included in his income, profits or gains Chargeable to 
tax under the said Acts in an assessment or reassessment for any 
assessment. year made under the said Acts on or after the 20th day of 
October, <year>1965</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1564990</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the net wealth of a person under the Wealth- tax 
Act, <year>1957</year>, (27 of <year>1957</year>) the value of the assets represented by the 
income, which, under sub- section (1) is not includible in his income, 
profits or gains, shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the 
said Act, not be taken into account in an assessment or re- assessment 
for any assessment year made under the said Act on or after the 20th 
day of October, <year>1965</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>261870</tid>
<number>3</number> (a) The name of the person subscribing to the National defence 
Gold Bonds, <year>1980</year>, and any particulars relating to the Bonds subscribed 
to by him, shall be treated as confidential, and, notwith-
 1 Rep. by Act 56 of <year>1974</year>. s. 20 Sch. I.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1296</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

standing anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no 
court shall be entitled to require any public servant to disclose the 
name of such person or any such particulars or to give any evidence in 
respect thereof.


<subsection><tid>1978283</tid>
<number>b</number>No public servant shall disclose the name of the person 
subscribing to the National Defence Gold Bonds, <year>1980</year> or any 
particulars relating to the Bonds subscribed to by him, except to an 
officer employed in the execution of any of the Acts mentioned in sub- 
section (1) or the Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year> (27 of <year>1957</year>) or to any officer 
appointed by the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or the 
Central Board of Direct Taxes (constituted under the Central Boards of  
  Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>)  (54 of <year>1963</year>). to audit income- tax receipts or 
refunds.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1695757</tid>
<number>4</number>In this section-

<subsection><tid>1428758</tid>
<number>a</number>" gold" means sold, including its alloy, whether virgin, 
melted, re- melted, wrought or unwrought, in any shape or 
form, and includes any gold coin (whether legal tender or  
  not), any ornament and any other article of gold;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>737816</tid>
<number>b</number>" public servant' includes an officer or other employee 
of the Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India or any 
subsidiary bank of the State Bank of India.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1102194</tid>
<number> 9</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1888268</tid>
<number>1</number>The Taxation Laws (Amendment and   
  Miscellaneous Provisions) Ordinance, <year>1965</year> (5 of <year>1965</year>) is, hereby 
repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>788819</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under this Act as if this Act had commenced on the 19th day of 
October, <year>1965</year>.


</section>

</article>



 </act>