<act><tid>1000140</tid>
<title>THE COFFEE ACT, <year>1942</year></title>

ACT NO. 7 OF <year>1942</year>
[ 2nd March, <year>1942</year>.]

An Act <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to provide for the development under the control of the 
Union of the coffee industry].

WHEREAS it is expedient <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to provide for the development under 
the control of the Union of the coffee industry];

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>854545</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and duration.
<section><tid>1613816</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Coffee Act], <year>1942</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1746414</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir].
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1888913</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Declaration as to expediency of Union control. It is hereby 
declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the Union 
should take under its control the coffee industry.]


</article>



<article><tid>738721</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>840500</tid>
<number>a</number>" the Board" means the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Coffee Board] constituted 
under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>734906</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;]

</section>

<section><tid>1304171</tid>
<number>b</number>" coffee" means the commodity derived from the fruit of 
the rubiaceous plant known by that name, and includes 
raw coffee, cured coffee, uncured coffee, roasted 
coffee and prepared coffee;

</section>

<section><tid>332181</tid>
<number>c</number>" Collector" means a Collector of Customs as defined 
in clause (8) of section 2 of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>; 
 (8 of <year>1878</year>.).
Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Havoli 
 (w. e. f. 1. 7. 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 2, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" Coffee Market Expansion Act" (w. e. f.  
  1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" except Part B 
States". 
4 Sub- section (3) omitted by Act 4 of <year>1947</year>, s. 2. 
5 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 4, for s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
6 Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 2, for" Indian Coffee Market Expansion 
Board". 
7 The word" Indian" omitted by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
8 Ins. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
9 Subs by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. <year>1994</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>704249</tid>
<number>d</number>" curing" means the application to raw coffee of 
mechanical processes other than pulping for the purpose 
of preparing it for marketing;

</section>

<section><tid>491153</tid>
<number>e</number>" curing establishment" means any place to which raw 
coffee is sent by a registered owner for curing, and 
includes any estate which the Board may declare to be a 
curing establishment for the purposes of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>362253</tid>
<number>ee</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" dealer" means a person carrying on the business of 
selling coffee, whether wholesale or by retail;]

</section>

<section><tid>1284994</tid>
<number>f</number>" estate" means an area administered as one unit which 
contains land planted with coffee plants;

</section>

<section><tid>420553</tid>
<number>ff</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" India" means the territory of India excluding the 
State of Jammu and Kashmir;]

</section>

<section><tid>1685214</tid>
<number>g</number>" Indian Coffee Cess Committee" means the Indian Coffee 
Cess Committee constituted under the Indian Coffee Cess 
Act, <year>1935</year> (14 of <year>1935</year>.); 
 (h) <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" free sale quota" means that portion, stated in terms 
of bulk or weight, of the whole of the coffee produced 
by the estate in the year, which a registered estate is 
permitted under this Act to sell;]

<subsection><tid>1425582</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" owner", in relation to any land planted with coffee 
plants, includes,--

<subsubsection><tid>1061558</tid>
<number>1</number>any agent of the owner, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>371856</tid>
<number>2</number>a mortgagee, lessee or other person in actual 
possession of the land;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1523966</tid>
<number>j</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>309679</tid>
<number>k</number>" registered estate" means an estate in respect of which 
an owner is registered under sub- section (1) of section 
14, and includes also any estate in respect of which an 
owner is required to be registered under the provisions 
of that sub- section;

</section>

<section><tid>535863</tid>
<number>l</number>" registered owner" means an owner of a registered estate 
who has been or is required to be registered under sub- 
section (1) of section 14;
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1944</year>, s. 2. 
2 Ins. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
3 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 2, for cl. (i)  (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
4 Cl. (ll), ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. 
5 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>)

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>760914</tid>
<number>m</number>" surplus pool" means the stock of coffee accumulated by 
the Board out of the amounts delivered to the Board 
under section 25;

</section>

<section><tid>1404225</tid>
<number>n</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" year" means the period of twelve months beginning 
with the first day of July and ending with the 
thirtieth day of June next following.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>53785</tid>
<number> 4</number> Constitution of the Board.
<section><tid>1925510</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board constituted by the  
name of the Indian Coffee Market Expansion Board under section 4 of 
the Indian Coffee Market Expansion Ordinance, <year>1940</year> (13 of <year>1940</year>.), 
shall be the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Coffee Board] for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>704549</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>137250</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government by 
notification in the Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1287796</tid>
<number>b</number>three Members of Parliament of whom two shall be elected 
by the House of the People and one by the Council of 
States; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>825015</tid>
<number>c</number>such number of other members not exceeding twenty- nine 
as the Central Government may think expedient, to be 
appointed by that Government by notification in the 
Official Gazette from among persons who are in its 
opinion capable of representing,--

<subsubsection><tid>1348794</tid>
<number>i</number>Governments of the principal coffee- growing 
States;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>669676</tid>
<number>ii</number>coffee- growing industry;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1816177</tid>
<number>iii</number>coffee trade interests;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>858862</tid>
<number>iv</number>curing establishments;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1529534</tid>
<number>v</number>interests of labour;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>309296</tid>
<number>vi</number>interests of consumers; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>648717</tid>
<number>vii</number>such other interests as, in the opinion of 
the Central Government, ought to be represented on the 
Board.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>461324</tid>
<number>2A</number>The number of persons to be appointed as members from each 
of the categories specified in clause (c) of sub- section (2), the term 
of office of, the procedure to be followed in the discharge of their
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 2, for cl. (n)  (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 6, for" Indian Coffee Board" (w. e. f.  
  1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
3 Sub- sections (2) and (3) ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 3. 
4 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 6, for sub- section (2)  (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
5 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 3, for sub- sections (2) and (2A) 
 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


functions by, and the manner of filling vacancies among, the members 
of the Board shall be such as may be prescribed.]


</section>

<section><tid>1347368</tid>
<number>2B</number>Any officer of the Central Government when deputed by that 
Government in this behalf shall have the right to attend meetings of 
the Board and take part in the proceedings thereof but shall not be 
entitled to vote.]
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>942416</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>] No act done by the Board shall be questioned on the 
ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
constitution of, the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>587662</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It is hereby declared that the office of member of the 
Board shall not disqualify its holder for being chosen as, or for 
being, a member of either House of Parliament.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>574583</tid>
<number>5</number>Incorporation of the Board. The Board shall be a body 
corporate by the name of the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Coffee Board], having perpetual 
succession and a common seal, with power to acquire and hold property, 
both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall by the said 
name sue and be sued.


</article>



<article><tid>553824</tid>
<number>6</number>Vesting of property in the Board. So long as this Act remains 
in force all property, movable or immovable, of or belonging to the 
Indian Coffee Cess Committee shall vest in the Board and all debts and 
liabilities of the said Committee shall be transferred to the Board, 
and the officers and servants of the said Committee shall be officers 
and servants on the staff of the Board and the said Committee shall be 
suspended.


</article>



<article><tid>945960</tid>
<number>6A</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Consultation with the Board. Before taking any action 
touching the affairs of the Board under this Act, the Central 
Government shall ordinarily consult the Board:
Provided that no action taken by the Central Government shall be 
invalid or called in question merely on the ground that the action was 
taken without such consultation.]



</article>



<article><tid>193116</tid>
<number> 7</number> Committees, staff and agents. <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>
<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (3) which was ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 3, omitted by 
Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
2 The original sub- section (2) renumbered as sub- section (4) by Act 
7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 3. 
3 Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year> s. 4, for" Indian Coffee Market Expansion 
Board". 
5 The word" Indian" omitted by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
6 Ins. by s. 8, ibid, (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
7 Sub- section (1) omitted by s. 9, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<section><tid>446193</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may appoint such committees for such purposes and 
may employ such staff as it thinks necessary for the efficient 
discharge of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1090012</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board may authorise agents to discharge on its behalf its 
functions in relation to the marketing, storing and curing of coffee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1165386</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Salary and allowances of Chairman. The Chairman shall be 
entitled to such salary and allowances and such conditions of service 
in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters as may, 
from time to time, be fixed by the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>846965</tid>
<number>8A</number>Vice- Chairman. The Board shall elect from amongst its members 
a Vice- Chairman who shall exercise such of the powers and perform such 
of the duties of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be 
delegated to him by the Chairman.


</article>



<article><tid>259738</tid>
<number> 9</number> Chief Coffee Marketing Officer, Secretary and other staff.
<section><tid>1213823</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall appoint an officer to be called the Chief 
Coffee Marketing Officer and a Secretary to the Board and may appoint 
a Deputy Secretary to the Board and such number of Marketing Officers 
as may be necessary, to exercise such powers and to perform such 
duties under the direction of the Board as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1994231</tid>
<number>2</number>The officers appointed under this section shall be entitled 
to such salaries and allowances and such conditions of service in 
respect of leave, pension, provident fund and other matters as may, 
from time to time, be fixed by the Central Government.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>992492</tid>
<number>10</number>Dissolution of the Board. When the Board is dissolved by 
reason of this Act having ceased to be in force, the unexpended 
balance of all money received by the Board under the Coffee Market 
Expansion Ordinance, <year>1940</year> (13 of <year>1940</year>.), or under this Act except 
money in the pool fund, shall be disposed of in such manner as the 
Central Government may direct, The Central Government shall disburse 
the money in the pool fund in the same manner as the Board would have 
done had it continued to exist.
Duties of Customs and of Excise



</article>



<article><tid>1224199</tid>
<number>11</number>Duty of customs. A duty of customs shall be levied on all 
coffee produced in India and exported from <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> at such 
rate not exceeding
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 10, for ss. 8 and 9 (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States". 
3 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 11, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1960</year>, s. 5, for" at such rate not exceeding 
six rupees per hundredweight" (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1960</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>7</footcitenum> fifty rupees] per quintal] as may be fixed by the Central 
Government by notification in the Official Gazette.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Duty of excise.



</article>



<article><tid>830695</tid>
<number> 13</number> Payment of proceeds of duty to the Board. <footcitenum>11</footcitenum> 13.
<section><tid>1848128</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Proceeds of the duty of customs levied under this Act (all off which  
  shall from part of the Consolidated Fund of India), reduced by 
the cost of collection as determined by the Central Government, shall, 
if Parliament by appropriation made by law in this behalf so provides, 
be paid to the Board for being utilised for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1942791</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>, and the rules and 
regulations made thereunder, shall, as far as may be, apply in relation 
to--

<subsection><tid>1741222</tid>
<number>a</number>the refund of the duty of customs where coffee is 
exported and subsequently imported into India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>807723</tid>
<number>b</number>the export, without payment of the duty of customs, of 
coffee which is subsequently to be imported into India.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1960</year>, s. 5 for" at such rate not exceeding six 
rupees per hundredweight" (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1960</year>). 
2 The words" on the recommendation of the Board" omitted by Act 50 
of <year>1954</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
3 Certain words omitted by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 4 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 13, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
5 The words" and of any fees" omitted by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 5 
 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
6 Sub- section (2) omitted by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 13, (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
7 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
8 Subs. by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
9 Subs. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
10 Amitted by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>). 
11 Subs. by s. 4 ibid. (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1789338</tid>
<number> 14</number> Registration of owners of coffee estates. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>389328</tid>
<number>1</number>Every owner  
of land planted with coffee plants, whether such land is comprised in 
one estate or in more than one estate and whether it is situated 
wholly or only partly in India, shall, before the expiration of one 
month from the date on which he first became owner of such estate or 
estates, apply to the registering officer appointed in this behalf by 
the State Government to be registered as an owner in respect of each 
estate owned by him; and any registration made before the commencement 
of the Coffee (Amendment) Act, <year>1961</year> (48 of <year>1961</year>), shall be deemed to 
have been made under this sub- section.]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>580953</tid>
<number>3</number>A registration once made shall continue in force until it is 
cancelled by the registering officer.
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>74042</tid>
<number> 15</number> Power of State Government to make rules.
<section><tid>1652628</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
carry into effect the provisions of section 14.

</section>

<section><tid>1776158</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
such rules may prescribe the form of the application for registration 
and for cancellation of registration, the fee payable on such 
applications, the particulars to be included in such applications, the 
procedure to be followed in granting and cancelling registration, the 
registers to be kept by registering officers, and the supply by 
registering officers of information to the Board.
Control of Sale, Export and Re- import of Coffee




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>367339</tid>
<number> 16</number> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Fixation of prices for sale of coffee.
<section><tid>770126</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> by notification in the Official Gazette fix the 
price or prices at which coffee may be sold wholesale or retail in the 
Indian market.

</section>

<section><tid>1917599</tid>
<number>2</number>No registered owner or licensed curer or dealer shall sell 
coffee wholesale or retail in the Indian market at a price or prices 
higher than the price or prices fixed under this section.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1960</year>, s. 5, for" hundredweights" (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1960</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 6, for sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 19- 4-  
  <year>1962</year>). 
3 Sub- section (2) omitted by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
4 Sub- section (4) omitted by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
5 Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 5, for s. 16. 
6 The words" after consultation with the Board" omitted by Act 50 
of <year>1954</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>







</section>

</article>



<article><tid>492633</tid>
<number> 18</number> Sale of coffee, how made. No registered owner shall sell 
coffee unless either--
<section><tid>198713</tid>
<number>a</number>it has been cured at or is delivered to the buyer 
through a curing establishment licensed under section 
28, or

</section>

<section><tid>1407398</tid>
<number>b</number>it is sold under and in accordance with the provisions 
of a licence procured from the Board under section 24.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1227187</tid>
<number>19</number>[ Storage or sale of coffee on or from unregistered estate.] 
Rep. by the Coffee (Amendment) Act, <year>1961</year> (48 of <year>1961</year>), s. 8 (w. e. f.  
  19- 4- <year>1962</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1784148</tid>
<number> 20</number> Export of coffee. NO coffee shall be exported from <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India] 
otherwise than the Board or under an authorisation granted by the 
Board in the prescribed manner and in the prescribed cases, and the 
provisions of the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Customs Act, <year>1962</year>, (52 of <year>1962</year>) shall have effect 
as if the provision made by this section had been made by notification 
issued under section 11"].
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Provided that nothing herein contained shall apply to coffee--

<section><tid>261677</tid>
<number>i</number>shipped as stores on board any vessel or aircraft in 
such quantity as the Collector considers reasonable, 
having regard to the number of the crew and passengers 
and the length of the voyage or journey, as the case 
may be, on which the vessel or aircraft is about to 
proceed, or

</section>

<section><tid>1221280</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> carried as personal baggage of a passenger, not 
exceeding such quantities as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, 
or

</section>

<section><tid>325666</tid>
<number>iii</number>exported for such purposes and in such quantities as 
the Central Government may specify in the like 
manner:]]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 7, for certain words (w. e. f. 19- 4-  
  <year>1962</year>). 
2 Added by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 6. 
3 Proviso omitted by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States". 
5 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 16, for the first proviso (w. e. f. 1-  
  8- <year>1955</year>). 
6 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 9, for cls. (ii), (iii) and (iv) 
 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
7 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>). 
8 Subs. by s. 6, ibid (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided further that the Central Government may, by order in 
writing, specify the quantity of coffee which shall be permitted for 
export during any year and where any such order is made, no coffee 
shall be exported from India in excess of the said quantity:]

Provided further that the Central Government may exempt from the 
operation of this section, either absolutely or subject to conditions, 
the export of coffee from <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> to the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir] or to any foreign settlement bounded by India.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1725858</tid>
<number> 21</number> Re- import of coffee exported from India.
<section><tid>460620</tid>
<number>1</number>No coffee which  
has been exported from India shall be re- imported into <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] 
except under and in accordance with a permit granted by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1512992</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may in any fit case grant such a permit and no 
charge shall be made therefor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1305634</tid>
<number> 22</number> Free sale quota <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> 22.
<section><tid>310929</tid>
<number>1</number>Unless with the previous sanction  
of the Central Government the Board decides that no free sale quotas 
shall be allotted, the Board shall, as soon as may be, allot to each 
registered estate a free sale quota for the year.

</section>

<section><tid>844830</tid>
<number>2</number>The free sale quota shall be a fixed percentage, common to 
all registered estates, not exceeding fifty per cent of the probable 
total production of the estate in the year as estimated by the Board:
Provided that the Board may, with the previous sanction of the 
Central Government, allot such quota at a percentage higher than fifty 
per cent of the said probable total production.


</section>

<section><tid>1426482</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board may at any time vary the free sale quota by varying 
the fixed percentage common to all registered estates, or may express 
the whole or any part of the free sale quota of an estate in terms of 
bulk instead of in terms of weight.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1528898</tid>
<number> 23</number> Returns to be made by registered owners.
<section><tid>1985234</tid>
<number>1</number>A registered  
owner shall furnish to the Board at the prescribed times and in the 
prescribed manner such returns as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1335058</tid>
<number>2</number>If any registered owner fails to furnish the returns required 
under sub- section (1) in respect of any estate, the Board may 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> without prejudice to any penalty to which the said owner is liable 
under section 37A] refuse to allot to that estate, or, where an free 
sale quota has already been allotted, may cancel it.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States". 
3 Subs. by s. 3 and Sch., ibid., for" to a Part B State". 
4 Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 8. 
5 Ins. by s. 9, ibid. 
6 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>). 
7 Subs by s. 8, ibid. (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>840012</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board may authorise an officer to visit any estate at any 
time to verify the accuracy of any return made under this section or 
to ascertain the productive capacity of the estate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>816196</tid>
<number>24</number>Licences for sale of uncured coffee. The registered owner of 
any estate may, subject to the prescribed conditions and so long as 
the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> free sale quota] allotted to that estate will not be exceeded 
by the proposed s of obtain from the Board a licence for the sale 
from that estate of uncured coffee.


</article>



<article><tid>267542</tid>
<number> 25</number> Surplus coffee and surplus pool.
<section><tid>87998</tid>
<number>1</number>All coffee produced by  
a registered estate in excess of the amount specified in the 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> free sale quota] allotted to that estate <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or when no <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> free sale 
quota] have been allotted to estates, all coffee produced by the 
estate], shall be delivered to the Board for inclusion in the surplus 
pool by the owner of the estate or by the curing establishment rece- 
iving the coffee from the estate:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that where no <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> free sale quotas] have been allotted 
to estates, the Chairman may allow the owner of any estate to retain 
with himself for purposes of consumption by his family and for 
purposes of seed, such quantity of coffee as the Chairman may think 
reasonable:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 10. 
2 Added by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
3 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 14- 1-- <year>1994</year>). 
  4 Subs. by s. 10, ibid. 9w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided further that where the Central Government is satisfied 
that it is not practicable for any class of owners producing coffee in 
any specified area to comply with the provisions of this sub- section 
on account of the small quantity of coffee produced by them or on 
account of their estates being situated in a remote locality, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
exempt such class of owners from the provisions of this sub- section.]


</section>

<section><tid>452449</tid>
<number>2</number>Delivery shall be made to the Board in such places, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> at 
such times] and in such manner as the Board may direct, and such 
directions may provide for partial delivery to the surplus pool at any 
time whether or not at that time the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> free sale quota] has been 
exceeded; and the coffee delivered shall be such as to represent 
fairly in kind and quality the produce of the estate. The Board may 
reject any consignment offered for delivery which does not satisfy 
this requirement, but shall not reject any consignment merely for a 
defect in curing.

</section>

<section><tid>1536942</tid>
<number>3</number>Coffee delivered for inclusion in the surplus pool shall upon 
delivery to the Board remain under the control of the Board which 
shall be responsible for storage, curing where necessary, and 
marketing of the coffee.

</section>

<section><tid>964571</tid>
<number>4</number>The Board shall <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> from time to time] prepare a 
differential scale for the valuation of coffee, and shall in 
accordance with that scale classify the coffee in each consignment 
delivered for inclusion in the surplus pool according to its kind and 
quality, and shall make an assessment of its value based on its 
quantity, kind and quality.

</section>

<section><tid>256934</tid>
<number>5</number>The Board may, with the consent of a registered owner, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
treat as having been delivered for inclusion in the surplus pool any 
coffee from such estate which the registered owner may agree to have 
so treated.

</section>

<section><tid>1737022</tid>
<number>6</number>When coffee has been delivered or is treated as having been 
delivered for inclusion in the surplus pool, the registered owner 
whose coffee has been so delivered or is treated as having been so 
delivered shall retain no rights in respect of such coffee except his 
right to receive the payments referred to in section 34.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>216072</tid>
<number> 26</number> Sales of coffee by the Board.
<section><tid>20135</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall take all  
practical measures to market the coffee included in the surplus pool, 
and all sales thereof shall be conducted by or through the Board.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 10. 
2 The words" with the concurrence of the Chief Coffee Marketing 
Officer" omitted by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 17 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
3 The words" before an internal sale quota has been allotted to an 
estate" omitted by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 10. 
4 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1128405</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may purchase for inclusion in the surplus pool 
coffee not delivered for inclusion in it.
Curing of Coffee




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>918948</tid>
<number>27</number>Coffee to be cured in licensed curing establishments. No 
registered owner shall cause or allow coffee to be cured elsewhere 
than in a licensed curing establishment, whether the curing 
establishment is maintained by himself or by another person.


</article>



<article><tid>1406346</tid>
<number>28</number>Licensing of curing establishments. Every establishment for 
curing coffee shall obtain from the Board a licence to operate as 
such.


</article>



<article><tid>606053</tid>
<number> 29</number> Information to be supplied to the Board in connection with 
curing.
<section><tid>403423</tid>
<number>1</number>A registered owner when sending coffee to a curing  
establishment shall report to the Board, separately for each estate 
from which coffee is sent, the amount of coffee sent; and the curing 
establishment shall, in accordance with such instructions as may be 
issued by the Board and having regard to the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> free sale quota] of 
the estate <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> where one has been allotted], apportion each such 
consignment into two parts, one part consisting of coffee intended 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> free sale quota] and one part of coffee intended to be delivered 
for inclusion in the surplus pool and shall report to the Board the 
amount of coffee in each such part. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where no <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> free sale quotas] 
have been allotted to estates, the curing establishment shall report 
merely the whole amount of coffee sent in each such consignment.]

</section>

<section><tid>643289</tid>
<number>2</number>A registered owner curing coffee in a curing establishment 
maintained by himself shall supply to the Board the information 
specified in sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1947159</tid>
<number>3</number>A curing establishment which buys or receives uncured coffee 
from any person shall ascertain the estate on which the coffee was 
produced and shall report to the Board the quantity of coffee so 
obtained and the estate or estates from which it came.

</section>

<section><tid>585530</tid>
<number>4</number>Every curing establishment shall maintain accounts in such 
forms as may be required by the Board and such accounts shall be open 
to inspection at any time by the Board or by an officer authorised in 
this behalf by the Board.
Finance




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>867234</tid>
<number>30</number>Separate funds to be maintained by the Board. The Board shall 
maintain two separate funds, a general fund and a pool fund.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 11. 
2 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>376878</tid>
<number> 31</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> General fund.
<section><tid>52538</tid>
<number>1</number>To the general fund shall be credited-- 

<subsection><tid>159390</tid>
<number>a</number>all amounts paid to the Board by the Central Government 
under sub- section (1) of section 13; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>246473</tid>
<number>b</number>any sums transferred to the general fund under the 
proviso to sub- section (2) of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 32; and]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>437333</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> all fees levied and collected by the Board under this 
Act.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>906076</tid>
<number>2</number>The general fund shall be applied--

<subsection><tid>978291</tid>
<number>a</number>to meet the expenses of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1348376</tid>
<number>b</number>to meet the cost of such measures as the Board may 
consider advisable to undertake for promoting 
agricultural and technological research in the interest 
of the coffee industry in India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>318215</tid>
<number>c</number>for making such grants to coffee estates or for meeting 
the cost of such other assistance to coffee estates as 
the Board may think necessary for the development of 
such estates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1437152</tid>
<number>d</number>to meet the cost of such measures as the Board considers 
advisable to undertake for promoting the sale and 
increasing the consumption in India and elsewhere of 
coffee produced in India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>134294</tid>
<number>e</number>to meet the expenses for securing better working 
conditions and the provision and improvement of 
amenities and incentives for workers.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1656752</tid>
<number> 32</number> Pool fund.
<section><tid>149406</tid>
<number>1</number>To the pool fund shall be credited all sums  
realised by sales by the Board of coffee from the surplus pool.

</section>

<section><tid>1273517</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the pool fund] shall be applied only to--

<subsection><tid>1521901</tid>
<number>a</number>the making to registered owners of estates of payments 
proportionate to the value of the value of the coffee 
delivered by them for inclusion in the surplus pool;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1255468</tid>
<number>b</number>the costs of storing, curing and marketing coffee 
deposited in and of administering the surplus pool;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>634202</tid>
<number>c</number>the purchase of coffee not delivered for inclusion in 
the surplus pool:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that where, after the requirements of the clauses of 
this sub- section have been met, there remains any excess in the pool 
fund, the Board may, with the previous sanction of the Central 
Government, transfer the whole or any part of such excess to the 
credit of the general fund.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 18, for s. 31 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 10, for" section 32." (w. e. f. 19- 4-  
  <year>1962</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 10, ibid. (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>). 
4 Added by Act 16 of <year>1944</year>, s. 3. 
5 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 12, (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1811986</tid>
<number>32A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power of the Board to make donation to the Gandhi 
National Memorial Fund. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 
32, the Board may apply any part of the pool fund to the making of a 
donation to the Fund known as the Gandhi National Memorial Fund.]


</article>



<article><tid>1842452</tid>
<number>33</number>Power to borrow. The Board may, subject to any prescribed 
conditions, borrow on the security of the general fund or the pool 
fund for any purposes for which it is authorised to expend money from 
such fund, or on the security of the coffee delivered or treated as 
delivered for inclusion in the surplus pool for any purposes for which 
it is authorised to expend money from the pool fund.


</article>



<article><tid>1542108</tid>
<number> 34</number> Payments to registered owners.
<section><tid>647567</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall at such  
times as it thinks fit make to registered owners who have delivered 
coffee for inclusion in the surplus pool such payments out of the pool 
fund as it may think proper.

</section>

<section><tid>994370</tid>
<number>2</number>The sum of all payments made under sub- section (1) to any one 
registered owner shall bear to the sum of the payments made to all 
registered owners the same proportion as the value of the coffee 
delivered by him out of the year' s crop to the surplus pool bears to 
the value of all coffee delivered to the surplus pool out of that 
year' s crop:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that in calculating the sum of all payments made 
under sub- section (1) and the value of the coffee delivered to the 
surplus pool out of the year' s crop, respectively, any payment 
accepted by a registered owner as final payment in immediate 
settlement for coffee delivered by him for inclusion in the surplus 
pool and the value of any such coffee shall be excluded.]

Penalties and Procedure




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1060070</tid>
<number>35</number>Failure to register. Any owner of a coffee estate who fails 
to apply for registration in accordance with section 14 shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees and to a 
further fine which may extend to five hundred rupees for each month 
after the first during which such failure continues.


</article>



<article><tid>748179</tid>
<number> 36</number> Contraventions of sections 16, 17 and 18.
<section><tid>687106</tid>
<number>1</number>Any registered  
owner who contravenes the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 16, 
or section 17 or section 18, any licensed curer <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or dealer] who 
contravenes the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 16, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> shall 
be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 34 of <year>1949</year>, s. 2. 
2 Added by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 12. 
3 Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1944</year>, s. 3. 
4 Certain words omitted by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1570881</tid>
<number>2</number>When a registered owner is convicted under this section, the 
Board may thereafter deduct from any payment to be made under section 
 34 to such registered owner a sum equal to the value as estimated by 
the Board of any coffee unlawfully sold by him.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1174265</tid>
<number>37</number>Unlicensed during establishment. If any curing establishment 
operates as such without a licence, the owner shall be punishable with 
fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1265496</tid>
<number> 37A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Contravention of section 23
<section><tid>100073</tid>
<number>1</number>Any registered owner who  
fails to furnish the return required by sub- section (1) of section 23 
as required by that sub- section shall be punishable with fine which 
may extend to one thousand rupees.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1509100</tid>
<number>38</number>False returns. Any person who makes in any return to be 
furnished under section 23 or in any report to be made under section 
 29 any statement which is false and which he knows to be false or does 
not believe to be true shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
to one thousand rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1996313</tid>
<number> 38A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Contravention of section 25. Any registered owner or 
licensed curer who fails to deliver any coffee to the Board as 
required by or under sub- sections
<section><tid>43722</tid>
<number>1</number>and (2) of section 25 shall be  
punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, and the 
Court by which such person is convicted may order the confiscation and 
delivery to the Board of any coffee in respect of which the offence 
was committed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>18270</tid>
<number>38B</number>Powers to seize coffee with held from inclusion in surplus 
pool. If the Board is satisfied that any coffee which is required 
under the provisions of section 25 to be delivered for inclusion in 
the surplus pool is being or is likely to be disposed of otherwise 
than by such delivery, the Board may order the seizure of such coffee, 
and may authorise an officer of the Board to effect seizure thereof 
for delivery for inclusion in the surplus pool, and such authorisation 
shall be sufficient warrant for such officer to take all steps 
necessary to secure possession of the coffee.]


</article>



<article><tid>1578259</tid>
<number>39</number>Obstruction. Whoever obstructs any member or officer of the 
Board or any person authorised by the Board or by the Central 
Government in the discharge of any duty imposed on or entrusted to him 
under this Act, or who having control over or custody of any records 
fails to produce such records when required to do so or refuses 
information lawfully
<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 13. 
2 Ins. by s. 14, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


asked for by a member or officer of the Board or by a person 
authorised by the Board or by the Central Government to inspect such 
records or ask for such information shall be punishable with fine 
which may extend to one thousand rupees.



</article>



<article><tid>755421</tid>
<number> 39A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1528561</tid>
<number>1</number>If the person committing any  
offence under this Act is a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to punishment provided in this Act if he proves 
that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>133284</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>260365</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>663598</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>264881</tid>
<number> 40</number> Cognizance of offences.
<section><tid>1011258</tid>
<number>1</number>No Court other than the Court of  
a Magistrate of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of 
the first class". 
the first class shall take cognizance of any offence 
punishable under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1287530</tid>
<number>2</number>No Court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under 
section 35 except on complaint made by an officer authorised in this 
behalf by the State Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or of the offence specified in 
subsection (2) of section 16 except on complaint made by an officer 
authorised in this behalf either by the State Government or by the 
Board] or of an offence punishable under any other section except on 
complaint made with the previous sanction, of the Central Government 
by an officer authorised in this behalf by the Board:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 1- 8- <year>1955</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1944</year>, s. 4. 
3 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. <year>1994</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, direct that the previous sanction of the Central 
Government shall not be necessary for complaints in such cases or 
classes of cases as may be specified in the notification.]

General




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1049867</tid>
<number>41</number>[ Power of Board to determine amount of coffee sold by an 
estate.] Rep. by the Coffee (Amendment) Act, <year>1961</year> (48 of <year>1961</year>), s. 12 
 (w. e. f. 19- 4- <year>1962</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1303384</tid>
<number> 42</number> Control by the Central Government.
<section><tid>840684</tid>
<number>1</number>All acts of the Board  
shall be subject to the control of the Central Government which may 
cancel, suspend or modify as it thinks fit any action taken by the 
Board.

</section>

<section><tid>640384</tid>
<number>2</number>The records of the Board shall be open to inspection at all 
reasonable times by any officer authorised in this behalf by the 
Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>974165</tid>
<number> 43</number> Appeals to the Central Government.
<section><tid>992826</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved  
by an order of the Board refusing a licence to or cancelling the 
licence of a curing establishment may, within sixty days of the making 
of the order, appeal to the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>221478</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person making an appeal under this section shall pay a 
fee of five rupees which shall be credited to Central Revenues.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1289989</tid>
<number>44</number>Inspection of records. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Any person authorised in this 
behalf by the Central Government or by the Board or any member of the 
Board so authorised by the Chairman in writing or any officer of the 
Board, may enter at all reasonable times] any estate or any curing 
establishment <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or any place where coffee is stored or exposed for 
sale,] and may require the production for his inspection of any 
records kept therein, or ask for any information relating to the 
production, storage or sale of coffee <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</article>



<article><tid>1503487</tid>
<number> 45</number> Accounts of the Board.
<section><tid>1319352</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall keep accounts in  
such manner as may be prescribed of all money received and expended by 
it.

</section>

<section><tid>1126317</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts shall be kept separately for the general fund 
and the pool fund.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 15. 
2 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 20, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
3 Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 16. 
4 The words" by the estate" omitted by s. 16, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1842557</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall cause the accounts to be audited annually by 
auditors appointed by the Central Government, and the auditors shall 
have power to disallow any item of expenditure which has, in their 
opinion, been incurred otherwise than in accordance with this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>378946</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may on the application of the Board 
allow any item of expenditure disallowed by the auditors under sub- 
section (3).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1821662</tid>
<number>46</number>Inspection of records of the Board and obtaining of copies. 
Any registered owner <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> may, subject to the prescribed conditions, 
inspect the records maintained by the Board and may on payment of the 
prescribed fee obtain copies of any proceedings or orders of the 
Board.


</article>



<article><tid>1026250</tid>
<number>47</number>Contracts. All contracts for the sale of coffee in so far as 
they are at variance with the provisions of this Act shall be void:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to 
contracts to which under section 47 of the Coffee Market Expansion 
Ordinance, <year>1940</year> (13 of <year>1940</year>.), that Ordinance did not apply.



</article>



<article><tid>890363</tid>
<number>47A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Bar of legal proceedings. No suit, prosecution or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against the Board or any officer of the 
Board for or in respect of anything in good faith done or intended to 
be done under this Act.]


</article>



<article><tid>1838169</tid>
<number> 48</number> Power of the Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>1674202</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>737949</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, rules may be made providing for all or any of the following 
matters:--

<subsection><tid>980708</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the constitution of the Board, the number of persons 
to be appointed as members from each of the categories 
specified in clause (c) of sub- section (2) of section 
4, the term of office and other conditions of service 
of, the procedure to be followed by, and the manner of 
filling vacancies among, the members of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>324268</tid>
<number>ii</number>the circumstances in which, and the authority by which, 
members may be removed;]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" to whom an internal sale quota is allotted" omitted by 
Act 7 of <year>1943</year>, s. 17. 
2 Ins. by s. 18, ibid. 
3 Subs. by Act 50 of <year>1954</year>, s. 21, for sub- section (2)  (w. e. f. 1- 8-  
  <year>1955</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 13, for cls. (i) and (ii)  (w. e. f. 19-  
  4- <year>1962</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>289314</tid>
<number>iii</number>the procedure to be followed at meetings of the Board 
and at committees thereof for the conduct of business 
and the number of members which shall form a quorum at 
a meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>406028</tid>
<number>iv</number>the maintenance by the Board of records of business 
transacted by the Board and the submission of copies 
thereof to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1526797</tid>
<number>v</number>the holding of a minimum number of meetings of the Board 
every year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1262758</tid>
<number>vi</number>the powers of the Board, its Chairman and committees 
thereof with respect to the incurring of expenditure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177333</tid>
<number>vii</number>the conditions subject to which the Board may incur 
expenditure outside India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>833165</tid>
<number>viii</number>the preparation of budget estimates of receipts and 
expenditure of the Board and the authority by which the 
estimates are to be sanctioned;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>303206</tid>
<number>ix</number>the maintenance of the accounts of income and 
expenditure of the Board and the audit of such 
accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1248850</tid>
<number>x</number>the deposit of the funds of the Board in banks and the 
investment of such funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1950561</tid>
<number>xi</number>the re- appropriation of the estimated savings from any 
budget head to any other budget head;

<subsubsection><tid>1211137</tid>
<number>xii</number>the conditions subject to which the Board may borrow 
funds;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1526968</tid>
<number>xiii</number>the conditions subject to which and the manner in 
which contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of 
the Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>826772</tid>
<number>xiv</number>the delegation to the committee or Chairman or Vice- 
Chairman or members or officers of the Board of any of 
the powers and duties of the Board under this Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1619962</tid>
<number>xv</number>the staff which may be employed by the Board and the 
pay and allowances and leave and other conditions of 
service of officers (other than those appointed by the  
  Central Government) and other employees of the Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>844981</tid>
<number>xvi</number>the travelling and other allowances of members of the 
Board and of committees thereof;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>285409</tid>
<number>xvii</number>the maintenance of the registers and other records of 
the Board and its various committees;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>659425</tid>
<number>xviii</number>the manner in which the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> free sale quota] of coffee 
estates shall be determined;
 1 Subs. by Act 23 of <year>1994</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 14- 1- <year>1994</year>).


<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1565342</tid>
<number>xix</number>the manner in which the Board shall exercise its 
powers of buying and selling coffee;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1999878</tid>
<number>xx</number>the appointment by the Board of agents;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1538629</tid>
<number>xxi</number>the conditions to be fulfilled by a curing 
establishment before a licence to operate as such can 
be issued;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>768925</tid>
<number>xxii</number>the form of, and the particulars to be contained in, 
any returns or reports to be made to the Board under 
this Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1929667</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>the form of, manner of application for, fees payable 
for, procedure in granting and conditions governing, 
the licences and permits to be issued by the Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1423566</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>the collection of any information or statistics in 
respect of coffee or any product of coffee;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1798359</tid>
<number>xxv</number>any other matter (other than any matter specified in  
  section 15) which is to be or may be prescribed under 
this Act.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>157833</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>153582</tid>
<number>49</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Repeal of Act 14 of <year>1935</year>. The Indian Coffee Cess Act, <year>1935</year> 
 (14 of <year>1935</year>.), is hereby repealed.]


</article>



<article><tid>1448113</tid>
<number>50</number>[ Repeals and savings.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending 
Act, <year>1947</year> (2 of <year>1948</year>), s. 2 and Sch.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1961</year>, s. 13, for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 19- 4-  
  <year>1962</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1947</year>, s. 4, for s. 49. 
3 Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1985</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>