<act><tid>1077635</tid>
<title>THE SALARY, ALLOWANCES AND PENSION OF MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT (AMENDMENT) 
ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 9 of <year>2004</year>
[ 9th January, <year>2004</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members 
of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1848409</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1844581</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year> (30 of <year>1954</year>)  (hereinafter  
  referred to as the principal Act), after clause (a), the following 
clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (aa)" dependent" means any of the relatives of a deceased member, 
namely:-

<section><tid>1502535</tid>
<number>i</number>a minor legitimate son, and an unmarried legitimate daughter and a 
widowed mother; or

</section>

<section><tid>629832</tid>
<number>ii</number>if wholly dependent on the earnings of the member at the time of 
his death, a son or a daughter who has attained the age of eighteen 
years and who is infirm; or

</section>

<section><tid>1719860</tid>
<number>iii</number>if wholly or in part dependent on the earnings of the member at 
the time of his death,- 
 (a) the parent; or

<subsection><tid>813535</tid>
<number>b</number>a minor brother or an unmarried sister; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1197040</tid>
<number>c</number>a widowed daughter- in- law; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>738927</tid>
<number>d</number>a minor child of a pre- deceased son; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1372214</tid>
<number>e</number>a minor child of a pre- deceased daughter where no parent of the 
child is alive; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>513819</tid>
<number>f</number>the paternal grandparent if no parent of the member is alive; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1478532</tid>
<number>g</number>such other person as may be specified by the rules made under 
section 9 by the Joint Committee;'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1721800</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act, 0
<section><tid>1810162</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), after the second proviso, the following 
provisos shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided also that in case a member resides within a distance of three 
hundred kilometers from Delhi, he or his spouse, for the journey 
performed by him by road, may draw the mileage allowance referred to in 
sub- clause (ii) of clause (c) of sub- section (1) in place of the 
traveling allowance which would have been admissible to him had he 
performed such journey by rail or by road, as the case may be:

Provided also that in case a member resides in the States of Arunachal 
Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland, Sikkim or 
Tripura, he or his spouse may draw the mileage allowance referred to in 
sub- clause (ii) of clause (c) of sub- section (1) for journey performed 
by him by road from his residence in any of the said States to the 
nearest airport.";


</section>

<section><tid>1851229</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (4) There shall be paid to a person-


</section>

<section><tid>1810162</tid>
<number>a</number>who has been elected in a biennial election as a member of the 
Council of States but the notification in the Official Gazette 
notifying his name under section 71 of the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>) has not been published in the Official Gazette; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>1851229</tid>
<number>b</number>who has been elected as a member of the House of the People in a 
general election held for the purpose of constituting a new House of 
the People but the notification in the Official Gazette notifying his 
name under section 73 of the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43  
  of <year>1951</year>) has not been published in the Official Gazette; or

</section>

<section><tid>1608962</tid>
<number>c</number>who has been elected in a bye- election as a member of either House 
of Parliament or nominated as a member to either House of Parliament,
an amount equivalent to the fare in respect of every journey performed 
by him for coming to Delhi before the publication of notification 
referred to in clause (a) or clause (b), or election or nomination 
under clause (c):

Provided that in case the journey is performed by rail or steamer or 
road, he shall be entitled to the reimbursement of the fare or road 
mileage to which a member is entitled:

Provided further that in case he performs the journey by air, such 
journey shall be included for the purpose of counting thirty- two 
journeys referred to in the first proviso to sub- section (2) of section 
5.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1637948</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, in sub- 
section (2), after the second proviso, the following proviso shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Provided also that the spouse or companion of a member, as the case 
may be, may alone perform maximum eight journeys by air from any place 
of India to the place in India for the purpose of visiting such member 
and such journey shall be included for the purpose of counting thirty- 
two journeys referred to in the first proviso to sub- section (2).".



</article>



<article><tid>1549893</tid>
<number>5</number>Insertion of new section 5A.- After section 5 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
Transit accommodation.

" 5A. Transit accommodation.- Where a person referred to in sub- section 
 (4) of section 4 comes to Delhi, he shall be entitled to such transit 
accommodation for such period as may be specified by the rules made 
under clause (ccc) of sub- section (3) of section 9 by the Joint 
Committee.".



</article>



<article><tid>842557</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 8A.- In section 8A of the principal Act, for 
sub- sections
<section><tid>1591251</tid>
<number>1</number>and (1A), the following sub- sections shall be  
substituted, namely:-
' (1) With effect from the commencement of the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>, there shall be 
paid a pension of three thousand rupees per mensem to every person who 
has served for any period, as a member of the Provisional Parliament or 
either House of Parliament:

Provided that where any person has served as a member of the 
Provisional Parliament or either House of Parliament for a period 
exceeding five years, there shall be paid to him an additional pension 
of six hundred rupees per mensem for every year in excess of five years.

Explanation.- For the purpose of this sub- section," Provisional 
Parliament" shall include the body which functioned as the Constituent 
Assembly of the Dominion of India immediately before the commencement 
of the Constitution.


</section>

<section><tid>1808699</tid>
<number>1A</number>With effect from the commencement of the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>, there shall be 
paid a pension of rupees one thousand and five hundred per mensem, to 
the spouse, if any, or dependent of any member who dies during his term 
of office as such member, for a period of five years from the date of 
his death.
Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
spouse or the dependent of the member referred to in this sub- section 
shall be entitled to receive the family pension even if the member has 
died on or before the commencement of the Salary, Allowances and 
Pension of Members of Parliament (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1589334</tid>
<number> 7</number> Substitution of new section for section 8AA.- For section 8AA of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
Travel facilities to ex- Members.

" 8AA. Travel facilities to ex- Members.- Every person who is not a 
sitting Member but has served for any period as a Member of either 
House of Parliament shall be,-

<section><tid>305578</tid>
<number>a</number>with effect from the 18th day of January, <year>1999</year>, entitled along with 
a companion to travel in any train by any railway in India in air- 
conditioned two- tier class; or

</section>

<section><tid>837678</tid>
<number>b</number>entitled to travel alone in any train by any railway in India in 
air- conditioned first class,
without payment of any charges on the basis of an authorisation issued 
for this purpose by the Secretariat of either House of Parliament as 
the case may be.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>693187</tid>
<number>8</number>Insertion of new section 8AB.- After section 8AA of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
Rounding off period of pension.

" 8AB. Rounding off period of pension.- Where the period for which the 
pension is payable under this Act contains a part of a year, then, if 
such part is nine months or more, it shall be reckoned equivalent to 
complete one year for the purpose of payment of additional pension 
under sub- section (1) of section 8A and if such part is less than nine 
months, it shall be ignored.".



</article>



<article><tid>1045512</tid>
<number> 9</number> In section 9 of the principal Act, in sub- section (3),-
<section><tid>984623</tid>
<number>i</number>after clause (a), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (aa) the person who may be specified as dependent under sub- clause (g) 
of clause (aa) of section 2;"; 
 (ii) after clause (cc), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-

" (ccc) the transit accommodation and the period for which such 
accommodation may be provided under section 5A;";


</section>

<section><tid>1248883</tid>
<number>iii</number>after clause (ff), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (fff) to provide for carry forward of unutilized free telephone calls 
pertaining to any year beginning on or after the 1st day of April, <year>2002</year> 
to any subsequent year;".

T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>