<act><tid>1083794</tid>
<title>THE ESSENTIAL SERVICES MAINTENANCE (ASSAM) ACT, <year>1980</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1980</year>
[ 19th July, <year>1980</year>.]

An Act to provide for the maintenance of certain essential services 
and the normal life of the community in Assam.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- first Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--









<article><tid>149143</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.
<section><tid>1943322</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless the context otherwise  
requrires,- 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<subsection><tid>586183</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" essential service" means--

<subsubsection><tid>1959971</tid>
<number>i</number>any transport service for the carriage of passengers or 
goods, by land or water, with respect to which the Legislative 
Assembly of the State of Assam has power to make laws;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1535662</tid>
<number>ii</number>any service connected with the production, storage, 
supply or distribution, as the case may be, of gas or water;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1942716</tid>
<number>iii</number>any service connected with the maintenance of public 
health and sanitation, including hospitals and dispensaries;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1986874</tid>
<number>iv</number>any public services and posts in connection with the 
affairs of the State, and also persons appointed to the secre- 
tarial staff of the Legislative Assembly of the State of Assam;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>627192</tid>
<number>v</number>any other service or employment or class thereof, conne- 
cted with matters with respect to which the Legislative Assembly 
of the State of Assam has power to make laws and which the State 
Government, being of opinion that strikes therein would prejudi- 
cially affect the maintenance of any public utility service, the 
public safety of the maintenance of the supplies and services 
necessary for the life of the community or would result in the 
Official Gazette, declare to be an essential service for the 
purposes of this Act;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1347365</tid>
<number>bb</number>" State Government" means the State Government of Assam;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>188</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 40 of <year>1981</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 26- 7- <year>1981</year>). It shall 
cease to have effect on the expiry of nine years from the date 
of assent to the Act 40 of <year>1981</year> i. e. 23- 9- <year>1981</year>. 
2. Subs. by s. 13, ibid. (w. e. f. 26- 7- <year>1981</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1304296</tid>
<number>c</number>" strike" means the cessation of work by a body of 
persons employed in any essential service acting in combination 
or a concerted refusal or a refusal under a common understanding 
of any number of persons who are or who have been so employed to 
continue to work or to accept employment, and includes--

<subsubsection><tid>677652</tid>
<number>i</number>refusal to work overtime where such work is 
necessary for the maintenance of any essential service;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1473547</tid>
<number>ii</number>any other conduct which is likely to result in, or 
results in, cessation or substantial retardation of work in 
any essential service.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>189</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1883568</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification issued <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> under sub- clause (v)] of clause 
 (b) of sub- section (1) shall be laid before each House of Parliament 
immediately after it is made if it is in session and on the first day 
of the commencement of the next session of the House if it is not in 
session, and shall cease to operate at the expiration of forty days 
from the date of its being so laid or from the re- assembly of 
Parliament, as the case may be, unless before the expiration of that 
period a resolution approving the issue of the notification is passed 
by both Houses of Parliament.
Explanation.-- Where the Houses of Parliament are summoned to 
reassemble on different dates, the period of forty days shall be 
reckoned from the later of those dates.


</section>

<section><tid>1153297</tid>
<number>3</number>Any reference in this Act to any law which is not in force in 
any area of the State of Assam and to any authority under such law 
shall, in relation to that area, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law in force in that area and to the corresponding 
authority under such corresponding law.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>6878</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to prohibit strikes in certain employments.
<section><tid>1740056</tid>
<number>1</number>If the  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] is satisfied that in the public interest it is 
necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by general or special Order, 
prohibit strikes in the State of Assam in any essential service 
specified in the Order.

</section>

<section><tid>148873</tid>
<number>2</number>An Order made under sub- section (1) shall be published in 
such manner as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] considers best calculated to 
bring it to the notice of the persons affected by the Order.

</section>

<section><tid>1552670</tid>
<number>3</number>An Order made under sub- section (1) shall be in force for six 
months only, but the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may, by a like Order, extend 
it for any period not exceeding six months if it is satisfied that 
in the public interest it is necessary or expedient so to do.

</section>

<section><tid>1822300</tid>
<number>4</number>Upon the issue of an Order under sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1867658</tid>
<number>a</number>no person employed in any essential service to which the 
Order relates shall go or remain on strike;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1214350</tid>
<number>b</number>any strike declared or commenced, whether before or 
after the issue of the Order, by persons employed in any such 
service shall be illegal.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1613611</tid>
<number>4</number>Dismissal of employees participating in illegal strikes. Any 
person who commences a strike which is illegal under this Act, or goes 
or remains on, or otherwise takes part in, any such strike, shall be 
liable to disciplinary action (including dismissal) in accordance with 
the same provisions as are applicable for the purpose of taking such 
disciplinary action (including dismissal) on any other ground under 
the terms and conditions of service applicable to him in relation to 
his employment.


</article>



<article><tid>971394</tid>
<number>5</number>Penalty for illegal strikes. Any person who commences a strike 
which is illegal under this Act, or goes or remains on, or otherwise 
takes part in, any such strike shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1104543</tid>
<number>6</number>Penalty for instigation, etc. Any person who instigates or 
incites other persons to take part in, or otherwise acts in 
furtherance of, a strike which is illegal under this Act shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, 
or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.
</article>



<article><tid>299847</tid>
<number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1981</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 26- 7- <year>1981</year>). 
It shall cease to have effect on the expiry of nine years from 
the date of assent to the Act 40 of <year>1981</year>, i. e. 23- 9- <year>1981</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>190</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1697287</tid>
<number>7</number>Penalty for giving financial aid to illegal strikes. Any 
person who knowingly expends or supplies any money in furtherance or 
support of a strike which is illegal under this Act shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, 
or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>817876</tid>
<number>8</number>Power to arrest without warrant. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), any 
police officer may arrest without warrant any person who is reasonably 
suspected of having committed any offence under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1761071</tid>
<number>9</number>Offences to be tried summarily. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), all 
offences under this Act shall be tried in a summary way by a Judicial 
Magistrate of the first class specially empowered in this behalf by 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] and the provisions of sections 262 to 265 
 (both inclusive) of the said Code shall, as far as may be, apply to 
such trial:
Provided that in a case of conviction for any offence in a 
summary trial under this section, it shall be lawful for the 
Magistrate to pass a sentence of imprisonment for any term for which 
such offence is punishable under this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>950151</tid>
<number>10</number>Act to override other laws. The provisions of this Act and of 
any Order issued thereunder shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> 
 (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law for the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>514226</tid>
<number> 11</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>924615</tid>
<number>1</number>The Essential Services Maintenance  
 (Assam) Ordinance, <year>1980</year> (2 of <year>1980</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1595470</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under this Act, as if this Act had come into force on the 6th 
day of April, <year>1980</year>.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>299847</tid>
<number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1981</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 26- 7- <year>1981</year>), 
It shall cease to have effect on the existing of 0nine years from 
the date of assent to the Act 40 of <year>1981</year>, i. e. 23- 9- <year>1981</year>.

</article>



 </act>