<act><title>

The 
    Petroleum Act, 1934</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Petroleum Act, 1934.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***].]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 

 
 








 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “petroleum” means any liquid 
    hydrocarbon or mixture of hydrocarbons, and any inflammable mixture (liquid, 
    viscous or solid) containing any liquid hydrocarbon;
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>b</number>    
    “petroleum Class A” means petroleum having a flash-point below twenty-three 
    degree centigrade;
 </section><section>
<number>bb</number>    “petroleum Class B” means petroleum 
    having a flash-point of twenty-three degrees centigrade and above but below 
    sixty-five degrees centigrade;
 </section><section>
<number>bbb</number>    “petroleum Class C” means petroleum 
    having a flash-point of sixty-five degrees centigrade and above but below 
    ninety-three degree centigrade;]
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[“flash-point”] of any 
    petroleum means the lowest temperature at which it yields a vapour which 
    will give a momentary flash when ignited, determined in accordance with the 
    provisions of Chapter II and the rules made thereunder; 
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>    
    “to transport petroleum” means to move petroleum from one place to another 
    in India and includes moving from one place to another in India across a 
    territory which is not part of India;]
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    ‘to import” petroleum means to bring it 
    into <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[India] by land, sea or air, otherwise than during the 
    course of transport; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “to store” petroleum means to keep it 
    in any one place, but does not include any detention happening during the 
    ordinary course of transport; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “motor conveyance” means any vehicle, 
    vessel or aircraft for the conveyance of human beings, animals or goods, by 
    land, water or air, in which petroleum is used to generate the motive power;
    
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act.
 
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[***]
 
 
  









 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Import, 
    transport and storage of petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No one shall import, transport or store any petroleum save in accordance 
    with the rules made under section 4. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save 
    in accordance with the conditions of any licence for the purpose which he 
    may be required to obtain by rules made under section 4, no one shall import
    <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[petroleum 
    Class A], and no one shall transport or store any petroleum.
  









 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Rules for the import, transport and storage of petroleum.—The
    <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[Central Government] may makes rules—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    prescribing places where petroleum may 
    be imported and prohibiting its import elsewhere; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    regulating the import of petroleum;
    
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    prescribing the periods within which 
    licences for the import of <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[petroleum 
    Class A] shall be applied for, and providing for the disposal, by 
    confiscation or otherwise, of any <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[petroleum Class A] in respect 
    of which a licence has not been applied for within the prescribed period or 
    has been refused and which has not been exported;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    regulating the transport of petroleum;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    specifying the nature and condition of 
    all receptacles and pipe-lines in which petroleum may be transported;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    regulating the places at which and 
    prescribing the conditions subject to which petroleum may be stored;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    specifying the nature, situation and 
    condition of all receptacles in which petroleum may be stored; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    prescribing the form and conditions of 
    licences for the import of <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[petroleum Class A], and for the 
    transport or storages of any petroleum, the manner in which applications for 
    such licences shall be made, the authorities which may grant such licences 
    and the fees which may be charged for such licences; 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    determining in any class of cases 
    whether a licence for the transport of petroleum shall be obtained by the 
    consignor, consignee or carrier; 
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    providing for the granting of combined 
    licences for the import, transport and storage of petroleum, or for any two 
    of such purposes; 
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    prescribing the proportion in which any 
    specified poisonous substance may he added to petroleum and prohibiting the 
    import, transport or storage of petroleum in which the proportion of any 
    specified poisonous substance exceeds the prescribed proportion; and 

 </section><section>
<number>l</number>    generally, providing for any matter 
    which in <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[its] opinion is 
    expedient for proper control over the import, transport and storage of 
    petroleum <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[including the charging of fees for any service 
    rendered in connection with the import, transport and storage of petroleum].
 
 










 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Production, refining and blending of petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No one shall produce, refine or blend petroleum save in accordance with the 
    rules made under sub-section (2).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The
    <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may makes rules— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    prescribing the conditions subject to 
    which petroleum may be produced, refined or blended; and  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    regulating the removal of petroleum 
    from places where it is produced, refined or blended and preventing the 
    storage therein and removal therefrom, except as <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[petroleum 
    Class A], of any petroleum, which has not satisfied the prescribed tests.
 
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[***]
 
 







 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Receptacles of dangerous petroleum to show a warning.—All 
    receptacles containing <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[petroleum 
    Class A] shall have a stamped, embossed, painted or printed warning, either 
    on the receptacle itself or, where that is impracticable, displayed near the 
    receptacle, exhibiting in conspicuous characters the words “Petrol” or 
    “Motor Spirit”, or an equivalent warning of the dangerous nature of the 
    petroleum: 
 
Provided that 
    this section shall not apply to—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    any securely stoppered glass, stoneware 
    or metal receptacle of less than <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[ten 
    litres] capacity containing <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[petroleum Class A] which is not for 
    sale, or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    a tank incorporated in a motor conveyance, or 
    attached to an internal combustion engine, and containing petroleum intended 
    to be used to generate motive power for the motor conveyance or engine, or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    a pipe-line for the transport of 
    petroleum, or  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    any tank which is wholly under ground, 
    or  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    any class of receptacles which the 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt from 
    the operation of this section. 
 
 
  







 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> 
    No licence needed for transport or storage of limited quantities of 
    petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Chapter, a person need not obtain a licence for 
    the transport or storage of— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    petroleum Class B if the total quantity 
    in his possession at any one place does not exceed two thousand and five 
    hundred litres and none of it is contained in a receptacle exceeding one 
    thousand litres in capacity; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    petroleum Class C if the total 
    quantity in his possession at any one place does not exceed forty-five 
    thousand litres and such petroleum is transported or stored in accordance 
    with the rules made under section 4.]
  








 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> 
    No licence needed for import, transport or storage of small quantities of 
    petroleum Class A.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, a person need not obtain 
    a licence for the import, transport or storage of petroleum Class A not 
    intended for sale if the total quantity in his possession does not exceed 
    thirty litres. 3[8. 
    No licence needed for import, transport or storage of small quantities of 
    petroleum Class A.—(1) 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, a person need not obtain 
    a licence for the import, transport or storage of petroleum Class A not 
    intended for sale if the total quantity in his possession does not exceed 
    thirty litres. " 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Petroleum 
    Class A possessed without a licence under this section shall be kept in 
    securely stoppered receptacles of glass, stoneware or metal which shall not, 
    in the case of receptacles of glass or stoneware, exceed one litre in 
    capacity or, in the case of receptacles of metal exceed twenty-five litres 
    in capacity.] 
 
 
  






 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Exemptions for motor conveyances and stationary engines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The owner of a motor conveyance, who complies with the requirements of the 
    law for the time being in force relating to the registration and licensing 
    of such conveyance and its driver or pilot and the owner of any stationary 
    internal combustion engine, shall not be required to obtain a licence—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for the import, transport or storage of 
    any petroleum contained in any fuel tank incorporated in the conveyance or 
    attached to the internal combustion engine, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    for the transport or storage of <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[petroleum 
    Class A], not exceeding <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[one 
    hundred litres] in quantity in addition to any quantity possessed under 
    clause (a):
 
Provided the 
    petroleum is intended to be used to generate motive power for motor 
    conveyance or engine:
 
<footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[Provided 
    further that the total quantity of <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[petroleum 
    Class A] which may be stored without a licence under clause (b) shall not 
    exceed <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[one hundred litres], notwithstanding that such owner may 
    possess other motor conveyances or engines.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[Petroleum Class A] transported or stored without a licence <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[under 
    clause (b) of sub-section (1)] shall be kept as provided in sub-section (2) 
    of section 8, and, if it exceeds <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[thirty litres] in quantity, 
    shall be stored in an isolated place which does not communicate with any 
    room where any person resides or works or in any room where persons 
    assemble.
 
 
  









 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    No licence needed by railway administration acting as carrier.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Chapter, a railway administration as defined in 
    section 3 of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890)<footcitenum>26</footcitenum> need 
    not obtain any licence for the import or transport of any petroleum in its 
    possession in its capacity as carrier. 
 



  






 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>11</number> 
    Exemption of heavy oils.—Nothing 
    in this Chapter shall apply to any petroleum which has its flash-point not 
    below ninety-three degrees Centigrade.] 
 
 





 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    General power of exemption.—The
    <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt any 
    petroleum specified in the notification from all or any of the provisions of 
    this Chapter. 
 
 





 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Inspection of places.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may authorize any officer by name or by virtue of office to 
    enter any place where petroleum is being imported, stored, produced, refined 
    or blended, or is under transport, and inspect all receptacles, plant and 
    appliances used in connection with petroleum in order to ascertain if they 
    are in accordance with the provisions of this Chapter and the rules made 
    thereunder. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The
    <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may make rules regulating the procedure of officers authorized 
    under this section. 
 
 
  





 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Inspection and sampling of petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, authorize any 
    officer by name or by virtue of office to enter any place where petroleum is 
    being imported, transported, stored, produced, refined or blended and to 
    inspect and take samples for testing of any petroleum found therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The
    <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may make rules— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    regulating the taking of samples of 
    petroleum for testing; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    determining the cases in which payment 
    shall be made for the value of samples taken, and the mode of payment, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    generally, regulating the procedure of 
    officers exercising powers under this section. 
 
 
 
 





 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Standard Test Apparatus.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A standard apparatus for determining the 

    ![flash-point] of 
    petroleum shall be deposited with an officer to be appointed in this behalf 
    by the <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] by notification in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such 
    apparatus shall be engraved with the words “Standard Test Apparatus”, and 
    shall be verified and corrected from time to time and replaced when 
    necessary, in accordance with rules under section 21. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Standard Test Apparatus shall, on payment of the prescribed fee, be open to 
    inspection at all reasonable times by any person wishing to inspect it.
    
 
 





 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Certification of other test apparatus.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The officer appointed under section 15 shall, on payment of the prescribed 
    fee, if any, compare with the Standard Test Apparatus and apparatus for 
    determining the 

    1[flash-point] of 
    petroleum which may be submitted to him for this purpose. 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    apparatus is found by him to agree with the Standard Test Apparatus within 
    prescribed limits, the officer shall engrave such apparatus with a special 
    number and with the date of the comparison and shall give a certificate in 
    respect of it in the prescribed form, certifying that on the said date the 
    apparatus was compared with the Standard Test Apparatus and was found to 
    agree with it within the prescribed limits, and specifying any corrections 
    to be made in the results of tests carried out with the apparatus.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    certificate granted under this section shall be valid for such period as may 
    be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    certificate granted under this section shall, during the period for which it 
    is valid, be proof, until the contrary is proved, of any matter stated 
    therein.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    officer shall keep a register in the prescribed form of all certificates 
    granted by him under this section. 
 
 





 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Testing officers.—The
    <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may authorize any officer by name or by virtue of office to test 
    petroleum of which samples have been taken under this Act, or which may have 
    been submitted to him for test by any person, and to grant certificates of 
    the results of such tests.
 
 






 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Manner 
    of test.—All tests of petroleum 
    made under this Act shall be made with a test apparatus in respect of which 
    there is valid certificate under section 16, shall have due regard to any 
    correction specified in that certificate, and shall be carried out in 
    accordance with rules made under section 21. 

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Certificate of testing.—<footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The testing officer after testing samples of petroleum shall make out a 
    certificate in the prescribed form, stating whether the petroleum is 
    petroleum Class A or petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C and if the 
    petroleum is petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C, the flash-point of the 
    petroleum.]—2[(1) 
    The testing officer after testing samples of petroleum shall make out a 
    certificate in the prescribed form, stating whether the petroleum is 
    petroleum Class A or petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C and if the 
    petroleum is petroleum Class B or petroleum Class C, the flash-point of the 
    petroleum.]" 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    testing officer shall furnish the person concerned, at his request, with a 
    certified copy of the certificate, on payment of the prescribed fee, and 
    such certified copy may be produced in any court in proof of the contents of 
    the original certificate.  
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
    A certificate given under this section shall be admitted as evidence in any 
    proceedings which may be taken under this Act in respect of the petroleum 
    from which the samples were taken, and shall, until the contrary is proved, 
    be conclusive proof, that the petroleum is petroleum Class A or petroleum 
    Class B or petroleum Class C, and, if the petroleum is petroleum Class B or 
    petroleum Class C, of its flash-point.]  
 
 







 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Right 
    to require re-test.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner 
    of any petroleum, or his agent, who is dissatisfied with the result of the 
    test of the petroleum may, within seven days from the date on which he 
    received intimation of the result of the test, apply to the officer 
    empowered under section 14 to have fresh samples of the petroleum taken and 
    tested.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On such 
    application and on payment of the prescribed fee, fresh samples of the 
    petroleum shall be taken in the presence of such owner or agent or person 
    deputed by him, and shall be tested in the presence of such owner or agent 
    or person deputed by him. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, on 
    such re-test, it appears that the original test was erroneous the testing 
    officer shall cancel the original certificate granted under section 19, 
    shall make out a fresh certificate, and shall furnish the owner of the 
    petroleum, or his agent, with a certified copy thereof, free of charge. 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Power to make rules regarding tests.—The
    <footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may make rules——The
    

    1[Central Government] 
    may make rules—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    for the specification, verification, 
    correction and replacement of the Standard Test Apparatus;  
    
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    prescribing fees for the inspection of 
    the Standard Test Apparatus;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    regulating the procedure in comprising 
    a test apparatus with the Standard Test Apparatus;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    prescribing the form of certificate to 
    be given in respect of a test apparatus so compared, and the period for 
    which such certificate shall be valid;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    prescribing the form of the register of 
    such certificates;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    prescribing fees for comparing a test 
    apparatus with Standard Test Apparatus;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    regulating the procedure of testing 
    officers in carrying out tests of petroleum, providing for the averaging of 
    results where several samples of the same petroleum are tested, and 
    prescribing the variations from standard temperatures which may be allowed;  
    
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    prescribing the form of certificate of 
    tests of petroleum and the fees which may be charged therefor;  
    
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    providing, where the results of the 
    testing of samples raise a doubt as to the uniformity of the quality of the 
    petroleum in any lot under test, for the division of the lot into sub-lots, 
    and for the selection and testing of samples of each sub-lot and for the 
    averaging of results in accordance with the results of tests of those 
    samples;  
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    prescribing fees for re-tests under 
    section 20 and providing for their refund where the original test was 
    erroneous; and 
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    generally, regulating the procedure of 
    all officers performing duties connected with the testing of petroleum, and 
    providing for any matter incidental to such testing. 
 
 






 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Special rules for testing viscous or solid forms of petroleum.—The
    <footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may also make rules providing specially for the testing of any 
    form of petroleum which is viscous or solid or contains sediment or 
    thickening ingredients, and such rules may modify or supplement any of the 
    provisions of this Chapter or of the rules made under section 21 in order to 
    adapt them to the special needs of such tests.
 
 





 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> General 
    penalty for offences under this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in contravention of any of the 
    provisions of Chapter 1 or of any of the rules made thereunder, imports, 
    transports, stores, produces, refines or blends any petroleum, or  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    contravenes any rule made under section 
    4 or section 5, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[<number>c</number>    
    being the holder or a licence issued under section 4 or a person for the 
    time being placed by the holder of such licence in control or in charge of 
    any place where petroleum is being imported or stored, or is under 
    transport, contravenes any condition of such licence or suffers any 
    condition of such licence to be contravened, or]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    being for the time being in control or 
    in charge of any place where petroleum is being imported, stored, produced, 
    refined or blended or is under transport, refuses or neglects to show to any 
    officer authorized under section 13 any receptacle, plant or appliance used 
    in such place in connection with petroleum, or in any way obstructs or fails 
    to render reasonable assistance to such officer during an inspection, or  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    being for the time being in control or 
    in charge of any place where petroleum is being imported, transported, 
    stored, produced, refined or blended, refuses or neglects to show to any 
    officer authorized under section 14 any petroleum in such place, or to give 
    him such assistance as he may require for the inspection of such petroleum, 
    or refuses to allow him to take samples of the petroleum, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    being required, under section 27, to 
    give information of an accident, fails to give such information as so 
    required by that section, 
 
shall be 
    punishable <footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[with simple imprisonment which may extend to one 
    month, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both].
    
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    any person, having been convicted of an offence punishable under sub-section 
    (1), is again guilty of any offence punishable under that sub-section, he 
    shall be punishable for every such subsequent offence <footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[with 
    simple imprisonment which may extend to three months, or with fine which may 
    extend to five thousand rupees, or with both].
 
 
  








 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Confiscation of petroleum and receptacles.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any case in which an offence under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> or clause (b) or clause (c) 
    of sub-section (1) of section 23 has been committed, the convicting 
    Magistrate may direct that—
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    the petroleum in respect of which the 
    offence has been committed, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the offender is convicted of 
    importing, transporting or storing petroleum exceeding the quantity he is 
    permitted to import, transport or store, as the case may be, the whole of 
    the petroleum in respect of which the offence was committed, 
 
shall, together with the receptacles in which 
    it is contained, be confiscated.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> This power 
    may also be exercised by the High Court in the exercise of its appellate or 
    revisional powers.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Offences punishable under this Act shall be triable in the Presidency-towns, 
    by a Presidency Magistrate, and elsewhere by a Magistrate of the first 
    class, or by a Magistrate of the second class who has been specially 
    empowered by the <footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] in this behalf. 
 
 





 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Power of entry and search.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The <footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, authorize any 
    officer by name or by virtue of office to enter and search any place where 
    he has reason to believe that any petroleum is being imported, transported, 
    stored, produced, refined or blended otherwise than in accordance with the 
    provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, and to seize, detain 
    or remove any or all of the petroleum in respect of which in his opinion an 
    offence under this Act has been committed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of the 

    2[Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], relating to searches shall, so far as they are 
    applicable, apply to searches by officers authorized under this section.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The
    <footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may make rules regulating the procedure of authorized officers 
    in the exercise of their powers under this section subject, however, to the 
    provisions of sub-section (2). 
  











 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[<number>27</number> 
    Notice of accidents with petroleum.—Whenever 
    there occurs in or about, or in connection with, any place in which 
    petroleum is refined, blended or kept, or any carriage or vessel either 
    conveying petroleum or on or from which petroleum is being loaded or 
    unloaded, any accident by explosion or by fire as a result of the ignition 
    of petroleum or petroleum vapour attended with loss of human life or serious 
    injury to person or property, or of a description usually attended with such 
    loss or injury, the occupier of the place or the person for the time being 
    incharge of the petroleum or the person incharge of the carriage or the 
    master of the vessel, as the case may be, shall, within such time and in 
    such manner as may be prescribed, give notice thereof and of the attendant 
    loss of human life, or injury to person or property, if any, to the nearest 
    Magistrate or to the officer-in-charge of the nearest police station and to 
    the <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[Chief Controller of Explosives].] 
 
 







 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Inquiries into serious accidents with petroleum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The inquiry mentioned in section 176 of the 
<footcitenum>46</footcitenum>[Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], shall, <footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[unless section 8 
    of the Coroners Act, 1871 (4 of 1871), is applicable to the circumstances,] 
    be held in all cases where any person has been killed by an accident which 
    the Magistrate has reason to believe was the result of the ignition of 
    petroleum or petroleum vapour. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    Magistrate empowered to hold an inquest may also hold an inquiry under the 
    said section into the cause of any accident which he has reason to believe 
    was the result of the ignition of petroleum or petroleum vapour, if such 
    accident was attended by serious injury to person or property, 
    notwithstanding that no person was killed thereby. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For 
    the purposes of <footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[sub-section (2)] a Commissioner of Police <footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[***] <footcitenum>50</footcitenum>[***] shall be deemed to be a Magistrate empowered 
    to hold an inquest.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    result of all inquiries held in pursuance of this section <footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[and 
    of any inquiry held by a coroner in a case to which sub-section (1) refers] 
    shall be submitted as soon as may be to the <footcitenum>51</footcitenum>[Central Government]
    <footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[the <footcitenum>52</footcitenum>[Chief Controller of Explosives] and the State 
    Government.]
 
 











 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Provisions relating to rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In making any rules under this Act, the <footcitenum>53</footcitenum>[Central Government] 
    may—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    provide for any matter ancillary to 
    such rules for which in <footcitenum>54</footcitenum>[its] opinion provision is necessary to 
    protect the public from danger arising from the import, transport, storage, 
    production, refining or blending of petroleum, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    make special provision for the special 
    circumstances of any State or place. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    power to make rules conferred by this Act is subject to the condition of 
    previous publication. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    rules made under this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette <footcitenum>55</footcitenum>[***].
    
 


    4[(4) Every rule made 
    under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
    each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of 
    thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.]
 
 









 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> Power 
    to apply Act to other substances.—[Repealed 
    by the Inflammable Substances Act, 1952 (20 of 1952), section 7.]

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Power to limit powers of local authorities over petroleum.—Where 
    any enactment confers powers upon any local authority in respect of the 
    transport or storage of petroleum, the <footcitenum>57</footcitenum>[Central 
    Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette,— 

 <section>
       <number>a</number>    limit the operation of such 
    enactment, or 
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>    restrict the exercise of 
    such powers, in any manner 
2[it] 
    deems fit. 
 
 





 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Repeals.—[Repealed by the 
    Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Schedule.]

 
  


  
</article><form>
 

THE
PETROLEUM ACT,1934
 

 
 

THE SCHEDULE.—Enactments repealed.—[Repealed
by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938) sec. 2 and Schedule.] tc "THE SCHEDULE.—Enactments repealed.—[Repealed by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938) sec.
2 and Schedule.]"


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for sub-section (2).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   The words “except the State of Jammu and Kashmir” 
    omitted by Act 62 of 1956, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Came into force on  30th March, 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 3, for clause (b) (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 3, for “flashing-point” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 3, for clause (d) (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 62 of 1956, sec. 2 and Sch., for “the territories to 
    which this Act extends” (w.e.f. 1-11-1956).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Clause (i) ins. by the A.O. 1950 and omitted by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 4, for “any dangerous petroleum” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 5, for “dangerous petroleum” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 5, for “dangerous petroleum” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “his”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Ins. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 6, for “dangerous petroleum” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Sub-section (3) omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 7, for “dangerous petroleum” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 7, for “two gallons” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 8, for section 7 (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 8, for section 8 (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 9, for “dangerous petroleum” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 9, for “twenty gallons” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Ins. by Act 25 of 1940, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 9, for “six gallons” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Now the Railway Act, 1989 (24 of 1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 10, for section 11 (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 11, for “flashing-point” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 12, for “flashing-point” (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 13, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 
    1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, for sub-section (3) (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 1941, sec. 2, for clause (c).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 14, for “with fine which may extend 
    to five hundred rupees” (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number>   Subs. by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 14, for “with fine which way extend 
    to two thousand rupees” (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>   Subs by Act 31 of 1977, sec. 2, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.e.f. 12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>   Subs by Act 24 of 1970, sec. 15, for section 27 (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of 1977, sec. 3, for “Chief Inspector of 
    Explosives in India” (w.e.f. 12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of 1977, sec. 4, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.e.f. 12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>   Ins. by Act 25 of 1940, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>   Subs. by Act 25 of 1940, sec. 3, for “this section”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>   The words “in a Presidency-town”  omitted by Act 24 of 1970,  sec. 
    16 (w.e.f. 1-8-1976).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>   The words “or in Rangoon” omitted by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>   Subs. by A.O. 1937, for “local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of 1977, sec. 4, for “Chief Inspector of 
    Explosives in India” (w.e.f. 12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>   Subs. by A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “his”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>   The words “and in the local Official Gazette” omitted by the A.O. 
    1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of  1977, sec. 5, for sub-section (4) (w.e.f. 
    12-8-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>    Subs. by 
    A.O. 1937, for “Governor-General-in-Council”.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>