<act><title>

The 
    Export-Import Bank of India Act, 1981</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Export-Import Bank of India Act, 1981.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force no such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of 
    this Act. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Board” means the Board of Directors of 
    the Exim Bank referred to in section 6; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Development Bank” means the Industrial 
    Development Bank of India established under the Industrial Development Bank 
    of India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964); 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Exim Bank” means the Export-Import 
    Bank of India established under section 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “export” and “import” mean 
    respectively, export from or import into India or any other country of goods 
    or services, or both; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “goods” includes all materials, 
    commodities and articles in a solid, liquid or gaseous state and all forms 
    of energy; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “notification” means a notification 
    published in the Official Gazette; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    regulations made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve Bank 
    of India constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “scheduled bank” means a bank, for the 
    time being, included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of India 
    Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); 
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “services” includes,— 
 <subsection>
<number>I</number>    providing personnel (including skilled 
    or unskilled workmen and persons for rendering technical or other services) 
    for the purposes of any work or project (by whatever name called) or any 
    activity; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>II</number>    transferring of technology, including 
    transferring, or securing the transfer of rights, knowhow, expertises or 
    other skill with respect to any patent, invention, model, design, secret 
    formula or process or similar property; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>III</number>    furnishing any information, 
    blueprints, plans, or advice with respect to any matter; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>IV</number>    making available any other resources. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Establishment and incorporation of Export-Import Bank of 
      India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      With effect from such date1 as the Central Government 
      may, by notification, appoint, there shall be established for the purposes 
      of this Act a corporation to be known as the Export-Import Bank of 
      India.—(1) 
    With effect from such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, there shall be 
    established for the purposes of this Act a corporation to be known as the 
    Export-Import Bank of India." 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Exim Bank shall be a body corporate with 
      the name aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common seal with 
      power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose 
      of property and to contract, and may, by that name, sue or be sued. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The head office of the Exim Bank shall be at 
      Bombay or at such other place as the Central Government may, by 
      notification, specify. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Exim Bank may establish offices, 
      branches or agencies at such plances in or outside India as it may 
      consider necessary. 
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Authorised capital.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The authorised capital of the Exim Bank shall be one thousand crores of 
    rupees:—2[(1) 
    The authorised capital of the Exim Bank shall be one thousand crores of 
    rupees\:" 
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, by notification, increase the said capital up to 
    two thousand crores of rupees.] 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The issued 
    capital of the Exim Bank shall be wholly subscribed by the Central 
    Government. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Management.—
<section><number>1</number> The general 
    superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and business of the 
    Exim Bank shall vest in the Board, which may exercise all powers and do all 
    acts and things which may be exercised or done by the Exim Bank. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided in the regulations made under this Act,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the chairman, if he is a whole-time 
    director or if he is holding offices both as the chairman and the managing 
    director, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the managing director, if the chairman 
    is not a whole-time director, or, if the chairman being a whole-time 
    director, is absent, 
 
shall also have powers of general 
    superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and business of the 
    Exim Bank and may also exercise all powers and do all acts and things which 
    may be exercised or done by the Exim Bank.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this Act, the Board in discharging its functions shall act 
    on business principles with due regard to public interest. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the 
    discharge of its functions under this Act, the Exim Bank shall be guided by 
    such directions in matters of policy involving public interest as the 
    Central Government may give to it in writing. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Constitution of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Board of Directors of the Exim Bank shall consist of the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a chairman and a managing director 
    appointed by the Central Government: 
 
Provided that the same person may be appointed 
    to function both as chairman and as managing director; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    one director nominated by the Reserve 
    Bank; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    one director nominated by the 
    Development Bank; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    one director nominated by the Export 
    Credit and Guarantee Corporation Limited, being a Government Company within 
    the meaning of section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    not more than twelve directors 
    nominated by the Central Government of whom— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    five directors shall be officials of 
    the Central Government; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    not more than three directors shall be 
    from the scheduled banks; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    not more than four directors shall be 
    persons who have special knowledge of, or professional experience in, export 
    or import or financing thereof. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    chairman and the managing director shall hold office for such term, not 
    exceeding 

    1[five years], as the 
    Central Government may specify in this behalf and any person so appointed 
    shall be eligible for re-appointment.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central 
    Government shall have the right to terminate the term of office of the 
    chairman or the managing director, as the case may be, at any time before 
    the expiry of the term specified under sub-section (2), by giving him notice 
    of not less than three months in writing or three months’ salary and 
    allowances in lieu thereof, and the chairman or the managing director, as 
    the case may be, shall also have the right to relinquish his office at any 
    time before the expiry of the term specified under sub-section (2) by giving 
    to the Central Government notice of not less than three months in writing or 
    three months’ salary and allowances in lieu thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    chairman and the managing director shall receive such salary and allowances 
    as may be determined by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Central Government may, at any time, remove the chairman or the managing 
    director, as the case may be, from office:
 
Provided that 
    no person shall be removed from his office under this sub-section unless he 
    has been given an opportunity of showing cause against his removal.
 

2[(6) 
    Subject to the provisions contained in sub-section (7), any director 
    nominated under clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) or clause (e) of 
    sub-section (1) and not being an official of Government or not being a 
    whole-time director or official of the Reserve Bank or the Development Bank 
    or the said Export Credit and Guarantee Corporation Limited or a scheduled 
    bank, shall hold office for such term, not exceeding three years, as the 
    Central Government or, as the case may be, the authority nominating him, may 
    specify in this behalf 3[***] 
    and shall be eligible for re-nomination:
 
Provided that 
    no such director shall hold office continuously for a period exceeding six 
    years.]
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any
    

    4[***] director 
    nominated under this section shall hold office during the pleasure of the 
    authority nominating him.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Board 
    shall meet at such times and places and shall observe such rules of 
    procedure in regard to the transaction of business of its meetings as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The 
    chairman or, if for any reason he is unable to attend a meeting of the 
    Board, the managing director or, in the event of both the chairman and the 
    managing director being unable to attend a meeting, any other director 
    nominated by the chairman in this behalf and in the absence of such 
    nomination any director elected by the directors present from among 
    themselves, shall preside at the meeting. 
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> All 
    questions which come up before any meeting of the Board shall be decided by 
    a majority of votes of the directors present and voting, and in the event of 
    an equality of votes, the chairman, or in his absence, the managing 
    director, or in the absence of both the chairman and the managing director, 
    the person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote. 
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided in sub-section (10), every director of the Board shall 
    have one vote. 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board may 
    constitute such Committees whether consisting wholly of directors or wholly 
    of other persons or partly of directors and partly of other persons for such 
    purpose or purposes as it may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    Committee constituted under sub-section (1) shall meet at such times and 
    places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
    transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Fees and 
    allowances of directors and members of Committees.—The 
    directors and the members of a Committee shall be paid such fees and 
    allowances as may be prescribed for attending the meetings of the Board or 
    of any Committee constituted in pursuance of this Act and for attending to 
    any other work of the Exim Bank: 
 
Provided that 
    no fees shall be payable to the chairman, if he is appointed as a whole-time 
    chairman, or to the managing director or to any other director or member who 
    is an official of the Government, the Reserve Bank or the Development Bank. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Disqualifications.—No person 
    shall be a director of the Board constituted under this Act, who— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    is, or at any time has been, adjudged 
    insolvent, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    is of unsound mind and has been so 
    declared by a competent court, or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    is, or has been, convicted of an 
    offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral 
    turpitude, or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    has, in the opinion of the Central 
    Government, so abused his position as a director, as to render his 
    continuance on the Board detrimental to the interests of the general public, 
    or 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    has been, for any reason, removed from 
    the Board. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Business of Exim Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Exim Bank may grant in or outside India loans and advances by itself or in 
    participation with any bank or financial institution whether in or outside 
    India for the purposes of export or import and shall also function as the 
    principal financial institution for co-ordinating the working of 
    institutions engaged in financing of the export and import in such manner as 
    it may deem appropriate. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Exim 
    Bank may also carry on and transact all or any of the following kinds of 
    business, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    granting loans and advances to a 
    scheduled bank or any other bank or financial institution notified in the 
    Official Gazette by the Central Government in this behalf by way of 
    refinance of loans and advances granted by it for purposes of export or 
    import;. 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    underwriting the issue of stocks, 
    shares, bonds or debentures of any company engaged in export or import; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    issuing bid bonds or guarantees in or 
    outside India by itself or in participation with any Government, bank or 
    financial institution in or outside India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    accepting, collecting, discounting, 
    re-discounting, purchasing, selling or negotiating in or outside India, 
    bills of exchange or promissory notes arising out of transactions relating 
    to export or import and granting of loans and advances in or outside India 
    against such bills or promissory notes; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    granting, opening, issuing, confirming 
    or endorsing letters of credit and negotiating or collecting bills and other 
    documents drawn thereunder; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    undertaking any transaction involving a 
    combination of government to government and commercial credit for purposes 
    of export or import; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    granting lines of credit to the 
    government of any foreign State or any financial institution or person 
    outside India for purposes of export or import; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    granting loans and advances outside 
    India for any Indian joint venture; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    granting loans and advances to any 
    person in India in connection with his equity contribution in any joint 
    venture in any country outside India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    financing export or import of machinery 
    and equipment on lease basis;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    subscribing to, or investing in, or 
    purchasing of, stocks, shares, bonds or debentures of any development bank 
    or Export-Import Bank of any country outside India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    buying or selling of, or entering into 
    such other dealings in, foreign exchange, as may be necessary for the 
    discharge of its functions; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    opening of any account in any bank in 
    or outside India or the making of any agency arrangement with, or acting as 
    an agent or correspondent of, any bank or other institution in or outside 
    India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    transferring, for consideration, any 
    instrument relating to loans and advances granted by it; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    issuing participation certificates; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    subscribing to, or investing in, or 
    purchasing of stocks, shares, bonds or debentures to the extent necessary 
    for the enforcement of a lien, pledge or other contractual right; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>    undertaking and financing of research, 
    surveys, techno-economic or any other study in connection with the promotion 
    and development of international trade; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>    providing technical, administrative and 
    financial assistance of any kind for export or import; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>    planning, promoting, developing and 
    financing export-oriented concerns; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number>    forming or conducting subsidiaries for 
    carrying out its functions; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>    acting as agent of the Central 
    Government, any State Government, the Reserve Bank, the Development Bank or 
    any other person as the Central Government may authorise; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    collecting, compiling and disseminating 
    market and credit information in respect of international trade; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>w</number>    doing any other kind of business which 
    the Central Government may authorise; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>    generally doing such other acts and 
    things as may be incidental to, or consequential upon, the exercise of its 
    powers or the discharge of its duties under this Act or any other law for 
    the time being in force, including sale or transfer of any of its assets. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Exim 
    Bank may receive in consideration of any of the services mentioned in 
    sub-sections (1) and (2) such commission, brokerage, interest, remuneration 
    or fees as may be agreed upon. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Exim 
    Bank shall not grant any loan or advance or other financial accommodation on 
    the security of its own bonds or debentures. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Loans 
    by Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, advance to the Exim Bank— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    a loan of twenty crores of rupees at a 
    rate of interest of five and a quarter per cent. per annum repayable in 
    fifteen equal annual instalments, commencing on the expiry of a period of 
    fifteen years from the date of receipt of the loan; and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    such further sums of money by way of 
    loan on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon: 
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government may, on a request being made to it by the Exim Bank, 
    increase the number of instalments or alter the amount of any instalment or 
    vary the date on which any instalment is payable under clause (a). 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Borrowings and acceptance of deposits by Exim Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Exim Bank may, for the purposes of carrying out its functions under this 
    Act,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    issue and sell bonds and debentures 
    with or without the guarantee of the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    borrow money from the Reserve Bank— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    repayable on demand or on the expiry of 
    fixed periods not exceeding ninety days from the date on which the money is 
    so borrowed against the security of stocks, funds and securities (other than 
    immovable property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest trust money 
    by any law for the time being in force in India; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    against bills of exchange or 
    promissory notes arising out of bona fide commercial or trade 
    transactions and bearing two or more good signatures and maturing within 
    five years from the date of the borrowing; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    out of the National Industrial Credit 
    (Long Term Operations) Fund established under section 46C of the Reserve 
    Bank of India Act 1934 (2 of 1934), for any of the purposes specified in 
    that section;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    borrow money from such other authority, 
    organisation or institution in India as may generally or specially be 
    approved by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    accept deposits repayable after the 
    expiry of a period which shall not be less than twelve months from the date 
    of the making of the deposit on such terms as may generally or specially be 
    approved by the Reserve Bank. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, on a request being made to it by the Exim Bank, 
    guarantee the bonds and debentures issued by that Bank as to the repayment 
    of principal and the payment of interest at such rate as may be fixed by 
    that Government. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Loans 
    in foreign currency.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 
    1973), or in any other law for the time being in force relating to foreign 
    exchange, the Exim Bank may, for the purpose of granting loans and advances 
    under this Act, borrow, with the previous consent of the Central Government, 
    foreign currency from any foreign State or from any bank or financial 
    institution in any foreign country or otherwise. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Grants, 
    donations, etc., to Exim Bank.—The 
    Exim Bank may receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions from 
    Government or any other source in or outside India. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Export 
    Development Fund.—With effect 
    from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, the 
    Exim Bank shall establish a special fund to be called the Export Development 
    Fund. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Credits 
    to Export Development Fund.—To 
    the Export Development Fund shall be credited— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    all amounts received for the purposes 
    of that Fund by way of loans, gifts, grants, donations or benefactions from 
    Government or any other source in or outside India; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    repayments or recoveries in respect of 
    loans, advances or other facilities granted from the Fund; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    income or profits from investments made 
    from the Fund; and 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    income accruing or arising to the Fund 
    by way of interest or otherwise, on account of the application of the Fund 
    in accordance with the provisions of section 17. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Utilisation of Export Development Fund.—
<section><number>1</number>Where 
    the Exim Bank considers it necessary or desirable so to do, it may, subject 
    to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), disburse or spend from the 
    Export Development Fund any amount on account or in consequence of the grant 
    of any loan or advance, or on account or in consequence of entering into any 
    arrangement under sub-section (1) or clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) 
    or clause (q) or clause (r) or clause (s) or clause (w) or clause (x) of 
    sub-section (2) of section 10: 
 
Provided that 
    before granting any such loan or advance or entering into any such 
    arrangement, the Exim Bank shall obtain the prior approval of the Central 
    Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before 
    seeking the approval of the Central Government under sub-section (1), the 
    Exim Bank shall satisfy itself that banking or other financial institutions 
    or other agencies are not likely to grant such loan or advance, or to enter 
    into any such arrangement in the ordinary course of business. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government shall, before giving its approval, satisfy itself that 
    such loan, advance or arrangement is necessary as a matter of priority in 
    the interests of the international trade of the country. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the 
    removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that nothing contained in this 
    section shall be deemed to preclude the Exim Bank from granting any loan or 
    advance or from entering into any arrangement under sub-section (1) or 
    clause (b) or clause (c) or clause (d) or clause (q) or clause (r) or clause 
    (s) or clause (w) or clause (x) of sub-section (2) of section 10 without the 
    approval of the Central Government; if no amount in respect thereof is to be 
    disbursed or spent from the Export Development Fund. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Debits 
    to Export Development Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    To the Export Development Fund shall be debited— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    such amounts as may from time to time 
    be disbursed or spent under sub-section (1) of section 17; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such amounts as may be required for 
    discharging the liabilities in respect of loans received for the purposes of 
    that Fund; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any loss arising on account of 
    investment made out of that Fund; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    such expenditure arising out of, or in 
    connection with, the administration and application of the Fund as may be 
    determined by the Board. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No amount 
    shall be debited to the Export Development Fund except as provided for in 
    sub-section (1). 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Accounts and audit of Export Development Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The balance-sheet and accounts of the Export Development Fund shall be 
    prepared in such form and manner as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall cause the books and accounts of the Export Development Fund to 
    be closed and balanced as on the 31st day of December 

    1[or such other date 
    in each year as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, specify]. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Export 
    Development Fund shall be audited by one or more auditors appointed by the 
    Central Government under section 24 who shall make a separate report 
    thereon. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    provisions of sub-sections (2), (3), (4) and (6) of section 24 shall, so far 
    as may be, apply in relation to the audit of the Export Development Fund. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Exim 
    Bank shall furnish to the Central Government within four months from the 
    date on which the accounts of the Export Development Fund are closed and 
    balanced, a copy of the balance-sheet and accounts together with a copy of 
    the auditor’s report and a report on the operation of the Fund during the 
    relevant year and the Central Government shall, as soon as may be after they 
    are received by it, cause the same to be laid before each House of 
    Parliament: 
 


    2[Provided that with a 
    view to facilitating the transition from one period of accounting to another 
    period of accounting under this sub-section, the Central Government may, by 
    order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions as it 
    considers necessary or expedient for the closing and balancing of, or for 
    other matters relating to, the books or accounts in respect of the concerned 
    years.] 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Liquidation of Export Development Fund.—The 
    Export Development Fund shall not be closed or wound up save by order of the 
    Central Government and in such manner as that Government may direct. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> General 
    Fund.—All receipts of the Exim 
    Bank other than those which are to be credited to the Export Development 
    Fund under this Act shall be credited to a Fund to be called the General 
    Fund and all payments by the Exim Bank, other than those which are to be 
    debited to the Export Development Fund, shall be made out of the General 
    Fund. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Preparation of accounts and balance-sheet.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The balance-sheet and accounts of the Exim Bank shall be prepared in such 
    form and manner as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall cause the books and accounts of the Exim Bank to be closed and 
    balanced as on the 31st day of December 

    1[or such other date 
    in each year as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, specify:] 
 


    2[Provided that with a 
    view to facilitating the transition from one period of accounting to another 
    period of accounting under this sub-section, the Central Government may, by 
    order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions as it 
    considers necessary or expedient for the closing and balancing of, or for 
    other matters relating to, the books or accounts in respect of the concerned 
    years.] 
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Disposal of profits accruing to General Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Exim Bank may establish a Reserve Fund to which may be transferred such 
    sums as that Bank may deem fit out of the annual profits accruing to the 
    General Fund. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After 
    making provision for bad and doubtful debts, depreciation of assets and for 
    all other matters for which provision is necessary or expedient or which is 
    usually provided for by bankers and for the Reserve Fund referred to in 
    sub-section (1), the Exim Bank shall transfer the balance of the net profits 
    to the Central Government. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accounts of the Exim Bank shall be audited by auditors duly qualified to 
    act as auditors under sub-section (1) of section 226 of the Companies Act, 
    1956 (1 of 1956), who shall be appointed by the Central Government for such 
    term and on such remuneration as the Central Government may fix. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    auditors shall be supplied with a copy of the annual balance-sheet of the 
    Exim Bank and it shall be their duty to examine it together with the 
    accounts and vouchers relating thereto and they shall have a list delivered 
    to them of all books kept by the Exim Bank and shall at all reasonable times 
    have access to the books, accounts, vouchers and other documents of the Exim 
    Bank. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    auditors may, in relation to such accounts, examine any director or any 
    officer or other employee of the Exim Bank and shall be entitled to require 
    from the Board or officer or other employee of the Exim Bank such 
    information and explanation as they may think necessary for the performance 
    of their duties. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    auditors shall make a report to the Exim Bank upon the annual balance-sheet 
    and accounts examined by them and in every such report they shall state 
    whether in their opinion the balance-sheet is a full and fair balance-sheet 
    containing all necessary particulars and properly drawn up so as to exhibit 
    a true and fair view of the state of affairs of the Exim Bank and in case 
    they had called for any explanation or information from the Board or any 
    officer or other employee of the Exim Bank whether it has been given and 
    whether it is satisfactory. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Exim 
    Bank shall furnish to the Central Government within four months from the 
    date on which its accounts are closed and balanced, a copy of its balance- 
    sheet and accounts together with a copy of the auditors’ report and a report 
    of the working of the Exim Bank during the relevant year, and the Central 
    Government shall, as soon as may be after they are received by it, cause the 
    same to be laid before each House of Parliament. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Without 
    prejudice to anything contained in the preceding sub-sections, the Central 
    Government may, at any time, appoint the Comptroller and Auditor-General of 
    India to examine and report upon the accounts of the Exim Bank and any 
    expenditure incurred by him in connection with such examination and report 
    shall be payable by the Exim Bank to the Comptroller and Auditor-General of 
    India. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Saving.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in sub-section (4) of section 19, nothing contained in 
    this Chapter shall apply to the Export Development Fund. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Transfer of part of business of Development Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On such date as the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, all 
    business, property, assets and liabilities, rights, interests, privileges 
    and obligations of whatever nature of the Development Bank in so far as they 
    relate to the export financing functions of that Bank shall stand 
    transferred to, and vest in, the Exim Bank. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    transfer to, and vesting in, the Exim Bank under sub-section (1), the Exim 
    Bank shall pay to the Development Bank such amount in such manner and in 
    such number of instalments as may be determined by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    contracts, deeds, bonds, agreements, powers-of-attorney, grants of legal 
    representation and other instruments of whatever nature of the Development 
    Bank which relate to the export financing functions of that Bank and which 
    are subsisting or having effect immediately before the date referred to in 
    sub-section (1) and to which the said Bank is a party or which are in favour 
    of that Bank shall,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if they relate exclusively to the 
    export financing functions of that Bank, be of full force and effect against 
    or in favour of the Exim Bank, as the case may be, and may be enforced and 
    acted upon as fully and effectively as if instead of the Development Bank 
    the Exim Bank had been a party thereto or as if they had been issued in 
    favour of the Exim Bank; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if they relate not only to the export 
    financing functions of the Development Bank but also to any of the other 
    functions of that Bank, be of full force and effect against or in favour of 
    both the Development Bank and the Exim Bank and may be enforced or acted 
    upon as fully and effectively as if in addition to the Development Bank the 
    Exim Bank had also been a party thereto or as if they had been issued in 
    favour of the Development Bank and also the Exim Bank. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If, on the 
    date referred to in sub-section (1), any suit appeal or other legal 
    proceeding of whatever nature relating to the export financing functions of 
    the Development Bank is pending, the same shall not abate, be discontinued 
    or be in any way prejudicially affected by reason of the transfer to the 
    Exim Bank of the business of the Development Bank or of anything contained 
    in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where it relates exclusively to the 
    export financing functions of the Development Bank, be continued, prosecuted 
    and enforced by or against the Exim Bank; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where it relates not only to the export 
    financing functions of the Development Bank but also to any of the other 
    functions of that Bank, be continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against 
    the Development Bank and the Exim Bank or, if the Central Government by 
    special order in writing so directs, by or against such one of the said two 
    Banks, as may be specified in such order. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> If any 
    question arises as to whether any contract, deed, bond, agreement, powers- 
    of-attorney, grant of legal representation or other instrument referred to 
    in sub-section (3) or any suit, appeal or other legal proceeding referred to 
    in sub-section (4) relates or relates exclusively to the export financing 
    functions of the Development Bank, it shall be referred to the Central 
    Government for decision and the decision of the Central Government thereon 
    shall be final. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    provisions of this section shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964 (8 of 1964), 
    or any other law or any instrument having force by virtue of the said Act or 
    other law. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Staff 
    of Exim Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> The Exim Bank 
    may appoint such number of officers and other employees as it considers 
    necessary or desirable for the efficient performance of its functions and 
    determine the terms and conditions of their appointment and service. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), it shall be lawful for the 
    Exim Bank to utilise, and for the Development Bank to make available the 
    services of, such staff of the Development Bank having experience relating 
    to export financing functions on such terms and conditions as may be agreed 
    upon between the Exim Bank and the Development Bank. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The duties 
    and conduct, terms and conditions of service and the establishment and 
    maintenance of a provident Fund or any other Fund for the benefit of the 
    officers and other employees of the Exim Bank shall be such as may be 
    prescribed. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Delegation of powers.—The 
    Board may, by general or special order, delegate to any director or any 
    officer or other employee of the Exim Bank, subject to such conditions and 
    limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers 
    and functions under this Act as it may deem necessary.
  

 
 
The Board 
      has been authorised to delegate to any director or any officer or any 
      other employee of the Exim Bank, such powers and functions as may be 
      deemed necessary.



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Returns.—The Exim Bank shall 
    furnish, from time to time, to the Central Government such returns as the 
    Central Government may require. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Obligation as to fidelity and secrecy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Exim Bank shall not, except as otherwise required by this Act or any 
    other law, divulge any information relating to or to the affairs of, its 
    constituents except in circumstances in which it is, in accordance with the 
    law or practice and usage customary among bankers, necessary or appropriate 
    for the Exim Bank to divulge such information. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Exim 
    Bank may, for the purpose of efficient discharge of its functions under this 
    Act, collect from, or furnish to, the Central Government, the Development 
    Bank or any scheduled bank or such other financial institution, as may be 
    notified in the Official Gazette by the Central Government in this behalf, 
    credit information or other information as it may consider useful for the 
    purpose, in such manner and at such times, as it may think fit. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this sub-section, the expression “credit information” shall 
    have the same meaning as in clause (c) of section 45A of the Reserve Bank of 
    India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934), subject to the modification that “banking 
    company” referred to therein shall mean the Development Bank, any scheduled 
    bank or other financial institution as aforesaid. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    director, member of a committee, auditor or officer or other employee of the 
    Exim Bank or of the Development Bank whose services are utilised by the Exim 
    Bank under the provisions of this Act, shall, before entering upon his 
    duties, make a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in 
    the First Schedule. 
 


    1[(4) Nothing 
    contained in this section shall apply to the credit information disclosed 
    under the Credit Information Companies (Regulation) Act, 2005.] 
 
 

 




 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>31</number> Defects in appointments not to invalidate acts, etc. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> No act or proceeding of the Board or of any committee of the Exim 
Bank shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy 
in, or defect in the constitution of, the Board or the committee, as the case 
may be. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No act done by any person acting in good faith as a director 
shall be deemed to be invalid merely on the ground that he was disqualified to 
be a director or that there was any other defect in his appointment. 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Arrangement with Exim Bank on appointment of directors to prevail.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any arrangement entered into by the Exim Bank with a company provides 
    for the appointment by the Exim Bank of one or more directors of such 
    company, such provision and any appointment of directors made in pursuance 
    thereof shall be valid and effective notwithstanding anything to the 
    contrary contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or in any other 
    law for the time being in force or in the memorandum, articles of 
    association or any other instrument relating to the company, and any 
    provision regarding share qualification, age limit, number of directorships, 
    removal from office of directors and such like conditions contained in any 
    such law or instrument aforesaid, shall not apply to any director appointed 
    by the Exim Bank in pursuance of the arrangement as aforesaid. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    director appointed as aforesaid shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    hold office during the pleasure of the 
    Exim Bank and may be removed or substituted by any person by order in 
    writing of the Exim Bank; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    not incur any obligation or liability 
    by reason only of his being a director or for anything done or omitted to be 
    done in good faith in the discharge of his duties as a director or anything 
    in relation thereto; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    not be liable to retirement by rotation 
    and shall not be taken into account for computing the number of directors 
    liable to such retirement. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Indemnity of directors.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    director shall be indemnified by the Exim Bank against all losses and 
    expenses incurred by him, in, or in relation to, the discharge of his 
    duties, except such as are caused by his own wilful act or default. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A director 
    shall not be responsible for any other director or for any officer or other 
    employee of the Exim Bank or for any loss or expenses resulting to the Exim 
    Bank from the insufficiency or deficiency of the value of, or title to, any 
    property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the Exim Bank or the 
    insolvency or wrongful act of any debtor or any person under obligation to 
    the Exim Bank or anything done in good faith in the execution of the duties 
    of his office or in relation thereto. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>34</number> Protection of action taken in good 
      faith.—No suit or other legal 
      proceeding shall lie against the Exim Bank or any director or any officer 
      or other employee of the Exim Bank or any other person authorised by the 
      Exim Bank to discharge any functions under this Act for any loss or damage 
      caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or 
      intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any other law or provision 
      having the force of law. 
 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number> Act 18 of 1891 to apply in relation to Exim 
      Bank.—The Bankers’ Books 
      Evidence Act, 1891 shall apply in relation to the Exim Bank as if it were 
      a Bank as defined in section 2 of that Act. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>36</number> Section 34A and section 36AD only of Act 10 
      of 1949 to apply to Exim Bank.—Nothing contained in the Banking Regulation 
      Act, 1949, except section 34A and section 36AD thereof, shall apply to the 
      Exim Bank. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Act 43 
    of 1961 and Act 7 of 1964 not to apply to Exim Bank.—[Rep. 
    by the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1998 (21 of 1998), sec. 117 (w.e.f. 1-4-1999).] 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Liquidation of Exim Bank.—No 
    provision of any law relating to the winding up of companies or corporations 
    shall apply to the Exim Bank and the Exim Bank shall not be placed in 
    liquidation save by an order of the Central Government and in such manner as 
    it may direct. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Power to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board may, with the previous approval of the Central Government 


    1[by notification in 
    the Official Gazette], make regulations not inconsistent with this Act to 
    provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for 
    the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.—(1) 
    The Board may, with the previous approval of the Central Government 


    1[by notification in 
    the Official Gazette], make regulations not inconsistent with this Act to 
    provide for all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for 
    the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the times and places of the meetings of 
    the Board or of any committee constituted under this Act and the procedure 
    to be followed at such meetings including the quorum necessary for the 
    transaction of business; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the fees and allowances that may be 
    paid to the directors and the members of a committee; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the form and manner in which the 
    balance-sheets and the account of the Export Development Fund and the Exim 
    Bank shall be prepared: 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the duties and conduct, and the terms 
    and conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the Exim 
    Bank; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the establishment and maintenance of 
    provident fund or any other fund for the benefit of the officers and other 
    employees of the Exim Bank; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    any other matter which is to be, or may 
    be, prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    regulation made by the Board under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
    after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, 
    for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
    in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses 
    agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall 
    thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the 
    case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
    without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that 
    regulation. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>40</number> Amendment of certain 
      enactments.—[Rep. by the 
      Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 
      31-3-1988)]. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Power 
    to remove difficulty.—If any 
    difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, do anything, not inconsistent with such 
    provisions for the purpose of removing the difficulty: 
 
Provided that 
    no such order shall be made after the expiration of three years from the 
    date on which this Act receives the assent of the President. 
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Export-Import Bank of India Act, 1981
 

 
 

 
 


THE 
FIRST SCHEDULE
 


[See section 30(3)]
 


DECLARATION OF FIDELITY AND SECRECY
 

 
 


I,........................., do hereby declare 
    that I will faithfully, truly and to the best of my skill and ability 
    execute and perform the duties required of me as director, member of 
    ......................... committee, auditor, officer or other employee (as 
    the case may be) of the Export-Import Bank of India and which properly 
    relate to the office or position held by me in or in relation to the said 
    Exim Bank.
 


I further declare that I will not communicate 
    or allow to be communicated to any person not legally entitled thereto any 
    information relating to the affairs of the Export-Import Bank of India or to 
    the affairs of any person having any dealing with the said Exim Bank, nor 
    will I allow any such person to inspect or have access to any books or 
    documents belonging to or in the possession of the said Exim Bank and 
    relating to the business of the said Exim Bank or the business of any person 
    having any dealing with the said Exim Bank.
 


 
 


Signed before me.
 


(Signature)
 


 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    Export-Import Bank of India Act, 1981
 

 
 

 
 


THE SECOND SCHEDULE
 

 
 


Amendment of certain enactments.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), Sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 
    31-3-1988).]
 


 
 


 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>