<act><tid>1086169</tid>
<title>THE POST- GRADUATE INSTITUTE OF MEDICAL, EDUCATION AND 
RESEARCH, CHANDIGARH, ACT, <year>1966</year></title>

ACT NO. 51 OF <year>1966</year>
[ 17th December, <year>1966</year>.]

An Act to declare the institution known as the Post- Graduate 
Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, to be an 
institution of national importance and to provide for its 
incorporation and matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1806954</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1678348</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Post- Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, 
Act, <year>1966</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>784252</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1188032</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of Post- Graduate Institute of Medical Education and 
Research, Chandigarh, as an institution of national importance. 
Whereas the objects of the institution known as the Post- Graduate 
Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh in the Union 
territory of Chandigarh are such as to make the institution one of 
national importance, it is hereby declared that the institution known 
as the Post- Graduate Institute of Medical Education. and Research, 
Chandigarh is an institution of national importance.


</article>



<article><tid>297299</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1741830</tid>
<number>a</number>" Fund" means the Fund of the Institute referred to in 
section 16;

</section>

<section><tid>578149</tid>
<number>b</number>" Governing Body" means the Governing Body of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>128759</tid>
<number>c</number>" Institute" means the institution known as the Post- 
Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, 
incorporated under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>468810</tid>
<number>d</number>" member"' means a member of the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1667225</tid>
<number>e</number>" regulation" means a regulation made by the Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>673129</tid>
<number>f</number>" rule" means a rule made by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1724568</tid>
<number>4</number>Incorporation of Institute. The Post- Graduate Institute of 
Medical Education and ReSearch, Chandigarh, is hereby constituted a 
body corporate by the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 4. <year>1967</year>: Vide Notifn. No. S. O. 1115 (E), dt. 29. 3. <year>1967</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

name aforesaid and as such body corporate, it shall have perpetual 
succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions of 
this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract and 
shall, by that name, sue and be sued.



</article>



<article><tid>48679</tid>
<number> 5</number> Composition of Institute. The Institute shall consist of the 
following members, namely:-
<section><tid>1273786</tid>
<number>a</number>the Vice- Chancellor of the Punjab University, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>1498339</tid>
<number>b</number>the Director- General of Health Services, Government of 
India, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>586921</tid>
<number>c</number>the Director of the Institute, ex officio;

</section>

<section><tid>1527313</tid>
<number>d</number>three representatives of the Central Government to be 
nominated by that Government, one each from the Ministry of 
Finance, Ministry of Education and Ministry of Health and 
Family Planning;

</section>

<section><tid>841021</tid>
<number>e</number>seven persons of whom one shall be a non- medical 
scientist representing the Indian Science Congress 
Association, to be nominated by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>23538</tid>
<number>f</number>four representatives of the medical faculties of Indian 
Universities to be nominated by the Central Government in the 
manner prescribed by rules; and

</section>

<section><tid>807829</tid>
<number>g</number>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be 
elected from among themselves by the members of the House of 
the People (Lok Sabha) and one from among themselves by the 
members of the Council of States (Rajya Sabha).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>972209</tid>
<number> 6</number> Terms of office of, and vacancies among members.
<section><tid>231516</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise provided in this section, the term of office of a member 
shall be five years from the date of his nomination or election.

</section>

<section><tid>392485</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of a member elected under clause (g) of 
section 5 shall come to an end as soon as he ceases to be a member of 
the House from which he was elected.

</section>

<section><tid>1306285</tid>
<number>3</number>The term of office of an ex officio member shall continue so 
long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is such a member.

</section>

<section><tid>1242115</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of a member nominated or elected to fill 
a casual vacancy shall continue for the remainder of the term of the 
member in whose place he is nominated or elected.

</section>

<section><tid>1381261</tid>
<number>5</number>An out- going member other than a member elected under clause 
 (g) of section 5 shall, unless the Central Government other-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>125</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

wise directs, continue in office until another person is nominated as 
a member in his place.


</section>

<section><tid>4703</tid>
<number>6</number>An out- going member shall be eligible for re- nomination or 
re- election.

</section>

<section><tid>520953</tid>
<number>7</number>A member may resign his office by writing under his hand 
addressed to the Central- Government but he shall continue in office 
until his resignation is accepted by that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1897265</tid>
<number>8</number>The manner of filling vacancies among members shall be such 
as may be prescribed by rules.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>753131</tid>
<number> 7</number> President of Institute.
<section><tid>1412904</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a President of the  
Institute who shall be nominated by the Central Government from among 
the members other than the Director of the Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>855239</tid>
<number>2</number>The President shall exercise such powers and discharge such 
functions as are laid down in this Act or as may be prescribed by 
rules or regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>700908</tid>
<number>8</number>Allowances of President and members. The President and other 
members shall receive such allowances, if any, from the Institute as 
may be prescribed by rules.


</article>



<article><tid>876737</tid>
<number>9</number>Meetings of Institute. The Institute shall hold its first 
meeting at such time and place as may be appointed by the Central 
Government and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at the first meeting as may be laid down by 
that Government; and thereafter the Institute shall meet at such times 
and places and observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed by 
regulations.


</article>



<article><tid>199877</tid>
<number> 10</number> Governing Body and other committees of Institute.
<section><tid>1663234</tid>
<number>1</number>There  
shall be a Governing Body of the Institute which shall be constituted 
by the Institute in such manner as may be prescribed by regulations:
Provided that the number of persons who are not members of the 
Institute shall not exceed one- third of the total membership of the 
Governing Body.


</section>

<section><tid>1734020</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governing Body shall be the executive committee of the 
Institute and shall exercise such powers and discharge such functions 
as the Institute may, by regulations made in this behalf, confer or 
impose upon it.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>126</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1258861</tid>
<number>3</number>The President of the Institute shall be the Chairman of the 
Governing Body and as Chairman thereof shall exercise such powers and 
discharge such functions as may be prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>1571803</tid>
<number>4</number>The procedure to be followed in the exercise of its powers 
and discharge of its functions by the Governing Body, and the term of 
office of, and the manner of filling vacancies among, the members of 
the Governing Body shall be such as may be prescribed by regulations.

</section>

<section><tid>79124</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to such control and restrictions as may be 
prescribed by rules, the Institute may constitute as many standing 
committees and as many ad hoc committees as it thinks fit for 
exercising any power or discharging any function of the Institute or 
for inquiring into, or reporting or advising upon, any matter which 
the Institute may refer to them.

</section>

<section><tid>214025</tid>
<number>6</number>The Chairman and members of the Governing Body and the 
Chairman and members of a standing committee or an ad hoc committee 
shall receive such allowances, if any, as may be prescribed by 
regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1521751</tid>
<number> 11</number> Staff of Institute.
<section><tid>1652329</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be a chief executive  
officer of the Institute who shall be designated as the Director of 
the Institute and shall, subject to such rules as may be made by the 
Central Government in this behalf, be appointed by the Institute:
Provided that the first Director of the Institute shall be 
appointed by the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1289023</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director shall act as the Secretary to the Institute as 
well as the Governing Body.

</section>

<section><tid>812943</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director shall exercise such powers and discharge such 
functions as may be prescribed by regulations or as may be delegated 
to him by the Institute or the President of the Institute or by the 
Governing Body or the Chairman of the Governing Body.

</section>

<section><tid>1830290</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central Govern- 
ment in this behalf, the Institute may appoint such number of other 
officers and employees as may be necessary for the exercise of its 
powers and discharge of its functions and may determine the 
designations and grades of such other officers and employees.

</section>

<section><tid>1460721</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central Govern- 
ment in this behalf, the Director and other officers and employees of 
the Institute shall be entitled to such salary and allowances and 
shall be governed by such conditions of service in respect of leave, 
pension, provident fund and other matters as may be prescribed by 
regulations made in this behalf.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>127</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1127983</tid>
<number> 12</number> Objects of Institute. The objects of the Institute shall be-
<section><tid>755985</tid>
<number>a</number>to develop patterns of teaching in undergraduate and 
postgraduate medical education in all its branches so as to 
demonstrate a high standard of medical education;

</section>

<section><tid>1539320</tid>
<number>b</number>to bring together, as far as may be, in one place 
educational facilities of the highest order for the training 
of personnel in all important branches of health activity; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>868048</tid>
<number>c</number>to attain Self- sufficiency in post- graduate medical education 
to meet the country' s needs for specialists and medical 
teachers.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1413929</tid>
<number> 13</number> Functions of Institute. With a view to the promotion of the 
objects specified in section 12, the Institute may-
<section><tid>1264713</tid>
<number>a</number>provide for undergraduate and post- graduate teaching in 
the science of modem medicine and other allied sciences, 
including physical and biological sciences;

</section>

<section><tid>1644994</tid>
<number>b</number>provide facilities for research in the various branches 
of such sciences;

</section>

<section><tid>557694</tid>
<number>c</number>provide for the teaching of humanities;

</section>

<section><tid>666847</tid>
<number>d</number>conduct experiments in new methods of medical 
education, both undergraduate and post- graduate, in order to 
arrive at satisfactory standards of such education;

</section>

<section><tid>1740362</tid>
<number>e</number>prescribe courses and curricula for both undergraduate 
and post- graduate studies;

</section>

<section><tid>1307721</tid>
<number>f</number>not- withstanding anything contained in any other law for 
the time being in force, establish and maintain-

<subsection><tid>1872898</tid>
<number>i</number>one or more medical colleges with different 
departments, including a department of preventive and social 
medicine, sufficiently staffed and equipped to undertake not 
only undergraduate medical education but also post- graduate 
medical education in different subjects,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>577560</tid>
<number>ii</number>one or more well- equipped hospitals,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>243039</tid>
<number>iii</number>a dental college with such institutional 
facilities for the practice of dentistry and for the 
practical training of students as may be necessary,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1491678</tid>
<number>iv</number>a nursing college sufficiently staffed and equipped for 
the training of nurses,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>637381</tid>
<number>v</number>rural and urban health organisations which will form 
centers for the field training of the medical, dental

<pagefootnote><pagenum>128</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and nursing students of the Institute as well as for research 
into community health problems, and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>599965</tid>
<number>vi</number>other institutions for the training of different types 
of health workers, such as physiotherapists, occupational 
therapists, pharmacists, drug analysts and medical 
technicians of various kinds;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1808720</tid>
<number>g</number>train teachers for the different medical colleges in 
India;

</section>

<section><tid>595844</tid>
<number>h</number>hold examinations and grant such degrees, diplomas and 
other academic distinctions and titles in undergraduate and 
post- graduate medical education as may be laid down in the 
regulations;

</section>

<section><tid>275125</tid>
<number>i</number>institute, and appoint persons to, professorships, 
reader- ships, lecturerships and posts of any description in 
accordance with regulations;

</section>

<section><tid>496612</tid>
<number>j</number>receive grants from the Government and gifts, 
donations, benefactions, bequests and transfers of 
properties, both movable and immovable, from donors, 
benefactors, testators or transferors, as the case may be;

</section>

<section><tid>1893442</tid>
<number>k</number>deal with any property belonging to, or vested in, the 
Institute in any manner which is considered necessary for 
promoting the objects specified in section 12;

</section>

<section><tid>222488</tid>
<number>l</number>demand and receive such fees and other charges as may be 
prescribed by regulations;

</section>

<section><tid>1273369</tid>
<number>m</number>construct quarters for its staff and allot such housing 
to the staff in accordance with such regulations as may be 
made in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>207409</tid>
<number>n</number>borrow money, with the prior approval of the Central 
Government, on the security of the property of the Institute.

</section>

<section><tid>1218748</tid>
<number>o</number>do all such other acts and things as may be necessary 
to further the objects specified in section 12.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>153310</tid>
<number>14</number>Vesting of property. The properties of the Institute which 
had, by virtue of the Punjab Reorganisation Act, <year>1966</year> (31 of <year>1966</year>), 
vested in the Central Government shall, on the commencement of this 
Act, vest in the Institute.


</article>



<article><tid>75098</tid>
<number>15</number>Payment of Institute. The Central Government may, after due 
appropriation made by parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the 
Institute in each financial year such sums of money and in such manner 
as may be considered necessary by that Government for the exercise of 
its powers and discharge of its functions under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>416660</tid>
<number> 16</number> Fund of Institute.
<section><tid>1747012</tid>
<number>1</number>The Institute shall maintain a Fund to  
which shall be credited-

<subsection><tid>1653837</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys provided by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>540332</tid>
<number>b</number>all fees and other charges received by the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1270330</tid>
<number>c</number>all moneys received by the Institute by way of grants, 
gifts, donations; benefactions, bequests or transfers; and

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1806954</tid>
<number> 1</number> Relettered and Ins. by Act 30 of <year>1987</year>, s. 3

<pagefootnote><pagenum>129</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<section><tid>944878</tid>
<number>d</number>all moneys received by the Institute in any other manner 
or from any other source.

<subsection><tid>732346</tid>
<number>2</number>All moneys credited to the Fund shall be deposited in such 
banks or invested in such manner as the Institute may, with the 
approval of the Central Government, decide.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1894671</tid>
<number>3</number>The Fund shall be applied towards meeting the expenses of 
the Institute including expenses incurred in the exercise of its 
powers and discharge of its functions under section 13.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519434</tid>
<number>17</number>Budget of Institute. The Institute shall prepare in such form 
and at such time every year as may be prescribed by rules a budget in 
respect of the financial year next ensuing showing the estimated 
receipts and expenditure of the Institute and shall forward to the 
Central Government such number of copies thereof as may be prescribed 
by rules.


</article>



<article><tid>68172</tid>
<number> 18</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>668499</tid>
<number>1</number>The Institute shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts including the balance- sheet in such form as the Central 
Government may by rules prescribe, and in accordance with such general 
directions as may be issued by that Government, in consultation with 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1068302</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Institute shall be audited by the Comp- 
troller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred by 
him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Institute to 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>526049</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Institute shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts and, 
in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect the offices of the Institute as well as of the institutions 
established and maintained by it.

</section>

<section><tid>337280</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Institute as certified by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed 
by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>744569</tid>
<number>19</number>Annual report. The Institute shall prepare for every year a 
report of its activities during that year and submit the report to the 
Central

<pagefootnote><pagenum>130</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Government in such form and on or before such date as may be 
prescribed by rules and a copy of this report shall be laid before 
both Houses of Parliament within one month of its receipt.



</article>



<article><tid>790110</tid>
<number> 20</number> Pention and provident funds.
<section><tid>1494389</tid>
<number>1</number>The Institute shall  
constitute for the benefit of its officers, teachers and other 
employees in such manner and subject to such conditions as may be 
prescribed by regulations, such pension and provident funds as it may 
deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>60811</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such pension or provident fund has been 
constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provisions of 
the Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of 19225), shall apply to, such fund 
as if it were a Government Provident Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1966073</tid>
<number>21</number>Authentication of orders and instruments of Institute. All 
orders and decisions of the Institute shall be authenticated by the 
signature of the President or any other member authorised by the 
Institute in this behalf and all other instruments shall be 
authenticated by the signature of the Director or any other officer of 
the Institute authorised in like manner in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>8457</tid>
<number>22</number>Acts and proceedings not to be invalidated by vacancies, etc. 
No act done or proceeding taken by the Institute, Governing Body or 
any standing or ad hoc committee under this Act shall be questioned on 
the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or defect in the 
constitution of the Institute, Governing Body or such standing or ad 
hoc committee.


</article>



<article><tid>752876</tid>
<number>23</number>Grant of medical degrees, diplomas, etc., by Institute. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, the Institute shall have power to grant medical degrees, 
diplomas and other academic distinctions and titles under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>869481</tid>
<number>24</number>Recognition of medical qualifications granted by Institute. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Medical Council Act, 
<year>1956</year>, (1022 of <year>1967</year>) the medical degrees and diplomas granted by the 
Institute under this Act shall be recognised medical qualifications 
for the purposes of that Act and shall be deemed to be included in 
the First Schedule to that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>566845</tid>
<number>25</number>Control by Central Government. The Institute shall carry out 
such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the 
Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>131</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>9393</tid>
<number>26</number>Dispute between INstitute and Central Government. If in, or in 
connection with, the exercise of its powers and discharge of its 
functions by the Institute under this Act, any dispute arises between 
the Institute and the Central Government, the decision of the Central 
Government on such dispute shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1994108</tid>
<number>27</number>Returns and information. The Institute shall furnish to the 
Central Government such reports, returns and other information as that 
Government may require from time to time.


</article>



<article><tid>116626</tid>
<number>28</number>Transfer of service of existing employees. Subject to the 
provisions of this Act, every person who is employed in the Post- 
Graduate Institute of Medical Education and Research, Chandigarh, 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall, on and from 
such commencement, become an employee, of the Institute and shall hold 
his office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same 
remuneration and upon the same terms and conditions and with the same 
rights and privileges as to pension, leave, gratuity, provident fund 
and other matters as he would have held the same on the date of 
commencement of this Act if this Act had not been passed, and shall 
continue to do so unless and until his employment is terminated or 
until such tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly 
altered by regulations:
Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions 
of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage 
without the previous approval of the Central Government.



</article>



<article><tid>914476</tid>
<number>29</number>Continuance of facilities at Institute. The Institute shall 
continue to provide facilities to the Governments of the States of 
Haryana and Punjab and the Central Government in relation to the Union 
territories of Chandigarh and Himachal Pradesh and the people of the 
States and territories aforesaid and such facilities shall not, in 
any respect, be less favourable to such Governments and people than 
what were being provided to them before the 1st day of November, <year>1966</year> 
and shall be made available for such period and upon such terms and 
conditions (including those relating to any contributions to be made  
  for the provision of such facilities) as may be agreed upon between 
the Institute, Governments of the States of Haryana and Punjab and the 
Central Government before the 1st day of April. <year>1967</year>, or if no 
agreement is reached, by the said date, as may be fixed by order of 
the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>244523</tid>
<number>30</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, within a period of three years from the commencement of this Act, 
by order published in the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>132</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Official Gazette, make such provision or give such directions not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appears to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.



</article>



<article><tid>1226102</tid>
<number> 31</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>775926</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government, after  
consultation with the Institute, may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act:
Provided that consultation with the Institute shall not be neces- 
sary on the first occasion of the making of rules under this section, 
but the Central Government shall take into consideration any 
suggestions which the Institute may make in relation to the amendment 
of such rules after they are made.


</section>

<section><tid>371668</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the follow- 
ing matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>540943</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of nomination of members under clause (f) of 
section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1310475</tid>
<number>b</number>the control and restrictions in relation to the 
constitution of standing and ad hoc committees under sub- 
section (5) of section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>178984</tid>
<number>c</number>the conditions of service of, the procedure to be 
followed by, and the manner of filling vacancies among, 
members of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1542561</tid>
<number>d</number>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged 
by the President of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1406339</tid>
<number>e</number>the allowances, if any, to be paid to the President and 
other members of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1219339</tid>
<number>f</number>the number of officers and employees that may be 
appointed by the Institute and the manner of such 
appointment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>764148</tid>
<number>g</number>the form in which, and the time at which, the budgets 
and reports shall be prepared by the Institute and the number 
of copies thereof to be forwarded to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1169104</tid>
<number>h</number>the form and manner in which returns and information 
are to be furnished by the Institute to the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1354560</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which has to be or may be prescribed 
by rules.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1001178</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised

<pagefootnote><pagenum>133</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any 
modi- fication in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1122258</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power to make regulation.
<section><tid>1811076</tid>
<number>1</number>The Institute <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> with the  
previous approval of the Central Government, may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette,"] make regulations consistent with this Act and 
the rules made thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act, and 
without prejudice to the generality of this power, such regulations 
may provide for-

<subsection><tid>442849</tid>
<number>a</number>the summoning and holding of meetings, other than the 
first meeting, of the Institute, the time and place where 
such meetings are to be held, the conduct of business at such 
meetings and the number of members necessary to form a quorum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1008903</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner of constituting the Governing Body and 
standing and ad hoc committees, the term of office of, and 
the manner of filling vacancies among, the members of, the 
Governing Body and standing and ad hoc committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>945259</tid>
<number>c</number>the powers and functions to be exercised and discharged 
by the President of the Institute and the Chairman of the 
Governing Body;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>765650</tid>
<number>d</number>the allowances, if any, to be paid to the Chairman and 
the members of the Governing Body and of standing and ad hoc 
committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1686614</tid>
<number>e</number>the procedure to be followed by the Governing Body and 
standing and ad hoc committees in the conduct of their 
business. exercise of their powers and discharge of their 
functions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370314</tid>
<number>f</number>the tenure of office, salaries and allowances and other 
conditions of service of the Director and other officers and 
employees of the Institute including teachers appointed by 
the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5532</tid>
<number>g</number>the powers and duties of the Chairman of the Governing 
Body;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1215811</tid>
<number>h</number>the powers and duties of the Director and other 
officers and employees of the Institute;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>134</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>)





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>282939</tid>
<number>i</number>the management of the properties of the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>352451</tid>
<number>j</number>the degrees, diplomas and other academic distinctions 
and titles which may be granted by the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1003277</tid>
<number>k</number>the professorships, readerships, lecturerships and 
other posts which may be instituted and persons who may be 
appointed to such professorships, readerships, lecturerships 
and other posts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1246406</tid>
<number>l</number>the fees and other charges which may be demanded and 
received by the institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1217998</tid>
<number>m</number>the manner in which, and the conditions subject to 
which, pension and provident funds may be constituted for the 
benefit of officers, teachers and other employees of the 
Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1995405</tid>
<number>n</number>any other matter for which under this Act provisions 
may be made by regulations.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>923709</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
first regulations under this Act shall be made by the Central Govern- 
ment; and any regulations so made may be altered or rescinded by the 
Institute in exercise of its powers under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1461895</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, as 
soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that regulation."]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>135</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act. 4 of <year>1986</year>. s. 2. and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>