<act><title>


THE NATIONAL HIGHWAYS RULES, 19571</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—These 
rules may be called the National Highways Rules, 1957.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
      
<number>a</number> “Act” means the National Highways Act, 1956 (48 of 1956);
 
 

1[(b) “approved 
work” means any work relating to, or connected with, the development, 
maintenance, and repair of a national highway in respect of which the Central 
Government has accorded technical and administrative approval and financial 
sanction under rule 3;]
 </section><section>
      
<number>c</number> “completion report” means a report required to be furnished under rule 8;
 
 

2[(d) “executing 
agency” means—
 <subsection>
           
<number>i</number>  in the case of a Union territory, the administrator thereof to whom 
the functions of the Central Government in relation to the execution of works 
pertaining to national highways are delegated under Article 239 of the 
Constitution; and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>  in any 
other case, any officer or authority subordinate to the Central Government or 
the State Government to which such functions are delegated under section 5 of 
the Act;]
 
 

1[(e)  
"inventory" means a record as required to be prepared, maintained and furnished 
under sub-rule (2) of rule 7;
 </subsection></section><section>
      
<number>f</number>  “progress report” means a report required to be furnished under 
sub-rule (1) of rule 7;
 </section><section>
      
<number>g</number>  "work under delegated powers" means any work referred to in the 
sub-rule (2) of rule 3.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3</number> Estimate of 
work, its commencement, completion, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the estimate of the cost for the execution of any original work on a 
national highway exceeds 

2[Rs. 50 lakhs], a 
detailed estimate of the cost for the execution of the work shall be forwarded 
by the executing agency to the Central Government in such form as the Central 
Government may specify in that behalf and that Government may accord technical 
approval and financial sanction to such estimate subject to such conditions as 
it may think fit to impose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the estimate of 
the cost for the execution of any original work on a national highway does not 
exceed 

2[Rs. 50 lakhs], 
technical approval and financial sanction to such estimate for the execution of 
such work may be accorded by the executing agency concerned subject to the 
conditions specified in the Schedule annexed to these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The executing agency 
shall undertake detailed survey and investigations with regard to the work 
specified in sub-rules (1) and (2), as the Central Government may specify and a 
certificate to that effect shall accompany all proposals.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The estimate relating 
to the acquisition of land, shall be prepared by the executing agency and 
submitted for sanction to the Central Government well in advance of the 
estimates for the work component.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> For the work referred 
to in sub-rule (1), the proposals shall be sent to the Central Government in 
stages in the following order:—
 <subsection>
      
<number>a</number>  a technical appraisal note indicating the proposal in the form 
specified by the Central Government in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>b</number>  a project estimate on the basis of a technical parameters laid down by 
the Central Government in this regard.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> (a) The Central 
Government shall on, receipt of the documents referred to in clauses (a) to (b) 
of sub-rule (5), examine the same and if it is of the opinion that they are in 
accordance with approved standard, shall accord technical approval and financial 
sanction for such work subject to such conditions as it may thinks fit to 
impose.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The technical approval 
and financial sanction accorded under clause (a) shall lapse after 

3[one year] from 
date of its issue in case the work is not commenced within that period:
 
Provided that where the 
Central Government is of the opinion that the technical appraisal note or 
project estimate is not in accordance with the approved standard, it may return 
the same to the executing agency for bringing it in accordance with the approved 
standard.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> For the work referred 
to in sub-rule (2), a detailed estimate shall be prepared by the executing 
agency and only the general abstract of cost alongwith detailed information as 
the Central Government may specify, shall be forwarded to that Government for 
accord of administrative approval subject to the conditions specified in the 
Schedule annexed to the rules.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Save in exceptional 
cases, where acquisition of land is necessary for the execution of any work 
referred to in sub-rules (1) and (2), sanction to such work shall not be 
accorded by the Central Government or, as the case may be, by the executing 
agency, unless such acquisition has been given effect to, or on acquisition of 
such section of land which in the opinion of the Central Government or the 
executing agency as the case may be would facilitate traffic even if work is 
completed on such section of land.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> No original work on 
any national highway shall be commenced by the executing agency until technical 
approval and financial sanction thereon has been accorded by the appropriate 
sanctioning authority:
 
Provided that in case of 
work arising out of emergency such as flood, earthquake or any other force 
majeure, the commencement of which cannot be postponed, may be commenced 
immediately but the executing agency shall immediately report to the Central 
Government the nature of the emergency and the approximate expenditure involved.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The project estimate 
referred to in clause (b) of sub-rule (5) shall contain a time schedule in 
calender months for execution of the project in the following manner and all the 
activities shall be related there to:
 <subsection>
      
<number>a</number>  Pre-construction stage
 
           
Issue of notice inviting tender:
 
           
receipt of tender; and
 
           
finalisation of tender from the date of sanction of estimate.
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>b</number>  Construction stage.
 
Period of completion of 
various activities forming part of the work from the date of award of work.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>11</number> (a) The tenders for 
the execution of work shall be invited by the Officers empowered by the Central 
Government or the executing agency as the case may be, to accept them.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The work shall be 
tendered in the form specified by the Central Government in this regard.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Save as exceptional 
cases with the prior approval of the Central Government, the executing agency 
shall ensure that the work of all components in the project estimate is awarded 
to a single contractor and that the components in the project estimate are not 
split horizontally.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>12</number> Classification of 
contractors.
 <subsection>
      
<number>a</number>  The executing agency shall ensure that contractors are classified for 
jobs of various sizes, taking into consideration, employment of qualified 
engineers, kind of machinery and expertise available with them and the total 
workload which they can handle at a given time;
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>b</number>  The contractors for works of intricate nature or costing more than a 
specified amount a specified from time to time by the Central Government shall 
be considered for prequalification.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>13</number> Quality control.
 
The executing agency shall 
follow the directions issued by the Central Government from time to time for 
exercising quality control of national highway works as also the modes of 
utilising the quality control provision made in the estimates of work sanctioned 
by the Central Government of the executing agency as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> (a) The machinery 
wherever supplied by the Central Government shall be used in the execution of 
the work for which it was supplied.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The executing agency 
shall be responsible for maintenance records, history sheets, plant data sheets 
and log books for the machinery supplied by the Central Government as well as 
hire charge account, expenditure account on maintenance and repairs, as 
specified from time to time by the Central Government.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The executing agency 
shall maintain accounts of the machinery provided by the Central Government as 
per PWD Code.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> The machinery supplied 
by the Central Government and the records referred to in clauses (b) and (c) 
shall be made available for inspection by the officers of the State Government 
and the Central Government at all reasonable times.]
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Abstract of particulars of 
detailed estimate for maintenance of national highways.—1[
<section><number>1</number> An abstract of the 
particulars of the detailed estimate for the maintenance of each National 
Highway or a section thereof requiring maintenance during a financial year shall 
be forwarded by the executing agency to the Central Government in such form as 
the Central Government may require, not later than the 1st day of May of such 
other day as may be specified by the Central Government in that financial 
year.
 </section><section><number>1</number> A the executing agency shall 
in the said abstract of particulars include an annual renewal programme 
supported by bar charts in the form specified for each national highway or a 
section thereof approved by the regional officer of the Central Government 
dealing with national highways:
 Provided that the Central 
Government may in any particular case or class of cases, require the executing 
agency to forward a detailed estimate the maintenance of any national highway in 
such form as that Government may require.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government may 
accord approval to the abstract or the detailed estimate or estimates submitted 
to it under this rule subject to any conditions it may think fit to 
impose.
  



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>5</number> Revised 
detailed estimate.—Where 
the expenditure upon any original work on a national highway for the detailed 
estimate of the cost for which the Central Government has accorded technical 
approval and financial sanction, under sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 3, is likely at any 
time to exceed, or exceeds, the amount of such estimate by more than fifteen per 
cent. thereof or by a sum of one crore rupees, whichever is less, the executive 
agency shall forward a revised detailed estimate of the cost for such work to 
the Central Government in such form as that Government may specify in this 
behalf, and the Central Government may accord technical approval and financial 
sanction to the revised detailed estimate subject to such conditions as it may 
think fit to impose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the expenditure 
upon any original work on a national highway to the detailed estimate of the 
cost for which the 

2[executing agency] 
concerned has accorded technical approval and financial sanction, under sub-rule 
(2) of rule 3, is likely at any time to exceed, or exceeds, the amount of such 
estimate and the revised cost of the original work, including the excess, is 
likely at any time to exceed, or exceeds by more than fifteen per cent. of the 
original estimate or 

3[rupees fifty 
lakhs], the 

2[executing agency] 
shall forward a revised detailed estimate of the cost for such work to the 
Central Government in such form as that Government may specify and the Central 
Government may accord technical approval and financial sanction to such revised 
estimate subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (2), where the expenditure upon any original work 
on a national highway to the detailed estimate of the cost for which the 

2[executing agency] 
concerned has accorded technical approval and financial sanction, under sub-rule 
(2) of rule 3, is likely at any time to exceed, or exceeds, the amount of such 
estimate and the revised estimate of the cost for the original work, including 
the excess is likely at any time to exceed, or exceeds, by more than fifteen per 
cent. of the original estimate but by not more than fifteen per cent. of the 
rough estimate of the costs for the original work which the 

4[executing agency] 
had submitted to the Central Government and obtained the approval of that 
Government, technical approval and financial sanction to such revised estimate 
may be accorded by the 

4[executing agency] 
concerned subject to the conditions specified in the Schedule annexed to these 
rules:
 
Provided that the amount 
of the revised estimate is not likely to exceed, or does not exceed 

5[rupees fifty 
lakhs]:
 
Provided further that the 
excess of expenditure is caused only by routine factors such as increase in the 
cost of labour or material and not due to revision in the scope or enlargement 
of the work or specifications already approved.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the expenditure 
upon any original work on a national highway is likely at any time to exceed, or 
exceeds, the amount of the estimate of the cost for such work no funds shall be 
allotted to the work by the Central Government in the cases provided for in 
sub-rule (1), (2) or (3), unless the provisions of those sub-rules are complied 
with except in cases where the Central Government directs otherwise.
 
Explanation.—For 
the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that in cases where the excess of 
expenditure is less than the percentage or amount specified in sub-rule (1) or 
sub-rule (2), it is not necessary to obtain technical approval and financial 
sanction of the Central Government for the revised estimate in accordance with 
those sub-rules only if the excess of expenditure is caused by routine factors 
such as increase in the cost of labour or material and not due to revision in 
the scope or enlargement of the work or specifications already approved.]
 
 








</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Application for 
allotment of funds.—An 
application for the allotment of funds for meeting expenditure on any original 
work on a national highway or on the maintenance of a national highway during 
any financial year shall be made by the 

1[executing agency] 
to the Central Government in such form as that Government may require and the 
Central Government shall communicate its decision to the 

1[executing agency] 
on such application as soon as possible after such application is received.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>7</number> Progress 
reports and inventory.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The executing agency shall establish monitoring cells for the purpose of 
monitoring the progress of sanctioned work on a national highway, in the office 
of the Chief Engineer concerned with the works of such highway and the executing 
agency shall furnish to the Central Government progress reports in respect of 
such works in such form and at such intervals as may be specified by the Central 
Government from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The executing 
agency shall prepare and maintain inventory of national highways and measurement 
of roughness of the roads in the form specified by the Central Government, which 
shall be updated periodically.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The inventory prepared 
and updated under clause (a) shall be furnished to the Central Government at 
such intervals as may be specified by it.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>8</number> Deviation in 
work, sub-standard work and completion report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The executing agency shall not without the prior sanction of the appropriate 
sanctioning authority, deviate from the scope of the specifications and design 
of the project, failing which the expenditure on the component of the deviated 
work and the other components of the works affected thereby shall be debited to 
the executing agency.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The responsibility for 
the sub-standard work, if any, shall rest with the executing agency and all 
defects arising out of such sub-standard work shall be rectified by the 
executing agency at its own cost, within the period to be specified by the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (a) The executing 
agency shall furnish to the Central Government a completion report along with 
the drawings of the completed work in such forms as the Central Government may 
specify within six months of the actual date of completion, or from opening to 
traffic whichever is earlier.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The report shall also 
be accompanied by a certificate to the effect that the project has been 
completed according to the prescribed scope, specifications and approved 
designs.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> As early as possible 
after furnishing of the report and certificate specified in clauses (a) and (b) 
the executing agency shall furnish a financial report giving, inter alia, 
the expenditure figures.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>9</number> Inspection of 
works.—Director-General 
(Road Development) to the Government of India or any officer authorised by him 
in this behalf may inspect at any time any approved work in progress or 
completed work and a report of every such inspection shall be submitted to the 
Central Government.]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>10</number> Utilisation 
of space beneath the road, overbridges or flyovers.—The 
Central Government, where it deems fit, may accord permission to the State 
Government or the Government of a Union Territory, as the case may be, for 
utilisation of space beneath the road, overbridges or flyovers on national 
highways for which an yearly licence fee which shall be either—
 <section>
       
<number>i</number>  a percentage of capital cost; consisting of the cost of land and the 
cost, if any, incurred by the Central Government for covering or enclosing the 
space beneath the approach spans of road, overbridges or flyovers and for 
providing sanitary, water supply and electric installations, equal to such rate 
of interest as may from time to time be fixed by the President under FR 45A plus 
an addition for house or property tax, if any, payable by Government in respect 
of the covered space and for maintenance and repairs of the covered structure, 
or
 </section><section>
      
<number>ii</number>  six per cent. per annum of such capital cost, whichever is less, 
shall be fixed and levied on the terms and conditions as may be laid down by the 
Central Government in this respect. The rate of licence fee to be levied as 
above, shall be subject to revision after every five years to take into account 
any change in the market value of the land.]
 
 




</section></article><form>
 




THE NATIONAL HIGHWAYS RULES, 1957
 


 
 



1[THE SCHEDULE
 



2[See rule 
3(2) and 3(7)]
 


Conditions for the issue of 
technical approval and financial sanction to plan and estimate for execution of 
any original work on a national highway costing an amount not exceeding 

3[Rs. 50 lakhs] by 
the 

4[executing agency] 
concerned.
 



5[The excuting 
agency shall prepare detailed estimate and working drawings but forward to the 
Central Government for approval only the general abstract cost in respect of the 
works contained in the approved annual programme of works costing upto Rs. 50 
lakhs for a particular year. However, for projects involving surveys and 
investigations and land acquisitions the detailed estimate and drawings in the 
form specified by the Central Government shall be forwarded for approval. The 
executing agency shall accord technical approval and financial sanction to the 
detailed estimate already prepared in advance within three months form the date 
of according administrative approval by the Central Government and shall 
commence execution of the work within one year from the date of according 
administrative approval failing which, the administrative approval accorded by 
the Central Government shall stand cancelled automatically and the executing 
agency shall approach the Central Government for fresh administrative approval 
for the said work.]
 


(2) (a) Permissible job 
sizes shall be regulated according to description given in the annual Plan works 
programme mentioned under condition (1) and the work shall not be split up.
 


(b) In the case of items


6[In the Annual 
Plan] saving lump sum provision (such as improvement of geometrics, stabilising, 
slipping reaches, raising roads in submersible sections, each specific location 
supported by requisite details shall be treated individually.
 


(3) Technical approval and 
financial sanction shall be accorded only in respect of such items of work for 
which specific provision has been made in the budget during the year for the 
individual work on the basis of the approval given under condition (1).
 


(4) While sanctioning 
detailed estimates, the executive agency shall ensure that the rough cost 
estimate for the work appearing in the budget estimates accepted by the Central 
Government for presentation to Parliament is not exceeded by more than 15 per 
cent. or the total cost of detailed estimate to be sanctioned by that agency, in 
no case exceeds 

7[rupees fifty lakhs], 
whichever is less.
 


(5) Abstract of cost of 
sanctioned detailed estimates in all cases shall be submitted by the 

4[excuting agency] 
in respect of the works sanctioned by that agency and in the case of bridge 
estimates, in addition a general outline drawing shall also be submitted. 
Abstract of cost of sanctioned detailed estimates shall give justification for 
excess, if any, referred to under condition (4).
 


(6) Progress reports in 
respect of all works sanctioned by the 

4[executing agency] 
shall be submitted to the Central Government, in such form and at such 
periodicity as may be required by the Central Government from time to time.
 


(7) Technical approval and 
financial sanction to plans and estimates for execution of any original work on 
a national highway shall be accorded by the 

8[executing agency] 
only after the approval of an officer of the rank of Chief Engineer or 
Additional Chief Engineer or Principal Engineer in charge of national highway 
works has been obtained.
 



9[***]
 



10[(8)] In the 
matters relating to technical approval and financial sanction, the following 
procedure shall be followed, namely:—
 


         
(i)  In case of the works where standards and designs adopted in the 
estimates are in accordance with the Indian Roads Congress Code and 
specifications and any other relevant instructions, guidelines, standard bridge 
designs, etc., issued by the Central Government from time to time, copies of the 
sanctions accorded by the 

8[executing agency] 
shall invariably be endorsed to the Regional Officers concerned of the Ministry 
in the Central Government dealing with national highways along with complete 
copy of the estimate so that even after sanction, they could examine the matter 
and bring to the notice of 

8[executing agency] 
deviations from such Code, specifications, instructions, guidelines, standard 
bridge designs, if any.
 


 

11[(ii)  Where 
for any work, the deviations, from approved standards, specifications, 
instructions and guidelines issued by the Central Government have to be made due 
to local conditions, no work shall be sanctioned by any executing agency unless 
a complete copy of the estimate is furnished to the Regional Officer concerned 
of the Ministry in the Central Government dealing with National Highways, who 
shall forward the same to the Central Government with his comments thereon for 
approval. Technical approval and financial sanction may be issued by the 
executing agency only after such approval.]
 



12[***]
 



13[(iii)]  
After the budget estimates have been accepted by the Central Government, the 
funds likely to be available for the work shall be intimated to the 

8[executing agency] 
concerned. Work-wise allotment of funds shall be made by the Central Government 
and the same shall also be communicated to the 

8[executing agency] 
concerned for further necessary action as soon as the budget is passed by the 
Parliament. Sanction for entering into financial commitments may be accorded by 
the 

8[executing agency] 
only after the budget is passed by the Parliament and the same is intimated to 
the 

8[executing agency]. 
All other actions including technical sanction to the project, calling and 
receipt of tenders, negotiation for their settlement, etc., may, however, be 
taken by the 

8[executing agency] 
as soon as the acceptance of the budget estimate by the Central Government has 
been intimated to it.
 


 
 

—————
 


   1.  Ins. 
by S.O. 680(E), dated 15th October, 1976.
 


   2.  Subs. 
by S.O. 496(E), dated 20th August, 1986, for "[see rule 3(2)]" (w.e.f. 
20-8-1986).
 


   3.  Subs. 
by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993, for "Rs. 25 Lakhs" (w.e.f. 5-11-1993).
 


   4.  Subs. 
by S.O. 496(E), dated 20th August, 1986, for "executive agency" (w.e.f. 
20-8-1986).
 


   5.  Subs. 
by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993 (w.e.f. 5-11-1993).
 


   6.  Ins. 
by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993 (w.e.f. 5-11-1993).
 


   7.  Subs. 
by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993, for "rupees twenty-five lakhs" (w.e.f. 
5-11-1993).
 


   8.  Subs. 
by S.O. 496(E), dated 20th August, 1986, for "executive agency" (w.e.f. 
20-8-1986).
 


   9.  
Conditions (8) and (9) omitted by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993 (w.e.f. 
5-11-1993).
 


  10.  Renumbered 
by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993 (w.e.f. 5-11-1993).
 


  11.  Subs. by 
S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993 (w.e.f. 5-11-1993).
 


  12.  Clause 
(iii) omitted by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993 (w.e.f. 5-11-1993).
 


  13.  Renumbered 
by S.O. 855(E), dated 5th November, 1993 (w.e.f. 5-11-1993).
 

 
 


 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>