<act><tid>1104640</tid>
<title>THE CABLE TELEVISION NETWORKS (REGULATION) AMENDMENT ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 2 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 31st December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Cable Television Networks (Regulation) 
Act, <year>1995</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>813471</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Cable Television Networks 
 (Regulation) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1218694</tid>
<number> 2</number> Insertion of new section 4A.- In the Cable Television Networks 
 (Regulation) Act, <year>1995</year> (7 of <year>1995</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), after section 4, the following section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
' 4A. Transmission of programmes through addressable system, etc.- (1) 
Where the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary in the 
public interest so to do, it may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make it obligatory for every cable opera or to transmit or 
retransmit programme of any pay channel through an addressable system 
with effect from such date as may be specified in the notification and 
different dates may be specified for different States, cities, towns 
or areas, as the case may be.

<section><tid>493949</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary in the 
public interest so to do, it may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify one or more free- to- air channels to be included in 
the package of channels forming basic service tie and any or more such 
channels may be specified, in the notification, genre- wise for 
providing a programme mix of entertainment, information, education and 
such other programmes.

</section>

<section><tid>738642</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may specify in the notification referred to 
in sub- section (2), the number of free- to- air channels to be included 
in the package of channels forming basic service tier for the purposes 
different States, cities, towns or areas, as the case may be. of that 
sub- section and different numbers may be specified for

</section>

<section><tid>227292</tid>
<number>4</number>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is necessary in the 
public interest so to do, it may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify the maximum amount which a cable operator may demand 
from the subscriber for receiving the programm s transmitted in the 
basic service tier provided by such cable operator.

</section>

<section><tid>566888</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (4), the Central 
Government may, for the purposes of that sub- section, specify in the 
notification referred to in that sub- section different maximum amounts 
for different States, cities, towns or area, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1231915</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, programmes of 
basic service tier shall be receivable by any subscriber on the 
receiver set of a type existing immediately before the commencement of 
the Cable Television Networks (Regulation) Amendm nt Act, <year>2002</year> without 
any addressable system attached with such receiver set in any manner.

</section>

<section><tid>160688</tid>
<number>7</number>Every cable operator shall publicise, in the prescribed manner, to 
the subs- cribers the subscription rates and the periodic intervals at 
which such subscriptions are payable for receiving each pay channel 
provided by such cable operator.

</section>

<section><tid>1192996</tid>
<number>8</number>The cable operator shall not require any subscriber to have a 
receiver set of a particular type to receive signals of cable 
television network: Provided that the subscriber shall use an 
addressable system to be attached to his receiver set for receiving 
programmes transmitted on pay channel.

</section>

<section><tid>1451645</tid>
<number>9</number>Every cable operator shall submit a report to the Central 
Government in the prescribed form and manner containing the 
information regarding-

<subsection><tid>96410</tid>
<number>i</number>the number of total subscribers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>830802</tid>
<number>ii</number>subscription rates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1654561</tid>
<number>iii</number>number of subscribers receiving programmes transmitted in basic 
service tier or particular programme or set of programmes transmitted 
on pay channel, in respect of cable services provided by such cable 
operator through a cable television network, and such report shall be 
submitted periodically at such intervals as may be prescribed and 
shall also contain the rate of amount, if any, payable by the cab e 
operator to any broadcaster.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsubsection><tid>543822</tid>
<number>a</number>" addressable system" means an electronic device or more than one 
electronic devices put in an integrated system through which signals 
of cable television network can be sent in encrypted or unencrypted 
form, which can be decoded by the device or devi es at the premises of 
the subscriber within the limits of authorisation made, on the choice 
and request of such subscriber, by the cable operator to the 
subscriber;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>738567</tid>
<number>b</number>" basic service tier" means a package of free- to- air channels 
provided by a cable operator, for a single price to the subscribers of 
the area in which his cable television network is providing service 
and such channels are receivable for viewing by th subscribers on the 
receiver set of a type existing immediately before the commencement of 
the Cable Television Networks (Regulation) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year> without 
any addressable system attached to such receiver set in any manner;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1686104</tid>
<number>c</number>" channel" means a set of frequencies used for transmission of a 
programme;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1452817</tid>
<number>d</number>" encrypted", in respect of a signal of cable television network, 
means the changing of such signal in a systematic way so that the 
signal would be unintelligible without a suitable receiving equipment 
and the expression" unencrypted" shall be constru d accordingly;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>215564</tid>
<number>e</number>" free- to- air channel", in respect of a cable television network, 
means a channel, the reception of which would not require the use of 
any addressable system, to be attached with the receiver set of a 
subscriber;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>613939</tid>
<number>f</number>" pay channel", in respect of a cable television network, means a 
channel, the reception of which by the subscriber would require the 
use of an addressable system, to be attached to his receiver set.'.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1088710</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 9.- In section 9 of the principal Act, the 
following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the equipment required for the purposes of section 4A 
shall be installed by cable operator in his cable television network 
within six months from the date, specified in the notification issued 
under sub- section (1) of that section, in acco dance with the 
provisions of the said Act for said purposes.".



</article>



<article><tid>950845</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 11.- In section 11 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the word and figure" sections 3,", the word, 
figures and letter" section 3, 4A," shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1784378</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 16.- Section 16 of the principal Act shall be 
numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>1397128</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof, and after sub- section (1) as so  
numbered, the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), the contravention of section 4A shall be 
a cognizable offence under this section.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>759129</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 22.- In section 22 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), after clause (a), the following clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (aa) the manner of publicising the subscription rates and the 
periodical intervals at which such subscriptions are payable under 
sub- section (7) of section 4A;

<section><tid>1430427</tid>
<number>aaa</number>the form and manner of submitting report under sub- section (9) 
of section 4A and the interval at which such report shall be submitted 
periodically under that sub- section;".
SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>