<act><tid>1108265</tid>
<title>THE LAND ACQUISITION (MINES) ACT, <year>1885</year></title>

ACT NO. 18 OF <footcitenum>1885</footcitenum>
[ 16th October, <year>1885</year>.]

An Act to provide for cases in which Mines or Minerals are situate 
under land which it is desired to acquire under the Land Acquisition 
Act, <year>1870</year>. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>





<article><tid>1794151</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and local extent.
<section><tid>1620058</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Land Acquisition (Mines) Act, <year>1885</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>984896</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States.

</section>

<section><tid>153966</tid>
<number>3</number>It applies in the first instance to the territories which, 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in the 
States of Madras, Andhra, West Bengal, Bihar, Assam and Orissa; but 
any State Government may, from time to time, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, bring this Act into force in the whole or any 
specified part of the territories to which this Act extends, under its 
administration.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1710212</tid>
<number>2</number>Saving for mineral rights of the Government. Except as 
expressly provided by this Act, nothing in this Act shall affect the 
right of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Government]] to any mines or minerals.


</article>



<article><tid>966051</tid>
<number> 3</number> Declaration that mines are not needed.
<section><tid>1445637</tid>
<number>1</number>When the  
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> appropriate Government] makes a declaration under section 6 of the 
Land Acquisition Act, <year>1870</year> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> (10 of <year>1870</year>.), that land is needed for a 
public purpose or for a Company, it may, if it thinks fit, insert in 
the declaration a statement that the mines of coal, iron- stone, slate 
or other minerals lying under the land or any particular portion of 
the land, except only such parts of the mines or minerals as it may be 
necessary to dig or carry away or use in the construction of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. II of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
1 See now the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>). 
2 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for the 
former sub- sections (2) and (3). 
3 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Government". 
4 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Crown". 
5 Subs., ibid., for" the Provincial Government". 
6 See now s. 6 of the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


work for the purpose of which the land is being acquired, are not 
needed.


</section>

<section><tid>1679515</tid>
<number>2</number>When a statement as aforesaid has not been inserted in the 
declaration made in respect of any land under section 6 of the Land 
Acquisition Act, <year>1870</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> (10 of <year>1870</year>), and the Collector is of 
opinion that the provisions of this Act ought to be applied to the 
land, he may abstain from tendering compensation under section 11 of 
the said Land Acquisition Act in respect of the mines, and may--

<subsection><tid>1265234</tid>
<number>a</number>when he makes an award under section 14 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> of that Act, 
insert such a statement in his award;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>414450</tid>
<number>b</number>when he makes a reference to the Court under section 15 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of that Act, insert such a statement in his reference; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>647263</tid>
<number>c</number>when he takes possession of the land under section 17 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> 
of that Act, publish such a statement in such manner as 
the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, from time to time, 
proscribe.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1432792</tid>
<number>3</number>If any such statement is inserted in the declaration, award 
or reference, or published as aforesaid, the mines of coal, iron- 
stone, slate or other minerals under the land or portion of the land 
specified in the statement, except as aforesaid, shall not vest in 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Government]] when the land so vests under the said Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>235977</tid>
<number>4</number>Notice to be given before working mines lying under land. If 
the person for the time being immediately entitled to work or get any 
mines or minerals lying under any land so acquired is desirous of 
working or getting the same, he shall give the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> appropriate 
Government] notice in writing of his intention so to do sixty days 
before the commencement of working.


</article>



<article><tid>334029</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power to prevent or restrict working.
<section><tid>1860959</tid>
<number>1</number>At any time or times  
after the receipt of a notice under the last foregoing section and 
whether before or after the expiration of the said period of sixty 
days, the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may cause the mines or minerals 
to be inspected by a person appointed by it for the purpose; and

</section>

<section><tid>1582069</tid>
<number>2</number>If it appears to the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> appropriate Government] that the 
working or getting of the mines or minerals, or any part thereof, is 
likely to cause damage to the surface of the land or any works 
thereon, the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now s. 6 of the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>). 
2 See now s. 11, ibid. 
3 See now s. 19, ibid. 
4 See now s. 17, ibid. 
5 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Provincial Government". 
6 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Government". 
7 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Crown".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may publish <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a declaration of its 
willingness, either--


<subsection><tid>1812595</tid>
<number>a</number>to pay compensation for the mines or minerals still 
unworked or ungotten, or that part thereof, to all 
persons having an interest in the same; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>913243</tid>
<number>b</number>to pay compensation to all such persons in consideration 
of those mines or minerals, or that part thereof, being 
worked or gotten in such manner and subject to such 
restrictions as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may in 
its declaration specify.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1955936</tid>
<number>3</number>If the declaration mentioned in case (a) is made, then those 
mines or minerals, or that part thereof, shall not thereafter be 
worked or gotten by any person.

</section>

<section><tid>796624</tid>
<number>4</number>If the declaration mentioned in case (b) is made, then those 
mines or minerals, or that part thereof, shall not thereafter be 
worked or gotten by any person save in the manner and subject to the 
restrictions specified by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government.]

</section>

<section><tid>1427789</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every declaration made under this section shall be 
published in such manner as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may 
direct.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>138664</tid>
<number>6</number>Mode of determining persons interested and amount of 
compensation. When the working or getting of any mines or minerals has 
been prevented or restricted under section 5, the persons interested 
in those mines or minerals and the amounts of compensation payable to 
them respectively shall, subject to all necessary modifications, be 
ascertained in the manner provided by the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1870</year> 
 (10 of <year>1870</year>.) <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, for ascertaining the persons interested in the land 
to be acquired under that Act, and the amounts of compensation payable 
to them, respectively.


</article>



<article><tid>106664</tid>
<number> 7</number> If appropriate Government does not offer to pay compensation, 
mines may be worked in a proper manner.
<section><tid>136248</tid>
<number>1</number>If before the expiration  
of the said sixty days the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] does not publish 
a declaration as provided in section 5, the owner, lessee or occupier 
of the mines may, unless and until such a declaration is subsequently 
made, work the mines or any part thereof in a manner proper and 
necessary for the beneficial working thereof, and according to the 
usual manner of working such mines in the local area where the same 
are situate.

</section>

<section><tid>348106</tid>
<number>2</number>If any damage or obstruction is caused to the surface of the 
land or any works thereon by improper working of the mines, the owner, 
lessee or occupier of the mines shall at once, at his own expense, 
repair the damage or remove the obstruction, as the case may require.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. for" Provincial Government". 
2 The words" in such manner as the G. G. in C. may, from time to 
time, direct" rep. by the Devolution Act, <year>1920</year> (38 of <year>1920</year>), s. 2 and 
Sch. I. 
3 Ins. by s. 2 and Sch. I of the Devolution Act, <year>1920</year> (38 of <year>1920</year>). 
4 See now the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>116560</tid>
<number>3</number>If the repair or removal is not at once effected, or, if the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] so thinks fit, without writing for the same 
to be effected by the owner, lessee or occupier, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate 
Government] may execute the same and recover from the owner, lessee or 
occupier the expense occasioned thereby.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>540685</tid>
<number>8</number>Mining communications. If the working of any mines is 
prevented or restricted under section 5, the respective owners, 
lessees and occupiers of the mines, if their mines extend so as to lie 
on both sides of the mines the working of which is prevented or 
restricted, may cut and make such and so many airways, headways, 
gateways or water- levels through the mines, measures or strata, the 
working whereof is prevented or restricted, as may be requisite to 
enable them to ventilate, drain and work their said mines; but no such 
airway, headway, gateway or water- level shall be of greater dimensions 
or section than may be prescribed by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] in 
this behalf, and, where no dimensions are so prescribed, not greater 
than eight feet wide and eight feet high, nor shall the same be cut or 
made upon any part of the surface or works, or so as to injure the 
same, or to interfere with the use thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>942047</tid>
<number>9</number>Appropriate Government to pay compensation for injury done to 
mines; The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] shall, from time to time, pay to 
the owner, lessee or occupier of any such mines extending so as to lie 
on both sides of the mines, the working of which is prevented or 
restricted, all such additional expenses and losses as may be incurred 
by him by reason of the severance of the lands lying over those mines 
or of the continuous working of those mines being interrupted as 
aforesaid, or by reason of the same being worked in such manner and 
under such restrictions as not to prejudice or injure the surface or 
works, and for any minerals not acquired by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate 
Government] which cannot be obtained by reason of the action taken 
under the foregoing sections; and if any dispute or question arises 
between the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] and the owner, lessee or 
occupier as aforesaid, touching the amount of those losses or 
expenses, the same shall be settled as nearly as may be in the manner 
provided for the settlement of questions touching the amount of 
compensation payable under the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1870</year> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (10 of  
  <year>1870</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1356225</tid>
<number>10</number>and also for injury arising from any airway or other work. If 
any loss or damage is sustained by the owner or occupier of the lands 
lying over any such mines, the working whereof has been so prevented 
or restricted as aforesaid (and not being the owner, lessee or  
  occupier of those mines), by reason of the making of any such airway 
or other works as aforesaid, which or any like work it
<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Provincial Government". 
2 See now the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


would not have been necessary to make but for the working of the mines 
having been so prevented or restricted as aforesaid, the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] shall pay full compensation to that owner 
or occupier of the surface lands for the loss or damage so sustained 
by him.



</article>



<article><tid>1938949</tid>
<number>11</number>Power to officer of appropriate Government to enter and 
inspect the working of mines. For better ascertaining whether any 
mines lying under land acquired in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act are being worked, or have been worked, or are likely to be 
worked so as to damage the land or the works thereon, an officer 
appointed for this purpose by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may, 
after giving twenty- four hours' notice II writing, enter into and 
return from any such mines or the works connected therewith; and for 
that purpose the officer so appointed may make use of any apparatus or 
machinery belonging to the owner, lessee or occupier of the mines, and 
use all necessary means for discovering the distance from any part of 
the land acquired to the parts of the mines which have been, are 
being, or are about to be worked.


</article>



<article><tid>9542</tid>
<number>12</number>Penalty for refusal to allow inspection. If any owner, lessee 
or occupier of any such mines or works refuses to allow any officer 
appointed by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] for that purpose to enter 
into and inspect any such mines or works in manner aforesaid, he shall 
be punished with fines which may extend to two hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>653225</tid>
<number>13</number>If mines worked contrary to provisions of this Act, 
appropriate Government may require means to be adopted for safety of 
land acquired. If it appears that any such mines have been worked 
contrary to the provisions of this Act, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] 
may, if it thinks fit, give notice to the owner, lessee or occupier 
thereof to construct such works and to adopt such means as may be 
necessary or proper for making safe the land acquired, and the works 
thereon, and preventing injury thereto; and if, after such notice, any 
such owner, lessee or occupier does not forthwith proceed to construct 
the works necessary for making safe the land acquired and the works 
thereon, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate Government] may itself construct the works 
and recover the expense thereof from the owner, lessee or occupier.


</article>



<article><tid>767674</tid>
<number>14</number>Construction of Act when land acquired has been transferred 
to a local authority or Company. When a statement under section 3 has 
been made regarding any land, and the land has been acquired by the 
Government, and has been transferred to, or has vested by operation of 
law, in a local authority or Company, then sections 4 to 13, both 
inclusive, shall be read as if for the words" the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> appropriate 
Government]", wherever they occur in those sections, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> except in 
section 5, sub- section (5) and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Provincial Government". 
2 Ins. by Devolution Act, <year>1920</year> (38 of <year>1920</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


section 8], the words" the local authority or Company, as the case may 
be, which has acquired the land," were substituted.



</article>



<article><tid>431419</tid>
<number>15</number>[ Pending cases.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1937</year> 
 (20 of <year>1937</year>), s. 3 and Sch., II.


</article>



<article><tid>491002</tid>
<number> 16</number> Definition of local authority and Company. In this Act--
<section><tid>1607941</tid>
<number>a</number>" local authority" means any municipal committee, 
district board, body of port commissioners or other 
authority legally entitled to, or entrusted by the 
Government with, the control or management of any 
municipal or local fund; and

</section>

<section><tid>860148</tid>
<number>b</number>" Company" means a company registered under any of the 
enactments relating to Companies from time to time in 
force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], or formed in pursuance of an Act of 
parliament <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> of the United Kingdom] or by Royal 
Charter or Letters Patent;

</section>

<section><tid>517687</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" appropriate Government" means in relation to 
acquisition of land for the purposes of the Union, the 
Central Government, and, in relation to acquisition of 
land for any other purposes, the State Government.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1797786</tid>
<number>17</number>This Act to be read with Land Acquisition Act, <year>1870</year>. This Act 
shall, for the purposes of all enactments for the time being in force, 
be read with and taken as part of the Land Acquisition Act <year>1870</year>, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (10  
  of <year>1870</year>).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part A 
States and Part C States". 
2 Ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3 See now the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>