<act><tid>1109820</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN MEDICAL COUNCIL (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 34 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 3rd September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Indian Medical Council Act, <year>1956</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>621332</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Indian Medical Council 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>551779</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 13.- In the Indian Medical Council Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (102 of <year>1956</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in 
section 13,-
<section><tid>1132420</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (3), after the words" granted by medical 
institutions outside India", the words" before such date as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify" shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>304525</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (4), the following provisos and Explanation shall 
be inserted at the end, namely:-
' Provided that after the commencement of the Indian Medical Council 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>, no such amendment shall be made in Part II of 
the Third Schedule to include any primary medical qualification 
granted by any medical institution outside India:

Provided further that nothing contained in the first proviso shall 
apply to inclusion in Part II of the Third Schedule any primary 
medical qualification granted by any medical institution outside India 
to any person whose name is entered in the Indian M dical Register.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," primary medical 
qualification" means any minimum qualification sufficient for 
enrolment on any State Medical Register or for entering the name in 
the Indian Medical Register.';


</section>

<section><tid>1605879</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (4), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (4A) A person who is a citizen of India and obtains medical 
qualification granted by any medical institution in any country 
outside India recognised for enrolment as medical practitioner in that 
country after such date as may be specified by the Central Government 
under sub- section (3), shall not be entitled to be enrolled on any 
Medical Register maintained by a State Medical Council or to have his 
name entered in the Indian Medical Register unless he qualifies the 
screening test in India prescribed f r such purpose and such foreign 
medical qualification after such person qualifies the said screening 
test shall be deemed to be the recognised medical qualification for 
the purposes of this Act for that person.


<subsection><tid>537788</tid>
<number>4B</number>A person who is a citizen of India shall not, after such date as 
may be specified by the Central Government under sub- section (3), be 
eligible to get admission to obtain medical qualification granted by 
any medical institution in any foreign country without obtaining an 
eligibility certificate issued to him by the Council and in case any 
such person obtains such qualification without obtaining such 
eligibility certificate, he shall not be eligible to appear in the 
screening test referred to in sub- s ction (4A):
Provided that an Indian citizen who has acquired the medical 
qualification from foreign medical institution or has obtained 
admission in foreign medical institution before the commencement of 
the Indian Medical Council (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year> shall not be equired 
to obtain eligibility certificate under this sub- section but, if he is 
qualified for admission to any medical course for recognised medical 
qualification in any medical institution in India, he shall be 
required to qualify only the screening test prescribed for enrolment 
on any State Medical Register or for entering his name in the Indian 
Medical Register.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>125477</tid>
<number>4C</number>Nothing contained in sub- sections (4A) and (4B) shall apply to 
the medical qualifications referred to in section 14 for the purposes 
of that section.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>431166</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 33.- In section 33 of the principal Act, after 
clause (m), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (ma) the modalities for conducting screening tests under sub- section 
 (4A), and under the proviso to sub- section (4B), and for issuing 
eligibility certificate under sub- section (4B), of section 13;".

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>