<act><title>


THE NATIONAL HIGHWAYS (manner oF depositing the amount by the central government 
with the competent authority for acquisition of land) RULES, 19981</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the National Highways (Manner of Depositing the Amount 
by the Central Government with the Competent Authority for Acquisition of Land) 
Rules, 1998.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> The manner of 
depositing money with the competent authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of the Act, the existing agency authorised by the 
Central Government in this behalf shall deposit,—
 <subsection>
      
<number>a</number>  the amount determined under section 3G of the Act, and
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>b</number>  where the amount determined by the arbitrator under section 3G of the 
Act is in excess of the amount determined by the competent authority, the excess 
amount together with interest, if any, awarded by the arbitrator, within seven 
days of such determination or award by the competent authority or by the 
arbitrator, as the case may be, with the competent authority through demand 
draft.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The competent 
authority shall deposit the amount received under sub-rule (1) in a separate 
Public Deposit Account in the Public Account of India and the provisions of 
sub-sections (2) to (4) of section 3H of the Act shall apply to such deposit.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of this rule,—
 <subsection>
      
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the National Highways Act, 1956 (48 of 1956);
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>b</number> the expression “executing agency” shall have the same meaning as assigned to 
it under clause (d) of rule 2 of the National Highways Rules, 1957.
 
 
</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>