<act> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) 
Rules, 2003.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
Gazette.
  


</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> “Act” means the Trade Marks Act, 1999 (47 of 
1999);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> “address for service” means the address 
furnished by an applicant or appellant or respondent or his authorised agent or 
his legal practitioner at which service of summons, notices or other processes 
may be effected;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “agent” means a person duly authorized by an 
applicant or appellant or respondent to present application, appeal, counter- 
statement, reply, rejoinder, evidence or any other document on his behalf 
before the Appellate Board and shall include an agent referred to in section 
145;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> “appeal” means an appeal under section 91 of the 
Trade Marks Act, 1999 and includes Original Appeal (O.A.) and Transferred 
Appeal (T.A.);
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  “appellant” means a person making an appeal to 
the Appellate Board under section 91; 
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  “application” means an application for removal 
of registered trade mark from the register under section 47 or rectifying the 
register under section 57 or section 125;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  “Deputy Registrar” means the Deputy Registrar 
of the Appellate Board and includes any officer to whom the powers and 
functions of the Deputy Registrar may be delegated;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  “fee” means the fee prescribed under the Second 
Schedule of these rules;
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>  “form” means a form specified under the First 
Schedule to these rules;
 </section><section>        <number>j</number>  “legal practitioner” shall have the same 
meaning as is assigned to it in the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961);
 </section><section>       <number>k</number>  “legal representative” means a person who in 
law represents the estate of the deceased person;
 </section><section>        <number>l</number>  “pleadings” includes applications or appeals, 
counter-statements, rejoinders, replies and evidences supplementing them and 
other documents permitted to be filed before the Appellate Board;
 </section><section>       <number>m</number>  “Registry” means the Registry of the Appellate 
Board;
 </section><section>       <number>n</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>o</number>  “transferred application or appeal” means an 
application or an appeal or other proceedings which has been transferred to the 
Appellate Board under section 100;
 </section><section>       <number>p</number>  words and expressions used and not defined in 
these rules but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>3</number> Form of procedure of 
application or appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
application shall be filed in the Form 1 annexed to the Trade Marks 
(Applications and Appeals to the Intellectual Property Appellate Board) Rules, 
2003 by an aggrieved person in the Registry of the Appellate Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An appeal from any order or 
decision of the Registrar of Trade Marks shall be filed in the Forms 2, 3 or 4 
of the Trade Marks (Applications and Appeals to the Intellectual Property 
Appellate Board) Rules, 2003.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An application or appeal 
sent by post shall be deemed to have been presented before the Registry on the 
day it was received in the Registry.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>4</number> Payment of fee.—The 
prescribed fees shall be paid through bank draft payable at Chennai drawn in 
favour of the Deputy Registrar, Intellectual. Property Appellate Board.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>5</number> Language of the Appellate 
Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The proceedings of the 
Appellate Board shall be conducted in English or Hindi.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All decisions or orders of 
the Appellate Board shall be either in English or Hindi.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>6</number> Application or appeal to 
be in writing.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
application, appeal, counter-statement, rejoinder, reply or other document 
filed before the Appellate Board shall be typed or printed neatly.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application or appeal 
under sub‑rule (1) shall be presented in three sets in a paper-book form 
alongwith an empty file size envelope bearing full address of the respondent 
and, in case the respondents are more than one, then, sufficient number of 
extra paper‑books together with empty file size envelopes bearing full 
addresses of each respondent shall be furnished by the applicant or appellant.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>7</number> Presentation and scrutiny 
of application or appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Deputy Registrar shall endorse on every application or appeal the date on which 
it is presented.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If, on scrutiny, the 
application or appeal is in order, it shall be duly registered and given a 
serial number.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If an application or appeal 
is found to be defective and the defect noticed is formal in nature, the Deputy 
Registrar may allow  the applicant or appellant to rectify the same in his 
presence and if the said defect is not formal in nature, the Deputy Registrar 
may allow the applicant or appellant fifteen days’ time to rectify the defect 
as he may deem fit. If the application or appeal has been sent by post and 
found to be defective, the Deputy Registrar may communicate the defects to the 
applicant or appellant and allow the applicant or appellant fifteen days’ time 
from the date of receipt of the communication from the Deputy Registrar to 
rectify the defects.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the applicant or 
appellant fails to rectify the defects within the time allowed in sub‑rule (3) 
the application or appeal shall be deemed to have been abandoned.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>8</number> Documents to accompany 
application or appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
application shall be in triplicate in paper‑book form and all evidences shall 
be in the form of affidavits, if any.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every appeal shall be in 
triplicate in paper‑book form and shall be accompanied by the copies of the 
order, at least one of which shall be a certified copy against which the appeal 
is filed, alongwith evidences in the form of affidavits.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a party is 
represented by authorized representative, a copy of the authorization to act as 
the authorized representative shall be appended to the application or appeal.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>9</number> Notices of application or 
appeal to the respondent.—A copy of 
the application or appeal in paper‑book form shall be served by the Deputy 
Registrar on the respondent as soon as the same is registered in the Registry.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>10</number> Filing of 
counter-statement to the application or appeal and other documents by the 
respondent.—
<section><number>1</number> After receipt of the 
application or appeal filed in the prescribed Forms 1, 2, or 3 of the Trade 
Marks (Applications and Appeals to the Intellectual Property Appellate Board) 
Rules, 2003, the respondent may file three complete sets of counter-statement 
in the prescribed Form I under these rules containing the reply to the 
application or appeal along with documents including evidences in the form of 
affidavits, if any, in paper‑book form before the Registry within two months of 
the service of the notice on him of the filing of the application or appeal. A 
copy of the counter-statement shall be served to the applicant or appellant by 
the respondent directly under intimation to the Registry.
 </section><section><number>2</number> After receipt of the appeal 
filed in the prescribed Form 4 of the Trade Marks (Applications and Appeals to 
the Intellectual Property Appellate Board) Rules, 2003, the respondent may file 
three complete sets of counter-statement in the prescribed Form 2 under these 
rules containing the reply to the appeal in paper­book form before the Registry 
within two months of the service of the notice on him of the filing of appeal. 
A copy of the counter-statement shall be served to the appellant by the 
respondent directly under intimation to the Registry. The case would then 
proceed for hearing.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>11</number> Filing of reply by the 
applicant or appellant.—After 
receipt of counter-statement, the applicant or appellant, may file his reply 
within two months of the service of the counter-statement along with evidence 
in the form of affidavits, if any, in triplicate in the Registry. A copy of the 
reply shall be served on the respondent directly under intimation to the 
Registry.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>12</number> Exhibits.—Where 
there are exhibits to affidavits, a copy each of such exhibits shall be sent to 
the other party. The originals shall be left in the Appellate Board for 
inspection of the other party. These shall be produced at the hearing unless 
the Appellate Board otherwise directs.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>13</number> Translation of 
documents.—Where a document in a 
language other than Hindi or English is referred to in any proceedings, an 
attested translation thereof in Hindi or English shall be furnished in 
triplicate to the Appellate Board and a copy thereof shall be served upon the 
other party or parties directly under intimation to the Registry.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>14</number> Extension of time.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Appellate Board is satisfied, on an application made to it in the 
prescribed Form 3 under these rules, that there is sufficient cause for 
extending the time for doing any act prescribed under these rules (not being a 
time expressly provided for in the Trade Marks Act, 1999), whether the time so 
specified has expired or not, it may subject to such conditions as it may think 
fit to impose, extend the time and inform the parties accordingly.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing in sub‑rule (1) 
shall be deemed to require the Appellate Board to hear the parties before 
disposing off an application for extension of time and no appeal shall lie from 
any order of the Appellate Board under this rule.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>15</number> Intervention by third 
parties.—Any person other than the 
registered proprietor of a trade mark alleging interest in a registered trade 
mark in respect of which an appeal has been filed under section 91 against the 
order or decision of the Registrar for the removal of a trade mark or to cancel 
or vary the registration and to rectify the Register may apply in the 
prescribed Form 4 under these rules for leave to intervene stating the nature 
of his interest and the Deputy Registrar may refuse or grant such leave after 
hearing, if so required, the parties concerned upon such terms and conditions 
as he deems fit.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>16</number> Date of hearing to be 
notified.—The Appellate Board shall 
notify the parties the date and place of hearing of the application or appeal 
in such manner as the Chairman may by general or special order direct.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>17</number> Hearing of application 
or appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> On the day fixed or 
on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, the parties shall be 
heard by a Bench of the Appellate Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case where the applicant 
or appellant does not appear at the hearing, the case will be treated as 
abandoned.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>18</number> Adjournment of hearing.—A 
party to the hearing may make an application in triplicate for adjournment of 
the hearing in Form 5 under these rules with the prescribed fee fifteen days 
before the date of hearing alongwith the concurrence for the adjournment from 
the other party. The Appellate Board may consider the application and pass such 
orders as it deems fit.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>19</number> Award of costs by the 
Appellate Board.—The Appellate Board 
may award such costs as it deems fit to the parties having regard to all the 
circumstances of the case.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>20</number> Order to be signed and 
dated.—
<section><number>1</number> Every order of the 
Appellate Board shall be signed and dated by the Members of the Bench.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The order shall be 
pronounced in the sitting of the Bench.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>21</number> Communication of orders.—A 
certified copy of every order passed by the Bench shall be communicated to the 
parties to the proceedings.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>22</number> Publication of the 
orders.—The orders of the Bench as 
are deemed fit for publication in any authoritative report or the press may be 
released for such publication on such terms and conditions as the Chairman may 
lay down.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>23</number> Review petitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A petition in triplicate for review of an order of the Appellate Board may be 
made to the Registry in the prescribed Form 6 under these rules within two 
months from the date on which the order is communicated accompanied by a 
statement setting forth the grounds on which the review is sought. Where the 
order in question concerns more than one respondent, sufficient extra copies of 
such petition and statement shall be filed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registry shall forward 
the petition and statement to the respondents to the review petition.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The respondents may file 
counter-statement in Form 1 under these rules within two months from the date 
of receipt of the review petition and shall forward a copy of the counte-statement 
to the petitioner directly under intimation to the Registry.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The review petition shall 
be posted for hearing before a Bench by the Chairman.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>24</number> Continuation of 
proceedings after the death of a party, merger, assignment, acquisition or 
transmission.—On the death of a 
party or by merger, assignment, acquisition or transmission if a new party 
becomes entitled for continuation of the proceedings, the proceeding would be 
continued subject to filing a request with evidence in support therefor.
</article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>25</number> Fee for inspection of 
records and obtaining copies thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A fee of Rs. 150 for every hour or part thereof shall be charged for inspecting 
the records of a pending application or appeal or decided case.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A fee of Rs. 5 shall be 
charged for providing xerox copies of each page of the record.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>26</number> Functions of the Deputy 
Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> The Deputy Registrar 
shall discharge the functions under the general superintendence of the 
Chairman. He shall discharge such other functions as are assigned to him under 
these rules or by the Chairman by a separate order in writing.
 </section><section><number>2</number> He shall have the custody 
of the records of the Appellate Board.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The official seal of the 
Appellate Board shall be kept in the custody of the Deputy Registrar.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Subject to any general or 
special directions of the Chairman, the official seal of the Appellate Board 
shall not be affixed to any order, summons or other process save under the 
authority in writing from the Deputy Registrar.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The official seal of the 
Appellate Board shall not be affixed to any certified copy issued by the 
Appellate Board save under the authority in writing of the Deputy Registrar.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>27</number> Additional functions and 
duties of the Deputy Registrar.—In 
addition to the functions and duties assigned under rule 26, the Deputy 
Registrar shall have the following functions and duties subject to any general 
or special orders of the Chairman, namely:­—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  to receive all applications, appeals, 
counter-statements, replies and other documents;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  to decide all questions arising out of the 
scrutiny of the appeals and applications before they are registered;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number> to require any application, appeal, 
counter-statement, replies presented to the Appellate Board to be amended in 
accordance with the rules;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>  subject to the directions of the Chairman, to 
fix date of hearing of the application or appeals or other proceedings and 
issue notices therefor;
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  direct any formal amendment of records;
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>  to order supply of copies of documents to 
parties to proceedings;
 </section><section>      <number>vii</number>  to grant leave to inspect the record of the 
Appellate Board;
 </section><section>     <number>viii</number> to requisition records from the custody of any 
court, Registrar of Trade Marks or other authority;
 </section><section>       <number>ix</number>  to decide questions relating to extension of 
time in respect of filing of counter-statement, reply, rejoinder, etc.
</section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>28</number> Dress regulations for 
the Chairman, Vice‑Chairman, Technical Member of the Appellate Board and for 
the representatives of the parties.—
<section><number>i</number> 
The dress for the Chairman, Vice‑Chairman and other Members shall be white pant 
with black coat and black tie or a buttoned‑up black coat. If the officials are 
from the High Court Bench, then they shall be in their official robes.
 </section><section><number>ii</number> The dress for the 
professionals who appear before the Appellate Board shall be the professional 
dress, if any, and in case of other authorised representatives of the parties, 
it shall be the following:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  In the case of male, a black coat with a black 
tie or buttoned‑up black coat over a white pant.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  In the case of female, a black coat over white 
or any other sober coloured saree.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  All other persons appearing before the 
Appellate Board shall be properly dressed.
</subsection></section></article> 
 the 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board (Procedure) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>29</number> Seal and emblem.—The 
official seal and emblem of the Appellate Board shall be such as the Central 
Government may specify.
  
  
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>