<act><title>THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (FOREIGN EXCHANGE DERIVATIVE CONTRACTS) REGULATIONS, 20001</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>i</number> These regulations may be called the Foreign Exchange Management (Foreign Exchange Derivative Contracts) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> They shall come into force on the 1st day of June, 2000. 


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</subsection>
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these regulations, unless the context requires otherwise, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Act' means the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (42 of 1999); 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Authorised Dealer' means a person authorised as authorised dealer under sub-section (1) of section 10 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Cash Delivery' means delivery of foreign exchange on the day of transaction; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> Forward Contract' means a transaction involving delivery, other than Cash or Tom or Spot delivery, of foreign exchange; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract' means a financial transaction or an arrangement in whatever form and by whatever name called, whose value in derived from price movement in one or more underlying assets, and includes 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a transaction which involves at least one foreign currency other than currency of Nepal or Bhutan or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a transaction which involves at least one interest rate applicable to a foreign currency not being a currency of Nepal or Bhutan , or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a forward contract, but does not include foreign exchange transaction for Cash or Tom or Spot deliveries; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>va</number> Currency Futures' means a standardised foreign exchange derivative contract traded on a recognised stock exchange to buy or sell one currency against another on a specified future date, at a price specified on the date of contract, but does not include a forward contract;] 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> Registered Foreign Institutional Investor (FII)' means a foreign institutional investor registered with Securities and Exchange Board of India; 
 </section><section><number>vii</number> Schedule' means a Schedule annexed to these regulations; 
 </section><section><number>viii</number> Spot Delivery' means delivery of foreign exchange on the second working day after the day of transaction; 
 </section><section><number>ix</number> Tom Delivery' means delivery of foreign exchange on a working day next to the day of transaction; 
 </section><section><number>x</number> the words and expressions used but not defined in these regulations shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>


 
 <section><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Prohibition. </title>Save as otherwise provided in these Regulations, no person in India shall enter into a foreign exchange derivative contract <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[or currency futures] without the prior permission of the Reserve Bank. 


 
 <section><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Permission to a person resident in India to enter into a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract. </title>A person resident in India may enter into a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract in accordance with provisions contained in Schedule I, to hedge an exposure to risk in respect of a transaction permissible under the Act, or rules or regulations or directions or orders made or issued thereunder. 


 
 <section><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Permission to a person resident outside India to enter into a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract. </title>A person resident outside India may enter into a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract with a person resident in India in accordance with provisions contained in Schedule II, to hadge an exposure to risk in respect of a transaction permissible under the Act, of rules or regulations or directions or orders made or issued thereunder. 


 
 <section><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<title><number>5A</number> Permission to a person resident in India to enter into currency futures or currency options. </title>A person resident in India may enter into currency futures or currency options on a stock exchange recognized under section 4 of the Securities Contract (Regulation) Act, 1956, to hedge an exposure to risk or otherwise, subject to such terms and conditions as may be set forth in the directions issued by the Reserve Bank of India from time to time.] 












</article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<title><number>6</number> Commodity hedge. </title>
<section><number>i</number> Reserve Bank may, on an application made in accordance with the procedure specified in Schedule III, permit, subject to such terms and conditions as it may consider necessary, a person resident in India to enter into a contract in a commodity exchange or market outside India to hedge price risk in a commodity. 
 
 
 Explanation .The term stand-alone means that the unit in the SEZ is completely isolated from financial contracts with its parent or subsidiary in the mainland or within the SEZ(s) as far as its import/export transactions are concerned.] 


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</subsection>


</section><section><number>ii</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-regulation (1), an authorised dealer bank specially authorised in that behalf by the Reserve Bank may permit a company, resident in India and listed on a recognised stock exchange, to enter into contracts in a commodity exchange or market outside India, to hedge the price risk in a commodity <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***] subject to such terms and conditions as may be stipulated by the Reserve Bank from time to time: 
 Provided that such authorised dealer bank shall exercise such authority subject to the directions and guidelines issued to them by the Reserve Bank in that behalf. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> An authorised dealer bank may apply to the Reserve Bank of India , Foreign Exchange Department for grant of authority to grant permission under sub-regulation (ii) to its customers. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this regulation a unit in the special economic zone (SEZ') may enter into contracts in a commodity exchange or market outside India to hedge the price risk of the commodity of export/import, subject to the condition that such contract is entered into on a stand-alone basis. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<title><number>6A</number> Freight hedge. </title>
<section><number>i</number> Reserve Bank may, on an application made in accordance with such procedure as may be directed by Reserve Bank, permit a person resident in India, subject to such terms and conditions as may be considered necessary, to enter into a freight derivative contract in an exchange or a market out side India to hedge the freight risk such person is exposed to. 
 
 


 
 <subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</subsection>

</section><section><number>ii</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-regulation (i) an authorised dealer in India specially authorised by the Reserve Bank under sub-regulation (ii) of Regulation 6 may premit an oil refining company or a shipping company, resident in India, to enter into freight derivative contracts in an exchange or market outside India, to hedge the freight risk which the company is exposed to, subject to such terms and conditions as may be stipulated by the Reserve Bank from time to time: 
 Provided that such authorised dealer category-I bank shall exercise the authority subject to directions and guidelines issued to them by the Reserve Bank in that behalf.] 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Remittance related to a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract. </title>An authorised dealer in India may remit outside India foreign exchange in respect of a transaction, undertaken in accordance with these Regulations, in the following cases, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> option premium payable by a person resident in India to a person resident outside India , 
 </section><section><number>b</number> remittance by a person resident in India of amount incidental to a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract entered into in accordance with regulation 4, 
 </section><section><number>c</number> remittance by a person resident outside India of amount incidental to a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract entered into in accordance with regulation 5, 
 </section><section><number>d</number> any other remittance related to a Foreign Exchange Derivative Contract approved by Reserve Bank. 
</section>


 
 <section><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</section>
</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Remittance related to a Commodity Derivative Contract. </title>An authorised dealer in India may remit outside India foreign exchange in respect of a transaction, undertaken in accordance with these Regulations, in the following cases, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> option premium payable by a person resident in India to a person resident outside India ; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> remittance by a person resident in India of amount incidental to a commodity derivative contract entered into in accordance with regulation 6; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> any other remittance related to a commodity derivative contract approved by Reserve Bank.] 
</section>


 
 <section><number>G</number>S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 </section><section><number>G</number>S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 
</section>

</article><form>
 

THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (FOREIGN EXCHANGE DERIVATIVE CONTRACTS) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

Schedule I 
 

( See  regulation 4) 
 

Foreign exchange derivative contract permissible  

  for a person resident in India 
 

A. Forward Contract 
 

1. A person resident in India may enter into a forward contract with an authorised dealer in India to hedge an exposure to exchange risk in respect of a transaction for which sale and/or purchase of foreign exchange is permitted under the Act, or rules of regulations to directions or orders made or issued thereunder, subject to following terms and conditions 
 
 

(a) 2[the authorised dealer through verification of documentary evidence is satisfied about the genuineness of the underlying exposure or as otherwise permitted by the Reserve Bank from time to time,] 
 

(b) the maturity of the hedge does not exceed the maturity of the underlying transaction, 
 

(c) the currency of hedge and tenor are left to the choice of the customer, 
 

(d) where the exact amount of the underlying transaction is not ascertainable, the contract is booked on the basis of a reasonable estimate, 
 

(e) foreign currency loans/bonds will be eligible for hedge only after final approval is accorded by the Reserve Bank where such approval is necessary, 
 

(f) in case of Global Depository Receipts (GDRs) the issue price has been finalised, 
 

(g) balances in the Exchange Earner's Foreign Currency (EEFC) accounts sold forward in the account holders shall remain earmarked for delivery and such contracts shall not be cancelled. They may be, however, be rolled-over, 
 

3[(h) contracts involving the rupee as one of the currencies, once cancelled, shall not be rebooked except as otherwise permitted by the Reserve Bank from time to time although they can be rolled over at on-going rates on or before maturity. Such contracts booked by residents to hedge current account transactions, regardless of tenor, not being those booked on past performance basis without documents or booked to hedge transactions denominated in foreign currency but settled in Indian Rupee, may be cancelled and rebooked freely at on going rates. Contracts covering export transactions may also be cancelled, rebooked or rolled over at on going rates without any restriction,] 
 

(i) substitution of contracts for hedging trade transactions may be permitted by an authorised dealer on being satisfied with the circumstances under which such substitution has become necessary, 
 

4[(j) a person resident in India may, subject to the terms and conditions prescribed by Reserve Bank of India, enter into a forward contract with an authorised dealer in India to hedge an exposure to exchange risk in respect of transactions denominated in foreign currency but settled in Indian rupees.] 

 

5[AA. Forward Contract in respect of Economic Exposure. A person resident in India may, subject to such terms and conditions as may be stipulated by the Reserve Bank from time to time, enter into a forward contract with an authorised dealer in India to hedge an economic exposure to exchange risk in respect of such transactions as may be prescribed by the Reserve Bank from time to time.] 
 

B. Contract other than Forward Contract 
 

2. (1) A person resident in India who has borrowed foreign exchange in accordance with the provisions of the Foreign Exchange Management (Borrowing and Lending in Foreign Exchange) Regulations, 2000, may enter into an Interest rate swap or Currency swap or Coupon Swap or Foreign Currency Option or Interest rate cap or collar (Purchases) or Forward Rate Agreement (FRA) contract with an authorised dealer in India or with a branch outside India of an authorised dealer for hedging his loan exposure and unwinding from such hedges: 
 
 

Provided that 
 

(a) the contract does not involve rupee, 
 

(b) the Reserve Bank has accorded final approval for borrowing in foreign currency, 
 

(c) the notional principal amount of the hedge does not exceed the outstanding amount of the foreign currency loan, and 
 

(d) the maturity of the hedge does not exceed the un-expired maturity of the underlying loan. 
 

(2) A person resident in India , who owes a foreign exchange or rupee liability, may enter into a contract for foreign currency-rupee swap with an authorised dealer in India to hedge long term exposure. 
 

(3) The contract entered into under sub-paragraph 2, if cancelled shall not be rebooked or re-entered, by whatever name called. 

 

3. (1) A person resident in India may enter into a foreign currency option contract 6[not involving the rupee as one of the currencies] with an authorised dealer in India to hedge foreign exchange exposure of such person arising out of his trade: 
 
 

Provided that in respect of cost effective risk reduction strategies like range forwards, ratio-range forwards or any other variable by whatever name called there shall not be any net inflow of premium. 
 

Explanation .The contingent foreign exchange exposure arising out of submission of a tender bid in foreign exchange is also eligible for hedging under this sub-paragraph. 
 

(2) A transaction undertaken under sub-paragraph (1) may be freely booked and/or cancelled. 

 

--------- 
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 411(E), dated 3rd May, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
  Sec. 3 (i), dated 8th May, 2000 and subsequently amended vide : 
 
 

G.S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 

G.S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 

G.S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 

G.S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 

G.S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 

G.S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 

G.S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 

 

2. Subs. by G.S.R. 264(E), dated 5th March, 2002 (w.e.f. 9-4-2002). 
 

3. Subs. by G.S.R. 222(E), dated 16th April, 2006 (w.r.e.f. 26-6-2005). 
 

4. Added by G.S.R. 880(E), dated 21st October, 2003 (w.e.f. 11-11-2003). 
 

5. Ins. by G.S.R. 760(E), dated 17th September, 2007 (w.r.e.f. 13-12-2006). 
 

6. Ins. by G.S.R. 750(E), dated 19th December, 2005 (w.r.e.f. 7-3-2003). 
</form><form>
 

THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (FOREIGN EXCHANGE DERIVATIVE CONTRACTS) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

Schedule II 
 

( See regulation 5) 
 

Foreign exchange derivative contracts permissible  

  for a person resident outside India 
 

1. A Registered Foreign Institutional Investor (FII) may enter into a forward contract with rupee as one of the currencies with an authorised dealer in India to hedge its exposure in India : 
 

Provided that 
 
 

(a) 2[the value of the hedge does not exceed the market value of the underlying debt or equity instruments, provided forward contracts once booked shall be allowed to continue to the original maturity even if the value of the underlying portfolio shrinks, for reasons other than sale of securities,] 
 

3[***] 
 

4[(b) forward contracts may be cancelled and rebooked subject to such terms and conditions as may be stipulated by the Reserve Bank from time to time, or may be rolled over on or before maturity.] 
 

5[(c)] the cost of hedge is met out of repatriable funds and/or inward remittance through normal banking channel, 
 

5[(d)] all outward remittances incidental to hedge are not of applicable Indian taxes. 

 

2. A non-resident Indian 6[***] may enter into forward contract with rupee as one of the currencies, with an authorised dealer in India to hedge 
 
 

(a) the amount of dividend due to him/it on shares held in an Indian company; 
 

(b) the balances held in Foreign Currency Non-Resident (FCNR) account or Non-Resident External Rupee (NRE) account, 
 

(c) the amount of investment made under portfolio scheme in accordance with the provision of the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 or under notifications issued thereunder or is made in accordance with the provisions of the Foreign Exchange Management (Transfer or issue of Security by a person Resident outside India) Regulations, 2000 and in both cases subject to the terms and conditions specified in the proviso to paragraph 1 of this Schedule. 

 

7[2A. A non-resident Indian may, subject to conditions prescribed by the Reserve Bank of India from time to time, enter into cross currency (not involving the rupee) forward contracts to convert the balances held in FCNR (B) accounts in one foreign currency to another foreign currency in which FCNR (B) deposits are permitted to be maintained.] 
 

3. 8[Authorised dealers may offer forward contracts to persons resident outside India to hedge the investments made in India since January 1, 1993, subject to verification of the exposure in India. These forward contracts once cancelled are not eligible to be rebooked.] 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 411(E), dated 3rd May, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
  Sec. 3 (i), dated 8th May, 2000 and subsequently amended vide : 
 
 

G.S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 

G.S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 

G.S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 

G.S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 

G.S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 

G.S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 

G.S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 

 

2. Subs. by G.S.R. 532(E), dated 8th January, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-7-2003). 
 

3. Sub-clause (b) omitted by G.S.R. 532(E), dated 8th January, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-7-2003). 
 

4. Subs. by G.S.R. 760(E), dated 17th September, 2007, for clause (b) (w.r.e.f. 8-2-2007). Earlier clause (c) had been renumbered as clause (b) by G.S.R. 532(E), dated 8th January, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-7-2003). 
 

5. Clauses (c), (d) and (e) re-numbered as clauses (b), (c) and (d) respectively by G.S.R. 532 (E), dated 8th January, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-7-2003). 
 

6. Omitted by G.S.R. 836(E), dated 3rd October, 2003 (w.e.f. 23-10-2003). 
 

7. Added by G.S.R. 880(E), dated 21st October, 2003 (w.e.f. 11-11-2003). 
 

8. Subs. by G.S.R. 532(E), dated 8th January, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-7-2003). 
</form><form>
 

THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (FOREIGN EXCHANGE DERIVATIVE CONTRACTS) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

Schedule III 
 

( See regulation 6) 
 

Procedure for application for approval for  

  hedging of commodity price risk 
 

1. A person resident in India , engaged in export-import trade 2[or as permitted by the Reserve Bank], who seeks to hedge price risk in respect of any commodity including Gold, 3[***] may submit an application to the International Banking Division of an authorised dealer giving the following details: 
 
 

(i) A brief description of the hedging strategy proposed; namely: 
 
 

(a) description of business activity and nature of risk; 
 

(b) instruments proposed to be used for hedging; 
 

(c) name of commodity exchange and brokers through whom the risk is proposed to be hedged and credit lines proposed to be availed. The name and address of the regulatory authority in the country concerned may also be given; 
 

(d) size/average tenure of exposure and or total turnover in a year, together with expected peak positions thereof and the basis of calculation. 

 

(ii) Copy of the Risk Management Policy approved by the Management covering 
 
 

(a) risk identification, 
 

(b) risk measurements, 
 

(c) guidelines and procedures to be followed with respect to revaluation and/or monitoring of positions, 
 

(d) names and designations of the officials authorised to undertake transactions and limits. 

 

(iii) Any other relevant information. 

 

4[2. Authorised dealer, after ensuring that the application is supported by documents indicated in paragraph 1, as may be relevant, may forward the application with its recommendations to the Reserve Bank of India , where applicable. In all other cases, the application may be forwarded by the company concerned to an authorised dealer bank authorised to grant permission under sub-regulation (ii) of regulation 6, for consideration.] 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 411(E), dated 3rd May, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
  Sec. 3 (i), dated 8th May, 2000 and subsequently amended vide : 
 
 

G.S.R. 756(E), dated 28-9-2000. G.S.R. 750(E), dated 28-12-2005. 
 

G.S.R. 264(E), dated 9-4-2002. G.S.R. 222(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 

G.S.R. 579(E), dated 19-8-2002. G.S.R. 223(E), dated 19-4-2006. 
 

G.S.R. 222(E), dated 18-3-2003. G.S.R. 760(E), dated 7-12-2007. 
 

G.S.R. 532(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 577(E), dated 5-8-2008. 
 

G.S.R. 880(E), dated 11-11-2003. G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20-5-2009. 
 

G.S.R. 881(E), dated 11-11-2003. 

 

2. Added by G.S.R. 881(E), dated 21st October, 2003 (w.e.f. 11-11-2003). 
 

3. Omitted by G.S.R. 756(E), dated 5th September, 2000 (w.e.f. 5-9-2000). 
 

4. Subs. by G.S.R. 223(E), dated 16th April, 2006 (w.r.e.f. 23-7-2005). 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 577(E), dated 1st August, 2008 (w.e.f. 5-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 577(E), dated 1st August, 2008 (w.e.f. 5-8-2008).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 635(E), dated 19th July, 2010, for rule 5A (w.e.f. 27-7-2010). Earlier rule 5A was inserted by G.S.R. 577(E), dated 1st August, 2008 (w.e.f. 5-8-2008). Rule 5A, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 223(E), dated 16th April, 2006 (w.r.e.f. 23-7-2005). Earlier it was amended by G.S.R. 579(E), dated 27th July, 2002 (w.e.f. 19-8-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> The words imported/exported by it omitted by G.S.R. 760(E), dated 17th September, 2007 (w.r.e.f. 31-5-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 440(E), dated 20th May, 2009 (w.r.e.f. 4-2-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 760(E), dated 17th September, 2007 (w.r.e.f. 23-7-2005).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>