<act><tid>1134554</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN TOLLS ACT, <year>1851</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 8 OF <year>1851</year> 
[ 4th July, <year>1851</year>]
An Act for enabling Government to levy Tolls on Public Roads and 
Bridges.

Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to enable Government to levy 
tolls upon roads and bridges; It is enacted as follows:-




<article><tid>1573450</tid>
<number>1</number>[ Repeal of Acts.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1870</year> (14 of  
  <year>1870</year>), s. 1 and Sch, Pt. II.


</article>



<article><tid>889943</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Extent.-- This Act extends to the territories 
administered on the fourth of July, eighteen hundred and fifty- one, by 
the Governor of the Presidency of Fort William in Bengal, the 
Lieutenant- Governor of North- Western Provinces of Bengal and the 
Governor of the Presidency of Fort St. George in Council.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>).

This Act should be read with the Indian Tolls Act, <year>1864</year> (15  
  of <year>1864</year>), and the Indian Tolls Act, <year>1888</year> (8 of <year>1888</year>).

This Act has been amended in Assam by Assam Act 3 of <year>1931</year> 
and Act 1 of <year>1932</year>; C. P. by C. P. Act 8 of <year>1932</year>, Madras by Madras 
Act 6 of <year>1938</year>, Act 14 of <year>1942</year> and Act 26 of <year>1950</year>.

This Act is deemed to be in force throughout the territories 
administered by the Lieutenant- Governor of the Punjab on the 5th 
September, <year>1888</year> and to have been in force, from the 21st August 
<year>1857</year>, in the territories for the time being administered as part 
of the Punjab.

It has been extended under s. 3 of Act 15 of <year>1864</year> to Ajmer 
and Merwara, see Gazette of India <year>1889</year>, Pt. II, p. 562.

It has been declared to be in force in the C. P. and the 
Sambalpur District by the C. P. Laws Act, <year>1875</year> (20 of <year>1875</year>), s. 3; 
in the Sonthal Parganas by the Sonthal Parganas Settlement 
Regulation, <year>1872</year> (3 of <year>1872</year>), s. 3.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

The Districts of Hazaribagh, 
Lohardaga (now the Ranch  
Districts, see Calcutta Gazette, 
  <year>1899</year>, Pt. I. p. 44), and Man- 
bhum, and Pargana Dhalbhum 
and Kolhan in the District of 
Singhbum... See Gazette of India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

The District of Lahaul Ditto <year>1886</year>, Ot. I, p. 301.

It has been extended by notification under s. 5 of the last- 
mentioned Act, to the Scheduled District of Coorg, see Gazette of 
India, <year>1878</year>, Pt. I., p. 45; to the Scheduled Districts in Ganjam and 
Vizagapatam, see ibid., <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 720; to the Ducharti and 
Guditeru Muttahs, Yellavaram taluk, East Godavari Agency. see 
Notification No. 110, dated 22nd April, <year>1927</year>, Fort St. George Gazette, 
<year>1927</year>, Pt. I, p. 661, and to the District of Darjeeling, see Calcutta 
Gazetee, <year>1934</year>, Pt. I, p. 179.

It has been repealed in the Presidency of Bombay, to which it 
originally applied, by the Bombay Tolls Act <year>1875</year> (Bom. Act 3 of  
  <year>1875</year>,), s. 1 and has also been amended in Assam by assam Acts 3 of 
<year>1931</year> and 1 of <year>1932</year>; C. P. by C. P. Act 8 of <year>1932</year>; and Madras by Madras 
Acts 6 of <year>1938</year> and 14 of <year>1942</year>.

It has been repealed in Mysore by Mysory Act 29 of <year>1958</year>.

The Act has been extended to the whole of Madhya Pradesh by M. P. 
Act 23 of <year>1958</year> and to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of 
<year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

The Act has been amended in its application to Uttar Pradesh by 
U. P. Act 5 of <year>1957</year>, Andhra Pradesh by A. P. Act 17 of <year>1975</year> and West 
Bengal by W. B. Act 18 of <year>1978</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1150736</tid>
<number>2</number>Power to cause levy of tolls on roads and bridges within 
certain rates, and to appoint collectors. Collectors' 
responsibilities.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[ The State Government] may cause such rates 
of toll, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> it thinks fit], to be levied upon any road or 
bridge which has been, or shall hereafter be, made or repaired 4 
[ at the expense of the Central or any State Government]; and may 
place the collection of such tolls under the management of such 
persons as may appear to <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> it] proper: and all persons employed in 
the management and collection of such tolls shall be liable to the 
same responsibilities as would belong to them if employed in the 
collection of the land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>1998965</tid>
<number>3</number>Their powers for recovery of toll.-- In case of non- payment of 
any such toll on demand, the officers appointed to collect the same 
may seize any of the carriages or animals on which it is chargeable, 
or any part of their burden of sufficient value to defray the toll; 
and, if any toll remains undischarged for twenty- four hours, with the 
cost arising from such seizure, the case shall be brought before the 
officer appointed to superintend the collection of the said toll, who 
may sell the property seized for discharge of the toll, and all 
expenses occasioned by such nonpayment, seizure and sale, and cause 
any balance that may remain to be returned, on demand, to the owner of 
the property; and the said officer, on receipt of the property, shall 
forthwith issue a notice that, at noon of the next day, exclusive of 
Sunday, or any closed holiday, he will sell the property by auction:
Release of seized property on tender of dues.-- Provided that, if, 
at any time before the sale has actually begun, the person whose 
property, has been seized shall tender the amount of all the expenses 
incurred, and of double the toll payable by him, the said officer 
shall forthwith release the property seized.



</article>



<article><tid>1914410</tid>
<number>4</number>Exemptions from payment of toll.-- No tolls shall be paid for 
the passage <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> of Police- officers on duty, or of any person or 
property in their custody, but no other exemption from payment of the 
toll levied under this Act shall be allowed.


</article>



<article><tid>1283756</tid>
<number>5</number>Assistance of collectors by Police- officers.-- All Police- 
officers shall be bound to assist the toll- collectors, when required, 
in the execution of this Act; and, for that purpose, shall have the 
same power which they have in the exercise of their common police- 
duties.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. P. <year>1937</year>, for" The Governor of the Presidency of 
Fort William in Bengal, the Lieutenant- Governor of the North- 
Western Provinces of bengal and the Governor of Bengla and the 
Governor of the Presidency of Fort St. George in Council". The 
words" and the Governor of the Presidency of Bombay in Council" 
had been rep. by Act 8 of <year>1888</year>, s. 5.

The authority of the Provincial Government in any Province 
of India not specified in s. 1A to which this Act and the Indian 
Tolls Act, <year>1864</year> (15 of <year>1864</year>), may be or have been extended, is to 
be the same as if it had been originally specified in s. 2. See 
the Indian Tolls Act, <year>1888</year> (8 of <year>1888</year>), s. 2 (1).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" not exceeding the rates mentioned in the Schedule 
annexed to this Act" omitted by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, ibid., for" they respectively think fit."

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for" at the expense of the Govt.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs., ibid., for" them".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>The words" of troops and military stores and equipages on their 
march or" rep. by Act 2 of <year>1901</year>, s. 8 and Sch.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1491555</tid>
<number>6</number>Penalty for offences under Act. Compensation to Person 
aggrieved. Saving of his right to sue.-- Every person, other than the 
persons appointed to collect the tolls under this Act, who shall levy 
or demand any toll on any public road or bridge, or for passing 
through any bazar situated thereon, and also every person who shall 
unlawfully and extortionately demand, or take any other or higher toll 
than the lawful toll, or under colour of this Act seize or sell any 
property knowing such seizure or sale to be unlawful, or in any manner 
unlawfully extort money or any valuable thing from any person under 
colour of this Act, shall be liable on conviction before Magistrate to 
imprisonment for any term not exceeding six calendar months, or to 
fine not exceeding two hundred rupees, any part of which fine may be 
awarded by the Magistrate to the person aggrieved; but this remedy 
shall not be deemed to bar or affect his right to have redress by suit 
in the Civil Court. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</article>



<article><tid>180540</tid>
<number>7</number>Exhibition of table of tolls, and statement of penalties.-- A 
table of the tolls authorized to be taken at any toll- gate or station 
shall be put up in a conspicuous place near such gate or station 
legibly written or printed in English words and figures, and also in 
those of the vernacular language of the district, to which shall be 
annexed, written or printed in like manner, a statement of the 
penalties for refusing to pay the tolls and for taking any lawful 
toll.


</article>



<article><tid>1762782</tid>
<number>8</number>Application of proceeds of tolls.-- The tolls levied under this 
Act shall be deemed public revenue <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

</article>



 </act>