<act><title>THE RAILWAY CLAIMS TRIBUNAL 
(FINANCIAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE POWERS) RULES, 1989 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Railway Claims Tribunal (Financial 
and Administrative Powers) Rules, 1989. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the appointed 
day'<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> within the meaning of clause (b) of section 2 of the Act 
  

</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> </title>In these rules, unless 
the context otherwise requires, 
 <section><number>1</number> Act means the Railway Claims Tribunal Act, 1987 (54 of 
1987). </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Sitting of a Bench at a place other than the 
place where it ordinarily sits. </title>If at any time, the Chairman is 
satisfied that circumstances exist which necessitate sittings of the Bench at 
any place falling in its juris­diction other than the place at which it 
ordinarily sits, he may direct that the Bench may hold its sit­tings at any 
such place. </article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Powers of Chairman. </title>The 
Chairman shall have the same powers in respect of matters specified in the 
Schedule as are conferred on a General Manager of a railway administration under 
the Indian Railway Financial Code, Indian Railway Establishment Code, Railway 
Servants (Discipline and Appeal) Rules, 1968, Railway Servants (Conduct) Rules, 
1966, and Railway Servants (Pass) Rules, 1986: 
 Provided that the exercise of the financial powers shall be 
subject to any procedural or other instruc­tions issued from time to time by 
the Government and after obtaining the advice of the associated Financial 
Adviser and Chief Accounts Officer. </article><form>
 

THE RAILWAY CLAIMS TRIBUNAL 
(FINANCIAL AND ADMINISTRATIVE POWERS) RULES, 1989 
 

SCHEDULE 
 

1. Appointments and promotions against vacancies in respect of 
sanctioned posts. 
 

2. Grant of leave. 
 

3. Issue of passes. 
 

4. Establishment matters generally. 
 

5. Contingent expenditure within the amount allotted for this 
purpose in the sanctioned grant for each year. 
 

6. Re-appropriation from one sub-head to another. 
 

7. Write off of losses and deficiencies in stores. 
 

8. Disposal of worn out articles. 
 

9. Write off of losses of cash. 
 

10. Hiring of vehicles for official use. 
 

11. Sanction and write off of advances. 
 

12. Hiring of accommodation for official use. </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 8-11-1989,  vide  S.O. 
784(E), dated 5th October, 1989.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>