<act><title>
THE
NATIONAL ENVIRONMENT TRIBUNAL
ACT, 1995</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the National
Environment Tribunal Act, 1995. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It shall come into force on such date or dates as the Central Government may, by
notification, appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different States
and any reference in any provision of this Act to the commencement of this Act
shall be construed in relation to any State or part thereof as reference to the
coming into force of that provision in that State or part thereof.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section><number>a</number>
 “accident”
means an accident involving a fortuitous or sudden or unintended occurrence
while handling any hazardous substance resulting in continuous or intermittent
or repeated exposure to death of, or injury to, any person or damage to any
property or environment but does not include an accident by reason only of war
or radio-activity;
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
 “Bench” means
a Bench of the Tribunal;
 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
 “Chairperson”
means the Chairperson of the Tribunal;
 


 </section><section><number>d</number> “environment”
includes water, air and land and the inter-relationship which exists among and
between water, air and land, and human beings, other living creatures, plants,
micro-organism and property; 


 </section><section><number>e</number> “handling”, in
relation to any hazardous substance, means the manufacture, processing,
treatment, package, storage transportation by vehicle, use, collection,
destruction, conversion, offering for sale, transfer or the like of such
hazardous substance; 


 </section><section><number>f</number>
 “hazardous
substance” means any substance or preparation which is defined as hazardous
substance in the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986) and exceeding
such quantity as specified by the Central Government under the Public Liability
Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991); 


 </section><section><number>g</number> “Judicial
Members” means a Member of the Tribunal appointed as such under this Act, and
includes the Chairperson or a Vice-Chairperson who possesses any of the
qualifications specified in sub-section (3) of section 10; 


 </section><section><number>h</number> “Member” means
a Member (whether Judicial or Technical) of the Tribunal and includes the
Chairperson and a Vice-Chairperson; 


 </section><section><number>i</number>
 “notification”
means a notification published in the Official Gazette;
 


 </section><section><number>j</number>
 “prescribed”
means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 


 </section><section><number>k</number> “rules” means
the rules made under this Act;
 


 </section><section><number>l</number>
 “Technical
Member” means a Member of the Tribunal who is not a Judicial Member within the
meaning of clause (g);
 </section><section><number>m</number> “Tribunal”
means the National Environment Tribunal established under section 8;
 


 </section><section><number>n</number> “Vice-Chairperson”
means the Vice-Chairperson of the Tribunal.
 


 
Explanation.—In
the case of the Tribunal having two or more Vice-Chairpersons, references to the
Vice-Chairperson in this Act shall be construed as a reference to each of those
Vice-Chairpersons;
 


 </section><section><number>o</number> “owner” means
a person who owns, or has control over handling, any hazardous substance at the
time of accident and includes,—
 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
 in the case of a firm, any of its
partners; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
 in the case of an association, any
of its members; and 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
 in the case of a company, any of its
directors, managers, secretaries or other officers who is directly in charge of,
and is responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the
company. 
 

  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number>
Liability to pay compensation in certain cases on principle of no fault.—
<section><number>1</number> Where death of, or injury to, any person (other than a workman) or damage to
any property or environment has resulted from an accident, the owner shall be
liable to pay compensation for such death, injury or damage under all or any of
the heads specified in the Schedule.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In any claim for compensation under sub-section (1), the claimant shall not be
required to plead and establish that the death injury or damage in respect of
which the claim has been made was due to any wrongful act, neglect or default of
any person.
 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection><number>i</number> 
“workman” has the meaning assigned to it in the Workmen’s
Compensation Act, 1923;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> 
“injury” includes permanent total or permanent partial disability or
sickness resulting out of an accident.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
If the death, injury or damage caused by an accident cannot be attributed to any
individual activity but is the combined or resultant effect of several such
activities, operation and processes, the Tribunal may apportion the liability
for compensation amongst those responsible for such activities, operations and
processes on an equitable basis.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number>
Application for claim for compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for claim for
compensation may be made—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
 by the person who has sustained the
injury;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 by the owner of the property to
which the damage has been caused;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 where death has
resulted from the accident, by all or any of the legal representatives of the
deceased;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 by any agent duly authorised by such
person or owner of such property or all or any of the legal representatives of
the deceased, as the case may be;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 by any representative body or
organisation, functioning in the field environment and recognised in this behalf
by the Central Government, under all or any of the heads specified in the
Schedule; or
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
 by the Central Government or a State
Government or a local authority under all or any of the heads specified in the
Schedule:
 


 Provided
that where all the legal representatives of the deceased have not joined in any
such application for compensation, the application shall be made on behalf of or
for the benefit of all the legal representatives of the deceased and the legal
representatives who have not so joined shall be impleaded as respondents to the
application.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The Tribunal may, if it thinks fit, take up the cases for claims for
compensation suo motu.

 </section><section><number>3</number>
Any claimant making an application under sub-section (1) may also make an
application before the Tribunal for such relief as is provided in the Public
Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991): 
 

 Provided
that no such application shall be made if the relief has been received by the
claimant earlier or an application made by the claimant to the Collector under
the said Act is pending and has not been withdrawn. 
 

 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Tribunal shall have, and exercise, the same jurisdiction, powers and
authority in respect of the matters specified in the Public Liability Insurance
Act, 1991 (6 of 1991) as the Collector has and may exercise and, for this
purpose, the provisions of that Act shall have effect subject to the
modification that the references therein to the Collector shall be construed as
including a reference to the Tribunal. 
 

 </section><section><number>5</number>
Every application under sub-section (1) shall be made to the Tribunal and shall
contain such particulars and shall be accompanied by such documents and such
fee, not exceeding one thousand rupees, as may be prescribed: 
 

 Provided
that no fee shall be payable by a person whose annual income is below the
prescribed limit or by a representative body or organisation referred to in
clause (e) of sub-section (1) or by the Central Government, a State Government
or a local authority. 
 

 </section><section><number>6</number>
No application for compensation shall be entertained unless it is made within
five years of the occurrence of the accident. 
 

  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number>
Procedure and powers of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an application under
sub-section (1) of section 4, the Tribunal may, after such inquiry as it may
deem fit, reject the application summarily. 
 

 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where the Tribunal does not reject the application under sub-section (1), the
Tribunal may, after giving notice of the application to the owner and after
giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, hold an inquiry into the claim
or each of the claims and may make an award determining the amount of
compensation which appears to be just and specifying the person or persons to
whom such amount of compensation shall be paid. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the Code of Civil
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but shall be guided by the principles of natural
justice and, subject to the other provisions of this Act and of any rules, the
Tribunal shall have power to regulate its own procedure including the fixing of
places and times of its inquiry. 
 

 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Tribunal shall have, for the purpose of discharging its functions under this
Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the following
matters, namely:— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>
 summoning and enforcing the attendance of any
person and examining him on oath; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 requiring the discovery and production of
documents; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 receiving evidence on affidavits; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 subject to the provisions of sections 123 and
124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public
record or document or copy of such record or document from any office; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 issuing commissions for the examination of
witnesses or documents; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
 reviewing its decisions; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
 dismissing an application or default or
deciding it ex parte; 


 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
 setting aside any order of dismissal of any
application for default or any order passed by it ex parte; and 


 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
 any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed. 


  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number>
Conditions as to making of interim orders.—Notwithstanding anything
contained in any other provision of this Act or in any other law for the time
being in force, no interim order (whether by way of injunction or stay or in any
other manner) shall be made on, or in any proceedings relating to, an
application unless— 
 

 <section><number>a</number>
 copies of such application and of all
documents in support of the plea for such interim order are furnished to the
party against whom such application is made or proposed to be made; and
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
 opportunity is given to such party to be
heard in the matter:
 


 Provided
that the Tribunal may dispense with the requirements of clauses (a) and (b) and
make an interim order as an exceptional measure if it is satisfied for reasons
to be recorded in writing, that it is necessary so to do for preventing any loss
or damage being caused to the applicant which cannot be adequately compensated
in money but any such interim order shall, if it is not sooner vacated, cease to
have effect on the expiry of a period of fourteen days from the date on which it
is made unless the said requirements have been complied with before the expiry
of that period and the Tribunal has continued the operation of the interim
order. 
 

  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number>
Reduction of amount of relief paid under any other law.—Where in respect
of death of, or injury to, any person or damage to any property, the owner,
liable to pay compensation under this Act, is also liable to pay any amount as
relief under the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991) or any other
compensation under any other law, the amount of compensation payable under this
Act shall be reduced by the amount of relief and other compensation paid under
any other law. 
 

  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number>
Establishment of National Environment Tribunal.—The Central Government
shall, by notification, establish a Tribunal to be known as the National
Environment Tribunal, to exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority
conferred on it by or under this Act. 
 

  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number>
Composition of Tribunal and Benches thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal shall
consist of a Chairperson and such number of Vice-Chairpersons, Judicial Members
and Technical Members as the Central Government may deem fit and, subject to the
other provisions of this Act, the jurisdiction, powers and authority of the
Tribunal may be exercised by Benches thereof. 
 

 </section><section><number>2</number>
Subject to the other provisions of this Act, a Bench shall consist of one
Judicial Member and one Technical Member. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Chairperson— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>
 may, in addition to discharging the
functions of the Judicial Member or the Technical Member of the Bench to which
he is appointed, discharge the functions of the Judicial Member or, as the case
may be, the Technical Member, of any other Bench;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 may transfer the Vice-Chairperson or
other Member from one Bench to another Bench;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 may authorise the Vice-Chairperson
or the Judicial Member or the Technical Member appointed to one Bench to
discharge also the functions of the Vice-Chairperson or, as the case may be, the
Judicial Member or the Technical Member of another Bench; and 
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 may, for the purpose of securing
that any case or cases which, having regard to the nature of the questions
involved, requires or require, in his opinion or under the rules made by the
Central Government in this behalf, to be decided by a Bench composed of more
than two Members, issue such general or special orders, as he may deem fit:
 


 Provided
that every Bench constituted in pursuance of this clause shall include at least
one Judicial Member and one Technical Member. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this section
it shall be competent for the Chairperson or any other Member authorised by the
Chairperson in this behalf to function as a Bench consisting of a single Member
and exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority of the Tribunal in respect
of such classes of cases or such matters pertaining to such classes of cases as
the Chairperson may, by general or special order, specify: 
 

 Provided
that if at any stage of the hearing of any such case or matter, it appears to
the Chairperson or such Member that the case or matter is of such a nature that
it ought to be heard by a Bench consisting of two Members, the case or matter
may be transferred by the Chairperson or, as the case may be, referred to him
for transfer to such Bench as the Chairperson may deem fit. 
 

 </section><section><number>5</number>
Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Benches of the Tribunal shall
ordinarily sit at New Delhi (which shall be known as the principal Bench) and at
such other places as the Central Government may, by notification, specify. 
 

  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>10</number>
Qualifications for appointment as Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other Member.—
<section><number>1</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Chairperson unless he— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>
 is, or has been, a Judge of the
Supreme Court or a High Court; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 has, for at least two years, held
the office of Vice-Chairperson.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Vice-Chairperson unless
he— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>
 is, or has been, a Judge of a High
Court; or
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 has, for at least two years, held
the post of a Secretary to the Government of India or any other post under the
Central or a State Government carrying a scale of pay which is not less than
that of a Secretary to the Government of India; or
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
(i) has for at least five
years, held the post of an Additional Secretary to the Government of India or
any other post under the Central or  a State Government carrying a scale of
pay which is not less than that of an Additional Secretary to the Government of
India; and 
 

 <subsubsection><number>ii</number>
 has adequate knowledge of, or
experience in, legal, administrative, scientific or technical aspects of the
problems relating to environment; or 
 

 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 has, for at least three years, held
office as a Judicial Member or a Technical Member.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Judicial Member unless
he— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>
 is, or has been, or is qualified to
be, a Judge of a High Court; or
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 has been a member of the Indian
Legal Service and has held a post in grade I of that Service for at least three
years.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Technical Member unless he
has adequate knowledge of, or experience in, or capacity to deal with,
administrative, scientific or technical aspects of the problems relating to
environment. 
 

 </section><section><number>5</number>
Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (6) and (7) the Chairperson,
Vice-Chairperson and every other Member of the Tribunal shall be appointed by
the President. 
 

 </section><section><number>6</number>
No appointment of a person possessing the qualifications specified in this
section as the Chairperson or the Vice-Chairperson shall be made except after
consultation with the Chief Justice of India. 
 

 </section><section><number>7</number>
No appointment of a person as a Judicial Member or a Technical Member shall be
made except on the recommendation of a Selection Committee appointed by the
Central Government consisting of the following, namely:— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>   Chairperson
of the Tribunal;
Chairperson of the Committee, ex-officio;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   Secretary
to the Government 
member, ex-officio; 
of India 
in the Ministry of
 
            Environment and Forests;

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 Secretary
 to the Government    
member, ex-officio;


 
of
India in the Ministry of  

 
Law,
Justice and Company 
            Affairs
(Department of Legal Affairs);
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
Director-General, Council of 
member, ex-officio;
 
 
Scientific and Industrial Research;

 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 an Environmentalist to  be 
member. 
            nominated by the Central Government.
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Vice-Chairperson to act as Chairperson or to discharge his functions in certain circumstances. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In the event of the occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the Chairperson by reason of his death, resignation or otherwise, the Vice-Chairperson or, as the case may be, such one of the Vice-Chairpersons, as the Central Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf, shall act as the Chairperson until the date on which a new Chairperson, appointed in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill such vacancy, enters upon his office. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the Chairperson is unable to discharge his functions owing to absence, illness of any other cause, the Vice-Chairperson or, as the case may be, such one of the Vice-Chairpersons, as the Central Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf, shall discharge the functions of the Chairperson until the date on which the Chairperson resumes his duties. 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>12</number>
Term of office.—The Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson and other Member shall
hold office as such for a term of five years from the date on which he enters
upon his office, but shall be eligible for re-appointment for another term of
five years: 
 

 Provided
that no Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other Member shall hold office as such
after he has attained,— 
 

 <section><number>a</number>
 in the case of the Chairperson, the
age of seventy years;
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
 in the case of the Vice-Chairperson,
the age of sixty-five years; and
 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
 in the case of any other Member, the
age of sixty-two years.
 


  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>13</number>
Resignation and removal.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other
Member may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed to the President,
resign his office:
 Provided
that the Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other Member shall unless he is
permitted by the President to relinquish his office sooner, continue to hold
office until the expiry of three months from the date of receipt of such notice
or until a person duly appointed as his successor enters upon his office or
until the expiry of his term of office, whichever is the earliest.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or any other Member shall not be removed from
his office except by an order made by the President on the ground of proved
misbehaviour or incapacity after an inquiry made by a Judge of the Supreme Court
in which such Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other Member had been informed of
the charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in
respect of those charges.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for investigation
of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other
Member referred to in sub-section (2). 
 

  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>14</number>
Salaries and allowances and other terms and conditions of service of
Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson and other Members.—The salaries and
allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of service (including
pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the Chairperson,
Vice-Chairperson and other Member shall be such as may be prescribed: 
 

 Provided
that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of
service of the Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other Member shall be varied to
his disadvantage after his appointment. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>15</number>
Provision as to the holding of offices by Chairperson, etc., on ceasing to be
such Chairperson, etc.—On ceasing to hold office,— 
 <section><number>a</number>
 the Chairperson of the Tribunal
shall be ineligible for further employment either under the Government of India
or under the Government of a State;
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
 the Vice-Chairperson of the Tribunal
shall, subject to the other provisions of this Act, be eligible for appointment
as the Chairperson of the Tribunal, but not or any other employment either under
the Government of India or under the Government of a State;
 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
 a Member (other than the Chairperson
or Vice-Chairperson) of the Tribunal shall, subject to the other provisions of
this Act, be eligible for appointment as the Chairperson or Vice-Chairperson of
the Tribunal or as the Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or Member of any other
Tribunal, but not for any other employment either under the Government of India
or under the Government of a State;
 


 </section><section><number>d</number>
 the Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or
other Member shall not appear, act or plead before the Tribunal.
 


 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section, employment under the Government of India or under
the Government of a State includes employment under any local or other authority
within the territory of India or under the control of the Government of India or
under any corporation or society owned or controlled by the Government. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>16</number>
Financial and administrative powers of Chairperson.—The Chairperson shall
exercise such financial and administrative powers over the Benches as may be
vested in him under the rules: 
 Provided
that the Chairperson shall have authority to delegate such of his financial and
administrative powers as he may think fit to the Vice-Chairperson or any other
officer of the Tribunal subject to the condition that the Vice-Chairperson or
such officer shall, while exercising such delegated powers, continue to act
under the direction, control and supervision of the Chairperson. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>17</number>
Staff of the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall determine the
nature and categories of the officers and other employees required to assist the
Tribunal in the discharge of its functions and provide the Tribunal with such
officers and other employees as it may think fit. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The officers and other employees of the Tribunal shall discharge their functions
under the general superintendence of the Chairperson. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the officers and other
employees of the Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>18</number>
Distribution of business amongst the Benches.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any Benches of the
Tribunal are constituted, the Central Government may, from time to time, by
notification, make provisions as to the distribution of the business of the
Tribunal amongst the Benches and specify the matters which may be dealt with by
each Bench. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
If any question arises as to whether any matter falls within the purview of the
business allocated to a Bench, the decision of the Chairperson shall be final. 
 

 Explanation.—For
the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the expression “matters”
includes applications for interim relief. 
 
 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>19</number>
Bar of jurisdiction.—On and from the commencement of this Act, no court or
other authority except the Tribunal shall have, or be entitled to exercise, any
jurisdiction powers or authority to entertain any application or action for any
claim for compensation which may be entertained or dealt with by the Tribunal. 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>20</number>
Power of Chairperson to transfer cases from one Bench to another.—On the
application of any of the parties and after notice to the parties, and after
hearing such of them as he may desire to be heard, or on his own motion without
such notice, the Chairperson may transfer any case pending before one Bench, for
disposal, to any other Bench. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>21</number>
Decision to be taken by majority.—If the Members of a Bench differ in
opinion on any point, the point shall be decided according to the opinion of the
majority, if there is a majority, but if the Members are equally divided, they
shall state the point or points on which they differ, and make a reference to
the Chairperson who shall either hear the point or points himself or refer the
case for hearing on such point or points by one or more of the other Members and
such point or points shall be decided according to the opinion of the majority
of the Members who have heard the case including those who first heard it. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>22</number>
Deposit of amount payable for damage to environment.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any amount
of compensation is ordered to be paid under any award by the Tribunal on the
ground of any damage to environment, that amount shall be remitted to the
authority specified under sub-section (3) of section 7A of the Public Liability
Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991) for being credited to the Environmental Relief
Fund established under that section. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The amount of compensation credited to the Environmental Relief Fund under
sub-section (1) may be utilised by such person or authority, in such manner and
for such purposes of environment as may be prescribed. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>23</number>
Execution of award or order of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> An award made by the Tribunal
under this Act shall be executable by the Tribunal as a decree of civil court,
and for this purpose, the Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Tribunal may transmit
to the Collector having jurisdiction over the area in which the accident has
occurred the copy of the order made by it for payment of relief as provided in
the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991) and the Collector shall
execute the order in the same manner as if it were an order made by him under
that Act. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
Where the owner against whom the award or order is made by the Tribunal fails to
make the payment or deposit the amount as directed by the Tribunal within the
period specified in the award or order, such amount shall be recoverable from
the owner as arrears of land revenue or of public demand.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>24</number>
Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as provided in sub-section (2) and notwithstanding
anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) or in any
other law, an appeal shall lie against any award or other order, not being an
interlocutory order, of the Tribunal to the Supreme Court on one or more of the
grounds specified in section 100 of that Code. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No appeal shall lie against an award or other order made by the Tribunal with
the consent of the parties. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every appeal under this section shall be preferred within a period of ninety
days from the date of the award or other order appealed against: 
 

 Provided
that no appeal by the person who is required to pay any amount in terms of such
award shall be entertained by the Supreme Court unless he has deposited with it
the amount so awarded in the manner directed by the Supreme Court: 
 

 Provided
further that the Supreme Court may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the
said period of ninety days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented
by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal in time. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>25</number>
Penalty for failure to comply with orders of Tribunal.—Whoever fails to
comply with any order made by the Tribunal, he shall be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine which may
extend to ten lakh rupees, or with both. 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>26</number>
Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any offence under this Act has been
committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence was committed,
was directly in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct
of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be
guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against the punished
accordingly: 
 Provided
that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable
to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence was
committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to
prevent the commission of such offence. 
 

 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under
this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has
been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any
neglect on the part of, any director, manager secretary or other officer of the
company, such director, manager secretary or other officer shall also be deemed
to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and
published accordingly. 
 

 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section,— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>
 “company”
means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of
individuals; and
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 “director”, in
relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
 


  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>27</number>
Proceedings before the Tribunal to be judicial proceedings.—All
proceedings before the Tribunal shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings
within the meaning of sections 193, 219 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of
1860). 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>28</number>
Members and staff of Tribunal to be public servants.—The Chairperson,
Vice-Chairperson and other Members and the officers and other employees of the
Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21
of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>29</number>
Protection of action taken in good faith.—No suit, prosecution or other
legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or against the
Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other Member of the Tribunal or any other
person authorised by the Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson or other Member for
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this
Act or any rule or order made thereunder. 
  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Act to have overriding effect .—</title>Save as provided in the Public Liability Insurance Act, 1991 (6 of 1991), the provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in force or in any instrument having effected by virtue of any law other than this Act.
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>31</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification, make
rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 

 <subsection><number>a</number>
 the particulars which an application
shall contain, the documents and the fee which shall be accompanied with it and
the limit of annual income of a person so as to ennoble him to make application
without paying any fee, under sub-section (5) of section 4;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 any such matter in respect of which
the Tribunal shall have powers of a civil court, under clause (i) of sub-section
(4) of section 5;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 the case or cases which, having
regard to the nature of the questions involved, requires or require to be
decided by a Bench of more than two members, under clause (d) of sub-section (3)
of section 9;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 procedure for the
investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson, Vice-Chairperson
or other Member of the Tribunal under sub-section (3) of section 13;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 the salaries and allowances payable
to, and the other terms and conditions of service of, the Chairperson,
Vice-Chairperson and other Members under section 14;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
 financial and
administrative powers of the Chairperson over the Benches under section 16;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
 the salaries and allowances and
conditions of service of the officers and other employes of the Tribunal under
sub-section (3) of section 17;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
 the person or the authority by whom,
the manner in which and the purposes of environment for which the amount of
compensation credited to the Environmental Relief Fund shall be utilised under
sub-section (2) of section 22; and
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
 any other matter which is required
to be, or may be, prescribed.
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is
made, before each House of Parliament, which it is in session, for a total
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done
under that rules. 
 

  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE
NATIONAL ENVIRONMENT TRIBUNAL
ACT, 1995
 

 
 


THE
SCHEDULE
 


[See
Section 3 (1)]
 

HEADS
UNDER WHICH COMPENSATION FOR
DAMAGES MAY BE CLAIMED
 

 
 

(a)
 Death;
 

(b)
 Permanent,
temporary, total or partial disability or other injury or sickness;
 

(c)
 Loss of wages due to total or
partial disability or permanent or temporary disability;
 

(d)
 Medical expenses
incurred for treatment of injuries or sickness;
 

(e)
 Damages to private
property; 
 
 


 

(f)
 Expenses incurred
by the Government or any local authority in providing relief, aid and
rehabilitation to the affected persons;
 

(g)
 Expenses incurred
by Government for any administrative or legal action or to cope with any harm or
damage, including compensation for environmental degradation and restoration of
the quality of environment;
 

(h)
 Loss to Government or local
authority arising out of, or connected with, the activity causing any damage;
 

(i)
 Claims on account
of any harm, damage or destruction to the fauna including milch and draught
animals and aquatic fauna;
 

(j)
 Claims on account
of any harm, damage or destruction to flora including aquatic flora, crops,
vegetables, trees and orchards; 
 
 


 

(k)
 Claims including
cost of restoration on account of any harm or damage to environment including
pollution of soil, air, water, land and eco-systems;
 

(l)
 Loss and destruction of any property
other than private property;
 

(m)
 Loss of business or employment or
both; 
 
 


 

(n)
 Any other claim arising out of, or
connected with, any activity of handling of hazardous substance. 
 
 


 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>