<act><title>

The 
    Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 1948</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 
    1948. —(1) 
    This Act may be called the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 
    1948." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[except the State of Jammu and 
    Kashmir].
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— —In 
    this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—" 
 <section>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>   
    “Board” means a Dock Labour Board established under section 5A;]  
    2[(a) “Board” means a Dock Labour Board established 
    under section 5A;]" 
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number>]   “cargo” includes anything 
    carried or to be carried in a ship or other vessel;  
    3[(aa)] “cargo” includes anything carried or to be 
    carried in a ship or other vessel;" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “dock worker” means a person employed or 
    to be employed in, or in the vicinity of, any port on work in connection 
    with the loading, unloading, movement or storage of cargoes, or work in 
    connection with the preparation of ships or other vessels for the receipt or 
    discharge of cargoes or leaving port;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “employer”, in relation to a dock 
    worker, means the person by whom he is employed or to be employed as 
    aforesaid;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Government” means, in relation to any 
    major port, the Central Government and, in relation to any other port, the 
    State Government;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “scheme” means a scheme made under this 
    Act.
  
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Scheme for ensuring regular employment of workers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Provision may be made by a scheme for the registration of dock workers <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[and 
    employers] with a view to ensuring greater regularity of employment and for 
    regulating the employment of dock workers, whether registered or not, in a 
    port. —(1) 
    Provision may be made by a scheme for the registration of dock workers
    

    4[and employers] with 
    a view to ensuring greater regularity of employment and for regulating the 
    employment of dock workers, whether registered or not, in a port." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, a scheme may provide—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   for the application of the scheme to 
    such classes of dock workers and employers as may be specified therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   for defining the obligations of dock 
    workers and employers subject to the fulfilment of which the scheme may 
    apply to them and the circumstances in which the scheme shall cease to apply 
    to any dock workers or employers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   for regulating the recruitment and entry 
    into the scheme of dock workers, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[and the registration of dock 
    workers and employers], including the maintenance of registers, the removal 
    either temporarily or permanently, of names from the registers and the 
    imposition of fees for registration;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   for regulating the employment of dock 
    workers, whether registered or not, and the terms and conditions of such 
    employment, including rates of remuneration, hours of work and conditions as 
    to holidays and pay in respect thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   for securing that, in respect of periods 
    during which employment, or full employment, is not available for dock 
    workers to whom the scheme applies and who are available for work, such 
    workers will, subject to the conditions of the scheme, receive a minimum 
    pay;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   for prohibiting, restricting or 
    otherwise controlling the employment of dock workers to whom the scheme does 
    not apply and the employment of dock workers by employers to whom the scheme 
    does not apply;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>ff</number>   for creating such fund or 
    funds as may be necessary or expedient for the purposes of the scheme and 
    for the administration of such fund or funds;]  
    2[(ff) for creating such fund or funds as may be 
    necessary or expedient for the purposes of the scheme and for the 
    administration of such fund or funds;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   for the training <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[***] of 
    dock workers, in so far as satisfactory provision therefor does not exist 
    apart from the scheme;
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>gg</number>   for the welfare of the 
    officers and other staff of the Board;]
 
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[***] 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   for the manner in which, and the persons 
    by whom, the cost of operating the scheme is to be defrayed;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>j</number>   
    for constituting <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[***] the authority to be responsible for the 
    administration of the scheme;] 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>k</number>   for such incidental and supplementary 
    matters as may be necessary or expedient for the purposes of the scheme.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    scheme may further provide that a contravention of any provision thereof 
    shall be punishable with imprisonment for such term as may be specified but 
    in no case exceeding three months in respect of a first contravention or six 
    months in respect of any subsequent contravention, or with fine which may 
    extend to such amount as may be specified but in no case exceeding five 
    hundred rupees in respect of a first contravention or one thousand rupees in 
    respect of any subsequent contravention, or with both imprisonment and fine 
    as aforesaid.
  












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Making, variation and revocation of schemes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to 
    the condition of previous publication, make one or more schemes for a port 
    or group of ports, and may in the like manner and subject to the like 
    condition add to, amend, vary or revoke any scheme made by it. —(1) 
    The Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to 
    the condition of previous publication, make one or more schemes for a port 
    or group of ports, and may in the like manner and subject to the like 
    condition add to, amend, vary or revoke any scheme made by it." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of section 23 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), 
    shall apply to the exercise of a power given by sub-section (1) as they 
    apply to the exercise of a power given by a Central Act to make rules 
    subject to the condition of previous publication.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Government may direct the port authority of any port to prepare, in 
    accordance with such instructions as may from time to time be given to it, 
    one or more draft schemes for the port, and the port authority shall comply 
    with such direction.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Advisory Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Government may, or if it decides to make any scheme under section 4, 
    shall, constitute an Advisory Committee, to advise upon such matters arising 
    out of the administration of this Act or any scheme made thereunder as the 
    Government may refer to it for advice. —(1) 
    The Government may, or if it decides to make any scheme under section 4, 
    shall, constitute an Advisory Committee, to advise upon such matters arising 
    out of the administration of this Act or any scheme made thereunder as the 
    Government may refer to it for advice." 
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    The members of the Advisory Committee shall be appointed by the Government 
    and shall be of such number and chosen in such manner as may be prescribed 
    by rules made under this Act: 1[(2) 
    The members of the Advisory Committee shall be appointed by the Government 
    and shall be of such number and chosen in such manner as may be prescribed 
    by rules made under this Act\:" 
 
Provided 
    that the Advisory Committee shall include an equal number of members 
    representing—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the Government,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the dock workers, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the employers of dock workers, and 
    shipping companies.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman of the Advisory Committee shall be one of the members appointed to 
    represent the Government, nominated in this behalf by the Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Government shall publish in the Official Gazette the names of all members of 
    the Advisory Committee.
 
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[***] 
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>5A</number> 
    Dock Labour Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, establish a Dock Labour Board for a port or group of ports 
    to be known by such name as may be specified in the notification. 1[5A. 
    Dock Labour Board.—(1) The Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, establish a Dock Labour Board for a port or group of ports 
    to be known by such name as may be specified in the notification." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every such Board shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid, having 
    perpetual succession and a common seal with power to acquire, hold and 
    dispose of property and to contract and may, by that name, sue and be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every such Board shall consist of a Chairman and such number of other 
    members as may be appointed by the Government:
 
Provided 
    that every such Board shall include an equal number of members representing—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the Government,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the dock workers, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the employers of dock workers, and 
    shipping companies.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Chairman of a Board shall be one of the members appointed to represent the 
    Government, and nominated in this behalf by the Government.]
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>5B</number> 
    Functions of a Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Board shall be responsible for administering the scheme for the port or 
    group of ports for which it has been established and shall exercise such 
    powers and perform such functions as may be conferred on it by the scheme.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the exercise of its powers and the discharge of its functions, a Board shall 
    be bound by such directions as the Government may, for reasons to be stated 
    in writing, give to it from time to time.]
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>5C</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Board shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts, including a balance-sheet in such 
    form as may be prescribed by rules made under this Act. —(1) 
    Every Board shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts, including a balance-sheet in such 
    form as may be prescribed by rules made under this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Board shall be audited annually by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor General of India or by such other auditors qualified to act as 
    auditors of companies under the law for the time being in force relating to 
    companies, as the Government may appoint.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    auditors shall, at all reasonable times, have access to the books of 
    accounts and other documents of the Board and may, for the purposes of the 
    audit, call for such explanation and information as they may require or 
    examine any member or officer of the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    auditors shall forward to the Government a copy of their report together 
    with an audited copy of the accounts of the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    cost of the audit as determined by the Government shall be paid out of the 
    funds of the Board.] 
 





 



</section></article> 
 <title>THE DOCK WORKERS (REGULATION OF EMPLOYMENT) ACT, 1948 </title>
  
 <article><footcitenum>17</footcitenum> [ <title><number>5D</number> Annual report. </title>—Every Board shall prepare, in such form and at such time in each financial year as may be specified by rules made under this Act, its annual report, giving full accounts of its activities during the previous financial year, and submit a copy thereof to the Government. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>5E</number> Annual report and audited accounts, to be laid before Parliament or Legislature. </title>—The annual report, and the audited accounts of the Board, together with auditor's report thereon and a review by the Government on the working of the Board, shall, within a period of nine months of the close of the financial year, be laid before each House of Parliament, if such report and accounts have been submitted to the Central Government, and before the Legislature of the State, if such report and accounts have been submitted to the State Government: 
 Provided that where such report, accounts and the review are not laid before Parliament or, as the case may be, before the Legislature of the State within the said period, the same shall be so laid thereafter along with the reasons for the delay.] 


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such 
    persons as it thinks fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act at 
    such ports as may be specified in the notification. —(1) 
    The Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint such 
    persons as it thinks fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act at 
    such ports as may be specified in the notification." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of 
    the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    Inspector may, at any port for which he is appointed,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   enter, with such assistance (if any) as 
    he thinks fit, any premises or vessel where dock workers are employed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   require any authority or person to 
    produce any register, muster-roll or other document relating to the 
    employment of dock workers, and examine such document;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   take on the spot or otherwise the 
    evidence of any person for the purpose of ascertaining whether the 
    provisions of any scheme made for the port are, or have been, complied with.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, prescribed the 
    manner in which and the persons by whom complaints regarding contravention 
    of any provision of a scheme may be made to an Inspector and the duties of 
    the Inspector in relation to such complaints.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>6A</number> 
    Power to order inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> The Government may, at any time, appoint any 
    person to investigate or inquire into the working of a Board and submit a 
    report to the Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall give to the person so appointed all facilities for the proper 
    conduct of the investigation or inquiry and furnish to him such documents, 
    accounts or information in the possession of the Board as he may require.]
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>6B</number> 
    Power to supersede a Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, on consideration of the report under section 6A or otherwise, the 
    Government is of opinion— —(1) 
    If, on consideration of the report under section 6A or otherwise, the 
    Government is of opinion—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that, on account of a grave emergency, a 
    Board is unable to perform its functions, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that a Board has persistently made 
    default in the discharge of its functions or has exceeded or abused its 
    powers,
 
the Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, supersede the Board for such period as may be specified in 
    the notification:
 
Provided 
    that, before issuing a notification under this sub-section on any of the 
    grounds mentioned in clause (b), the Government shall give a reasonable 
    opportunity to the Board to show cause why it should not be superseded and 
    shall consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the Board.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the publication of a notification under sub-section (1),—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   all the members of the Board shall, as 
    from the date of such publication, vacate their offices as such members;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   all the powers and functions which may 
    be exercised or performed by the Board shall, during the period of 
    supersession, be exercised or performed by such person as may be specified 
    in the notification;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   all funds and other property vested in 
    the Board shall, during the period of supersession, vest in the Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification 
    issued under sub-section (1), the Government may—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   extend the period of supersession for 
    such further period as it may consider necessary; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   re-establish the Board in the manner 
    provided in section 5A.]
  







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>6C</number> Acts or proceeding of Board and Advisory Committee 
      not to be invalidated.—No act or proceeding of a Board or the Advisory 
      Committee shall be invalid merely by reason of—
 <section><number>a</number>   any vacancy in, or 
      any defect in the constitution of, the Board or the Advisory Committee, 
      or
 </section><section><number>b</number>   any defect in the 
      appointment of a person acting as a member of the Board or the Advisory 
      Committee, or
 </section><section><number>c</number>   any irregularity 
      in the procedure of the Board or the Advisory Committee not affecting the 
      merits of the case.] 
  



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No Court shall take cognizance of any offence made punishable by a scheme or 
    of any abetment thereof, except on a report in writing of the facts 
    constituting such offence or abetment made by an Inspector or by a person 
    specially authorised in this behalf by the Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure 1898<footcitenum>22</footcitenum> (5 
    of 1898), an offence made punishable by a scheme or an abetment thereof 
    shall be triable only by a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the 
    first class.
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[<number>7A</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> If the person committing an offence made 
    punishable by a scheme or any abetment thereof is a company, every person 
    who, at the time the offence or abetment was committed, was in charge of, 
    and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the 
    company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence 
    or abetment and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly: 2[7A. 
    Offences by companies.—(1) If the person committing an offence made 
    punishable by a scheme or any abetment thereof is a company, every person 
    who, at the time the offence or abetment was committed, was in charge of, 
    and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the 
    company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence 
    or abetment and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly\:" 
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence or abetment was 
    committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to 
    prevent the commission of such offence or abetment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence made 
    punishable by a scheme or any abetment thereof has been committed by a 
    company and it is proved that the offence or abetment has been committed 
    with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the 
    part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, 
    such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
    be guilty of that offence or abetment and shall be liable to be proceeded 
    against and punished accordingly.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm and other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a firm, means 
    a partner in the firm.] 
  






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the provisions of this Act. 3[8. 
    Power to make rules.—(1) The Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the provisions of this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the forgoing power, 
    such rules may provide for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the compositions of the Advisory 
    Committee and Boards and the manner in which members of the Advisory 
    Committee and the Boards shall be chosen;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the term of office of, and the manner of 
    filling casual vacancies among the members of a Board or the Advisory 
    Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the meetings of a Board and the Advisory 
    Committee, the quorum for such meetings and the conduct of business thereat;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the conditions subject to which, and the 
    mode in which, contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of a Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the allowances, if any, payable to the 
    members of a Board or the Advisory Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the disqualifications for membership of 
    a Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the form in which a Board shall prepare 
    its annual statement of accounts and the balance-sheet.
 
<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[***] 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>8A</number> 
    Schemes and rules to be laid before Parliament.—Every scheme and every 
    rule made under this Act by the Central Government shall be laid, as soon as 
    may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the scheme or 
    rule or both Houses agree that the scheme or rule should not be made, the 
    scheme or rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be 
    of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
    annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously 
    done under that scheme or rule.] 
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Saving.—Every 
    Dock Labour Board established for a port or a group of ports before the 
    commencement of the Dock Workers (Regulation of Employment) Amendment Act, 
    1962 (8 of 1962), under a scheme made under section 4, and functioning as 
    such immediately before such commencement shall be deemed to be a Board 
    established under section 5A and, accordingly, all the provisions of this 
    Act shall apply to every such Board.
 


 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “except Part B States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1962, 
    sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Clause (a) re-lettered 
    as clause (aa) by Act 8 of 1962, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1962, 
    sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by Act 8 of 
    1962, sec. 3, for “and their registration” (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by Act 49 of 
    1980, sec. 2 (retrospectively).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   The words “and 
    welfare” omitted by Act 54 of 1986, sec. 23 (w.e.f. 15-4-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Ins. by Act 31 of 
    1970, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Clause (h) omitted by 
    Act 54 of 1986, sec. 23 (w.e.f. 15-4-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    1949, sec. 2, for clause (j).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   The words “whether as 
    a body corporate or otherwise” omitted by Act 8 of 1962, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
    1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs.  by Act 8 of 
    1962, sec. 4, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Sub-section (5) 
    omitted by Act 8 of 1962, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   
    Ins.  by Act 8 of 1962, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   
    Ins.  by Act 8 of 1962, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   
    Ins.  by Act 8 of 1962, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1988, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Ins. by Act 56 of 1988, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1962, 
    sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1962, 
    sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1962, 
      sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   See now the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).  tc 
    "  1. See 
    now the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Ins. by Act 31 of 
    1970, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Ins. by Act 8 of 1962, 
    sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-6-1962).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Sub-section (3) 
    omitted by Act 49 of 1980, sec. 4.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Ins. by Act 49 of 
    1980, sec. 5.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>