<act><title>

    The ANTI-APARTHEID 
    (United Nations convention) act, 1981</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may 
    be called the Anti-Apartheid (United Nations Convention) Act, 1981.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Application of the International Convention on the suppression and 
    punishment of the crime of Apartheid.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law, such of 
    the provisions of the International Convention on the Suppression and 
    Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid as are set out in the Schedule 
    shall have the force of law in India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Government may, from time to time, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    amend the Schedule in conformity with any amendments, duly made and adopted, 
    of the provisions of the said Convention set out therein.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    notification issued under sub-section (2) shall be laid, as soon as may be 
    after it is issued, before each House of Parliament.

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Punishment for international criminal responsibility.—Every 
    person to whom international criminal responsibility applies under article 
    III of the said Convention, as set out in the Schedule, shall be punished 
    with death, or imprisonment for life, or imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to ten years, and shall also be liable to fine.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, the reference in clause 
<section><number>a</number> of article III of 
    the said Convention to “article II” shall be construed as a reference to the 
    provisions of article II of that Convention as set out in the Schedule.

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Offences 
    by companies, organisations or institutions.—Where 
    an offence under this Act has been committed by a company or an organisation 
    or an institution, every person who, at the time the offence was committed, 
    was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company, organisation or 
    institution, as the case may be, for the conduct of its business or affairs, 
    shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
    proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this section shall render any such person liable to any 
    punishment provided in this Act if he proves that the offence was committed 
    without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals.

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Place of 
    trial.—Any person committing an 
    offence under section 3 may be tried for the offence in any place in which 
    he may be found or in such other place as the Central Government may, by 
    general or special order, published in the Official Gazette, direct in this 
    behalf.

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Previous 
    sanction of the Central Government for arrest or prosecution.—No 
    person shall be arrested or prosecuted in respect of any offence under 
    section 3 except with the previous sanction of the Central Government or 
    such officer or authority as may be authorised by that Government by order 
    in writing in this behalf.

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number> Provisions as to Extradition 
      Act.—For the purposes of the 
      Extradition Act, 1962 (34 of  1962), the offence under section 3 
      shall not be considered to be an offence of a political 
      character.
  </article><form>
 

THE ANTI-APARTHEID 
  (UNITED NATIONS CONVENTION) ACT, 1981 
 

 
 

The Schedule 
 

( See  sections 2 and 3) 
 

Provisions of the International Convention on the Suppression and Punishment of the Crime of Apartheid  

  which shall have force of Law 
 

* * * * * 
 

Article II 
 

For the purpose of the present Convention, the term “the crime of apartheid ”, which shall include similar policies and practices of racial segregation and discrimination as practised in southern Africa, shall apply to the following inhuman acts committed for the purpose of establishing and maintaining domination by one racial group of persons over any other racial group of persons and systematically oppressing them: 
 

(a) Denial to a member or members of a racial group or groups of the right to life and liberty of person: 
 

(i) By murder of members of a racial group or groups; 
 

(ii) By the infliction upon the members of a racial group or groups of serious bodily or mental harm, by the infringement of their freedom or dignity, or by subjecting them to torture or to cruel, inhuman or degrading treatment or punishment; 
 

(iii) By arbitrary arrest and illegal imprisonment of the members of a racial group or groups; 
 

(b) Deliberate imposition on a racial group or groups of living conditions calculated to cause its or their physical destruction in whole or in part; 
 

* * * * * 
 

(e) Exploitation of the labour of the members of a racial group or groups, in particular by submitting them to forced labour; 
 

(f) Persecution of organisations and persons, by depriving them of fundamental rights and freedoms, because they oppose apartheid . 
 

Article III 
 

International criminal responsibility shall apply, irrespective of the motive involved, to individuals, members of organizations and institutions and representatives of the State, whether residing in the territory of the State in which the acts are perpetrated or in some other State, whenever they: 
 

(a) Commit, participate in, directly incite or conspire in the commission of the acts mentioned in article II of the present Convention; 
 

(b) Directly abet, encourage or co-operate in the commission of the crime of apartheid . 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>