<act><tid>1152907</tid>
<title>THE DELHI MOTOR VEHICLES TAXATION ACT, <year>1962</year></title>

ACT NO. 57 OF <year>1962</year>
[ 15th December, <year>1902</year>]

An Act to impose a tax on motor vehicles in the Union territory 
of Delhi and for other matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirteenth year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1525903</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>92652</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Delhi Motor Vehicles Taxation Act, <year>1962</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1638695</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Delhi.

</section>

<section><tid>1936396</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the[ Administrator] 2 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1743259</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires--
<section><tid>705655</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Administrator" means the Administrator of Delhi 
appointed by the president under article 239 of the 
Constitution:]

</section>

<section><tid>507827</tid>
<number>b</number>" Delhi" means the Union territory of Delhi;

</section>

<section><tid>51169</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1563692</tid>
<number>d</number>" quarter" means.. a period of three months commencing 
on the first day of April, the first day of July, the first 
day of October or the first day of January in each year;

</section>

<section><tid>317411</tid>
<number>e</number>registered owner" means the person in whose name a motor 
vehicle is registered under the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year>; (4  
  of <year>1939</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>1154821</tid>
<number>f</number>" tax" means the tax levied under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1899357</tid>
<number>g</number>" taxation authority" means any person or authority 
appointed by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Administrator] by notification in the 
Official Gazette to exercise' the powers and perform' the 
duties conferred or imposed upon a taxation authority by or 
under. this Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>402</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st April <year>1963</year>; vide Notification No. P. 21 (5) 63-PR (T), dated 
29- 3- <year>1963</year>, Delhi Gazette Extraordinary, Pt. IV, p. 283.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 17 of <year>1983</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1983</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by S. 3 ibid (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1983</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1370356</tid>
<number>h</number>" token of means a ticket to be displayed on A motor 
vehicle as an indication that the tax has been duly paid or 
that no tax is payable;

</section>

<section><tid>1368344</tid>
<number>i</number>" Year" means the financial year;

</section>

<section><tid>1281471</tid>
<number>j</number>all words and expressions used, but not, defined in 
this Act, and defined in the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year>, (4 of  
  <year>1939</year>) shall have the, 4 of meanings respectively assigned to 
them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>991785</tid>
<number> 3</number> Lavy of tax. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>236119</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions of this  
Act, on and from the commencement of the Delhi Motor Vehicles Taxation 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1989</year>, there shall be levied and collected on

<subsection><tid>1438309</tid>
<number>a</number>all motor vehicles described in column (1) of Part A of 
Schedule I and used or kept for use in Delhi, a tax at the 
rate specified in the corresponding entry in column (2) of 
the said Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1964197</tid>
<number>b</number>all motor vehicles described in column (1) of Part B of 
Schedule I and used or kept for use in Delhi

<subsubsection><tid>1927246</tid>
<number>i</number>on their first registration in Delhi, a one time tax at 
the amount specified in the corresponding entry in column (2) 
of the said Part;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1855451</tid>
<number>ii</number>the same having been earlier registered in Delhi or in 
any other State, then having regard to the month of their 
first registration in Delhi or, as the case may be, in that 
other State, a one time tax at the amount specified in the 
respective columns (3) to (14) of Part C of Schedule I:
Provided that where such motor vehicles are more than ten years 
old from the date of their first registration, the owners thereof 
shall present the registration certificates of such motor vehicles to 
the taxation authority for an endorsement therein to the effect that 
the motor vehicles are more than ten years old and their use or 
keeping for use in Delhi do not attract any tax.]

 2 (2) The Administrator may, by notification in the official 
Gazette, increase from time to time, the rate specified in Schedule I 
in relation to any motor vehicles:

Provided that the rate as so increased shall in no case exceed 
the rate as so specified by more than twenty- five per cent thereof:]

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided further that any such increase shall not apply in 
respect of a motor vehicle specified in part B of Schedule I on which 
one time tax has been levied and collected."]




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1369353</tid>
<number> 4</number> Declaration and payment of tax.
<section><tid>1175293</tid>
<number>1</number>Every registered owner  
or person having possession or, control of a motor vehicle used or 
kept for use in Delhi shall fill up, and sign a declaration in the 
prescribed form stating the prescribed particulars and shall deliver 
the same to the taxation authority within the prescribed time.

</section>

<section><tid>659008</tid>
<number>2</number>The tax to which a registered owner or person having pos- 
session or control of a motor vehicle appears by such declaration to 
be liable under section 3 shall be paid by him,-

<subsection><tid>1846012</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> where such vehicle is described in Part A of Schedule I,-

<subsubsection><tid>494804</tid>
<number>i</number>for a year at the rate specified in the corresponding 
entry in column (2) thereof (hereinafter referred to as the  
  annual rate); or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>838200</tid>
<number>ii</number>for one or more quarters, at one- fourth of the annual 
rate fox each quarter; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>363960</tid>
<number>iii</number>for any period less than a quarter expiring on the last 
day of the quarter, at one- twelfth of the annual rate for 
each complete month or part thereof included in such period; 
or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>184537</tid>
<number>b</number>where such vehicle is described in Part B of Schedule I, 
a one time tax at the amount specified in the corresponding 
entry in column (2) in the said Part or, as the case may be, 
the amount specified in the respective columns in Part C.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>772470</tid>
<number>3</number>The tax shall be paid within such time and in such manner 
as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1625951</tid>
<number>4</number>In calculating the tax due for any period less than one year, 
fraction of a rupee shall be counted as a rupee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1104319</tid>
<number> 5</number> Issue of token.
<section><tid>232825</tid>
<number>1</number>When a person pays the amount of tax  
leviable under section 3 in respect of any motor vehicle or proves to 
the satisfaction of the taxation authority that no such tax is payable 
In respect of such vehicle, the taxation authority shall,-

<subsection><tid>1032855</tid>
<number>a</number>issue to such person a token in the prescribed form 
specifying therein the period for which such tax has been 
paid or that no such, tax is payable, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>403</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1969</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 4- 69) renumbered.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 17 of <year>1983</year>, S. 4 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1983</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. and added by Act 25 of <year>1989</year> S. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1990</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by S. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1990</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1406431</tid>
<number>b</number>specify in the certificate of registration granted, in 
respect of the vehicle under the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year>, (4  
  of <year>1939</year>), or in the case of vehicles not registered under 
that Act, in a certificate in such form As may be prescribed, 
that the tax has been, paid for the period specified under 
clause (a) or that no tax is payable. in respect of that 
vehicle, as the case may be;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>530988</tid>
<number>2</number>No motor vehicle liable to tax under this Act shall be used 
or kept for use in DEW unless the registered owner or the person 
having possession or control of ouch vehicle has obtained a valid 
token in respect of that vehicle, and that token is displayed on the 
vehicle in the prescribed manner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1791155</tid>
<number> 6</number> Additional declaration.
<section><tid>995365</tid>
<number>1</number>When a motor vehicle used or kept  
for use in Delhi is altered or is proposed to be used in such manner 
as to render the registered owner or the person who has possession or 
control such vehicle liable to the payment of additional tax under 
section 7, such owner or person shall fill up, sign and deliver in the 
manner provided in sub- section (2), an additional declaration and 
shall along with such additional declaration (accompanied by the  
  certificate of registration in respect of such motor vehicle), pay to 
the taxation authority an additional tax payable under that section 
which he appears by such additional declaration to be liable to in 
respect of such vehicle.

</section>

<section><tid>179756</tid>
<number>2</number>The additional declaration shall be in the prescribed form 
containing the prescribed particulars and shall be delivered to the 
taxation authority after being duly filled up and signed within the 
prescribed time. The additional declaration shall indicate clearly 
also the nature of alteration made in the motor vehicle or, as the 
case may be, the altered use to which the vehicle is proposed to put.

</section>

<section><tid>1198395</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of the additional tax under sub- section (1), the 
taxation authority shall issue to the registered owner or the personal 
who has possession or control of the vehicle, a fresh taken in place I 
of the original token and shall cause an entry of such payment to be 
made in the certificate of registration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1485121</tid>
<number>7</number>Liability for additional tax. When any motor vehicle in respect 
of which a tax for any period is payable or has been paid, is altered 
during such period, or proposed to be used during such period in such 
manner, as, to, cause the vehicle to become a vehicle in respect of 
which a higher rate of tax is payable, the registered owner or the 
person who hap possession or control of the vehicle, shall in addition 
to the tax. if any, due from him for that period, be liable to pay for 
the unexpired portion of such period since the vehicle is altered or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>404</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

proposed to be used, an additional tax of a sum equal to the 
difference between the amount of tax payable for such unexpired 
portion at the higher rate and the rate at which the tax was payable 
or paid before the alteration or use of the vehicle for that portion; 
and until such additional tax has been paid, the taxation authority 
shall not grant a fresh token in respect of the vehicle so altered or 
proposed to be so used.

Explanation.- In calculating the unexpired portion under this 
section any broken period in a month shall be considered as a full 
month.



</article>



<article><tid>44748</tid>
<number>8</number>Production of certificate of insurance. Every registered owner 
or person having possession or control of a motor vehicle shall, at 
the time of making payment of the tax, produce before the taxation 
authority a valid certificate of insurance in respect of the vehicle 
complying with the requirements of Chapter VIII of the Motor Vehicles 
Act, <year>1939</year>. (4 of <year>1939</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>70697</tid>
<number> 9</number> Liability to pay arrears of tax of person succeeding to the 
ownership, possession or control of motor vehicles.
<section><tid>1309410</tid>
<number>1</number>If the tax  
leviable in respect of any motor vehicle remains unpaid by any person 
liable for payment thereof and such person before having paid the tax 
has transferred the ownership of such vehicle or has ceased to be in 
possession or control of such vehicle, the person to whom the 
ownership of the vehicle has been transferred or the person who has 
possession or control of such vehicle shall be liable to pay the said 
tax to the taxation authority.

</section>

<section><tid>73936</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to affect 
the liability to pay the said tax of the person who has transferred 
the ownership or has ceased to be in possession or control of such 
vehicle.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1341926</tid>
<number> 10</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Refund of tax.
<section><tid>847139</tid>
<number>1</number>When any person who has paid the tax in  
respect of a motor vehicle produces before the taxation authority a 
certificate signed by the registering authority stating that the tax 
token and the certificate of registration issued in respect of such 
vehicle have been surrendered on the date specified by the registering 
authority in his certificate, such person shall, on an application 
made in that behalf to the taxation authority and subject to such 
conditions is may be prescribed, be entitled to a refund,--

<subsection><tid>1541283</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case where payment of tax has been made in accord- 
ance with clause (a) of subsection (2) of section 4, for each 
complete month of the period for which such tax has been paid 
and which is unexpired on the date on which the tax token and 
the certificate of registration were surrendered, of an 
amount equal to one- twelfth of the annual tax payable in 
respect of such vehicle; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1936284</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where payment of tax has been made in accord- 
ance with clause (b) of sub- section (2) of section 4, at the 
rates specified in Schedule IA.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1948663</tid>
<number>2</number>When any person has paid the tax in respect of a motor 
vehicle and the vehicle is removed outside Delhi before the expiry of 
the period for which the tax has been paid and taxed in another State 
or the registration of such vehicle is cancelled before the expiry of 
the period for which the tax has been paid, such person shall, on an 
application made in that behalf to the taxation authority and subject 
to such conditions as may be prescribed, be entitled to a refund,-

<subsection><tid>1942205</tid>
<number>a</number>in a case where payment of tax has been made in ac- 
cordance with clause (a) of sub- section (2) of section 4, for 
each complete month of the period for which such tax has been 
paid, and during which the vehicle was removed from Delhi or 
such vehicle' s registration is cancelled, of an amount equal 
to one- twelfth of the annual tax payable in respect of such 
vehicle; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1311355</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where payment of tax has been made in ac- 
cordance with clause (b) of Sub- section (2) of section 4, at 
the rates specified in Schedule IB.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>471971</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the rates of tax leviable under Part B of Schedule I 
are increased by notification in the Official Gazette under. sub- 
section (2) of section 3, the Administrator may, from time to time, by 
the same notification or by a separate notification in the official 
Gazette, correspondingly increase the rates of refund payable under 
this section and the refund of tax payable, in respect of the vehicles 
registered on or after the date of such notification shall be at such 
increase rates."]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>405</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1989</year>, S. 4 (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1990</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1717521</tid>
<number>11</number>Penalty payable when tax not paid. When any registered owner 
or any person who has possession or control of any motor vehicle used 
or kept for use in Delhi is in default in making a payment of the tax 
the taxation authority may direct that, in addition to the amount of 
arrears, a sum not exceeding the annual tax payable in respect of such 
vehicle shall be recovered from him by way of penalty:
Provided that before giving any such direction the registered 
owner or such person shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard.



</article>



<article><tid>1317680</tid>
<number> 12</number> Arrears of tax and penalty recoverable as arrears of land 
revenue.
<section><tid>931483</tid>
<number>1</number>Any tax due and not paid as provided for by or under this  
Act and any sum directed to be recovered by way of penalty under 
section 11 shall be recoverable in the same manner as an arrear of 
land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>1578844</tid>
<number>2</number>The motor vehicle in respect of which the tax is due or in 
respect of which any sum has been directed to be recovered as penalty 
under section 11, or its accessories may be distrained and sold in 
pursuance of this section whether or not such vehicle or accessories 
is or are in the possession or control of the person liable to pay the 
tax or penalty.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1678253</tid>
<number> 13</number> Exemptions.
<section><tid>461536</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the registered owner or the person  
having possession or control of a motor vehicle is an agriculturist 
and that motor vehicle has been designed for agricultural operations 
and is used solely for such operations in relation to his own'. and 
then, that vehicle shall be exempt from the payment of the tax.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section the expression 
" agricultural operations" includes,-


<subsection><tid>773157</tid>
<number>i</number>tilling, sowing, harvesting, crushing of any agricultural 
produce or any other similar operation carried out for the 
purpose of agriculture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>888505</tid>
<number>ii</number>transport of manure, seeds, insecticides and other like 
articles required for work in the land from the market to the 
land; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>406</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1605522</tid>
<number>iii</number>transport of any agricultural produce from the land to 
the place of storage or from the place of storage to the 
market.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>230303</tid>
<number>2</number>When the registered owner or the person having possession or 
control of a motor vehicle has given previous intimation in writing to 
the taxation authority that the motor vehicle would not be used in any 
public place for a particular period, being not less than one month, 
and deposits the certificate of registration of such motor vehicle 
with the taxation authority and obtains an acknowledgment therefor 
from that authority, he shall be exempt from the payment of the tax 
for that period.

</section>

<section><tid>565441</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Administrator] is of opinion that it is neces- 
sary or expedient in the public interest so to do, he may, by notifi- 
cation in the Official Gazette, and subject to such conditions as he 
may specify in the notification, exempt either totally or partially 
any class of motor vehicles other than those falling under sub- section 
 (1) or any motor vehicles belonging to any class of persons from the 
payment of the tax.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1169014</tid>
<number> 14</number> Reduction of tax in cases of certain motor vehicles. Where 
the registered owner of a motor vehicle used or kept for use in Delhi 
is a co- operative society registered under any law relating to co- 
operative societies for the time being in force, the tax payable in 
respect of that motor vehicle shall be one half of the rates specified 
in Schedule I, if the taxation authority is satisfied, after such 
enquiry as it deems fit, that,-
<section><tid>1208701</tid>
<number>i</number>the co- operative society is solely engaged in the 
business of transport of goods or passengers or both from one 
place to another in motor vehicles;

</section>

<section><tid>1132186</tid>
<number>ii</number>at least seventy- five per cent. of the members of the 
cooperative society are its employees;

</section>

<section><tid>171756</tid>
<number>iii</number>at least fifty per cent of the members of the co- opera- 
tive society are not related to each other; and

</section>

<section><tid>301293</tid>
<number>iv</number>the motor vehicle is used or kept for use exclusively 
for the purpose of the co- operative society.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section a member shall be 
deemed to be related to any other member if that member is the hus- 
band, wife, brother or sister or any lineal ascendant or descendant of 
that other member.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>407</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 17 of <year>1983</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1983</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1692461</tid>
<number> 15</number> Effect of payment of tax in other States with respect to motor 
vehicles brought into Delhi. Where in respect of a motor vehicle the 
tax payable under law relating to taxation on motor vehicles in force 
in any State h been paid in that State for any period and that motor 
vehicle is brought into Delhi for use during that period, then,-
<section><tid>583302</tid>
<number>i</number>no tax under this Act shall be payable in respect of 
that motor vehicle; and

</section>

<section><tid>1692721</tid>
<number>ii</number>the token issued in that State in respect of that motor 
vehicle shall be deemed to be a token issued under this Act,
for such period or for a period of ninety days from the date on which 
the motor vehicle is brought into Delhi, whichever is shorter:

Provided that the registered owner or the person having posses- 
Sion or control of the motor vehicle complies with the provisions of 
sub- section (1) of section 4.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1501262</tid>
<number> 16</number> Appeal.
<section><tid>532787</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person who is aggrieved by any order or  
direction of the taxation authority may file an appeal before such 
person or authority, in such manner, within such time and on payment 
of such fees, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1770601</tid>
<number>2</number>The appeal shall be heard and decided in such manner as may 
be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1683336</tid>
<number>3</number>Every decision on such appeal shall be final and shall not 
be called in question in any court of law.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>730108</tid>
<number> 17</number> Powers of police officers and other officers. Any police 
officer in uniform, not below the rank of Sub- InSpector or any other 
officer prescribed in this behalf may-
<section><tid>1257286</tid>
<number>a</number>enter at any time between sunrise and sunset any premi- 
ses where he has reason to believe that a motor vehicle is 
kept, or,

</section>

<section><tid>1016675</tid>
<number>b</number>require the driver of any motor vehicle in any public 
place to stop such vehicle and cause it to remain stationary 
so long as may reasonably be necessary,
for the purpose of satisfying himself that the amount of the tax in 
respect of such vehicle, has been paid.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1578039</tid>
<number> 18</number> Penalty for incomplete and untrue declaration, etc. Whoever-
<section><tid>1579380</tid>
<number>a</number>delivers in respect of a motor vehicle a declaration or 
additional declaration wherein the particulars required by or 
under this Act to be therein set forth are not fully and 
truly stated, or

</section>

<section><tid>632914</tid>
<number>b</number>obstructs any officer in the exercise of the powers 
conferred by clause (a) of section 17 or fails to stop the 
motor vehicle

<pagefootnote><pagenum>408</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

when required to do so by such officer under clause (b) of that 
section,

shall on conviction be punishable-


<subsection><tid>697178</tid>
<number>i</number>with fine which may extend to a sum equal to the annual 
tax payable in respect of such vehicle; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1121614</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the event of such person having been previously 
convicted of an offence under this section, with fine which 
may extend to a sum equal to twice the annual tax payable in 
respect of such vehicle.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>240485</tid>
<number>19</number>Other penalties. Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of 
this Act or the rules made thereunder other than those punishable 
under section 18 shall on conviction be punishable with fine which may 
extend to one hundred rupees and in the event of such person having 
been previously convicted of an offence under this section, with fine 
which may extend to two hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>633814</tid>
<number> 20</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Utilization of the proceeds of tax. The proceeds of the tax 
collected under this Act (Which shall form part of the Consolidated  
  Fund of India) reduced by the cost of collection as determined by the 
Central Government shall, if Parliament by appropriation made by law 
in this behalf so provides, be paid to,-
<section><tid>1083498</tid>
<number>i</number>the Municipal Corporation of Delhi established under 
section 3 of the Delhi Municipal Corporation Act, <year>1957</year>; (66  
  of <year>1957</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1833623</tid>
<number>ii</number>the New Delhi Municipal Committee established under 
section 11 of the Punjab Municipal Act, <year>1911</year>, (Punjab Act 3 of  
  <year>1911</year>) as extended to Delhi; and

</section>

<section><tid>25246</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Cantonment Board, Delhi, constituted under the 
Cantonments Act, <year>1924</year>, (2 of <year>1924</year>).
for the performance of their respective functions under the said Acts 
and the payment shall be made in such proportion as may be prescribed




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1319914</tid>
<number>21</number>Trial of offences. No court inferior to that of a magistrate 
of the second class shall try an offence punishable under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>690477</tid>
<number>22</number>Protection for bona fide acts. No prosecution, suit or other 
proceedings shall lie against the taxation authority or any other 
authority for anything in good faith done or intended to be done under 
this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1041063</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1277464</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Administrator] may, subject to  
the condition of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>409</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1965</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 27- 11- 65).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 17 of <year>1983</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1983</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1888368</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provision, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Administrator] may or any of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1811399</tid>
<number>a</number>the time within which, and the manner in which, the tax 
shall be paid;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>825069</tid>
<number>b</number>the form of declaration and additional declaration, 
particulars to be stated therein and the time within which 
the declaration or additional declaration shall be delivered 
under section 4 or section 6, as the case may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>296548</tid>
<number>c</number>the form of the tax token and the manner in which the 
tax token shall be displayed in the motor vehicle under sec- 
tion 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1248593</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions subject to which refund of tax may be 
allowed under section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1485317</tid>
<number>e</number>the authority before which, the manner in which, the 
time within which and the fee on payment of which, an appeal 
may be filed and the manner in which such appeal shall be 
heard and decided under section 16;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>747966</tid>
<number>f</number>the issue of duplicate tokens and of certified copies 
of the records of the taxation authority and the fees 
chargeable therefor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>119971</tid>
<number>g</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>429670</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section and every notification 
issued under sub- section (2) of section 3, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and sub- section (3) of 
section 10] shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made or 
issued, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the 
session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
notification, or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made or 
the notification should not be issued, the rule or notification shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or notification"].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1635607</tid>
<number> 24</number> Repeal.
<section><tid>1469513</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the commencement of this Act, the Acts  
specified in Schedule II shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>594124</tid>
<number>2</number>The repeal of the said Acts by sub- section (1) shall not 
affect,-

<subsection><tid>940743</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of the said Acts or anything 
duly done or suffered thereunder; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1326113</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege, obligation or right conferred, 
accrued or incurred under any of the said Acts; or
 131 M of Law- 52

<pagefootnote><pagenum>410</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 17 of <year>1983</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1983</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by S. 5, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1983</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 25 of <year>1989</year>, S. 5, (w. e. f. 1. 2. <year>1990</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130559</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect 
of any offence committed against any of the said Acts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1996889</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation,. legal proceeding or remedy in res- 
pect of any- such right, privilege, obligation, liability, 
penalty forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid;
and any, such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy: may be 
instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed as if the said Acts had not been repealed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>923364</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (2) and 
notwithstanding the repeal of the Punjab Motor Vehicles Taxation Act 
<year>1924</year>, (Punjab Act 4 of <year>1924</year>.) as extended to Delhi,-

<subsection><tid>1598799</tid>
<number>i</number>every declaration delivered under that Act in respect 
of any motor vehicle shall be deemed to be a declaration 
delivered under this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>265765</tid>
<number>ii</number>every token issued under that Act and valid immediately 
before the commencement of this Act, shall continue to be 
valid after such commencement for the unexpired portion of 
the, period for which it has been issued.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>464653</tid>
<number>25</number>Amendment of section 184, Act 66 of <year>1957</year>. In the Delhi 
Municipal Corporation Act, <year>1957</year>, for section 184, he following section 
shall be substituted, namely--
" 184. Central Government to pay proceeds of entertainment and 
betting taxes to Corporation. The proceeds of the 
entertainment and betting, taxes collected in Delhi under the 
provisions of the U. P. Entertainment and Betting Tax Act, 
<year>1937</year>, (U. P. Act 8 of <year>1937</year>.) as extended to Delhi (which shall  
  form part of the Consolidated Fund of India) reduced by the 
cost of collection as determined by the Central Government 
shall if parliament by appropriation made by law in this 
behalf so provides, be paid to the Corporation for the 
performance of its functions under this Act."


</article>



 </act>