<act><tid>1155262</tid>
<title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> THE UNCLAIMED DEPOSITS ACT, <year>1866</year>]</title>

ACT No. 25 OF <year>1866</year>
An Act to transfer to the Government of India certain securities and 
moneys deposited in the High Courts of Judicature at Fort William, 
Madras and Bombay <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>. 
[ 11th July, <year>1866</year>.]

Preamble.

Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient that certain securities and 
sums of money deposited in the High Courts of Judicature at Fort 
William, Madras and Bombay, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in the course of suits in the said 
Courts or in the late Supreme Courts at Calcutta, Madras and Bombay, 
respectively, and now or hereafter appearing to have been in such 
deposit for a period of twenty years or upwards, without any claim 
thereto having been made and allowed during that period, should be 
transferred and paid to the Government of India for the general 
purposes of Government; <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>967268</tid>
<number>1</number>Money deposited in High Courts and unclaimed for twenty years 
transferred to Government.- All securities and sums of money deposited 
in the said High Courts <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or any of them, in the course of suits in 
any of the said Courts or of the late Supreme Courts of Calcutta, 
Madras and Bombay, and now or hereafter appearing to have been in such 
deposit for a period of twenty years or upwards, without any claim 
thereto having been made and allowed during that period, shall be 
transferred and paid to <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the Government of the State in which the 
Court has its principal seat].


</article>



<article><tid>963947</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Proceeds of estates administered under order of Supreme Court of 
Straits Settlements or in charge of Administrator General of Bengal.] 
Rep. by the Administrator General' s Act, <year>1867</year> (24 of <year>1867</year>) and the 
Repealing Act, <year>1874</year> (16 of <year>1874</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1298700</tid>
<number>3</number>Transfer not made pending suits.- Nothing in this Act shall 
authorize any transfer or payment of any such securities, sums of 
money or proceeds as aforesaid, pending
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>). 
2 The words" and the proceeds of certain estates in the charge of 
the Administrator General of Bengal" rep. by Act 24 of <year>1867</year>, and 
the words" and in the Supreme Court of the Straits Settlements" 
rep. by Act 16 of <year>1874</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I. 
3 The words" and in the Supreme Court of the Straits Settlements" 
rep. by Act 16 of <year>1874</year>, s. 2 and Sch. Pt. I. 
4 The second cl. of the preamble rep. by Act 12 of <year>1876</year>, s. 1 and 
Sch., Pt. I. 
5 The words" or Supreme Court of the Straits Settlements" rep. by 
Act 16 of <year>1874</year>. 
6 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the G. of I. for the general 
purposes of Govt.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


any suit already instituted or which shall hereafter be instituted in 
respect thereof.



</article>



<article><tid>1298866</tid>
<number>4</number>Repayment on subsequent establishment of claim.- If any claim 
shall hereafter be made to any part of the securities, monies or 
proceeds which shall be transferred and <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> paid to any Government] 
under the provisions of this Act, and if such claim shall, in the case 
of securities and monies transferred and paid under section 1 of this 
Act, be established to the satisfaction of the High Court <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> from 
which the transfer shall have been made, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Government of the 
State in which that Court has its principal seat shall pay] to the 
claimant the amount of the principal so transferred and paid as 
aforesaid, or so much thereof as shall appear to be due <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> to the 
claimant. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" paid to the G. of I." 
2 Certain words rep. by Act 16 of <year>1874</year>. 
3 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the G. of I. shall pay". 
4 As to the costs of petition under this section, see the Unclaimed 
Deposits Act, <year>1870</year> (5 of <year>1870</year>). 
5 The second sentence rep. by Act 24 of <year>1867</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>