<act><tid>1157644</tid>
<title>THE SUGAR DEVELOPMENT FUND ACT, <year>1982</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1982</year>
[ 19th March, <year>1982</year>.]

An Act to provide for the financing of activities for development of 
sugar industry and for matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>760351</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1478355</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Sugar Development Fund Act, <year>1982</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1604847</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1265102</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>715217</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1670739</tid>
<number>a</number>" Committee" means the Committee constituted under 
section 6;

</section>

<section><tid>1174953</tid>
<number>b</number>" Fund" means the Sugar Development Fund formed under 
section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>463096</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>855597</tid>
<number>d</number>all other words and expressions used in this Act and not 
defined, but defined in the Sugar Cess Act, <year>1982</year>, shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>309486</tid>
<number> 3</number> Sugar Development Fund.
<section><tid>984709</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be formed a fund to be  
called the Sugar Development Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1217422</tid>
<number>2</number>An amount equivalent to the proceeds of the duty of excise 
levied and collected under the Sugar Cess Act, <year>1982</year>, reduced by the 
cost of collection as determined by the Central Government, together 
with any moneys received by the Central Government for the purposes of 
this Act, shall, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law, be 
credited to the Fund.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 6- <year>1982</year>: Vide notification No. G. S. R. 436 (E) dated 29- 5- <year>1982</year>, 
Gazette of India, Extra ordinary <year>1982</year>, Pt. II Section 3 (i).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1566082</tid>
<number>3</number>The Fund shall consist of the amounts credited under sub- 
section (2) and any income from investment of such amounts.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>657529</tid>
<number> 4</number> Application of Fund.
<section><tid>1915382</tid>
<number>1</number>The Fund shall be applied by the  
Central Government,--

<subsection><tid>264413</tid>
<number>a</number>for making loans for facilitating the rehabilitation and 
modernisation of any sugar factory or any unit thereof or the 
undertaking of any scheme for development of sugarcane in the 
area in which any sugar factory is situated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130040</tid>
<number>b</number>for making grants for the purpose of any research 
project aimed at development of sugar industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1880385</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> for defraying expenditure for the purpose of 
building up and maintenance of buffer stocks of sugar with a view 
to establishing price of sugar;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1513201</tid>
<number>c</number>for defraying any other expenditure for the purposes of 
this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1723901</tid>
<number>2</number>The manner in which any loans or grants may be made under 
this section and the terms and conditions subject to which such loans 
or grants may be made shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1739511</tid>
<number>5</number>Applications for loans or grants. Every application for loan 
or grant under section 4 shall be made to the Committee in such manner 
and in such form as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1097728</tid>
<number> 6</number> Committee.
<section><tid>19323</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of securing speedy  
consideration and disposal of applications received under section 5 
and for considering any problems arising in the course of the 
administration of this Act, the Central Government may constitute a 
committee of officers of that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>252290</tid>
<number>2</number>The composition of the Committee and the procedure to be 
followed by the Committee in the discharge of its functions under this 
Act shall be such as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1479420</tid>
<number>7</number>Annual report of activities financed under the Act. The 
Central Government shall, as soon as may be, after the end of each 
financial year, cause to be published in the Official Gazette, a 
report giving an account of the activities financed under this Act 
during the financial year, together with a statement of accounts.


</article>



<article><tid>54653</tid>
<number>8</number>Power to call for reports and returns. The Central Government 
may require an occupier of a sugar factory to furnish, for the 
purposes of this Act, such statistical and other information, in such 
form and within such period as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1793733</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1950683</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Inserted by Act 64 of <year>1982</year> s. z (w. e. f 13- 11- <year>1982</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1729172</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for,--

<subsection><tid>712097</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which any loans or grants may be made and 
the terms and conditions subject to which such loans or grants 
may be made under section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1680956</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner and form in which applications may be made 
under section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1615220</tid>
<number>c</number>the composition of the Committee under section 6 and the 
procedure to be followed by the Committee in the discharge of its 
functions under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>667827</tid>
<number>d</number>the form in which and the period within which 
statistical and other information may be furnished under section 
8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>40426</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which is required to be or may be 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1106905</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without pejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>