<act> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>1</number> 
Short title.—This 
Act may be called the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872.
 <section>Extent.—1[It 
extends to the whole of India 

2[except 

3[the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in the States] 
of Travancore-Cochin, Manipur and Jammu and Kashmir].]4
 

5[***]
  










</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>2</number> 
Enactments repealed.—[Rep. 
by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch., Pt. I.]
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>3</number> 
Interpretation-clause.—In 
this Act unless there is something repugnant in the subject or context,—
 “Church 
of England” and “Anglican” mean and apply to the Church of England as by law 
established; 
 “Church 
of Scotland” means the Church of Scotland as by law established; 
 “Church 
of Rome” and “Roman Catholic” mean and apply to the Church which regards the 
Pope of Rome as its spiritual head;
 “Church” 
includes any chapel or other building generally used for public Christian 
Worship;
 

1[“India” means 
the 

2[territories] to 
which this Act extends;]
 “minor” 
means a person who has not completed the age of twenty-one years and who is not 
a widower or a widow;
 

3[***]
 the 
expression “Christian” means persons professing the Christian religion; 

 

4[and the 
expression “Indian Christians” includes the Christian descendants of natives of 
India converted to Christianity, as well as such converts;]
 

5[“Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages” means a Registrar General of Births, 
Deaths and Marriages appointed under the Births, Deaths and Marriages 
Registration Act, 1886 (6 of 1886)].
 STATE AMENDMENT
 Karnataka:—In 
section 3, the definition of “Registrar General of Births, Deaths and 
Marriages” shall be substituted as follows:
               “‘Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages’ means the Registrar General of Births, 
Deaths and Marriages appointed under the Mysore Registrar General of Births, 
Deaths and Marriages Act, 1956.” [Mysore Act 20 of 1956, sec. I read with Act 
31 of 1973, sec. 5.]











</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>4</number> 
Marriages to be solemnized according to Act.—Every 
marriage between persons, one or both of whom is 

1[or are] a 
Christian, or Christians, shall be solemnized in accordance with the provisions 
of the next following section; and any such marriage solemnized otherwise than 
in accordance with such provisions shall be void.
  




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>5</number> 
Persons by whom marriages may be solemnized.—Marriages 
may be solemnized in 

1[India]—
 <section>         <number>1</number> by any 
person who has received episcopal ordination, provided that the marriage be 
solemnized according to the rules, rites, ceremonies and customs of the Church 
of which he is a Minister;
 </section><section>         <number>2</number> by any 
Clergyman of the Church of Scotland, provided that such marriage be solemnized 
according to the rules, rites, ceremonies and customs of the Church of 
Scotland;
 </section><section>         <number>3</number> by any 
Minister of Religion licensed under this Act to solemnize marriages;
 </section><section>         <number>4</number> by, or in 
the presence of, a Marriage Registrar appointed under this Act;
 </section><section>         <number>5</number> by any 
person licensed under this Act to grant certificates of marriage between 

2[Indian] Christians.
  





</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>

1[<number>6</number> Grant and 
revocation of licenses to solemnize marriages.—The


2[State] 
Government, so far as regards the territories under its administration, 

3[***] may, by 
notification in the 

4[Official 
Gazette] 

5[***], grant 
licences to Ministers of Religion to solemnize marriages within such 
territories 

6[***] and may, by 
a like notification, revoke such licences.]
  









</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>7</number> 
Marriage Registrars.—The 
State Government may appoint one or more Christians, either by name or as 
holding any office for the time being, to be the Marriage Registrar or Marriage 
Registrars for any district subject to its administration.
 Senior 
Marriage Registrar.—Where 
there are more Marriage Registrars than one in any district, the State 
Government shall appoint one of them to be the Senior Marriage Registrar.
 
Magistrate when to be Marriage Registrar.—When 
there is only one Marriage Registrar in a district, and such Registrar is 
absent from such district, or ill, or when his office is temporarily vacant, 
the Magistrate of district shall act as, and be, Marriage Registrar thereof 
during such absence, illness, or temporary vacancy.
 STATE AMENDMENT
 Karnataka:—In 
section 7, for the words “Magistrate of the District”, the words “District 
Magistrate” shall be substituted. [Mysore Act 13 of 1965, sec. 66 and Sch, 
read with Act 31 of 1973, sec. 5.]
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>8</number> 
Marriage Registrars in Indian States.—[Rep. 
by A.O. 1950].
  
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>9</number> 
Licensing of persons to grant certificates of marriage between Indian 
Christians.—The


1[State 
Government] 

2[*** ] may grant 
a license to any Christian either by name or as holding any office for the time 
being, authorizing him to grant certificates of marriage between 

3[Indian] 
Christians.
 Any such 
license may be revoked by the authority by which it was granted and every such 
grant or revocation shall be notified in the Official Gazette.













</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>10</number> 
Time for solemnizing marriage.—Every 
marriage under this Act shall be solemnized between the hours of six in the 
morning and seven in the evening:
 <section>
Exceptions.—Provided 
that nothing in this section shall apply to—
 <subsection>         <number>1</number> a Clergyman 
of the Church of England solemnizing a marriage under a special license 
permitting him to do so at any hour other than between six in the morning and 
seven in the evening, under the hand and seal of the Anglican Bishop of the 
Diocese or his Commissary, or
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>2</number> a Clergyman 
of the Church of Rome solemnizing a marriage between the hours of seven in the 
evening and six in the morning, when he has received a general or special 
license in that behalf from the Roman Catholic Bishop of the Diocese or 
Vicariate in which such marriage is so solemnized, or from such person as the 
same Bishop has authorised to grant such license, 
1[or
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>3</number> a Clergyman 
of the Church of the Scotland 
solemnizing a marriage according to the rule, rites, ceremonies and customs of 
the Church of Scotland.]
  




</subsection></section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>11</number> 
Place for solemnizing marriage.—No 
Clergyman of the Church of England shall solemnize a marriage in any place 
other than a Church 

1[where worship is 
generally held according to the norms of the Church of England,]
 unless 
there is no 

1 [such] church 
within five miles distance by the shortest road from such place, or
 unless he 
has received a special license authorizing him to do so under the hand and seal 
of the Anglican Bishop of the Diocese or his Commissary.
 Fee 
for special license.—For 
such special license, the Registrar of the Diocese may charge such additional 
fee as said Bishop from time to time authorizes.







</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>12</number> 
Notice of intended marriage.—Whenever 
a marriage is intended to be solemnized by a Minister of Religion licensed to 
solemnize marriages under this Act—
 one of 
the persons intending marriage shall give notice in writing, according to the 
form contained in the First Schedule hereto annexed, or to the like effect, to 
the Minister of Religion whom he or she desires to solemnize the marriage, and 
shall state therein—
 <section>         <number>a</number> the name 
and surname, and the profession or condition, of each of the persons intending 
marriage;
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> the 
dwelling-place of each of them;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number> the time 
during which each has dwelt there; and
 </section><section>         <number>d</number> the church 
or private dwelling in which the marriage is to be solemnized:
 Provided 
that, if either of such persons has dwelt in the place mentioned in the notice 
during more than one month, it may be stated therein that he or she has dwelt 
there one month and upwards.
</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>13</number> 
Publication of such notice.—If 
the persons intending marriage desire it to be solemnized in a particular 
church, and if the Minister of Religion to whom such notice has been delivered 
be entitled to officiate therein, he shall cause the notice to be affixed in 
some conspicuous part of such church.
 Return 
or transfer of notice.—But 
if he is not entitled to officiate as a Minister in such church, he shall, at 
his option, either return the notice to the person who delivered it to him, or 
deliver it to some other Minister entitled to officiate therein, who shall 
thereupon cause the notice to be affixed as aforesaid.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>14</number> 
Notice of intended marriage in private dwelling.—If 
it be intended that the marriage shall be solemnized in a private dwelling, the 
Minister of Religion, on receiving the notice prescribed in section 12, shall 
forward it to the Marriage Registrar of the district, who shall affix the same 
to some conspicuous place in his own office.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>15</number> 
Sending copy of notice to Marriage Registrar when one party is a 
minor.—When one 
of the persons intending marriage is a minor, every Minister receiving such 
notice shall, unless within twenty-four hours after its receipt he returns the 
same under the provisions of section 13, send by the post or otherwise a copy of 
such notice to the Marriage Registrar of the district, or, if there be more than 
one Registrar of such district, to the Senior Marriage 
Registrar.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>16</number> 
Procedure in receipt of notice.—The 
Marriage Registrar or Senior Marriage Registrar, as the case may be, on 
receiving any such notice, shall affix it to some conspicuous place in his own 
office, and the latter shall further cause a copy of the said notice to be sent 
to each of the other Marriage Registrars in the same district who shall 
likewise publish the same in the manner above directed.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>17</number> Issue 
of certificate of notice given and declaration made.—Any Minister of Religion 
consenting or intending to solemnize any such marriage as aforesaid, shall, on 
being required so to do by or on behalf of the person by whom the notice was 
given, and upon one of the persons intending marriage making the declaration 
hereinafter required, issue under his hand a certificate of such notice having 
been given and of such declaration having been made:
 <section><number>Proviso</number>—Provided—
 <subsection>         
<number>1</number> that no such certificates shall be issued until the expiration of four days 
after the date of the receipt of the notice by such Minister;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>2</number> that no lawful impediment be shown to his satisfaction why such certificate 
should not issue; and
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>3</number> that the issue of such certificate has not been forbidden, in manner 
hereinafter mentioned, by any person authorized in that 
behalf.</subsection></section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>18</number> 
Declaration before issue of certificate.—The 
certificate mentioned in section 17 shall not be issued until one of the 
persons intending marriage has appeared personally before the Minister and made 
a solemn declaration—
 <section>         <number>a</number> that he or 
she believes that there is not any impediment of kindred or affinity, or other 
lawful hindrance, to the said marriage,
 and, when either or both 
of the parties is or are a minor or minors,
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> that the 
consent or consents required by law has or have been obtained thereto, or that 
there is no person resident in India having authority to give such consent, as 
the case may be.
</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>19</number> 
Consent of father, or guardian or mother.—The 
father, if living, of any minor, or, if the father be dead, the guardian of the 
person of such minor, and, in case there be no such guardian, then the mother 
of such minor, may give consent to the minor’s marriage, 
 and such 
consent is hereby required for the same marriage, unless no person authorised 
to give such consent be resident in India.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>20</number> 
Power to prohibit by notice issue of certificate.—Every 
person whose consent to a marriage is required under section 19, is hereby 
authorized to prohibit the issue of the certificate by any Minister, at any 
time before the issue of the same, by notice in writing to such Minister, 
subscribed by the person so authorized with his or her name and place of abode 
and position with respect to either of the persons intending marriage, by 
reason of which he or she is so authorized as aforesaid.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>21</number> 
Procedure on receipt of notice.—If 
any such notice be received by such Minister, he shall not issue his 
certificate and shall not solemnize the said marriage until he has examined 
into the matter of the said prohibition, and is satisfied that the person 
prohibiting the marriage has no lawful authority for such prohibition,
 or until 
the said notice is withdrawn by the person who gave it.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>22</number> 
Issue of certificate in case of minority.—When 
either of the persons intending marriage is a minor, and the Minister is not 
satisfied that the consent of the person whose consent to such marriage is 
required by section 19 has been obtained, such Minister shall not issue such 
certificate until the expiration of fourteen days after the receipt by him of 
the notice of marriage.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>23</number> 
Issue of certificate to 

1[Indian] 
Christians.—When 
any 

1[Indian] 
Christian about to be married takes a notice of marriage to a Minister of 
Religion, or applies for a certificate from such Minister under section 17, 
such Minister shall, before issuing the certificate, ascertain whether such


1[Indian] 
Christian is cognizant of the purport and effect of the said notice or 
certificate, as the case may be, and, if not, shall translate or cause to be, 
translated the notice or certificate to such 

1[Indian] 
Christian into some language which he understands.
  




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>24</number> 
Form of certificate.—The 
certificate to be issued by such Minister shall be in the form contained in the 
Second Schedule hereto annexed, or to the like effect.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>25</number> 
Solemnization of marriage.—After 
the issue of the certificate by the Minister, marriage may be solemnized 
between the persons therein described according to such form or ceremony as the 
Minister thinks fit to adopt:
 Provided 
that the marriage be solemnized in the presence of at least two witnesses 
besides the Minister.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>26</number> 
Certificate void if marriage not solemnized within two months.—Whenever a marriage is not 
solemnized within two months after the date of the certificate issued by such 
Minister as aforesaid, such certificate and all proceedings (if any) thereon 
shall be void, 
 and no 
person shall proceed to solemnize the said marriage until new notice has been 
given, and a certificate thereof issued in manner aforesaid.




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>27</number> 
Marriages when to be registered.—All 
marriages hereafter solemnized in 

1[India] between 
persons one or both of whom professes or profess the Christian religion, except 
marriages solemnized under Part V or Part VI of this Act, shall be registered2 in 
manner hereinafter prescribed.
  





</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>28</number> 
Registration of marriages solemnized by Clergymen of Church of 
England.—Every 
Clergyman of the Church of England shall keep a register of marriages and shall 
register therein, according to the tabular form set forth in the Third Schedule 
hereto annexed, every marriage which he solemnizes under this 
Act.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>29</number> 
Quarterly returns to Archdeaconry.—Every 
Clergyman of the Church of England shall send four times in every year returns 
in duplicate, authenticated by his signature, of the entries in the register of 
marriages solemnized at any place where he has any spiritual charge, to the 
Registrar of the Archdeaconry to which he is subject, or within the limits of 
which such place is situate.
 
Contents of returns.—Such 
quarterly returns shall contain all the entries of marriages contained in the 
said register from the first day of January to the thirty-first day of March, 
from the first day of April to the thirtieth day of June, from the first day of 
July to the thirtieth day of September and from the first day of October to the 
thirty-first day of December, of each year, respectively, and shall be sent by 
such Clergyman within two weeks from the expiration of each of the quarters 
above specified.
 The said 
Registrar upon receiving the said returns shall send one copy thereof to the


1[Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages].
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>30</number> 
Registration and returns of marriages solemnized by Clergymen of Church of 
Rome.—Every 
marriage solemnized by a Clergyman of the Church of Rome shall be registered by 
the person and according to the form directed in that behalf by the Roman 
Catholic Bishop of the Diocese or Vicariate in which such marriage is 
solemnized, 
 and such 
person shall forward quarterly to the 1[Registrar General of Births, 
Deaths and Marriages] returns of the entries of all marriages registered by him 
during the three months next preceding.
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>31</number> 
Registration and returns of marriages solemnized by Clergymen of Church of 
Scotland.—Every 
Clergyman of the Church of Scotland shall keep a register of marriages, 

 and shall 
register therein, according to the tabular form set forth in the Third Schedule 
hereto annexed, every marriage which he solemnizes under this Act,
 and shall 
forward quarterly to the 1[Registrar General of Births, 
Deaths and Marriages], through the Senior Chaplain of the Church of Scotland, 
returns, similar to those prescribed in section 29, of all such 
marriages.
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>32</number> 
Certain marriages to be registered in duplicate.—Every 
marriage solemnized by any person who has received episcopal ordination, but 
who is not a Clergyman of the Church of England, or of the Church of Rome, or 
by any Minister of Religion licensed under this Act to solemnize marriages, 
shall immediately after the solemnization thereof, be registered, in duplicate 
by the person solemnizing the same; (that is to say) in a marriage 
register-book to be kept by him for that purpose, according to the form 
contained in the Fourth Schedule hereto annexed, and also in a certificate 
attached to the marriage-register-book as a counterfoil.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>33</number> 
Entries of such marriages to be signed and attested.—The 
entry of such marriage in both the certificate and marriage-register-book shall 
be signed by the person solemnizing the marriage, and also by the persons 
married, and shall be attested by two credible witnesses, other than the person 
solemnizing the marriage, present at its solemnization.
 Every 
such entry shall be made in order from the beginning to the end of the book, 
and the number of the certificate shall correspond with that of the entry in 
the marriage-register-book.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>34</number> 
Certificate to be forwarded to Marriage Registrar, copied and sent to 
Registrar-General.—The person solemnizing the 
marriage shall forthwith separate the certificate from the 
marriage-register-book and send it, within one month from the time of the 
solemnization, to the Marriage Registrar of the district in which the marriage 
was solemnized, or, if there be more Marriage Registrars than one, to the Senior 
Marriage Registrar.
 who shall 
cause such certificate to be copied into a book to be kept by him for that 
purpose,
 and shall 
send all the certificates which he has received during the month, with such 
number and signature or initials added thereto as are hereinafter required to 
the 1[Registrar General of Births, 
Deaths and Marriages].
  


</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>35</number> 
Copies of certificates to be entered and numbered.—Such 
copies shall be entered in order from the beginning to the end of the said 
book, and shall bear both the number of the certificate as copied, and also a 
number to be entered by the Marriage Registrar, indicating the number of the 
entry of the said copy in the said book, according to the order in which he 
receives each certificate.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>36</number> 
Registrar to add number of entry to certificate and send to 
Registrar-General.—The Marriage Registrar shall 
also add such last-mentioned number of the entry of the copy in the book to the 
certificate, with his signature or initials, and shall, at the end of every 
month, send the same to the 1[Registrar General of Births, 
Deaths and Marriages].
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>37</number> 
Registration of marriages between Indian Christians by persons referred to in 
clauses 
<section><number>1</number>, (2) and (3) of section 5.—When 
any marriage between 

1[Indian] 
Christians is solemnized 

2[by any such 
person, Clergyman or Minister of Religion as is referred to in clause (1), 
clause (2) or clause (3) of section 5,] the person solemnizing the same shall, 
instead of proceeding in the manner provided by sections 28 to 36, both 
inclusive, register the marriage in a separate register-book, and shall keep it 
safely until it is filled, or, if he leaves the district in which he solemnized 
the marriage before the said book is filled, shall make over the same to the 
person succeeding to his duties in the said district.
 
Custody and disposal of register-book.—Whoever 
has the control of the book at the time when it is filled, shall send it to the 
Marriage Registrar of the district, or, if there be more Marriage Registrars 
than one, to the Senior Marriage Registrar, who shall send it to the 

3[Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages], to be kept by him with the records of 
his office.









</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>38</number> 
Notice of intended marriage before Marriage Registrar.—When a marriage is intended to 
be solemnized by, or in the presence of, a Marriage Registrar, one of the 
parties to such marriage shall give notice in writing, in the form contained in 
the First Schedule hereto annexed, or to the like effect, to any Marriage 
Registrar of the district within which the parties have dwelt, 
 or, if the 
parties dwell in different districts, shall give the like notice to a Marriage 
Registrar of each district, 
 and shall 
state therein the name and surname, and the profession or condition, of each of 
the parties intending marriage, the dwelling-place of each of them, the time 
during which each has dwelt therein, and the place at which the marriage is to 
be solemnized:
 Provided 
that, if either party has dwelt in the place stated in the notice for more than 
one month, it may be stated therein that he or she has dwelt there one month and 
upwards.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>39</number> 
Publication of notice.—Every 
Marriage Registrar shall, on receiving any such notice, cause a copy thereof to 
be affixed in some conspicuous place in his office.
 When one 
of the parties intending marriage is a minor, every Marriage Registrar shall, 
within twenty-four hours after the receipt by him of the notice of such 
marriage, send, by post or otherwise, a copy of such notice to each of the 
other Marriage Registrars (if any) in the same district, who shall likewise 
affix the copy in some conspicuous place in his own office.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>40</number> 
Notice to be filed and copy entered in Marriage Notice Book.—The Marriage Registrar shall 
file all such notices and keep them with the records of his office, 
 and shall 
also forthwith enter a true copy of all such notices in a book to be furnished 
to him for that purpose by the 1[State] Government, and to be 
called the” Marriage Notice Book”,
 and the 
Marriage Notice Book shall be open at all reasonable times, without fee, to all 
persons desirous of inspecting the same.
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>41</number> 
Certificate of notice given and oath made.—If 
the party by whom the notice was given requests the Marriage Registrar to issue 
the certificate next hereinafter mentioned, and if one of the parties intending 
marriage has made oath as hereinafter required, the Marriage Registrar shall 
issue under his hand a certificate of such notice having been given and or such 
oath having been made:
 <section>
<number>Proviso</number>—Provided—
 that no 
lawful impediment be shown to his satisfaction why such certificate should not 
issue;
 that the 
issue of such certificate has not been forbidden, in manner hereinafter 
mentioned, by any person authorized in that behalf by this Act;
 that four 
days after the receipt of the notice have expired, and further;
 that 
where, by such oath, it appears that one of the parties intending marriage is a 
minor, fourteen days after the entry of such notice have expired.
</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>42</number> 
Oath before issue of certificate.—The 
certificate mentioned in section 41 shall not be issued by any Marriage 
Registrar, until one of the parties intending marriage appears personally 
before such Marriage Registrar, and makes oath1—
 <section>         <number>a</number> that he or 
she believes that there is not any impediment of kindred or affinity, or other 
lawful hindrance, to the said marriage, and
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> that both 
the parties have, or (where they have dwelt in the districts of different 
Marriage Registrars) that the party making such oath has, had their, his or her 
usual place of abode within the district of such Marriage Registrar, 

 and, where either or 
each of the parties is a minor,
 </section><section>         <number>c</number> that the 
consent or consents to such marriage required by law has or have been obtained 
thereto, or that there is no person resident in India authorized to give such 
consent, as the case may be.
  





</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>43</number> 
Petition to High Court to order certificate in less than fourteen 
days.—When one 
of the parties, intending marriage is a minor, and both such parties are at the 
time resident in any of the towns of Calcutta, Madras and Bombay, and are 
desirous of being married in less than fourteen days after the entry of such 
notice as aforesaid, they may apply by petition to a Judge of the High Court, 
for an order upon the Marriage Registrar to whom the notice of marriage has been 
given, directing him to issue his certificate before the expiration of the said 
fourteen days required by section 41.
 Order on 
petition.—And 
on sufficient cause being shown, said Judge may, in his discretion, make an 
order upon such Marriage Registrar, directing him to issue his certificate at 
any time to be mentioned in the said order before the expiration of the fourteen 
days so required. 
 And the said 
Marriage Registrar, on receipt of the order, shall issue his certificate in 
accordance therewith.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>44</number> 
Consent of father or guardian.—The 
provisions of section 19 apply to every marriage under this Part, either of the 
parties to which is a minor;
 
Protest against issue of certificate.—And 
any person whose consent to such marriage would be required thereunder may 
enter a protest against the issue of the Marriage Registrar’s certificate, by 
writing, at any time before the issue of such certificate, the word “forbidden” 
opposite to the entry of the notice of such intended marriage in the Marriage 
Notice Book, and by subscribing thereto his or her name and place of abode, and 
his or her position with respect to either of the parties, by reason of which 
he or she is so authorized.
 Effect 
of Protest.—When 
such protest has been entered, no certificate shall issue until the Marriage 
Registrar has examined into the matter of the protest, and is satisfied that it 
ought not to obstruct the issue of the certificate for the said marriage, or 
until the protest be withdrawn by the person who entered it.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>45</number> 
Petition where person whose consent is necessary is insane, or unjustly 
withholds consent.—If any person whose consent is 
necessary to any marriage under this Part is of unsound mind, 
 or if any 
such person (other than the father) without just cause withholds his consent to 
the marriage, 
 the parties 
intending marriage may apply by petition, where the person whose consent is 
necessary is resident within any of towns of Calcutta, Madras and Bombay, to a 
Judge of the High Court, or if he is not resident within any of the said towns, 
then to the District Judge.
 Procedure 
on petition.—And the said Judge of the High 
Court, or District Judge, as the case may be, may examine the allegations of the 
petition in a summary way;
 and, if upon 
examination such marriage appears proper, such Judge of the High Court or 
District Judge, as the case may be, shall declare the marriage to be a proper 
marriage.
 Such 
declaration shall be as effectual as if the person whose consent was needed had 
consented to the marriage;
 and, if he 
has forbidden the issue of the Marriage Registrar’s certificate, such 
certificate shall be issued and the like proceedings may be had under this Part 
in relation to marriage as if the issue of such certificate had not been 
forbidden.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>46</number> 
Petition when Marriage Registrar refuses certificate.—Whenever a Marriage Registrar 
refuses to issue a certificate under this Part, either of the parties intending 
marriage may apply by petition, where the district of such Registrar is within 
any of the towns of Calcutta, Madras and Bombay, to a Judge of the High Court, 
or if such district is not within any of the said towns, then to the District 
Judge.
 Procedure 
on petition.—The said Judge of the High 
Court, or District Judge, as the case may be, may examine the allegations of the 
petition in a summary way, and shall decide thereon.
 The decision 
of such Judge of the High Court or District Judge, as the case may be, shall be 
final, and the Marriage Registrar to whom the application for the issue of 
certificate was originally made shall proceed in accordance 
therewith.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>47</number> 
Petition when Marriage Registrar in Indian State refuses certificate.—[Rep. 
by the A.O. 1950].
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>48</number> 
Petition when Registrar doubts authority of person forbidding.—Whenever a Marriage Registrar, 
acting under the provisions of section 44, is not satisfied that the person 
forbidding the issue of the certificate is authorized by law so to do, the said 
Marriage Registrar shall apply by petition, where his district is within any of 
the towns of Calcutta, Madras and Bombay, to a Judge of the High Court, or if 
such district be not within any of the said towns, then to the District 
Judge.
 Procedure 
on petition.—The said petition shall state 
all the circumstances of the case, and pray for the order and direction of the 
court concerning the same,
 and the said 
Judge of the High Court or District Judge, as the case may be, shall examine 
into the allegations of the petition and the circumstances of the case, 

 and if, upon 
such examination, it appears that the person forbidding the issue of such 
certificate is not authorized by law so to do, such Judge of the High Court or 
District Judge, as the case may be, shall declare that the person forbidding the 
issue of such certificate is not authorized as aforesaid,
 and 
thereupon such certificate shall be issued, and the like proceedings may be had 
in relation to such marriage as if the issue had not been forbidden.
 1[***]
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>49</number> 
Liability for frivolous protest against issue of certificate.—Every person entering a protest 
with the Marriage Registrar, under this Part, against the issue of any 
certificate, on grounds which such Marriage Registrar, under section 44, or a 
Judge of the High Court or the District Judge, under section 45 or 46, declares 
to be frivolous and such as ought not to obstruct the issue of the certificate, 
shall be liable for the costs of all proceedings in relation thereto and for 
damages, to be recovered by suit by the person against whose marriage such 
protest was entered.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>50</number> 
Form of certificate.—The 
certificate to be issued by the Marriage Registrar under the provisions of 
section 41 shall be in the form contained in the Second Schedule to this Act 
annexed or to the like effect,
 and the


1[State] 
Government shall furnish to every Marriage Registrar a sufficient number of 
forms of certificate.
  




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>51</number> 
Solemnization of marriage after issue of certificate.—After the issue of the 
certificate of the Marriage Registrar,
 or, where 
notice is required to be given under this Act to the Marriage Registrars for 
different districts, after the issue of the certificates of the Marriage 
Registrars for such districts,
 marriage 
may, if there be no lawful impediment to the marriage of the parties described 
in such certificate, or certificates, be solemnized between them, according to 
such form and ceremony as they think fit to adopt.
 But every 
such marriage shall be solemnized in the presence of some Marriage Registrar (to 
whom shall be delivered such certificate or certificates as aforesaid), and of 
two or more credible witnesses besides the Marriage Registrar.
 And in some 
part of the ceremony each of the parties shall declare as follows, or to the 
like effect:—
           
“I do solemnly declare that I know not of any lawful impediment why I, A.B., may 
not be joined in matrimony to C.D.”.
 And each of 
the parties shall say to the other as follows or to the like effect:—
           
“I call upon these persons here present to witness that I, A.B., do take thee, 
C.D., to be my lawful wedded wife (or husband)”.
  </article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>52</number> When 
marriage not held within two months after notice, new notice 
required.—Whenever a marriage is not 
solemnized within two months after the copy of the notice has been entered by 
the Marriage Registrar, as required by section 40, the notice and the 
certificate, if any, issued thereupon, and all other proceedings thereupon, 
shall be void;
 and no 
person shall proceed to solemnize the marriage, nor shall any Marriage Registrar 
enter the same, until new notice has been given, and entry made, and certificate 
thereof given, at the time and in the manner aforesaid.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>53</number> 
Marriage Registrar may ask for particulars to be registered.—A Marriage Registrar before 
whom any marriage is solemnized under this Part may ask of the persons to be 
married the several particulars required to be registered touching such 
marriage.</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>54</number> 
Registration of marriages solemnized under Part V.—After 
the solemnization of any marriage under this Part, the Marriage Registrar 
present at such solemnization shall forthwith register the marriage in 
duplicate; that is to say, in a marriage-register-book, according to the form 
of the Fourth Schedule hereto annexed, and also in a certificate attached to 
the marriage-register-book as a counterfoil.
 The entry 
of such marriage in both the certificate and the marriage-register-book shall 
be signed by the person by or before whom the marriage has been solemnized, if 
there be any such person, and by the Marriage Registrar present at such 
marriage, whether or not it is solemnized by him, and also by the parties 
married and attested by two credible witnesses other than the Marriage 
Registrar and person solemnizing the marriage.
 Every 
such entry shall be made in order from the beginning to the end of the book, 
and the number of the certificate shall correspond with that of the entry in 
the marriage-register-book.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>55</number> 
Certificate to be sent monthly to Registrar-General.—The 
Marriage Registrar shall forthwith separate the certificate from the 
marriage-register-book and send it, at the end of every month, to the 

1[Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages].
 
Custody of register-book.—The 
Marriage Registrar shall keep safely the said register-book until it is filled, 
and shall then send it to the 

1[Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages,] to be kept by him with the records of 
his office.
  





</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>56</number> 
Officers to whom Registrar in Indian States shall send 
certificates.—[Rep. by the A.O. 
1950].</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>57</number> 
Registrars to ascertain that notice and certificate are understood by Indian 
Christians.—When any 1[Indian] Christian about to be 
married gives a notice of marriage, or applies for a certificate from a Marriage 
Registrar, such Marriage Registrar shall ascertain whether the said 1[Indian] Christian understands 
the English language, and, if he does not, the Marriage Registrar shall 
translate, or cause to be translated such notice or certificate, or both of 
them, as the case may be, to such 1[Indian] Christian into a 
language which he understands;
 or the 
Marriage Registrar shall otherwise ascertain whether the 1[Indian] Christian is cognizant 
of the purport and effect of the said notice and certificate.
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>58</number> 
1[Indian] Christians to be made 
to understand declarations.—When any 1[Indian] Christian is married 
under the provisions of this Part, the person solemnizing the marriage shall 
ascertain whether such 1[Indian] Christian understands 
the English language, and, if he does not, the person solemnizing the marriage 
shall, at the time of the solemnization, translate, or cause to be translated, 
to such 1[Indian] Christian, into a 
language which he understands, the declarations made at such marriage in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act.
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>59</number> 
Registration of marriages between 

1[Indian] 
Christians.—The 
registration of marriages between 

1[Indian] 
Christians under this Part shall be made in conformity with the rules laid down 
in section 37 (so far as they are applicable), and not otherwise.








</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>60</number> On 
what conditions marriages of 

1[Indian] 
Christians may be certified.—Every 
marriage between 

1[Indian] 
Christians applying for a certificate, shall, without the preliminary notice 
required under Part III, be certified under this Part, if the following 
conditions be fulfilled, and not otherwise:—
 <section>         <number>1</number> the age of 
the man intending to be married 

2[shall not be under 

3[twenty-one years]], and the age of 
the woman intending to be married 

4[shall not be under 

5[eighteen years]];
 </section><section>         <number>2</number> neither of 
the persons intending to be married shall have a wife or husband still living;
 </section><section>         <number>3</number> in the 
presence of a person licensed under section 9, and of at least two credible 
witnesses other than such person, each of the parties shall say to the other—
                  “I call 
upon these persons here present to witness that, I, A.B., in the presence of 
Almighty God, and in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ, do take thee, C.D., to 
be my lawful wedded wife or husband” or words to the like effect:
 

6[***]
  








</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>61</number> 
Grant of certificate.—When, 
in respect to any marriage solemnized under this Part, the conditions 
prescribed in section 60 have been fulfilled, the person licensed as aforesaid, 
in whose presence the said declaration has made, shall, on the application of 
either of the parties to such marriage, and, on the payment of a fee of four 
annas, grant a certificate of the marriage.
 The 
certificate shall be signed by such licensed person, and shall be received in 
any suit touching the validity of such marriage as conclusive proof of its 
having been performed.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>

1[<number>62</number> Keeping of 
register-book and deposit of extracts therefrom with Registrar-General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person licensed under section 9 shall keep in English, or in the 
vernacular language in ordinary use in the district or State in which the 
marriage was solemnized, and in such form as the 

2[State] 
Government by which he was licensed may from time to time prescribe, a 
register-book of all marriages solemnized under this Part in his presence, and 
shall deposit in the office of the 

3[Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages] for the territories under the 
administration of the said 

2[State] 
Government, in such form and at such intervals as that Government may 
prescribe, true and duly authenticated extracts from his register-book of all 
entries made therein since the last of those intervals.]
 

4[***]
  







</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>63</number> 
Searches in register-book and copies of entries.—Every 
person licensed under this Act to grant certificates of marriages, and keeping 
a marriage-register-book under section 62 shall, at all reasonable times, allow 
search to be made in such book, and shall, on payment of the proper fee, give a 
copy, certified under his hand, of any entry therein.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>64</number> 
Books in which marriages of Indian Christians under Part I or Part III are 
registered.—The 
provisions of sections 62 and 63, as to the form of register-book depositing 
extracts therefrom, allowing searches thereof, and giving copies of the entries 
therein, shall, mutatis mutandis, apply to the books kept under section 
37.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>65</number> 
Part VI not to apply to Roman Catholics.—This 
Part of this Act, except so much of sections 62 and 63 as are referred to in 
section 64, shall not apply to marriages between Roman Catholics.
 Saving 
of certain marriages.—But 
nothing herein contained shall invalidate any marriage celebrated between Roman 
Catholics under the provisions of Part V of Act No. 25 of 18641, 
previous to the twenty-third day of February, 1865.








</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>

1[<number>66</number> False 
oath, declaration, notice or certificate for procuring marriage.—Whoever, 
for the purpose of procuring a marriage or licence of marriage, intentionally,—
 <section>         <number>a</number> where an 
oath or declaration is required by this Act, or by any rule or custom of a 
Church according to the rites and ceremonies of which a marriage is intended to 
be solemnized, such Church being the Church of England or of Scotland or of 
Rome, makes a false oath or declaration, or
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> where a 
notice or certificate is required by this Act, signs a false notice or 
certificate,
 shall be deemed to have 
committed the offence punishable under section 193 of the Indian Penal Code, 
1860 (45 of 1860) with imprisonment of either description for a term which may 
extend to three years and, at the discretion of the court, with fine.]
  





</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>67</number> 
Forbidding by false personation, issue of certificate by Marriage Registrar.—Whoever, 
forbids the issue, by a Marriage Registrar, of a certificate, by falsely 
representing himself to be a person whose consent to the marriage is required 
by law, knowing or believing such representation to be false, or not having 
reason to believe it to be true, shall be deemed guilty of the offence 
described in section 205 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860).
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>

1[<number>68</number> Solemnizing 
marriage without due authority.—Whoever, 
not being authorized by section 5 of this Act to solemnize marriages, 
solemnizes or professes to solemnize, in the absence of a Marriage Registrar of 
the district in which the ceremony takes place, a marriage between persons one 
or both of whom is or are a Christian or Christians, shall be punished with 
imprisonment which may extend to ten years, or (in lieu of a sentence, of 
imprisonment for seven years or upwards) with transportation for a term of not 
less than seven years, and not exceeding ten years,
 

2[***]
 and shall also be liable to 
fine.]
  





</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>69</number> 
Solemnizing marriage out of proper time, or without witnesses.—Whoever 
knowingly and wilfully solemnizes a marriage between persons, one or both of 
whom is or are a Christian or Christians, at any time other than between the 
hours of six in the morning and seven in the evening, or in the absence of at 
least two credible witnesses other than the person solemnizing the marriage, 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, 
and shall also be liable to fine.
 Saving 
of marriages solemnized under special licence.—This 
section does not apply to marriages solemnized under special licences granted 
by the Anglican Bishop of the Diocese or by his Commissary, nor to marriages 
performed between the hours of seven in the evening and six in the morning by a 
Clergyman of the Church of Rome, when he has received the general or special 
licence in that behalf mentioned in section 10.
 

1[Nor does this 
section apply to marriages solemnized by Clergyman of the Church of Scotland 
according to the rules, rites, ceremonies and customs of the Church of 
Scotland.]
  




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>70</number> 
Solemnizing without notice or within fourteen days after notice, marriage with 
minor.—Any 
Minister of Religion licensed to solemnize marriages under this Act, who, 
without a notice in writing, or, when one of the parties to the marriage is a 
minor and the required consent of the parents or guardians to such marriage has 
not been obtained, within fourteen days after the receipt by him of notice of 
such marriage, knowingly and wilfully solemnizes a marriage under Part III, 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, 
and shall also be liable to fine.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>71</number> 
Issuing certificate, or marrying, without publication of notice.—A 
Marriage Registrar under this Act, who commits any of the following offences:—
 <section>         <number>1</number> knowingly 
and wilfully issues any certificate for marriage, or solemnizes any marriage, 
without publishing the notice of such marriage as directed by this Act;
                   
marrying after expiry of notice.—1[(2) 
after the expiration of two months after the copy of the notice has been 
entered as required by section 40 in respect of any marriage, solemnizes such 
marriage;]
                   
solemnizing marriage with minor within fourteen days, without authority of 
court or without sending copy of notice.—(3) 
solemnizes, without an order of a competent court authorizing him to do so, any 
marriage, when one of the parties is a minor, before the expiration of fourteen 
days after the receipt of the notice of such marriage, or without sending, by 
the post or otherwise, a copy of such notice to the Senior Marriage Registrar 
of the district if there be more Marriage Registrars of the district than one, 
and if he himself be not the Senior Marriage Registrar;
                   
issuing certificate against authorized prohibition.—(4) 
issues any certificate the issue of which has been prohibited, as in this Act 
provided, by any person authorized to prohibit the issue thereof,
 shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, and shall also be 
liable to fine.
  




</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>72</number> 
Issuing certificate after expiry of notice, or, in case of minor, within 
fourteen days after notice, or against authorized prohibition.—Any 
Marriage Registrar knowingly and wilfully issuing any certificate for marriage 
after the expiration of 

1[two months] 
after the notice has been entered by him as aforesaid,
 or 
knowingly and wilfully issuing, without the order of a competent court 
authorizing him so to do, any certificate for marriage, where one of the 
parties intending marriage is a minor, before the expiration of fourteen days 
after the entry of such notice, or any certificate the issue of which has been 
forbidden as aforesaid by any person authorized in this behalf,
 shall be 
deemed to have committed an offence under section 166 of the Indian Penal Code, 
1860 (45 of 1860).
  




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
  
 <article><number>73</number> 
Persons authorized to; solemnize marriage (other than clergy of Churches of 
England, Scotland or Rome).—Whoever 
being authorized under this Act to solemnize a marriage, 
 and not 
being a Clergyman of the Church of England solemnizing a marriage after due 
publication of banns, or under a licence from the Anglican Bishop of the 
Diocese or a Surrogate duly authorized in that behalf,
 or, not 
being a Clergyman of the Church of Scotland, solemnizing a marriage according 
to the rules, rites, ceremonies and customs of that Church,
 or, not 
being a Clergyman of the Church of Rome, solemnizing a marriage according to 
the rites, rules, ceremonies and customs of that Church,
 
issuing certificate, or marrying, without publishing notice, or after expiry of 
certificate.—knowingly 
and wilfully issues any certificate for marriage under this Act, or solemnizes 
any marriage between such persons as aforesaid, without publishing, or causing 
to be affixed, the notice of such marriage as directed in Part III of this Act, 
or after the expiration of two months after the certificate has been issued by 
him;
 
issuing certificate for, or solemnizing, marriage with minor, within fourteen 
days after notice.—or 
knowingly and wilfully issues any certificate for marriage, or solemnizes a 
marriage between such persons when one of the persons intending marriage is a 
minor, before the expiration of fourteen days after the receipt of notice of 
such marriage, or without sending, by the post or otherwise, a copy of such 
notice to the Marriage Registrar, or, if there be more Marriage Registrars than 
one, to the Senior Marriage Registrar of the district;
 
issuing certificate authorizedly forbidden.—or 
knowingly and wilfully issues any certificate the issue of which has been 
forbidden, under this Act, by any person authorized to forbid the issue;
 
solemnizing marriage authorizedly forbidden.—or 
knowingly and wilfully solemnizes any marriage forbidden by any person 
authorized to forbid the same;
 shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to four years, and shall 
also be liable to fine.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>74</number> 
Unlicensed person granting certificate pretending to be licensed.—Whoever, 
not being licensed to grant a certificate of marriage under Part VI of this 
Act, grants such certificate intending thereby to make it appear that he is so 
licensed, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
five years, and shall also be liable to fine.
 

1[Whoever, being 
licensed to grant certificate of marriage under Part VI of this Act, without 
just cause refused or wilfully neglects or omits, to perform any of the duties 
imposed upon him by that Part shall be punished with fine which may extend to 
one hundred rupees.]
  




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>75</number> 
Destroying or falsifying register-book.—Whoever, 
by himself or another, wilfully destroys or injures any register-book or the 
counterfoil certificates thereof, or any part thereof, or any authenticated 
extract therefrom,
 or 
falsely makes or counterfeits any part of such register-book or counterfoil 
certificates, 
 or 
wilfully inserts any false entry in any such register-book or counterfoil 
certificate or authenticated extract,
 shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years, and 
shall also be liable to fine.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>76</number> 
Limitation of prosecutions under Act.—The 
prosecution for every offence punishable under this Act shall be commenced 
within two years after the offence is committed.



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>77</number> 
What matters need not be proved in respect of marriage in accordance with Act.—Whenever 
any marriage has been solemnized in accordance with the provisions of sections 
4 and 5, it shall not be void merely on account of any irregularity in respect 
of any of the following matters, namely:—
 <section>         <number>1</number> any 
statement made in regard to the dwelling of the persons married, or to the 
consent of any person whose consent to such marriage is required by law,
 </section><section>         <number>2</number> the notice 
of the marriage;
 </section><section>         <number>3</number> the 
certificate or translation thereof;
 </section><section>         <number>4</number> the time 
and place at which the marriage has been solemnized;
 </section><section>         <number>5</number> the 
registration of the marriage.
</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>78</number> 
Corrections or errors.—Every 
person charged with the duty of registering any marriage, who discovers any 
error in the form or substance of any such entry, may, within one month next 
after the discovery of such error, in the presence of the persons married, or 
in case of their death or absence, in the presence of two other credible 
witnesses, correct the error by entry in the margin, without any alteration of 
the original entry, and shall sign the marginal entry, and add thereto the date 
of such correction, and such person make the like marginal entry in the 
certificate thereof.
 And every 
entry made under this section shall be attested by the witnesses in whose 
presence it was made.
 And, in 
case such certificate has been already sent to the 

1[Registrar-General 
of Births, Deaths and Marriages], such person shall make and send in like 
manner a separate certificate of the original erroneous entry, and of the 
marginal correction therein made.
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>79</number> 
Searches and copies of entries.—Every 
person solemnizing a marriage under this Act, and hereby required to register 
the same,
 and every 
Marriage Registrar or 

1[Registrar 
General of Births, Deaths and Marriages] having the custody for the time being 
of any register of marriages, or any certificate, or duplicate, or copies of 
the certificate, under this Act,
 shall, on 
payment of the proper fees, at all reasonable times, allow searches to be made 
in such register, or for such certificate, or duplicate or copies, and give a 
copy under his hand of any entry in the same.
  



</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>80</number> 
Certified copy of entry in marriage-register, etc., to be evidence.—Every 
certified copy, purporting to be signed by the person entrusted under this Act 
with the custody of any marriage-register or certificate, or duplicate, 
required to be kept or delivered under this Act, of any entry of a marriage in 
such register or of any such certificate or duplicate, shall be received 
evidence of the marriage purporting to be so entered, or of the facts 
purporting to be so certified therein, without further proof of such register 
or certificate, or duplicate, or of any entry therein, respectively, or of such 
copy.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>

1[<number>81</number> Certificates 
of certain marriages to be sent to Central Government.—The 
Registrar-General of Births, Deaths and Marriages 

2[***] shall, at 
the end of every quarter in each year, select, from the certificates of 
marriages forwarded to 

3[him], during 
such quarter, the certificates of the marriages of which 

4[the Government 
by whom he was appointed] may desire that evidence shall be transmitted to 
England, and shall send the same certificates, signed by 

3[him] to the


5[Central 
Government].]
  








</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article><number>82</number> 
State Government to prescribe fees.—Fees 
shall be chargeable under this Act for—
 receiving 
and publishing notices of marriages;
 issuing


1[certificates for 
marriages] by Marriage Registrars, and registering marriages by the same;
 entering 
protest against, or prohibitions of, the issue of 

2[certificates for 
marriage] by the said Registrars;
 searching 
register-books or certificates, or duplicates, of copies thereof;
 giving 
copies of entries in the same under sections 63 and 79,
 the State 
Government shall fix the amount of such fees respectively, and may from time to 
time vary or remit them either generally or in special cases, as to it may seem 
fit.
  





</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> Power to make rules.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The 

2[State] 
Government 

3[may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] in regard to the disposal of 
the fees mentioned in section 82, the supply of register books, and the 
preparation and submission of returns of marriage solemnized under this Act.
 

4[(2) Every rule 
made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before the State Legislature.]
  







</section></article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> Power to prescribe 
fees and rules for Indian States.—[Rep. 
by the A.O. 1950.]
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> Power to declare who 
shall be District Judge.—The


1[State] 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare who shall, in 
any place to which this Act applies, be deemed to be the District Judge.
  




</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>
<number>86</number> Powers and functions 
exercisable as regards Indian States.—[Rep. 
by the A.O. 1950.]
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>
<number>87</number> Saving of Consular 
marriages.—Nothing 
in this Act applies to any marriage performed by any Minister, Consult, or 
Consular Agent between subjects of the State which he represents and according 
to the laws of such State.
</article> 
 The Indian 
Christian Marriage
Act, 1872
  
 <article>
<number>88</number> Non-validation of 
marriages within prohibited degrees.—Nothing 
in this Act shall be deemed to validate any marriage which the personal law 
applicable to either of the parties forbids him or her to enter into.



</article><form>
 

The Indian 
Christian Marriage Act, 1872
 


 
 


SCHEDULE V
 


[Enactments Repealed.]
 


[Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 
1938), sec. 2 and Sch. Pt. I]
 


 
 


—————
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>