<act><title>


The Ozone depleting substances
(Regulation and Control) Rules, 20001</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Ozone 
Depleting Substances (Regulation and Control) Rules, 2000. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “Act” means the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> “authority” means an authority mentioned in columns (4) and (6) of 
  Schedule V; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> “base level' means the quantity of ozone depleting substance produced 
  or consumed, as the case may be, in the year or average of the years listed in 
  column (3) of Schedule II and Schedule III; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> “consumption” with respect to any ozone depleting substance means the 
  amount of that substance produced in India in addition to the amount imported, 
  less the amount exported <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[and the amount used as feedstock 
  substance which is used entirely in the manufacture of other chemicals, with 
  negligible emissions, if any;] 
 </section><section><number>e</number> “calculated level of production, sale, import or export”, as the case 
  may be, means level determined by multiplying quantity of the ozone depleting 
  substance by its ozone depleting potential specified in column (5) of 
  Schedule I; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> “calculated level of consumption” shall be determined by adding 
  together, calculated levels of production and imports and subtracting 
  calculated level of exports; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> “Group” means collection of one or more ozone depleting substances as 
  specified in column (4) of Schedule I; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> “manufacture” in relation to any ozone depleting substance includes— 
  
 </section><section><number>i</number> any process or part of a process for making, altering, finishing, 
  packing, labelling, blending or otherwise <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[treating of any ozone 
  depleting substance] with a view to sell, distribute or use but does not 
  include the repacking or breaking up of any ozone depleting substance in the 
  ordinary course of retail business; and 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> any process in which a preparation containing ozone depleting 
  substance is formulated; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “ozone depleting substance” means the ozone depleting substances 
  specified in column (2) of Schedule I, whether existing by itself or in a 
  mixture, excluding any such substance or mixture (blend) which is in a 
  manufactured product other than a container used for the transportation or 
  storage of such substance; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> “parties” means, unless the text otherwise indicates, parties to the 
  protocol <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[and parties to the amendments thereof]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> “pre-shipment applications” are those treatments applied directly 
  preceding and in relation to export, to meet the phytosanitary or sanitary 
  requirements of the importing country or existing phytosanitary or sanitary 
  requirements of the exporting country; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> “production” in relation to any ozone depleting substance means the 
  manufacture of an ozone depleting substance from any raw material or feedstock 
  chemicals, but does not include­— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> the manufacture of a substance that is used and entirely consumed 
    (except for trace quantity) in the manufacture of other chemicals; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> quantities which are produced incidentally in the manufacture of 
    other chemical substances; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> quantities which are recycled or reused; or . 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> quantities which are destroyed by technologies to be specified by 
    the Central Government; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> “Protocol” means the Montreal Protocol on Substances that Deplete the 
  Ozone Layer, adopted on 16th September, 1987; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> “quarantine applications”, with respect to Group VIII of Schedule I 
  ozone depleting substance, are treatments to prevent the introduction, 
  establishment and or spread of quarantine pests (including diseases), or to 
  ensure their control as specified by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> “recovery” means collection and storage of ozone depleting substances 
  from machinery, equipment, or containment vessel during servicing or prior to 
  disposal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> “reclamation” means reprocessing and upgrading of a recovered ozone 
  depleting substance through such methods as filtering, drying, distillation 
  and, or chemical treatment in order to restore the substance to a specified 
  standard of performance; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule annexed to these rules. 
</subsection></section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> </title><title>Regulation of production and consumption of ozone 
depleting substances. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall produce or cause to produce 
any ozone depleting substance after the date specified in column (5) of Schedule 
V unless he is registered with the authority specified in column (4) of that 
Schedule: 
 Provided that for the twelve month period commencing on the date specified in 
column (6) of Schedule II, and in each twelve month period thereafter, no person 
shall produce or cause to be produced any group of ozone depleting substances in 
excess of the corresponding percentage of his calculated base level of 
production specified in column (4) of that Schedule <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[excluding the 
substances which is for the use of as feedstock in the manufacture of other 
chemicals, with negligible emissions, if any]: 
 Provided further that calculated level of consumption of such substances in 
India shall, as a percentage of calculated level of consumption in base years 
does not exceed the number specified in column (5) of Schedule II. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall produce or cause to produce ozone depleting substances 
specified as Group I and Group III in column (4) of Schedule I during the period 
from 1st August, 2000 to 1st January, 2010 in excess of the quantity specified 
in column (4) of Schedule III and the calculated level of 
consumption of such substances in India shall as a percentage of calculated 
level of consumption in base year does not exceed the number specified in column 
(5) of that Schedule. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> A person having received financial assistance from the 
Multilateral Fund in accordance with articles 10 and 10A of the protocol to 
which the Central Government is a party for gradual reduction of production and 
consumption of ozone depleting substances— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> specified as Group I and Group III in column (4) of Schedule I shall, 
  limit the production of ozone depleting substances as specified in column (4) 
  of Schedule III; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> specified as Group IV in column (4) of Schedule I shall limit the 
  production and consumption of ozone depleting substance specified in columns 
  (4) and (5) of Schedule II; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> specified as Group I and Group II in column (4) of Schedule I shall 
  limit the consumption of ozone depleting substance as specified in column (5) 
  of Schedule III, in each year from 1st August, 2000 to 1st January, 2010 to 
  quantities specified in column (4) for each year given in column (6) of 
  Schedule III as per the agreement approved by the Executive Committee of the 
  Multilateral Fund. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> In order to implement the agreement, referred to in sub-rule (3), the 
Central Government shall introduce implementation modalities, such as quota 
system for production and consumption of chlorofluorocarbons and carbon 
tetrachloride for non-feedstock use and verification system for feedstock 
application, and non-compliance with such modalities shall result in 
consequential penalties laid down in the said agreements.] 
  



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Prohibition on 
export to or import from countries not specified in Schedule VI.—No 
person shall import or cause to import from or export or cause to export to, any 
country not specified in Schedule VI any ozone depleting substance after the 
commencement of these rules.
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Ozone depleting substances are to be exported to or imported from 
countries specified in Schedule VI under a licence. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No person 
shall import or cause to import from or export or cause to export to, any 
country specified in Schedule VI, any ozone depleting substance unless he 
obtains a licence issued by the authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No licence shall be issued under sub-rule (1) unless the said authority 
is satisfied that the grant of licence shall not cause calculated level of 
consumption of that group of ozone depleting substances 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***] in the relevant twelve month period, as a percentage of 
corresponding calculated consumption in base years, to exceed the number 
specified in column (5) of Schedule II. 
 <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[***] (4) The calculated base level of consumption and the 
calculated base level of production for India as a whole for each group of ozone 
depleting substances shall be notified by the Central Government. 



 
 “(3) No licence shall be issued under sub-rule (1) unless the 
  said authority is satisfied that the grant of licence shall not cause 
  calculated level of consumption of ozone depleting substance given in Group 1 
  and Group III in column (4) of Schedule I in the relevant twelve months period 
  as specified in column (6) of Schedule III, as a percentage of calculated 
  consumption in base years to exceed the number specified in column (5) of that 
  Schedule.”. 

</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number>
Regulation of the sale of ozone depleting substances.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall 
either himself or by any other person on his behalf or enterprise sell, stock or 
exhibit for sale or distribute any ozone depleting substance after the date 
specified in column (5) of Schedule V unless he is registered with the authority 
specified in column (4) of that Schedule:
 
Provided that no person or 
enterprise shall sell ozone depleting substances specified in column (3) of 
Schedule IV for activities specified in column (2) of that Schedule unless the 
person engaged in that activity has got himself registered with the authority 
and has given a declaration in accordance with these rules and the person 
selling ozone depleting substances has verified particulars of the registration 
given in the declaration with the certificate of registration as per procedure 
specified in Part II of Schedule XII:
 
Provided further that 
after the date specified in column (4) of Schedule IV, no person or enterprise 
shall sell, stock, distribute or exhibit or cause to be sold, stocked, 
distributed or exhibited ozone depleting substances specified in column (3) for 
activities specified in column (2) of that Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall either 
himself or by any person on his behalf, or enterprise sell, stock or exhibit for 
sale or distribute any ozone depleting substance to any person or enterprise who 
has informed the Central Government that he or that enterprise shall not use the 
specified ozone depleting substances in manufacturing or other activities after 
the date specified by such person or as the case may be, the enterprise.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
shall notify the list of persons, ozone depleting substances and dates informed 
to it under sub‑rule (2).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number>
Regulation on the purchase of ozone depleting substances.—No person shall 
either himself or by any person on his behalf or enterprise, purchase ozone 
depleting substances specified in column (3) of Schedule IV from any person for 
making stock or for using such ozone depleting substances for activities 
specified in column (2) of that Schedule unless he has given the declaration 
specified in Part I of Schedule XII to the seller of such substances within the 
time period specified in serial number 4 of column (5) of Schedule V.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number>   Regulation on the 
use of ozone depleting substance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person or enterprise shall engage in any activity specified in column (2) of 
Schedule IV that uses ozone depleting substances specified in column (3) of that 
Schedule after the date specified in column (5) of Schedule V unless he is 
registered with the authority specified in column (4) of that Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall engage 
in any activity specified in column (2) of Schedule IV using ozone depleting 
substances specified in column (3) of that Schedule after the date specified in 
column (5) of Schedule V unless the products are labelled to indicate the ozone 
depleting substance they contain.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No person shall engage 
in any activity specified in column (2) of Schedule IV using ozone depleting 
substances specified in column (3) after the date specified in column (4) of 
that Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No person shall engage 
in any activity specified in column (2) of Schedule IV without using label 
indicating absence of use of ozone­ depleting substance mentioned in column (3) 
after the date specified in column (4) of that Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A person, having 
received financial and technical assistance from the Multilateral Fund in 
accordance with the Articles 10 and 10A of the Montreal Protocol on Substances 
that Deplete the Ozone Layer, to which the Central Government is a party for 
phasing out of ozone depleting substances specified in column (2) of Schedule II 
used in activities specified in column (2) of Schedule IV, either himself or by 
any person on his behalf or through any enterprise, shall not engage in such 
activity as specified in column (2) of Schedule IV using ozone depleting 
substances specified in column (3) of the Schedule, after the date of completion 
of the conversion work or signing of the Handing Over Protocol, or the 
submission of the completion report to change from ozone depleting substance 
technology to non-ozone depleting substance technology and the said date be 
registered with the authority specified in column (4) of the Schedule V.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any person or 
enterprise having received, financial assistance from the Multilateral Fund in 
accordance with the Articles 10 and 10A of the Montreal Protocol on Substances 
that Deplete the Ozone Layer shall submit an affidavit or declaration with the 
authority specified in column (4) of Schedule V stating that replaced equipment, 
resulted from completion of conversion process from ozone depleting substance 
technology to non-ozone depleting substance technology, have been destroyed, 
dismantled, rendered unusable and that no ozone depleting substance should be 
used after the date of the completion of project and the said date be registered 
with the authority specified in the column (4) of the Schedule V.
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Prohibition on new investments with ozone depleting substances. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall establish or expand or cause to establish or 
expand any manufacturing facility for production of any ozone depleting 
substance after the date specified in column (7) of Schedule II and Schedule 
III. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall establish or expand or cause to establish or expand any 
manufacturing facility, with a view to manufacturing products which contain, or 
are made with, any ozone depleting substance after the date specified in column 
(8) of Schedule II and Schedule III. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> The provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2) of this rule shall 
not apply to any ozone depleting substance which is produced for the use of as 
feedstock in the manufacturing of other chemicals, with negligible emissions, if 
any.] (3) A person having received financial and technical assistance from 
the Multilateral-Fund in accordance with the Articles 10 and 10A of the Montreal 
Protocol on Substances that Deplete the Ozone Layer for phasing out of ozone 
depleting substances specified in column (2) of Schedule II used in activities 
specified in column (2) of Schedule IV to which the Central Government is a 
party, shall not establish or expand or cause to establish or expand the 
manufacturing facility for production of any ozone depleting substance or with a 
view to manufacturing products which contain or are made with any ozone 
depleting substances after the approval of the project for conversion and date 
of completion of the conversion work from the ozone depleting substance 
technology to non-ozone depleting substance technology. 


  

</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Regulation of import, export and sale of products made with or 
containing ozone depleting substances. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall import 
<title></title>or cause to import any product specified in column (2) of 
Schedule VII which are made with or contain ozone depleting substances specified 
in column (3) after the date specified in column (4) of that Schedule unless he 
obtains a license issued by the authority: 
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Provided that no person shall import or cause to import any 
product specified in column (2) of Schedule VII which are made with or contain 
ozone depleting substances as listed in Group I, Group II and Group III in 
Schedule I from the date of commencement of the Ozone Depleting Substances 
(Regulation and Control) Amendment Rules, 2007: 
 Provided further that such products] which do not contain such ozone 
depleting substances shall carry a label to that effect before its import is 
allowed after the date specified in column (4) of Schedule VII. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person or enterprise shall export or cause to export any product 
specified in column (2) of Schedule VII unless such product carries a label 
specifying whether or not the product has been made with or contains, as the 
case may be, ozone depleting substances specified in column (3) of that 
Schedule, after the date specified in column (5) of that Schedule. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No person shall either himself or by any other person or enterprise on 
his behalf sell, stock or exhibit for sale or distribute any product resulting 
out of activities, or provide services, specified in column (2) of Schedule IV 
using ozone depleting substances specified in column (3) after the date 
specified in column (4) of that Schedule. 


  

</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Regulation on 
reclamation and destruction of ozone depleting substances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall reclaim or cause to reclaim any ozone depleting substance after 
the date specified in column (5) of Schedule V unless he has registered with the 
authority specified in column (4) of that Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person shall 
destroy or cause to destroy any ozone depleting substance after the date 
specified in column (5) of Schedule V unless he has registered with the 
authority specified in column (4) of that Schedule.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>12</number> Regulation on manufacture, 
import and export of compressors.—No person shall manufacture, 
import or export compressors after the date specified in column (5) of Schedule 
v unless he has registered with 
the authority specified in column (4) of that Schedule.</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Procedure for registration, cancellation of registration and 
appeal against such orders. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The procedure for registration and 
conditions of registration under various provisions of these rules shall be as 
specified in Schedule IX. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The registering authority shall not register if he is not satisfied that 
the procedure for registration or conditions of registration are fulfilled. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The registering authority shall cancel the registration if he is 
satisfied that condition(s) of registration has (have) been violated. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The registering authority shall give the concerned person an opportunity 
of being heard before passing orders under sub-rules (2) and (3) and the orders 
shall be made in writing. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> An appeal against an order of the registering authority shall lie with 
the authority specified in column (6) of Schedule V within thirty days of 
communication of such order. 
 <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[***] 
 </section><section>[<number>8</number> Every application for registration or renewal of 
registration under these rules shall be disposed of within sixty days from the 
date of receipt of such complete application by the authority specified in 
column (4) of Schedule V. (9) The concerned registering authority specified 
in column (4) of Schedule V shall decide the issue fo cancellation of any 
registration granted under these rules within sixty days from the date of 
service of the show cause notice given by him to the registration holder.] 


 
  “(6) The registration shall be valid for the period 
  specified in Schedule IX and its renewal shall be necessary. (7) The 
  procedure for and conditions of renewal of registration shall be the same as 
  applicable to registration.”.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Monitoring and 
reporting requirements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person who produces, imports, exports or sells any ozone depleting 
substance shall maintain records and file reports in the manner specified in 
Part I of Schedule X.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person stocking 
or purchasing any ozone depleting substance for use in activities specified in 
column (2) of Schedule IV shall maintain records and file reports in the manner 
specified in Part II of Schedule X.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every person who has 
received technical or financial assistance from any international organisation 
or any financial assistance, which includes concession or exemption from payment 
of duties, from the Central Government, shall maintain records and file reports 
in the manner specified in Part III of Schedule X and the list of such persons 
shall be notified by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every person who has 
facility to reclaim an ozone depleting substance shall maintain records and file 
reports in the manner specified in Part IV of Schedule X.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every person who has 
facility to destroy any ozone depleting substance shall maintain records and 
file reports in the manner specified in Part V of Schedule X.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every person who 
manufactures, imports, exports or sells compressors shall maintain records and 
file reports in the manner specified in Part VI of Schedule X.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The records maintained 
in accordance with the above sub‑rules shall be made available for inspection as 
specified in Part VII of Schedule X.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Exemption.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Nothing contained in these rules shall apply to applications or circumstances 
specified in Schedule VIII.
 
 
</section></article><form>
 

The 
Ozone depleting substances 
(Regulation and Control) Rules, 
2000
 

 
 

Schedule 
x
 

[See rules 14(1), (2), (3), (4), (5), 
(6) and (7)]
 

Part 
I
 

A. 
Records to be 
Maintained
 

Records regarding production of 
ozone depleting substances
 

     
(1)   Dated records and related documents in respect of each producing 
plant, of—
 

      (a) 
  The actual quantity of each ozone depleting substances 
produced;
 

      (b) 
  The actual quantity of each ozone depleting substance used as feed stock, 
and
 

       
(c)   Information specified in 2(b) and 2(c) below. Records regarding sale 
and offer for sale of ozone depleting substances.
 

     
(2)   Dated records and related documents in respect of—
 

      (a) 
  The actual quantity of each ozone depleting substances purchased; 

 

      (b) 
  The actual quantity of each ozone depleting substances sold within India; 
the name and address of the recipient of the each shipment and the purpose for 
which ozone depleting substances was purchased by the recipient. These purposes 
to be maintained are:
 

       
(i)   Manufacture of aerosols
 

       
(ii)   Manufacture of foam products
 

      
(iii)   Manufacture of fire extinguishers and fire extinguishing 
systems
 

      
(iv)   Manufacture of Mobile Air-conditioners
 

      
(v)   Manufacture of other Refrigeration and Air-conditioning 
products.
 

      
(vi)   Solvents use
 

     
(vii)   Exempted use
 

    
(viii)   Selling
 

      
(ix)   Others (please specify).
 

Records regarding exports of Ozone 
depleting substances.
 

     
(3)   Dated records and related documents containing information in 
respect of each column of Form 3 or 4, as the case may be, of Schedule 
XI.
 

Records regarding imports of ozone 
depleting substances
 

     
(4)   Dated records and related documents containing information in 
respect of each column of Form 5 or 6, as the case may be, of Schedule 
XI.
 

Record and related document 
regarding manufacture, import and export of compressor.
 

     
(5)   Dated records and related document containing information in 
respect of each column of Form 12 or 13, as the case may be, of Schedule 
XI.
 

            
Declaration signed by the recipient in Form 12 of Schedule XI.
 

B. 
Reports to be 
submitted
 

     
(1)   Report on production of ozone depleting substances as per Form 1 
of Schedule XI.
 

     
(2)   Report on imports of ozone depleting substances as per Form 2 of 
Schedule XI.
 

     
(3)   Report on exports of ozone depleting substances as per Form 3 of 
Schedule XI.
 

     
(4)   Report on sales of ozone depleting substances as per Form 4 
of Schedule XI.
 

     
(5)   Reports mentioned in Sr. Nos. l to 3 above shall be submitted to 
the Ministry of Environment and Forests. Reports mentioned in Sl. No. 4 
above shall be submitted to the registering authority specified in column (4) of 
Schedule V, who will submit compiled version of the reports, duly countersigned 
by such authority to the Ministry of Environment and Forests in hard copy as 
well as in floppy on request.
 

Part 
II
 

A. 
Records to be 
maintained
 

Records regarding purchase of ozone 
depleting substances for use in activities specified in column (2) of Schedule 
IV.
 

     
(1)   Dated records of—
 

      
(a)   the actual quantity of each ozone depleting substance purchased 
from an Indian supplier and the name and address of the Indian 
supplier;
 

      
(b)   the actual quantity of each ozone depleting substance used 
separately for each plant and each activity.
 

B. 
Reports to be 
submitted
 

     
(1)   Report on purchase of ozone depleting substances as per Form 5 
of Schedule XI.
 

     
(2)   These reports shall be submitted to the concerned registering 
authority specified in column (4) of Schedule V, who will submit compiled 
version of the report to the Ministry of Environment and Forests. Individual 
reports will also be submitted by such authority to the Ministry of Environment 
and Forests on request.
 

Part 
III
 

A. 
records to be 
maintained
 

Records regarding purchase of 
non-ozone depleting substances by beneficiary companies for use in manufacture 
of products.
 

(1) Dated records and related 
documents in respect of—
 

     (1)   
Actual quantity of each non-ozone depleting substances purchased and the name 
and address of supplier;
 

     
(2)   Actual quantity of each non-ozone depleting substance used in 
manufacturing operations separately for each plant and each manufacturing 
operation.
 

. 
Reports to be 
submitted
 

     
(1)   Report on use of non-ozone depleting substances by beneficiary 
companies as per Form 6 of Schedule XI.
 

     
(2)   These reports shall be submitted to the concerned authority 
specified in column (4) of Schedule V, who will submit compiled version of the 
report to the Ministry of Environment and Forests. Individual reports will also 
be submitted by such authority to the Ministry of Environment and Forests on 
request.
 

Part 
IV
 

A. 
Records to be 
maintained
 

Records regarding 
reclamation
 

     
(1)   Dated records and related documents in respect of—
 

      
(a)   the actual quantity of each ozone depleting substance recovered; 
the name and address of the individual or company from which the ozone depleting 
substance is recovered and the name and address, if different of the site at 
which the ozone depleting substance is reclaimed;
 

B. 
Reports to be 
submitted
 

      
(1)  Report on reclamation of ozone depleting substances as per Form 7 of 
Schedule XI.
 

      
(2)  These reports shall be submitted to the Ministry of Environment and 
Forests through the concerned registering authority specified in column (4) of 
Schedule V.
 

Part 
V
 

A. 
Records to be 
maintained
 

Records regarding 
destruction
 

     
(1)   Dated records of—
 

      
(a)   the actual quantity of each ozone depleting substance destroyed 
on the basis of destruction efficiency of the facility employed.
 

B. 
Reports to be 
submitted     
 

      
(1)  Report on destruction of ozone depleting substances as per Form 7 of 
Schedule XI.
 

      
(2)  These reports shall be submitted to the Ministry of Environment and 
Forests through the concerned registering authority specified in column (4) of 
Schedule V.
 

Part 
VI
 

A. Records to be 
maintained
 

Records regarding manufacture, 
import and export of compressor
 

     (1)   
Dated records and related documents containing information in respect of each 
column of Form 12 of Schedule XI.
 

B. 
Reports to be 
submitted
 

     
(1)   Report on manufacture, import, export and sale of compressor and 
use of refrigerants in compressors sold as per Form 12 of Schedule 
XI.
 

     
(2)   These reports shall be submitted to the concerned registering 
authority specified in column (4) of Schedule V, who will submit compiled 
version of the reports to the Ministry of Environment and Forests. Individual 
reports will also be submitted by such authority to the Ministry of Environment 
and Forests on request.
 

Part 
VII
 

Production of 
records
 

(1) Records being maintained 
pursuant to requirements of rule 13 shall be available for inspection at any 
reasonable time on request by an officer of the registering authority specified 
in column (4) of Schedule V, not below in rank to a Section Officer to the 
Government of India, However, persons who are engaged in selling any locally 
produced ozone depleting substances, except ozone depleting substances specified 
in Group VIII of Schedule I, shall make records available for inspection at any 
reasonable time on request by an officer of the concerned producing enterprise 
not below in rank of Assistant Manager or on request by an officer of the 
Ministry of Environment and Forests not below in rank of a Section 
Officer.
 

 
 

 
 

 </form><form>
 

The 
Ozone depleting substances 
(Regulation and Control) Rules, 
2000
 

 
 

SCHEDULE 
VIII
 

[See rule 15]
 

Exemption
 

     (i)  
Use of Methyl Bromide, the ozone depleting substance covered in Group viii of Schedule 1, in quarantine and 
pre‑shipment applications.
 

    (ii)  Ozone 
depleting substance which are used in laboratory or for analytical purposes 
subject to following conditions:—
 

            
(a)  laboratory uses include equipment calibration; use as extraction 
solvents, diluents, or carriers for chemical analysis; biochemical research; 
inert solvents for chemical reactions, as a carrier or laboratory chemical and 
other critical analytical and laboratory purposes.
 

            
(b)  ozone depleting substances should have been manufactured to the 
following purities:—
 

                            
CTC (reagent 
grade)                                
99.5
 

                            
1, 1, 
1‑trichloroethane                             
99.0
 

                            
CFC‑11                                   
99.5
 

                            
CFC‑13                                   
99.5
 

                            
CFC‑12                                   
99.5
 

                            
CFC‑113                                 
99.5
 

                            
CFC‑114                                 
99.5
 

                            
Other w/Boiling P &gt; 
20°C                                              
99.5
 

                            
Other w/ Boiling P&lt; 
20°C                                              
99.0
 

            
(c)  these pure ozone depleting substances can be subsequently mixed 
by   manufacturers, agents, or distributors with other chemicals, as 
is customary for laboratory and analytical uses.
 

            
(d)  these high purity ozone depleting substance and mixtures containing 
ozone depleting substances shall be supplied only in re‑closable containers or 
high pressure cylinders smaller than three litres or in 10 millilitre or smaller 
glass ampoules, marked clearly as ozone depleting substances, restricted to 
laboratory use and analytical purposes and specifying that used or surplus ozone 
depleting substances should be collected and recycled, if practical. The ozone 
depleting substances should be destroyed if recycling is not 
practical.
 

   (iii)  Import, 
export, and production of Group IV, Schedule I ozone depleting substances is 
excluded from the definition of consumption if such imports and production meant 
to be used in manufacture of ozone depleting substances specified in Group I of 
Schedule I.
 

   (iv)  Import and 
export of any recovered or reclaimed ozone depleting substances is excluded from 
the definition of consumption.
 

    (v)  
Sub‑rule (1) of rule 10 shall not apply to non‑commercial sale of products which 
have been used for at least one year.
 

   (vi)  Any rule in 
public interest with specific approval of the Central Government.
 

  (vii)  Use of Group II 
substances of Schedule I for essential critical application shall as Defence 
Aircraft, Battle tank and Aviation Industries to be certified by an essential 
use panel.</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 2007 (w.e.f. 
18-9-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by S.O. 996(E), dated 27th August, 2003 (w.e.f. 
29-8-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 2007 (w.e.f. 
18-9-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 2007 (w.e.f. 
18-9-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 2007, for 
sub-rules (3) and (4) (w.e.f. 18-9-2007). Sub-rules (3) and (4), before 
substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> The words “except Group I and Group III given in column (4) 
of s chedule I” omitted by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 2007 (w.e.f. 
18-9-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Sub-rule (3) omitted by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 
2007 (w.e.f. 18-9-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 2007 (w.e.f. 
18-9-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th September, 2007, for 
“Provided that such products” (w.e.f. 18-9-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Sub-rules (6) and (7) omitted by S.O. 1561(E), dated 18th 
September, 2007 (w.e.f. 18-9-2007). Sub-rules (6) and (7), before omission, 
stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>