<act><tid>1170410</tid>
<title>THE REPEALING AND AMENDING ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 30 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 3rd September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act to repeal certain enactments and to amend certain other 
enactments.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1992685</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Repealing and Amending 
Act, <year>2001</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1431297</tid>
<number>2</number>Repeal of certain enactments.- The enactments specified in the 
First Schedule are hereby repealed to the extent mentioned in the 
fourth column thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>1417139</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of certain enactments.- The enactments specified in the 
Second Schedule are hereby amended to the extent and in the manner 
mentioned in the fourth column thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>712621</tid>
<number>4</number>Savings.- The repeal by this Act of any enactment shall not affect 
any other enactment in which the repealed enactment has been applied, 
incorporated or referred to; and this Act shall not affect the 
validity, invalidity, effect or consequences of anything already done 
or suffered, or any right, title, obligation or liability already 
acquired, accrued or incurred, or any remedy or proceeding in respect 
thereof, or an release or discharge of or from any debt, penalty, 
obligation, liability, claim or demand, or any indemnity already 
granted, or the proof of any past act or thing; nor shall this Act 
affect any principle or rule of law, or established jurisdiction, form 
or course of pleading, practice or procedure, or existing usage, 
custom, privilege, restriction, exemption, office or appointment, 
notwithstanding that the same res ectively may have been in any manner 
affirmed or recognised or derived by, in or from any enactment hereby 
repealed;
nor shall the repeal by this Act of any enactment revive or restore 
any jurisdiction, office, custom, liability, right, title, privilege, 
restriction, exemption, usage, practice, procedure or other matter or 
thing not now existing or in force.


</article>



 </act>