<act><title>

The  Noise  
    Pollution  (Regulation and  Control)  Rules,  20001</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Noise Pollution (Regulation and Control) Rules, 
    2000.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force into the date of their publication in the official Gazette.
 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise require.— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “Act” means the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 of 1986); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> “area/zone” means all areas which fall in either of the four categories 
  given in the Schedule annexed to these rules; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> “authority” means and includes any authority or officer 
  authorized by the Central Government, or as the case may be, the State 
  Government in accordance with the laws in force and includes a District 
  Magistrate, Police Commissioner, or any other officer not below the rank of 
  the Deputy Superintendent of Police designated for the maintenance of the 
  ambient air quality standards in respect of noise under any law for the time 
  being in force;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> "court" means a governmental body consisting of one or 
  more judges who sit to adjudicate disputes and administer justice and includes 
  any court of law presided over by a judge, judges or a magistrate and acting 
  as a tribunal in civil, taxation and criminal cases; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> "educational institution" means a school, seminary, college, 
  university, professional academies, training institutes or other educational 
  establishment, not necessarily a chartered institution and includes not only 
  buildings, but also all grounds necessary for the accomplishment of the full 
  scope of educational instruction, including those things essential to mental, 
  moral and physical development; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> "hospital" means an institution for the reception and care of sick, 
  wounded, infirm or aged persons, and includes government or private hospitals, 
  nursing homes and clinics;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>g</number> "person" shall include any company or association or body 
  of individuals, whether incorporated or not;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>h</number>] “State Government” in relation to a Union territory means 
  the Administrator thereof appointed under Article 239 of the Constitution. 

 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>i</number> “public place” means any place to which the public have 
  access, whether as of right or not, and includes auditorium, hotels, public 
  waiting rooms, convention centres, public offices, shopping malls, cinema 
  halls, educational institutions, libraries, open grounds and the like which 
  are visited by general public; and] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>j</number> “night time” means the period between 10.00 p.m. and 6.00 
  a.m.] 
  </section>






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Ambient air quality standards in respect of noise for different 
areas/zones. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The ambient air quality standards in respect of noise 
for different areas/zones shall be such as specified in the Schedule annexed to 
these rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[shall categorize] the area into 
industrial, commercial residential or silence areas/zones for the purpose of 
implementation of noise, standards for different area. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government shall take measures for abatement of noise including 
the noise emanating from vehicular movements, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[blowing of horns, 
bursting of sound emitting fire crackers, use of loud speakers or public address 
system and sound producing instruments] and ensure that the existing noise 
levels do not exceed the ambient air quality standards specified under these 
rules. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> All development authorities, local bodies and other concerned authorities 
while planning developmental activity or carrying out functions relating to town 
and country planning shall take into consideration all aspects of noise 
pollution as a parameter of quality of life to avoid noise menace and to achieve 
the objective of maintaining the ambient air quality standards in respect of 
noise. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> An area comprising not less than 100 metres around hospital, educational 
institutions and courts may be declared as silence area/zone for the purpose of 
these rules. 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Responsibility as to enforcement of noise pollution control measures.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The noise levels in any area/zone shall not exceed the ambient air quality 
    standards in respect of noise as specified in the Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    authority shall be responsible for the enforcement of noise pollution 
    control measures and the due compliance of the ambient air quality standards 
    in respect of noise. 
1[(3) The respective 
    State Pollution Control Boards or Pollution Control Committees in 
    consultation with the Central Pollution Control Board shall collect, compile 
    and publish technical and statistical data relating to noise pollution and 
    measures devised for its effective prevention, control and abatement.] 



 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Restrictions on the use of loud speakers/public address system 
</title><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[and sound producing instruments]. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A 
loud speaker or a public address system shall not be used except after obtaining 
written permission from the authority. 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum></title>[<number>2</number> A loud speaker or a public address system 
or any sound producing instrument or a musical instrument or a sound amplifier 
shall not be used at night time except in closed premises for communication 
within, like auditoria, conference rooms, community halls, banquet halls or 
during a public emergency.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>10</footcitenum></title>[<number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
sub-rule (2), the State Government may, subject to such terms and conditions as 
are necessary to reduce noise pollution, permit use of loud speakers or 
<title><footcitenum>11</footcitenum></title>[public address system and the like during nights 
hours] (between 10.00 p.m. to 12.00 midnight) on or during any cultural or 
religious festive occasion of a limited duration not exceeding fifteen days in 
all during a calendar year.] <title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum></title>[The concerned State 
Government shall generally specify in advance, the number and particulars of the 
days on which such exemption would be operative.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum></title>[<number>4</number> The noise level at the boundary of the 
public place, where loudspeaker or public address system or any other noise 
source is being used shall not exceed 10 dB (A) above the ambient noise 
standards for the area or 75 dB (A) whichever is lower;] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum></title>[<number>5</number> The peripheral noise level of a privately 
owned sound system or a sound producing instrument shall not, at the boundary of 
the private place, exceed by more than 5 dB (A) the ambient noise standards 
specified for the area in which it is used.] 







</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>5A</number> Restrictions on the use of horns, sound emitting 
construction equipments and bursting of fire crackers. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No horn 
shall be used in silence zones or during night time in residential areas except 
during a public emergency. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Sound emitting fire crackers shall not be burst in silence zone or during 
night time. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Sound emitting construction equipments shall not be used or operated 
during night time in residential areas and silence zones.] 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title>[<number>6</number> Consequences of any violation in silence zone/area. </title>—Whoever, in any place covered under the silence zone/area commits any of the following offence, he shall be liable for penalty under the provisions of the Act:— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> whoever, plays any music or uses any sound amplifiers, 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> whoever, beats a drum or tom-tom or blows a horn either musical or pressure, or trumpet or beats or sounds any instrument, or 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> whoever, exhibits any mimetic, musical or other performance of a nature to attract crowds. 
 </section><section>[<number>iv</number> whoever, bursts sound emitting fire crackers; or 
 </section><section><number>v</number> Whoever, uses a loud speaker or a public address system.] 
</section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Complaints to be made to the authority. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A person 
may, if the noise level exceeds the ambient noise standards by 10 d b (A) or 
more given in the corresponding columns against any area/zone <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[or, 
if there is a violation of any provision of these rules regarding restrictions 
imposed during night time], make a complaint to the authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority shall act on the complaint and take action against the 
violator in accordance with the provisions of these rules and any other law in 
force. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power to 
    prohibit etc. continuance of music sound or noise.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the authority is satisfied from the report of an officer in charge of a 
    police station or other information received by him that it is necessary to 
    do so in order to prevent annoyance, disturbance, discomfort or injury or 
    risk of annoyance, disturbance, discomfort or injury to the public or to any 
    person who dwell or occupy property on the vicinity, he may, by a written 
    order issue such directions as he may consider necessary to any person for 
    preventing, prohibiting, controlling or regulating:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  the incidence or continuance in or upon 
    any premises of—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  any vocal or instrumental music,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>  sounds caused by playing, beating, 
    clashing, blowing or use in any manner whatsoever of any instrument 
    including loudspeakers, public address system, application or apparatus or 
    contrivance which is capable of producing or re-producing sound, or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  the carrying on in or upon, any premises 
    of any trade, avocation or operation or process resulting in or attended 
    with noise.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    authority empowered under sub-rule (1) may, either on its own motion, or on 
    the application of any person aggrieved by an order made under sub-rule (1), 
    either rescind, modify or alter any such order:
 
Provided 
    that before any such application is disposed of, the said authority shall 
    afford to the applicant 1[and 
    to the original complainant, as the case may be,] an opportunity of 
    appearing before it either in person or by a person representing him and 
    showing cause against the order and shall, if it rejects any such 
    application either wholly or in part, record its reasons for such rejection.
 




 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The  Noise  
    Pollution  (Regulation and  Control)  Rules,  2000
 

 
 




    Schedule
 


[See
    rules 3(1) and 4(1)]
 




    Ambient Air Quality Standards in respect of Noise
 
 
 
Area Code
 
Category of Area / Zone
 
Limits in dB (A) Leq*

 
  
  
 
Day Time
 Night 
        Time

 
 
(A)
 
Industrial Area
 
75
 70

 
 
(B)
 
Commercial Area
 
65
 55

 
 
(C)
 
Residential Area
 
55
 45

 
 
(D)
 
Silence Zone
 
50
 40


 



    Note.—
 


1.  Day time shall mean 
    from 6.00 a.m. to 10.00 p.m.
 


2.  Night time shall mean 
    from 10.00 p.m. to 6.00 a.m.
 



1[3.  
    Silence zone is an area comprising not less than 100 metres around 
    hospitals, educational institutions, courts, religious places or any other 
    area which is declared as such by the competent authority.]
 


4.  Mixed categories of 
    areas may be declared as one of the four above mentioned categories by the 
    competent authority.
 


*dB(A) Leq denotes the 
    time weighted average  of the level of sound in decibels on Scale A which is 
    relatable to human hearing.
 


A “decibel” is a unit in 
    which noise is measured.
 


“A”, in dB(A) Leq, 
    denotes the frequency weighting in the measurement of noise and corresponds 
    to frequency response characteristics of the human ear.
 


Leq: It is an energy mean 
    of the noise level over a specified period.
 


 
 


----------------------
 


1.
Subs. by S.O. 1046 (E), 
    dated 22nd November, 2000 (w.e.f. 24-11-2000).
 


----------------------

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by S.O. 1046(E), dated 22nd November, 2000 (w.e.f. 
24-11-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by S.O. 1046(E), dated 22nd November, 2000 (w.e.f. 
24-11-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Clause (d) relettered as clause (g) thereof and clause (g) so 
relettered substituted by S.O. 1046(E), dated 22nd November, 2000 (w.e.f. 
24-11-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Clause (e) relettered as clause (h) by S.O. 1046(E), dated 
22nd November, 2000 (w.e.f. 24-11-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010 (w.e.f. 
11-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by S.O. 1046(E), dated 22nd November, 2000 (w.e.f. 
24-11-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010 (w.e.f. 
11-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010 (w.e.f. 
11-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010, for sub-rule 
(2) (w.e.f. 11-1-2010). Sub-rule (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by S.O. 1088(E), dated 11th October, 2002 (w.e.f. 
11-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010, for “public 
address systems during night hours” (w.e.f. 11-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Ins. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010 (w.e.f. 
11-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Ins. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010 (w.e.f. 
11-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Ins. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010 (w.e.f. 11-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Ins. by S.O. 50(E), dated 11th January, 2010 (w.e.f. 
11-1-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>