<act><tid>1186941</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL INDUSTRIAL SECURITY FORCE (AMENDMENT AND VALIDATION) ACT, 
<year>1999</year>.</title>

ACT NO. 40 OF <year>1999</year>
[ 29th December, <year>1999</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Central Industrial Security Force Act, 
<year>1968</year>, and to validate certain revision petitions disposed of under the 
rules made under the said Act.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fiftieth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>722575</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Central Industrial 
Security Force (Amendment and Validation) Act, <year>1999</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1981459</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of long title.- In the Central Industrial Security Force 
Act, <year>1968</year> (50 of <year>1968</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal  
  Act), for the long title, the following long title shall be 
substituted, namely:-" An Act to provide for the constitution and 
regulation of an armed force of the Union for the better protection 
and security of industrial undertakings owned by the Central 
Government, certain other industrial undertakings, employees of all 
such underta ings and to provide technical consultancy services to 
industrial establishments in the private sector and for matters 
connected therewith.".


</article>



<article><tid>630946</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after clause (c), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-' (ca)" industrial establishment" means an 
industrial undertaking or a company as defined under section 3 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or a firm registered under section 59 
of the Indian Partnership Act, <year>1932</year> (9 of <year>1932</year>) which is engaged in 
any ndustry, or in any trade, business or service;'.


</article>



<article><tid>1644686</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, the words" and to perform such other duties as may be 
entrusted to it by the Central Government" shall be inserted at the 
end.


</article>



<article><tid>1943669</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 8.- In section 8 of the principal Act,- (i) in 
clause (i), after the word" remove", the words", order for compulsory 
retirement of" shall be inserted;
<section><tid>1493305</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (ii), after sub- clause (c), the following sub- clauses 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" (d) withholding of increment of pay with or without cumulative 
effect; 
 (e) withholding of promotion; 
 (f) censure.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>539434</tid>
<number> 6</number> In section 9 of the principal Act,- (i) in sub- section 1, for 
the words, brackets and figure" subject to the provisions of 
sub- section (3)", the words, brackets, figures and letters" subject to 
the provisions of sub- section (2A), sub- section (2B) and sub- section 
 (3)" shall be substitute;
<section><tid>4274</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (2), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-" (2A) Any enrolled member of the Force aggrieved by 
an order passed in appeal under sub- section (1) may, within a period 
of six months from the date on which the order is communicated to him, 
prefer a revision petition against the order to such authority as may 
be prescribed and in disposing of the revision petition, the said 
authority shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed.

<subsection><tid>1043255</tid>
<number>2B</number>The authority, as may be prescribed for the purpose of this 
sub- section, on a revision petition preferred by an aggrieved enrolled 
member of the Force or suo moto, may call for, within a prescribed 
period, the records of any proceeding under sectio 8 or sub- section 
 (2) or sub- section (2A) and such authority may, after making inquiry 
in the prescribed manner, and subject to the provisions of this Act, 
pass such order thereon as it thinks fit.";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1727812</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- section (3), for the words, figures and brackets" under 
section 8 or under sub- section (2)", the words, figures, brackets and 
letters" under section 8, sub- section (2), sub- section (2A) or 
sub- section 10 of the principal Act, after clause (e), the following 
clauses shall be inserted, namely:- (2B)" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>834567</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 10.- In section" (f) to provide technical 
consultancy services relating to security of any private sector 
industrial establishments under section 14A;
<section><tid>955658</tid>
<number>g</number>to protect and safeguard the organisations owned or funded by the 
Government and the employees of such organisations as may be entrusted 
to him by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1941645</tid>
<number>h</number>any other duty which may be entrusted to him 
by the Central Government from time to time.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>327347</tid>
<number> 8</number> Insertion of new section 14A.- After section 14 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-" 14A. 
Technical Consultancy Service to industrial establishments.-
<section><tid>202934</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to any general directions which may be issued by the Central 
Government, it shall be lawful for the Director- General, on a request 
received from the Managing Director of an in ustrial establishment in 
the private sector or any other person authorised by him in this 
behalf, to direct the members of the Force to provide technical 
consultancy services relating to security, to such industrial 
establishments in such manner and on payment of such fee as may be 
prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>635541</tid>
<number>2</number>The fee received under sub- section (1) shall be credited to the 
Consolidated Fund of India. Explanation.- For the purposes of this 
section, the expression" Managing Director", in relation to an 
industrial establishment, means the person whether called general 
manager, manager, chief executive officer or a partner of a firm or by 
any other name who exercises control over the affairs of the 
establishment.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>436031</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 22.- In section 22 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),- (i) after clause (ggg), the following clauses shall 
be inserted, namely:-" (gggg) prescribing authority under sub- section 
 (2A) of section 9 and the procedure to be followed by such authority 
in disposing of the revision petition; (ggggg) prescribing authority 
under sub- section (2B) of section 9, the period within which such 
authority may call for the records and the manner in which such 
authority may make inquiry;";
<section><tid>377689</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (h), the word" and" occurring at the end shall be 
omitted; (iii) after clause (h), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-" (hh) the manner in which and the fee on payment of 
which the technical consultancy services shall be provided under 
sub- section (1) of section 14A; and".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1664839</tid>
<number>10</number>Validation of the disposal of certain revision 
petitions.- Notwithstanding any judgment, decree or order of any court 
to the contrary, rule 49 of the Central Industrial Security Force 
Rules, <year>1969</year> published with the notification of the Government of India 
in the Ministry of Home Affairs number S. O. 4632, dated the 12th 
November, <year>1969</year> shall be deemed to be, and to have always been, made 
under the principal Act as amended by this Act as if the principal Act 
as so amended had been in force at all materia times before the 
commencement of this Act and accordingly the disposal of any revision 
petition under the said rule 49 before the commencement of this Act or 
any order made or purporting to have been made or any action or thing 
taken or done in or under such petition shall not be deemed to be 
invalid or ever to have become invalid merely on the ground that the 
Central Government had no power under the principal Act to make the 
said rule 49.

</article>



 </act>