<act><title>
The
Permanent Lok Adalat (Other Terms and Conditions of Appointment of Chairman and
Other Persons)

Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Permanent Lok Adalat (Other Terms and Conditions
of Appointment of Chairman and Other Persons) Rules, 2003.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette. 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number> “Act” means the Legal Services Authorities Act, 1987 (39 of
1987); 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number> “Chairman” means a person appointed as Chairman of the Permanent
Lok Adalat established by the Central Authority or a State Authority under
sub-section (1) of Section 22-B of the Act; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number> “other person” means a person nominated under clause (b) of
sub-section (2) of Section 22-B; 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number> “Section” means a section of the Act; 
 

 </section><section><number>e</number> “Permanent Lok Adalat” means a Permanent Lok Adalat established
under sub-section (1) of Section 22-B; 
 

 </section><section><number>f</number> words and expressions used in these rules and not defined but defined
in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Sitting Fee and other allowances of Chairman and other persons of Permanent Lok
Adalat.—
<section><number>1</number> When a serving judicial
officer is appointed as Chairman, he shall receive the salary, allowances and
other perquisites as are admissible to a serving judicial officer.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
When a retired judicial officer is appointed as Chairman, he shall be entitled
to a sitting fee of Rupees Five hundred per sitting.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Any other person shall be entitled to a sitting fee of Rupees Four hundred per
sitting.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Chairman and other person shall be entitled to such travelling and daily
allowances on official tour as are admissible to Group ‘A’ officers of the
Central Government.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
For the purpose of attending the sittings of Permanent Lok Adalat, the Chairman
and other person shall be entitled to conveyance allowance of Rupees Three
thousand per month.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Terms and Conditions of Service of Chairman and other persons of Permanent Lok
Adalat.—
<section><number>1</number> Before appointment, the
Chairman and other person shall have to take an undertaking that he does not and
will not have any such financial or other interest as is likely to affect
prejudicially his functions as such Chairman or other person.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Chairman and other persons shall hold office for a term of five years and
shall not be eligible for reappointment.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (2), Chairman or other persons
may—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number> by writing under his hand and addressed to the Central Authority or,
as the case may be, the State Authority, resign his office at any time; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> be removed from his office in accordance with the provisions of
Rule 5.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
When the Chairman is unable to discharge his functions owing to absence, illness
or any other cause, the seniormost (in order of appointment) person of Permanent
Lok Adalat holding office for the time being shall discharge the functions of
the Chairman until the day on which the Chairman resumes the charge of his
functions.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
The Chairman or any other person ceasing to hold office as such shall not hold
any appointment in, or be connected with, the management or administration of an
organisation which has been the subject of the proceeding under the Act during
his tenure for a period of five years from the date on which he ceases to hold
such office.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Resignation and removal.—The Central
Authority or State Authority, as the case may be, may remove from office,
Chairman or other person who—
 


 <section><number>a</number> has been adjudged an insolvent; or 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number> has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the
Authority, involves moral turpitude; or 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number> has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as such
Chairman or other person; or 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number> has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect
prejudicially his functions as Chairman or other person; or 
 

 </section><section><number>e</number> has or so abused his position as to render his continuance in office
prejudicial to the public interest: 
 

 Provided
that the Chairman or any other person shall not be removed from his office on
the grounds specified in clauses (d) and (e), except on inquiry held in
accordance with the procedure prescribed in Rule 6.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Procedure for Inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever
the Central Authority or, as the case may be, State Authority is of the opinion
that an allegation under clause (d) or clause (e) of Rule 5 is required to be
inquired into, it may hold an inquiry against the Chairman or other person and
shall draw or cause to be drawn up the substance of the allegation which shall
contain a statement of relevant facts and a list of documents and witnesses.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Central Authority or, as the case may be, State Authority shall deliver or
cause to be delivered to the Chairman or other person a copy of the allegation
and a list of documents and witnesses and shall require him to submit within
such time as may be allowed, a written reply or statement of his defence.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
If the allegations are admitted by the Chairman or other person, the Central
Authority or, as the case may be, State Authority shall record reasons and
remove the Chairman or other person. 
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Where the charges have been denied by the Chairman or the other person, the
Central Authority or, as the case may be, State Authority may appoint an officer
to inquire into the truth of the allegations and it may also appoint a
Presenting Officer to present the case on behalf of the Central Authority or, as
the case may be, State Authority before the Inquiry officer.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
The Inquiry Officer shall give an opportunity to the Presenting Officer to
present the case within such time as may be allowed by the Inquiry Officer from
time to time. After the evidence is closed by the Presenting Officer, the
Chairman or other person, as the case may be, shall be given an opportunity to
present his defence in respect of allegations within such time as may be allowed
by the Inquiry Officer.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
The Inquiry Officer shall have power to call witnesses and record their
statements or receive evidence on affidavits or call for production of documents
or other relevant records, which may be necessary for the inquiry.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
The Inquiry Officer shall submit his report within a period of six months or
within such time as may be extended by the Central Authority or, as the case may
be, State Authority.
 


 </section><section><number>8</number>
If the Central Authority or, as the case may be, State Authority is satisfied
that the charges are proved on the basis of the report submitted by the Inquiry
Officer, it shall remove the delinquent Chairman or other person, as the case
may be.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Place of sittings.—
<section><number>1</number> The Permanent
Lok Adalat may sit at a place specified by the Central Authority or the State
Authority, as the case may be.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The working days and office hours of the Permanent Lok Adalat shall be the same
as that of the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The sitting of the Permanent Lok Adalat, as and when necessary, shall be
convened by the Chairman.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Staff of Permanent Lok Adalat.—The
Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, shall provide
such staff as may be necessary to assist the Permanent Lok Adalat in its
day-to-day work and perform such other functions as are provided under the Act
and these rules or assigned to it by the Chairman. The salary payable to such
staff shall be defrayed out of the Consolidated Fund of India or the
Consolidated Fund of the State, as the case may be.
  

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>