<act> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the 2[Banking 
Regulation (Companies) Rules], 1949.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They extend to the 
whole of India.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Interpretation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  “the Act” means the Banking 
Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949);      
 
 

1[(aa)  “ineligible Director” means a 
Director who is not eligible under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-section (2) 
of section 10A of the Act;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  “principal office of the 
Reserve Bank” means the office of the Reserve Bank to which the returns 
prescribed under the Act or these rules are required to be submitted;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  “principal office of the 
banking company” means the office of the banking company which will be 
responsible for the submission of returns prescribed under the Act or these 
rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  “quarter” means a period of 
three months ending on the last day of March, June, September or December of 
any year;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  “place of business” of a 
banking company includes any sub-office, pay-office, sub-pay-office and any 
place of business at which deposits are received, 

2[cheques cashed, moneys lent or any 
other form of business referred to in sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act 
is transacted.]
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  “commencement of these rules” 
means—
 <subsubsection>
              <number>i</number>  in the case of any 
banking company whose registered office or principal place of business referred 
to in sub-rule (2) of rule 3 is or was in:—
 <subsubsubsection>
                 <number>A</number>  the territories merged 
in the former Part A States, or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                  <number>B</number>  the States of 
Hyderabad, Mysore, Travancore, Cochin, Bhopal, Manipur and Tripura, as these 
States existed before the 1st day of November, 1956, or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                 <number>C</number>  those parts of the 
State of Rajasthan which formerly comprised the Indian States of Jaipur, 
Bikaner, Jaisalmer and Jodhpur, the 22nd day of November, 1952;
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ii</number>  in the case of any 
banking company whose registered office or principal place of business referred 
to in sub-rule (2) of rule 3 is or was in the State of Jammu and Kashmir, the 
1st day of November, 1956;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number>  in the case of the State 
Bank of India, the date on which the Banking Companies (Amendment) Rules, 1961, 
are published in the Gazette of India;
 
 

3[(iv)  in the case of a subsidiary 
bank, the date on which the Banking Regulation (Companies) Amendment Rules, 
1985, are published in the Gazette of India;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>v</number>  in the case of a 
corresponding new bank, the date on which the Banking Regulation (Companies) 
Amendment Rules, 1985, are published in the Gazette of India;
 
 

4[(vi)  in the case of a Regional 
Rural Bank, the date on which the Banking Regulation (Companies) Amendment 
Rules, 1985, are published in the Gazette of India;]
 
 

5[(vii)]  in any other case, the 26th 
day of March, 1949:
 
                   Provided that nothing 
contained in 

6[sub-clauses (iii) to (vi) both 
inclusive] shall affect the previous operation of any of these rules by virtue 
of the provisions of the Act; and 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  “Chief Executive Officer” means 
in the case of a banking company incorporated outside India, the Officer, by 
whatever name called, managing or in charge of all the branches of that company 
in India, or if there is no such Officer, the Officer, by whatever name called 
managing or in charge of the principal office of the company in India.
 
 









</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>2A</number> Application 
of rules to State Bank of India, subsidiary banks, corresponding New Banks and 
Regional Rural Banks.—These 
rules and the forms appended thereto excluding rules 6 to 11 and Forms II to V 
and XI, shall also apply, so far as may be, to the State Bank of India, a 
Subsidiary Bank, a corresponding new bank and a Regional Rural Bank, as they 
apply to and in relation to a banking company:
 
Provided that in the 
rules and forms as so applied, the expression “registered office” shall mean 
the central office or the head office, as the case may be.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Submission of returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A return prescribed under the Act or these rules shall be submitted in the form 
prescribed for the purpose or as near thereto as circumstances admit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such return shall be 
submitted in the manner hereinafter provided:
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  By a banking company 
incorporated in India, from its registered office to the office of the Reserve 
Bank situated in the State in which the banking company has its registered 
office.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  By a banking company 
incorporated outside India and having a principal place out business as 
declared in terms of section 277(1)(e) of the Indian Companies Act, 1913, or as 
the case may be, section 592(1)(e) of the Companies Act, 1956, from that 
principal place of business to the office of the Reserve Bank situated in the 
State in which the banking company has its principal place of business.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  In any other case, from such 
office of the banking company to such office of the Reserve Bank as may be 
specified by the Reserve Bank on an application to be made in this behalf to 
the Reserve Bank of India, 

1[Department of Banking Operations 
and Development] at Bombay.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  Notwithstanding anything 
contained in clauses (i), (ii) and (iii) the Reserve Bank may, at any time, 
direct that the returns prescribed under the Act or these rules shall be 
submitted from any specified office of a banking company to any specified 
office of the Reserve Bank.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever a return 
prescribed under the Act or these rules relates to a particular day or date, 
and where such day or date is not a holiday for all the offices of a banking 
company the return shall be prepared on the basis of the figures of that day or 
date in respect of offices working on that day or date, and the preceding 
working day’s figures in respect of offices where that day or date is a 
holiday.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A banking company 
shall within one month from the commencement of these rules or from the 
commencement of business, whichever is later, intimate to the principal office 
of the Reserve Bank, the address of its principal office and shall intimate to 
that office any change in such address within one month of such change.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> List of Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) A banking company shall, not later than one month from the commencement of 
these rules or from the commencement of business, whichever is later send to 
the principal officer of the Reserve Bank a written statement containing a list 
of—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the names, the official 
designations and specimen signatures of the officers authorised to sign on 
behalf of the banking company returns required under the Act or these rules, 
and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the names and addresses of the 
Directors of the banking company.
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> Any change in the 
list referred to in clause (i) of this sub-rule shall be intimated to the 
principal office of the Reserve Bank within one month from the occurrence of 
such change.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A banking company 
incorporated outside India, which at the commencement of these rules has a 
place of business in India, and every such company which after the commencement 
of these rules establishes such a place of business in India, shall, within one 
month from the commencement of these rules or from the establishment of such 
place of business, as the case may be, furnish to the principal office of the 
Reserve Bank the full address of the principal place of business declared in 
terms of section 227(1)(e) of the Indian Companies Act, 1913, or as the case 
may be section 592(1)(e) of the Companies Act, 1956, and the name and address 
of one or more persons resident in India authorised to accept on behalf of the 
company any notice or order required to be served on the company under the Act 
or these rules and shall intimate to the principal office of the Reserve Bank 
any change in such name or address within one month of the occurrence of the 
change:
 
Provided that information 
furnished by a banking company under rule 4 of the Banking Companies (Control) 
Rules, 1948, shall be deemed to have been furnished under this rule.
</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>5A</number> 
Determination of the Directors who are to cease to hold office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The ascertainment or the Director or Directors who shall cease to be such, on 
the occasion of a reconstitution of the Board of Directors under sub-section 
(3) of section 10A of the Act, and of the person or persons who are to be 
removed from the membership of the Board of Directors in pursuance of 
sub-section (5) of the said section 10A, shall be done as hereinafter laid 
down.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board of 
Directors or, as the case may be, the Reserve Bank, shall ascertain the number 
of Directors out of the ineligible Directors, who have to cease to hold the 
office, or, as the case may be, have to be removed from such Board.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The names of the 
Directors who are to cease to hold office, or, as the case may be, have to be 
removed from the Board of Directors, shall be determined by drawing lots from 
among the names of the ineligible Directors, the names of such number of 
Directors, as is determined under sub-rule (2) above.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the purposes of 
sub-rule (3), the following provisions shall be observed, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  the names of the ineligible 
Directors shall be ground according to the periods for which the Directors have 
held office;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  if there are two such groups 
only, the names of the Directors in the group representing a shorter period of 
office shall be excluded;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  if there are more than two 
such groups, the names of those in the group representing the shortest period 
of office shall be excluded:
 
                   Provided that such 
exclusion under clause (ii) or clause (iii) shall not be made if thereby the 
number of Directors whose names are to be included in the draw in not more than 
the number determined under sub-rule (2).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The drawin of lots in 
pursuance of sub-section (3) of section 10A of the Act shall be done by the 
Board of Directors at a meeting of such Board.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The drawing of lots 
of the Reserve Bank under sub-section (5) of section 10A of the Act shall be 
done by an Officer of the Reserve Bank duly authorised in this behalf, and 
after giving a reasonable opportunity to the banking company to nominate a 
Director or Officer of the Banking Company to be present at the time of the 
drawing of lots.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The deposit specified in sub-section (2) of section 11 of the Act shall be 
maintained at the principal office of the Reserve Bank.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The value of each 
security deposited under sub-rule (1) shall be estimated at its market rate, 
ex-dividend.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Securities shall be 
duly transferred to the Reserve Bank by the banking company.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Upon receipt of a 
deposit under sub-rule (1) the principal office of the Reserve Bank shall, as 
soon as possible, send to the principal office of the banking company a 
certificate in Form II.
</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Withdrawals of 
Deposits.—The 
principal office of the Reserve Bank shall not be bound to return securities 
actually deposited, but may substitute therefor new scrip of securities of the 
same description and amount.
</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Changes in Deposits.—When 
the form or amount of deposit is changed by reason of a subsequent deposit or 
withdrawal, the principal office of the Reserve Bank shall, as soon as 
possible, send to the principal office of the banking company a fresh 
certificate in Form II.
</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Maturing of Security 
Deposits.—When 
a security in deposit matures or when any yield on such a security ceases to 
accrue, the principal office of the Reserve Bank shall not be bound to inform 
the banking company; but upon the receipt of a requisition in writing from the 
banking company the principal office of the Reserve Bank, shall, as soon as 
possible, collect the discharge value and hold the amount in deposit for 
purposes of sub-section (2) of section 11 of the Act.
</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Interest on Deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No interest shall be payable on cash deposits.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The principal office 
of the Reserve Bank shall credit, as soon as possible, the current account of 
the banking company maintained with it with the interest realised on 
securities, subject to the usual charges.
</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Licensing of Banking 
Companies.—A 
company desiring to have a licence under section 22 of the Act shall apply to 
the principal office of the Reserve Bank in a form specified below, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  in the case of a company 
incorporated in India and desiring to commence banking business, in 

1[Form III],
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  in the case of company 
incorporated in India and in existence at the commencement of the Act, in


1[Form IV], and 
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  in the case of company 
incorporated outside India and desiring to commence/carry on banking business 
in India, in 

1[Form V].
 
 


</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Opening of New Places 
of Business.—An 
application by a banking company for permission to open a new place of business 
or change the location of an existing place of business under section 23 of the 
Act shall be submitted to be principal office of the Reserve Bank in 

1[Form VI].
 
 



</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> List of Offices.—A 
banking company shall, within a period of one month from the close of every 
quarter, send to the principal office of the Reserve Bank a 

1[list relating to 
its offices in India in 

2[Form VII].
 
 




</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>13A</number> Return 
under sections 18 and 24.—The 
return under sections 18 and 24 of the Act shall be furnished to the Reserve 
Bank in Form VIII.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Publication of 
approved currencies and securities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Reserve Bank shall, not later than one month from the commencement of these 
rules, by a notification in the Gazette of India, publish for the purpose of 
section 25 of the Act a list of currencies in which export bills drawn in, and 
import bills drawn on and payable in India may be expressed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Reserve Bank may, 
by notification in the Gazette of India, publish for the purpose of section 25 
of the Act, a list of securities approved by it.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any alteration in the 
list referred to in sub-rules (1) and (2) shall also be published in the 
Gazette of India.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An alteration, adding 
a currency or security to the list, shall take effect from the date of 
publication of the alteration while an alteration, omitting a currency or 
security from the list, shall take effect at the expiry of three months from 
the date of publication of the alteration.
</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14A</number> Return 
under sections 25 and 27.—The 
return to be made by a banking company under sections 25 and 27 of the Act 
shall be in Form X.
 
 




</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>14B</number> Return under section 
26.—The return 
to be made by a banking company under section 26 of the Act shall be in Form 
IX.]
</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Manner of publication 
of accounts and balance-sheet.—The 
balance-sheet and profit and loss account prepared in terms of section 29 of 
the Act together with the Auditor’s report shall be published within a period 
of six months from the end of the period to which they relate in a newspaper 
which is in circulation at the place where the banking company has its 
principal office.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, the expression ‘newspaper’ means any newspaper or 
journal published at least once a week, but does not include a journal other 
than a banking commercial, financial or economic journal.
</article> 
 The Banking Regulation (Companies) 
 Rules, 1949
  
 <article><number>15A</number> The list of debtors under 
section 45D of the Act shall be in 1[Form XI] or as near thereto as 
the circumstances permit.
  



</article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>15B</number> Manner of 
holding inquiries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of holding an inquiry under sub-section (2) of section 47A of 
the Act, the Reserve Bank shall appoint in writing one of its Officers for 
holding the inquiry and shall also authorise him to exercise the powers 
conferred on the Reserve Bank under sub-section (3) of the said section 47A.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The said Officer 
shall send to the banking company, at its registered office or principal 
office, a statement giving sufficient particulars of the contravention of the 
nature referred to in sub-section (3) or, as the case may be, sub-section (4) 
of section 46 of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A banking company, to 
which a communication is addressed under sub-rule (2), shall before the expiry 
of thirty days from the receipt of such communication send in writing to said 
Officer its answer to the said statement, together with particulars of the 
documentary or other evidence on which it proposes to rely.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The said Officer 
shall appoint a date for holding the inquiry and intimate the same to the 
banking company at its registered office or the principal office. The date so 
appointed shall not be earlier than thirty days from the date of issue of the 
notice to the banking company.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> At the inquiry, the 
Banking Company shall be entitled to be represented by any of its Directors or 
Officers but shall not be entitled to be represented by a legal practitioner.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> At the inquiry, an 
Officer of the Reserve Bank, not being the Officer conducting the inquiry, 
shall present the case for the Reserve Bank, including the evidence on the 
matter. Thereafter the representative of the banking company shall present the 
case of the banking company including the evidence in relation thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The representative of 
the banking company and the Officer of the Reserve Bank presenting the case for 
the Reserve Bank may cross-examine a witness other than a witness produced by 
the said representative or, as the case may be, the said Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> After the conclusion of the inquiry, the 
Officer conducting the inquiry, the Officer shall record his findings and 
submit the entire record to the Reserve Bank.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Banking Regulation (Companies)
 
Rules, 1949
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Power to exempt in certain cases.—The 
Central Government may, on the recommendation of the Reserve Bank, declare by 
notification in the Official Gazette that any or all of the provisions of these 
rules shall not apply to any banking company or to any class of banking 
companies either generally or for such period as may be specified.
</article><form>
 


The Banking 
Regulation (Companies)  

Rules, 1949
 




 



1[***]
 


—————
 


   1.  Form I omitted by 
S.O. 268(E), dated 
29th March, 1985 (w.e.f. 
29-3-1985).
 


 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>