<act><tid>1202900</tid>
<title>THE COAL GRADING BOARD (REPEAL) ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 17 OF <year>1959</year> AN ACT TO REPEAL THE COAL GRADING BOARD ACT, <year>1925</year>, AND TO 
PROVIDE FOR CERTAIN
[ 9th May, <year>1959</year>.]





<article><tid>551248</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>294065</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Coal Grading Board (Repeal) Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1015157</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Definitions.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>171543</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1552984</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date on which this Act come into 
force;

</section>

<section><tid>777966</tid>
<number>b</number>" Coal Board" means the Coal Board established under section 
 4 of the Coal Mines (Conservation and Safety) Act, <year>1952</year>; (12 of <year>1952</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>1294465</tid>
<number>c</number>" Coal Grading Board" means the Coal Grading Board 
constituted under section 3 of the Coal Grading Act, <year>1925</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Repeal of Act 31 of <year>1925</year> and dissolution of coal Granding Board.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>837197</tid>
<number>3</number>Repeal of Act 31 of <year>1925</year> and dissolution of coal Granding 
Board. On the appointed day, the Coal Grading Board Act, <year>1925</year>, 
 (31 of <year>1925</year>) shall stand repealed, and the Coal Grading Board shall 
stand dissolved.


</article>



<article><tid>537741</tid>
<number> 4</number> Consequential provisions.
<section><tid>1804555</tid>
<number>1</number>All- moneys and other property,  
of whatever kind, owned by or vested in, the Coal Grading Board 
immediately before the appointed day and all debts, liabilities and 
obligations of that Board then existing shall, on the appointed day, 
stand transferred to and vested in the Coal Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1724828</tid>
<number>2</number>Anything done or any action taken before the appointed day 
by the Coal Grading Board shall, so far as it is not inconsistent with 
any of the provisions of the Coal Mines (Conservation and Safety) Act, 
<year>1952</year>, (12 of <year>1952</year>) or the rules made thereunder, be as valid and 
effectual as if it had been done or taken by the Coal Board.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 14th August, <year>1959</year>, vide Notification No. S. O. 1771, dated the 7th 
August, <year>1959</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), p. 
439.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>