<act><title>
THE WORKMEN’S 
    COMPENSATION (VENUE OF PROCEEDINGS) RULES, 19961</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Workmen’s Compensation (Venue of Proceedings) 
    Rules, 1996.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> These rules shall come into force from the 1st day of October, 1996. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules,  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923;  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>   “Form” means a form appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>   “Commissioner” means a Commissioner appointed under section 20.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> Processing of an application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application under section 19 or section 22 shall be processed before or 
    by a Commissioner for the area in which—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>   the accident took place which resulted in the injury; or  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>   the workmen or in case of his deah the dependants claiming the 
    compensation ordinarily reside; or  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>   the employer has his registered office.  
 


    Provided that no matter shall be processed before or by a Commissioner other 
    than the Commissioner having the jurisdiction over the area in which the 
    accident took place without his giving notice in Form A to the Commissioner 
    having jurisdiction over the area and the State Government concerned.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> The Commissioner under section 21(1)(b) or (c) may initiate proceedings 
    afresh or he may continue the previous proceedings initiated under section 
    21(1)(a) as if the same or any of its part had been taken before him if he 
    is satisfied that the interest of the parties shall not thereby be 
    prejudiced.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Transfer of records or money.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any matter under the Act is required to be processed before or by a 
    Commissioner other than the Commissioner having jurisidiction over the area 
    in which the accident took place the former may for the proper disposal of 
    the matter call for in Form-B a detailed report including transfer of any 
    records or money remaining with the latter and on receipt of such a request 
    he shall comply with the same:  
 


    Provided that if any further enquiry is necessary in the area in which the 
    accident took place for framing of issues or for determining the amount of 
    compensation, the Commissioner, before whom the application has been filed, 
    may require the Commissioner of the area in which the Accident took place to 
    conduct such enquiries and to serve such notices or orders as may be 
    necessary for the prupose of such enquiries.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Money deposited with one Commissioner under section 8 shall be 
    transmitted to another Commissioner either by remittance transfer receipt or 
    by money order or by bank cheque.  
  

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE WORKMEN’S 
    COMPENSATION (VENUE OF PROCEEDINGS) RULES, 1996
 



 



 




    Form A
 




    [See rule 3]
 

 
 




    Whereas a claim for compensation has been made by.................... 
    (applicant) against.................... and the said applicant has claimed 
    that he is entitled to file an application under clause (b) or (c) of 
    section 21(1) of the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923;
 




    And whereas the undersigned is satisfied that the said applicant is entitled 
    to file the aforesaid claim;
 




    Now, therefore, the Commissioner for Workmen’s 
    Compensation.............................. /Government 
    of..............................is hereby given notice that the undersigned 
    proposes to settle the claim of the applicant as provided under the Act.
 

 
 




    Date................        
 




    Commissioner
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE WORKMEN’S 
    COMPENSATION (VENUE OF PROCEEDINGS) RULES, 1996
 



 



 




    Form B
 




    [See rule 4]
 

 
 




    To,
 




    ........................................
 




    ........................................
 

 
 




    Sir,
 




    The report about an accident which occurred 
    on....................at....................(here enter details of premises) 
    and which resulted in death/disablement of the workman is furnished as given 
    below:—
 




           1. (a)   Name of the workman.
 




               (b)   Sex, age and monthly wage.
 




               (c)   Nature of employment.
 




               (d)   Name of the employer.
 




               (e)   Full postal address of the workman/dependants (local and 
    permanent both.)
 




               (f)   Full postal address of the factory/establishment where its 
    registered office is located.
 




    2. The circumstances leading to death/disablement of the workman:—        
    
 




               (a)   Time of the accident.
 




               (b)   Place where the accident occurred.
 




               (c)   Manner in which deceased was/were employed at that time.
 




               (d)   Cause of the accident.
 




    3. The amount of money deposited by the employer with the Commissioner under 
    section 8.
 




         4. (a)   Details of compensation paid, if any.
 




             (b)   Particulars of money invested for the benefit of dependants 
    of deceased workman.
 




    5. Documents forwarded (in original) as under:—
 




               (a)   Death certificate.
 




               (b)   Disablement certificate from the competent medical 
    authority.
 




               (c)   Receipt for Deposit of Compensation by the employer.
 




               (d)   Statement of Disbursement.
 




               (e)   Receipt of compensation from the workman/dependants.
 




               (f)   Memorandum of Agreement, if any.
 

 
 




    Date....................    
 




    Commissioner
 





 

  




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>