<act><title>


The Railway Passengers (Manner of 
    Investigation of Untoward Incidents) Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Railway Passengers (Manner of Investigation of 
    Untoward Incidents) Rules, 2003. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette.
 






  


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> ‘Act' means the Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> ‘Claims Tribunal' means Tribunal constituted under the Railway Claims Tribunal Act, 1987; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> ‘diary' means the station diary being maintained by the Station Superintendent for recording daily events happened at the station; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> ‘Divisional Office' means the divisional headquarter of the Zonal Railway; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> ‘Divisional Railway Manager' means the administrative in-charge of the divisional office; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> ‘Divisional Security Commissioner' means administrative in-charge of the force of Divisional Office; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> ‘Force' means the Railway Protection Force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> ‘Form' means the Form appended to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> ‘Inquest Report' means the report prepared by the police containing details of incident; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> ‘Jama Talashi' means the report about the recovery of any belongings of the person affected by the untoward incident; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> ‘Police' means a State Police; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> ‘Station Superintendent' includes Deputy Station Superintendent, Station Master and Assistant Station Master or other officer being in-charge of the station; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> ‘Supervisor' means official-in-charge of the guard or driver or Train Ticket Examiner booking office; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> ‘Technical Survey' means survey carried out by a team of railway officials nominated by the Station Superintendent or any other official being in-charge of railway station; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> ‘untoward incident' means an incident defined under clause (c) of section 123 of the Act; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> ‘Zonal Railway' means a zonal railway constituted under section 3 of the Act. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Report 
    about untoward incident.—Any 
    railway servant, including guard and driver of the train, on coming to know 
    of the occurrence of an untoward incident, shall report the incident 
    immediately to the nearest Station Superintendent.  

  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Duties of guard, driver and Train Ticket Examiner.</title>—Any guard or driver or Train Ticket Examiner, who is on duty at the time of occurrence of untoward incident, shall,
 
 <section> 
    <number>i</number> immediately arrange for medical assistance to the injured passengers, and 
    (ii) report the occurrence of such incident to the Supervisor in Form-I. 
</section>
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Duties of Supervisor.</title>—On receipt of a report in Form-I, the Supervisor shall forward the same to the Divisional Railway Manager.
  
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Duties of Station Superintendent. </title>—The Station Superintendent, on receipt of an information about the occurrence of an untoward incident under rule 3, shall,— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> make necessary entries to this effect in the station diary; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> arrange for medical assistance to the injured passengers; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> make out a brief report in respect of spot of the untoward incident and forward copies thereof to the Divisional Office, Zonal Railways, police and in-charge of the Force; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> carry out technical survey of the untoward incident himself or through his representative; and 
 </section><section><number>v</number> depute his representative to assist the force to complete the process of investigation. 
</section>
  
  
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Conducting of investigation and submission of report by the Force. </title>—  

<section><number>1</number> On receipt of information under rule 6, an officer of the Force, not below the rank of Inspector, shall carry out the investigation and shall,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> obtain copies of the inquest report, post mortem report and Jama Talashi report from the police investigating the incident; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> obtain copy of the technical survey carried out by the railway official nominated by the Station Superintendent; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> obtain information about the untoward incident in Form-2; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> record statement of additional witnesses, if so required; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> collect any other evidence required by the circumstances of the case. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The officer of the Force, on completion of the investigation, shall submit a report to the authorities specified under sub-rule (2) of rule 10. 
</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Conducting of investigation and submission of report by the Police.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The police on receipt of the report under clause (iii) of rule 6, shall 
    immediately initiate investigation and prepare inquest report or injury 
    report in accordance with the procedure laid down in Criminal Procedure 
    Code, 1973.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After 
    preparation of report, as mentioned in sub-rule (1), the police shall 
    immediately give clearance certificate for movement of trains from the site 
    of incident so that minimum delay is caused in restoration of train 
    movement.  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> The 
    injured and the next of kin of the deceased passenger may submit evidence 
    and assist police and Force.—The 
    injured and the next of kin of the deceased passengers may submit all the 
    relevant evidence before the Police and assist the Police and the Force to 
    complete the investigation.  

  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Forwarding of investigation report by the Police and the Force. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The police on completion of the investigation, shall forward the report thereof to the Magistrate, as required under the Criminal Procedure Code, 1973. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The officer of the Force shall forward the report prepared under sub-rule (2) of rule 7 to the Divisional Railway Manager and Divisional Security Commissioner of the Force. 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Action on the report by the Divisional Railway Manager. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Divisional Railway Manager, on receipt of the report, shall immediately examine the same. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When, on examination, Divisional Railway Manager is satisfied that the investigation is complete, he shall pass an order accepting the said report. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the Divisional Railway Manager has reason to believe that some more inquiry is required in the matter, it shall refer the same back for investigation to the officer of the Force along with his observations for further investigation. 
(4) On receipt of a reference under sub-rule (3), the officer of the Force shall investigate the matter further and submit the report immediately to the Divisional Railway Manager.

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Communication of order.—Final 
    orders passed on the report by the Divisional Railway Manager shall be 
    communicated to the Station Superintendent who shall maintain the records 
    and make necessary entries in the Station Diary to this effect. 
 


  


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Investigation report to be placed before Divisional Railway Manager.</title>—The investigation report along with comments of the Divisional Railway Manager thereon shall be placed before the Claims Tribunal by Railway Administration while filing written statement in the case in which compensation has been claimed on the basis of such untoward incident.

</article><form>
 
 
  
 
 




The Railway Passengers (Manner of 
    Investigation of Untoward Incidents) Rules, 2003
 



 



    Form 1
 


(See rule 4)
 



Report Of Untoward Incident
 


1.  Kilometer at which untoward incident 
    occurred:  
 


2.  Name of Driver of the train with 
    Headquarter:  
 


3.  Name of Guard of the train with 
    Headquarter:  
 


4.  Name of Train Ticket Examiner of train, if 
    posted, with Headquarter:  
 


5.  Nature of the untoward incident:  
 


(a) accidental fall  
 


(b) bomb blast  
 


(c) rioting/shootout  
 


(d) others  
 


6.  Time of occurrence:  
 


7.  Position of human body in relation to 
    track:  
 


8.  Whether medical help was given to the 
    injured:  
 


9.  Whether train stopped or not:  
 


10.  Condition of doors and occupation of 
    coach:  
 

 
 


Date:
 


Signature          
    
 


 Name and designation
 

 
 



 




  


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>    Came into force on 8th August, 2003</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>