<act><tid>1210757</tid>
<title>THE INSURANCE (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 42 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 9th August, <year>2002</year>]

An Act further to amend the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1677127</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>174585</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Insurance (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1765488</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
Provided that different dates may be appointed for different 
provisions of this Act and any reference in any such provision to the 
commencement of this Act shall be construed as a reference to the 
coming into force of that provision.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1360825</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4  
  of <year>1938</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act),-
<section><tid>1523203</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (1), for the words" qualifications as may be 
prescribed", the words" qualifications as may be specified by the 
regulations made by the Authority" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1965864</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (3), sub- clause (v) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>948118</tid>
<number>c</number>after clause (8), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (8A)" insurance co- operative society" means any insurer being a 
co- operative society,-


</section>

<section><tid>1523203</tid>
<number>a</number>which is registered on or after the commencement of the Insurance 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, as a co- operative society under the 
Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>) or under any other law 
societies or under the Multi- State Co- operative Societies Act, <year>1984</year> 
 (51 pf <year>1984</year>); for the time being in force in any State relating to 
co- o erative

</section>

<section><tid>1965864</tid>
<number>b</number>having a minimum paid- up capital (excluding the deposits required  
  to be made under section 7) of rupees one hundred crores;

</section>

<section><tid>948118</tid>
<number>c</number>in which no body corporate, whether incorporated or not, formed or 
registered outside India, either by itself or through its subsidiaries 
or nominees, at any time, holds more than twenty- six per cent. of the 
capital of such co- operative society;

</section>

<section><tid>445868</tid>
<number>d</number>whose sole purpose is to carry on life insurance business or 
general insurance business in India;';

</section>

<section><tid>445868</tid>
<number>d</number>after clause (10A), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (10B)" intermediary or insurance intermediary" shall have the meaning 
assigned to it in clause (f) of sub- section (1) of section 2 of the 
Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, <year>1999</year> (41 of  
  <year>1999</year>).'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1063385</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 2C.- In section 2C of the principal Act, after 
sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be inserted at the 
end, namely:-
" (3) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), an 
insurance co- operative society may carry on any class of insurance 
business in India under this Act on or after the commencement of the 
Insurance (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.".



</article>



<article><tid>1587307</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 15.- In section 15 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the portion beginning with the words" to the 
Authority in the case of the accounts and statements" and ending with 
the words" from the end of the period to which they refer", the words 
" to the Authority within six months from the end of the period to 
which they refer" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>758150</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 28A.- In section 28A of the principal Act, for 
the words" in the prescribed form" at both the places where they 
occur, the words", in the form specified by the regulations made by 
the Authority," shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>582772</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 28B.- In section 28B of the principal Act, for 
the words" in the prescribed form" at both the places where they 
occur, the words", in the form specified by the regulations made by 
the Authority," shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1951219</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 31B.- In section 31B of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for the words" the sum of five thousand rupees in 
that year", the words" such sum as may be specified by the regulations 
made by the Authority" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>737017</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of section 40.- In section 40 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1772987</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" except an insurance agent or a 
principal, chief or special agent", the words" except an insurance 
agent or an intermediary or insurance intermediary" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>207285</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2A), for the words" no insurance agent", the words 
" no insurance agent or intermediary or insurance intermediary" shall 
be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1980619</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 42.- In section 42 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>261334</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (3), for the brackets and letter" (e)", the 
brackets and letters" (e), (ea)" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>67607</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (4),-

<subsection><tid>1248165</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (e), for the words" that he does not possess", the words 
" that in the case of an individual, he does not possess" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1918325</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (e), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ea) that in the case of a company or firm making an application 
under sub- section (1) or sub- section (3), a director or a partner or 
one or more of its officers or other employees so designated by it and 
in the case of any other person, the chief execu ive, by whatever name 
called, or one or more of his employees designated by him, do not 
possess the requisite qualifications and practical training and have 
not passed such an examination as required under clauses (e) and 
 (f);".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>919618</tid>
<number>10</number>Amendment of section 42A.- In section 42A of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (8), the following sub- section shall be inserted at 
the end, namely:-
" (9) No insurer shall, on or after the commencement of the Insurance 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, appoint or transact any insurance business in 
India through any principal agent, chief agent or special agent.".



</article>



<article><tid>1519126</tid>
<number> 11</number> Insertion of new section 42E.- After section 42D of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 42E. Commission, brokerage or fee payable to intermediary or 
insurance intermediary.- (1) No intermediary or insurance intermediary 
shall be paid or contract to be paid by way of commission, fee or as 
remuneration in any form, an amount exceeding thirty er cent. of the 
premium payable as may be specified by the regulations made by the 
Authority, in respect of any policy or policies effected through him:

Provided that the Authority may specify different amounts payable by 
way of commission, fee or as remuneration to an intermediary or 
insurance intermediary or different classes of business of insurance.

<section><tid>445508</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions contained in this Act, the 
Authority may, by the regulations made in this behalf, specify the 
requirements of capital, form of business and other conditions to act 
as an intermediary or insurance intermediary.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643968</tid>
<number> 12</number> Amendment of section 49.- In section 49 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>941982</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1326328</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words and figure" balancesheet in Form I as set forth in 
the Fourth Schedule", the words" balance- sheet in such form as may be 
specified by the regulations made by the Authority" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>391777</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the second proviso, the following proviso shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" Provided further that the share of any such surplus allocated to or 
reserved for the shareholders (including any amount for the payment of  
dividends guaranteed to them, whether by way of first charge or 
  otherwise) shall not exceed such sums as may be sp cified by the 
Authority and such share shall in no case exceed ten per cent. of 
such surplus in case of participating policies and in other cases the 
whole thereof.";


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1273213</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words, figures and brackets" paragraph 
8 (1) of the abstract prepared in accordance with Part II of the Fourth 
Schedule to this Act", the words, brackets and figures" an abstract 
of the report of the actuary referred to in sub- section (1) of section 
13" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1544801</tid>
<number>13</number>Amendment of section 64VB.- In section 64VB of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (5), the following sub- section shall be inserted at 
the end, namely:-
" (6) The Authority may, from time to time, specify, by the regulations 
made by it, the manner of receipt of premium by the insurer.".



</article>



<article><tid>187697</tid>
<number>14</number>Insertion of new Part IIIA.- After Part III of the principal Act, 
the following Part shall be inserted, namely:-
" PART IIIA

INSURANCE CO- OPERATIVE SOCIETIES

</article>



<article><tid>797585</tid>
<number> 94A</number> Insurance co- operative society to be an insurer.-
<section><tid>1359372</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
insurance co- operative society shall be deemed to be an insurer for 
the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>809302</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all the provisions 
applicable to an insurer being an Indian insurance company shall, so 
far as may be, apply to an insurance co- operative society:
Provided that the Authority may, by notification, direct that any of 
the provisions of this Act,-


<subsection><tid>1265459</tid>
<number>a</number>shall not apply to any insurance co- operative society; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1503140</tid>
<number>b</number>shall apply to any insurance co- operative society only with such 
exceptions, modifications and adaptations as may be specified in the 
notification.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1252948</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of every notification proposed to be issued under proviso 
to sub- section (2), shall be laid in draft before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or ore successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in disapproving the issue of the notification or both 
Houses agree in making any modification in t e notification, the 
notification shall not be issued or, as the case may be, shall be 
issued only in such modified form as may be agreed upon by both the 
Houses.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>993879</tid>
<number>15</number>Amendment of section 101A.- In section 101A of the principal Act, 
in sub- section (8), for clause (ii), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
' (ii)" Indian re- insurer" means an Indian insurance company which has 
been granted a certificate of registration under sub- section (2A) of 
section 3 by the Authority to carry on exclusively the re- insurance 
business in India.'.



</article>



<article><tid>945296</tid>
<number>16</number>Amendment of section 114.- In section 114 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), clause (a) shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1908442</tid>
<number> 17</number> Amendment of section 114A.- In section 114A of the principal Act, 
in sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>1539200</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (a), the following clauses shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (a) the qualifications to be possessed by actuaries;


<subsection><tid>688305</tid>
<number>aa</number>the matters including fee relating to the registration of 
insurers under section 3;";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>27853</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (g), for the words" fourth proviso", the words" fifth 
proviso" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1274847</tid>
<number>iii</number>after clause (i), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ia) the form in which a return showing the investments made out of 
the controlled fund shall be submitted by an insurer carrying on life 
insurance business under sub- section (1) of section 28A;


<subsection><tid>423454</tid>
<number>ib</number>the form in which a return showing all the changes that occurred 
in the investments shall be submitted by an insurer carrying on life 
insurance business under sub- section (2) of section 28A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>365558</tid>
<number>ic</number>the form in which a return showing the investment made out of 
assets shall be submitted by an insurer carrying on general insurance 
business under sub- section (1) of section 28B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>922177</tid>
<number>id</number>the form in which a return showing all the changes that occurred 
in the investments shall be submitted by an insurer carrying on 
general insurance business under sub- section (2) of section 28B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1689827</tid>
<number>ie</number>the form of the statement and the sum to be specified under 
sub- section (2) of section 31B;";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>168993</tid>
<number>iv</number>after clause (v), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (va) the amount of commission, fee or as remuneration in any form not 
exceeding thirty per cent. to be paid or contract to be paid under 
sub- section (1) of section 42E;


</section>

<section><tid>1263021</tid>
<number>vb</number>the requirements of capital, form of business and other 
conditions to act as an intermediary or insurance intermediary under 
sub- section (2) of section 42E;

</section>

<section><tid>403807</tid>
<number>vc</number>the form of balance- sheet as may be specified by the Authority 
under sub- section (1) of section 49;";

</section>

<section><tid>1282331</tid>
<number>v</number>after clause (za), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (zb) the manner of receipt of premium to be specified under 
sub- section (6) of section 64VB.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>805985</tid>
<number>18</number>Omission of Schedules.- The First Schedule, the Second Schedule, 
the Third Schedule and the Fourth Schedule to the principal Act shall 
be omitted.
SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>