<act><title>

The
prevention of seditious meetings Act, 1911</title> 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called The Prevention of Seditious Meetings Act, 1911.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[territories
which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B
States,] but shall have operation only in such States or parts of States as the
State Government may from time to time notify in the Official Gazette.
   







</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Power of State Government to notify proclaimed areas.—
<section><number>1</number>
The State Government may, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]
by notification in the Official Gazette, declare the whole or any part of a
State, in which this Act is for the time being in operation, to be a proclaimed
area.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A notification made under sub-section (1) shall not remain in force for more
than six months, but nothing in this sub-section shall be deemed to prevent the
State Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]
from making any further notifications in respect of the same area from time to
time, as it may think fit. 
  




</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Definition.—
<section><number>1</number>
In this Act, the expression “public meeting” means a meeting which is open
to the public or any class or portion of the public.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A meeting may be a public meeting notwithstanding that it is held in a private
place and notwithstanding that admission thereto may have been restricted by
ticket or otherwise.
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Notice to be given of public meetings.—
<section><number>1</number>
No public meeting for the furtherance or discussion of any subject likely to
cause disturbance or public excitement, or for the exhibition or distribution of
any writing or printed matter relating to any such subject, shall be held in any
proclaimed area—
 <subsection><number>a</number> unless written notice of the intention to
hold such meeting and of the time and place of such meeting has been given to
the District Magistrate or the Commissioner of Police, as the case may be, at
least three days previously; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> unless permission to hold such meeting has
been obtained in writing from the District Magistate or the Commissioner or
Police, as the case may be. 
 
Power
of Magistrate to cause Report to be taken
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The District Magistrate or any Magistrate of the first class authorised by the
District Magistrate in this behalf may, by order in writing, depute one or more
police-officers, not being below the rank of head constable, or other persons,
to attend any such meeting for the purpose of causing a report to be taken of
the proceedings.
 
Exception
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Noting in this section shall apply to any public meeting held under any
statutory or other express legal authority, or to public meetings convened by a
Sheriff, or to any public meetings or class of public meetings exempted for that
purpose by the State Government by general or special order.
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Power to prohibit public meetings.—The
District Magistrate or the Commissioner of Police, as the case may be, may at
any time, by order in writing, of which public notice shall forthwith be given,
prohibit any public meeting in a proclaimed area if, in his opinion, such
meeting is likely to promote sedition or disaffection or to cause a disturbance
of the public tranquillity. 
  
</article> 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any person concerned in the promotion or conduct of a public meeting held in a
proclaimed area contrary to the provisions of Section 4 shall be punished with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, or with
both.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any public meeting which has been prohibited under Section 5 shall be deemed to
be an unlawful assembly within the meaning of Chapter VIII of the Indian Penal
Code and of Chapter IX of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898. 
  









</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Penality for delivery of speeches in public places.—Whoever,
in a proclaimed area, in a public place or a place of public resort, otherwise
than at a public meeting held in accordance with, or exempted from, the
provisions of section 4, without the permission in writing of the Magistrate of
the district or of the Commissioner of police, as the case may be, previously
obtained, delivers any lecture, address or speech on any subject likely to cause
disturbance or public excitement to persons then present, may be arrested
without warrant and shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may
extend to six months, or with fine, or with both.
  
  
</article> 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Cognisance of offences.—No
Court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or of a Magistrate of the
first class or Sub-Divisional Magistrate shall try any offence against this Act.
</article> 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Repeals.—[Repealed
by the Repealing Act, 1927 (XII of 1927), sec. 2 and Sch.]
</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, 1956, for “Part B
States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
The words “with the previous sanction of the G.G. in C.” rep. by the
Government of India (Adaptation of Indian Laws) Order, 1937</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>