<act><title>THE MEDICAL COUNCIL OF INDIA (PREVENTION AND 
PROHIBITION OF RAGGING IN MEDICAL COLLEGES/INSTITUTIONS) REGULATIONS, 
20091 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, commencement and applicability </title>
 <section><number>i</number> These regulations may be called the Medical Council of India (Prevention 
and Prohibition of Ragging in Medical Colleges/Institutions) Regulations, 2009. 

 </section><section><number>ii</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette. 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Objective: </title>
 To root out ragging in all its forms from medical colleges/institutions in 
the country by prohibiting it by law, preventing its occurrence by following the 
provisions of these regulations and punishing those who indulge in ragging as 
provided for in these regulations and the appropriate law in force. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Definitions:</title> For the purposes of these regulations: 
 </article><article><number>3</number>1 "Medical College" means an institution, whether known as such or by any 
other name, which provides for a programme, beyond 12 years of schooling, for 
obtaining recognized MBBS qualification from a university and which, in 
accordance with the rules and regulations of such university, is recognized as 
competent to provide for such programmes of study and present students 
undergoing such programmes of study for the examination for the award of 
recognized MBBS/PG Degree/Diploma qualifications. 
 </article><article><number>3</number>2 "Head of the institution" means the Dean/Principal/Director of the 
concerned medical college/institution. 
 </article><article><number>3</number>3 "Ragging" includes the following: 
 Any conduct whether by words spoken or written or by an act which has the 
effect of harassing, teasing, treating or handling with rudeness any other 
student, indulging in rowdy or undisciplined activities which causes or is 
likely to cause annoyance, hardship or psychological harm or to raise fear or 
apprehension thereof in a fresher or a junior student or asking the students to 
do any act or perform something which such student will not in the ordinary 
course and which has the effect of causing or generating a sense of shame or 
embarrassment so as to adversely affect the physique or psyche of a fresher or a 
junior student. 
 </article><article><number>3</number>4 "MCI" means MCI constituted in terms of Section 3 of the Indian Medical 
Council Act, 1956. 
 </article><article><number>3</number>5 "University" means a university established or incorporated by or under a 
Central Act, a Provincial Act or a State Act, an institution deemed to be 
university under Section 3 of the UGC Act, 1956, or an institution specially 
empowered by an Act of Parliament to confer or grant degrees. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Punishable ingredients of Ragging: </title>
 
 . Abetment to ragging; 
 . Criminal conspiracy to rag; 
 . Unlawful assembly and rioting while ragging; 
 . Public nuisance created during ragging; 
 . Violation of decency and morals through ragging; 
 . Injury to body, causing hurt or grievous hurt; 
 . Wrongful restraint; 
 . Wrongful confinement; 
 . Use of criminal force; 
 . Assault as well as sexual offences or even unnatural offences; 
 . Extortion; 
 . Criminal trespass; 
 . Offences against property; 
 . Criminal intimidation; 
 . Attempts to commit any or all of the above mentioned offences against the 
  victim(s); 
 . Physical or psychological humiliation; 
 . All other offences following from the definition of "Ragging". 
  <title></title>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Measures for prohibition of ragging: </title>
 </article><article><number>5</number>1 The Medical College/Institution/University shall strictly observe the 
provisions of the Act of the Central Government and the State Governments, if 
any, or if enacted and/or for the time being in force, considering ragging as a 
cognizable offence under the law at par with rape and other atrocities against 
women and ill-treatment of persons belonging to the SC/ST and prohibiting 
ragging in all its forms in all institutions. 
 </article><article><number>5</number>2 Ragging in all its forms shall be totally banned in the entire Medical 
College/Institution/University including its departments, constituent units, all 
its premises (academic, residential, sports, canteen, etc.) whether located 
within the campus or outside and in all means of transportation of students 
whether public or private. 
 </article><article><number>5</number>3 The Medical College/Institution/University shall take strict action 
against those found guilty of ragging and/or of abetting ragging. 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Measures for prevention of ragging at the institution level: 
</title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>1 Before admissions: 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.1 The advertisement for admissions shall clearly mention that ragging is 
totally banned/prohibited in the Medical College/Institution and anyone found 
guilty of ragging and/or abetting ragging is liable to be punished 
appropriately. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.2 The brochure of admission/instruction booklet for candidates shall 
print in block letters these Regulations in full (including Annexures). 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.3 The 'Prospectus' and other admission related documents shall 
incorporate all directions of the Hon'ble Supreme Court and/or the Central or 
State Governments as applicable, so that the candidates and their 
parents/guardians are sensitized in respect of the prohibition and consequences 
of ragging. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.4 A Brochure or booklet/leaflet shall be distributed to each student at 
the beginning of each academic session for obtaining undertaking not to indulge 
or abet ragging and shall contain the blueprint of prevention and methods of 
redress. 
 The application form for admission/enrolment shall have a printed 
undertaking, preferably both in English/Hindi and in one of the regional 
languages known to the institution and the applicant (English version given in 
Annexure I, Part I), to be filled up and signed by the candidate to the effect 
that he/she is aware of the law regarding prohibition of ragging as well as the 
punishments, and to the effect that he/she has not been expelled and/or debarred 
from admission by any institution and that he/she, if found guilty of the 
offence of ragging and/or abetting ragging, is liable to be punished 
appropriately. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.5 The application form shall also contain a printed undertaking, 
preferably both in English/Hindi and in one of the regional languages known to 
the institution and the parent/guardian (English version given in Annexure I, 
Part II), to be signed by the parent/guardian of the applicant to the effect 
that he/she is also aware of the law in this regard and agrees to abide by the 
punishment meted out to his/her ward in case the latter is found guilty of 
ragging and/or abetting ragging. 
 A database shall be created out of affidavits affirmed by each student and 
his/her parents/guardians stored electronically, and shall contain the details 
of each student. The database shall also function as a record of ragging 
complaints received. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.6 The application for admission shall be accompanied by a document in the 
form of the School Leaving Certificate/transfer certificate/migration 
certificate/Character Certificate which shall include a report on the 
behavioural pattern of the applicant, so that the institution can thereafter 
keep intense watch upon a student who has a negative entry in this regard. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.7 A student seeking admission to the hostel shall have to submit 
additional undertaking in the form of Annexure I (both Parts) along with his/her 
application for hostel accommodation. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.8 At the commencement of the academic session the Head of the Institution 
shall convene and address a meeting of various functionaries/agencies, like 
Wardens, representatives of students, parents/guardians, faculty, district 
administration including police, to discuss the measures to be taken to prevent 
ragging in the institution and steps to be taken to identify the offenders and 
punish them suitably. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.9 To make the community at large and the students in particular aware of 
the dehumanising effect of ragging, and the approach of the institution towards 
those indulging in ragging, big posters (preferably multi-coloured with 
different colours for the provisions of law, punishments, etc.) shall be 
prominently displayed on all Notice Boards of all departments, hostels and other 
buildings as well as at vulnerable places. Some of such posters shall be of 
permanent nature in certain vulnerable places. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.10 Apart from placing posters mentioned in sub-clause 6.1.9 above at 
strategic places, the Medical College/Institution shall undertake measures for 
extensive publicity against ragging by means of audio-visual aids, by holding 
counselling sessions, workshops, painting and design competitions among students 
and other methods as it deems fit. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.11 The Medical College/Institution/University shall request the media to 
give adequate publicity to the law prohibiting ragging and the negative aspects 
of ragging and the institution's resolve to ban ragging and punish those found 
guilty without fear or favour. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.12 The Medical College/Institution/University shall identify, properly 
illuminate and man all vulnerable locations. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.13 The Medical College/Institution/University shall tighten security in 
its premises, especially at the vulnerable places. If necessary, intense 
policing shall be resorted to at such points at odd hours during the early 
months of the academic session. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>1.14 The Medical College/Institution/University shall utilize the vacation 
period before the start of the new academic year to launch wide publicity 
campaign against ragging through posters, leaflets, seminars, street plays, etc. 

 </article><article><number>6</number>1.15 The faculties/departments/units of the Medical 
College/Institution/University shall have induction arrangements (including 
those which anticipate, identify and plan to meet any special needs of any 
specific section of students) in place well in advance of the beginning of the 
academic year with a clear sense of the main aims and objectives of the 
induction process. <title></title>
 The Principal or Head of the Institution/Department shall obtain an 
undertaking from every employee of the institution including teaching and 
non-teaching members of staff, contract labour employed in the premises either 
for running canteen or as watch and ward staff or for cleaning or maintenance of 
the buildings/lawns, etc. that he/she would report promptly any case of ragging 
which comes to his/her notice. A provision shall be made in the service rules 
for issuing certificates of appreciation to such members of the staff who report 
ragging which will form part of their service record. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>2. On admission: 
 </article><article><number>6</number>2.1 Every fresher admitted to the Medical College/Institution/University 
shall be given a printed leaflet detailing when and to whom he/she has to turn 
to for help and guidance for various purposes (including Wardens, Head of the 
institution, members of the anti-ragging committees, relevant district and 
police authorities), addresses and telephone numbers of such 
persons/authorities, etc., so that the fresher need not look up to the seniors 
for help in such matters and get indebted to them and start doing things, right 
or wrong, at their behest. Such a step will reduce the freshers' dependence on 
their seniors. 
 Every institution should engage or seek the assistance of professional 
counsellors at the time of admissions to counsel 'freshers' in order to prepare 
them for the life ahead, particularly for adjusting to the life in hostels. 
<title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>2.2 The Medical College/Institution/University through the leaflet 
mentioned above shall explain to the new entrants the arrangements for their 
induction and orientation which promote efficient and effective means of 
integrating them fully as students. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>2.3 The leaflet mentioned above shall also inform the freshers about their 
rights as bona fide students of the institution and clearly instructing 
them that they should desist from doing anything against their will even if 
ordered by the seniors, and that they have nothing to fear as the institution 
cares for them and shall not tolerate any atrocities against them. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>2.4 The leaflet mentioned above shall contain a calendar of events and 
activities laid down by the institution to facilitate and complement 
familiarization of freshers with the academic environment of the institution. 

 </article><article><number>6</number>2.5 The Medical College/Institution/University shall also organize joint 
sensitization programmes of 'freshers' and seniors. 
 On the arrival of senior students after the first week or after the second 
week as the case may be, further orientation programmes must be scheduled as 
follows: 
 
 <section><number>i</number> joint sensitization programme and counselling of both 'freshers' and 
  senior by a Professional counselor; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> joint orientation programme of 'freshers' and seniors to be addressed 
  by the principal/Head of the institution, and the anti -ragging committee; 

 </section><section><number>iii</number> organization on a large scale of cultural, sports and other 
  activities to provide a platform for the 'freshers' and seniors to interact in 
  the presence of faculty members; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> in the hostel, the warden should address all students; may request two 
  junior colleagues from the college faculty to assist the warden by becoming 
  resident tutors for a temporary duration. </section>
 </article><article><number>6</number>2.6 Freshers shall be encouraged to report incidents of ragging, either as 
victims, or even as witnesses. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>3. At the end of the academic year: 
 </article><article><number>6</number>3.1 At the end of every academic year the Dean/Principal/Director shall 
send a letter to the parents/guardians of the students who are completing the 
first year, informing them about the law regarding ragging and the punishments, 
and appealing to them to impress upon their wards to desist from indulging in 
ragging when they come back at the beginning of the next academic session. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>3.2 At the end of every academic year the Medical 
College/Institution/University shall form a 'Mentoring Cell' consisting of 
Mentors for the succeeding academic year. There shall be as many levels or tiers 
of Mentors as the number of batches in the institution, at the rate of one 
Mentor for six freshers and one Mentor of a higher level for six Mentors of the 
lower level. 
 Each batch of freshers should be divided into small groups and each such 
group shall be assigned to a member of the staff. Such staff member should 
interact individually with, each member of the group on a daily basis for 
ascertaining the problems/difficulties if any faced by the fresher in the 
institution and extending necessary help. 
 In the case of freshers admitted to a hostel it shall be the responsibility 
of the teacher in charge of the group to coordinate with the warden of the 
hostel and to make surprise visits to the rooms in the hostel where the members 
of the group are lodged. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>4. Setting up of Committees and their functions: 
 </article><article><number>6</number>4.1 The Anti-Ragging Committee :-Every institution shall have an 
Anti-Ragging Committee and an Anti -Ragging Squad. The Anti-Ragging Committee 
shall be headed by the Head of the institution and shall consist of 
representatives of civil and police administration, local media, Non Government 
Organizations involved in youth activities, faculty members, parents, students 
belonging to the freshers' category as well as seniors and non-teaching staff. 
It shall monitor the anti-ragging activities in the institution, consider the 
recommendations of the Anti-Ragging Squad and take appropriate decisions, 
including spelling out suitable punishments to those found guilty. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>4.2 The Anti-Ragging Squad :-The Anti-Ragging Squad shall be 
nominated by the Head of the institution with such representation as considered 
necessary and shall exclusively consist of members belonging to the various 
sections of the campus community. The Squad shall have vigil, oversight and 
patrolling functions. It shall be kept mobile, alert and active at all times and 
shall be empowered to inspect places of potential ragging and make surprise 
raids on hostels and other hot spots. The Squad shall investigate incidents of 
ragging and make recommendations to the Anti-Ragging Committee and shall work 
under the overall guidance of the Anti-Ragging Committee. 
 All matters of discipline within teaching institutions must be resolved 
within the campus except those impinging on law and order or breach of peace or 
public tranquility, all of which should be dealt with under the penal laws of 
the land. <title></title>
 University Monitoring Cell .-At the level of the University, we 
recommend that there should be a Monitoring Cell on Ragging, which should 
coordinate with the affiliated colleges and institutions under its domain. The 
Cell should call for reports from the Heads of institutions in regard to the 
activities of the Anti-Ragging Committee, Anti-Ragging Squads, Monitoring Cells 
at the level of the institution, the compliance with instructions on conducting 
orientation programmes, counselling sessions, the incidents of ragging, the 
problems faced by wardens or other officials. It should also keep itself abreast 
of the decisions of the District level Anti-Ragging Committee. This Monitoring 
Cell should also review the efforts made by institutions to publicize 
anti-ragging measures, soliciting of undertaking from parents and students each 
year to abstain from ragging activities or willingness to be penalized for 
violations; and should function as the prime mover for initiating action on the 
part of the appropriate authorities of the university for amending the Statutes 
or Ordinances or Bye-laws to facilitate the implementation of anti-ragging 
measures at the level of the institution. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>5. Other measures: 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.1 The Annexures mentioned in 6.1.4, 6.1.5 and 6.1.7 of these Regulations 
shall be furnished at the beginning of each academic year by every student, that 
is, by freshers as well as seniors. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.2 The Medical College/Institution/University shall arrange for regular 
and periodic psychological counselling and orientation for students (for 
freshers separately, as well as jointly with seniors) by professional 
counsellors during the first three months of the new academic year. This shall 
be done at the institution and department/course levels. Parents and teachers 
shall also be involved in such sessions. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.3 Full-time warden shall be appointed as per the eligibility criteria 
laid down for the post reflecting both the command and control aspects of 
maintaining discipline, as well as the softer skills of counselling and 
communicating with the youth outside the class-room situations. Wardens shall be 
accessible at all hours and shall be provided with mobile phones and the details 
of their telephone number must be widely publicized. Similarly, the telephone 
numbers of the other important functionaries - Heads of institutions, Faculty 
members, Members of the anti-ragging committees, district and sub-divisional 
authorities and State authorities where relevant, should also be widely 
disseminated for the needy to get in touch or seek help in emergencies. The 
institution shall review and suitably enhance the powers and perquisites of 
Wardens and authorities involved in curbing the menace of ragging. 
 Further the institutions shall provide necessary incentives for the post of 
full-time warden, so as to attract suitable candidates. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.4 Freshers shall be lodged in a separate hostel block, wherever possible, 
and where such facilities are not available, the college/institution shall 
ensure that seniors' access to freshers' accommodation is strictly monitored by 
wardens, security guards and college staff. 
 As ragging takes place mostly in the hostels after the classes are over in 
the college, a round the clock vigil against ragging in the hostel premises 
shall be provided. It is seen, that college canteens and hostel messes are also 
places where ragging often takes place. The employers/employees of the 
canteens/mess shall be given necessary instructions to keep strict vigil and to 
report the incidents of ragging to the college authorities if any. 
<title></title>
 The security personnel posted in hostels shall be under the direct control of 
the Wardens and assessed by them. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.5 Private commercially managed lodges and hostels shall be registered 
with the local police authorities, and this shall be done necessarily on the 
recommendation of the Head of the institution. Local police, Local 
administration and the institutional authorities shall ensure vigil on incidents 
that may come within the definition of ragging and shall be responsible for 
action in the event of ragging in such premises, just as they would be for 
incidents within the campus. Managements of such private hostels shall be 
responsible for action in the event of ragging in such premises, just as they 
would be for incidents within campuses. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.6 Besides registering private hostels as stated above, the towns or 
cities where educational institutions are located should be apportioned as 
sectors among faculty members, as is being done by some institutions, so that 
they could maintain vigil and report any incidents of ragging outside campuses 
and en route while 'freshers' commute. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.7 The Head of the institution shall take immediate action on receipt of 
the recommendations of the Ant-Ragging Squad. He/She shall also take action 
suo motu if the circumstances so warrant. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.8 Freshers who do not report the incidents of ragging either as victims 
or as witnesses shall also be punished suitably. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.9 Anonymous random surveys shall be conducted across the 1st year batch 
of students (freshers) every fortnight during the first three months of the 
academic year to verify and cross-check whether the campus is indeed free of 
ragging or not. The institution may design its own methodology of conducting 
such surveys. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.10 The burden of proof shall lie on the perpetrator of ragging and not on 
the victim. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.11 The institution shall file an FIR with the police/local authorities 
whenever a case of ragging is reported, but continue with its own enquiry and 
other measures without waiting for action on the part of the police/local 
authorities. Remedial action shall be initiated and completed within the one 
week of the incident itself. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.12 The Migration/Transfer Certificate issued to the student by the 
Medical College/Institution/University shall have an entry, apart from those 
relating to general conduct and behaviour, whether the student has been punished 
for the offence of committing or abetting ragging, or not, as also whether the 
student has displayed persistent violent or aggressive behaviour or any 
inclination to harm others. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.13 Preventing or acting against ragging shall be the collective 
responsibility of all levels and sections of authorities or functionaries in the 
Medical College/Institution/University, including faculty, and not merely that 
of the specific body/committee constituted for prevention of ragging. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>5.14 As such the college canteens and hostel messes are also places where 
ragging often takes place, hence the employers/employees of the canteens/mess 
shall be given necessary instructions to keep strict vigil and to report the 
incidents of ragging to the college authorities, if any. <title></title>
 Further <title></title>access to mobile phones and public phones shall be 
unrestricted in hostels and campuses, except in class-rooms, seminar halls, 
library, etc., where jammers shall be installed to restrict the use of mobile 
phones. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>6</number>6 Measures for encouraging healthy interaction between freshers and 
seniors: 
 </article><article><number>6</number>6.1 The Medical College/Institution/University shall set up appropriate 
committees including the Course-in-charge, Student advisor, Warden and some 
senior students to actively monitor, promote and regulate healthy interaction 
between the freshers and senior students. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>6.2 Freshers' welcome parties shall be organized in each department by the 
senior students and the faculty together soon after admissions, preferably 
within the first two weeks of the beginning of the academic session, for proper 
introduction to one another and where the talents of the freshers are brought 
out properly in the presence of the faculty, thus helping them to shed their 
inferiority complex, if any, and remove their inhibitions. 
 </article><article><number>6</number>6.3 The Medical College/Institution/University shall enhance the 
student-faculty interaction by involving the students in all matters of the 
institution, except those relating to the actual processes of evaluation and of 
faculty appointments, so that the students shall feel that they are responsible 
partners in managing the affairs of the institution and consequently the credit 
due to the institution for good work/performance is due to them as well. 
<title></title>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Regulatory Measures: </title>
 The inspecting/visiting committees of MCI shall cross verify that the medical 
college/institution has strictly complied with the anti ragging measures and has 
a blemishless record in terms of there being no incident of ragging during the 
impending period ( i.e. from earlier inspection) or otherwise. 
<title></title>
 <title></title>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Awardable Punishments: </title>
 </article><article><number>8</number>1 At the Medical College/Institution level: 
 Depending upon the nature and gravity of the offence as established by the 
Anti-Ragging Committee of the institution, the possible punishments for those 
found guilty of ragging at the institution level shall be any one or any 
combination of the following: 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.1 Suspension from attending classes and academic privileges; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.2 Withholding/withdrawing scholarship/fellowship and other benefits; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.3 Debarring from appearing in any test/examination or other evaluation 
Process; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.4. Withholding results; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.5 Debarring from representing the institution in any regional, national 
or international meet, tournament, youth festival, etc.; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.6 Suspension/expulsion from the hostel; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.7 Cancellation of admission; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.8 Rustication from the institution for period ranging from 1 to 4 
semesters; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.9 Expulsion from the institution and consequent debarring from admission 
to any other institution for a specific period; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.10 Fine of Rs. 25,000 and Rs. 1 lakh; 
 </article><article><number>8</number>1.11 Collective punishment : When the persons committing or 
abetting the crime of ragging are not identified, the institution shall resort 
to collective punishment. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>8</number>2 Penal consequences for the heads of the institutions/administration of 
the institution who do not take timely steps in the prevention of ragging and 
punishing those who rag 
 The authorities of the institution particularly the Head of the institution, 
shall be responsible to ensure that no incident of ragging takes place in the 
institution. In case any incident of ragging takes place, the Head shall take 
prompt and appropriate action against the person(s) whose dereliction of duty 
lead to the incident. The authority designated to appoint the Head shall, in its 
turn, take prompt and appropriate action against the Head. 
 In addition to penal consequences, departmental enquiries be initiated 
against such heads institutions/members of the administration/faculty 
members/non-teaching staff, who display an apathetic or insensitive attitude 
towards complaints of ragging. <title></title>
 </article><article><number>8</number>3 At the MCI level 
 </article><article><number>8</number>3.1 Impose an exemplary fine of Rs. 1 lakh for each incident of ragging 
payable by erring medical college/institution to such authority as may be 
designated by the appropriate Govt., as the case may be. 
 </article><article><number>8</number>3.2 Declare the erring Medical College /Institution/ University as not 
having the minimum academic standards and warning the potential candidates for 
admission at such institution through public notice and posing on the MCI 
website. 
 </article><article><number>8</number>3.3 Declare the erring Medical College/Institution/University to be 
ineligible for preferring any application under Section 10A of the Indian 
Medical Council Act, 1956 for a minimum period of one year, extendable by such 
quantum by the Council as would be commensurate with the wrong. 
 <title></title>


</article><form>
 

THE MEDICAL COUNCIL OF INDIA (PREVENTION AND 
PROHIBITION OF RAGGING IN MEDICAL COLLEGES/INSTITUTIONS) REGULATIONS, 
20091 
 

 
 

ANNEXURE I 
 

Part I 
 

 UNDERTAKING BY THE CANDIDATE/STUDENT 
 

1. I, 
............................................................................................................................................... 
S/o. D/o. of Mr./Mrs./Ms. 
............................................................................, 
have carefully read and fully understood the law prohibiting ragging and the 
directions of the Supreme Court and the Central/State Government in this regard. 

 

2. I have received a copy of the MCI Regulations on Curbing the Menace of 
Ragging in Higher Educational Institutions, 2009. 
 

3. I hereby undertake that- 
 
 

. I will not indulge in any behaviour or act that may come under the 
  definition of ragging, 
 

. I will not participate in or abet or propagate ragging in any form, 
 

. I will not hurt anyone physically or psychologically or cause any other 
  harm. 
 

4. I hereby agree that if found guilty of any aspect of ragging, I may be 
punished as per the provisions of the MCI Regulations mentioned above and/or as 
per the law in force. 
 

Signed this ................................................ day 
of...................................................... month 
of........................ year. 
 

 Signature 
 

 Address: ...................................... 
 

....................................................... 
 

....................................................... 
 

Name: 
 

(1) Witness:    
 

(2) Witness: 
 

Part II 
 

UNDERTAKING BY PARENT/GUARDIAN 
 

1. I, 
............................................................................................................................................... 
F/o, M/o, 
G/o............................................................................, 
have carefully read and fully understood the law prohibiting ragging and the 
directions of the Hon'ble Supreme Court and the Central/State Government in this 
regard as well as the MCI Regulations on Curbing the menace of ragging in Higher 
Educational Institutions, 2009. 
 

2. I assure you that my son/daughter/ward will not indulge in any act of 
ragging. 
 

3. I hereby agree that if he/she is found guilty of any aspect of ragging, 
he/she may be punished as per the provisions of the MCI Regulations mentioned 
above and/or as per the law in force. 
 

Signed this....................................................... day 
of................................................. month 
of.................................. Year. 
 

 Signature 
 

 Address: ...................................... 
 

....................................................... 
 

....................................................... 
 

 Name: 
 

 
 

(1) Witness:    
 

(2) Witness: 
 

 
 

-------------
 

1. Vide Notification No. MCI-34(1)/2009-Med./25453, dated 3rd 
August, 2009.</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>