<act><tid>1216565</tid>
<title>THE DOURINE ACT, <year>1910</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <footcitenum>19101</footcitenum>
[ 25th February, <year>1910</year>.]

An Act to provide for the prevention of the spread of Dourine.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the prevention of the 
spread of dourine; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>198110</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>522879</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Dourine Act, <year>1910</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>244419</tid>
<number>2</number>This section extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the 
territories which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were 
comprised in Part B States]: the rest of this Act extends only to such 
areas as the State Government may, by notification 3 in the Official 
Gazette, direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>87724</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.
<section><tid>1379783</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, the expressions" inspector"  
and" veterinary practitioner" mean, respectively, the officers 
appointed as such under this Act, acting within the local limits for 
which they are so appointed.

</section>

<section><tid>874266</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of this Act in so far as they relate to 
entire horses shall, if the State Government, by notification as 
aforesaid, so directs, apply also to entire asses used for mule- 
breeding purposes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1001674</tid>
<number>3</number>Registration of horses. The State Government may, by 
notification as aforesaid, make such orders as it thinks fit directing 
and regulating the registration of entire horses maintained for 
breeding purposes.


</article>



<article><tid>904901</tid>
<number> 4</number> Appointment of inspectors and veterinary practitioners.
<section><tid>860221</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by notification as aforesaid, appoint any 
persons it thinks fit to be inspectors, and any qualified veterinary 
surgeons to be veterinary practitioners, under this Act,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to the State of Goa, Daman and Diu by 
Reg. 11 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

The Act has been amended in its application to the State of 
Maharashtra by Maharashtra Act 34 of <year>1960</year>.

The Act has been repealed in its application to Bellary District 
by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>.

This Act has been declared to be in force in the Khondmals 
District by the Khondmals Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (4 of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and 
Sch.; and in the Angul District by the Angul Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (5  
  of <year>1936</year>). s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part 
B States",

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>It has been so extended to Coorg, see Coorg Gazette, <year>1919</year>, Pt. 
I; p. 118, to Bombay, see Bombay Gazette, <year>1919</year>, Pt. I. p. 3001; to 
the C. P., see C. P. Gazette, <year>1922</year>, Pt. I, p. 1151.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

and to exercise and perform, within any area prescribed by the noti- 
fication, the powers conferred and duties imposed by this Act upon 
such officers respectively.


</section>

<section><tid>1764372</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person so appointed shall be deemed to be a public 
servant within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1950900</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of inspector. An inspector may, subject to such rules 
as the State Government may make in this behalf,-
<section><tid>822435</tid>
<number>a</number>enter and search any building, field or other place for 
the purpose of ascertaining whether there is therein any 
horse which is affected with dourine; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1626536</tid>
<number>b</number>prohibit, by order in writing, the owner or keeper of 
any horse, which in his opinion is affected with dourine, 
from using such horse for breeding purposes, pending 
examination by the veterinary practitioner;

</section>

<section><tid>840454</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> direct, by order in writing, the owner or keeper of 
any horse which, in the opinion of the inspectors, is 
affected with dourine to remove it or permit it to be removed 
for the purpose of segregation to a place specified in the 
order, and such direction shall be sufficient authority for 
the detention of the horse in that place for that purpose.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>234073</tid>
<number>6</number>Duties of inspector. An inspector issuing an order under 
section 5, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> shall forthwith forward a copy of such order to the 
veterinary practitioner.


</article>



<article><tid>209340</tid>
<number>7</number>Inspection of horses. A veterinary practitioner receiving a 
copy of an order forwarded under section 6 shall, as soon as possible 
after receipt of such copy, examine the horse mentioned therein, and 
may for such purpose enter any building, field or other place.


</article>



<article><tid>802565</tid>
<number> 8</number> Powers of veterinary practitioner. A veterinary 
practitioner may-
<section><tid>225251</tid>
<number>a</number>cancel any order issued under section 5, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" and" rep. by Act 8 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 2, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The word and letter" clause (b)" rep. by s. 3, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The word and letter" clause (b)" rep. by. s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>935304</tid>
<number>b</number>if on microscopical examination <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or by other 
scientific test] he finds that any horse is affected with 
dourine,-

<subsection><tid>766579</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of an entire horse, cause it to be 
castrated,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>166716</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in the case of a mare, with the previous sanc- 
tion of such authority as the State Government may 
appoint in this behalf, or, if so empowered by the State 
Government, without such sanction, cause it to be 
destroyed.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1920</year>, s. 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for the original sub- clause.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>950351</tid>
<number> 9</number> Compensation for horse destroyed, etc. When any horse is 
castrated or destroyed under section 8, the market- value of such horse 
immediately before it became affected with dourine shall be 
ascertained; and the State Government shall pay as compensation to the 
owner thereof-
<section><tid>1650136</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a mare which has been destroyed, or of 
an entire horse which has died in consequence of castration, 
such market- value, and,

</section>

<section><tid>663805</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of an entire horse which survives 
castration, half the amount by which such value has been 
diminished owing to infection with dourine and castration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>393328</tid>
<number> 10</number> Settlement of compensation.
<section><tid>710845</tid>
<number>1</number>A veterinary practitioner  
may award, as compensation to be paid under section 9 in respect of 
each horse castrated or destroyed under section 8, a sum not exceeding 
two hundred and fifty rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>952053</tid>
<number>2</number>If, in the opinion of the veterinary practitioner, the 
amount which should be paid as such compensation exceeds two hundred 
and fifty rupees, he shall report accordingly to the Collector, who 
shall decide the amount to be so paid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1174463</tid>
<number> 11</number> Committees for hearing appeals.
<section><tid>1667242</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government  
shall, by rules published in the Official Gazette, make provision for 
the constitution of a committee or committees for the hearing of 
appeals from decisions under section 10.

</section>

<section><tid>1106339</tid>
<number>2</number>Such rules shall provide that not less than one member of 
any committee constituted thereunder shall be a person not in the 
service of the Government or of a local authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297170</tid>
<number>12</number>Appeals. Any owner may, within two months from the date of 
a decision under section 10, appeal against such decision to the 
committee constituted in that behalf by rules made under section 11, 
and the decision of such committee shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1461754</tid>
<number> 13</number> Vexatious entries and searches.
<section><tid>751115</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever, being an  
inspector appointed under this Act, vexatiously and unnecessarily 
enters or searches any field, building or other place, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with 
both.

</section>

<section><tid>92764</tid>
<number>2</number>No prosecution under this section shall be instituted after 
the expiry of three months from the date on which the offence has been 
committed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1707458</tid>
<number> 14</number> Rules.
<section><tid>1413116</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may make rules for the  
purpose of carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>456502</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power such rules as aforesaid may-

<subsection><tid>1986485</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> regulate the exercise of the powers conferred on 
inspectors under section 5;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>227498</tid>
<number>b</number>regulate the action to be taken by veterinary 
practitioners under section 8; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>887534</tid>
<number>3</number>All such rules shall be published in the Official Gazette, 
and, on such publication, shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>164979</tid>
<number>4</number>In making any rule under this section the State Government 
may direct that a breach of it shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1889231</tid>
<number> 15</number> Penalties. Whoever uses or permits to be used for breeding 
purposes-
<section><tid>1730992</tid>
<number>a</number>any horse which has not been registered in accordance 
with the requirements of a notification under section 3, or

</section>

<section><tid>577036</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> any horse in respect of Which an order under clause 
 (b) or clause (c) of section 5 is in force,]
shall be punishable with fine which may amount, in the case of a first 
conviction, to fifty rupees, or, in the case of a second or subsequent 
conviction, to one hundred rupees.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>933397</tid>
<number>16</number>Protection to persons acting under Act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for 
anything which is, in good faith, done or intended to be done under 
this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1920</year>, s, 5, for the original clause.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The word" and" at the end of cl. (b) and the whole of clause 
 (c) rep. by s. 5, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1920</year>, s. 6, for the original cls. (b) and 
 (c)

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>