<act><title>THE FOOD SAFETY AND STANDARDS AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
(SALARIES, ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND 
MEMBERS) RULES, 20081 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Food Safety and Standards Authority of India (Salaries, Allowances 
and other Conditions of Service of Chairperson and Members) Rules, 2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Food Safety and Standards Act, 2006 (34 of 2006); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Authority means the Food Safety and Standards Authority of India 
  established under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Chairperson means the Chairperson of the Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> meeting means a meeting convened by the Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Member means a member of the Authority. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All other words and expressions used herein but not defined shall have 
the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number>Salaries and allowances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson shall be 
paid a salary of twenty-six thousand rupees per month (fixed). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson shall be entitled to draw dearness allowance and city 
compensatory allowance at the rate admissible to officers holding Group A' post 
of the Central Government drawing an equivalent pay: 
 Provided that in case of appointment of a person as the Chairperson who has 
retired from the service under the Central Government or a State Government and 
who is in receipt of, or has received or has become entitled to receive any 
retirement benefits by way of pension, gratuity, employers contribution to the 
Contributory Provident Fund or other forms of retirement benefits, the pay of 
such person shall be reduced by the gross amount of pension or employers 
contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund or any other form of retirement 
benefits, if any (except pension equivalent of gratuity), drawn or to be drawn 
by him: 
 Provided further that if a person who has retired from any service including 
service under Central Government or a State Government, Public Sector 
Undertakings or Autonomous Bodies is appointed as the Chairperson, he shall be 
entitled to receive dearness allowance at the same rate as is admissible to 
officers holding Group A' post of the Central Government drawing an equivalent 
pay, but he shall not be entitled to receive dearness relief on pension during 
the period he holds office as such Chairperson. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Leave. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson shall be entitled to thirty 
days of earned leave, for every year of service. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The payment of leave salary during leave shall be governed by rule 40 of 
the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Chairperson shall be entitled to encashment of fifty per cent. of 
earned leave standing to his credit at any time. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Provident Fund. </title>The Chairperson shall be entitled to 
subscribe to the Contributory Provident Fund at his option and in case of his so 
opting shall be governed by the Contributory Provident Fund Rules, 1962. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Travelling allowance and daily allowance. </title>The 
Chairperson shall be entitled to travelling allowance and daily allowance for 
transportation of personal effects while on tour or on transfer (including the 
journey undertaken to join the Authority or on the expiry of his term with the 
Authority to proceed to his home-town), at the same rates as are admissible to 
officers holding Group A' post of the Central Government drawing an equivalent 
pay. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Domestic official tours. </title>The Chairperson, while on tour, 
shall be entitled to the facility of Government accommodation in guest houses or 
inspection bungalows run by the Central Government, wherever available, on 
payment of normal rent at outstations while on tour as is admissible to officers 
holding to Group A' post of the Central Government drawing an equivalent pay: 

 Provided that where Government accommodation is not available, while on 
domestic official tour, the Chairperson shall be entitled to stay in India 
Tourism Development Corporation hotels on a reimbursement basis and wherever 
India Tourism Development Corporation hotels are not available, in other hotels 
on reimbursement basis, reimbursement in both cases being limited to lodging 
charges only, and on a single room occupancy basis. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Leave Travel Concession. </title>The Chairperson shall be 
entitled to leave travel concession at the same rate as is admissible to 
officers holding Group A' post of the Central Government drawing an equivalent 
pay. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Medical treatment. </title>The Chairperson shall be entitled to 
medical treatment and hospital facilities, as provided in the Central Government 
Health Scheme and at places where the Central Government Health Scheme is not in 
operation, the Chairperson shall be entitled to facilities as provided in the 
Central Services (Medical Attendance) Rules, 1944. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Official visits abroad. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson shall be 
entitled to undertake official visits abroad with the prior approval of the 
Minister of the Government of India in-charge of the Ministry of Health and 
Family Welfare and after clearance from the Ministry of External Affairs on the 
points relating to political affairs. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The daily allowance and provision of hotel accommodation during the 
period of tour abroad shall be regulated in accordance with the Government 
instructions as applicable to officers of equal grade in the Government of 
India. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Indian Missions abroad shall take care of arrangements and extend 
facilities as are admissible to officers holding Group A' post of the Central 
Government drawing an equivalent pay. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Conveyance facility. </title>The Chairperson shall be entitled 
to conveyance facilities as are admissible to officers holding Group A' post of 
the Central Government drawing an equivalent pay. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Accommodation. </title>The Chairperson shall be entitled to 
rent-free accommodation at the rates specified by the Central Government or 
house rent allowance at the rate of thirty per cent. of his pay in lieu thereof; 
and on demitting office, the Chairperson shall be entitled for retention of 
residential accommodation for one month on the same terms and conditions. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Retirement from Government service. </title>Chairperson, who on 
the date of his appointment to the Authority, was in service of the Central 
Government or a State Government, shall seek retirement from such service before 
his appointment to the Authority. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Meeting allowance to a member. </title>A member, not being an 
ex officio member, shall be entitled to receive an allowance of two 
thousand rupees for a meeting of the Authority attended by him: 
 Provided that total of such allowance to a member shall not exceed twenty-six 
thousand rupees per month. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Conveyance allowance to a member. </title>A member, not being 
an ex officio member, shall, for attending a meeting of the Authority, 
be reimbursed an amount of five hundred rupees or the actual expenses incurred 
by him, whichever is less, and the reimbursement shall be claimed on 
self-certification basis: 
 Provided that no conveyance allowance shall be admissible to a Government 
officer appointed as a member of the Authority: 
 Provided further that where a member is called upon to go out of the ordinary 
place of his residence for discharging his duties as such member shall be 
entitled to travelling allowance, daily allowance, and accommodation at the same 
rates as are admissible to the Chairperson: 
 Provided also that official visits abroad by such member shall be governed by 
the same provisions as are applicable to the Chairperson. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Oath of office and secrecy. </title>Every person appointed to 
be the Chairperson or a Member shall, before entering upon his office, make and 
subscribe an oath of office and secrecy, in Forms I and II annexed to these 
rules. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Interpretation. </title>If any question arises relating to the 
interpretation of these rules, the same shall be referred to the Central 
Government for its decision. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Residuary provision. </title>Any matter, not expressly provided 
in these rules, shall be referred to the Central Government for its decision, 
and the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Power to relax. </title>The Central Government shall have power 
to relax any of the provisions of these rules in respect of any class or 
category of persons. 

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 5-7-2008 .</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>