<act><title>


the EMPLOYEES’ PROVIDENT FUNDS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 19971</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Employees’ Provident Funds Appellate Tribunal 
(Procedure) Rules, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force from the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
  <number>a</number>  “Act” means the 
Employees’ Provident Funds and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1952 (19 of 1952);
 </section><section>
  <number>b</number>  “agent” means a 
person duly authorised by a party to present an appeal or a written reply on its 
behalf before the Tribunal;
 </section><section>
  <number>c</number>  “appellant” means a 
person or the establishment making an appeal to the Tribunal under section 7-I;
 </section><section>
  <number>d</number>  “Form” means a Form 
specified in Appendix;
 

1[(dd)   “Fund” 
means Provident Fund, Pension Fund and Insurance Fund established under the 
Act;]
 </section><section>
  <number>e</number>  “legal 
practitioner” shall have the same meaning as is assigned to it in the Advocates 
Act, 1961 (25 of 1961);
 </section><section>
   <number>f</number>  “legal 
representative” means a person who in law represents the estate of the deceased;
 </section><section>
  <number>g</number>  “Registrar” means 
the Registrar appointed for the Tribunal and includes any officer to whom the 
powers and functions of the Registrar may be delegated under these rules;
 </section><section>
  <number>h</number>  “Registry” means 
the Registry of the Tribunal;
 </section><section>
   <number>i</number>  “Tribunal” means 
the Employees’ Provident Funds Appellate Tribunal established under sub-section 
(1) of section 7D of the Act;
 </section><section>
   <number>j</number>  the words and 
expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall 
have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Language of the 
Tribunal.—The 
language of the Tribunal shall be English:
 
Provided that the parties 
proceeding before the Tribunal may file documents drawn up in Hindi, if they so 
desire:
 
Provided further that—
 <section>
  <number>a</number> the Tribunal may, in 
its discretion permit the use of Hindi in the proceedings but the final order 
shall be in English;
 </section><section>
  <number>b</number> the Tribunal hearing 
the matter, may in its discretion, direct the English translation of pleadings 
and documents to be filed.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Procedure for filing 
appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
appeal to this Tribunal shall be presented in Form I by the appellant in person 
or by an agent or by a duly authorised legal practitioner to the Registry or any 
other officer authorised in writing by the Registrar to receive the same or be 
sent by registered post with acknowledgment duly addressed to the Registrar of 
the Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The appeal under 
sub-rule (1) shall be presented in triplicate in a paper-book form along with 
one unused file size envelope bearing full address of the respondent.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the number of 
respondents is more than one, as many extra copies of the appeal in paper book 
form as there are respondents together with unused file size envelopes bearing 
the full address of each respondent shall be furnished by the appellant:
 
Provided that where the 
number of respondents is more than five, the Registrar may permit the appellant 
to file the extra copies of the appeal at the time of issue of notice to the 
respondents.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The appellant may 
attach to and present with his appeal a receipt slip in Form II which shall be 
signed by the Registrar or the officer receiving the appeal on behalf of the 
Registrar in acknowledgment of the receipt of the appeal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Presentation and 
scrutiny of appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar or the officer authorised by him under rule 4, shall endorse on 
every appeal the date on which it is presented or deemed to have been presented 
under that rule and shall sign the endorsement.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, on scrutiny, the 
appeal is found to be in order it shall be duly registered and given a serial 
number.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the appeal, on 
scrutiny, is found to be defective and the defect noticed is formal in nature, 
the Registrar may allow the party to rectify the same in his presence and if the 
said defect is not formal in nature, the Registrar may allow the appellant such 
time to rectify the defect as he may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the appellant fails 
to rectify the defect within the time allowed under sub-rule (3), the Registrar 
may by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, decline to register the 
appeal and inform the appellant accordingly.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Place of filing 
appeals.—The 
appeal shall ordinarily be filed by the appellant with the Registrar of the 
Tribunal within whose jurisdiction:—
 <section>
   <number>i</number>  the appellant is 
residing for the time being, or
 </section><section>
   <number>ii</number>  the cause of 
action has arisen, or
 </section><section>
  <number>iii</number>  the respondent or 
any of the respondents against whom relief is sought, ordinarily resides:
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Fee, time for filing 
appeal, deposit of amount due on filing appeal.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Every appeal filed with the Registrar shall be accompanied by a fee of Rupees 
Five hundred to be remitted in the form of Crossed Demand Draft on a 
nationalised bank in favour of the Registrar of the Tribunal and payable at the 
main branch of that Bank at the station where the seat of the said Tribunal 
situate.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person aggrieved 
by a notification issued by the Central Government or an order passed by the 
Central Government or any other authority under the Act, may within 60 days from 
the date of issue of the notification/order prefer an appeal to the Tribunal:
 
Provided that the Tribunal 
may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause 
from preferring the appeal within the prescribed period, extend the said period 
by a further period of 60 days:
 
Provided further that no 
appeal by the employer shall be entertained by a Tribunal unless he has 

1[deposited with 
the Tribunal a Demand Draft payable in the Fund and bearing] 75 per cent of the 
amount due from him as determined under section 7A:
 
Provided also that the 
Tribunal may for reasons to be recorded in writing, waive or reduce the amount 
to be deposited under section 7-O.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Content of the 
appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every appeal filed under rule 4 shall set forth concisely under distinct heads 
the grounds for such appeal. Such grounds shall be numbered consecutively. Every 
appeal, including any miscellaneous appeal shall be typed in double space on one 
side on thick paper of good quality.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Documents to 
accompany the appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every appeal shall be accompanied by a paper book containing:
 <subsection>
   <number>i</number>  an attested true 
copy of the order against which the appeal is filed;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>ii</number>  copies of the 
documents relied upon by the appellant and referred to in the appeal;
 </subsection><subsection>
  <number>iii</number>  an index of the 
documents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The documents referred 
to in sub-rule (1) may be attested by a legal practitioner or by a gazetted 
officer and each document shall be marked serially the Annexures A1, A2, A3 and 
so on.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an appeal is 
filed by an agent, document authorising him to act as such agent shall also be 
appended to the appeal:
 
Provided that where an 
appeal is filed by a legal practitioner, it shall be accompanied by a duly 
executed “Vakalatnama”.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Plural remedies.—An 
appeal shall be based upon a single cause of action and may seek one or more 
reliefs provided that they are consequential to one another.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Service of notices 
and processes issued by the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notices or processes to be issued by the Tribunal may be served by any of the 
following modes directed by the Tribunal:—
 <subsection>
   <number>i</number>  service by the 
party itself;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>ii</number>  by hand delivery 
(Dasti) through process server;
 </subsection><subsection>
  <number>iii</number>  by registered 
post with acknowledgement due;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where notice issued by 
the Tribunal is served by the party himself by “hand delivery” (Dasti), 
he shall file with the Registry of the Tribunal, the acknowledgment, together 
with an affidavit of service.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1) the Tribunal may, taking into account the 
number of respondents and their places of residence or work and other 
circumstances, direct that notice of the appeal shall be served upon the 
respondents in any other manner including any manner of substituted service, as 
it appears to the Tribunal just and convenient.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything done under sub-rule (1) the Tribunal may, in its discretion, having 
regard to the nature and urgency of the case, direct the service of the notice 
on the Standing Counsel appointed as such by the Central Government or any State 
Government or any other authority under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every notice issued by 
the Tribunal shall, unless otherwise ordered, be accompanied by a copy of the 
appeal along with a copy of the paper-book.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every appellant shall 
pay a fee for the service or execution of processes in such manner as the 
Tribunal may direct under sub-rule (3) such a sum, not exceeding the actual 
charges incurred in effecting the service, as may be determined by the Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The fee for the 
service or execution of processes under sub-rule (3) shall be remitted in the 
manner prescribed in rule 7 within one week of the date of the order determining 
the fee or within such extended time as the Registrar may permit.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rules (1) to (4), if the Tribunal is satisfied that it 
is not reasonably practicable to serve notice of appeal upon all the 
respondents, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, direct that the 
appeal shall be heard notwithstanding that some of the respondents have not been 
served with notice of the application: provided that no appeal shall be heard 
unless—
 <subsection>
   <number>i</number>  notice of the 
appeal has been served on the Central Government or the State Government or the 
Central Board or if such Government or the Board is a respondent;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>ii</number>  notice of the 
appeal has been served on the authority which passed the order against which the 
appeal has been filed; and
 </subsection><subsection>
  <number>iii</number>  the Tribunal is 
satisfied that the interests of the respondents on whom notice of the appeal has 
not been served are adequately and sufficiently represented by the respondents 
on whom notice of the appeal has been served.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Filing of reply and 
other document by the respondents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Each respondent intending to contest the appeal, shall file in triplicate the 
reply to the appeal and the documents relied upon in paper-book form with the 
Registry within one month of the service of notice of the appeal on him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the reply field 
under sub-rule (1), the respondent shall specifically admit, deny or explain the 
facts stated by the appellant in his appeal and may also state such additional 
facts as may be found necessary for the just decision of the case. It shall be 
signed and verified as a written statement by the respondent or any other person 
duly authorised by him in writing in the same manner as provided for in Order 
VI, Rule 15 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The documents referred 
to in sub-rule (2) shall also be filed along with the reply and the same shall 
be marked as R1, R2, R3 and so on.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The respondent shall 
also serve a copy of the reply along with documents as mentioned in sub-rule (1) 
on the appellant or his legal practitioner, if any, and file proof of such 
service in the Registry.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Tribunal may allow 
filing of the reply after the expiry of the prescribed period.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Date and place of 
hearing to be notified.—The 
Tribunal shall notify to the parties the date and the place of hearing of the 
appeal in such manner as the Presiding Officer may by general or special order 
direct.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Calendar of cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Tribunal shall draw up a calendar for the hearing of cases and, as far as 
possible, hear and decide the cases according to the calendar.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every appeal shall be 
heard and decided, as far as possible, within six months from the date of its 
registration.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Tribunal shall 
have the power to decline an adjournment and also to limit the time for oral 
arguments.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>15</number> Action on appeal for 
appellant’s default.—
<section><number>1</number> Where on the date fixed for 
hearing of the appeal or on any other date to which such hearing may be 
adjourned, the appellant does not appear when the appeal is called for hearing, 
the Tribunal may, in its discretion either dismiss the appeal for default or 
hear and decide it on the merit.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an appeal has been 
dismissed for default and the appellant files an appeal within thirty days from 
the date of dismissal and satisfied the Tribunal that there was sufficient cause 
for his non-appearance when the appeal was called for hearing, the Tribunal 
shall make an order setting aside the order dismissing the appeal and restore 
the same:
 Provided, however, where the case 
was disposed of on the merits the decision shall not be reopened except by way 
of review.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Ex parte 
hearing and disposal of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where on the date fixed for hearing the appeal or on any other date to which 
such hearing may be adjourned, the appellant appears and the respondent does not 
appear when the appeal is called for hearing, the Tribunal may, in its 
discretion adjourn the hearing or hear and decide the appeal ex parte.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an appeal has 
been heard ex parte against a respondent or respondents, such respondent 
or respondents may apply to the Tribunal for an order to set it aside and if 
such respondent or respondents satisfy the Tribunal that the notice was not duly 
served or that he or they were prevented by any sufficient cause from appearing 
when the appeal was called for hearing the Tribunal may make an order setting 
aside the ex parte hearing as against him or them upon such terms as it 
thinks fit, and shall appoint a day for proceeding with the appeal:
 
Provided that where the 
ex parte order on the appeal is of such nature that it cannot be set aside 
as against one respondent only, it may be set aside as against all or any of the 
other respondents also:
 
Provided further that in 
cases covered by sub-rule (8) of rule 11, the Tribunal shall not set aside ex 
parte order of an appeal merely on the ground that it was not served upon a 
respondent or respondents.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Substitution of 
legal representatives.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the case of death of a party during the pendency of the proceedings before 
the Tribunal, the legal representatives of the deceased party may apply within 
thirty days of the date of such death for being brought on record as necessary 
parties.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where no application 
is received from the legal representatives within the period specified in 
sub-rule (1), the proceedings against the deceased party shall abate:
 
Provided that on good and 
sufficient reasons the Tribunal, on an application, may set aside the order of 
abatement and substitute the legal representatives.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Adjournment of 
hearing.—The 
Tribunal may if sufficient cause is shown at any stage of proceedings grant time 
to the parties or any of them, and adjourn the hearing of the appeal.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Order to be signed 
and dated.—
<section><number>i</number> 
Every order of the Tribunal shall be in writing and shall be signed by the 
Presiding Officer who pronounced the order.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The order shall be 
pronounced in open court.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Communication of 
orders to parties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every final order passed on any appeal shall be communicated to the appellant 
and to the respondent concerned either by hand delivery or by registered post 
free of cost.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the appellant or 
the respondent to any proceeding requires a copy of any document or proceedings 
the same shall be supplied to him on such terms and conditions on payment of 
such fees as may be fixed by the Presiding Officer by general or special order.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Orders and 
directions in certain cases.—The 
Tribunal may make such orders or give such directions as may be necessary or 
expedient to give effect to its orders or to prevent abuse of its process or to 
secure the ends of justice.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Working hours of 
the Tribunal.—Except 
on Saturdays, Sundays and other public holidays, the office of the Tribunal 
shall, subject to any order made by the Presiding Officer remain open from 9.30 
A.M. to 6.00 P.M.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Sitting hours of 
the Tribunal.—The 
sitting hours of the Tribunal shall ordinarily be from 10.30 A.M. to 1.30 P.M. 
and 2.30 P.M. to 5.00 P.M. subject to any general or special order made by the 
Presiding Officer.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Powers and 
functions of the Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall have the custody of the records of the Tribunal and shall 
exercise such other functions as are assigned to him under these rules or by the 
Presiding Officer by separate order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The official seal 
shall be kept in the custody of the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to any general 
or special direction by the Presiding Officer, the seal of the Tribunal shall 
not be affixed to any order, summons or other process save under the authority 
in writing of the Registrar.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The seal of the 
Tribunal shall not be affixed to any certified copy issued by the Tribunal save 
under the authority in writing of the Registrar.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Additional powers 
and duties of Registrar.—In 
addition to the powers conferred elsewhere in other rules, the Registrar shall 
have the following powers and duties subject to any general or special order of 
the Presiding Officer, namely:—
 <section>
   <number>i</number>  to receive all 
appeals and other documents;
 </section><section>
   <number>ii</number>  to decide all 
questions arising out of the scrutiny of the appeals before they are registered;
 </section><section>
  <number>iii</number>  to require any 
appeal presented to the Tribunal to be amended in accordance with the Act and 
the rules;
 </section><section>
  <number>iv</number>  subject to the 
direction of the Tribunal, to fix the date of first hearing of the appeals or 
other proceedings and issue notices thereof;
 </section><section>
  <number>v</number>  to direct any 
formal amendment of records;
 </section><section>
  <number>vi</number>  to order grant of 
copies of documents to parties to the proceedings;
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>  to grant leave to 
inspect the records of the Tribunal;
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>  to dispose of all 
matters relating to the service of notices or other processes for the issue of 
fresh notices and for extending the time for filing such appeals and to grant 
time not exceeding 15 days for filing of reply or rejoinder, if any, and to 
place the matter before the Tribunal for appropriate orders after the expiry of 
the aforesaid period;
 </section><section>
  <number>ix</number>  to requisition 
records from the custody of any court or other authority;
 </section><section>
   <number>x</number>  to receive appeals 
within thirty days from the date of death for substitution of legal 
representatives of the deceased parties during the pendency of the appeals;
 </section><section>
  <number>xi</number>  to receive and 
dispose of appeals for substitution, except where the substitution would involve 
setting aside on order of abatement;
 <subsection>
<number>xii</number>  to receive and 
dispose of application by parties for return of documents.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Seal and emblem.—The 
official seal and emblem of the Tribunal shall be in a round shape bearing the 
name of the Tribunal in capital letters with Ashoka Pillar in the centre.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Dress of the 
presiding officer and staff of the Tribunal.—The 
dress for the Presiding Officer of the Tribunal and members of the staff of the 
Tribunal shall be such as the Presiding Officer may specify.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Dress of the 
parties.—A 
legal practitioner or, as the case may be, a Presiding Officer shall appear 
before the Tribunal in his professional dress, if any; and if there is no such 
dress—
 <section>
   <number>i</number>  if a male, in a 
closed collared coat and trousers or in lounge suit;
 </section><section>
   <number>ii</number>  if a female, in a 
saree or any other customary dress of a sober colour.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Expenses of the 
Tribunals.—The 
entire administrative expenses of the Tribunals shall be borne by the Central 
Board of Trustees, Employees’ Provident Fund 

1[and the fee or 
any other money received by the Tribunal shall form a part of the Administrative 
Fund of the Central Board].
 
 



</article><form>
 




the EMPLOYEES’ PROVIDENT FUNDS APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (PROCEDURE) RULES, 1997
 


 
 


FORM II
 


[See rule 4(4)]
 


RECEIPT SLIP
 


Receipt of the appeal filed 
in the Employees’ Provident Funds Appellate Tribunal by Shri/Kum./Smt./........................................working 
in/for ............................. of ................. ........... residing 
at........................................................is hereby 
acknowledged.
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 


 
 



Date.........................                                                                                                                                         For Registrar
 



Seal...........................                                                                                                                         EPF Appellate Tribunal
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>