<act><title>


The National Highways Act, 1956</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the National Highways Act, 1956.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Declaration of 
certain highways to be national highways.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Each of the highways specified in the Schedule 

1[***] is hereby 
declared to be a national highway.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare any other highway to be a 
national highway and on the publication of such notification such highway shall 
be deemed to be specified in the Schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
may, by like notification, omit any highway from the Schedule and on the 
publication of such notification, the highway so omitted shall cease to be a 
national highway.






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3</number> 
Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  “competent authority” means any person or authority authorised by the 
Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, to perform the 
functions of the competent authority for such area as may be specified in the 
notification;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  “land” includes benefits to arise out of land and things attached to 
the earth or permanently fastened to anything attached to the earth.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3A</number> Power to 
acquire land, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Central Government is satisfied that for a public purpose any land is 
required for the building, maintenance, management or operation of a national 
highway or part thereof, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
declare its intention to acquire such land.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every notification 
under sub-section (1) shall give a brief description of the land.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The competent 
authority shall cause the substance of the notification to be published in two 
local newspapers, one of which will be in a vernacular language.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3B</number> Power to 
enter for survey, etc.—On 
the issue of a notification under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 3A, it shall be 
lawful for any person, authorised by the Central Government in this behalf, to—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  make any inspection, survey, measurement, valuation or enquiry;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  take levels;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  dig or bore into sub-soil;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  set out boundaries and intended lines of work;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  mark such levels, boundaries and lines placing marks and cutting 
trenches; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>f</number>  do such other acts or things as may be laid down by rules made in this 
behalf by that Government.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3C</number> Hearing of 
objections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person interested in the land may, within twenty-one days from the date of 
publication of the notification under sub-section (1) of section 3A, object to 
the use of the land for the purpose or purposes mentioned in that sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every objection under 
sub-section (1) shall be made to the competent authority in writing and shall 
set out the grounds thereof and the competent authority shall give the objector 
an opportunity of being heard, either in person or by a legal practitioner, and 
may, after hearing all such objections and after making such further enquiry, if 
any, as the competent authority thinks necessary, by order, either allow or 
disallow the objections.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this sub-section, “legal practitioner” has the same meaning as 
in clause (i) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 
1961).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any order made by the 
competent authority under sub-section (2) shall be final.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3D</number> 
Declaration of acquisition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where no objection under sub-section (1) of section 3C has been made to the 
competent authority within the period specified therein or where the competent 
authority has disallowed the objection under sub-section (2) of that section, 
the competent authority shall, as soon as may be, submit a report accordingly to 
the Central Government and on receipt of such report, the Central Government 
shall declare, by notification in the Official Gazette, that the land should be 
acquired for the purpose or purposes mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 3A.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the publication of 
the declaration under sub-section (1), the land shall vest absolutely in the 
Central Government free from all encumbrances.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where in respect of 
any land, a notification has been published under sub-section (1) of section 3A 
for its acquisition but no declaration under sub-section (1) has been published 
within a period of one year from the date of publication of that notification, 
the said notification shall cease to have any effect:
 
Provided that in computing 
the said period of one year, the period or periods during which any action or 
proceedings to be taken in pursuance of the notification issued under 
sub-section (1) of section 3A is stayed by an order of a court shall be 
excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A declaration made by 
the Central Government under sub-section (1) shall not be called in question in 
any court or by any other authority.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3E</number> Power to 
take possession.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any land has vested in the Central Government under sub-section (2) of 
section 3D, and the amount determined by the competent authority under section 
3G with respect to such land has been deposited under sub-section (1) of section 
3H, with the competent authority by the Central Government, the competent 
authority may by notice in writing direct the owner as well as any other person 
who may be in possession of such land to surrender or deliver possession thereof 
to the competent authority or any person duly authorised by it in this behalf 
within sixty days of the service of the notice.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any person refuses 
or fails to comply with any direction made under sub-section (1), the competent 
authority shall apply—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  in the case of any land situated in any area falling within the 
metropolitan area, to the Commissioner of Police;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  in case of any land situated in any area other than the area referred 
to in clause (a), to the Collector of a District,
 
and such Commissioner or 
Collector, as the case may be, shall enforce the surrender of the land, to the 
competent authority or to the person duly authorised by it.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3F</number> Right to 
enter into the land where land has vested in the Central Government.—Where 
the land has vested in the Central Government under section 3D, it shall be 
lawful for any person authorised by the Central Government in this behalf, to 
enter and do other act necessary upon the land for carrying out the building, 
maintenance, management or operation of a national highway or a part thereof, or 
any other work connected therewith.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3G</number> 
Determination of amount payable as compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any land is acquired under this Act, there shall be paid an amount which 
shall be determined by an order of the competent authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the right of 
user or any right in the nature of an easement on, any land is acquired under 
this Act, there shall be paid an amount to the owner and any other person whose 
right of enjoyment in that land has been affected in any manner whatsoever by 
reason of such acquisition an amount calculated at ten per cent. of the amount 
determined under sub-section (1), for that land.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Before proceeding to 
determine the amount under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the competent 
authority shall give a public notice published in two local newspapers, one of 
which will be in a vernacular language inviting claims from all persons 
interested in the land to be acquired.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Such notice shall 
state the particulars of the land and shall require all persons interested in 
such land to appear in person or by an agent or by a legal practitioner referred 
to in sub-section (2) of section 3C, before the competent authority, at a time 
and place and to state the nature of their respective interest in such land.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the amount 
determined by the competent authority under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) 
is not acceptable to either of the parties, the amount shall, on an application 
by either of the parties, be determined by the arbitrator to be appointed by the 
Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the provisions of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 
1996 (26 of 1996) shall apply to every arbitration under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The competent 
authority or the arbitrator while determining the amount under sub-section (1) 
or sub-section (5), as the case may be, shall take into consideration—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  the market value of the land on the date of publication of the 
notification under section 3A;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  the damage, if any, sustained by the person interested at the time of 
taking possession of the land, by reason of the severing of such land from other 
land;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  the damage, if any, sustained by the person interested at the time of 
taking possession of the land, by reason of the acquisition injuriously 
affecting his other immovable property in any manner, or his earnings;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  if, in consequences of the acquisition of the land, the person 
interested is compelled to change his residence or place of business, the 
reasonable expenses, if any, incidental to such change.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3H</number> Deposit 
and payment of amount.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The amount determined under section 3G shall be deposited by the Central 
Government in such manner as may be laid down by rules made in this behalf by 
that Government, with the competent authority before taking possession of the 
land.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As soon as may be 
after the amount has been deposited under sub-section (1), the competent 
authority shall on behalf of the Central Government pay the amount to the person 
or persons entitled thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where several persons 
claim to be interested in the amount deposited under sub-section (1), the 
competent authority shall determine the persons who in its opinion are entitled 
to receive the amount payable to each of them.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any dispute arises 
as to the apportionment of the amount or any part thereof or to any person to 
whom the same or any part thereof is payable, the competent authority shall 
refer the dispute to the decision of the principal civil court of original 
jurisdiction within the limits of whose jurisdiction the land is situated.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the amount 
determined under section 3G by the arbitrator is in excess of the amount 
determined by the competent authority, the arbitrator may award interest at nine 
per cent. per annum on such excess amount from the date of taking possession 
under section 3D till the date of the actual deposit thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the amount 
determined by the arbitrator is in excess of the amount determined by the 
competent authority, the excess amount together with interest, if any, awarded 
under sub-section (5) shall be deposited by the Central Government in such 
manner as may be laid down by rules made in this behalf by that Government, with 
the competent authority and the provisions of sub-sections (2) to (4) shall 
apply to such deposit.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3-I</number> Competent 
authority to have certain powers of civil court.—The 
competent authority shall have, for the purposes of this Act, all the powers of 
a civil court while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
1908), in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him 
on oath;
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  requiring the discovery and production of any document;
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  reception of evidence on affidavits;
 </section><section>
        
<number>d</number>  requisitioning any public record from any court or office;
 </section><section>
        
<number>e</number>  issuing commission for examination of witnesses.]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>3J</number> Land Acquisition Act 1 of 
1894 not to apply.—Nothing in the Land Acquisition 
Act, 1894 shall apply to an acquisition under this Act.]





</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> National highways to 
vest in the Union.—All 
national highways shall vest in the Union, and for the purposes of this Act 
“highways” include—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  all lands appurtenant thereto, whether demarcated or not;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  all bridges, culverts, tunnels, causeways, carriageways and other 
structures constructed on or across such highways; and
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  all fences, trees, posts and boundary, furlong and milestones of 
such highways or any land appurtenant to such highways.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Responsibility for 
development and maintenance of national highways.—It 
shall be the responsibility of the Central Government to develop and maintain in 
proper repair all national highways; but the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any function in relation to 
the development or maintenance of any national highway shall, subject to such 
conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, also be exercisable 
by the Government of the State within which the national highway is situated or 
by any officer or authority subordinate to the Central Government or to the 
State Government.


</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power to issue 
directions.—The 
Central Government may give directions to the Government of any State as to the 
carrying out in the State of any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule, 
notification or order made thereunder.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Fees for services or 
benefits rendered on national highways.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, levy fees 
at such rates as may be laid down by rules made in this behalf for services or 
benefits rendered in relation to the use of ferries, 

1[permanent bridges 
the cost of construction of each of which is more than rupees twenty-five lakhs 
and which are opened to traffic on or after the 1st day of April, 1976,] 
temporary bridges and tunnels on national highways 

2[and the use of 
sections of national highways].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such fees when so 
levied shall be collected in accordance with the rules made under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any fee leviable 
immediately before the commencement of this Act for services or benefits 
rendered in relation to the use of ferries, temporary bridges and tunnels on any 
highway specified in the Schedule shall continue to be leviable under this Act 
unless and until it is altered in exercise of the powers conferred by 
sub-section (1):
 

3[Provided that if 
the Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary in the public interest 
so to do, it may, by like notification, specify any bridge in relation to the 
use of which fees shall not be leviable under this sub-section.]








</section></article> 

 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8A</number> Power of 
Central Government to enter into agreements for development and maintenance of 
national highways.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the 
Central Government may enter into an agreement with any person in relation to 
the development and maintenance of the whole or any part of a national highway.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 7, the person referred to in sub-section (1) is 
entitled to collect and retain fees at such rate, for services or benefits 
rendered by him as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify having regard to the expenditure involved in building, 
maintenance, management and operation of the whole or part of such national 
highway, interest on the capital invested, reasonable return, the volume of 
traffic and the period of such agreement.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person referred to 
in sub-section (1) shall have powers to regulate and control the traffic in 
accordance with the provisions contained in Chapter VIII of the Motor Vehicles 
Act, 1988 (59 of 1988) on the national highway forming subject-matter of such 
agreement, for proper management thereof.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8B</number> Punishment 
for mischief by injury to national highway.—Whoever commits mischief by 
doing any act which renders or which he knows to be likely to render any 
national highway referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 8A impassable or less 
safe for travelling or conveying property, shall be punished with imprisonment 
of either description for a term which may extend to five years, or with a fine, 
or with both.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  the manner in which, and the conditions subject to which, any function 
in relation to the development or maintenance of a national highway or any part 
thereof may be exercised by the State Government or any officer or authority 
subordinate to the Central Government or the State Government;
 
      
1[(aa)  the 
manner in which the amount shall be deposited with the competent authority under 
sub-sections (1) and (6) of section 3H;]
 
         
2[(b)  the 
rates at which fees for services rendered in relation to the use of ferries, 
permanent bridges, temporary bridges and tunnels on any national highway 

3[and the use of 
sections of any national highway] may be levied, and the manner in which such 
fees shall be collected, under section 7;]
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  the periodical inspection of national highways and the submission of 
inspection reports to the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  the reports on works carried out on national highways;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  any other matter for which provision should be made under this Act.
 

4[(3) Every rule 
made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, 
the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.]
 
 







</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Laying of 
notifications, rules, etc., before Parliament.—All 
notifications or agreements issued or entered into under this Act shall be laid 
before both Houses of Parliament as soon as may be after they are issued or 
entered into 

1[***].
 
 





</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>