<act><title>THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR ELECTRICITY (SALARIES, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) RULES, 
20041</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Appellate Tribunal for Electricity (Salaries, Allowances and Other 
Conditions of Service of Chairperson and Members) Rules, 2004. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Electricity Act, 2003; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Appellate Tribunal means the Appellate Tribunal for Electricity 
  established under Section 110 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Chairperson means the Chairperson the Appellate Tribunal appointed 
  under section 113 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Member means a Member of the Appellate Tribunal appointed 
  under section 113 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> Words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the 
  Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Salary, allowances, payable to the Chairperson. </title>The 
Chairperson shall be entitled to a monthly salary and to such allowances and 
other benefits, as are admissible to a Judge of the Supreme Court: 
 Provided that in case a person appointed as the Chairperson is in receipt of 
any pension, to pay of such Chairperson shall be reduced by the gross amount of 
pension drawn by him: 
 Provided further that the Chairperson shall be entitled to draw allowances on 
the original basic pay before such fixation of pay. 
  

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Contribution to contributory provident fund. </title>The 
Chairperson shall be entitled to subscribe to the Contributory Provident Fund 
which shall be governed by the Contributory Provident Fund Rules ( India ), 
1962. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Other conditions of service. </title>The other conditions of 
service of Chairperson shall be governed by the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions 
of Service) Act, 1958 and the rules made thereunder. <title></title>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Salary and allowances payable to Member. </title>A Member of the 
Appellate Tribunal shall be entitled to a monthly salary, and such allowances 
and other benefits as are admissible to a serving Judge of the High Court of 
Delhi: <title></title>
 Provided that in case a person appointed as the Member is in receipt of any 
pension, the pay of such Member shall be reduced by the gross amount of pension 
drawn by him: Provided further that the Member shall be entitled to draw 
allowances on the original basic pay before such fixation of pay. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Contribution to contributory provident fund. </title>The Member 
shall be entitled to subscribe to the Contributory Provident Fund which shall be 
governed by the Contributory Provident Fund Rules ( India ), 1962. 
<title></title>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Other conditions of service of Member. </title>The other 
conditions of service of a Member shall be governed by the High Court Judges 
(Salaries and Conditions of Service) Act, 1954, and the rules made thereunder 
for a serving Judge of the High Court of Delhi. <title></title>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Oath of office and secrecy. </title>Every person appointed as 
the Chairperson or a Member shall, before entering upon his office, make and 
subscribe an oath of office and secrecy <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***] in Form 1 and Form II 
respectively annexed to these rules. <title></title>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Declaration of financial or other interest. </title>Every 
person, on his appointment as the Chairperson or Member, as the case may be, 
shall give a declaration in Form III annexed to these rules, to the satisfaction 
of the Central Government, that he does not have any such financial or other 
interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as such Chairperson 
or Member, as the case may be. <title></title>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Residuary provision. </title>Matter relating to the terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson or Member with respect to which no 
express provision has been made in these rules, shall be referred by the 
Appellate Tribunal to the Central Government for its decision. 
<title></title>


</article><form>
 

THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR ELECTRICITY (SALARIES, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) RULES, 
20041
 

FORM I
 

(See rule 9) 
 

FORM OF OATH OF OFFICE FOR THE CHAIRPERSON/MEMBERS OF 
THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR ELECTRICITY 
 

I, .........................................................., having been 
appointed as the Chairperson Member (Cross out portion not applicable) do 
solemnly affirm and do swear in the name of God that I will faithfully and 
conscientiously discharge my duties as the Chairperson/Member (Cross out portion 
not applicable), of the Appellate Tribunal for Electricity, to the best of my 
ability, knowledge and judgment, without fear or favour, affection or ill-will 
and that I will uphold the Constitution and the laws of the land. 
 

Dated............................. 
 

(Name of the Chairperson/Member) 
 

Appellate Tribunal for Electricity 
 

-------
 

1. Vide . G.S.R. 259(E), dated 13th April, 2004, 
published in the Gazette of India Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 13th April, 
2004, No. 184.</form><form>
 

THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR ELECTRICITY (SALARIES, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) RULES, 
20041
 

FORM II 
 

(See rule 9) 
 

FORM OF OATH OF SECRECY FOR THE CHAIRPERSON/MEMBERS OF 
THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR ELECTRICITY 
 

I, .........................................................., having been 
appointed as the Chairperson/Member (Cross out portion not applicable) do 
solemnly affirm and swear in the name of God that I will not directly or 
indirectly communicate or reveal to any person or persons any matter which shall 
be brought under my consideration or shall become known to me as the 
Chairperson/a Member (Cross out portion not applicable of the Appellate Tribunal 
for Electricity except as may be required for the due discharge of my duties as 
the Chairperson/a Member (Cross out portion not applicable). 
 

Dated.............................
 

(Name of the Chairperson/Member) 
 

Appellate Tribunal for Electricity 
 

-------
 

1. Vide . G.S.R. 259(E), dated 13th April, 2004, 
published in the Gazette of India Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 13th April, 
2004, No. 184.</form><form>
 

THE APPELLATE TRIBUNAL FOR ELECTRICITY (SALARIES, 
ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND MEMBERS) RULES, 
20041
 

FORM III 
 

( See rule 10) 
 

DECLARATION AGAINST ACQUISTION OF ANY ADVERSE FINANCIAL 
OR OTHER INTEREST 
 

I, .........................................................., having been 
appointed as the Chairperson/Member (Cross out portion not applicable) of the 
Appellate Tribunal for Electricity, do solemnly affirm and declare that I do not 
have, nor shall have in future any financial or other interest which is likely 
to affect prejudicially my functioning as the Chairperson/Member (Cross out 
portion not applicable) of the Appellate Tribunal for Electricity. 
 

Dated............................. 
 

(Name of the Chairperson/Member) 
 

Appellate Tribunal of Electricity 
 

 
 

-------
 

1. Vide . G.S.R. 259(E), dated 13th April, 2004, 
published in the Gazette of India Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 13th April, 
2004, No. 184.</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 13-4-2004 .</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> The words, before the minister in charge of the Ministry of 
Power omitted by G.S.R. 700(E), dated 29th September, 2008 (w.e.f. 30-9-2008).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>