<act><title>

The 
    powerS-of-attorney act, 1882</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—This Act may be called the 
    Powers-of-Attorney Act, 1882.
 
Local 
    extent.—It 
    applies to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[except the State of Jammu and 
    Kashmir];
 <section>

    <number>Commencement</number>—And it shall come 
    into force on the first day of May, 1882.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> 
    Definition.—In 
    this Act, “Power-of-Attorney” includes any instruments empowering a 
    specified person to act for and in the name of the person executing it.]3[1A. 
    Definition.—In 
    this Act, “Power-of-Attorney” includes any instruments empowering a 
    specified person to act for and in the name of the person executing it.]" 
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Execution under power-of-attorney.—The 
    donee of a power-of-attorney may, if he thinks fit, execute or do any <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] 
    instrument or thing in and with his own name and signature, and his own 
    seal, where sealing is required, by the authority of the donor of the power; 
    and every <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] instrument and thing so executed and done, shall 
    be as effectual in law as if it had been executed or done by the donee of 
    the power in the name, and with the signature and seal, of the donor 
    thereof.
 
This section 
    applies to powers-of-attorney created by instruments executed either before 
    or after this Act comes into force. 
  




















 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Payment by attorney under power, without notice of death, etc., good.—Any 
    person making or doing any payment or act in good faith, in pursuance of a 
    power-of-attorney, shall not be liable in respect of the payment or act by 
    reason that, before the payment or act, the donor of the power had died or 
    become <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] of unsound mind, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] or insolvent, or 
    had revoked the power, if the fact of death <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] unsoundness of 
    mind, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] insolvency or revocation was not, at the time of the 
    payment or act, known to the person making or doing the same.
 
But this 
    section shall not affect any right against the payee of any person 
    interested in any money so paid; and that person shall have the like remedy 
    against the payee as he would have had against the payer, if the payment had 
    not been made by him.
 
This section 
    applies only to payments and acts made or done after this Act comes into 
    force. 
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Deposit of original instruments, creating powers-of-attorney.—
<section><number>a</number> 
    An instrument creating a power-of-attorney, its execution being verified by 
    affidavit, statutory declaration or other sufficient evidence, may, with the 
    affidavit or declaration, if any, be deposited in the High Court <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[or 
    District Court] within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the instrument 
    may be.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A separate 
    file of instruments so deposited shall be kept; and any person may search 
    that file, and inspect every instrument so deposited, and a certified copy 
    thereof shall be delivered out to him on request. 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A copy of 
    an instrument so deposited may be presented at the office and may be stamped 
    or marked as a certified copy, and, when so stamped or marked, shall become 
    and be a certified copy.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A 
    certified copy of an instrument so deposited shall, without further proof, 
    be sufficient evidence of the contents of the instrument and of the deposit 
    thereof in the High Court <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[or District Court].
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> The High 
    Court may, from time to time, make rules for the purposes of this section, 
    and prescribing, with the concurrence of the State Government, the fees to 
    be taken under clauses (a), (b) and (c).
 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***]              
    
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> This 
    section applies to instruments creating powers-of-attorney executed either 
    before or after this Act come into force.
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Power-of-attorney of married women.—<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[A 
    married woman of full age shall, by virtue of this Act, have power, as if 
    she were unmarried,] by a non-testamentary instrument, to appoint an 
    attorney on her behalf, for the purpose of executing any non-testamentary 
    instrument or doing any other act which she might herself execute or do; and 
    the provisions of this Act, relating to instruments creating 
    powers-of-attorney shall apply thereto.
 
This section 
    applies only to instruments executed after this Act come into force.
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number>
Act 28 of 1866, section 39, repealed.—[Repealed by the Amending 
    Act, 1891 (12 of 1891), section 2 and Schedule].
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by the Part B 
    States (Laws) Act, 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “except Part B States”. tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the Part B States (Laws) Act, 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for 
    “except Part B States”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 
    1982, sec. 2. tc " 3. Ins. by Act 55 of 1982, sec. 2."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   The word “assurance” 
    omitted by Act 55 of 1982, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Certain words omitted 
    by Act 55 of 1982, sec. 4.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by Act 55 of 
    1982, sec. 5. tc " 2. Ins. by Act 55 of 1982, sec. 5."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Clause (f) repealed by 
    the Lower Burma Courts Act, 1900, sec. 48 and Sch. II.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 55 of 
    1982, sec. 6, for certain words (w.e.f. 22-10-1982).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>