<act><title>


The Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution)
    Rules, 19821</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Air (Prevention and Control of Pollution) 
    Rules, 1982. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   ‘‘Act’’ means the Air (Prevention and 
    Control of Pollution) Act, 1981;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   ‘‘Chairman’’ means the Chairman of the 
    Central Board;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   ‘‘form’’ means a form set out in the 
    Schedules;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   ‘‘meeting’’ means a meeting of the 
    Central Board or a meeting of Committee constituted by the Central Board;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   ‘‘member-Secretary’’means the 
    member-Secretary of the Central Board;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   ‘‘Schedule’’ means a schedule appended 
    to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   ‘‘Section’’ means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   ‘‘Year’’ means the financial year 
    commencing on the Ist day of April;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   words and expressions not defined in 
    these rules but defined in the Act shall have the meaning assigned to them 
    in the Act.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Notice of meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Meeting of the Central Board shall be held on such dates as may be fixed by 
    the Chairman. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairman shall, upon a written request of not less than five members of the 
    Central Board or upon a direction of the Central Government, call a special 
    meeting of the Central Board. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Fifteen clear days ‘notice of an ordinary meeting and three days’ notice of 
    a special meeting specifying the time, the place at which such meeting is to 
    be held and an agenda of the business to be transacted thereat, shall be 
    given by the member-Secretary or Chairman to the members or any other 
    officers of the Board. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notice of the meeting may be given to the members by delivering the same by 
    messenger or sending it by registered post to his last known place of 
    residence or business or in such other manner as the Chairman may, in the 
    circumstances of the case, think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No 
    member shall be entitled to bring forward for the consideration of a meeting 
    any matter of which he has not given ten clear days’ notice to the 
    member-Secretary unless the Chairman, in his discretion, permits him to do 
    so. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If 
    the Chairman or presiding officer adjourns a meeting from day to day or any 
    particular day he shall give reason thereof and no fresh notice shall be 
    required for such an adjourned meeting. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Presiding Officer.—Every 
    meeting shall be presided over by the Chairman and in his absence, by a 
    presiding officer to be elected by the members present from amongst 
    themselves. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    All questions to be decided by majority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    All questions at a meeting shall be decided by a majority of votes of 
    members present and voting shall be by raising of hands in favour of the 
    proposal. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    case of an equality of votes, the Chairman or presiding officer shall have a 
    second or casting vote. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Quorum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Five members shall form the quorum for any meeting. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    at any time fixed for any meeting or during the course of any meeting a 
    quorum is not present, the Chairman or presiding officer shall adjourn the 
    meeting and if a quorum is not present after the expiration of fifteen 
    minutes from such adjournment, the presiding officer shall adjourn the 
    meeting to such time on the following or on such other future date as he may 
    fix. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the meeting is adjourned to some future date due to lack of quorum, fresh 
    notice will be given to the absentee members as to the date and time on 
    which the next meeting will be held. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    matter which had not been on the agenda of the original meeting shall be 
    discussed at such adjourned meeting. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Minutes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Record of the proceedings of every meeting alongwith the names of members 
    who attended the meeting shall be kept by the member-Secretary in a book 
    maintained by him exclusively for the purpose. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    minutes of the previous meeting shall be read at the beginning of every 
    succeeding meeting and shall be confirmed and signed by the Chairman or 
    presiding officer at such meeting. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    proceedings shall be open to inspection by any member at the office of the 
    Central Board during office hours. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Maintaining order at meetings.—The 
    Chairman or presiding officer shall preserve order at a meeting. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Business to be transacted at a meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No business shall be transacted in the meeting without quorum. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Except with the permission of the Chairman or presiding officer, no business 
    which is not entered in the agenda or of which notice has not been given by 
    a member under sub-rule (5) of the rule 3, shall be transacted at any 
    meeting. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Order of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any meeting business shall be transacted in the order in which it is 
    entered in the agenda circulated to the members under sub-rule (3) of Rule 
    3. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Either at the beginning of the meeting or after the conclusion of the debate 
    on a motion during the meeting, the Chairman or presiding officer or a 
    member may suggest a change in the order of business as entered in the 
    agenda and if the majority of the members present agree, the Chairman or 
    presiding officer shall agree to such a change. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Procedure for transaction of business of committees constituted by the Board 
    under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 11.—(1) 
    The time and place of the meeting of a committee constituted by the Central 
    Board under sub-section (1) of section 11 shall be as specified by the 
    Chairman of the Committee. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Provisions of Chapter 2 of these rules shall, as far as practicable, apply 
    to the meetings of the committees constituted under section 11. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number>
    A member of 
    committee other than a member of the Board shall be paid an allowance of 
    rupees fifty if he is a resident of Delhi and rupees seventy-five (inclusive 
    of daily allowance) and also travelling allowance at such rate as is 
    admissible to a Grade-I Officer of the Central Government in the case of 
    non-resident, for each day of the actual meeting of the committee which he 
    attends:  
 
Provided 
    that in case of a Member of Parliament who is also a Member of the Central 
    Board, the said daily and travelling allowances will be admissible when the 
    Parliament is not in session and on production of a certificate by the 
    member that he has not drawn any such allowance for the same journey and 
    halts from any other Government source. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Manner and purpose of association of persons with the Central Board under 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12.—The 
    Central Board may invite any person whose assistance or advise is considered 
    useful in performing any of its functions, to participate in the 
    deliberations of any of its meetings or the meetings of a committee formed 
    by it. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Fees and allowances to be paid to such temporary association of persons 
    under sub-section (3) of section 12.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the person associated with the Board under rule 13 happens to be a 
    non-official resident in Delhi, he shall be entitled to get an allowance of 
    rupees fifty per day for each day of actual meeting of the Central Board in 
    which he is so associated. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    such person is non-resident of Delhi, he shall be entitled to get an 
    allowance of rupees seventy-five per day (inclusive of daily allowance) for 
    each day of actual meeting of the Central Board when he is so associated and 
    also to travelling allowance at such rates as is admissible to a Grade I 
    Officer of the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything in sub-rules (1) and (2) if such person is a 
    Government servant or any employee in a Government undertaking, he shall be 
    entitled to travelling and daily allowances only at the rates admissible 
    under the relevant rules applicable to him: 
 
Provided 
    that in case of a Member of Parliament who is also a Member of the Central 
    Board, the said daily and travelling allowances will be admissible when the 
    Parliament is not in session and on production of a certificate by the 
    member that he has not drawn any such allowance for the same journey and 
    halts from any other Government source. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Form of budget estimates under section 34.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The form in which and time within which the budget may be prepared and 
    forwarded to the Government shall be as provided in Forms I, II, III and IV 
    of Schedule I. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    estimated receipts and expenditure shall be accompanied by the revised 
    budget estimates for the current year. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    budget shall, as far as may be, based on the account heads specified in 
    Schedule II. 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Form of annual report under section 35.—The 
    annual report in respect of the year last ended giving a true and full 
    account of the activities of the Central Board during the previous financial 
    year shall contain the particulars specified in Schedule III and shall be 
    submitted to the Central Government before 15th of May each year. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Form of annual statement of accounts of the Central Board under section 36.—The 
    annual statement of accounts of the Central Board shall be in Forms V to IX.
   


 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>