<act><tid>1238203</tid>
<title>THE TEXTILES COMMITTEE ACT, <year>1963</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1963</year>
[ 3rd December, <year>1963</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of a Committee for ensuring 
the quality of textiles and textile machinery and for matters 
connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fourteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>930478</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1612388</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Textiles Committee Act, <year>1963</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>527197</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>432569</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>189229</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>395238</tid>
<number>a</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>770901</tid>
<number>b</number>" Committee" means the Committee established under 
section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>51969</tid>
<number>ba</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" fibre" means man- made fibre including regenerated 
cellulose rayon, nylon and the like;]

</section>

<section><tid>1223163</tid>
<number>c</number>" Fund" means the Textiles Fund referred to in section 7;

</section>

<section><tid>1534579</tid>
<number>ca</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" handloom industries" has the meaning assigned to it 
in the Khadi and Other Handloom Industries 
Development (Additional Excise Duty on Cloth) Act, 
 <year>1953</year> (12 of <year>1953</year>.);]

</section>

<section><tid>492580</tid>
<number>d</number>" member" means a member of the Committee and includes 
the Chairman and the Vice- Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>167779</tid>
<number>da</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" powerloom" means a loom which is worked by power as 
defined in clause (g) of section 2 of the 
Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>.), and which is 
used or capable of being used only for weaving 
cloth wholly or partly out of cotton yarn or 
woollen yarn, or fibre, or any kind of mixed yarn;

</section>

<section><tid>144795</tid>
<number>db</number>" powerloom industry" means an industry in which a 
manufacturer of textiles has, at any time during the 
period fixed by
<pagefootnote><pagenum>208</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>). 
2.  22nd August, <year>1964</year>; vide Notification No. S. O. 2913, dated the 
22nd August, <year>1964</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 
3 (ii), p. 741.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the Committee under clause (a) of sub- section (5) of 
section 5A, not more than fifty powerlooms (without any  
  spinning plants) in the factory or factories owned, 
controlled or managed by him.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this Clause, the 
expression" factory" has the meaning assigned to it in 
the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>.);]


</section>

<section><tid>800379</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1987970</tid>
<number>f</number>" textile machinery" means the equipment employed 
directly or indirectly for the processing of textile 
fibre into yarn and for the manufacture of fabric 
therefrom by weaving or knitting and includes equipment 
used either wholly or partly for the finishing, folding 
or packing of textiles;

</section>

<section><tid>1771796</tid>
<number>g</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" textiles" means any fabric or cloth or yarn or 
garment or any other article made wholly or in 
part of--

<subsection><tid>1817993</tid>
<number>i</number>cotton; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>530755</tid>
<number>ii</number>wool; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>521626</tid>
<number>iii</number>silk; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1751620</tid>
<number>iv</number>artificial silk or other fibre,
and includes fibre;]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>441694</tid>
<number>h</number>" Vice- Chairman" means the Vice- Chairman of the 
Committee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>453188</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Construction of references to any law not in force, or any 
functionary not in existence, in the State of Jammu and Kashmir. Any 
reference in this Act to any law which is not in force, or any 
functionary not in existence, in the State of Jammu and Kashmir, 
shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law in force, or to the corresponding functionary in 
existence in that State.]


</article>



<article><tid>1724979</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of Textiles Committee.
<section><tid>752756</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish 
with effect from such date <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as may be specified in the notification, 
a Committee to be known as the Textiles Committee, which shall be a 
body corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with 
power to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract and 
may, by that name, sue or be sued.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>209</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 3, for the former clause. 
2. Ins. by s. 4, ibid. 
3.  22nd August, <year>1964</year>; vide Notification No. S. O. 2914, dated the 
22nd August, <year>1964</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 
3 (ii), p. 741.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1400633</tid>
<number>2</number>The Head Office of the Committee shall be in Bombay.

</section>

<section><tid>1770113</tid>
<number>3</number>The Committee shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>1248580</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1127822</tid>
<number>b</number>a Vice- Chairman who shall be the Textile Commissioner, 
ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>815527</tid>
<number>c</number>a Joint Secretary to the Government of India to be 
appointed by the Central Government, ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1788337</tid>
<number>d</number>such other members as the Central Government may think 
fit to appoint who, in the opinion of that Government, 
have special knowledge or practical experience in 
matters relating to the textile industry and trade and 
the manufacture of textile machinery.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1402557</tid>
<number> 4</number> Functions of the Committee.
<section><tid>1602301</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act, the functions of the Committee shall generally be to ensure 
by such measures, as it thinks fit, standard qualities of textiles 
both for internal marketing and export purposes and the manufacture 
and use of standard type of textile machinery.

</section>

<section><tid>1114215</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub- 
section (1), the Committee may--

<subsection><tid>927229</tid>
<number>a</number>undertake, assist and encourage, scientific, 
technological and economic research in textile industry 
and textile machinery;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>500942</tid>
<number>b</number>promote export of textiles and textile machinery and 
carry on propaganda for that purpose;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1943985</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> establish or adopt or recognise standard 
specifications for--

<subsubsection><tid>1641216</tid>
<number>i</number>textiles, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1420119</tid>
<number>ii</number>packing materials used in the packing of 
textiles or textile machinery,
for the purposes of export and for internal consumption 
and affix suitable marks on such standardised varieties 
of textiles and packing materials;]


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>724965</tid>
<number>d</number>specify the type of quality control or inspection which 
will be applied to textiles or textile machinery;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>903777</tid>
<number>da</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> provide for training in the techniques of quality 
control to be applied to textiles or textile 
machinery;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>988843</tid>
<number>e</number>provide for the inspection and examination of--

<subsubsection><tid>539837</tid>
<number>i</number>textiles;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>368214</tid>
<number>ii</number>textile machinery at any stage of manufacture 
and also while it is in use at mill- heads;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>210</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 5, for the former cl. (c). 
2. Ins. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>346942</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> packing materials used in the packing of 
textiles or textile machinery;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>442629</tid>
<number>f</number>establish laboratories and test houses for the testing 
of textiles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>839697</tid>
<number>g</number>provide for testing textiles and textile machinery in 
laboratories and test houses other than those 
established under clause (f);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>290062</tid>
<number>h</number>collect statistics for any of the above mentioned 
purposes from--

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>781363</tid>
<number>i</number>manufacturers of, and dealers in, textiles;

<subsubsection><tid>23096</tid>
<number>ii</number>manufacturers of textile machinery; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1753907</tid>
<number>iii</number>such other persons as may be prescribed;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>5442</tid>
<number>i</number>advise on all matters relating to the development of 
textile industry and the production of textile 
machinery;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>308869</tid>
<number>j</number>provide for such other matters as may be prescribed.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1019196</tid>
<number>3</number>In the discharge of its functions, the Committee shall be 
bound by such directions as the Central Government may, for reasons to 
be stated in writing, give to it from time to time.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>961815</tid>
<number>5</number>Powers of the Committee. The Committee may exercise all such 
powers as may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of carrying 
out its functions under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1031315</tid>
<number> 5A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Imposition of cess on textiles and textile machinery 
manufactured in India.
<section><tid>1208025</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and collected as a  
cess for the purposes of this Act, a duty of excise on all textiles 
and on all textile machinery manufactured in India at such rate, not 
exceeding one per cent. ad valorem as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, fix:
Provided that no such cess shall be levied on textiles 
manufactured from out of handloom or powerloom industry.


</section>

<section><tid>1555244</tid>
<number>2</number>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be in 
addition to any cess or duty leviable on textiles or textile machinery 
under any other law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>480137</tid>
<number>3</number>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be 
collected by the Committee, in accordance with the rules made in this 
behalf, from every manufacturer of textiles or textile machinery 
 (hereinafter in this section and in sections 5C and 5D referred to as  
  the manufacturer).

</section>

<section><tid>1542093</tid>
<number>4</number>The manufacturer shall pay to the Committee the amount of the 
duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) within one month from the 
date on which he receives a notice of demand therefor, from the 
Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>273872</tid>
<number>5</number>For the purpose of enabling the Committee to assess the 
amount of the duty of excise levied under sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1931974</tid>
<number>a</number>the Committee shall, by notification in the Gazette of 
India, fix the period in respect of which assessments 
shall be made; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>211</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 6, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>350993</tid>
<number>b</number>every manufacturer shall furnish to the Committee a 
return, not later than fifteen days after the expiry of 
the period to which the return relates, specifying the 
total quantity of textiles or textile machinery 
manufactured by him during the said period and such 
other particulars as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1620793</tid>
<number>6</number>If any manufacturer fails to furnish the return referred to 
in sub- section (5) within the time specified therein, or furnishes a 
return which the Committee has reason to believe is incorrect or 
defective, the Committee may assess the amount of the duty of excise 
in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>674094</tid>
<number>7</number>Any manufacturer aggrieved by an assessment made under this 
section may appeal to the Tribunal, constituted under section 5B for 
cancellation or modification of the assessment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1225172</tid>
<number>5B</number>Constitution of Tribunal. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Tribunal consisting 
of one person, who is or has been, or is qualified for appointment as 
a Judge of a High Court and who is not connected with the Committee to 
exercise the powers and discharge the functions conferred or imposed 
on the Tribunal by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>715975</tid>
<number> 5C</number> Hearing of appeals by Tribunal.
<section><tid>529566</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal under sub-  
section (7) of section 5A may be preferred to the Tribunal within one 
month from the date on which the notice of demand regarding the 
assessment is served on the manufacturer:
Provided that the Tribunal may admit an appeal after the 
expiration of the period aforesaid, if it is satisfied that the 
appellant had sufficient cause for not preferring it within that 
period.


</section>

<section><tid>411916</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal referred to in sub- section (1) shall be in the 
prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and 
shall be accompanied with such fees as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1177961</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal shall fix a day and place for the hearing of the 
appeal and shall give notice of the same to the appellant and to the 
Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1288462</tid>
<number>4</number>The Tribunal may, after giving the appellant and the 
Committee an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as 
it thinks fit:
Provided that no order enhancing the assessment shall be made 
unless the appellant has had a reasonable opportunity of showing cause 
against such enhancement.


</section>

<section><tid>393722</tid>
<number>5</number>The Tribunal shall send a copy of any order passed under this 
section to the appellant and to the Committee and such order shall be 
final.

</section>

<section><tid>689377</tid>
<number>6</number>In discharging the functions under this section, the Tribunal 
may, subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, follow such 
procedure as it thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>212</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1411347</tid>
<number>7</number>The Tribunal shall have all the powers of a civil court while 
trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>.), in 
respect of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>340102</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1968827</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of any documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1966284</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>654752</tid>
<number>d</number>requisitioning any public record or copy thereof from 
any court or office;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1933110</tid>
<number>e</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses and 
documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>23647</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>864676</tid>
<number>8</number>The expenses of the Tribunal shall be borne by the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>903350</tid>
<number>5D</number>Recovery of duty of excise. If any manufacturer fails to pay 
the duty of excise levied under section 5A, within the period 
specified in sub- section (4) of that section, or where an appeal has 
been preferred by him against an order of assessment under sub- section 
 (7) of section 5A, within one month from the date of disposal of such 
appeal, the duty payable by him shall be recoverable as an arrear of 
land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>1128675</tid>
<number>5E</number>Power to exempt. If the Central Government is of opinion that 
in the interests of trade or in the public interest it is necessary so 
to do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt such 
variety of textiles or such textiles machinery as may be specified in 
the notification from the whole or any part of the duty of excise 
leviable under section 5A.


</article>



<article><tid>517194</tid>
<number>5F</number>Payment of proceeds of cess to the Committee. The proceeds of 
the duty of excise collected under section 5A, reduced by the cost of 
collection as determined by the Central Government, shall first be 
credited to the Consolidated Fund of India and the Central Government 
may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law, pay to the 
Committee from out of such proceeds, such sums or money as it thinks 
fit for being utilised for the purposes of this Act.]


</article>



<article><tid>1758956</tid>
<number>6</number>Grants by Central Government to the Committee. For the purpose 
of enabling the Committee to discharge its functions under this Act, 
the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament 
by law in this behalf, pay to the Committee in each financial year 
such sums of money as that Government considers necessary by way of 
grant, loan or otherwise.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>213</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1702438</tid>
<number> 7</number> Constitution of Fund.
<section><tid>161817</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee shall have a Fund to  
be called the Textiles Fund and there shall be credited thereto--

<subsection><tid>277313</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys transferred to it under clause (a) of sub- 
section (2) of section 24;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>292816</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the proceeds of the duty of excise made over to the 
Committee by the Central Government under section 
5F;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1856550</tid>
<number>b</number>all moneys paid by the Central Government under section 
6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>984285</tid>
<number>c</number>all fees and other charges levied under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>620852</tid>
<number>d</number>all moneys received by the Committee by way of grant, 
gift, donation, contribution, transfer or otherwise.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1592282</tid>
<number>2</number>The moneys in the Fund shall be applied for--

<subsection><tid>1138931</tid>
<number>a</number>meeting the pay and allowances of the officers and other 
employees of the Committee and other administrative 
expenses of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>958288</tid>
<number>b</number>carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>671873</tid>
<number>3</number>All moneys in the Fund shall be deposited in the State Bank 
of India or be invested in such securities as may be approved by the 
Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>46070</tid>
<number> 8</number> Standing or ad hoc Committees.
<section><tid>455623</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee may  
constitute Standing Committees or ad hoc Committees for exercising any 
power or discharging any duty of the Committee or for inquiring into 
or reporting and advising on any matter which the Committee may refer 
to them.

</section>

<section><tid>1413315</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> A Standing Committee or an ad hoc Committee constituted 
under sub- section (1) may include persons who are not members of the 
Committee, but their number shall not exceed one- half of its 
strength.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1627309</tid>
<number> 9</number> Officers and other employees of the Committee.
<section><tid>1966317</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, in consultation with the Committee, appoint a person 
to be the Secretary of the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>1493556</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central 
Government in this behalf, the Committee may appoint such other 
officers and employees as it considers necessary for the efficient 
performance of its functions.

</section>

<section><tid>2847</tid>
<number>3</number>The methods of appointment, the conditions of service and the 
scales of pay of the officers and other employees of the Committee 
shall,--

<subsection><tid>1943302</tid>
<number>a</number>as respects the Secretary, be such as may be prescribed; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1367217</tid>
<number>b</number>as respect the other officers and employees, be such as 
may be determined by regulations made by the Committee 
under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>214</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 7. 
2. Subs. by s. 8, ibid., for the former sub- sections (2) and (3) 
 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1693236</tid>
<number>10</number>Transfer of service of existing employees to the Committee. 
Subject to the provisions of this Act, every person employed by the 
Cotton Textiles Fund Committee constituted under section 5 of the 
Cotton Textiles Fund Ordinance, <year>1944</year>, (34 of <year>1944</year>.) immediately before 
the date of establishment of the Committee shall, on and from such 
date, become an employee of the Committee with such designation as the 
Committee may determine and shall hold his office or service therein 
by the same tenure, at the same remuneration and upon the same terms 
and conditions as he would have held on such date if the Committee had 
not been established and shall continue to do so unless and until his 
employment in the Committee is terminated or until such tenure, 
remuneration and terms and conditions are duly altered by the 
Committee:
Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions 
of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage 
without the previous approval of the Central Government.



</article>



<article><tid>1154242</tid>
<number> 11</number> Inspection.
<section><tid>1879195</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee may, on application made to it  
or otherwise, direct an officer specially authorised in that behalf to 
examine the quality of textiles or the suitability of textile 
machinery for use at the time of manufacture or while in use in a 
textile mill and submit a report to the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>574160</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to any rules made under this Act, such an officer 
shall have power to--

<subsection><tid>1366596</tid>
<number>a</number>inspect any operation carried on in connection with the 
manufacture of textiles or textile machinery in 
relation to which construction particulars, marks or 
inspection standards have been specified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>748092</tid>
<number>b</number>take samples of any article or of any material or 
substance used in any article or process in relation to 
which construction particulars, marks or inspection 
standards have been specified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1547040</tid>
<number>c</number>exercise such other powers as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1838313</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of the report referred to in sub- section (1), the 
Committee may tender such advice, as it may deem fit, to the 
manufacturer of textiles, the manufacturer of textile machinery and 
the applicant.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>999493</tid>
<number> 12</number> Levy of fees for inspection and examination.
<section><tid>1826935</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Committee may levy such fees as may be prescribed--

<subsection><tid>1123315</tid>
<number>a</number>for inspection and examination of textiles;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>215</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (b) omitted by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>98720</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] for any <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> special] service which the Committee may 
render to the manufacturers <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or exporters] of 
textiles and textile machinery:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that no fees shall be levied in respect of inspection 
and examination of textiles on which a duty of excise is leviable 
under this Act:]

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided further that] the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, exempt from the payment of fees, 
generally or in any particular case.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1238096</tid>
<number>2</number>Any sum payable to the Committee under sub- section (1) may be 
recovered as an arrear of land revenue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1156697</tid>
<number> 13</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>940091</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts, including the balance- sheet, in accordance with such general 
directions as may be issued, and in such form as may be prescribed, by 
the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>770785</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Committee shall be audited annually by 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure 
incurred by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
Committee to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1532473</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Committee shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Committee.

</section>

<section><tid>649968</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Committee as certified by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in 
this behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1206659</tid>
<number>14</number>Delegation of powers and duties. The Committee may, by 
general or special order in writing, direct that all or any of the 
powers or duties which may be exercised or discharged by it shall, in 
such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be 
specified in its order, be exercised or discharged also by any officer 
or employee of the Committee specified in this behalf in the order.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>216</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (c) re- lettered as cl. (b) thereof by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 9. 
2. Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for" other". 
3. Ins. by s. 9, ibid. 
4. Subs. by s. 9, ibid., for" Provided that".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>225464</tid>
<number> 15</number> Acts or proceedings of Committee not to be invalidated. No 
act or proceeding of the Committee shall be invalidated merely by 
reason of--
<section><tid>445585</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, 
the Committee; or

</section>

<section><tid>1976768</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a 
member of the Committee; or

</section>

<section><tid>1493498</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Committee not 
affecting the merits of the case.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1995054</tid>
<number>16</number>Officers and employees of the Committee to be public 
servants. All officers and employees of the Committee shall, while 
acting or purporting to act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act 
or of any rule or regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be public 
servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. 
 (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>1075373</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to prohibit exports and internal marketing of textiles 
and textile machinery.
<section><tid>702876</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Committee has established,  
adopted or recognised standard specifications for textiles either for 
internal consumption or for the purposes of export or has established, 
adopted or recognised standard type of textile machinery and on the 
recommendation made to it in this behalf, the Central Government is of 
opinion that any textiles or textile machinery which do not conform to 
the standards laid by the Committee in respect thereof, should not be 
exported or sold for internal consumption, the Central Government may, 
by order published in the Official Gazette, prohibit such export or 
sale.

</section>

<section><tid>533463</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person contravenes any order issued under sub- section 
 (1) prohibiting--

<subsection><tid>672706</tid>
<number>a</number>the export of any textiles or textile machinery, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>427511</tid>
<number>b</number>the sale of any textiles or textile machinery for 
internal consumption,
he shall, on conviction, be punishable,--


<subsubsection><tid>1751451</tid>
<number>i</number>for the first offence with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to one year or with fine or with both;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1168818</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the second or a subsequent offence with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year 
and also with fine and in the absence of special and 
adequate reasons to be mentioned in the judgment of the 
court, such imprisonment shall not be less than three 
months.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>520853</tid>
<number>3</number>Any court trying the contravention of an order prohibiting 
the marketing of textile or textile machinery under sub- section (1) 
may, without prejudice to the provisions of clause (b) of sub- section 
 (2), direct that the textiles or textile machinery in respect of which 
the court is satisfied that such contravention has been committed, 
shall be forfeited to the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>216A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702623</tid>
<number> 18</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>4369</tid>
<number>1</number>If the person committing any  
offence under this Act is a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to such punishment provided in this Act if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1983924</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any negligence on the part of, 
any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section--


<subsection><tid>1081172</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means a body corporate and includes a firm or 
other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1446266</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1963424</tid>
<number>19</number>Procedure for prosecution. No prosecution for any offence 
punishable under this Act shall be instituted except by or with the 
consent of the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>689917</tid>
<number>20</number>Jurisdiction of courts. No court inferior to that of a 
Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class, shall try 
any offence punishable under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1817871</tid>
<number>21</number>Protection of action taken under the Act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Committee 
or any member, officer or employee of the Committee for anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act 
or of any rule or regulation made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1919151</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>322659</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, subject  
to the condition of previous publication, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>217267</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>866311</tid>
<number>a</number>the number of members and the composition of the 
Committee and the manner in which the members shall be 
chosen;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>157410</tid>
<number>b</number>the term of office of and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among the members of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1976941</tid>
<number>c</number>the allowances, if any, payable to the members of the 
Committee;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>216B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>772791</tid>
<number>d</number>the disqualification for membership of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>151344</tid>
<number>da</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manner in which the duty of excise leviable 
under section 5A may be assessed, paid or 
collected, and the manner in which any refund of 
such duty paid or collected in excess of the 
amount due may be made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>931421</tid>
<number>db</number>the conditions of service of the person constituting 
the Tribunal under section 5B;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>418537</tid>
<number>dc</number>the form and the manner in which an appeal to the 
Tribunal constituted under section 5B may be preferred 
and verified, the fees payable on such appeals and the 
procedure to be followed by the Tribunal in disposing 
of such appeals;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1935454</tid>
<number>e</number>the scale of fees that may be levied <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> under section 
12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1316216</tid>
<number>f</number>the form in which the Committee shall prepare its annual 
statement of accounts and balance- sheet;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1777746</tid>
<number>g</number>the method of appointment, the conditions of service and 
the scale of pay of the Secretary of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1868975</tid>
<number>h</number>the collection of any information or statistics in 
respect of textile industry and trade and the 
manufacture of textile machinery;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520031</tid>
<number>i</number>the mode of inspection by the Committee and the manner 
in which samples may be taken by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>472201</tid>
<number>j</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1161645</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall, 
thereafter, have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>188714</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>1710818</tid>
<number>1</number>The Committee may, with the  
previous sanction of the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make regulations, not inconsistent with this Act and 
the rules made thereunder to provide for all matters for which 
provision is necessary or expedient for the purpose of giving effect 
to the provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>216C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 51 of <year>1973</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>). 
2. The words" for inspection and examination" omitted by s. 10, 
ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1975</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 10, ibid., for the former sub- section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1780223</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1125138</tid>
<number>a</number>the meeting of the Committee, Standing Committees and ad 
hoc Committees, the quorum for such meetings and the 
conduct of business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1532402</tid>
<number>b</number>the allowances payable to the members of the Standing 
Committees or the ad hoc Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>144663</tid>
<number>c</number>the methods of appointment, the conditions of service 
and the scales of pay of the officers (other than the  
  Secretary) and other employees of the Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1898524</tid>
<number>d</number>the duties and conduct of officers and other employees 
of the Committee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1810724</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter in respect of which the Committee is 
empowered or required to make regulations under this 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1273892</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, amend, vary or rescind any regulation which it has 
sanctioned; and thereupon the regulation shall have effect 
accordingly, but without prejudice to the exercise of the powers of 
the Committee under sub- section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>578428</tid>
<number> 24</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>679333</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect from the date on which the  
Committee is established under section 3, the Cotton Textiles Fund 
Ordinance, <year>1944</year> (34 of <year>1944</year>.) shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1189557</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the said Ordinance,--

<subsection><tid>1248271</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys at the credit of the Cotton Textiles Fund 
established under the repealed Ordinance immediately 
before the said date shall with effect from the said 
date stand transferred to and form part of the Textiles 
Fund referred to in section 7:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>117766</tid>
<number>b</number>any rules made or deemed to have been made or anything 
done or any action taken in exercise of any of the 
powers conferred by or under the said Ordinance shall 
be deemed to have been made, done or taken in exercise 
of the powers conferred by or under this Act, as if 
this Act were in force on the day on which such rules 
were made, such thing was done or such action was 
taken.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>