<act><tid>1245858</tid>
<title>THE STATE- ASSOCIATED BANKS (MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1962</year></title>

ACT NO. 56 OF <year>1962</year>
[ 14th December, <year>1962</year>]

An Act further to amend the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year>, the State 
Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year>, and the Bankers' books 
Evidence Act, <year>1891</year>, and to provide for the winding up of certain minor 
State- associated banks and for matters connected therewith.





<article><tid>444530</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1092117</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
State- Associated Banks (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, <year>1962</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>939116</tid>
<number>2</number>Section 3, except clauses (ii), (iv) and (vii) thereof, shall 
come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and the rest of this 
Act shall come into force at once.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>384450</tid>
<number>2</number>[ Amendment of the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of  
  <year>1955</year>).]-- Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1974</year> (56 of <year>1974</year>), s. 
 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>610491</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Amendment of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 
 <year>1959</year> (38 of <year>1959</year>)]-- Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1974</year> (56  
  of <year>1974</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>1128276</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Amendment of the Bankers' Books Evidence Act, <year>1891</year> (18 of  
  <year>1891</year>).]-- Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1974</year> (56 of <year>1974</year>), s. 
 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>1915192</tid>
<number> 5</number> Provisions in respect of the State Bank Dholpur.
<section><tid>623985</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law or 
in any order or other instrument--

<subsection><tid>1914185</tid>
<number>a</number>the Central Government may by order appoint one or more 
officers to take over the management of the Dholpur 
bank or to wind up its affairs and distribute its 
assets
<pagefootnote><pagenum>222</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st January, <year>1963</year>, vide Notification No. G. S. R. 1781, dated 18- 
12- <year>1962</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1962</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i) p. 2141.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and any expenditure incurred in connection with such 
appointment, management, winding up or distribution 
shall be payable by that bank;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1946061</tid>
<number>b</number>the principal civil court of original jurisdiction in 
the district in which the Dholpur bank' s head office is 
situated shall have exclusive jurisdiction to entertain 
and decide any claim made by or against the Dholpur 
bank or any question whatever, whether of law or of 
fact, which may relate to or arise in the course of the 
winding up of that bank, whether such claim or question 
has accrued or arisen before or accrues or arises after 
the date of the widing up order, and any suit or other 
legal proceeding, whether of a civil or criminal 
nature, relating to any such claim or question and 
pending in any other court at the commencement of this 
Act shall not be proceeded with except in accordance 
with this section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1525260</tid>
<number>c</number>in regard to the admissibility of the entries in the 
books of account as evidence in the course of the 
proceedings for the winding up of the bank, the 
settlement of the list of debtors of the bank, the 
passing of orders for the payment of the amounts due by 
the said debtors, the execution of the said orders or 
any other orders or decrees of the court, the priority 
of the claims on the bank, the making of preferential 
payments and the discharge of the other liabilities of 
the bank and any other incidental or connected matters, 
the law relating to the winding up of banking 
companies, as in force for the time being shall apply 
as if the Dholpur bank were a banking company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1157747</tid>
<number>d</number>the period of limitation for any suit or application 
relating to any payment due to the Dholpur bank which 
has accrued before or may accrue on or after the date 
of the first appointment of the officer aforesaid, 
whichever may of the bank shall be twelve years from 
the date of the accrual of the claim or five years from 
the date of such first appointment of the officer 
aforesaid, whichever may end later; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507798</tid>
<number>e</number>after the repayment of all the deposit liabilities and 
any other amounts due to be paid by the bank including 
the amounts due to the Government of Rajasthan, the 
remaining assets, if any, of the bank shall be 
utilised, as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>223</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

far as may be, for the purposes and objects specified 
in the State Bank, Dholpur Act, <year>1915</year>, and other 
relevant documents.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1584677</tid>
<number>2</number>In this section," Dholpur bank" means the bank known as the 
Dholpur State Bank and governed at the commencement of this section by 
the State Bank, Dholpur Act, <year>1915</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>630252</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Amendment of the State Bank of Kurundwad (Junior) Act, 
<year>1933</year>.]-- Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1974</year> (56 of <year>1974</year>), s. 
 2 and Sch. I.

</article>



 </act>