<act><tid>1252554</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN INDEPENDENCE PAKISTAN COURTS (PENDING PROCEEDINGS) 
ACT, <year>1952</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>1952</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 23rd February, <year>1952</year>.]

An Act to render ineffective certain decrees and orders passed by 
Courts in Pakistan against a Government in India and to provide an 
alternative remedy to persons who have secured such decrees or orders.

[ 23rd February, <year>1952</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>1338486</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Indian Independence 
Pakistan Courts (Pending Proceedings) Act, <year>1952</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>437643</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act, the expression" decree to which this 
Act applies" means any such judgment, decree or order as is referred 
to in-
<section><tid>419062</tid>
<number>i</number>clause (3) of article 4 of the Indian Independence 
 (Legal Proceedings) Order, <year>1947</year>, or

</section>

<section><tid>1884556</tid>
<number>ii</number>paragraph (5) or paragraph (6) of article 13 of the 
High Courts (Bengal) Order, <year>1947</year>, or

</section>

<section><tid>394494</tid>
<number>iii</number>paragraph (4) or paragraph (6) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> of article 13] of 
the High Courts (Punjab) Order, <year>1947</year>,
which has been or may hereafter be passed by a Court in Pakistan and 
which imposes any liability or obligation on a Government in India.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1976911</tid>
<number>3</number>Certain Pakistan decrees not to be given effect to in India. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any of the Orders referred to in 
section 2, no decree to which this Act applies shall be given effect 
to by any Court or authority in India in so far as such decree imposes 
any liability or obligation on any Government in India.


</article>



<article><tid>974600</tid>
<number>4</number>Right of holder of a decree to which this Act applies to 
institute fresh proceedings in India. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 3 of the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9 of <year>1908</year>), 
any person in whose favour a decree to which this Act applies has been 
passed may, within one year from the commencement of this Act, or 
within one year from the date of the decree, whichever is later, 
institute a fresh suit or other legal proceeding in respect of the 
cause of action on which such decree was based, and any such suit or 
other legal proceeding may,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>568</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to and brought into force in Dadar and 
Nagar Haveli (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
I. 
2 Ins. by Act 48 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


notwithstanding anything contained in section 20 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>.), or in any other law or in any agreement 
to the contrary relating to the place of suing, be instituted in any 
Court otherwise competent to try it, within the local limits of whose 
jurisdiction the person instituting it voluntarily resides or carries 
on business or personally works for gain.



</article>



<article><tid>1958807</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Repeal of Ordinance 6 of <year>1951</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1957</year> (36 of <year>1957</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.

</article>



 </act>