<act><title>


THE DRUGS AND MAGIC REMEDIES (OBJECTIONABLE 
    ADVERTISEMENTS) RULES, 19551</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Drugs and Magic Remedies (Objectionable 
    Advertisements) Rules, 1955. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint. 
 

 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>

    <number>1</number>   the “Act” means the Drugs and Magic Remedies Objectionable 
    Advertisements) Act, 1954 (21 of 1954); and 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number>   “section” means a section of the Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[3]. 
    Scrutiny of misleading advertisements relating to drugs.—2[Any 
    person authorised by the State Government in this behalf may, if satisfied, 
    that an advertisement relating to a drug contravenes the provisions of 
    section 4], by order, require the manufacturer, packer, distributor or 
    seller of the drug to furnish, within such time as may be specified in the 
    order or such further time as may be allowed in this behalf by the person so 
    authorised information regarding the composition of the drug or the 
    ingredients thereof or any other information in regard to that drug as he 
    deems necessary for holding the scrutiny of the advertisement and where any 
    such order is made, it shall be the duty of the manufacturer, packer, 
    distributor or seller of the drug to which the advertisement relates to 
    comply with the order. Any failure to comply with such order shall, for the 
    purposes of section 7, be deemed to be a contravention of the provisions of 
    section 4: 
 

    Provided that no publisher or advertising agency of any medium for the 
    dissemination of any advertisement relating to a drug shall be deemed to 
    have made any contravention merely by reason of the dissemination by him or 
    if any such advertisement, unless such publisher or advertising agency has 
    failed to comply with any discretion made by the authorised person in this 
    behalf calling upon him or it to furnish the name and address of the 
    manufacturer, packer, distributor, seller or advertising agency, as the case 
    may be, who or which caused such advertisement to be disseminated. 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[4]. 
    Procedure to be followed in prohibiting import into, and export from India 
    of certain advertisements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Customs Collector has reasons to believe that any consignment 
    contains documents of the nature referred to in section 6, he may and if 
    requested by an officer appointed for the purpose by the Central Government, 
    shall detain the consignment and dispose it of in accordance with the 
    provisions of the Sea Customs Act, 1878 (VIII of 1878), and the rules made 
    there­under, and shall also inform the importer or exporter of the order so 
    passed: 
 

    Provided that if the importer or exporter feels aggrieve by an order passed 
    by the Customs Collector under this sub‑rule and makes a representation to 
    him within one week of the date of the order and has given an undertaking in 
    writing not to dispose of the consignment without the consent of the Customs 
    Collector and to return the consignment when so required to do by the 
    Customs Collector, the Customs Collector shall pass an order making over the 
    consignment to the importer or exporter, as the case may be: 
 

    Provided further that before passing any order under this sub‑rule or under 
    the first proviso thereto, the Customs Collector shall consult the officer 
    appointed for the purpose by Central Government. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> If the importer or exporter who has given an undertaking under the first 
    proviso to sub‑rule (1) is required by the Customs Collector to return the 
    consignment or any portion thereof, he shall return the consignment or 
    portion thereof within ten days of the receipt of the notice.
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[5].
    

    2[Manner 
    in which advertisements may be sent confidentially.—All 
    documents containing advertisements relating to drugs referred to in clause 
    (c) of sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 14, shall be sent by post to a registered 
    medical practitioner by name or to a wholesale or retail chemist, the 
    address of such registered medical practitioner or wholesale or retail 
    chemist being given. Such document shall bear at the top, printed in 
    indelible ink in a conspicuous manner, the words. “For the use only of 
    registered medical practitioners or a hospital or a laboratory”].
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    1[2[6]. 
    Prohibition of advertisement of drugs for treatment of disease, etc.—No 
    person shall also take part in the publication of any advertisement 
    referring to any drug in terms which suggest or are calculated to lead to 
    the use of that drug for the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment or 
    prevention of any disease, disorder, or condition specified in the Schedule 
    annexed to these rules.
 







 



</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




THE DRUGS AND MAGIC REMEDIES (OBJECTIONABLE 
    ADVERTISEMENTS) RULES, 1955
 

 
 

 
 



    1[Schedule
 



    (See rule 6)
 



    1. Asthma
 



    2. AIDS]]
 




 



    ------------------
 


        
    1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 447 (E), dated 25th June, 2002 (w.e.f. 
    25-6-2002).
 



    ------------------
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Vide S.O. 512, dated 26th February, 1955.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Rule 3 omitted and rules 4 to 7 re-numbered as rules 3 to 6 by 
    S.O. 1688, dated 22nd May, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Rule 3 omitted and rules 4 to 7 re-numbered as rules 3 to 6 by 
    S.O. 1688, dated 22nd May, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Rule 3 omitted and rules 4 to 7 re-numbered as rules 3 to 6 by S.O. 
    1688, dated 22nd May, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Rule 3 omitted and rules 4 to 7 re-numbered as rules 3 to 6 by S.O. 
    1688, dated 22nd May, 1962.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>