<act><tid>1267294</tid>
<title>THE RAILWAYS (SECOND AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 51 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 23rd December, <year>2003</year>]

An Act further to amend the Railways Act, <year>1989</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1206312</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1450909</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Railways (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1327835</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>848592</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Railways Act, <year>1989</year> (24  
  of <year>1989</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act),-
<section><tid>345914</tid>
<number>a</number>after clause (26), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (26A)" officer authorised" means an officer authorised by the Central 
Government under sub- section (2) of section 179;';


</section>

<section><tid>1517432</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (34), after the words" service of a railway", the 
following shall be inserted, namely:-
" including member of the Railway Protection Force appointed under 
clause (c) of sub- section (1) of section 2 of the Railway Protection 
Force Act, <year>1957</year> (23 of <year>1957</year>)".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>187838</tid>
<number> 3</number> Substitution of new section for section 179.- For section 179 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
Arrest for offences under certain sections.

" 179. Arrest for offences under certain sections.- (1) If any person 
commits any offence mentioned in sections 150 to 152, he may be 
arrested without warrant or other written authority by any railway 
servant or police officer not below the rank of a head constable.

<section><tid>385302</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person commits any offence mentioned in sections 137 to 139, 
 141 to 147, 153 to 157, 159 to 167 and 172 to 176, he may be arrested, 
without warrant or other written authority, by the officer authorised 
by a notified order of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>122669</tid>
<number>3</number>The railway servant or the police officer or the officer 
authorised, as the case may be, may call to his aid any other person to 
effect the arrest under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), as the case 
may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1768073</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person so arrested under this section shall be produced before 
the nearest Magistrate within a period of twenty- four hours of such 
arrest excluding the time necessary for the journey from the place of 
arrest to the court of the Magistrate.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1614734</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 180.- In section 180 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1772966</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1923093</tid>
<number>i</number>for the word and figures" section 179", the words, brackets and 
figures" sub- section (2) of section 179" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>63386</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" any railway servant authorised in this behalf or 
any police officer not below the rank of a head constable", the words 
" the officer authorised" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1012735</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" The railway servant or the 
police officer", the words" The officer authorised" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>978279</tid>
<number>5</number>Insertion of new sections 180A to 180G.- After section 180 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
Inquiry by officer authorised to ascertain commission of offence.

" 180A. Inquiry by officer authorised to ascertain commission of 
offence.- For ascertaining facts and circumstances of a case, the 
officer authorised may make an inquiry into the commission of an 
offence mentioned in sub- section (2) of section 179 and may file a 
complaint in the competent court if the offence is found to have been 
committed.

Powers of officer authorised to inquire.

</article>



<article><tid>211186</tid>
<number> 180B</number> Powers of officer authorised to inquire.- While making an inquiry, 
the officer authorised shall have power to,-
<section><tid>1688750</tid>
<number>i</number>summon and enforce the attendance of any person and record his 
statement;

</section>

<section><tid>679861</tid>
<number>ii</number>require the discovery and production of any document;

</section>

<section><tid>60663</tid>
<number>iii</number>requisition any public record or copy thereof from any office, 
authority or person;

</section>

<section><tid>1096198</tid>
<number>iv</number>enter and search any premises or person and seize any property or 
document which may be relevant to the subject- matter of the inquiry.
Disposal of persons arrested.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1063349</tid>
<number>180C</number>Disposal of persons arrested.- Every person arrested for an 
offence punishable under sub- section (2) of section 179 shall, if the 
arrest was made by a person other than the officer authorised, be 
forwarded, without delay, to such officer.
Inquiry how to be made against arrested person.

</article>



<article><tid>881987</tid>
<number> 180D</number> Inquiry how to be made against arrested person.-
<section><tid>373451</tid>
<number>1</number>When any  
person is arrested by the officer authorised for an offence punishable 
under this Act, such officer shall proceed to inquire into the charge 
against such person.

</section>

<section><tid>431484</tid>
<number>2</number>For this purpose, the officer authorised may exercise the same 
powers and shall be subject to the same provisions as the officer in 
charge of a police station may exercise and is subject to the 
provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), when 
investigating a cognizable case:
Provided that-


<subsection><tid>409805</tid>
<number>a</number>if the officer authorised is of the opinion that there is 
sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion against the 
accused person, he shall either admit him to bail to appear before a 
Magistrate having jurisdiction in the case, or forward him in custody 
to such Magistrate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>43142</tid>
<number>b</number>if it appears to the officer authorised that there is not 
sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion against the 
accused person, he shall release the accused person on his executing a 
bond, with or without sureties as the officer authorised may direct, to 
appear, if and when so required, before the Magistrate having 
jurisdiction.
Search, seizure and arrest how to be made.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>572734</tid>
<number>180E</number>Search, seizure and arrest how to be made.- All searches, seizures 
and arrests made under this Act shall be carried out in accordance with 
the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), 
relating respectively to searches and arrests made under that Code.
Cognizance by Court on a complaint made by officer authorised.

</article>



<article><tid>1232837</tid>
<number>180F</number>Cognizance by Court on a complaint made by officer authorised.- No 
court shall take cognizance of an offence mentioned in sub- section (2) 
of section 179 except on a complaint made by the officer authorised.
Punishment for certain offences in relation to inquiry.

</article>



<article><tid>51544</tid>
<number>180G</number>Punishment for certain offences in relation to inquiry.- Whoever 
intentionally insults or causes any interruption in the inquiry 
proceedings or deliberately makes a false statement before the 
inquiring officer shall be punished with simple imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees, or with both.".
T. K. VISHWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.




</article>



 </act>