<act><title>


    THE EMBLEMS AND NAMES (PREVENTION OF </title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, 
    extent, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Emblems and Names (Prevention of Improper Use) 
    Act, 1950. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
    whole of India 

    1[***] and also 
    applies to citizens of India outside India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
    force on such date2 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint. 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “emblem” means 
    any emblem, seal, flag, insignia, coat-of-arms or pictorial representation 
    specified in the Schedule; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “competent 
    authority” means any authority competent under any law for the time being in 
    force to register any company, firm or other body of persons or any trade 
    mark or design or to grant a patent; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “name” includes 
    any abbreviation of a name. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Prohibition of 
    improper use of certain emblems and names.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any law for the time being in force, no person shall, 
    except in such cases and under such conditions as may be prescribed by the 
    Central Government, use, or continue to use, for the purpose of any trade, 
    business, calling or profession or in the title of any patent, or in any 
    trade mark or design, any name or emblem specified in the Schedule or any 
    colourable imitation thereof without the previous permission of the Central 
    Government or of such officer of Government as may be authorised in this 
    behalf by the Central Government. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Prohibition of 
    registration of certain companies, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in force, 
    no competent authority shall,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   register any 
    company, firm or other body of persons which bears any name, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   register a trade 
    mark or design which bears any emblem or name, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   grant a patent 
    in respect of an invention which bears a title containing any emblem or 
    name, 
 
if the use of such 
    name or emblem is in contravention of section 3. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any question 
    arises before a competent authority whether any emblem is an emblem 
    specified in the Schedule or a colourable imitation thereof, the competent 
    authority may refer the question to the Central Government, and the decision 
    of the Central Government thereon shall be final. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Penalty.—Any 
    person who contravenes the provisions of section 3 shall be punishable with 
    fine which may extend to five hundred rupees. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Previous 
    sanction for prosecution.—No 
    prosecution for any offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted, 
    except with the previous sanction of the Central Government or of any 
    officer authorised in this behalf by general or special order of the Central 
    Government. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Savings.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall exempt any person from any suit or other proceeding which 
    might, apart from this Act, be brought against him. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power of the 
    Central Government to amend the Schedule.—The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, add to or 
    alter the Schedule, and any such addition or alteration shall have effect as 
    if it had been made by this Act. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 


    IMPROPER USE) ACT, 1950
  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to make 
    rules.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules to carry out the purposes of this Act. 
 

    2[(2) Every 
    rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
    before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period 
    of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.]
 
 




 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>