<act><tid>1269443</tid>
<title>THE SUPREME COURT JUDGES (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) ACT, <year>1958</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1958</year>
[ 17th October, <year>1958</year>.]

An Act to regulate certain conditions of service of the Judges of 
the Supreme Court.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Ninth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1096434</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Supreme Court Judges 
 (Conditions of Service) Act, <year>1958</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1037497</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act. unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1441</tid>
<number>a</number>" acting Chief Justice" means a Judge appointed 
under article 126 of the Constitution to perform the 
duties of the Chief Justice of India;

</section>

<section><tid>1945940</tid>
<number>b</number>" actual service" includes-

<subsection><tid>435382</tid>
<number>i</number>time spent by a Judge on duty as a Judge, or in 
the performance of such other functions as he may, at 
the request of the President, undertake to discharge; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>913073</tid>
<number>ii</number>vacations;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1474057</tid>
<number>c</number>" Chief Justice" means the Chief Justice of India, 
but does not include an acting Chief Justice;

</section>

<section><tid>422798</tid>
<number>d</number>" High Court" means the High Court for a State;

</section>

<section><tid>32512</tid>
<number>e</number>" Judge" means a Judge of the Supreme Court and 
includes the Chief Justice and an acting Chief Justice;

</section>

<section><tid>1617696</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>414591</tid>
<number>g</number>" service as a Judge in India" means service 
rendered either in the Federal Court or in the Supreme 
Court or in any such Court and in one or more of the 
High Courts, and" Judge in India" and" service for 
pension as a Judge in India" shall be construed 
accordingly;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>48</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>912089</tid>
<number>h</number>" service for pension" includes-

</section>

<section><tid>651140</tid>
<number>i</number>actual service;

<subsection><tid>1193270</tid>
<number>ii</number>time spent by a Judge of a High Court in attending 
the sittings of the Supreme Court as an ad hoc Judge 
under article 127 of the Constitution. if he is 
subsequently appointed as a Judge:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>288857</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the amount, actually taken, of each period of 
leave on full allowances at a rate equal to the monthly 
rate of the salary];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1281638</tid>
<number>i</number>" vacation" means such period or periods during a 
year as may be fixed as vacation by or under the rules 
of the Supreme Court made with the prior approval of the 
President.
CHAP

LEAVE

CHAPTER II

LEAVE




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>990010</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>53951</tid>
<number>1</number>Kinds of leave admissible to a Judge. Subject to the  
provisions of this Act, leave granted to a Judge a may be at his 
option either-

<subsection><tid>1525182</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> leave on full allowances (including commuted leave on half  
  allowances into leave on full allowances on medical certificate); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>841081</tid>
<number>b</number>leave on half allowances: or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>916636</tid>
<number>c</number>leave partly on full allowances and partly on half 
allowances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1824688</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this Chapter, any period of leave on 
full allowances shall be reckoned as double that period of leave on 
half allowances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>357403</tid>
<number> 4</number> 
<section><tid>789298</tid>
<number>1</number>Leave account showing the amount of leave due. A leave  
account shall be kept for each Judge showing therein the amount of 
leave due to him in terms of leave on half allowances.

</section>

<section><tid>517674</tid>
<number>2</number>In the leave account of a Judge-

<subsection><tid>50643</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be credited to him-

<subsubsection><tid>1978483</tid>
<number>i</number>one- fourth of the time spent by him on actual service;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>49</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1980</year>, s. 7, for sub- cl. (iii).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 77 of <year>1971</year>. s. 2, for cl. (a)  (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The word" and" omitted by s. 3, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1958</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>950740</tid>
<number>ii</number>where the Judge, by reason of his having been 
detained for the performance of duties not connected 
with the Supreme Court, cannot enjoy any vacation which 
he would otherwise have been entitled to enjoy had he 
not been so detained, as compensation for the vacation 
not enjoyed, a period equal to double the period by 
which the vacation enjoyed by him in any year falls 
short of one month; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1451451</tid>
<number>iii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> where the Judge was, prior to his appointment 
as such, a Judge of a High Court, the period of leave 
earned by him as a Judge of the High Court, so, 
however, that such period shall not exceed two hundred 
and forty days <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in terms of leave on fall allowances] <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> 
and]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1964936</tid>
<number>b</number>there shall be debited to him all leave with 
allowances taken by him.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1307622</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall be deemed to have come into force on the 
 1st day of May, <year>1958</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>481269</tid>
<number> 5</number> 
<section><tid>1321600</tid>
<number>1</number>Aggregate amount of leave which may be granted. The  
aggregate amount of leave which may be granted to a Judge during the 
whole period of his service as such shall not exceed in terms of leave 
on half allowances three years <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[ including the period credited to 
his leave account under sub- section 2 a iii of section 4 as leave 
earned by him as a Judge of a High Court]] together with the 
aggregate of the periods, if any, credited to his leave account under 
sub- section (2) a ii of section 4 as compensation for vacation not 
enjoyed.

</section>

<section><tid>788779</tid>
<number>2</number>The aggregate amount of leave on full allowances which may 
be granted to a Judge during the whole period of his service as such 
shall not exceed one- twenty- fourth of the period spent by him on 
actual service together with one- half of the aggregate periods, if 
any, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> credited to his leave account-

<subsection><tid>1707597</tid>
<number>a</number>under sub- section (2) a (ii). of section 4 as 
compensation for vacation not enjoyed, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>525608</tid>
<number>b</number>under sub- section (2) a (iii) of section 4 as leave 
earned by him as a Judge of a High Court.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>50</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 77 of <year>1971</year>, s 3, (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1958</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 17- 10- <year>1958</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs, by s, 4, ibid., for: certain words (w. e. f. 17- 10- <year>1958</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1986</year>, S. 7 (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1989</year>, s 3 (w. e. f. 1. 11. <year>1986</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1852770</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 
5A, the maximum period of leave which may be granted] at one time 
shall be, in the case of leave on full allowances, five months and in 
the case of leave with allowances of any kind, sixteen months.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1689863</tid>
<number> 5A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>495310</tid>
<number>1</number>Commutation of leave on half allowances into leave on  
full a allowances. Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section 
 (2) of section 5, a Judge may be permitted to commute leave on half 
allowances into leave on full allowances on medical certificate up to 
a maximum of three months during the whole period of his leave as a 
Judge.

</section>

<section><tid>31757</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the maximum period of leave on full allowances 
which may be granted at one time to a Judge under sub- section (3) of 
section 5, the amount of commuted leave permitted to him under this 
section shall not be taken into account.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1913761</tid>
<number> 6</number> Grant of leave not due. Subject to the maximum limit 
specified in sub- section
<section><tid>1490432</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 5, leave on half allowances  
may be granted to a Judge in excess of the amount at his credit-

<subsection><tid>182394</tid>
<number>i</number>on medical certificate; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>976681</tid>
<number>ii</number>otherwise than on medical certificate, for a 
period not exceeding six months, or for two or more 
periods not exceeding in the aggregate six months, 
during the whole period of his service as a Judge:
Provided that no such leave shall be granted if the Judge is not 
expected to return to duty at the end of such leave and earn the leave 
granted.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1071982</tid>
<number>7</number>Special disability leave. Special disability leave may be 
granted to a Judge under such circumstances, on such allowances and 
for such periods as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1585104</tid>
<number>8</number>Extraordinary leave. Extraordinary leave may be granted to a 
Judge for a period not exceeding six months, or for two or more 
periods not exceeding in the aggregate six months, during the whole 
period of his service as a Judge in excess of any leave permissible 
under the foregoing provisions of this Chapter but no salary or 
allowances shall be payable in respect of such leave.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>50A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 77 of <year>1971</year>, s. 4, for" The maximum period of leave 
which may be granted" (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 77 of <year>1971</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1972</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1413794</tid>
<number> 9</number> 
<section><tid>1392980</tid>
<number>1</number>Leave allowances. The monthly rate of leave allowances  
payable to a Judge while on leave on full allowances shall be for the 
first forty- five days of such leave a rate equal to the monthly rate 
of the salary <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and thereafter, in the case of the Chief Justice, 
fifty per cent of the monthly rate of his salary and in the case of 
each of the other Judges, fifty- five per cent of the monthly rate of 
his salary"]:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that where leave on full allowances is granted to a 
Judge on medical certificate, the monthly rate of leave allowances 
shall, for the first one hundred and twenty days of such leave, be a 
rate equal to the monthly rate of his salary.]


</section>

<section><tid>1132866</tid>
<number>2</number>The monthly rate of leave allowances payable to a Judge 
while on leave on half allowances shall be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the case of the Chief 
Justice, twenty- five per cent. of the monthly rate of his salary, and 
in the case of each of the other Judges, twenty- seven and a half per 
cent, of the monthly rate of his salary"]:
[ Provided that the monthly rate of leave allowances payable to a 
Judge in respect of leave credited to his leave account under sub- 
section (a)  (iii) of section 4 shall not exceed the rate of leave 
allowances admissible to him therefore as a Judge of a High Court and 
shall be payable by the State Government concerned.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1729211</tid>
<number> 10</number> Combining leave with vacation. A Judge may be permitted to 
combine vacation on full salary with leave, if-
<section><tid>1121367</tid>
<number>a</number>where the vacation consists of one continuous 
period, the leave is taken either at the commencement or 
at the end of the vacation but not at both;

</section>

<section><tid>1524637</tid>
<number>b</number>where the vacation is divided into two periods, 
the leave is taken for the interval, or part of the 
interval, between the two periods of that vacation, or 
for the interval, or part of the interval, between the 
second period of that vacation and the commencement of 
the next ensuing vacation:
Provided that no such permission to combine vacation with leave 
shall be granted, if it becomes necessary to appoint an acting Chief 
Justice during the period of vacation or if the Judge is not expected 
to return to duty at the end of such leave.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>493750</tid>
<number> 11</number> 
<section><tid>1438926</tid>
<number>1</number>Consequences of over staying leave of vacation. If a  
Judge overstays his leave or any vacation, whether combined with leave 
or not, he shall receive no salary in respect of the period of his 
absence in excess of the leave granted to him or beyond the end of the 
vacation, as the case may be:
Provided that. if such absence is due to circumstances beyond his 
control, the period thereof may be treated as leave and may be debited 
to his leave account.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>50B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>2</number>Added by Act 57 of <year>1980</year>, s. 8.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins, by Act 77 of <year>1971</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 15- 1- <year>1972</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 32 of <year>1989</year>, S. 6 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1986</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1226667</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this Act shall be construed as requiring a Judge 
to rejoin on the expiration of the period of leave when that period 
expires immediately before the commencement of vacation, nor as 
authorising any acting Chief justice to continue to hold the acting 
appointment during the vacation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1031675</tid>
<number>12</number>Authority competent to grant leave. The authority competent to 
grant or refuse leave to a Judge or to revoke or curtail the leave 
already granted to a Judge shall be the President who shall exercise 
the power after consultation with the Chief Justice.
CHAP

PENSIONS

CHAPTER III

PENSIONS



</article>



<article><tid>142008</tid>
<number> 13</number> Pension payable to judges. Subject to the provisions of this 
Act, a pension shall be payable in accordance with the provisions of 
Part I of the Schedule to a Judge of the Supreme Court on his 
retirement if, but only if,-
<section><tid>635356</tid>
<number>a</number>he has completed not less than seven years of 
service for pension as a Judge in India; or

</section>

<section><tid>1560644</tid>
<number>b</number>he has attained' the age of sixty- five years; or

</section>

<section><tid>287030</tid>
<number>c</number>his retirement is medically certified to be 
necessitated by ill health.
Explanation.- In this section," Judge" means a Judge who is not a 
member of the Indian Civil Service or has not held any other 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> pensionable post] under the Union or a State and includes a person 
who was in service as a Judge on the 20th May, <year>1954</year>, and also includes 
a Judge who being a member of the Indian Civil Service or having held 
any other <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> pensionable post] under the Union or a State has elected 
to receive the pension payable under Part I of the Schedule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1613171</tid>
<number> 14</number> Special Provisions for pension in respect of Judges who are 
members of service. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>459994</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Judge- 

<subsection><tid>115475</tid>
<number>a</number>who is a member of the Indian Civil Service shall, on 
his retirement, be paid a pension in accordance with the pro- 
visions of Part II of the Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>981378</tid>
<number>b</number>who is not a member of the Indian Civil Service but has 
held any other <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> pensionable post] under the Union or a State 
shall, on his retirement, be paid a pension in accordance 
with the provisions of Part III of the Schedule;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>51</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1980</year>, s. 9, for" pensionable civil post" 
 (retrospectively 

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>S. 14 renumbered as sub- section (1) thereof by Act 36 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1974</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided that every such Judge shall elect to receive the pension 
payable to him either under Part I of the Schedule or, as the case may 
be, Part II or Part Ill of the Schedule, and the pension payable to 
him shall be calculated accordingly.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>49088</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), any 
Judge to whom that sub- section applies and who is in service on or 
after the 1st day of October, <year>1974</year>, may, if he has elected under the 
proviso to that sub- section to receive the pension payable to him 
under Part II or, as the case may be, Part III of the Schedule before 
the date on which the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions of Service) 
Amendment Act, <year>1976</year>. (36 of <year>1976</year>). receives the assent of the 
President, cancel such election and elect afresh to receive the 
pension payable to him under Part I of the Schedule and any such Judge 
who dies before the date of such assent, shall deemed to have elected 
afresh to be governed by the provisions of said Part I if the 
provisions of that Part are more favourable in his case.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1336495</tid>
<number> 15</number> Power of President to add to the service for pension. The 
President may, for special reasons, direct that any period not 
exceeding three months shall be added to the service for pension of a 
Judge, and any such period so added shall count for pension purposes-
<section><tid>946666</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a Judge who has served in the 
Supreme Court as Chief Justice, as service as Chief 
Justice; and

</section>

<section><tid>1461273</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any other Judge, as service as any 
other Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1136197</tid>
<number>16</number>Extraordinary pension. Extraordinary pensions and gratuities 
may be granted to a Judge under such circumstances and on such scales 
as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1996351</tid>
<number> 16A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Family pension and gratuity. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>318277</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a Judge who, being  
in service on or after the commencement of the High Court and Supreme 
Court Judges Conditions of Service Amendment Act, <year>1986</year>,-

<subsection><tid>793982</tid>
<number>a</number>dies before retirement, family pension calculated at the 
rate of fifty per cent of the pension admissible to him on the date of 
his death shall be payable to the person or persons entitled thereto 
and the amount so payable shall be paid from the day following the 
date of death of the Judge for a period of seven years or for a period 
up to the date on which the Judge would have attained the age of 
sixty- five years, had he survived, whichever is earlier, and 
thereafter at the rate of half of the family pension so admissible; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1558579</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> dies after retirement after seeking premature retirement 
and before attaining the age of sixty- five years, family pension 
admissible and shall be payable to the persons or persons entitled 
thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>805572</tid>
<number>c</number>dies after retirement after seeking premature retirement and 
before attaining the age of sixty- five years, family pension shall be 
calculated at the rates specified in clause (a) and shall be payable 
to the person or persons entitled thereto."]
Explanation.- For the purposes of determining the person persons 
entitled to family pension under this sub- section,-


<subsubsection><tid>571911</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to a Judge who elects or is eligible to receive 
pension under Part I of the Schedule, the rules, notifications and 
orders for the time being in force with regard to the person or 
persons entitled to family pension in relation to an officer of the 
Central Civil Services, Group' A', shall apply;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>954869</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to a Judge who elects to receive pension under 
Part II or Part III of the Schedule, the ordinary rules of his service 
if he had not been appointed a Judge with respect to the person or 
persons entitled to family pension shall apply and his service as a 
Judge being treated as service therein."]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1666977</tid>
<number>2</number>The rules, notifications and orders for the time being in 
force with respect to the grant of death- cum- retirement gratuity 
benefit to or in relation to an officer of the Central Civil Services, 
Class I (including the provisions relating to deductions from pension  
  for the purpose) shall apply to or in relation to the grant of death- 
cum- retirement gratuity benefit to or in relation to a Judge who, 
being in service on or after the 1st day of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>52</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 36 of <year>1976</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1974</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 3 ibid., (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1974</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1986</year>, S. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1989</year>, S. 7.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

October, <year>1974</year>, retires, or dies in circumstances to which section 16 
does not apply, subject to the modifications that-


<subsection><tid>493890</tid>
<number>i</number>the minimum qualifying service for the purpose of 
entitlement to the gratuity shall be two years and six 
months;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>275188</tid>
<number>ii</number>the amount of gratuity shall be calculated on the 
basis of twenty days' salary for each completed year of 
service as a Judge;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>746917</tid>
<number>4</number>Sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall be deemed to have come 
into force on the 26th day of January, <year>1950</year> and sub- section (1A) shall 
be deemed to have comes into force on the 9th day- of May, <year>1986</year> and 
any rule made under, any of the said sub- sections may be made so as to 
be retrospective to any date not earlier than the commencement of the 
respective sub- section. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> fifty thousand rupees]
Explanation.- <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In sub- section (2) the expression" Judge" has the 
same meaning as in section 13.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>822433</tid>
<number>17</number>Pension payable to a Judge who was in receipt of pension at 
the time of appointment as such. If, at the time of his appointment 
to the Supreme Court, a Judge is in receipt of a pension in respect of 
any previous service either as a Judge of a High Court or in any other 
pensionable civil post under the Union or a State, the pension payable 
to him under this Act shall be an additional pension for service in 
the Supreme Court equal to the difference between his original pension 
and the pension to which he would have been entitled under this Act, 
if his service in the Supreme Court had been rendered in continuation 
of the previous service for which his original pension was granted.


</article>



<article><tid>1826485</tid>
<number>18</number>Conversion of sterling pension into rupees. Pensions expressed 
in sterling only shall, if paid in India, be converted into rupees at 
such rate of exchange as the Central Government may, from time to 
time, specify in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>1406872</tid>
<number>19</number>Commutation of pension. The Civil Pensions (Commutation) Rules 
for the time being in force shall, with necessary modifications, apply 
to Judges.


</article>



<article><tid>812488</tid>
<number>20</number>Provident Fund. Every Judge shall be entitled to subscribe to 
the Central Provident Fund (Central Services):
Provided that a Judge who is a member of the Indian Civil Service 
or has held any other pensionable civil post under the Union or a 
State shall continue to subscribe to the provident fund to which he 
was subscribing before his appointment as a Judge:

Provided further that a Judge who was appointed before the 
commencement of this Act may continue to subscribe to the provident 
fund to which he was subscribing immediately before such commencement.



</article>



<article><tid>1296179</tid>
<number>20A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Deposit Linked Insurance Scheme. The Deposit Linked 
Insurance Scheme for the time being in force under the General 
Provident Fund (Central Services) Rules, <year>1960</year>, shall apply to every 
Judge whether he subscribes to the General Provident Fund (Central  
  Services) or any other Provident Fund referred to in section 20.


</article>



<article><tid>558426</tid>
<number>21</number>Authority competent to grant pension. Save as may be otherwise 
expressly provided in the relevant rules relating to the grant of 
extraordinary pensions and gratuities, the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>53</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by S. 9 ibid. (w. e. f. 5- 9- <year>1997</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 20 of <year>1988</year>, S. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

authority competent to grant to a Judge under the provisions of this 
Act shall be the President.

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1967532</tid>
<number>22</number>Travelling all owance to a Judge. A Judge shall receive such 
reasonable allowance to reimburse him for expenses incurred in 
travelling on duty within the territory of India and shall be afforded 
such reasonable facilities in connection with travelling as may, from 
time to time be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>433733</tid>
<number> 23</number> 
<section><tid>1716321</tid>
<number>1</number>Facilities for rent- free houses and other conditions of  
service. Every Judge shall be entitled without payment of rent to the 
use of an official residence in accordance with such rules as may, 
from time to time, be made in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1323208</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where a Judge does not avail himself of the use of an 
official residence, he may be paid every month an allowance of three 
thousand rupees."]

</section>

<section><tid>1267501</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Judge and the his family shall be entitled to such 
facilities for medical treatment and for accommodation in hospitals as 
may, from time to time. be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1917052</tid>
<number>3</number>The conditions of service of a Judge for which no express 
provision has been made in this Act shall be such as may be determined 
by rules made under this Act.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1500762</tid>
<number>23A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Conveyance facilities. Every Judge shall be entitled to a 
staff car and one hundred and fifty liters of petrol every month or 
the actual consumption of petrol per month, whichever is less."]
</article>



<article><tid>1775818</tid>
<number>23B</number>Sumptuary allowance. The Chief Justice and each of the 
other Judges shall be entitle to a sumptuary allowance of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> one 
thousand two hundred and fifty per month and seven hundred and fifty 
rupees"] per month respectively.
</article>



<article><tid>1363162</tid>
<number>23C</number>Medical facilities for retired Judges. Every retired 
Judge shall, with effect from the date on which the Supreme Court 
Judges (Conditions of Service) Amendment Act, <year>1976</year> (36 of <year>1976</year>) 
receives the assent of the President, be entitled, for himself and his 
family to the same facilities as respects medical treatment and on the 
Same conditions as a retired officer of the Central Civil Services, 
Class I and his family, are entitled under any rules and orders of the 
Central Government for the time being in force.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>54</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1986</year> S 10 (w. e. f. 1- 01- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs by S. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. and Subs, by Act 72 of <year>1993</year>, S 2


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>502919</tid>
<number> 23D</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Exemption from liability to pay income- tax on certain 
perquisites received by a Judge.[ Notwithstanding anything contained in 
the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>,-
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or the allowance paid to him under sub- section (1A) 
of that section."]

<section><tid>1320041</tid>
<number>a</number>the value of rent- free official residence provided 
to a Judge under sub- section (1) of section 23;

</section>

<section><tid>1464235</tid>
<number>b</number>the value of the conveyance facilities provided to 
a Judge under section 23A;

</section>

<section><tid>1913007</tid>
<number>c</number>the sumptuary allowance provided to a Judge under 
section 23B,

</section>

<section><tid>1902551</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the value of leave travel concession provided to 
a Judge and members of his family"]
shall not be included in the computation of his income 
chargeable under the head" Salaries" under section 15 of 
the Income- tax Act <year>1961</year>.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1401674</tid>
<number> 24</number> 
<section><tid>779180</tid>
<number>1</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1181740</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>940859</tid>
<number>a</number>leave of absence of a Judge, including special 
disability leave;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1809432</tid>
<number>b</number>pension payable to a Judge, including 
extraordinary pensions and gratuities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>313729</tid>
<number>c</number>travelling allowances to a Judge;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1210204</tid>
<number>d</number>use of official residence by a Judge;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1633998</tid>
<number>e</number>facilities for medical treatment and other 
conditions of service of a Judge;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>503330</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>274332</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised, in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>626759</tid>
<number>25</number>Savings. Nothing contained in this Act shall have effect so 
as to give to a Judge who is serving as such at the commencement of 
this Act less favourable terms in respect of his privileges and 
allowances or his rights in respect of leave of absence (including  
  leave allowances) or pension than those to which he would have been 
entitled, if this Act had not been passed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>55</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 36 of 19- 76, s. 5, for sub- section (3)  (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1974</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1988</year> S. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 72 of <year>1993</year> S. 3 (w. e. f. 9- 5- <year>1986</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1994</year>, S. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>