<act> 
 The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 20031
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall extend to the 
whole of India except the Sate of Jammu and Kashmir. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 
 The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Forest (Conservation) Act, 
1980 (69 of 1980);
 
1[(b)   
“Committee” means the Forest Advisory Committee constituted under section 3 of 
the Act;]
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the 
Committee;
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>   “member” means a member of the Committee;
 </section><section>        <number>e</number>   “Nodal Officer” means any officer not below 
the rank of Conservator of Forests, authorised by the State Government to deal 
with the forest conservation matters under the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>f</number>   “Regional Office” means a Regional Office of 
the Central government in the 
Ministry of Environment and Forests established as part of the Ministry to deal 
with the forest conservation matters under the Act;
 </section><section>        <number>g</number>   “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>        <number>h</number>   “user agency” means any person, organisation 
or Company or Department of the Central or State Government making a request for 
diversion or de-notification of forest land for non-forest purpose or using 
forest land for non-forest purpose in accordance with the permission granted by 
the Central Government under the Act or the rules.
  


</section></article> 
 
 The  Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
    
 <article>1[<number>3</number> Composition of the Forest Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The  Forest Advisory Committee shall be composed of the following
members, namely:—
 <subsection>          
<number>i</number>  the Director General of Forests, Ministry of  
Environment and Forests                                                                —Chairperson
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>ii</number>  the Additional Director General of Forests,  
Ministry of Environment and Forests                                               —Member
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>iii</number>  the Additional Commissioner (Soil Conservation),  
Ministry of Agriculture                                                                     —Member
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>iv</number>  three non-official members who shall be  
experts one each in Mining, Civil  
Engineering and Development Economics                                        —Members
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>v</number>  the Inspector General of Forests (Forest  
Conservation), Ministry of Environment  
and Forests                                                                                   —Members
Secretary.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Additional Director General of
Forests shall act as the Chairperson in the absence of Director General of
Forests.]
  









</section></article> 
 
 The  Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
   
 <article>1[<number>3A</number> Constitution of the Regional Empowered Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> A Regional Empowered Committee shall be
constituted at each of the Regional Offices and shall consist of the following
members, namely:—
             (i) the Regional Principal Chief Conservator  
of Forests (Central)                                                                       —Chairperson
            (ii) three non-official members who shall be  
experts one each in Mining, Civil Engineering  
and Development Economics                                                          —Members
           (iii) the Conservator of Forests or the Deputy                                       —Member 
Conservator of Forests in the Regional Office                                  Secretary.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The terms of appointment of
non-official Members shall be as specified in rule 4 of these rules.]
  



</section></article> 
 The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>4</number> Terms of appointment of 
non-official members shall be as follows.—
 <section>         <number>i</number>   a non-official member shall hold his office 
for a period of two years;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>   a non-official member shall cease to hold 
office if he becomes of unsound mind, becomes insolvent or is convicted by court 
of law on a criminal offence involving moral turpitude;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>   a non-official member may be removed from his 
office if he fails to attend three consecutive meetings of the Committee without 
any sufficient cause or reasons;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>   any vacancy in the membership caused by any 
reason mentioned in clauses (ii) and (iii) shall be filled by the
government for the unexpired 
portion of two years term.
 </section><section>        <number>v</number>   travelling and daily allowance shall be 
payable to the non-official members of the Committee at the highest rate 
admissible to the Government servants of Group ‘A’ under the rules and orders 
made by the central
government and for the time being 
in force:
 Provided that the payment of 
travelling allowance and daily allowance to a member who is a Member of the 
Parliament or a Member of a State Legislature shall be regulated in accordance 
with the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, 1954 (30 
of 1954) or the respective provisions of law pertaining to the member of the 
concerned State Legislature.
</section></article> 
 The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>5</number> Conduct of business of the 
Committee.—
 <section>         <number>i</number>   The chairperson 
shall call the meeting of the Committee whenever considered necessary, but not 
less than once in a month.
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>   The meeting of the Committee shall be held at 
New Delhi.
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>   In a case where the Chairperson is satisfied 
that inspection of site or sites of forest land proposed to be used for 
non-forest purposes shall be necessary or expedient in connection with the 
consideration of the proposal or proposals received under sub-rule (3) of rule 
6, he may direct that the meetings of the Committee to be held at a place other 
than New Delhi from where such inspection of site or sites is necessary.
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>   The Chairperson shall preside over every 
meeting of the Committee at which he is present.
 </section><section>        <number>v</number>   Every question upon which the Central 
Government is required to be advised shall be considered in the meeting of the 
Committee provided that in urgent cases if the meeting cannot be convened within 
a month, the Chairperson may direct that papers may be circulated and sent to 
the members for their opinion within the stipulated time.
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>   The quorum of the meeting of the Committee 
shall be three.
</section></article> 
 The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
  
 <article>

1[<number>6</number> Submission of proposals seeking 
approval of the central
government under section 2 of the 
Act.—
<section><number>1</number> Every user agency, who wants 
to use any forest land for non-forestry purposes, shall make its proposal in the 
relevant Form appended to these rules, i.e., Form A for proposals seeking 
first time approval under the Act, and Form B for proposals seeking renewal of 
leases, where approval of the Central Government under the Act had already been 
obtained, to the Nodal Officer of the concerned State Government or the Union 
Territory Administration, as the case may be, along with requisite information 
and documents, complete in all respects.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The user agency shall 
endorse a copy of the proposal, along with a copy of the receipt obtained from 
the office of the Nodal Officer, to the concerned Divisional Forest Officer or 
the Conservator of Forests, Regional Office, as well as the Monitoring Cell of 
the Forest Conservation Division of the Ministry of Environment and Forests, 
Paryavaran Bhawan, CGO Complex, New Delhi–110003.
 </section><section><number>3</number> (a) After having received 
the proposal, the State Government or the Union Territory Administration, as the 
case may be, shall process and forward it to the Central Government within a 
period of two hundred and ten days of the receipt of the proposal including the 
transit period.
 <subsection><number>b</number> The Nodal Officer of State 
Government or as the case may be, the Union Territory Administration, after 
having received the proposal under sub‑rule (1) and on being satisfied that the 
proposal is complete in all respects, and requires prior approval under section 
2 of the Act, shall send the proposal to the concerned Divisional Forest Officer 
within a period of ten days of the receipt of the proposal:
 Provided that on the 
determination regarding completeness of the proposal or the expiry of ten days, 
whichever is earlier, the question of completeness or otherwise of the proposal 
shall not be raised.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> If the Nodal Officer of the 
State Government or the Union Territory Administration, as the case may be, 
finds that the proposal is incomplete, he shall return it within the period of 
ten days as specified under clause (b), to the user agency and this time period 
shall not be counted for any future reference.
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> The Divisional Forest 
Officer or the Conservator of Forests shall examine the factual details and 
feasibility of the proposal, certify the maps, carry out site‑inspection and 
enumeration of the trees­ and forward his findings in the format specified in 
this regard to the Nodal Officer within a period of ninety days of the receipt 
of such proposal from him.
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> (i) The Nodal Officer, 
through the Principal Chief Conservator of Forests shall forward the proposal to 
State Government or the Union Territory Administration, as the case may be, 
alongwith his recommendations, within a period of thirty days of the receipt of 
such proposal from the Divisional Forest Officer or the Conservator of Forests.
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> The State Government or the 
Union Territory Administration, as the case may be, shall forward the complete 
proposal, along with its recommendations, to the Regional Office or the Ministry 
of Environment and Forests, Paryavaran Bhawan, CGO Complex, New Delhi-110003, as 
the case may be, in the specified Forms within a period of sixty days of the 
receipt of the proposal from the Nodal Officer:
 Provided that all proposals 
involving clearing of naturally grown trees on the forest land or a portion 
thereof for the purpose of using it for reforestation shall be sent in the form 
of Working Plan or Management Plan:
 Provided further that the 
concerned State Government or, as the case may be, the Union Territory 
Administration, shall simultaneously send the intimation to the user agency 
about forwarding of the proposal, alongwith its recommendations, to the Regional 
Office or the Ministry of Environment and Forests, as the case may be.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>f</number> If the proposal, alongwith 
the recommendations, is not received from the concerned State Government or the 
Union Territory Administration, as the case may be, till fifteen days of the 
expiry of the time limit as specified under clause (a), it shall be construed 
that the concerned State Government or, as the case may be, the Union Territory 
Administration, has rejected the proposal and the concerned State Government or 
the Union Territory Administration shall inform the user agency accordingly:
 Provided that in case the State 
Government or the Union Territory Administration, as the case may be, 
subsequently forward the proposal, alongwith its recommendations, to the 
Regional Office or the Ministry of Environment and Forests, as the case may be, 
the proposal shall not be considered by the Central Government unless an 
explanation for the delay to the satisfaction of the Central Government is 
furnished, together with action taken against any individual held to be 
responsible for the delay.
 *[(4) The proposal referred to 
in clause (e) (ii) of sub‑rule (3), involving forest land upto forty hectares 
shall be forwarded by the concerned State Government or as the case may be, the 
Union Territory Administration, alongwith its recommendations, to the Chief 
Conservator of Forests or the Conservator of Forests of the concerned Regional 
Office of the Ministry of Environment and Forests, Government of India, who 
shall, within a period of forty‑five days of the receipt of the proposal from 
the concerned State Government or the Union Territory Administration, as the 
case may be (a) decide the diversion proposal upto five hectares other than the 
proposal relating to mining and encroachments, and (b) process, scrutinise and 
forward diversion proposal of more than five hectares and upto forty hectares 
including all proposals relating to mining and encroachments upto forty 
hectares, alongwith the recommendations, if any, to the Ministry of Environment 
and Forests, Paryavaran Bhawan, CGO Complex, New Delhi-110003, for obtaining the 
decision of the Central Government and inform the State Government or the Union 
Territory Administration, as the case may be, and the User Agency concerned.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> The Regional Empowered 
Committee shall decide the proposal involving diversion of forest, land upto 
forty hectares other than the proposal relating to mining and encroachments, 
within forty‑five days of the receipt of such proposal from the State Government 
or the Union Territory Administration, as the case may be:
 Provided that the Central 
Government may, if consider it necessary, enhance or reduce the limit of the 
area of the forest land.
 

2[(6) The proposal referred to in clause 
(e) (ii) of sub-rule (3), involving forest land of more than forty hectares, 
shall be forwarded by the concerned State Government or as the case may be, the 
Union Territory Administration, alongwith its recommendations, to the Ministry 
of Environment and Forests, Paryavaran Bhawan, CGO Complex, New Delhi–110003.]
  









</section></article> 
 The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
   
 <article><number>7</number> Committee to advise on 
proposals received by the Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall refer every proposal, complete in all respects, 
received by it under 

1[sub-rule (6) of rule 6] including site 
inspection report, wherever required, to the Committee for its advice thereon.
 

2[(1A) These proposals shall be processed 
and put up before the Committee and the recommendations of the Committee shall 
be placed within a period of ninety days of the receipt of such proposals from 
the State Government or the Union Territory Administration, as the case may be, 
before the Central Government for its decision.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The
committee shall have due regard 
to all or any of the following matters while tendering its advice on the 
proposals referred to it under sub-rule (1), namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   whether the forests land proposed to be used 
for non-forest purpose forms part of a nature reserve, national park wildlife 
sanctuary, biosphere reserve or forms part of the habitat or any endangered or 
threatened species of flora and fauna or of an area lying in severely eroded 
catchment;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   whether the use of any forest land is for 
agricultural purposes or for the rehabilitation of persons displaced from their 
residences by reason of any river valley or hydro-electric project;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   whether the State Government
3[or the 
Union Territory Administration, as the case may be,] has certified that it has 
considered all other alternatives and that no other alternatives in the 
circumstances are feasible and that the required area is the minimum needed for 
the purpose; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>d</number>   whether the State Government
3[or the 
Union Territory Administration, as the case may be,] undertakes to provide at 
its cost for the acquisition of land of an equivalent area and afforestation 
thereof. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> While tendering the advice, 
the Committee may also suggest any conditions or restrictions on the use of any 
forest land for any non-forest purpose, which in its opinion, would minimise 
adverse environmental impact.
  




</section></article> 
 The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>9</number> Proceedings against 
persons guilty of offences under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, authorise any officer not below the 
rank of Conservator of Forests or the concerned forest officer having 
territorial jurisdiction over the forest land in respect of which the said 
offence is said to have been committed, to file complaints against the person 
(s) prima facie found guilty of offence under the Act or the violation of 
the rules made thereunder, in the court having jurisdiction in the matter:
 Provided that no complaint shall 
be filed in the court, without giving the person(s) or officer(s) or 
authority(ies) against whom the allegations of offence exist, an opportunity to 
explain his or their conduct and to show cause, by issuing a notice in writing 
of not less than sixty days, as to why a complaint should not be filed in the 
court against him or them for alleged offences.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The officer authorised by 
the Central Government in sub-rule (1) may require any State Government or its 
officer or any person or any other authority to furnish to it within a specified 
period any reports, documents, statistics and any other information related to 
contravention of the Act or the rules made thereunder, considered necessary for 
making a complaint in any court of jurisdiction and every such State
government or officer or person 
or authority shall be bound to do so.
</section></article><form>
 

The Forest (Conservation) Rules, 2003
 

 
 

Appendix 
 

Form A
 

(See
rule 6)
 

Form for seeking prior approval under section 2  

of the proposals by the State Governments  

and other authorities 
 

Part I
 

(to be filled up by user 
agency)
 

1. Project details:
 

         (i)  Short narrative of the proposal and 
project/scheme for which the forest land is required.
 

        (ii)  Map showing the required forest land, 
boundary of adjoining forest on a 1:50,000 scale map.
 

        (iii)  Cost of the project.
 

       (iv)  Justification for locating the project in 
forest area.
 

        (v)  Cost-benefit analysis (to be enclosed).
 

       (vi)  Employment likely to be generated.
 

2. Purpose-wise break-up of the total land required:
 

3. Details of displacement of people due to the project, if 
any:
 

         (i)  Number of families.
 

        (ii)  Number of Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribe 
families.
 

        (iii)  Rehabilitation plan (to be enclosed).
 

4. Whether clearance under Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 
required? (Yes/No).
 

5. Undertaking to bear the cost of raising and maintenance of 
compensatory afforestation and/or penal compensatory afforestation as well as 
cost for protection and regeneration of Safety Zone, etc., as per the scheme 
prepared by the State Government (undertaking to be enclosed).
 

6. Details of Certificate/documents enclosed as required under 
the instructions.
 


                                                                          
Signature 
 


                                                                          (Name 
in Block letters)
 


Date.............................                                            
Designation
 


Place.............................                                           
Address (of User Agency)
 

      State Serial No. 
of proposal.......................................................
 

(To be filled up by 
the Nodal Officer with date of receipt)
 

 
 

Part II
 

(To be filled by the 
concerned Deputy Conservator of Forests)
 

State Serial No. of 
proposal................................
 

7. Location of the project/Scheme:
 

         (i)  State/Union Territory
 

        (ii)  District
 

        (iii)  Forest Division
 

       (iv)  Area of forest land proposed for diversion (in 
ha.)
 

        (v)  Legal status of forest
 

       (vi)  Density of vegetation
 

       (vii)  Species-wise (scientific names) and diameter 
class-wise enumeration of trees (to be enclosed. In case of irrigation/hydel 
projects enumeration at FRL, FRL-2 meter &amp; FRL-4 meter also to be enclosed)
 

      (viii)  Brief note on vulnerability of the forest 
area to erosion
 

       (ix)  Approximate distance of proposed site for 
diversion from boundary of forest
 

        (x)  whether forms part of National Park, wildlife 
sanctuary, biosphere reserve, tiger reserve, elephant corridor, etc. (If so, the 
details of the area and comments of the Chief Wildlife Warden to be annexed)
 

       (xi)  whether any rare/endangered/unique species of 
flora and fauna found in the area if so details thereof
 

       (xii)  whether any protected archaeological/heritage 
site/defence establishment or any other important monument is located in the 
area. If so, the details thereof with NOC from competent authority, if required.
 

8. Whether the requirement of forest land as proposed by the 
user agency in col. 2 of Part I is unavoidable and barest minimum for the 
project. If no, recommended area item-wise with details of alternatives 
examined.
 

9. Whether any work in violation of the Act has been carried 
out (Yes/No). If yes, details of the same including period of work done, action 
taken on erring officials. Whether work in violation is still in progress.      

 

10. Details of compensatory afforestation scheme:  
 

         (i)  Details of non forest area/degraded forest 
area identified for compensatory afforestation, its distance from adjoining 
forest, number of patches, size of each patch.
 

        (ii)  Map showing non forest/degraded forest area 
identified for compensatory afforestation and adjoining forest boundaries.
 

        (iii)  Detailed compensatory afforestation scheme 
including species to be planted, implementing agency time schedule, cost 
structure, etc.        
 

       (iv)  Total financial outlay for compensatory 
afforestation scheme.
 

        (v)  Certificates from competent authority 
regarding suitability of area identified for compensatory afforestation and from 
management point of view. (To be signed by the concerned Deputy Conservator of 
Forests).     
 

11. Site inspection report of the DCF (to be enclosed) 
especially highlighting facts asked in columns 7 (xi, xii), 8 and 9 
above.         
 

12.             Division/District profile:  
 

         (i)  Geographical area of the district.
 

        (ii)  Forest area of the district.
 

        (iii)  Total forest area diverted since 1980 with 
number of cases.
 

       (iv)  Total compensatory afforestation stipulated in 
the district/division since 1980 on—
 

            (a) forest land including penal compensatory 
afforestation,
 

            (b) non-forest land.
 

        (v)  Progress of compensatory afforestation as on 
(date).....................................on—
 

            (a) forest land
 

            (b) non-forest land.
 

13. Specific recommendations of the DCF for acceptance or 
otherwise of the proposal with reasons.           
 


                                                                                                                              
Signature
 


Date.................................                                                        
Name
 


Place­................................                                                        
Official Seal
 

 
 

PART III
 


(To be filled by the concerned Conservator of Forests)
 

14. Whether site, where the forest land involved is located 
has been inspected by concerned Conservator of Forests (Yes/No). If yes, the 
date of inspection and observations made in form of inspection note to be 
enclosed.
 

15. Whether the concerned Conservator of Forests agree with 
the information given in Part­-B and the recommendations of Deputy Conservator 
of Forests.
 

16. Specific recommendation of concerned Conservator of 
Forests for acceptance or otherwise of the proposal with detailed reasons.
 


                                                                                          
Signature
 


Date.................................                                                        
Name
 


Place­................................                                                        
Official Seal
 

 
 

PART IV
 


(To be filled in by the Nodal Officer or Principal Chief Conservator of Forests 
or Head of Forest department)
 

17. Detailed opinion and specific recommendation of the State 
Forest Department for acceptance of otherwise of the proposal with remarks.
 

(While giving opinion, the adverse comments made by concerned 
Conservator of Forests or Deputy Conservator of Forests should be categorically 
reviewed and critically commented upon).            
 


                                                                              
Signature
 


Date­.................................                                            
Name &amp; Designation 
 


Place­................................                                            
(Official Seal)
 

 
 

 
 

PART V
 


(To be filled in by the Secretary in charge of Forest Department or  

by any other authorised officer of the State Government not  

below the rank of an Under Secretary)
 

18. Recommendation of the State Government:
 

(Adverse comments made by any officer or authority in Part B 
or Part C or Part D above should be specifically commented upon)           
 


                                                                              
Signature
 


Date­.................................                                            
Name &amp; Designation 
 


Place­................................                                            
(Official Seal)
 

 
 


INSTRUCTIONS (for Part
I):
 

1 The project authorities may annex a copy of the approved 
project/plan in addition to filling Col. 1 (i), e.g., IBM approved mining 
plan for major minerals/CMPDI plan with subsidence analysis reports, etc.
 

2 Map has to be in original duly authenticated jointly by 
project authorities and concerned DCF—Col. 1 (ii).
 

3 Complete details of alternative alignments examined 
especially in case of project like roads, transmission lines, railway lines, 
canals, etc., to be shown on map with details of area of forest land involved in 
each alternative to be given—Col. 1 (iii).
 

4 For proposals relating to mining, certificate from competent 
authority like District Mining Officer about non-availability of the same 
mineral in surrounding/nearby non­-forest areas.
 

5 In case the same company/individual has taken forest land 
for similar project in the State, a brief detail of all such approvals/leases be 
given as an enclosure along with current status of the projects.
 

6. The latest clarifications issued by the Ministry under 
Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980 may be kept in mind. In case such information do 
not fit in the given columns, the same shall be annexed separately.
 

GENERAL INSTRUCTIONS­
 

1. On receipt of proposal, Nodal Officer shall issue a receipt 
to the user agency indicating therein the name of the proposal, user agency, 
area in hectare, serial number and date of receipt.
 

2. If the space provided above is not sufficient to specify 
any information, please attach separate details/documents.
 

3. While forwarding the proposal to the Central Government, 
complete details on all aspects of the case as per Form prescribed above read 
with the clarifications issued by the Ministry of Environment and Forests, 
Government of India, New Delhi should be given. Incomplete or deficient 
proposals shall not be considered and shall be returned to the State Government 
in original.
 

4. The State Government shall submit the proposal to the 
Central Government within stipulated time limits. In case of delay while 
forwarding, the reasons for the same to be given in the forwarding/covering 
letter.
 

 
 

FORM B
 

(See rule 6)
 

Form for seeking prior approval under section 2 of  

the proposals by the State Governments and other authorities in respect of 
renewal of leases, which  

have been earlier granted clearance under  

Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980
 


PART I
 


(To be filled up by user agency)
 

1. Letter No. and date vide which clearance under 
Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980 accorded by the Central Government (copy to be 
enclosed):
 

2. Project details:
 

         (i)  Short narrative of the proposal and 
project/scheme for which the forest land is required.
 

        (ii)  Map showing the required forest land, 
boundary of adjoining forest on a 1 :50,000 scale map.
 

        (iii)  Cost of the project.
 

3. Purpose-wise break-up of the total land required (already 
broken &amp; to be broken). 
 

4. Details of Certificates/documents enclosed as required 
under the instructions.       
 


                                                                              
Signature
 


                                                                              
(Name in Block letters)
 


Date...........................                                                  
Designation
 


P1ace..........................                                                 
Address (of User Agency)
 

 
 


                                          State Serial No. of 
proposal..................................
 

(To be filled up by 
the Nodal Officer with date of receipt)
 

 
 

PART II
 


(To be filled by the concerned Deputy Conservator of Forests)
 

      State Serial No. 
of proposal.........................................
 

5. Location of the project/Scheme: 
 

         (i)  State/Union Territory
 

        (ii)  District
 

        (iii)  Forest Division
 

       (iv)  Area of forest land proposed for diversion (in 
ha.)
 

        (v)  Legal status of forest
 

       (vi)  Density of vegetation
 

       (vii)  Species-wise (scientific names) and diameter 
class-wise enumeration of trees in unbroken area
 

      (viii)  Whether forms part of National Park, wildlife 
sanctuary, biosphere reserve, tiger reserve, elephant corridor, etc. (If so, the 
details of the area and comments of the Chief Wildlife Warden to be annexed).
 

6. Whether any work in violation of the Act has been carried 
out (Yes/No). If yes, details of the same including period of work done, action 
taken on erring officials. Whether work in violation is still in progress.      

 

7. Site inspection report of the DCF (to be enclosed) in 
respect to status of compliance of conditions stipulated during earlier 
approval.
 

8. Division/District profile:
 

         (i)  Geographical area of the district
 

        (ii)  Forest area of the district
 

        (iii)  Total forest area diverted since 1980 with 
number of cases
 

       (iv)  Total compensatory afforestation stipulated in 
the district/division since 1980 on 
 

            (a) forest land including penal compensatory 
afforestation,
 

            (b) non-forest land.
 

        (v)  Progress of compensatory afforestation as on 
(date)...........................on—
 

            (a) forest land
 

            (b) non-forest land.      
 

9. Specific recommendations of the DCF for acceptance or 
otherwise of the proposal with reasons.           
 


                                                                              
Signature
 


Date.................................                                            
Name 
 


Place­................................                                            
(Official Seal)
 

 
 


PART III
 


(To be filled by the concerned Conservator of Forests)
 

10. Whether site, where the forest land involved is located 
has been inspected by concerned Conservator of Forests (Yes/No). If yes, the 
date of inspection &amp; observations made in form of inspection note to be 
enclosed.
 

11. Whether the concerned Conservator of Forests agree with 
the information given in Part­ B and the recommendations of Deputy Conservator 
of Forests.
 

12. Specific recommendation of concerned Conservator of 
Forests for acceptance or otherwise of the proposal with detailed reasons.
 


                                                                              
Signature
 


Date.................................                                            
Name 
 


Place­................................                                            
(Official Seal)
 

 
 

PART IV
 

(To be filled in by the 
Nodal Officer or Principal Chief Conservator of 
 

Forests or Head of Forest 
Department)
 

13. Detailed opinion and specific recommendation of the State 
Forest Department for acceptance of otherwise of the proposal with remarks.
 

(While giving opinion, the adverse comments made by concerned 
Conservator of Forests or Deputy Conservator of Forests should be categorically 
reviewed and critically commented upon).             
 


                                                                              
Signature
 


Date.................................                                            
Name &amp; Designation 
 


Place................................                                            
(Official Seal)
 

 
 

PART V
 

(To be filled in by the 
Secretary in charge of Forest Department or by  

any other authorised officer of the State Government not  

below the rank of an Under Secretary)
 

14. Recommendation of the State Government:
 

(Adverse comments made by any officer or authority in Part B 
or Part C or Part D above should be specifically commented upon)           
 


                                                                              
Signature
 


Date­.................................                                            
Name &amp; Designation 
 


Place................................                                            
(Official Seal)
 


INSTRUCTIONS (for Part I):
 

1. The project authorities may annex a copy of the approved 
project/plan in addition to filling col. 2 (i), e.g., IBM approved mining 
plan for major minerals/CMPDI plan with subsidence analysis reports, etc.
 

2. Map has to be in original duly authenticated jointly by 
project authorities and concerned DCF—Col. 2 (ii).
 

3. In case the same company/individual has taken forest land 
for similar project in the State, a brief detail of all such approvals/leases be 
given as an enclosure along with current status of the projects.
 

4. Item-wise requirement (Col. 3) should be separately shown 
for broken up and fresh areas. 
 

5. The latest clarifications issued by the Ministry under 
Forest (Conservation) Act, 1980 may be kept in mind. In case such information do 
not fit in the given columns, the same shall be annexed separately.        
 

GENERAL INSTRUCTIONS­:
 

1. On receipt of proposal, Nodal Officer shall issue a receipt 
to the user agency indicating therein the name of the proposal, user agency, 
area in hectare, serial number and date of receipt.
 

2. If the space provided above is not sufficient to specify 
any information, please attach separate details/documents.
 

3. While forwarding the proposal to the Central Government, 
complete details on all aspects of the case as per Form prescribed above read 
with the clarifications issued by the Ministry of Environment and Forests, 
Government of India, New Delhi should be given. Incomplete or deficient 
proposals shall not be considered and shall be returned to the State Government 
in original.
 

4. The State Government shall submit the proposal to the 
Central Government within stipulated time limits. In case of delay while 
forwarding, the reasons for the same to be given in the forwarding/covering 
letter.
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>