<act><title>


The Works of Licensees Rules, 20061</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Works of Licensees Rules, 2006. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “The Act” means the Electricity Act, 
    2003;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “occupier” of any building or land 
    means a person in lawful occupation of that building or land.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All other 
    words and expression used herein and not defined in these rules, shall have 
    the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Licensee 
    to carry out works.—
<section><number>1</number> A licensee 
    may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    carry out works, lay down or place any 
    electric supply line or other works in, through, or against, any building, 
    or on, over or under any land whereon, whereover or whereunder any electric 
    supply-line or works has not already been lawfully laid down or placed by 
    such licensee, with the prior consent of the owner or occupier of any 
    building or land;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    fix any support of overhead line or any 
    stay or strut required for the purpose of securing in position any support 
    of an overhead line on any building or land or having been so fixed, may 
    alter such support:  
 
     Provided that in case where the owner or 
    occupier of the building or land raises objections in respect of works to be 
    carried out under this rule, the licensee shall obtain permission in writing 
    from the District Magistrate or the Commissioner of Police or any other 
    officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, for carrying out 
    the works:  
 
     Provided further that if at any time, the 
    owner or occupier of any building or land on which any works have been 
    carried out or any support of an overhead line, stay or strut has been fixed 
    shows sufficient cause, the District Magistrate or the Commissioner of 
    Police, or the officer authorised may by order in writing direct for any 
    such works, support, stay or strut to be removed or altered.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When making 
    an order under sub-rule (1), the District Magistrate or the Commissioner of 
    Police or the officer so authorised, as the case may be, shall fix, after 
    considering the representations of the concerned persons, if any, the amount 
    of compensation or of annual rent, or of both, which should in his opinion 
    be paid by the licensee to the owner or occupier.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every order 
    made by a District Magistrate or a Commissioner of Police or an authorised 
    officer under sub-rule (1) shall be subject to revision by the Appropriate 
    Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing 
    contained in this rule shall effect the powers conferred upon any licensee 
    under section 164 of the Act.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Works 
    affecting streets, railway, tramway, canal or waterway.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the exercise of any of the powers of a licensee in relation to the 
    execution of any works involves the placing of any works in, under, over, 
    along or across any street, part of a street, railway, tramway, canal or 
    waterway, the licensee shall serve upon the person responsible for the 
    repair of the street or part of a street (hereinafter referred to as “the 
    repairing authority”) or upon the person for the time being entitled to work 
    the railway, tramway, canal or waterway (hereinafter referred to as ‘’works 
    authority”), as the case may be, a notice in writing, not less than 15 days 
    before commencing the execution of the works describing the proposed works, 
    together with a section and plan thereof on a scale sufficiently large to 
    show clearly the details of the proposed works, and not in any case smaller 
    than one inch to eight feet vertically and sixteen inches to the mile 
    horizontally and intimating the manner in which, and the time at which, it 
    is proposed to interfere with or alter any existing works, and shall, upon 
    being required to do so by the repairing authority or works authority, as 
    the case may be, from time to time give such further information in relation 
    thereto as may be desired.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    repairing authority intimates to the licensee that it disapproves of such 
    works, section or plan giving reasons for disapproval, or approves thereof 
    subject to amendment, the licensee may, unless settled by an agreement, 
    appeal to the Appropriate Commission within one week of receiving such 
    intimation, whose decision, after considering the reasons given by the 
    repairing authority for its action, shall be final.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    repairing authority fails to give notice in writing of its approval or 
    disapproval to the licensee within 15 days of the receipt of the notice, it 
    shall be deemed to have approved of the works, section and plan, and the 
    licensee, after giving not less than forty-eight hours’ notice in writing to 
    the repairing authority, may proceed to carry out the works in accordance 
    with the notice and the section and plan served under sub-rule (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the 
    works authority disapproves of such works, section or plan giving reasons 
    for disapproval, or approves thereof subject to amendment, he may, within 15 
    days after the service of the notice under sub-rule (1) of rule 5, serve a 
    requisition upon the licensee demanding that any question in relation to the 
    works or to compensation, or to the obligations of the works authority to 
    others in respect thereof, shall be determined, unless settled by agreement, 
    by the Appropriate Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where no 
    requisition has been served by the works authority upon the licensee within 
    the time period provided under sub-rule (4), the works authority shall be 
    deemed to have approved of the works, section and plan, and in that case, or 
    where after the matter has been determined by the Appropriate Commission, 
    the works may, upon payment or securing of compensation, be executed 
    according to the notice and the section and plan, subject to such 
    modifications as may have been determined by the Appropriate Commission or 
    agreed upon between the parties.  
 
Explanation.—In 
    sub-rules (1) to (5), the word “works” includes a service line in, under, 
    over, along or across a railway even if such line is immediately attached or 
    intended to be immediately attached to a distributing main, but does not 
    include any other service line so attached or intended to be so attached to 
    a distributing main, or works which consist of the repair, renewal or 
    amendment of existing works of which the character or position is not to be 
    altered.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    works to be executed consist of the laying of any underground service line 
    immediately attached, or intended to be immediately attached, to a 
    distributing main, the licensee shall give to the repairing authority or the 
    works authority, as the case may be, not less than forty-eight hours’ notice 
    in writing of his intention to execute such works.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where the 
    works to be executed consist of the repair, renewal or amendment of existing 
    works of which the character or position is not to be altered, the licensee 
    shall, except in cases of emergency, give to the repairing authority, or to 
    the works authority, as the case may be, not less than forty-eight hours’ 
    notice in writing of his intention to execute such works, and, on the expiry 
    of such notice, such works shall be commenced forthwith and shall be carried 
    on with all reasonable despatch, and, if possible, both by day and by night 
    until completed.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Repairs 
    and works during emergency.—The 
    licensee may, in case of emergency due to the breakdown of an underground 
    electric supply-line, after informing the repairing authority or the works 
    authority, as the case may be, of his intention to do so, place an overhead 
    line without complying with the provisions of rule 4:  
 
Provided that 
    such overhead line shall be used only until the defect in the underground 
    electric supply-line can be made good, and in no case (unless with the 
    written consent of the repairing authority, works authority or occupier as 
    the case may be) for a period exceeding six weeks, and shall be removed as 
    soon as may be after such defect is removed.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Procedure 
    for carrying out other works near sewers, pipes or other electric lines or 
    works.—
<section><number>1</number> The licensee or any 
    duly authorised person, as the case may be (hereinafter in this rule 
    referred to as “the operator”), shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    where the licensee requires to dig or 
    sink any trench for laying down any new electric supply-lines or other 
    works, near to which any sewer, drain, water-course or work under the 
    control of the State Government or of any local authority, or any pipe, 
    syphon, electric supply-line or other work belonging to any duly authorised 
    person, has been lawfully placed; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where any duly authorised person is 
    required to dig or sink any trench for laying down or constructing any new 
    pipes or other works, near to which any electric supply-lines or works of a 
    licensee have been lawfully placed,  
 
unless it is otherwise agreed upon between the 
    parties interested or in case of sudden emergency, give to the State 
    Government or local authority, or to such duly authorised person or to the 
    licensee, as the case may be (hereinafter in this rule referred to as “the 
    owner”), not less than forty-eight hours’ notice in writing before 
    commencing to dig or sink the trench and the owner shall have the right to 
    be present during the execution of the work, which shall be executed to the 
    reasonable satisfaction of the owner.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    operator finds it necessary to undermine, but not to alter, the position of 
    any pipe, electric supply-line or work, he shall support it in position 
    during the execution of the work, and before completion shall provide a 
    suitable and proper foundation for it where so undermined.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    operator (being the licensee) lays any electric supply-line across, or so as 
    to be liable to touch, any pipes, lines or service-pipes or service-lines 
    belonging to any duly authorised person or to any person supplying, 
    transmitting or using energy under the Act, he shall not, except with the 
    written consent of such person and in accordance with the regulations on 
    safety as specified under section 53 of the Act, lay his electric 
    supply-lines so as to come into contact with any such pipes, lines or 
    service-pipes or service-lines.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the 
    operator makes default in complying with any of the provisions of this rule, 
    he shall make full compensation for any loss or damage incurred by reason 
    thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where any 
    difference or dispute arises under this rule, the matter shall be determined 
    by the Appropriate Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    licensee is a local authority, the references in this rule to the local 
    authority and to sewers, drains, water-courses or works under its control 
    shall not apply.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Alteration of the position of pipes, electric line, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any licensee may alter the position of any pipe (not forming part of a local 
    authority’s main sewer), or of any wire under or over any place which he is 
    authorised to open or break up, if such pipe or wire is likely to interfere 
    with the exercise of his powers under the Act; and any person may alter the 
    position of any electric supply-lines or works of a licensee under or over 
    any such place as aforesaid, if such electric supply-lines or works are 
    likely to interfere with the lawful exercise of any powers vested in him.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    licensee or other person desiring to make the alteration, unless otherwise 
    agreed, shall, not less than one month before commencing any 
    alteration, serve upon the person for the time being entitled to the pipe, 
    wire, electric supply-lines or works, as the case may be (hereinafter in 
    this rule referred to as “the owner”), a notice in writing, describing the 
    proposed alteration, together with a section and plan thereof on a scale 
    sufficiently large to show clearly the details of the proposed works, and 
    not in any case smaller than one inch to eight feet vertically and sixteen 
    inches to the mile horizontally, and intimating the time when it is to be 
    commenced, and shall subsequently give such further information in relation 
    thereto as the owner may desire.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The owner 
    may, within fourteen days after the service of the notice, section and plan, 
    serve upon the operator a requisition to the effect that any question 
    arising upon the notice, section or plan, shall, unless settled by 
    agreement, be determined by Appropriate Commission, and thereupon the matter 
    shall be determined by the Appropriate Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Appropriate Commission to whom a reference is made under sub-rule (3), shall 
    have regard to any duties or obligations which the owner is under, and may 
    require the operator to execute any temporary or other works so as to avoid, 
    as far as possible, interference therewith.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where no 
    requisition is served upon the operator under sub-rule (3) within the time 
    limit, or where such a requisition has been served and the matter has been 
    settled by agreement or determined by the Appropriate Commission, the 
    alteration may, upon payment or securing of any compensation accepted or 
    determined by the Appropriate Commission, be executed in accordance with the 
    notice, section and plan and subject to such modifications agreed upon 
    between the parties or as may have been determined by the Appropriate 
    Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    operator desiring to make the alteration makes default in complying with any 
    of these provisions, he shall make full compensation for any loss or damage 
    incurred by reason thereof, and, where any difference or dispute arises as 
    to the amount of such compensation, the matter shall be determined by the 
    Appropriate Commission.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where the 
    owner or occupier desires to carry out certain works himself,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    he may, at least ten days before the 
    operator desiring to make the alteration of pipes or wires is entitled to 
    commence the alteration, serve upon the operator a statement in writing to 
    the effect that he desires to execute the alteration himself and requires 
    the operator to give such security for the repayment of any expenses as may 
    be agreed upon or, in default of agreement, determined by the Appropriate 
    Commission;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    where a statement is served upon the 
    operator under clause (i), he shall, not less than forty-eight hours before 
    the execution of the alteration is required to be commenced, furnish such 
    security and serve upon the owner a notice in writing intimating the time 
    when the alteration is required to be commenced, and the manner in which it 
    is required to be made; and thereupon the owner may proceed to execute the 
    alteration as required by the operator;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    where the owner declines to comply, 
    or does not, within the time and in the manner prescribed by a notice served 
    upon him under clause (ii), comply with the notice, the operator may himself 
    execute the alteration;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    all expenses incurred by the owner in 
    complying with a notice served upon him by the operator under clause (ii) 
    may be recovered by him from the operator.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Works not 
    repairable by the Appropriate Government, licensee or local authority.—The 
    licensee shall open or break up any street not repairable by the Central 
    Government or the State Government or a local authority only with the 
    written consent of the person by whom the street is repairable or with the 
    written consent of the Appropriate Government:  
 
Provided that 
    the Appropriate Government shall not give any such consent as aforesaid, 
    until the licensee has given notice by advertisement or otherwise as that 
    Government may direct, and within such period as that Government may fix in 
    this behalf, to the person above referred to, and until all representations 
    or objections received in accordance with the notice have been considered by 
    that Government.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Procedure 
    for fencing, guarding, lighting and other safety measures relating to works 
    and immediate reinstatement of streets, railways, sewers, drains or tunnels.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any person, in exercise of any of the powers conferred by or under 
    these rules opens or breaks up the soil or pavement of any street, railway 
    or tramway, or any sewer, drain or tunnel, he shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    immediately cause the part opened or 
    broken up to be fenced and guarded and fix caution boards to alert traffic;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    cause a light or lights, sufficient for 
    the warning of passengers before sunset, to be set up and maintained until 
    sunrise against or near the part opened or broken up;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    make suitable arrangements for smooth 
    flow of traffic;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    fill in the ground and reinstate and 
    make good the soil or pavement, or the sewer, drain or tunnel, opened or 
    broken up with all reasonable speed, and carry away the rubbish occasioned 
    by such opening or breaking up; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    after reinstating and making good the 
    soil or pavement, or the sewer, drain or tunnel broken or opened up, keep 
    the same in good repair for three months and for any further period, not 
    exceeding nine months, during which subsidence continues.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    person fails to comply with any of the provisions of sub-rule (1), the 
    person having the control or management of the street, railway, tramway, 
    sewer, drain or tunnel in respect of which the default has occurred, may 
    cause to be executed the work which the defaulter has delayed or omitted to 
    execute, and may recover from him the expenses incurred in such execution.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any 
    difference or dispute arises as to the amount of the expenses incurred under 
    sub-rule (2), the matter shall be determined by the Appropriate Commission.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Avoidance of public nuisance, environmental damage and unnecessary damage to 
    the public and private property by such works.—The 
    licensee shall, while carrying out works, ensure that such works do not 
    cause public nuisance, environmental damage and unnecessary damage to the 
    public or private property.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Manner 
    of deposit of amount for restoration of railways, tramways, waterways etc.—The 
    licensee shall deposit the amount for restoration of railways, tramways, 
    waterways etc. under these rules by means of demand draft in favour of the 
    officer-in-charge of the maintenance of the works concerned.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Manner 
    of restoration of property affected by such works and maintenance thereof.—The 
    licensee shall carry out the restoration of property affected by works and 
    undertake necessary maintenance thereof for one month.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Determination and payment of compensation to affected persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the licensee makes default in complying with any of the provisions of 
    these rules, he shall make full compensation for any loss or damage incurred 
    by reason thereof to the person affected, as may be determined by the 
    District Magistrate or by any other officer authorised by the State 
    Government in this behalf, if not agreed mutually between the parties 
    concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    difference and dispute arises as to the amount of compensation determined 
    under sub-rule (1), the matter shall be determined by the Appropriate 
    Commission.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Procedure for deposit of compensation payable by the licensee and furnishing 
    of security.—
<section><number>1</number> The amount of 
    compensation payable by the licensee under these rules shall be deposited by 
    means of demand draft.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    security required to be furnished under these rules shall be in the form of 
    Bank Guarantee from a Scheduled Bank or in any other form as may be notified 
    by the Appropriate Government from time to time.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Determination of dispute or difference by the Appropriate Commission.—When 
    a matter is brought to the Appropriate Commission for determination under 
    these rules, the matter shall be determined by the Appropriate Commission 
    within a period of thirty days and after hearing the parties concerned.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Service 
    of notice etc.—Whenever a notice 
    or intimation is required to be served upon a person under these rules, the 
    procedure provided under section 171 of the Act and rules made thereunder 
    shall be followed.
  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>