<act> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 19391
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title.—These 
rules may be called the Insurance Rules, 1939.
 
 


</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules,—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  “the Act” means the Insurance 
Act, 1938 (4 of 1938);
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  “ the Bank” means the Reserve 
Bank of India;
 
 

1[(iii)  “Bombay area” means the area 
comprising the State of Maharashtra, Gujarat and Madhya Pradesh and 

2[the Union Territories 
of Goa, 
Daman and Diu, and Dadar and Nagar Haveli]; ]
 
 

3[(iv)  “Calcutta area” means the area 
comprising the States of Assam, Bihar, Manipur, Meghalaya, Orissa, West Bengal, 
Sikkim and Tripura and the Tuensang district in the State of Nagaland and the 
Union Territories of Arunachal Pradesh, Mizoram and Andaman and Nicobar Island;]
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  “Delhi area” means the area 
comprising the States of Jammu and Kashmir, Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Punjab, 
Rajasthan and Uttar Pradesh and the
Union Territories 
of Delhi and Chandigarh;
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  “Madras area” means the area 
comprising the States of Andhra Pradesh, Karnataka, Kerala, and Tamil Nadu, and 
the Union Territories of Pondicherry and Lakshadweep; and 
 </section><section>
      <number>vii</number>  words used but not defined in 
these rules have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Qualifications of 
actuaries.—Any 
person signing as actuary under the Act shall be a Fellow of the Institute of 
Actuaries, London, or a Fellow of the Faculty of Actuaries in Scotland 

1[or a Fellow of 
the Actuarial Society of India]:
 
Provided that where 
application is made to the Controller of Insurance and it is shown to his 
satisfaction that the employment of an Associate of such Faculty of Actuaries,


1[or of such 
Actuarial Society,] or of any other person having actuarial knowledge for any 
specified purpose is expedient in order to enable an insurer or a provident 
society to carry out any of his or its obligations under the Act, the Controller 
of Insurance may grant the application and permit such person to sign as actuary 
for the specified purpose, subject to such conditions and restrictions as the 
Controller or Insurance thinks fit to impose.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
[Omitted]
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Deposits with the Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Deposits made in pursuance of the Act shall be held by that office of the Bank 
(hereinafter referred to as the appropriate Indian office) in whose area of 
administration the principal office in the State of the depositor is situated:
 
Provided that deposits in 
sterling securities shall be held by the London office of the Bank on behalf of 
the appropriate Indian office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Deposits in sterling 
securities shall be sent by the depositor with a covering letter to the manager 
of the London office of the Bank, and shall not be brought on the books of the 
appropriate Indian office until the receipt of an intimation in Form I from the 
London office.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Deposits, other than 
deposits in sterling securities, shall be sent by the depositor with a covering 
letter to the manager of the appropriate Indian office of the Bank.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Securities shall be 
duly transferred to the Bank by the depositor.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Upon receipt of the 
intimation referred to in sub-rule (2) or of a deposit under sub-rule (3) the 
appropriate Indian office of the Bank shall send—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a certificate in Form II to the 
depositor; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  a statement in Form III to the 
Controller of Insurance:
 
Provided that, if the Bank 
is not satisfied as to the validity of the title of the depositor to the 
securities, it may return them to him with the request that they shall first be 
renewed or that such other measures as may be necessary shall be taken to clear 
the title.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The market value of 
sterling securities held by the Bank shall be converted at 1s. 6d. to the 
rupees.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Changes in deposits.—When 
the form or amount of a deposit is changed by reason of subsequent deposit, a 
substitution or a payment under sub-section (9) or sub-section (10) of section 7 
of the Act or a sale or investment under sub-section (9A) of the said section, 
the Bank shall, within two weeks from the entry of such change in the books of 
the Bank, send a fresh certificate and a fresh statement of the nature, and in 
the manner, described in clauses 
<section><number>a</number> and (b) of sub-rule (5) of rule 5.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Maturing of deposits.—When 
a security in deposit matures, or when any yield on such security ceases to 
accrue, the Bank shall not be bound to inform the depositor; but, upon receipt 
of a requisition from the depositor made in writing and in accordance with the 
provision of the Act, the Bank shall, within six weeks of such a receipt, 
collect the discharge value and hold the amount in cash to the credit of the 
depositor or invest it in securities specified by the depositor.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Interest and dividends 
on deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No interest shall be paid on cash deposits.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Interest or dividends 
on sterling securities shall, at the option of the depositor, be either paid in 
London by the London office of the Bank after deduction of a commission of 5s. 
on every sum of £100 or part thereof, or remitted by the London 
office of the Bank to the appropriate Indian office of the bank at the 
telegraphic transfer rate on India prevailing on the 
date of realisation of the interest or dividends.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The appropriate Indian 
office of the Bank shall remit interest or dividends on securities other than 
sterling securities, and amounts if any, received from the London office of the 
Bank under sub-rule (2) without delay to the depositor at an office in India to 
be specified by the depositor,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  if the office so specified is at 
a place where there is in office of the Bank or a branch of the Imperial Bank of 
India, by means of a Government draft; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in other cases, by a Security 
Deposit Interest Payment Draft on the nearest Government Treasury;
 
after deduction of a commission or annas four 
on every sum of Rs. 100 or part thereof.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Withdrawals, etc., of 
deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Withdrawals and payments from deposits and purchases of securities shall not be 
made save in accordance with the provisions of the Act and on receipt by the 
Bank of a requisition in writing and in accordance with the provisions of the 
Act from the depositor, a liquidator acting in accordance with law or a court of 
competent jurisdiction, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Bank shall not be 
bound, in pursuance of sub-rule (1), to return securities actually deposited, 
but may substitute therefor new scrip of securities of the same description and 
amount.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Bank shall be 
entitled to charge, for the purpose or sale of securities, any brokerage payable 
by the Bank in respect of such purchase or sale.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Information as regards 
deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Controller of Insurance shall be entitled, free of any fee or inspect or to 
require from the Bank any information relating to any security deposited with 
the Bank under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Bank shall, if so 
required, furnish the Controller of Insurance, or any person authorized by him 
in that behalf in writing with a copy of any entry in any register or book 
maintained by the Bank relating to any deposit made with the bank under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Bank shall publish 
as soon as may be after the 1st January in each year in such manner as the 
Central Government may direct a list in Form IV of deposits made with it under 
the Act, as at 31st December of the preceding year.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>10A</number> Pakistan securities.—Securities 
guaranteed fully as regards principal and interest by a Provincial Government in 
Pakistan or charged on the revenues of any part of that Dominion and debentures 
or other securities for money issued by or on behalf of the trustees of the Port 
of Karachi shall be recognized, in the case of insurers incorporated or 
domiciled in India, as approved securities—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  for the purposes of sections 7, 
98 or 73, if such securities had been deposited with the Bank in pursuance of 
the Act before the 15th day of August, 1947, and continue to be so deposited 
with the Bank since that date, and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  for the purposes of sections 27 
and 27A, if such securities had been acquired by an insurer or a provident 
society before the 15th day of August, 1947, and continue to be held since that 
date by the insurer or the provident society.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>10B</number> Assets deemed to be 
approved investments.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
For the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 27 of the Act, the following 
assets shall be deemed to be assets invested or kept invested in approved 
investments specified in sub-section (1) of section 27A of the Act—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  interest, dividend and rents 
(outstanding and accrued);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  cash in hand and with banks 
(other than banks in liquidation) in current and collection accounts;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  bills receivable;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  value of furniture, fittings, 
machinery, stationery and library but not exceeding Rs. 10,000 or one per cent 
of the sum referred to in sub-section (1) of section 27 of the Act, whichever is 
greater;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  value of motor cars but not 
exceeding Rs. 20,000 or one-half per cent of the sum referred to in sub-section 
(1) of section 27 of the Act, whichever is greater;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  stamps on hand;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  amount of income-tax directed by 
the income-tax authority, to be refunded;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  temporary advances granted to 
chief, special and insurance agents to the extent permitted under clause (b) of 
sub-section (3) of section 29 of the Act.
 

2[(2) (i) For the 
purposes of sub-section (2) of section 27B of the Act, the following assets 
shall be deemed to be assets invested or kept invested in approved investments 
specified in sub-section (1) of that section, namely:—
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>a</number>  interest, dividend and rents 
(outstanding and accrued);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  cash in hand and with banks 
(other than banks in liquidation) in current and collection accounts;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  bills receivable;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  amounts due from other insurers 
in respect of reinsurance recoveries and deposits or reserves with other 
insurers in respect of treaties for reinsurances as to be accepted.
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> In respect of 
insurance specified in clause (c) of sub-section (16) of section 27B of the Act, 
three-fourths of the value of the following assets shall also be deemed to be 
approved investments specified in sub-section (1) of section 27B of the Act, 
namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
       <number>a</number>  motor cars,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>b</number>  stamps on hand,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>c</number>  amounts of income-tax directed by 
the income-tax authorities to be refunded.]
 
 




</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>10C</number> Returns of 
investments and changes in investments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The return to be furnished under sub-section (1) of section 28A of the Act shall 
show all the investments made out of the controlled fund and subsisting as at 
the 31st day of December of the preceding year and shall be in Form IVA:
 

1[Provided that in 
the case of the Life Insurance Corporation of India, 
the aforesaid return shall show the said investments subsisting as at the last 
day of the preceding financial year and shall be in Form IVAAA.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The return to be 
furnished under sub-section (2) of section 28A of the Act shall be in Form IVB


1[and in the case 
of the Life Insurance Corporation of India the said return 
shall be in Form IVBBB.]
 

2[(3) The return to 
be furnished under sub-section (1) of section 28B of the Act, shall show all the 
investments made out of the assets and subsisting as at the 31st day of December 
of the preceding year shall be in Form IVAA.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The return to be 
furnished under sub-section (2) of section 28B of the Act shall be in Form IVBB.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>10D</number> Charging Assets.—An 
insurer may subject the assets forming his controlled fund, not being securities 
kept invested in pursuance of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 27, to a charge in 
favour of a banking company for the purpose of raising an over-draft, and 
investing the money so raised:
 
Provided that the assets 
charged do not exceed in value ten per cent of the controlled fund and the 
charge is created for a period not exceeding six months.
 

1[(2) For the 
purpose of sub-section (11) of section 27B the charge created in favour of one 
or more banking companies in respect of assets offered as security for any loan 
taken for purposes of any investment or for payment of claims shall be subject 
to the condition that any loan taken against such assets shall be repaid within 
a period of three months.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Prospectuses and 
tables.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
person shall supply or exhibit any prospectus or table of premium rates to any 
other person with a view to the issue of a policy of insurance unless a such 
prospectus or table includes,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a description of the contingency 
or contingencies to be covered by insurance and the class or classes of lives or 
property eligible for insurance under the terms of such prospectus or table;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  a full statement of the 
circumstances, if any, in which rebates of the premiums quoted in the prospectus 
or table shall be allowed on the effecting or renewal of a policy, together with 
the rates of rebate applicable to each case; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  a copy of section 41 of the Act 
but not including the proviso to sub-section (1) thereof.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
sub-rule (1) shall be deemed to have been complied with if to every such 
prospectus or table of premium rate supplied or exhibited after the date of 
commencement of the Act is attached in the form of an addendum a statement 
containing so much of the matters referred to in sub-rule (1) as is not already 
included in the said prospectuses or tables, but every prospectus and table of 
premium rates printed after the coming into force of the Act shall have the 
matters referred to in the said clauses incorporated therein.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Proposal Forms.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be clearly indicated—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in every proposal form in the 
case of life insurance; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in the document, if any, forming 
the basis of the contract in the case of any other form of insurance, that 
rebate of premiums shall be allowed only in accordance with the details given in 
the prospectus or table of premium rates or, as the case may be, the relevant 
document, and that an offer or acceptance of any other rebate shall be an 
offence under section 41 of the Act.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of 
sub-rule (2) of rule 11 shall apply mutatis mutandis to proposal forms, 
except that, where an addendum is attached to a proposal form, it shall also be 
signed by the person who signs the proposal form.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>12A</number> List of insurers.—The 
Controller shall cause to be published in the Gazette of India a list of the 
members and associate members of the Life Insurance and General Insurance 
Councils of the Insurance Association of India once every year in the month of 
January.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>12B</number> Constituencies of 
insurers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Members of the Insurance Association of India who are insurers carrying on life 
insurance business and having premium income in such business of more than three 
lakhs of rupees in the preceding year shall elect four individuals as members of 
the Executive Committee of the Life Insurance Council of the Insurance 
Association of India in the following manner:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  are individual by such members as 
have their head offices in the Calcutta area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  two individuals by such members 
as have their head offices in the Bombay area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  one individual by such members as 
have their head offices in the Delhi and Madras areas, the members in each area 
alternately electing the individual, the first election being held in the Delhi 
area.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Members of the 
Insurance Association of India who are insurers carrying on general insurance 
business and having a premium income in such business of less than three lakhs 
of rupees in the preceding year shall elect four individuals members of the 
Executive Committee of the Life Insurance Council of the Insurance Association 
of India in the following manner:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  one individual by such members as 
have their head offices in the Calcutta area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  one individual by such members as 
have their head offices in the Bombay area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  one individual by such members as 
have their head offices in the Madras area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  one individual by such members as 
have their head offices in the Delhi area.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Members of the 
Insurance Association of India who are insurers carrying on general insurance 
business shall elect eight individuals as members of the Executive Committee of 
the General Insurance Council of the Insurance Association of India in the 
following manner:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  one individual authorized to 
stand as a candidate by a member having his head office in the Calcutta area and 
whose premium income in such business in the preceding year exceeded ten lakhs 
of rupees and elected to the Committee by such members as have their head 
offices in the Calcutta area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  one individual authorized to 
stand as a candidate by a member having his head office in the Calcutta area and 
whose premium income in such business in the preceding year did not exceed ten 
lakhs of rupees and elected to the Committee by such members as have their head 
offices in the Calcutta area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  two individuals each of whom is 
authorized to stand as a candidate by a member having his head office in the 
Bombay area and whose premium in such business in the preceding year exceeded 
five lakhs of rupees and elected to the Committee by such members as have their 
head offices in the Bombay area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  two individuals each of whom is 
authorized to stand as a candidate by a member having his head office in the 
Bombay area and whose premium in such business in the preceding year did not 
exceed five lakhs of rupees and elected to the Committee by such members as have 
their head offices in the Bombay area;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  one individual elected to the 
Committee by such members as have their head offices in the Madras area;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  one individual elected to the 
Committee by such members as have their head offices in the Delhi area.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> For the purpose of 
this rule if any dispute arises as to which area as insurer belongs, or as to 
the premium income of an insurer, the Controller shall decide the question and 
his decision shall be final.
 
Explanation.—In 
this rule,—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  “preceding year” means the 
calendar year preceding the calendar year in which the election takes place;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  “premium income” means the 
gross direct premium income of the insurer without taking into account premium 
income on re-insurance accepted or ceded.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>12C</number> Duties of Dissolved 
Executive Committees.—When 
the Executive Committee of the Life Insurance Council or of the General 
Insurance Council is dissolved, the outgoing members thereof who continue to 
hold office until a new Executive Committee is constituted, shall be entitled to 
discharge the following duties in the meantime:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  keep and maintain up-to-date a 
copy of the list of all members and associate members of the Life Insurance 
Council or the General Insurance Council, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  supervise the work of officers 
and servants employed by the Committee;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  collect the prescribed fees; and
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  help the Chairman and the 
Secretary to conduct the necessary elections to the new Executive Committee.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>12D</number> Joint Meetings of 
Executive Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a request is received by the Central Government from—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the Controller of Insurance, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  six individuals who are members 
of either or both of the Executive Committees of the Life Insurance Council and 
the General Insurance Council, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  thirty insurers,
 
that a joint meeting of the Executive 
Committees should consider a matter specified in the request, the Central 
Government may, on being satisfied that the matter is one of common interest to 
the two Executive Committees, direct that a joint meeting of the two Executive 
Committees be convened to consider the matter.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall be the duty 
of the Chairmen of the two Executive Committees to convene, as soon as may be 
after the issue of the direction under preceding sub-rule a joint meeting of all 
the members of the two Executive Committees at such place and at such time and 
date as the two Chairmen may decide.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At such meeting, one 
of the two Chairmen shall be elected by the members present to preside and the 
matter referred to and no other matter shall be considered.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The meeting may be 
adjourned from time to time to be held not necessarily at the same place, with 
the consent of the members present for further consideration of the matter or 
for considering a report from any sub-committee appointed for the purpose by the 
members present, but minutes of each meeting shall be kept and a copy thereof 
shall be furnished to the Controller of Insurance immediately after the meeting.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Qualifications of 
elected directors of insurance companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person shall be eligible for election as a director of an insurance company 
under section 48 of the Act, if he holds one or more policies of life insurance 
issued by the company and satisfying the provisions of the said section and both 
the following requirements, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the policies shall insure either 
a total sum, including any bonuses that may have attached to them before the 
date of election, of not less than Rs. 3,000, where the company has at that date 
been carrying on life insurance business for not less than five years, or of not 
less than Rs. 1,000 in other cases, or annuities on human life of a total amount 
of not lees than Rs. 250 per annum without regard to the age of the company, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  where the company has been 
carrying on life insurance business for more than two years, all the policies 
held in compliance with clause (a) shall have been in force for not less than 
one, two or three years, according as the company has at the date of election 
been carrying on life insurance business for not more than five years, for more 
than five but not more than eight years, or for more than eight years:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government may, in respect of any insurer after taking into account the maximum 
sum assured permissible according to constitution or rules and regulations and 
other conditions, modify the above qualifications by fixing (i) for the sum 
insured or annuity, an amount lower than the corresponding amount mentioned in 
clause (a), or (ii) for the period, a period shorter than the one mentioned in 
clause (b), or (iii) both.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If at any date after 
election as a director, a person ceases to be a person holding one or more 
policies of life insurance satisfying the provisions of section 48 and both the 
requirements specified in sub-rule (1) he shall forthwith cease to be an elected 
director of the company.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Election of directors 
under section 48.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The election of directors under section 48 of the Act shall take place at a 
meeting (to be held at the place where the principal office of the company is 
situated or, with the prior consent and approval in writing of the Controller of 
Insurance, at any other place) of the holders of policies of life insurance 
issued by the company, who are eligible to vote at such election and the first 
such election shall be held as soon as possible after the said section becomes 
applicable.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Not less than three 
months before the meeting is to be held, there shall be intimation in a 
newspaper published in the English language and in a newspaper published in an 
Indian language circulating in the place where the principal office of the 
company is situated and, if there are policy-holders of the company residing in 
a State other than that in which the principal office of the company is 
situated, in a newspaper published in the English language and, if the company 
so desires, in a newspaper published in a principal language of the State, both 
being papers circulating in that State, a notice stating the number of directors 
to be elected at, and the time and place of, such meeting, which shall be fixed 
with a view to affording voters the fullest opportunities for attending, and 
informing policy-holders how to obtain admission to the meeting according to the 
manner hereinafter described. Such notice shall also set forth the 
qualifications which a person must possess in order to be eligible for election 
as a director, and shall invite applications from eligible persons prepared to 
accept office:
 
Provided that, where a 
company prints on its policies the qualifications of elected directors as set 
forth in rule 13, and issued, at least six months before the election, to all 
existing policy-holders whose policies do not contain a statement of those 
qualifications as modified up-to-date, a notice setting forth such modified 
qualifications, the notice to be published in newspapers in accordance with this 
sub-rule need not set forth those qualifications:
 
Provided further that a 
company may, in respect of one or more States instead of publishing the notice 
in newspapers, send it by post to every policy-holder residing therein.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The applications from 
eligible persons prepared to accept office as elected directors of the company 
shall be sent by registered post to the principal office of the company so as to 
reach it not less than two months before the date of the meeting. Such 
applications shall be made in the English language or in a principal language of 
the State in which the principal office of the company is situated. If the 
number of such applicants does not exceed the number of directors to be elected, 
all such applicants shall be deemed to have been elected as directors and it 
shall not be necessary to hold the meeting of policy-holders as previously 
announced. The company shall in that event inform the policy-holders forthwith 
by notice inserted in newspapers as in sub-rule (2), or by notice sent 
individually by post to those policy-holders who are eligible to vote and who 
apply for a certificate of admission under sub-rule (4) or by both methods of 
the names of persons elected as directors and of the cancellation of the 
meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>3A</number> An application sent 
under sub-rule (3) shall give the applicant’s name and address and the numbers 
of and amounts of the sums insured by the policies by virtue of which he claims 
to be eligible for election.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every policy-holder 
who desires to attend the meeting shall apply to the company for a certificate 
of admission, such application to reach the company not less than two months 
before the date of the meeting, and the company on being satisfied that the 
applicant holds a policy of life insurance issued by the company not less than 
six months before the date of election shall issue a certificate at least one 
month before the date of the meeting. Such certificate shall, if applied for by 
post, be sent only to the address of the policy-holder or if applied for in 
person be delivered only on production of the relevant policy and shall, in any 
case, be accompanied by a statement of the names and addresses of the eligible 
persons prepared to accept office whose applications have been received by the 
company under sub-rule (3). A certificate of admission shall not be 
transferable.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No person other than 
those whose presence is, in the opinion of the Chairman necessary for the 
conduct of the meeting shall be admitted to the meeting unless he produces the 
certificate of admission granted to him under sub-rule (4).
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The meeting shall be 
presided over by the Chairman for the time being of the Board of directors of 
the company, or in his absence by any director nominated by him, or in the 
absence of any such director by a Chairman elected by the policy-holders present 
at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Votes for the election 
of directors may be given at the meeting either personally or by proxy and in 
the manner hereinafter provided in this rule. The instrument appointing a proxy 
shall be in writing in Form IVC under the hand of the appointer in favour of a 
policy-holder, and shall be presented at the principal office of the company not 
less than one month before the date of the meeting. No policy-holder shall 
appoint more than one proxy irrespective of policies he holds.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every policy-holder 
present at the meeting shall be given one voting paper on his own behalf 
irrespective of the number of policies he holds and one voting paper in respect 
of each proxy, if any, which he holds. The number of votes to be given on each 
voting paper shall not exceed the number of directors to the elected and no more 
than one vote shall be given on each voting paper to any one candidate:
 
Provided that a 
policy-holder may, if he prefers, vote on one voting paper in respect of all the 
proxies he holds. In that event, the number of votes to be given on the voting 
paper shall not exceed the number of directors to be elected multiplied by the 
number of proxies held and the number of votes given to any one candidate on 
that paper shall not exceed the number of proxies held.
 </section><section>
<number>8A</number> If any policy-holder 
is a lunatic or an idiot, he may vote by his legal representative; and if any 
policy-holder is a minor he may vote by his legally appointed guardian, or any 
one of such guardians, if more than one.
 </section><section>
<number>8B</number> If a policy has been 
proposed for, and taken out jointly by, more than one person having insurable 
interest between them, each such person shall be entitled to vote as a holder of 
that policy.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The votes shall be 
counted by the company’s auditors if present in that capacity, or failing them 
by scrutineers appointed by the meeting, and working under the supervision of 
the Chairman. The result of the ballot shall be announced at the meeting and in 
the event of an equality of votes the election shall be decided by lot:
 
Provided that if the 
counting of votes is not likely to be completed by 7 p.m. on the date of the 
meeting, the Chairman may lock, seal and take charge of the ballot box in the 
presence of the meeting and postpone the counting of votes by not more than 48 
hours. The opening of the ballot box shall be done by the Chairman and the 
counting shall be carried out by the same persons as are specified in this 
sub-rule for this purpose within the said 48 hours after reasonable notice of 
the time and place where the counting is to take place has been given to the 
candidates but no others except those presence is necessary for the purpose of 
making the counting and the declaration. Each candidate or in his absence his 
authorized representative shall be allowed to be present to witness the opening 
and the counting. The result of the ballot shall then the communicated by notice 
published in newspapers as in sub-rule (2) or individually by post to all 
policy-holders who were present in person at the election or by both methods.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> For the purposes of 
sub-rule (3) of rule 15, a list shall be prepared of those of the unsuccessful 
candidates in whose favour any valid votes are cast in descending order of the 
number of such votes cast for each. If two more such candidates have an equal 
number of such votes cast for them, they shall be placed in the list in the 
alphabetical order of their applications under sub-rule (3). For the purposes of 
this sub-rule, no valid vote shall be deemed to be cast for a candidate if his 
own vote is the only vote cast for him.
 </section><section>
<number>10A</number> No election shall be 
held at any meeting convened under these rules unless a quorum of policy-holders 
holding certificates issued under sub-rule (4) is personally present at the time 
when the meeting proceeds to business. The number of such certificate holders 
who must personally be present to constitute a quorum shall be five times the 
number of directors to be elected at that meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>10B</number> If within half an 
hour from the time appointed for the meeting a quorum is not present, the 
meeting shall stand adjourned to the same day in the next week at the same time 
and place, if at the adjourned meeting a quorum is not present within half an 
hour from the time appointed for the meeting, the policy-holders present and 
holding certificates issued under sub-rule (4) shall be a quorum.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> An election held in 
accordance with this rule shall not be invalid merely by reason of the 
accidental omission to send any notice or other document to, or the non-receipt 
of any notice or other document by, any policy-holder, or of any other 
accidental irregularity or informality in the observance of the provisions of 
this rule.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Period of office of 
directors and filling of vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An election of directors under these rules (other than the first such election) 
shall be held not later than three years from the date of the last such 
election:
 
Provided that an election 
for the holding of which the latest date otherwise permissible under this 
sub-rule is a date in the year 1943 may be postponed to a date not later than 
the 31st December, 1944.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At every meeting of 
policy holders held in pursuance of sub-rule (1), all the directors elected or 
appointed under these rules shall retire, but any director so retiring shall, if 
he remains eligible under rule 13, be eligible for re-election.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the event of casual 
vacancy arising among the directors elected or appointed under these rules, the 
vacancy shall be filled by appointing the person highest in the list prepared 
under sub-rule (10) of rule 14, who remains eligible under rule 13 and is 
willing to act as a director.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person in the said 
list who is not appointed in his turn under sub-rule (3), either because he has 
ceased to be eligible under rule 13 or because of his unwillingness to act shall 
be removed from the list.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the event of there 
being no person available for appointment under sub-rule (3), the casual vacancy 
shall be filled by the remaining directors (if not less than two in number) 
elected or appointed under these rules by appointing a person eligible under 
rule 13, or if such directors (or a majority of them) are unable to agree upon a 
person to be appointed, the appointment shall be decided by lot from amongst the 
persons eligible under rule 13 who have been considered for the appointment by 
the said remaining directors.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In the event of there 
being only one or no such remaining director, the casual vacancy shall be filled 
by an election in accordance with these rules to be held not later than six 
months from the date on which the vacancy occurred, unless the company secures 
from the Central Government within two months from the said date an exemption 
for that purpose from the provisions of section 48 of the Act under clause (b) 
of sub-section (3) thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any person appointed 
or elected to fill a casual vacancy shall be subject to retirement at the same 
time as would have been the director in whose place he is appointed or elected.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> An election held in 
pursuance of sub-rule (6) to fill a casual vacancy shall not be reckoned as an 
election for the purpose of sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Nothing in the rule 
shall be deemed to affect the application of Regulations 78 and 79 in Table A of 
the First Schedule to the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913)1, 
to directors elected or appointed otherwise than under these rules.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Licence fee for 
insurance agents and collection thereof.—The 
fee for obtaining or renewing a licence to act as an insurance agent shall be Rs.


1[15] provided that 
an additional fee of Rs. 

1[7] shall be paid 
if the application for the renewal of the licence does not reach the Controller 
at least thirty days before the date on which the licence ceases to remain in 
force.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16A</number> Issue of licences to 
insurance agents.—An 
applicant who desires to obtain or renew a licence to act as an insurance agent 
shall proceed as follows:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the applicant shall obtain from 
the Controller of Insurance a form of application for a licence which shall be,—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  in the case of an 
individual, Form V, or Form VA, if he applies for the grant of a licence for the 
first time or for the renewal of the licence held by him, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  in the case of a company or 
firm, Form VP, or Form VPA, if it applies for the grant of a licence for the 
first time or for the renewal of the licence held by it, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  in the case of a 
co-operative society or a Panchayat, Form VS, or Form VSA, if it applies for the 
grant of a licence for the first time or for the renewal of the licence held by 
it, as the case may be;
 
 

1[(iv) in the case of a society 
registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), Form VSS or 
Form VSSA, if it applies for the grant of a licence for the first time or for 
the renewal of the licence held by him, as the case may be.]
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>b</number>  He shall then send to the 
Controller of Insurance the completed application form with the fee which shall 
be paid in the form of stamps to the value of 

2[Rs. 15 or Rs. 22], as the case may 
be, and the stamp shall be affixed to the application in the proper place.
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  The Controller of Insurance or 
the officer authorized by him under sub-section (1) of section 42 of the Act, 
shall issue a licence after taking all reasonable steps to satisfy himself that 
the application is in order and that the applicant is not disqualified from 
holding a licence. No application shall be considered by the Controller of 
Insurance unless the particulars in Form VB, Form VPB, 

3[Form VSB or Form VSSB] as the case 
may be, have been filled in by the applicant.
 
In the case of—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  an individual, the licence shall 
be in Form VB;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  a company or firm, shall be in 
Form VPB;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  a co-operative society or a 
Panchayat, it shall be in Form VSB;
 
 

3[(iv)  a society registered under the 
Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), it shall be in Form VSSB];
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>d</number>  No application for the renewal of 
licence will be accepted if it reaches the Controller on or after the date on 
which the licence ceases to be in force:
 
Provided, however, that if 
an applicant desires that his application should be considered under the proviso 
to sub-section (3A) of section 42 of the Act, he shall forward along with such 
application a request to that effect, with stamps to the value of 

4[Rs. 75] affixed 
thereon and a statement of all the facts and particulars which are to be taken 
into consideration by the Controller for the purpose of examining whether undue 
hardship would be caused if no renewal of licence is granted:
 
Provided further that the 
applicant, if required to do so by the Controller, shall furnish documentary 
proof of any of the particulars or facts mentioned in the statement referred to 
above.
 
 






</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16B</number> Bona fide 
insurance agents for the purposes of section 41.—The 
conditions to be satisfied by an insurance agent to establish that he is a 
bona fide insurance agent reemployed by the insurer for the purposes of the 
proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 41 of the Act shall be the following, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  He must have secured policies on 
six different lives excluding his own.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  He must have been an insurance 
agent continuously from the time of his soliciting or procuring the first policy 
on each of such six lives or proposing for the policy on his own life, whichever 
is earlier, till the time when the policies on those six lives and the policy on 
his own life have all been issued.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16C</number> Fee for principal, 
chief and special agents.—The 
fee for obtaining or renewing a certificate to act as a principal agent or chief 
agent shall be Rs. 25 and the fee for obtaining or renewing a certificate to act 
as a special agent shall be Rs. 10:
 
Provided that an 
additional fee of Rs. 5 in the case of a principal agent or a chief agent, and 
Rs. 3 in the case of a special agent, shall be paid, if the application for 
renewal of the certificate reaches the Controller on or after the date on which 
the certificate ceases to be in force but within 12 months of the aforesaid 
date.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16D</number> Issue of certificates 
to principal, chief and special agents.—A 
person, who desires to obtain or renew a certificate to act as a principal 
agent, or chief agent or special agent, shall proceed as follows:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  He shall obtain from the 
Controller a form of application for a certificate which form shall be as 
prescribed in Form VC or Form VD. Form VC shall be used when an applicant 
applies for a certificate the first time, or for a fresh certificate, while Form 
VD shall be used when an applicant applies for the renewal of certificate 
already held by him. No application for the renewal of a certificate will be 
accepted if it reaches the Controller after a period of twelve months from the 
date on which the certificate ceases to be in force.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  He shall then send to the 
Controller the completed application form with stamps to the value of Rs. 25 or 
Rs. 30 or Rs. 10 or Rs. 13, as the case may be, affixed thereon in the proper 
place.
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  The controller or the officer 
authorized by him under sub-section (1) of section 42A of the Act shall, after 
taking all reasonable steps to satisfy himself that the application is in order 
and that the applicant is not disqualified from holding a certificate, issue a 
certificate in Form VE.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16E</number> Issue of duplicate 
licenses and certificates.—
<section><number>a</number> 
A person to whom a licence or a certificate has been issued 

1[under section 42 
or section 42A of the Act] shall, if such licence or certificate has been lost, 
destroyed or mutilated, submit to the Controller an application requesting the 
issue of a duplicate licence or certificate with a fee of Re. 1 in the case of a 
licence, and Rs. 2 in the case of a certificate, paid in the form of stamp duly 
affixed thereon and with a declaration giving full details regarding the issue 
and loss, destruction or mutilation of the licence or certificate, and the 
mutilated pieces, if any, shall be returned to the Controller with the said 
application.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The Controller, after 
satisfying himself that the original licence or certificate has been lost, 
destroyed, or mutilated, issue a duplicate licence in Form VB or Form VPB or 
Form VSB 

2[or Form VSSB] or 
a certificate in Form VE, as the case may be, with an endorsement thereon that 
it is a duplicate.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16F</number> Description of stamp.—Any 
fee specified in rules 16, 16A, 16C, 16D and 16E shall be paid in the form of 
“Government of India Insurance” stamps available from a Government treasury.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16G</number>
Allowance for unused stamps.—Where an applicant for licence or a 
certificate has inadvertently used ‘Government of India Insurance’ stamp of a 
greater value than is necessary or where no licence or certificate in respect of 
an application bearing such stamp has been issued, refund may be made of the 
excess of the necessary fee or of the value of the stamp, as the case may be, on 
such application.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>16H</number> Cancellation of 
licences or certificates.—Where 
the Controller cancels the licence of an insurance agent under sub-section (5) 
of section 42 or the certificate of a principal or chief or special agent under 
sub-section (4) of section 42A, he shall—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  inform all the officers 
authorized by him under sub-section (1) of section 42 or section 42A that the 
licence or the certificate, as the case may be, has been cancelled;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  require the person concerned to 
return the licence or certificate issued to him; and
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  cause the fact of cancellation to 
be published in the Gazette of India and in such State Gazettes or Gazette as he 
deems fit.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Declaration as to the 
nature of ownership of shares.—The 
declaration to be furnished by a transferee in pursuance of clause (b)
<section><number>i</number> of 
sub-section (4) of section 6A of the Act to a public company limited by shares 
having its registered office in the States and carrying on 

1[any class of] 
insurance businuess shall be in Form VF.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>17A</number> Declaration as to 
beneficial interest in shares.—The 
declaration to be made in pursuance of sub-section (5) of section 6A of the Act 
to a public company limited by shares having its registered office in the States 
and carrying on life-insurance business by a person who has any interest in any 
of its shares standing in the name of another person shall be in Form VG.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17AA</number> Form for 
declaration.—The 
declaration to be made in pursuance of sub-section (5) of section 6A of the Act 
to a public company limited by shares having its registered office in India and 
carrying on general insurance business by a person who has any interest in any 
of its shares standing in the name of another person shall be in Form VGG].
 
 



</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>17B</number> Disposal of shares by 
Administrator-General.—As 
soon as the Administrator-General of a State has taken charge of any shares of a 
public company vesting in him under sub-section (8) of section 6A of the Act he 
shall furnish full details of the shares of the Controller and he shall try, as 
soon as may be, to sell the shares, whether as a whole or in part or whether in 
the open market or by private sale, at a price not lower than the price fixed by 
the Controller who may vary the price fixed from time to time. The proceeds 
shall be handed over to such person as, in the opinion of the 
Administrator-General, is by law entitled thereto.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>17C</number> Statement of the 
bases of premiums.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The statement of the bases of premiums under sub-section (1) of section 40B of 
the Act shall be in Form VH.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In respect of premiums 
currently used by an insurer at the commencement of the Insurance (Amendment) 
Act, 1950, the statement of the bases of premiums certified by an actuary shall 
be furnished to the Controller within six months from such commencement.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A statement on the 
basis of premiums to be newly used after such commencement certified by an 
actuary shall be furnished to the Controller before such premiums are offered by 
the insurer to prospective policy-holders.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>17F</number> Head Office expenses.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The share of the Head Office expenses in the case of an insurer having his 
principal place of business outside India for the purposes of sections 40B and 
40C of the Act shall not be less than—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  in respect of life-insurance 
business 10 per cent of the first year’s premium as shown in the revenue 
account, and 1 per cent of the renewal premiums as shown in the revenue account 
in respect of that business transacted in India during the year; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  in respect of general insurance 
business 5 per cent of the gross premium income written direct in India during 
the year in respect of that business.
 

2[(2) The share of 
the Head Office expenses in the case of an insurer having his principal place of 
business in India for the purposes of sub-clause (i) of clause (b) of the 
Explanation to section 40C of the Act, shall not exceed 5 per cent of the gross 
premium income written direct outside India during the year.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17FA</number> 
Principal Office expenses.—For the purposes of sub-clause (ii) of clause (b) 
of the Explanation to section 40C of the Act, the share of the expenses 
in the case of an insurer having his principal place of business outside India 
in respect of general-insurance business transacted by him outside India through 
his office in India shall not exceed 5 per cent of the gross 5 per cent of the 
premium income written direct outside India through his office in India during 
the year.]
 
 



</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17FB</number> 
Calculation of proper share of managerial expenses.—For the purposes of 
sub-clause (iii) of clause (b) of the Explanation to section 40C of the Act the 
proper share of managerial expenses, that may be excluded in computing the 
expenses of management in India, shall be computed in the following manner, 
namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  in the case of an insurer having 
his principal place of business in India, same proportion of the total 
remuneration received by the Chief Executive Officer of the insurer (by whatever 
name called) as 15 per cent of the paid-up capital of the insurer bears to the 
total gross premium written direct in India by the insurer;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in the case of an insurer having 
his principal place of business outside India, nil.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>17G</number> Action against 
Extravagant Life Insurers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If it appears from the report of an actuarial valuation under sub-section (3) of 
section 64K of the Act read with the statutory returns relating to the accounts 
that the insurer concerned is insolvent, the Controller may cancel the 
registration of such insurer and request the Executive Committee of the Life 
Insurance Council to consider whether in the circumstances of the case it is 
possible to have the business of the insurer reconstructed or whether some other 
insurer is willing to take over the business.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When such a request is 
received, the Executive Committee of the Life Insurance Council shall meet not 
later than one month of the receipt of such request to consider the matter and 
within seven days of such meeting shall communicate its decision to the 
Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the Executive 
Committee is unable to meet within the time specified in sub-rule (2) or is 
unable to suggest any practical steps for the reconstruction or transfer, the 
Controller may, as soon as may be, apply to the court for the winding up of that 
insurer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the valuation under 
sub-section (3) of section 64K does not disclose the insurer to be insolvent, 
the actuary making the investigation shall append to his report a statement 
whether an encroachment on the bonus loadings contained in the premium has 
occurred and whether such encroachment is due either partly or wholly to heavy 
expenses incurred by the insurer after giving credit for any profits made in 
other directions. The Controller may request the Executive Committee of the Life 
Insurance Council for advice so that such encroachment may neither continue nor 
recur and the Executive Committee shall meet within a month of the receipt of 
such request and make such recommendations as it deems fit.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On receipt of the 
recommendations referred to in sub-rule (3) or sub-rule (4), the Controller may 
issue such directions to the insurer concerned as he deems fit and if the 
insurer complies with such directions, the cancelled registration may be 
received whether possible or where it is not so possible, the insurer may be 
registered afresh.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If the directions are 
not complied with, the Controller may apply to the court for the winding up of 
the insurer.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>17H</number> Action against 
Extravagant General Insurers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In pursuance of sub-section (3) of section 64M of the Act the Controller may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  cancel the registration of the 
insurer under the Act, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  request the Executive Committee 
of the General Insurance Council to consider practical steps for the 
reconstruction of the insurer concerned or for transferring its business to some 
other insurer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When such a request as 
is referred to in the preceding sub-rule is received by the Executive Committee 
of the General Insurance Council, it shall meet not later than one month of the 
receipt of such request to consider the request and within seven days of such 
meeting shall communicate its decision to the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Controller may, 
after considering the recommendations of the Executive Committee in this behalf 
apply to the court for the winding up of the insurer concerned if he thinks fit.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Transaction of bond 
investment business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Provident societies which immediately before the commencement of the Act were 
transacting bond investment business may continue to receive premiums or 
contributions and to make payments in respect of such business but shall not 
undertake any new business of that class.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
sub-rule (1), “bond investment business” means the business of effecting 
contracts by the issue of bonds, endowment certificates or other documents, 
whereby in return for one or more premiums paid to the provident society, the 
payment is insured of a sum or series of sums, at a future date or dates, 
whether fixed before hand or determined by chance.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Rules of Provident 
Societies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every provident society shall in addition to the matters specified in clauses 

<subsection><number>a</number> to (o) of sub-section (1) of section 74 of the Act set forth in its rules—
 <subsubsection>
        <number>i</number>  that where a policy is applied 
for on the life of a person other than the person paying the premiums on such 
policy, the name of the person paying the premiums and his relationship to the 
life insured shall be inserted in the policy, the policy shall not be issued 
till the life insured (or if he be not of age his legal guardian) has given his 
consent in writing to the insurance being effected, and the amount secured shall 
not be excessive having regard to the interest of the person paying the premiums 
in the life insured;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the disqualifications, if any, 
due to change of occupation, residence, or other specified cause;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iii</number>  the terms upon which any policy 
may be kept in force for a reduced benefit without liability to payment of 
further premiums;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iv</number>  a statement to the effect that 
all policies issued after the commencement of the Act shall have clearly set out 
therein the matters referred to in clauses (f), (g), (h), (i) and (j) of 
sub-section (1) of section 74 of the Act and those referred to in clauses (ii) 
and (iii) above;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>v</number>  the method of voting at the 
meeting of the managing body and the number constituting a quorum;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>vi</number>  a statement that no dividend 
shall be declared except as a result of a valuation under sub-section (1) of 
section 81;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>vii</number>  a statement that no bonus other 
than an interim bonus shall be declared except as a result of a valuation made 
in accordance with sub-section (1) of section 81, that the rate of such bonus 
shall not exceed that recommended by the actuary, and that no interim bonus 
shall be declared at a rate exceeding that approved by an actuary; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>viii</number>  a statement that the paid-up 
capital shall not be treated as part of the society’s assets or the purpose of 
showing a divisible surplus at the time of any investigation made under 
sub-section (1) of section 81, and that where assets of the nature of 
organisation or preliminary expenses exceed the paid-up capital the fund shall 
be diminished by the amount of such excess for the purpose of ascertaining the 
financial condition of the society.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> All rules made by a 
Local or Provincial Government under section 24 of the Provident Insurance 
Societies Act, 1912, are hereby repealed.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>19A</number> 
Every provident society shall, commencing from a date not later than the 1st 
January, 1943, maintain at its principal office in the States the following 
registers in the forms specified below or as near thereto as possible provided 
the information to be shown is not reduced thereby in respect of all its 
transactions subsisting on or after that date, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  A register of members (but not 
including membership merely by virtue of being policy-holders), proprietors and 
share holders.......in Form VIA.
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  A register of directors, 
manager, secretary and other officers.......in Form VIB.
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  A proposal register.......in 
Form VIC.
 </section><section>
       <number>iv</number>  A register of 
policies.............. in Form VID in respect of all policies issued from a date 
not later than 1st January, 1943. (Separate registers shall be maintained for 
each contingency specified in or prescribed under sub-section (1) of section 65 
of the Act in respect of which the society carries on business).
 </section><section>
       <number>v</number>  A premium register .......in Form 
VIE.
 </section><section>
       <number>vi</number>  A lapse register showing the 
details in respect of each policy which is treated by the society as having 
lapsed .......in Form VIF.
 </section><section>
      <number>vii</number>  A register of claims not 
including annuities....... in Form VIG.
 </section><section>
     <number>viii</number>  A register of annuity 
payments....... in Form VIH.
 </section><section>
       <number>ix</number>  A register of agents ....... in 
Form VIII:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  any register printed after this 
rule is made and purporting to contain the information specified in any of the 
registers prescribed by this rule shall be in the form prescribed therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  if any of the registers required 
to be kept in accordance with section 79 of the Act, as it stood before the 
commencement of the Insurance (Amendment) Act, 1941, is not kept, or if any of 
the registers so kept is exhausted, the society shall maintain forthwith the 
corresponding register or registers prescribed by this rule;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  if no registers are maintained 
corresponding to the registers prescribed by clauses (iii), (v) and (vi) of the 
rule, the society shall, commencing from a date not later than 1st April, 1942, 
maintain the registers prescribed by these clauses;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  it shall not be necessary to show 
the name of the life insured in addition to the policy number in the register in 
Form VID, VIE, VIF, VIG or VIH, the register concerned is prepared by mechanical 
means.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Forms of accounts and 
statements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The revenue account and balance-sheet of a provident society shall be prepared 
in accordance with Forms VII and VIII, respectively, and in their completion 
regard shall be had to the notes appended thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If it so desires a 
provident society may submit a profit and loss account in addition to a revenue 
account and balance-sheet.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The statements 
required under clauses (a)(i) and (b) of sub-section (2) of section 80 of the 
Act shall be prepared in accordance with Forms IX and X, respectively.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Actuarial reports.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whenever an investigation is made into the financial condition of a provident 
society under section 81 of the Act the report of the actuary—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  shall, so far as practicable, be 
prepared in accordance with the regulations and requirements contained in the 
Fourth Schedule to the Act except that it shall not be necessary to supply a 
consolidated revenue account in Form G, a statement in Form DDD of additions to 
and deductions from policies and a statement in Form DDDD of particulars of 
policies forfeited or lapsed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  shall contain in the appropriate 
places the information required in clauses (a) to (e) of sub-section (2) of 
section 81;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  shall state the proportion of the 
renewal premium income spent in payment of commission and other expenses in each 
year during the period since the last investigation after allowing as the cost 
of the new business of the year, 71/2 per 
cent of single premiums and 90 per cent of first year’s premiums falling due in 
the year after deduction of those unpaid under policies allowed to lapse in the 
year;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  shall state whether the actuary 
has taken steps to prevent the policy reserve values from being less than the 
minimum surrender values;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  shall have appended to it a 
certificate as prescribed in sub-section (2) of section 81; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  shall contain a statement that 
in no case where a policy has been written off as a lapse does there exist any 
further liability actual or contingent.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an investigation 
into the financial condition of a provident society is made as at a date other 
than the expiration of the year of account, the accounts for the period since 
the expiration of the last year of account and the balance-sheet as at the date 
at which the investigation is made shall be prepared and audited in the manner 
provided by the Act and these rules.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Signatures of returns 
furnished by provident societies.—Every 
return furnished to the Controller of Insurance under sub-section (2) of section 
82 of the Act shall be signed in accordance with the provisions of sub-section 
(2) of section 15 of the Act.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Notices under section 
92(6).—The 
notices referred to in sub-section (6) of section 92 of the Act shall be sent by 
post to the last known addresses of the persons concerned as recorded in the 
society’s books and certificates of posting shall be obtained therefor:
 
Provided that the 
liquidator may at his discretion send all or any of the notices by registered 
post.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>23A</number> Security from 
liquidator.—Where 
a liquidator is appointed by the Controller under the provisions of sub-section 

<section><number>1</number> of section 90 of the Act, the Controller may demand from the liquidator such 
security and in such form as he may determine.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Fees under the Act and 
the manner of collection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fee for registration under section 3 of the Act shall be five hundred rupees 
for each of the following classes of insurance business done or to be done by 
the insurer, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  life insurance;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  fire insurance;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  marine insurance;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  miscellaneous insurance:
 
Provided that where the 
business done or to be done is marine insurance only and relates exclusively to 
country craft or cargo of country craft or both the fee for registration shall 
be two hundred and fifty rupees:
 
Provided further that 
where an insurer who is already registered for carrying on marine insurance 
business relating exclusively to country craft or cargo of country craft or both 
and no other class of insurance business, subsequently, applies for registration 
for carrying on the entire class of marine insurance or any other class of 
insurance business specified above, the fees or such registration shall be two 
hundred and fifty rupees plus the fee for registration of the class, if 
any, of insurance business other than marine insurance business for which 
registration is sought.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>1A</number> The fee for issue of 
a duplicate certificate of registration under sub-section (7) of section 3 shall 
be ten rupees.
 

1[(2) The fee for 
renewal of registration under section 3A of the Act for each class of insurance 
business for which the insurer is registered shall be—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  in the case of an insurer not 
carrying on solely re-insurance, business, one-fourth of one per cent of the 
total gross premium written direct in India in that class of insurance business 
during the year preceding the year in which the application for renewal of 
registration is required to be made by insurer, (the amount of fee so arrived 
at, if not an integral number of rupees, being rounded off to the next lower 
integral rupee), or five hundred rupees whichever is greater;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  in the case of an insurer 
carrying on solely reinsurance business one-fourth of one per cent of the total 
premiums in respect of facultative reinsurances accepted by the insurer in that 
class of insurance business during the year preceding the year in which the 
application for renewal of registration is required to be made (the amount of 
fees so arrived at, if not on integral number of rupees, being rounded off to 
the next lower integral rupee) or five hundred rupees whichever is greater].
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The fee or 
registration under section 70 of the Act shall be two hundred rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>3A</number> The fee for issue of 
duplicate certificate or registration under sub-section (7) of section 70 shall 
be three rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The fee for renewal of 
registration under section 70A of the Act shall be fifty rupees where the total 
gross premium income including annuity considerations, admission fees and other 
fees, if any, as shown in the revenue account last furnished under the Act was 
less than fifty thousand rupees per annum or one hundred rupees in all other 
cases.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The fee payable for 
obtaining copies under section 119 of the Act shall be two rupees for each 
fullscape page or part of a page of the copy, the copy being prepared with 
reasonable margin and spacing.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any fee specified in 
this rule or payable under sub-section (1) of section 20 of the Act shall be 
paid into the Bank or where there is no office of the Bank, into the Imperial 
Bank of India acting as the agent of that Bank or into any Government Treasury 
for credit under the head 

2[“XXI—Miscellaneous 
Department—Fees realised under the Insurance Act, 1938], and the receipt shall 
be sent along with the relevant application.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>24A</number> Fees payable on 
referring disputed claims to Controller.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fee payable at the time of referring to the Controller a dispute relating to 
the settlement of a claim on a policy of life insurance under sub-section (1) of 
section 47A of the Act is rupees ten or one rupee for each hundred rupees or 
part thereof of the amount of the claim (including any profit or bonus), 
whichever is greater.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any fee specified in 
this rule shall be paid in the form of “Government of India Insurance” stamps 
available on payment from a Government Treasury and the stamp shall be affixed 
on the application or letter referring the dispute to the Controller and 
superscribed with the signature of the claimant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where in respect of 
any fee specified in this rule “Government of India Insurance” stamps of a 
greater value than is necessary have been inadvertently used or where the 
application or letter referring a dispute to the Controller bearing such stamps 
is not entertained by the Controller under section 47A of the Act for any 
reason, refund may be made of the excess over the necessary fee, or of the value 
of the stamps affixed, as the case may be.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>24B</number> Fees payable to the 
Councils.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fees payable by a member or associate member who is an insurer carrying on 
life-insurance business to the Life Insurance Council in each calendar year 
shall be fifty rupees for every lakh of rupees or part thereof of his gross 
direct premium income from life-insurance business in India in the last but one 
preceding calendar year subject to a maximum of one thousand and two hundred and 
fifty rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fees payable by a 
member or associate member who is an insurer carrying on general insurance 
business to the General Insurance Council in each calendar year shall be 
twenty-five rupees for every ten thousand rupees or part thereof of his gross 
direct premium income in India in general insurance business in the last but one 
preceding calendar year.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any fee specified in 
this rule shall be paid by means of a crossed bank draft on the Simla Branch of 
the Imperial Bank of India 
drawn in favour of the Secretary of the Council concerned.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Additional particulars 
to be given by actuary.—An 
actuary investigating the financial condition of an insurer shall, in addition 
to the reports, statements and abstracts, required to be furnished under section 
13 or clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 16 of the Act, furnish statements 
with regard to the following matters:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  whether he has taken steps to 
prevent the policy reserve values from being less than the minimum surrender 
values;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the proportion of renewal premium 
income spent in payment of commission and other expenses in each year during the 
period since the last investigation after allowing, as the cost of the new 
business of the year, seven and half per cent of single premiums including 
consideration for annuities granted and seven and half per cent for each year of 
the maximum premiums-paying period, but not exceeding ninety per cent in all, of 
first year’s premium falling due in the year after deduction of those unpaid 
under policies allowed to lapse in the year:
 
Provided that in respect 
of any year or accounting period ending on a date earlier than the 31st day of 
December, 1946, the allowance out of first year’s premiums as the cost of the 
new business shall be ninety per cent irrespective of the premium-paying period.
 
Explanation 1.—Where 
the maximum premiums-paying period includes a fraction of a year, such fraction 
shall be ignored.
 
Explanation 2.—In 
the case of a whole life policy with premium payable throughout the duration of 
the policy the maximum premiums-paying period shall be assumed to be twelve 
years.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>25A</number> 
The conditions with which a Mutual Insurance Company shall comply for the 
purposes of sub-section (2) of section 4 are that such company shall confine its 
activities to members of any one profession only or to employees under one 
employer only and that if any question arises whether or not a particular group 
of persons belongs to any one profession or is employed under any one employer, 
the Controller of Insurance shall decide the question and his decision shall be 
final.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Form of declaration 
under section 16(2)(d).—The 
declaration referred to in clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 16 of the 
Act shall be in Form XI and one copy of the declaration shall be signed in the 
manner described in sub-section (2) of section 15 of the Act.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Returns in respect of 
dividing insurance business.—Every 
insurer, so long as he has policies on the dividing principal remaining in 
force, shall submit all returns required under the Act or these rules in respect 
of such business separately from the corresponding returns in respect of other 
insurance business, and along with the revenue account shall also furnish in 
respect of such business returns in Forms XII, XIII and XIV, respectively. Four 
copies shall be submitted of each of these three last mentioned returns, of 
which one of each shall be signed in the manner described in sub-section (2) of 
section 5 of the Act.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
The sub-clauses of miscellaneous insurance business in respect of each of which 
a separate account of receipts and payments is to be kept as required under 
sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 10 of the Act on and after the 1st January, 1943, 
shall be—
 </section><section>
       <number>1</number>  Capital Redemption insurance 
business.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  Continuous Disability insurance 
business.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  Employer’s Liability insurance 
business.
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  The business of insuring the 
payment on the happening of each of the contingencies (a) birth, (b) marriage, 
and (c) failure of issue, each contingency to constitute a separate business 
unless the contingencies are combined in a single contract, but not being 
business comprising insurance contracts which are terminable by the insurer at 
intervals not exceeding twelve months and under which if a claim arises, the 
insurer’s liability to pay benefit ceases within one year from the date on which 
the claim arose.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
For the purpose of the 
Act, the business of an insurer shall be deemed to be transacted—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  in India, if the insurance 
business, wherever effected, relates to any property situate in India or to any 
vessel or aircraft registered in India;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in India or the States, according 
as the premiums in respect of those transactions are ordinarily paid in India or 
the States, as the case may be:
 
Provided that if any 
question arises whether any premiums are ordinarily paid inside or outside the 
States of India, the Controller shall decide the question and his decision shall 
be final.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Activities of 
insurers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An insurer may do all acts necessary for making investments permissible under 
the Act for the protection of such investments and for the realisation of such 
investments and may in that connection take over and administer mortgaged 
property until a suitable occasion arises for its disposal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An insurer carrying on 
general insurance business may act as the manager in charge of a branch office 
of another insurer in respect of general insurance business.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Statement of 
emoluments.—The 
statement of emoluments exceeding Rs. 5,000 to be furnished under sub-section 
(2) of section 31 shall be in Form XV.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Payment where nominee 
is a minor.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The holder of a policy of life insurance may, in any case where the nominee is a 
minor, appoint any person to receive the money secured by the policy in the 
event of his death during the minority of the nominee, and communicate such 
appointment to the insurer concerned by forwarding the documents relating to 
such appointment which should be endorsed by the appointee to show his consent 
thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any such appointment 
in order to be effectual shall unless incorporated in the text of the policy 
itself, be made by an endorsement on the policy.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any such appointment 
may at any time before the policy matures for payment be cancelled or changed by 
an endorsement or further endorsement, as the case may be, and communicated to 
the insurer.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Summary of 
balance-sheet and revenue account.—The 
summary to be published in pursuance of section 100 of the Act shall be in Form 
XVI.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Term of office.—The 
term of office of the non-official members of the Advisory Committee constituted 
under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 101B of the Act (hereafter in this rule and 
rules 35 to 38 referred to as the Committee) shall be two years from the date of 
their nomination. The official members of the Committee shall hold office during 
the pleasure of the Central Government. All outgoing members shall be eligible 
for re-nomination.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Resignation and 
filling of casual vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any member of the Committee may resign his membership of the Committee by notice 
in writing addressed to the Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of 
Finance 

1[Department of 
Company Affairs and Insurance] to that effect and such resignation shall take 
effect from the date on which it is accepted by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Casual vacancies in 
the Committee whether caused by resignation, death or otherwise, shall be filled 
by nomination by the Central Government and any person, other than an official, 
so nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office until the expiry of the term 
of office of the member in whose place he is nominated.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Secretary.—The 
Central Government may appoint a secretary to the Committee for the purpose of 
performing such functions as are assigned to him by these rules or as may be 
assigned to him by the Chairman of the Committee.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Procedure for the 
conduct of business, etc., of the Committee.—
<section><number>1</number>
Meetings of the Committee.—Meetings of the Committee may be held at such 
places and at such times as may be decided by the Chairman of the Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notice of meeting.—Notice 
of any meeting of the Committee shall be sent by the Secretary of the Committee 
to every member at least seven days before the date of the meeting. The notice 
shall state briefly the business to be transacted at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Quorum for the 
meeting.—Three members shall constitute quorum for a meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Adjournment of a 
meeting.—If the requisite quorum is not available within half an hour of the 
appointed time for a meeting, the Chairman or in his absence any person 
nominated by him under sub-rule (5) may adjourn the meeting to such date and 
time as he may decide.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Chairman to preside 
at meeting.—The Chairman shall preside at all meetings of the Committee. If 
the Chairman is unable to attend, he may nominate a member of the Committee to 
preside in his absence.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Decision at a 
meeting.—All matters required to be decided by the Committee shall be 
decided by the majority of the votes of the members present. The voting shall be 
by show of hands.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Decision by 
circulation.—Any matter for consideration of the Committee may at the 
discretion of the Chairman be decided by circulation among the members as an 
alternative to convening a meeting for the purpose:
 
Provided that the decision 
arrived at shall not be valid unless at least three members express an opinion 
on that matter.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Minutes.—The 
minutes of the proceedings of every meeting shall be circulated to the members 
of the Committee. The minutes shall be confirmed at the next meeting of the 
Committee and shall thereafter be recorded in a Minute Book and signed by the 
Chairman.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Allowances payable to 
members of the Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every non-official member shall be entitled for attending meetings of the 
Committee to travelling and other allowances as under:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  Travelling allowance for 
journeys from the usual place of residence or the place of commencement of the 
journey to the place of the meeting and the return journey to the place of 
commencement of the journey or the usual place of residence, whichever is 
shorter in each case, at the maximum rate for the time being admissible to a 
Central Government servant of the first grade. Subject to the foregoing, the 
members shall be entitled to travel either by air-conditions class or by air.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Daily allowance at the maximum 
rate for the time being admissible to Central Government servants of the first 
grade at the place of the meeting for the days on which the meeting is held and 
in respect of one day previous to the commencement of the meeting and one day 
after the meeting if the member actually arrives on or before and leave on or 
after the respective days.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The travelling 
allowances and daily allowances of an official member shall be governed by the 
rules for the time being applicable to him for journeys performed on official 
duty.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>39</number> Minimum 
information to be maintained and the checks and other verifications to be 
adopted.—
<section><number>1</number> Every insurer shall maintain at the principal place of business 
of the insurer in India the items of information specified in sub-rules (2) and 
(3):
 
Provided that where it is 
not convenient or practicable to maintain any item of information in full detail 
at such principal office it may be maintained at the branches or other offices 
in such way, however, that each such branch or office maintains the relevant 
part of the information applicable to its working:
 
Provided further than an 
insurer carrying on solely re-insurance business shall be deemed to have 
complied with the provisions of sub-rules (2) and (3) if the information 
required to be maintained under those sub-rules is readily available from the 
records of such insurer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The following items of 
information shall be maintained in respect of each class or sub-class or 
insurance business, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  a record of cover-notes issued 
specifying the identification number, name of party, dates of commencement and 
where applicable expiry of risk, type of cover granted or cross-reference to the 
relevant policy and the amount of premium or other money received:
 
               Provided that if duplicate 
copies of cover-notes are maintained in serial order, the requirement of the 
provision shall be deemed to have been complied with;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  a record of policies, which 
should be serially numbered listing all policies issued, entered in 
chronological order, stating the number of policy, dates of commencement and 
expiry of risk, name of the insured, premium received, cross-reference to the 
relevant Bank Guarantee or deposit and the nature of risk granted, 
cross-reference to any endorsement passed subsequent to the issue of the policy:
 
               Provided that a serially filed 
collection of duplicate copies of policies issued shall be deemed sufficient 
compliance with this requirement, if they are serially numbered and all the 
relevant information specified in this clause are entered therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  a record of premium showing 
according to chronological order of receipt of premiums received, date of 
receipt, the amount, and name of party from whom received and with 
cross-reference to policy number or to other document showing the occasion for 
the payment of such premium:
 
                 Provided that if this 
information is readily available otherwise from the records, a separate record 
under this head need not be maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  a record of endorsements 
mentioning the policy number to which attached, dates of commencement and expiry 
of the endorsement, the type of endorsement and the additional premium charged 
or refund premium due and cross-reference to the premium register:
 
               Provided that serially filed 
duplicate copies of endorsements shall be deemed to comply with this requirement 
if they are serially numbered and each copy contains information about the 
policy number of the policy to which it is attached;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  a record of bank guarantees and 
deposits giving particulars of the party, amount and conditions of guarantee or 
deposit and cross-reference to the relevant policy or policies:
 
                 Provided that if this 
information is readily available otherwise from the records, a separate record 
under this head need not be maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  a record of claims intimated 
mentioning name of claimant, giving reference to policy number, date of 
intimation of claim, interest covered, nature and cause of the loss or damage, 
provisional estimate of loss, amount at which settled, date of settlement of 
claim, recoveries from salvage or otherwise and whether surveyed:
 
                 Provided that two separate 
records, one relating to claims intimated and the other relating to claims paid, 
may be maintained if there is adequate cross-referencing of information between 
them and if the information required under this clause is readily available from 
them taken together.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The following item of 
information shall be maintained for the business of the insurer as a whole, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  a register of agents, giving in 
respect of each agent, name, address and particulars of agents’ licence held, 
date of appointment and date of termination of appointment if any:
 
                 Provided that a collection 
of cards or folios shall be deemed sufficient compliance with this requirement 
if they are filed in a systematic order and contain all the information required 
under this clause;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  a record of agents giving 
particulars of business procured by each agent, the amount of premium received 
on such business and the amount of commission paid thereon;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  duplicate copies of appointment 
letters issued to the agents, field workers and members of the staff and changes 
therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  a record of employees, excluding 
salaried field workers, showing name, date of appointment, present designation, 
present salary and cross-reference to appointment letter and date of 
termination, if any;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  a record of field workers showing 
name, date of appointment, present designation, and present salary, showing the 
business expected from and written by them with cross-reference to appointment 
letters and date of termination, if any;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  cash book and disbursement book;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>vii</number>  a record of investments giving 
separately for immovable property, securities and scripts, loans on mortgages 
and other loans, particulars of all the investments held showing the changes 
occurring therein from time to time;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>viii</number>  a record of other assets, such 
as, deposits, amounts due, sundry debtors, furniture and fixtures, stationery, 
and cash in hand and with banks:
 
               Provided that in respect of 
cash in hand and with banks the requirements of this clause shall be deemed to 
be complied with if the information about the amount of such cash is readily 
available from the cash book or other records.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every insurer shall 
obtain and maintain legally valid receipt for every payment made and shall 
maintain the receipts filed in a systematic manner either chronologically or in 
some other convenient order.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every insurer shall, 
in respect of any payment made to an employee or other person on account of 
travelling expenses, maintain a record showing full details of the journey 
performed, purpose of the journey, details of the fares paid and allowances 
granted.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every office of an 
insurer shall maintain an attendance register of clerical and subordinate staff 
indicating employees who attend the office each day.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every office of an 
insurer issuing any documents used for evidencing of the assumption of risk 
shall ensure that such documents are serially numbered, shall maintain a record 
of the serial numbers of the forms of the documents issued to each person, and 
shall maintain a proper check to verify that all the forms of documents issued 
are properly accounted for.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every insurer shall 
retain all the documents relating to claims settled including copies of any 
survey or loss assessment reports connected therewith:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  in respect of every loss or 
damages on which a claim of less than Rs. 5,000 has been made, for a period of 
three years;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  in respect of every loss or 
damage on which a claim of Rs. 5,000 or more but less than Rs. 20,000 has been 
made, for a period five years;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  in respect of every loss or 
damage on which a claim of Rs. 20,000 or more but less than rupees one lakh has 
been made, for a period of seven years; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  in respect of every loss or 
damage on which a claim of rupees one lakh or more has been made, for a period 
of twelve years;
 
such period being counted from the date on 
which the claim is settled.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number> Every insurer shall 
maintain a record setting out the names of each insurance company with which he 
has entered into any permanent facultative re-insurance arrangement, and such 
record shall show the terms on which re-insurance arrangements have been entered 
into and the commissions paid or received under each transaction.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> Every insurer shall 
maintain a record setting out particulars of each and every facultative 
re-insurance ceded or accepted and such record shall show the name of each 
insurer with whom the transaction has been entered into.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> Every insurer shall 
maintain a record setting out the names of each insurer with which he has 
entered into re-insurance treaties from any of his offices in India, and such 
record shall include all the details of the terms of the treaties.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> (a) Every insurer 
shall maintain the following accounts in his ledgers, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  Re-insurance Accepted Account;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Re-insurance Commission Paid 
Account;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  Re-insurance Claims Payable 
Account;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  Re-insurance Claims Paid 
Account;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  Re-insurance Ceded Account;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  Re-insurance Commission Received 
Account;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>vii</number>  Re-insurance Claims Recoverable 
Account;
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>viii</number>  Re-insurance Claims Recovered 
Account;
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> An insurer shall be 
deemed to have complied with the provisions of clause (a) if the information 
required is otherwise readily available from the existing books and accounts of 
the insurer.]
 
 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Search and seizure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The powers of search and seizure under section 34H of the Act shall be exercised 
in accordance with sub-rules (2) to (14).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller may, 
after recording his reasons for doing so authorise any officer subordinate to 
him not lower in rank than an Assistant Controller of Insurance (hereinafter in 
this rule referred to as the authorized officer) for the purposes of section 34H 
of the Act; provided that such authorization shall—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  be in writing under his 
signature;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  bear his seal; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  authorize the authorized 
officer to enter and search any building or place specified therein, and to 
exercise the powers and perform the functions under sub-section (1) of section 
34H of the Act with such assistance of police officers or of the officer of the 
Central Government, or both, as may be required.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever any building 
or place authorized to be searched is closed, any person residing in or being in 
charge of such building or place shall, on demand by the authorized officer and 
on production of the authority, allow him free ingress thereto and afford all 
reasonable facilities for a search therein.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If ingress into such 
building or place cannot be so obtained it shall be lawful for the authorized 
officer executing the authority, with such assistance of police officers or of 
officers of the Central Government or of both as may be required, to enter such 
building or place and search therein and in order to effect an entrance into 
such building or place, to break open any outer or inner door or window of any 
building or place, whether that of the person to be searched or of any other 
persons, if after notification of his authority and purpose and demand of 
admittance duly made, he cannot otherwise obtain admittance:
 
Provided that, if any such 
building or place is an apartment in actual occupancy of a woman, who according 
to custom does not appear in public, the authorised officer, shall, before 
entering such apartment, given notice to such woman that she is at liberty to 
withdraw and shall afford her every reasonable facility for withdrawing and may 
then break open the apartment and enter it.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The authorised officer 
may require any person who is the owner, or has the immediate possession, or 
control, of any box, locker, safe, almirah or any other receptacle situate in 
such building or place, or open the same and allow access to inspect or examine 
its contents, and where the keys thereof are not available or where such person 
fails to comply with any such requirement, may cause any action to be taken 
including the breaking open of such box, locker, safe, almirah or other 
receptacle which the authorized officer may deem necessary for carrying out all 
or any of purposes specified in the authority issued under sub-rule (2).
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The authorized officer 
may, where it is not practicable to seize any book, account or document, serve 
an order on the owner or the person who is an immediate possession or control 
thereof that he shall not remove, part with or otherwise deal with it except 
with the previous permission of the authorized officer who may take such steps 
as may be necessary for ensuring compliance with this sub-rule.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where any person in or 
about such building or place is reasonably suspected of concealing about his 
person any book, account or document for which search is being made, such person 
may also be searched by the authorized officer with such assistance as he may 
consider necessary. If such person is a woman, the search shall be made by 
another woman with a strict regard to decency.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Before making a 
search, the authorized officer about to make it shall call upon two or more 
respectable inhabitants of the locality in which the building or place to be 
searched is situate to attend and witness the search and may issue an order in 
writing to them or any of them so to do.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The search shall be 
made in the presence of the witnesses aforesaid and a list of all books, 
accounts and documents seized in the course of such search and of the places in 
which they were respectively found shall be prepared by the authorized officer 
and signed by such witnesses; but no person witnessing a search shall be 
required to attend as a witness of the search in any proceedings under the Act 
unless specifically summoned.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The occupant of the 
building or place searched or some person in his behalf shall be permitted to 
attend during the search and a copy of the list prepared under sub-rule (9) 
shall be delivered to such occupant or person. A copy shall also be forwarded to 
the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> When any person is 
searched under sub-rule (7) a list of all books, accounts and documents taken 
possession of shall be prepared and a copy thereof shall be delivered to such 
person. A copy shall also be forwarded to the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> The authorized 
officer may convey the books, accounts and other documents, if any, seized by 
him in the course of the search made by him to the office of the Controller or 
to the office of the authorized officer or to any other office under the 
jurisdiction of the Controller.
 </section><section>
<number>13</number> The Controller or the 
officer in charge of the office mentioned in sub-rule (12), as the case may be, 
shall take such steps as he may consider necessary for the safe custody of 
books, accounts and other documents conveyed to him.
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> The authorization of 
the Controller referred to in sub-rule (2) shall be in Form No. XVII.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>41</number> Constitution.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The representatives of insurer on Tariff Advisory Committee shall be elected as 
follows, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  four members to be elected by 
insurers registered under the Act in the public sector in such manner that not 
more than one member shall represent each insurer;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  four members to be elected by 
insurers other than referred to in clause (i), registered under the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  one member to be elected by 
reinsurers registered under the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  one member to be elected by 
organisations exempted under section 118 of the Act and Provident Societies 
under section 65 of the Insurance Act, 1938;
 

2[(2) For the 
purposes of this rule, if any dispute concerning the election of any member 
arises, it shall be referred to the Central Government for its decision 
thereon.]]
 
 













</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 






 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>43</number> Election of 
Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The election of members shall be held in every fourth calendar year, the first 
election after the commencement of the Insurance (Amendment) Rules, 2004 being 
held before the 31st December, 2004.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every election shall 
be conducted by the Secretary to the Advisory Committee in accordance with the 
procedure specified in the regulations made by the authority.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 





 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 



 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 













 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 







 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 


















 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 






 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 

1[***]
 
 




 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> The fees payable to 
the Tariff Advisory Committee.—The 
fees payable to the Tariff Advisory Committee under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
64UK in respect of a calendar year shall be paid before the 31st December of 
that year and shall be paid by means of a crossed bank draft on any branch of 
the State Bank of India in Bombay City drawn in favour of the Committee.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>53A</number> Fund of 
the Tariff Advisory Committee and custody of its moneys.—
<section><number>1</number> The Tariff 
Advisory Committee shall have its own and all receipts of Committee shall be 
carried thereto and all payments by the Committee shall be made therefrom.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to any 
regulations that may be made in this behalf, all moneys belonging to the Tariff 
Advisory Committee which are not immediately required by the Committee for any 
purpose shall be deposited with the State Bank of India.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>53B</number> Accounts, 
audit and annual report of the Tariff Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The Tariff 
Advisory Committee shall cause regular accounts to be kept of all its moneys and 
properties in respect of the affairs of the Committee in such form as may be 
determined by the Central Government in consultation with the auditor appointed 
by that Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The annual accounts of 
the Committee shall be audited by the auditor or by any person authorized by him 
in this behalf and any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall 
be payable by the Committee to the auditor.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The auditor and any 
person appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Committee shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in connection 
with such auditor as the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India has in 
connection with the audit of Government accounts, and in particular, shall have 
the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and 
other necessary documents and papers.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The auditor or any 
person appointed by him in this behalf—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  shall communicate the results of 
the audit to the Committee which shall submit a copy of the audit report along 
with its observation to the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  shall forward a copy of the 
report direct to the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The Committee shall, 
as soon as may be, after the end of each calendar year, prepare and submit to 
the Central Government a report giving an account of its activities during the 
previous calendar year.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Apportionment of 
Provident Fund.—Where 
on or after the commencement of the Insurance (Amendment) Act, 1968 (62 of 
1968), all the employees of the Tariff Committee and the Regional Councils of 
the General Insurance Council do not become employees of the Tariff Advisory 
Committee under section 64UH of the Act, all the moneys and other assets 
belonging to the provident fund or superannuation fund any other like fund 
referred to in sub-section (3) of section 64UF of the Act shall be apportioned 
between the Tariff Advisory Committee and the trustees of the fund in the 
following manner, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  the moneys and other assets of 
any provident fund shall be apportioned in the proportion which the total of the 
amounts lying to the credit of the persons becoming employees of the Tariff 
Advisory Committee bears to the total of the amounts lying to the credit of the 
persons who do not become employees of the Tariff Advisory Committee;
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number>  the moneys and other assets of 
any superannuation fund shall be apportioned in the proportion which the 
liability of the fund in respect of the persons becoming employees of the Tariff 
Advisory Committee bears to a similar liability in respect of persons who do not 
become employees of the Tariff Advisory Committee, such liability to be 
ascertained on such basis as may be determined by the Tariff Advisory Committee 
and approved by the Central Government; and
 </section><section>
       <number>iii</number>  the moneys and other assets of 
any other like fund shall be apportioned in accordance with the principles set 
out in clause (i) or clause (ii) as the case may be.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule the assets of a provident fund, superannuation fund or 
any other like fund shall be valued at the market rate as on the date of 
commencement of the Insurance (Amendment) Act, 1968 (62 of 1968).
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Licence fee for 
surveyor or loss assessors and collection thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fee for obtaining a licence to act as a surveyor or loss assessor, shall be 
Rs. 250 and for renewing such licence shall be Rs. 200.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any fee specified in 
this rule shall be paid into the Bank or where there is no office of the Bank, 
into the State Bank of India acting as the agent of that Bank or into Government 
Treasury for credit under the central head “XXI—Miscellaneous Department—Fees 
realized under the Insurance Act, 1938” and the receipt shall be sent along with 
the relevant application.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Issue of licences to 
surveyor or loss assessors.—An 
applicant who desires to obtain or renew a licence to act as a surveyor or loss 
assessor shall proceed as follows:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the applicant shall obtain from 
the Controller of Insurance a form of application for a licence which shall be—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  in the case of an 
individual, whether working as a sole proprietor of a firm or not Form XVIIIAI 
or XVIIIBI. Form XVIIIAI shall be used when the applicant applies for a licence 
for the first time or for a licence, while Form XVIIIBI shall be used when the 
applicant applies for the renewal of the licence already held by him;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  in the case of a company or 
firm, Form XVIIIAF, or Form XVIIIBF, Form XVIIIAF shall be used when the 
applicant applies for a licence for the first time or for a fresh licence, while 
Form XVIIIBF shall be used when the applicant applies for the renewal of the 
licence already held by him;
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>b</number>  he shall then send to the 
Controller of Insurance the completed application form along with the receipt 
showing payment of the fees specified in the rule 55;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  the Controller of Insurance or 
the officer authorized by him may, after taking all reasonable steps to satisfy 
himself that the application is in order, that the applicant fulfils the 
requirements of clause (D) of sub-section (1) of section 64UM of the Act and 
that the applicant is not disqualified from holding a licence, issue a licence 
to him or, as the case may be, renew the licence. The licence shall be in Form 
XVIIIAAI in the case of an individual and in Form XVIIIAAF in the case of a 
company or firm. Renewal of licence shall be in Form XVIII BBI in the case of an 
individual and in Form XVIIIBBF in the case of a company or firm;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  no application for the renewal of 
a licence shall be entertained if it does not reach the Controller at least 
thirty days before the date on which the licence ceases to be in force.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>56A</number> 
Additional technical qualifications for surveyors and loss assessors.—The 
following shall be the technical qualifications for purposes of item 
<section><number>i</number> of 
sub-clause (i) of clause (D) of sub-section (1) of section 64UM of the Act, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  Fellowship or Associateship or 
Licenciateship held on the 26th October, 1968 or Fellowship or Associateship by 
examination subsequently acquired by the Institute of Insurance Surveyors 
and Adjusters, Bombay.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  Fellowship or Associateship of 
the Royal Institute of British Architects, London, and/or a Degree or Diploma in 
Architecture of a recognized University or Institute secured after attending 
full time course or by passing examination of such University or Institute.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  Fellowship or Associate 
membership of the Institute of
Chartered Accountants in England and 
Wales.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  Fellowship or Associate 
membership of the Institute of
Chartered Accountants in Scotland.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  Fellowship or Associate 
membership of the Institute of
Chartered Accountants in Ireland.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  Fellowship or Associate 
membership of the Institute of Cost 
and Works Accountants in the United 
Kingdom.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  A degree or diploma of a 
recognized Institute of Engineering 
secured after attending full time course and by passing the examination of such 
Institute.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  A certificate of competence as 
Master of Ship or as First Class Marine Engineer issued by a recognized 
authority.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  A degree or diploma in Naval 
Architecture of a recognized University or Institute.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  A Fellow or Associate on the 
26th October, 1968, or a Fellow or Associate by examination, of the Chartered 
Institute of Loss Adjusters, London, held after the 26th October, 1968.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  Any technical qualification 
recognized by the Government of India as equivalent or superior to the 
qualification listed in items (b) and (c) of sub-clause (i) of clause (D) of 
sub-section (1) of section 64UM of the Act.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Manner of bringing up 
the excess of the value of assets over the amount of the liabilities to the 
relevant amount.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the case of an insurer carrying on general insurance business at the 
commencement of the Insurance (Amendment) Act, 1968 (62 of 1968) the excess of 
the value of his assets over the amount of his liabilities shall be brought up 
to the “relevant amount” as defined in sub-section (1) of section 64VA of the 
Act, in four stages as specified in the following table:—
 
Table
 
 

  Stage    Dates            Excess of the value of the assets over the amount of 
  liabilities to be maintained as at the date mentioned in column (2) and 
  thereafter, shall be not less than
 
 </section><section>
   
  <number>1</number>       (2)                                        (3)
 
   I   
31-12-1969        
One-fourth of the “relevant amount” arrived at in the manner specified in 
sub-section (1) of section 64VA of the Act.
 
   II  
31-12-1970        
One-half of the “relevant amount” arrived at in the

 

                                manner specified in sub-section (1) of section 
64VA of the Act.
 
   III 
31-12-1971        
Three-fourths of the “relevant amount” arrived at in the manner specified in 
sub-section (1) of section 64VA of the Act.
 
   IV 
31-12-1972        
The “relevant amount” arrived at in the manner specified in sub-section (1) of 
section 64VA of the Act.
 
 
 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where in the case of 
an insurer referred to in sub-rule (1) the Central Government has, under the 
provisions of the third proviso to sub-section (1) of section 64VA extended the 
date of the 31st December, 1972 referred to in the said proviso to a subsequent 
date, the excess of the value of assets over the amount of the liabilities shall 
be brought up to the relevant amount in four stages in accordance with sub-rule 
(1) but the dates mentioned in column (2) of the Table in that sub-rule shall be 
deemed to have been altered as follows:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the date against Stage I shall be 
extended by one-fourth of the interval between the 31st December, 1972 and the 
extended date;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the date against Stage II shall 
be extended by one-half of the interval between the 31st December, 1972 and the 
extended date;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the date against Stage III shall 
be extended by three-fourths of the interval between the 31st December, 1972 and 
the extended date;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  in Stage IV, the extended date 
shall be substituted in place of the 31st December, 1972 mentioned against that 
stage:
 
              Provided that if any such 
altered date against Stage I, II, or III is not the last day of a calendar 
month, it shall be changed to the last day of the immediately preceding calendar 
month.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Advance payment of 
premiums.—For 
the purposes of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 64VB of the Act, a risk in respect of 
a policy may be assumed before the premium payable in respect thereof is 
received—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  if the entire amount of the 
premium is guaranteed to be paid by a Banking Company before the end of the 
calendar month next succeeding to the month in which the risk is assumed, if the 
premium due is not paid by the insured before that date;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  if an advance deposit is made 
with the insurer to the credit of the insured sufficient to cover the payment of 
the entire amount of the premium together with the premium, if any, due from the 
insured in respect of any other risk already assumed against such deposit, being 
agreed to be adjusted towards the premium before the end of the month next 
succeeding to the month in which the risk is assumed, if the premium due is not 
paid by the insured before that date.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Relaxation.—In 
respect of the categories of insurance policies mentioned hereunder the 
requirements of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 64VB shall stand relaxed to the 
extend and in the manner mentioned against each category of policy, subject to 
the conditions mentioned therein:
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  Policies issued to Government 
and semi-Government bodies.—The risk may be covered on such policies on the 
strength of an undertaking by the proposer to pay the premium within 30 days of 
the date of intimation of the amount of premium or within such further period as 
the Controller may fix in any particular case.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  Policies under 

1[Sickness Insurance, Group Personal 
Accident Insurance, Medical Benefits Insurance and Hospitalisation Insurance 
Schemes.]—Premiums on such 
policies may be accepted in instalment covering a particular period shall be 
received 

1[within 15 days from the date of 
commencement of the period.
 
 

2[(c)  Fidelity Guarantee Insurance.—Fidelity 
Guarantee Insurance policies covering Government and semi-Government employees 
may be issued without receipt of premium in advance if the policy is not in 
renewal of an existing policy and subject to the condition that the premium is 
paid within thirty days from the date of appointment of the person covered by 
the policy.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  Policies covering risks where 
exact premium cannot be ascertained without reference to Head Office, Principal 
Office, etc.—Where the exact premium for a risk cannot be ascertained 
without reference to Head Office, Principal Office or Controlling Office or the 
Tariff Advisory Committee for Regional Committee or for any other reason, the 
risk may be assumed if there is a deposit made by or on behalf of the insured 
with the insurer at a suitable rate not less than 2.5 per mile but the premium 
in such cases shall be paid or adjusted within thirty days of the commencement 
of risk or, where a reference is made to the Tariff Advisory Committee or a 
Regional Committee, within fifteen days of the date of the advice from the 
Tariff Committee or the Regional Committee as the case may be, failing which the 
cover shall be cancelled on the expiry of the period of thirty days or fifteen 
days as the case may be: 
 
              Provided that in the case of 
policies covering carriers’ liability, the adjustment of premium may be made 
after the expiry of the policy.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  Declaration Policies.—Risk 
in respect of such policies may be assumed if at least the premium calculated on 
75 per cent of the sum assured has been received before assumption of the risk.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  Policies issued on the basis 
of adjustable premiums.—Risk in respect of policies issued on the basis of 
adjustable premiums, such as, workmen’s compensation, cash in transit, etc., may 
be assumed on receipt of provisional premiums based on a fair estimate.
 
 

2[(g)  Annual Insurances connected 
with aircraft hulls and other aviation risks and connected with marine hulls.—Facilities 
for delayed payment of premium or the payment of premium by means of instalments 
not exceeding four in number may be allowed at the discretion of the insurer on 
policies covering the following risks, namely:—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  aircraft hulls,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  marine hulls,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  legal liability to 
passengers,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number>  automatic personal accident 
insurance to passengers,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>v</number>  blanket policies covering 
liability in excess of basic cover connected with aviation risks.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vi</number>  war risk insurance of air 
passengers and aircraft hulls,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vii</number>  third party, and other 
liability risks connected with aviation risks and marine hull risks,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>viii</number>  SRCC risk connected with 
aviation risk and marine hull risks:
 
                  Provided to that a clause 
to that affect is endorsed on the policy.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  Short period covers in respect 
of insurance connected with aircraft hulls and other aviation risks and marine 
hulls.—Short period covers may be granted on a hull covered basis on the 
following risks namely:—
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>i</number>  aircraft hulls,
 <subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  marine hulls,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  legal liability to 
passengers,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number>  automatic personal accident 
insurance to passengers,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>v</number>  blanket policies covering 
liability in excess of basic cover connected with aviation risks,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vi</number>  war risk insurance of air 
passengers and aircraft hulls,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>vii</number>  third party and other 
liability risks connected with aviation risks and marine hull risks,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>viii</number>  SRCC risks connected with 
aviation risk and marine hull risks; subject to the condition that the premium 
or additional premium in respect of risks assumed in a calendar month shall be 
paid by end of the next calendar month.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>i</number>  Policies issued 


3[for a period of more than one year].—In 
the case of policies issued 

3[for a period of more than one year], 
such contract Performance Bonds or Guarantees, Contractors’ “All Risk” policies, 
Machinery Election policies and the like, the premium may be staggered as 
necessary according to custom, over the period of the cover, provided that the 
first equated instalment is higher than any other instalment by at least 5 per 
cent of the total premiums payable and each instalment is paid in advance. Where 
the premiums are payable by declarations, they may be paid within fifteen days 
from the dates of receipt of declaration.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>j</number>  Schedule and consequential 
loss policies.—In such cases a provisional amount towards the premium shall 
be collected before the date of inception or renewal of risk on the basis of the 
previous year’s premium.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>k</number>  Marine covers other than 
hulls.—(i) In the case of inland shipments and transit risks, risk may be 
assumed under open policies in respect of seasonal crops, such as, tea, on the 
payment of a provisional premium based on a fair estimate.
 <subsubsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  In the case of exports 
overseas, risk may be assumed subject to the condition that the premium shall be 
paid within fifteen days from the date of sailing of the overseas vessel.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  In the case of imports, 
risk may be assumed subject to the condition that the premium shall be paid 
within fifteen days of the receipt of declaration in India from the insurer’s or 
insured’s representative overseas:
 
              Provided that the relaxations 
under sub-clauses (ii) and (iii) shall apply to marine cover notes only and not 
to marine policies.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>l</number>  Policies relating to 
insurances.—The premium shall be deemed to have been duly paid if paid on 
the full insurance to any one of the co-insurers.
 
 

4[(m)  Policies of re-insurance.—(i) 
Risk may be assumed without payment of premium in advance on insurances accepted 
under automatic re-insurance contracts.
 <subsubsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  In the case of facultative 
re-insurances accepted, risk may be assumed without payment of premium in 
advance if the ceding insurer lies given an undertaking to pay his share of the 
premium, instalment of premium, premium subject to delayed payment or, where a 
deposit premium or provisional premium was paid on the original policy, the 
adjusted premium, or, in the case of premiums subject to delayed payment, the 
delayed premium as the case may be, before the end of the calendar month 
succeeding the month in which the premium is due under the original policy.]
 
 






</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>60</number> Term of 
office.—Any person nominated as a member of the Consultative Committee 
constituted under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 110-G of the Act (thereafter 
referred to in rules 61 to 65 as the Committee) shall hold office for a period 
not exceeding three years or such further periods not exceeding three years at a 
time as the Central Government may specify.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Resignation and 
filling of casual vacancies.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Any member of the Committee may resign his membership of the Committee by notice 
in writing addressed to the Secretary to the Government of India, Ministry of 
Finance (Department of Revenue and Insurance) to that effect and such 
resignation shall take effect from the date on which it is accepted by the 
Central Government or on the expiry of a period of thirty days from the date of 
its receipt by the Central Government, whichever is earlier.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Casual vacancies in 
the Committee whether caused by resignation, death or otherwise, shall be filled 
by nomination by the Central Government.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Secretary.—The 
Central Government may appoint a Secretary to the Committee for the purpose of 
performing such functions as are assigned to him by these rules or as may be 
assigned to him by the Chairman of the Committee.
</article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Procedure for the 
conduct of business of the Committee.—Procedure 
for the conduct of business of the Committee shall be as follows, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>1</number>  Meetings of the Committee.—Meetings 
of the Committee may be held at such places and at such times as may be decided 
by the Chairman of the Committee.
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  Notice of meeting.—Notice 
of any meeting of the Committee shall be sent by the Secretary of the Committee 
to every member at least seven days before the date of the meeting.
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  Quorum for the meeting.—Two 
members in addition the Chairman shall constitute quorum for a meeting.
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  Adjournment of a meeting.—If 
the requisite quorum is not available within half an hour of the appointed time 
for a meeting, the Chairman may adjourn the meeting to such date and time as he 
may decide.
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number>  Chairman to preside at meeting.—The 
Chairman shall preside at all meetings of the Committee.
 </section><section>
       <number>6</number>  Record of deliberations.—The 
results of the deliberations of every meeting shall be recorded in the form of a 
note explaining, in brief, the matters referred to the Committee and the 
recommendations thereon of each of the members (other than the Chairman) 
present. Such record shall be signed by the Chairman and the members present.
 </section><section>
       <number>7</number>  Circulation.—Any matter 
for consideration of the Committee may at the discretion of the Chairman be 
referred to the members for suggestions by circulation as an alternative to 
convening a meeting for the purpose.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Allowances payable to 
members of the Consultative Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every non-official member shall be entitled for attending meetings of the 
Committee to travelling and other allowances as under:
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  travelling allowance for 
journeys from the usual place or residence or the place of commencement of the 
journey to the place of the meeting and the return journey to the place of 
commencement of the journey or the usual place of residence, whichever is 
shorter in each case, at the maximum rate or the time being admissible to a 
Central Government servant of the first grade. Subject to the foregoing, the 
member shall be entitled to travel either by air-conditioned class or by air;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  daily allowance at the maximum 
rate for the time being admissible to the Central Government servants of the 
first grade at the place of the meeting or the days on which the meeting is held 
and in respect of one day previous to the commencement of the meeting and one 
day after the meeting if the member actually arrives on or before and leaves on 
or after the respective days.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The travelling 
allowances and daily allowances of an official member shall be governed by the 
rules for the time being applicable to him for journeys performed on official 
duty.
</section></article> 
 
The Insurance Rules, 1939
 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Fees of members.—A 
non-official member shall be entitled to a fee for attending meetings of the 
Committee of Rs. 100 for each day of the meeting.]
 
 
 
 
</article><form>
 


The Insurance Rules, 1939
 


 
 



1[***]
 


 
 


—————
 


1. 
Schedule II omitted by G.S.R. 623(E), dated 20th September, 
2004 (w.e.f. 20-9-2004).
 


 
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>