<act><title>


THE MINIMUM WAGES (CENTRAL) RULES, 19501</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
extent.—The 
rules may be called The Minimum Wages (Central) Rules, 1950.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Interpretation.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  ‘Act’ means 
the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 1948);
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  ‘Advisory 
Committee’ means an Advisory Committee appointed under section 6 and includes an 
advisory sub-committee appointed under that section;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  ‘authority’ 
means the authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 20;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  ‘Board’ 
means the Advisory Board appointed under section 7;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number> ‘Chairman’ 
means the Chairman of the Advisory Board, the committee or the Advisory 
Committee, as the case may be, appointed under section 9;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  ‘committee’ 
means a committee appointed under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 5 and 
includes a sub-committee appointed under that section;
 </section><section>
        <number>ff</number>  ‘day’ means 
a period of twenty-four hours beginning at midnight;
 </section><section>
         <number>g</number>  ‘Form’ means 
a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>h</number>  ‘Inspector’ 
means a person appointed as Inspector under section 19;
 </section><section>
          <number>i</number>  ‘registered 
trade union’ means a trade union registered under the Indian Trade Unions Act, 
1926 (16 of 1926);
 </section><section>
          <number>j</number>  ‘section’ 
means a section of the Act; and
 </section><section>
         <number>k</number>  all other 
words and expressions used herein and not defined shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them under the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Term of office of 
the members of the committee and the Advisory Committee.—The 
term of office of the members of the committee or an Advisory committee shall be 
such as in the opinion of the Central Government is necessary for completing the 
enquiry into the scheduled employment concerned and the Central Government may, 
at the time of the constitution of the committee, or Advisory Committee, as the 
case may be, fix such terms and may, from time to time, extend it as 
circumstances may require.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Term of office of 
members of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise expressly provided in these rules the term of office of a 
non-official member of the Board, shall be two years commencing from the date of 
his nomination:
 
Provided that such member 
shall, notwithstanding the expiry of the said period of two years continue to 
hold office until his successor is nominated.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A non-official member 
of the Board nominated to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office for the 
remaining period of the term of office of the member in whose place he is 
nominated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The official member of 
the Board shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central Government.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4A</number> Nomination of 
substitute-members.—If 
a member is unable to attend a meeting of the committee or the Board, the 
Central Government or the body which nominated him may, by notice in writing 
signed on its behalf and by such member and addressed to the Chairman of the 
said committee or the Board, nominate a substitute in his place to attend that 
meeting. Such a substitute-member shall have all the rights of a member in 
respect of that meeting.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Travelling 
allowance.—A 
non-official member of the committee, an Advisory Committee or the Board, shall 
be entitled to draw travelling and halting allowance for any journey performed 
by him in connection with his duties as such member at the rates and subject to 
the conditions applicable to a Government servant of the first class under the 
appropriate rules of the Central Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Staff.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may appoint a Secretary to the committee, an Advisory 
Committee or the Board and such other staff as it may think necessary, and may 
fix the salaries and allowances payable to them and specify their conditions of 
service.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>(i) The Secretary shall 
be the Chief Executive Officer of the committee, the Advisory Committee, or the 
Board, as the case may be. He may attend the meetings of such committee, 
Advisory Committee or Board but shall not be entitled to vote at such meetings.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The Secretary shall 
assist the Chairman in convening meetings and shall keep a record of the minutes 
of such meetings and shall take necessary measures to carry out the decisions of 
the Committee, the Advisory Committee or the Board, as the case may be.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Eligibility for 
re-nomination of the members of the committee, Advisory Committee and the Board.—An 
outgoing member shall be eligible for re-nomination for the membership of the 
committee, the Advisory Committee or the Board of which he was a member.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Resignation of the 
Chairman and members of the Committee and the Board and filling of the casual 
vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A member of the Committee or the Board, other than the Chairman, may, by giving 
notice in writing to the Chairman, resign his membership. The Chairman may 
resign by a letter addressed to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A resignation shall 
take effect from the date of communication of its acceptance or on the expiry of 
30 days from the date of resignation whichever is earlier.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When a vacancy occurs 
or is likely to occur in the membership of the committee or the Board, the 
Chairman shall submit a report to the Central Government immediately. The 
Central Government shall take steps to fill the vacancy.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Cessation and 
restoration of membership.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If a member of the committee, Advisory Committee, or the Board fails to attend 
three consecutive meetings, he shall, subject to the provisions of sub-rule (2), 
cease to be a member thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person, who ceases 
to be a member under sub-rule (1) shall be given intimation of such cessation by 
a letter sent to him by registered post within fifteen days from the date of 
such cessation. The letter shall indicate that if he desires restoration of his 
membership, he may apply therefor within thirty days from the receipt of such 
letter. The application for restoration of membership, if received within the 
said period, shall be placed before the committee, the Advisory Committee or the 
Board, as the case may be, and if a majority of members present at the next 
meeting is satisfied that the reasons for failure to attend three consecutive 
meetings are adequate, the member shall be restored to membership immediately 
after a resolution or to that effect is adopted.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Disqualification.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person shall be disqualified for being nominated as, and for being a member of 
the committee, Advisory Committee or the Board, as the case may be—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  if he is 
declared to be of unsound mind by a competent court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  if he is an 
undischarged insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  if before 
or after the commencement of the Act, he has been convicted of an offence 
involving moral turpitude.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any question arises 
whether a disqualification has been incurred under sub-rule (1), the decision of 
the Central Government thereon shall be final.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Meetings.—The 
Chairman may, subject to the provisions of rule 12, call a meeting of the 
committee, Advisory Committee or the Board, as the case may be, at any time he 
thinks fit:
 
Provided that on a 
requisition in writing from not less than one-half of the members, the Chairman 
shall call a meeting within fifteen days from the date of the receipt of such 
requisition.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Notice of meetings.—The 
Chairman shall fix the date, time and place of every meeting and a notice in 
writing containing the aforesaid particulars along with a list of business to be 
conducted at the meeting shall be sent to each member by registered post at 
least fifteen days before the date fixed for such meeting:
 
Provided that in the case 
of an emergent meeting, notice of seven days only may be given to every member.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman shall preside at the meetings of the committee, Advisory Committee 
or the Board, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the absence of the 
Chairman at any meeting, the members shall elect from amongst themselves by a 
majority of votes, a member, who shall preside at such meeting.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>14</number> Quorum.—No 
business shall be transacted at any meeting unless at least one-third of the 
members are present:
 
Provided that if at any 
meeting less than one-third of the members are present, the Chairman may adjourn 
the meeting to a date not later than seven days from the date of the original 
meeting and it shall thereupon be lawful to dispose of the business at such 
adjourned meeting irrespective of the number of members present:
 

2[Provided further 
that the date, time and place of such adjourned meeting shall be intimated to 
all the members by telegram or by a written communication.]]
 
 




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Disposal of 
business.—All 
business shall be considered at a meeting of the committee, Advisory Committee 
or the Board, as the case may be, and shall be decided by a majority of the 
votes of members present and voting. In the event of an equality of votes, the 
Chairman shall have a casting vote:
 
Provided that the Chairman 
may, if he thinks fit, direct that any matter shall be decided by the 
circulation of necessary papers and by securing written opinion of the members:
 
Provided further that no 
decision on any matter under the preceding proviso shall be taken, unless 
supported by not less than two-thirds, majority of the members.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Method of voting.—Voting 
shall ordinarily be by show of hands, but if any member asks for voting by 
ballot, or if the Chairman so decides, the voting shall be by secret ballot and 
shall be held in such manner as the Chairman may decide.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Proceedings of the 
meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The proceedings of each meeting inter alia the names of the members 
present there shall be forwarded to each member and to the Central Government as 
soon after the meeting as possible, and in any case, not less than seven days 
before the next meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The proceedings of 
each meeting shall be confirmed with such modifications, if any, as may be 
considered necessary at the next meeting.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Summoning of 
witnesses and production of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A committee, Advisory Committee or the Board may summon any person to appear as 
a witness in the course of an enquiry. Such summons may require a witness to 
appear before it on a date specified therein and to produce any books, papers or 
other documents and things in his possession or under his control relating to 
any matter to the enquiry.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A summons under 
sub-rule (1) may be addressed to an individual or an organisation of employers 
or a registered trade union of workers.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A summons under this 
rule may be served—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  in the case 
of an individual, by being delivered or sent to him by registered post;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  in the case 
of an employers’ organisation or the registered trade union of workers by being 
delivered or sent by registered post to the secretary or other principal officer 
of the organisation or union, as the case may be.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The provisions of the 
Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), relating to the summoning and 
enforcement of the appearance of witnesses and the production of documents 
shall, so far as may be, apply to proceedings before a Committee, Advisory 
Committee or the Board.
 

1[(5) All books, 
papers and other documents or things produced before a committee, or the Board 
in pursuance of a summons issued under sub-rule (1) may be inspected by the 
Chairman and independent members, and also by such parties as the Chairman may 
allow with the consent of the other party, but the information so obtained shall 
be treated as ‘confidential’ and the same shall be made public only with the 
consent in writing of the party concerned:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this rule shall apply to the disclosure of any such information for 
the purpose of a prosecution under section 193 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
1860).]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Expenses of 
witnesses.—Every 
person who is summoned and appears as a witness before the committee, the 
Advisory Committee or the Board shall be entitled to an allowance for expenses 
by him in accordance with the scale for the time being in force for payment of 
such allowance to witnesses appearing in Civil Courts in the State.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Mode of computation 
of the cash value of wages.—The 
retail prices at the nearest market shall be taken into account in computing the 
cash value of wages paid in kind and of essential commodities supplied at 
concessional rates. This computation shall be made in accordance with such 
directions as may be issued by the Central Government from time to time.
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Time and conditions of payment of wages and the deduction permissible from wages. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> (i) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[The wages of a worker in any scheduled employment] shall be paid on a working day,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in the case of establishment for which less than one thousand persons are employed, before the expiry of the seventh day, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in the case of other establishments before the expiry of the tenth day after the last day of the wage period in respect of which the wages are payable. 
</subsection>
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Where the employment of any person is terminated by or on behalf of the employer, the wages earned by him shall be paid before the expiry of the second working day after the day on which his employment is terminated. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The wages of an employed person shall be paid to him without deduction of any kind except those authorised by or under these rules. 
 Explanation. —(1) Every payment made by the employed person to the employer or his agent shall, for the purposes of these rules be deemed to be a deduction from wages. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Deductions from the wages of a person employed in a scheduled employment shall be of one or more of the following kinds, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> fines in respect of such acts and omissions on the part of employed persons as may be specified by the Central Government by general or special order in this behalf; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> deductions for absence from duty; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> deductions from damage to or loss of goods expressly entrusted to the employed person for custody, or for loss of money for which he is required to account, where such damage or loss is directly attributable to his neglect or default; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> deductions for house accommodation supplied by the employer; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> deductions for such amenities and services supplied by the employer as the Central Government may, by general or special order, authorise; 
</subsection>
 Explanation. —The words ‘amenities and services' in this clause do not include the supply of tools and protectives required for the purposes of employment; 
 
 <subsection><number>vi</number> deductions for recovery of advances or for adjustment of overpayment of wages: 
 Provided that such advances do not exceed an amount equal to wages for two calendar months of the employed person and, in no case, shall the monthly instalment of deduction exceed one-fourth of the wages earned in that month; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> deductions of income-tax payable by the employed person; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> deductions required to be made by order of a Court or other competent authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> deductions for subscriptions to and for repayment of advances from any Provident Fund to which the Provident Funds Act, 1952 (19 of 1952), applies or any Recognised Provident Fund as defined in section 58A of the Indian Income Tax Act, 1922 (11 of 1922), or any Provident Fund approved in this behalf by the Central Government during the continuance of such approval; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>x</number> deductions for payment to Co-operative Societies <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[or deductions for recovery of loans advanced by an employer from out of a fund maintained for the purpose by the employer and approved in this behalf by the Central Government] or deductions made with the written authorisation of the person employed, for payment of any premium on his life insurance policy to the Life Insurance Corporation of India established under the Life Insurance Act, 1956 (31 of 1956);] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>xi</number> deductions for recovery of adjustment of amounts, other than wages paid to the employed person in error in excess of what is due to him;] 
 <subsubsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>xii</number> deductions made with the written authorisation of the employed persons (which may be given once generally and not necessarily every time a deduction is made), for the purchase of securities of the Government of India or of any State Government or for being deposited in any Post Office Savings Bank in furtherance of any savings scheme of any such Government;] 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>xiii</number> deductions made with the written authorisation of the employed person for contributions to the National Defence Fund or the Prime Minister's National Relief Fund or to any Defence Savings Scheme <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[approved by the Central Government] or to such other Fund as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf;] 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>xiv</number> deductions for recovery of loans granted for house building or other purposes approved by the Central Government, and for the interest due in respect of such loans, subject to any rules made or approved by the Central Government regulating the extent to which such loans may be granted and the rate of interest payable thereon,] 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 Provided that prior approval of the Inspector or any other officer authorised by the Central Government in this behalf is obtained in writing before making the deductions, unless the employee gives his consent in writing to such deductions. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules, the total amount of deductions which may be made under sub-rule (2) in any wage period, from the wages of an employee shall not exceed— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> 75 per cent. of such wages in cases where such deductions are wholly or partly made for payments to Consumer Co-operative Stores run by any Co-operative Society under clause (x) of  
    sub-rule (2); and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> 50 per cent. of such wages in any other case: 
</subsection>
 Provided that where the total amount of deductions which have to be made under sub-rule (2) in any wage period from the wages of any employee exceeds the limit specified in clause (i), or, as the case may be, clause (ii) of this sub-rule, the excess shall be carried forward and recovered from the wages of succeeding wage period or wage periods, as the case may be, in such number of instalments as may be necessary.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any person desiring to impose a fine on an employed person or to make a deduction for damage or loss caused by him shall explain to him personally and also in writing the act or omission or the damage or loss, in respect of which the fine or deduction is proposed to be imposed or made and give him an opportunity to offer any explanation in the presence of another person. The amount of the said fine or deduction shall also be intimated to him. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>4</number> The amount of fine or deduction for damage or loss mentioned in sub-rule (3) shall be subject to such limits as may be specified in this behalf by the Central Government. All such fines imposed and deductions made shall be recorded in the register maintained in Forms I and II, respectively. These registers shall be kept at the workspot and maintained up-to-date. Where no fine or deduction has been imposed or made on or from any employee in a wage period, a ‘nil' entry shall be made across the body of the relevant register at the end of the wage period, indicating also in precise terms the wage period to which the ‘nil' entry relates.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> Every employer shall send annually a return in Form III <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[***] so as to reach the Inspector not later than the 1st February following the end of the year to which it relates.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> The amount of fine imposed under sub-rule (3) shall be utilised only for such purposes beneficial to the employees as are approved by the Central Government.] 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Nothing in this rule shall be deemed to affect the provisions of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936). 













</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>22</number> Publicity to the minimum wage 
fixed under the Act.—Notices in 1[Form IXA] containing the minimum 
rates of wages fixed together with 2[extracts of] the Act, the rules 
made thereunder and the name and address of the Inspector shall be displayed in 
English and in a language understood by the majority of the workers in the 
employment 2[at the main entrances to the 
establishment and at its office] and shall be maintained in a clean and legible 
condition. Such notices shall also be displayed on the notice-boards of all 
sub-divisional and district offices.
  



</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[ <title><number>23</number> Weekly day of rest. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of this rule, an employee in a scheduled employment in respect of which minimum rates of wages have been fixed under the Act, shall be allowed a day of rest every week (hereinafter referred to as the ‘rest day') which shall ordinarily be Sunday, but the employer may fix any other day of the week as the rest day for any employee or class of employees in that scheduled employment: 
 Provided that the employee has worked in the scheduled employment under the same employer for a continuous period of not less than six days: 
 Provided further that the employee shall be informed of the day fixed as the rest day and of any subsequent change in the rest day before the change is effected, by display of a notice to that effect in the place of employment at the place specified by the Inspector in this behalf.] 
 Explanation. —For the purpose of computation of the continuous period of not less than six days specified in the first proviso to this sub-rule— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> any day on which an employee is required to attend for work but is given only an allowance for attendance and is not provided with work, <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[***] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any day on which an employee is laid off on payment of compensation under the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947); <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any leave or holiday, with or without pay, granted by the employer to an employee in the period of six days immediately preceding the rest day], 
 shall be deemed to be days on which the employee has worked. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any such employee shall not be required or allowed to work in a scheduled employment on the rest day unless he has or will have a substituted rest day for a whole day on one of the five days immediately before or after the rest day: 
 Provided that no substitution shall be made which will result in the employee working for more than ten days consecutively without a rest day for a whole day. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where in accordance with the foregoing provisions of this rule, any employee works on a rest day and has been given a substituted rest day on any one of the five days before or after the rest day, the rest day shall, for the purpose of calculating the weekly hours of work, be included in the week in which the substituted rest day occurs. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An employee shall be granted for rest day wages calculated at the rate applicable to the next preceding day and in case he works on the rest day and has been given a substituted rest day, he shall be paid wages for the rest day on which he worked, at the overtime rate and wages for the substituted rest day at the rate applicable to the next preceding day: 
 Provided that where the minimum daily rate of wages of the employee as notified under the Act has been worked out by dividing the minimum monthly rate of wages by twenty-six, or where the actual daily rate of wages of the employee has been worked out by dividing the monthly rate of wages by twenty-six and such actual daily rates of wages is not less than the notified minimum daily rate of wages of the employee, no wages for the rest day shall be payable, and in the case the employee works on the rest day and has been given a substituted rest day, he shall be paid, only for the rest day on which he worked, an amount equal to the wages payable to him at the overtime rate; and if any dispute arises whether the daily rate of wages has been worked out as aforesaid, the Chief Labour Commissioner may, on application made to him in this behalf, decide the same, after giving an opportunity to the parties concerned to make written representations: 
 Provided further that in the case of an employee governed by a piece-rate scheme, the wages for the rest day, or, as the case may be, the rest day, and the substituted rest day, shall be such as the Central Government may, by notification in the Gazette of India, prescribe, having regard to the minimum rate of wages fixed under the Act, in respect of the scheduled employment. 
 Explanation. —In this sub-rule ‘next preceding day' means the last day on which the employee has worked, which precedes the rest day or the substituted rest day, as the case may be; and where the substituted rest day falls on a day immediately after the rest day, the next preceding day means the last day on which the employee has worked, which precedes the rest day. 
 <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>5</number>] The provisions of this rule shall not operate to the prejudice of more favourable terms, if any, to which an employee may be entitled under any other law or under the terms of any award, agreement or contract of service, and in such a case, the employee shall be entitled only to the more favourable terms aforesaid. 
 Explanation. —For the purposes of this rule, ‘week' shall mean a period of seven days beginning at midnight on Saturday night. 






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Number of hours of 
work which shall constitute a normal working day.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The number of hours which shall constitute a normal working day, shall be—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  in the case 
of an adult, 9 hours;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  in the case 
of a child, 4½ hours.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The working day of an 
adult worker shall be so arranged that inclusive of the intervals of rest, if 
any, shall not spread over more than twelve hours on any day.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The number of hours of 
work in the case of an adolescent shall be the same as that of an adult or a 
child accordingly as he is certified to work as an adult or a child by a 
competent medical practitioner approved by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The provisions of 
sub-rules (1) to (3) shall, in the case of workers in agricultural employment, 
be subject to such modifications as may, from time to time, be notified by the 
Central Government.
 

1[(4A) No child 
shall be employed or permitted to work for more than 4½ hours on any day.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall be deemed to affect the provisions of the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 
1948).
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>24A</number> Night 
shifts.—Where a worker in a scheduled employment works on a shift which 
extends beyond midnight—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  a holiday 
for the whole day for the purposes of rule 23 shall, in his case mean a period 
of twenty-four consecutive hours beginning from the time when his shift ends; 
and 
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  the 
following day in such a case shall be deemed to be the period of twenty-four 
hours beginning from the time when such shift ends, and the hours after midnight 
during which such worker was engaged in work shall be counted towards the 
previous day.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>25</number> Extra wages 
for overtime.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a worker works in an employment for more than nine hours on any day or for 
more than forty-eight hours in any week, he shall in respect of overtime work, 
be entitled to wages,—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  in the case 
of employment in agriculture, at one and a half times the ordinary rate of 
wages;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  in the case 
of any other scheduled employment, at double the ordinary rate of wages.
 
 Explanation.—The 
expression ‘ordinary rate of wages’ means the basic wage plus such 
allowance including the cash equivalent of the advantages accruing through the 
concessional sale to the person employed of foodgrains and other articles as the 
person employed is for the time being entitled to but does not include a bonus.]
 

2[(2) A register of 
overtime shall be maintained by every employer in Form IV in which entries under 
the columns specified therein shall be made as and when overtime is worked in 
any establishment. The register shall be kept at the work-spot and maintained 
up-to-date. Where no overtime has been worked in any wage-period, a ‘nil’ entry 
shall be made across the body of the register at the end of the wage-period 
indicating also in precise terms the wage-period to which the ‘nil’ entry 
relates.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this rule 
shall be deemed to affect the provisions of the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 
1948).
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Form of registers 
and records.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
A register of wages shall be maintained by every employer at the work-spot in 
Form X.
 

2[(1A) Every 
employer shall in respect of each person employed in the establishment, complete 
the entries pertaining to a wage period—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  in columns 1 
to 15 of Form X, before the date on which the wages for such wage-period fall 
due;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  in columns 
16 and 17 of the said Form, on the date when payment is made and obtain the 
signature or thumb impression of the employee in column 18 of the said Form on 
the date when payment is made.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A wage slip in Form XI 
shall be issued by every employer to every person employed by him at least a day 
prior to the disbursement of wages.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every employer shall 
get the signature or thumb-impression of every person employed on the 

3[Register of 
Wages] and wage slip.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Entries in the 

3[Register of 
Wages] and wage slips shall be authenticated by the employer or any person 
authorised by him in this behalf.
 

4[(5) A Muster Roll 
shall be maintained by every employer at the work-spot and kept in Form V and 
the attendance of each person employed in the establishment shall be recorded 
daily in that Form within 3 hours of the commencement of the work shift or relay 
for the day as the case may be.]
 

5[***]
 
 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>26A</number> 
Preservation of registers.—A register required to be maintained under rules 
21(4), 25(2) and 26
<section><number>1</number> and 

2[the muster roll 
required to be maintained under rule 26(5)] shall be preserved for a period of 
three years after the date of last entry made therein.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>26B</number> 
Production of registers and other records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All registers and records required to be maintained by an employer under these 
rules shall be produced on demand before the Inspector during the course of 
inspection of the establishment:
 
Provided that the 
Inspector may, if it is necessary, demand the production of the registers and 
records in his office or such other public place as may be nearer to the 
employer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any infringement of 
the provisions of the Act or these rules noticed by the Inspector and 
communicated to the employer during the course of an inspection or otherwise 
shall be rectified by the employer and compliance report in respect thereof 
shall be submitted to the Inspector, on or before the date specified by him in 
this behalf.]
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article>1[<number>26C</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in these rules, where a combined (alternative) form is sought to be 
used by the employer to avoid duplication of work for compliance with the 
provisions of any other Act or the rules framed thereunder, an alternative 
suitable form in lieu of any of the forms prescribed under these rules may be 
used with the previous approval of the 2[Central Government]].
  



</article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>27</number> 
Applications.—
<section><number>1</number> An application under sub-section (2) of section 20 or 
sub-section (1) of section 21, by or on behalf of an employed person or group of 
employed persons shall be made in duplicate in Forms VI, VIA or VII, as the case 
may be, one copy of which shall bear the prescribed court-fee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A single application 
under section 20, read with sub-section (1) of section 21 may be presented on 
behalf or in respect of a group of employed persons, if they are borne on the 
same establishment and their claim relates to the same wage-period or periods.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Authorisation.—The 
authorisation to act on behalf of an employed person or persons, under 
sub-section (2) of section 20 or sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 21 shall be given in 
Form VIII by an instrument which shall be presented to the Authority hearing the 
application and shall form part of the record.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Appearance of 
parties.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
an application under sub-section (2) of section 20 or section 21 is entertained, 
the Authority shall serve upon the employer by registered post a notice in Form 
IX to appear before him on a specified date with all relevant documents and 
witnesses, if any, and shall inform the applicant of the date as specified.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the employer or his 
representative fails to appear on the specified date, the Authority may hear and 
determine the application ex parte.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the applicant or 
his representative fails to appear on the specified date, the Authority may 
dismiss the application.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An order passed under 
sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (3) may be set aside on sufficient cause being shown by 
the defaulting party within one month of the date of the said order, and the 
application shall then be re-heard after service of notice on the opposite party 
of the date fixed for re-hearing in the manner specified in sub-rule (1).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Costs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority, for reasons to be recorded in writing, may direct that the cost 
of any proceeding before it shall not follow the event.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The costs which may be 
awarded shall include,—
 <subsection>
               <number>i</number>  
expenses incurred on account of court-fees;
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>ii</number>  
expenses incurred on subsistence money to witness; and
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number>  
pleader’s fees to the extent of ten rupees provided that the Authority in any 
proceeding may reduce the fees to a sum not less than five rupees or for reasons 
to be recorded in writing increase it to a sum not exceeding twenty-five rupees.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where there are more 
than one pleaders or more than one applicants or opponents the Authority may, 
subject as aforesaid, award to the successful party or parties such costs as it 
may deem proper.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Court-fees.—The 
court-fees payable in respect of proceeding under section 20 shall be—
 <section>
          <number>i</number>  for every 
application to summon a witness—one rupee in respect of each witness;
 </section><section>
         <number>ii</number>  for every 
application made by or on behalf of an individual—one rupee;
 

          1[(iii) 
for every application made on behalf or in respect of a number of employees—one 
rupee per employee subject to a maximum of twenty rupees:]
 
Provided that the 
Authority may, if in its opinion, the applicant is a pauper, exempt him wholly 
or partly from the payment of such fees:
 
Provided further that no 
fee shall be chargeable—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  from persons 
employed in agriculture; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  in respect 
of an application made by an Inspector.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 
 
 <article><title><footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>32</number> Saving.</title> — These rules shall not apply in relation to any scheduled employment in so far as there are in force rules applicable to such employment, which, in the opinion of the Central Government, make equally satisfactory provisions for the matters dealt with by these rules and such opinion shall be final.] 





</article><form>
 




THE MINIMUM WAGES (CENTRAL) RULES, 1950
 


 
 




1[Form 
XI
 


[Rule 26(2)]
 




Wage slip
 


Name of the 
establishment....................................
 



Place..............................................
 


1.   Name of employee with
 


      father's/husband's 
name..........................................
 


2.   Designation
 


3.   Wages Period.
 


4.   Rate of wages payable:
 


      (a) Basic
 


      (b) D.A.
 


5.   Total attendance/units 
of work done
 


6.   Overtime wages.
 


7.   Gross wages payable
 


8.   Total deductions
 


9.   Net wages paid
 


 
 



..............................                                                                                    ................................................................
 



Pay-in-charge                                                                                             Employee's signature/thumb impression].
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by the Minimum 
Wages (Central) (Amdt.) Rules, 1966.
 



</form><form>
 




THE MINIMUM WAGES (CENTRAL) RULES, 1950
 


 
 




1[Form 
VI
 




Form of Application by an Employee Under section 20(2)
 


In 
the Court of the Authority appointed under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, 
for............................area.
 


Application 
No........................... of 20.........
 



(1).......................................................................Applicant 
(through........................ a legal practitioner/an official of 
................... which is a registered Trade Union),
 



Address................................................
 


Versus
 



(1)................................................
 



(2)................................................
 



(3)................................................                                                                        
Opponent(s)
 



Address................................................
 


The applicant above named 
states as follows:—
 


       (1)  The applicant 
was/has been employed from.............to..........as..........(Category) 
in........................(establishment) of Shri/Messrs...............engaged 
in............... (nature of work) which is a scheduled employment within the 
meaning of section 2(g) of the Minimum Wages Act.
 


        (2)  The opponent(s) 
is/are the employer(s) within the meaning of section 2(a) of the Minimum Wages 
Act.
 


      (3) *(a)  The 
applicant has been paid wages at less than the minimum rate of wages fixed for 
his category of employment under the Act by Rs.........per day for the period 
from.........to...........;
 


            *(b)  The 
applicant has not been paid wages at Rs.....................per day for weekly 
days of rest from........to..........;
 


            *(c)  The 
applicant has not been paid wages at the over time rate for the period 
from................to............
 


        (4)  The applicant 
estimates the value of relief sought by him on each account as under:
 


              (a)  Rs..............................
 


              (b)  Rs..............................
 


              (c)  Rs..............................
 


      Total Rs..............................
 


        (5)  The applicant, 
therefore, prays that a direction may be issued under section 20(3) of the Act 
for:
 


            *(a)  payment 
of the difference between the wages payable under the Minimum Wages Act and the 
wages actually paid.
 


            *(b)  payment 
of remuneration for the days of rest.
 


            *(c)  payment 
of wages at the overtime rates.
 



               2[(d)  
compensation amounting to Rs........]
 


        (6)  The applicant 
begs leave to amend or add to or make alterations in the application, if and 
when necessary, with the permission of the Authority.
 


        (7)  The applicant 
does solemnly declare that the facts stated in this application are true to the 
best of his knowledge, belief and information.
 



Date..........................                                                                                             
Signature or thumb impression 
                                                                                                                                       of 
the employed person, or legal 
                                                                                                                                       practitioner 
or official of a 
                                                                                                                                       Registered 
Trade Union duly 
                                                                                                                                       authorised.
 


* Delete the portions not 
required.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1301, dated 28th October, 1960.
 


   2.  Ins. by the Minimum 
Wages (Central) (Second Amendment) Rules, 1961.
</form><form>
 




THE MINIMUM WAGES (CENTRAL) RULES, 1950
 


 
 



1[Form 
VIA]
 




Form of Group Application Under section 21(1)
 


In the Court of the 
Authority appointed under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, 

for.......................... area
 


Application 
No.........................of 20................
 


Between A.B.C. and (state 
the number)............................others:
 


Applicants (through a legal 
practitioner/an official of ......................... which is a registered 
trade Union),
 



Address..........................
 


and
 


x.y.z 
...........................................................opposite party
 



Address..........................
 


The applicants state as 
follows:—
 


        (1)  The applicants 
whose names appear in the attached schedule were/have been employed 
from.............. to................ as............... 
(categories).................... in................ (establishment) of Shri/Messrs............. 
engaged in .................... (nature of work) which is/are scheduled 
employments) within the meaning of section 2(g) of the Minimum Wages Act.
 


        (2)  The opponent(s) 
is/are the employer(s) within the meaning of section 2(e) of the Minimum Wages 
Act.
 


      (3) *(a)  the 
applicants have been paid wages at less than the minimum rates of wages fixed 
for their category (categories) of employment(s) under the Act by Rs................  
per day for the period (s) from...............to.......
 


            *(b)  The 
applicants have not been paid wages at Rs............. per day for the weekly 
days of rest from..............to..................:
 


            *(c)  The 
applicants have not been paid wages at the overtime rates(s) for the period 
from............ to........................
 


        (4)  The applicants 
estimate the value of relief sought by them on each account as under:
 


              (a)  Rs........................
 


               (b  Rs........................
 


              (c)  Rs........................
 


Total Rs.....................
 


        (5)  The 
applicants, therefore, pray that a direction may be issued under section 20(3) 
of the Act for:
 


            *(a)  payment 
of the difference between the wages payable under the Minimum Wages Act and the 
wages actually paid;
 


            *(b)  payment 
of remuneration for the days of rest;
 


            *(c)  payment 
of wages at the overtime rate(s);
 



               2[(d)  
compensation amounting to Rs........]
 


        (6)  The applicants 
beg leave to amend or add to or make alterations in the application, if and when 
necessary, with the permission of the Authority.
 


        (7)  The applicants 
do solemnly declare that the facts stated in this application are true to the 
best of their knowledge, belief and information.
 



Date........................                                                                                   
Signature or thumb impression of the 

                                                                                                                        
employed persons or legal practitioner, or 
                                                                                                                         official 
of a Registered Trade Union duly 
                                                                                                                         authorised.
 


*Delete the portions not 
required.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1301, dated 28th October, 1960.
 


   2.  Ins. by the Minimum 
Wages (Central) (Second Amendment) Rules, 1961.
 


 
</form><form>
 

THE 
MINIMUM WAGES (CENTRAL) RULES, 1950
 

 
 

Form 
VIII
 

Form 
in Authority in favour of a Legal Practitioner or any Official  
of a 
Registered Trade Union referred to in section 20(2)
 

In the 
Court of the Authority appointed under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 
for.....................................area.
 

Application 
No.....................of 20..........
 

(1)..........................................................................................................................
 

(2).......................................................................................................Applicant(s)†
 

(3) 
.......................................................................................................................
 

Versus
 

(1) 
...................................................................................................................................
 

(2) 
.......................................................................................................Opponent(s)
 

(3) 
......................................................................................................................
 

I hereby authorise Mr. 
..........................a legal practitioner/an official of the registered 
trade union of .......................... to appear and act on my behalf in the 
above described proceedings and to do all things incidental to such appearing 
and acting.
 

 
 

Date.......................                                                                                                             
Signature or thumb impression
 

                                                                                                                                           
of the employee.</form><form>
 




THE MINIMUM WAGES (CENTRAL) RULES, 1950
 


 
 




Form IX
 




Form of summons to the opponent to appear before the authority  

when an application under sub-section (2) of section 20 or  

under section 21 is entertained
 



(Title of the application)
 



To...................................................(Name, description and 
place of residence)
 



Whereas........................has made the above said application to me under 
the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, you are hereby summoned to appear before me in 
person or by a duly authorised agent, and able to answer all material questions 
relating to the application, or who shall be accompanied by some person able to 
answer all such questions on the.........day of ........20............. 
at................ O'clock in the................. noon, to answer the claim; 
and as the day fixed for the appearance is appointed for the final disposal of 
the application, you must be prepared to produce on that day all the witnesses 
upon whose evidence and all the documents upon which you intend to rely in 
support of your defence.
 


Take notice that in default 
of your appearance on the day before mentioned, the application will be heard 
and determined in your absence.
 


 
 



Date.....................        
                                                                                                                                         
Signature.
 


 
 


    †  When the application 
is by a group of employees, the thumb-impressions or signatures of two of the 
applicants need be put to the application and a full list of applicants should 
be attached to the application.
</form><form>
 




THE MINIMUM WAGES (CENTRAL) RULES, 1950
 


 
 




1[FORM 
IXA
 



(Rule 22)
 




Notice
 



2[Abstracts 
of] the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 and the  

rule made thereunder
 


I. Whom the Act affects
 


    1. (a) The Act applies 
to persons engaged on scheduled employments or in specified class of work in 
respect of which minimum wages have been fixed.
 


        (b) No employee can 
give up by contract or agreement his rights in so far as it purports to reduce 
the minimum rates of wages fixed under the Act.
 


II. Definition of wages
 


(1) ‘Wages’ means all 
remuneration payable to an employed person on the fulfilment of his contract of 
employment 

3[and includes house 
rent allowance]. It excludes—
 


         (i)  the value of 
any house‑accommodation, supply of light, water, medical attendance or any other 
amenity or any service extended by general or special order of the appropriate 
Government;
 


        (ii)  contribution 
paid by the employer to any Pension Fund or Provident Fund or under any scheme 
of Social Insurance;
 


        (iii)  the 
travelling allowance or the value of any travelling concession;
 


       (iv)  the sum paid 
to the person employed to defray special expenses entailed by him by nature of 
his employment;
 


        (v)  gratuity 
payable on discharge.
 


(2) The minimum rate of 
wages may consist of—
 


         (i)  a basic rate 
of wages and special allowance called the cost of living allowance;
 


        (ii)  a basic rate 
of wages with or without a cost of living allowance and the cash value of any 
concessions, like supplies of essential commodities at concession rates; and
 


        (iii)  in all 
inclusive rate comprising basic rate, cost of living allowance and cash value of 
concession, if any.
 


(3) The minimum wages 
payable to employees of scheduled employments notified under section 5 read with 
section 3 or as revised from time to time under section 10, read with section 3, 
may be—
 


        (a)  a minimum time 
rate,
 


        (b)  a minimum 
piece rate,
 


        (c)  a guaranteed 
time rate,
 


        (d)  an overtime 
rate, 
 


differing with (1) 
different scheduled employments, (2) different classes of work, (3) different 
localities, (4) different wage‑periods, and (5) different age groups.
 


III. Computation and 
conditions of payment
 


The employer shall pay to 
every employee engaged in scheduled employment under him wages at a rate not 
less than the minimum rate of wages fixed for that class of employee.
 


The minimum wages payable 
under this Act shall be paid in cash unless the Government authorises payment 
thereof either wholly or partly in kind.
 


Wage‑period shall be fixed 
for the payment of wages at intervals not exceeding one month 

4[or such other 
larger period as may be prescribed].
 


Wage shall be paid on a 
working day within seven days of the end of the wage‑period or within ten days 
if 1000 or more persons are employed.
 


The wages of a person 
discharged shall be paid not later than the second working day after his 
discharge,
 


If an employee is employed 
on any day for a period less than the normal working day, he shall be entitled 
to receive wages for a full normal working day provided his failure to work is 
not caused by his unwillingness to work but by the omission of the employer to 
provide him with work for that period.
 


Where an employee does two 
or more classes of work to each of which a different minimum rate of wages is 
applicable, the employer shall pay to such employee in respect of the time 
respectively occupied in each such class of work, wages at not less than the 
minimum rate in force in respect of each such class.
 


Where an employee is 
employed on piece work for which minimum time rate and not a minimum piece‑rate 
has been fixed, the employer shall pay to such employee wages at not less than 
the minimum time rate,
 


IV. Hours of work and 
holidays
 


The number of hours which 
shall constitute a normal working day shall be—
 


        (a)  in the case of 
an adult, 9 hours
 


        (b)  in the case of 
a child, 4 

1/2 hours.
 


The working day of an adult 
worker inclusive of the intervals of rest shall not exceed twelve hours on any 
day.
 



5[The employer shall 
allow a day of rest with wages to the employees every week. Ordinarily, Sunday 
will be the weekly day of rest, but any other day of the week may be fixed as 
such rest day. No employee shall be required to work on a day fixed as rest day, 
unless he is paid wages for that day at the overtime rate and is also allowed a 
substituted rest day with wages. (See rule 23).]
 


When a worker works in an 
employment for more than nine hours on any day or for more than forty‑eight 
hours in any week, he shall in respect of overtime worked be entitled to wages 
in scheduled employment other than agriculture, at double the ordinary rate of 
wages.
 


V. Fines and deductions
 


No deduction shall be made 
from wages except those authorised by or under the rules.
 


Deductions from the wages 
shall be one or more of the following kinds, namely:—
 


         (i)  Fines: An 
employed person shall be explained personally and also in writing the act or 
omission in respect of which the fine is proposed to be imposed and given an 
opportunity to offer any explanation in the presence of another person. The 
amount of the said fine shall also be intimated to him. 

6[It shall be 
subject to such limits as may be specified in this behalf by the Central 
Government]. It shall be utilised in accordance with the directions of the 
Central Government;
 


        (ii)  deductions 
for absence from duty;
 


        (iii)  deductions 
for damage to or loss of goods entrusted to the employee for custody, or for 
loss of money for which he is required to account, where such damage or loss is 
directly attributable to his neglect or default. The employed person shall be 
explained personally and also in writing the damage or loss, in respect of which 
the deduction is proposed to be made and given an opportunity to offer any 
explanation in the presence of another person. The amount of the said deduction 
shall also be intimated to him. 

7[It shall be 
subject to such limits as may be specified in this behalf by the Central 
Government];
 


       (iv)  deductions for 
house-accommodations supplied by the employer or by a State Government or any 
authority constituted by a State Government for providing housing accommodation8;
 


        (v)  deductions for 
such amenities and services supplied by the employer as the Central Government 
may by general or special order authorise. These will not include the supply of 
tools and protectives required for the purposes of employment;
 


       (vi)  deductions for 
recovery of advances or for adjustment of overpayment of wages, such advances 
shall not exceed an amount equal to wages for two calendar months of the 
employed person and the monthly instalment of deduction shall not exceed 
one‑fourth of the wages earned in that month;
 


       (vii)  deductions of 
income‑tax payable by the employed person,
 


      (viii)  deductions 
required to be made by order of court or other competent authority;
 


       (ix) deductions for 
subscription to and for repayment of advances from any provident fund;
 



       9[(x)  
deductions for payment to co‑operative societies 

10[or deductions for 
recovery of loans advanced by an employer from out of a fund maintained for the 
purpose by the employer and approved in this behalf by the Central Government] 
or deductions made with the written authorisation of the person employed, for 
payment of any premium on his life insurance policy to the Life Insurance 
Corporation of India established under the Life Insurance Act, 1956 (31 of 
1956);
 


       (xi)  deductions for 
recovery or adjustment of amount other than wages, paid to the employed person 
in error or in excess of what is due to him:
 


                    
Provided that prior approval of the Inspector or any other officer authorised by 
the Central Government in this behalf is obtained in writing before making the 
deductions, unless the employee gives his consent in writing to such deduction];
 



    10[(xii)  
deductions made with the written authorisation of the employed person (which may 
be given once generally and not necessarily every time a deduction is made) for 
the purchase of securities of the Government of India or of any State Government 
or for being deposited in any Post Office Savings Bank in furtherance of any 
Savings Scheme of any such Government.
 


Every employer shall send 
annually a return in Form III showing the deductions from wages so as to reach 
the Inspector not later than the 1st February following the end of the year to 
which it relates.] 
 


VI. Maintenance of 
Registers and Records
 


Every employer shall 
maintain at the workspot a register of wages 

11[in the form 
prescribed] specifying the following particulars for each period in respect of 
each employed person:—
 


        (a) the minimum 
rates of wages payable,
 


        (b) the number of 
days in which overtime was worked,
 


        (c) the gross 
wages.
 


        (d) all deductions 
made from wages,
 


        (e) the wages 
actually paid and the date of payment.
 


Every employer shall issue 
wage‑slips 

11[in the form 
prescribed] containing prescribed particulars to every person employed.
 


Every employer shall get 
the signature or the thumb‑impression of every person employed on the wage‑book 
and wage‑slips
 


Entries in the wage‑book 
and wage‑slip, shall be properly authenticated by the employer or his agent.
 



12[A muster‑roll, 
register of fines, register of deductions for damage or loss and register of 
overtime shall be maintained by every employer at the workspot in the form 
prescribed.]
 



12[Every employer 
shall keep exhibited at main entrance to the establishment and its office], 
notice in English and in a language understood by a majority of the workers of 
the following particulars in a clean and legible form:
 


        (a) minimum rate of 
wages,
 


        (b) 

13[abstracts of] the 
Acts and the rules made thereunder,
 


        (c) name and 
address of the Inspector.
 



11[Register of 
wages, muster‑roll, register of fines, register of deductions for damage or loss 
and register of overtime shall be preserved for a period of three years after 
the date of last entry made therein.
 


All registers and records 
required to be maintained by an employer under the rules shall be produced on 
demand before the Inspector provided that where an establishment has been 
closed, the Inspector may demand the production of the registers and records in 
his office or such other place as may be nearer to the employers.]
 


VII. Inspectors
 


An Inspector can enter in 
any premises and can exercise powers of Inspector (including examination of 
document and taking of evidence) as he may deem necessary for carrying out the 
purposes of the Act.
 


VIII. Claims and 
complaints
 


Where an employee is paid 
less than the minimum rates of wages fixed for his class work, or less than the 
amount due to him under the provisions of this Act, he can make an application 
in the prescribed form within six months to the authority appointed for purpose. 
An application delayed beyond this period may be, admitted if the Authority is 
satisfied that the applicant had sufficient cause for not making the application 
within such period.
 


Any legal practitioner, 
official or a registered trade union, Inspector under the Act or other person 
acting with the permission of the Authority can make the complaint on behalf of 
an employed person.
 



14[A single 
application may be presented on behalf of or in respect of a group of employed 
perons whose wages have been delayed, if they are borne on the same 
establishment and their claim relates to the same wage‑period or periods.)
 



15[A complaint under 
section 22(a) relating to payment of less than the minimum rates of wages or 
less than the amount due to an employee under the provisions of the Act can be 
made to the Court only after an application in respect of the facts constituting 
the offence has been presented under section 20 and has been granted wholly, or 
in part, and the appropriate Government or an officer authorised by it in this 
behalf has sanctioned the making of the complaint;
 


A complaint under section 
22(b) or 22(a) regarding contravention of the provisions relating to hours of 
work and weekly day of rest or other miscellaneous offences relating to 
maintenance of registers, submission of returns, etc., can be made to the Court 
by or with the sanction of an Inspector. The time‑limits for making such 
complaints is one month from the date of grant of sanction by the Inspector, in 
the case of offences falling under section 22(b) and six months; from the date 
on which the offence is alleged to have been committed, in the case of offences 
falling under section 22(a).]
 


IX. Action by the 
Authority
 


The Authority may direct 
the payment of the amount by which the minimum wages payable exceed the amount 
actually paid together with the payment of compensation not exceeding ten times 
the amount of such excess. The Authority may direct payment of compensation in 
cases where the excess is paid before the disposal of the application.
 


If a malicious or vexatious 
complaint is made, the Authority may impose a penalty not exceeding Rs. 50 on 
the applicant and order that it be paid to the employer.
 


Every direction of the 
Authority shall be final. 
 


X. 

15[Penalties for 
offences under the Act]
 


Any employer who pays to 
any employee less than the amount due to him under the provisions of this Act or 
infringes any order or rules in respect of normal working day, weekly holiday, 
shall be punishable with imprisonment of either description for a term which may 
extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees or 
with both,
 



15[Any employer who 
contravenes any provision of the Act or of any rule or order made thereunder 
shall, if no other penalty is provided for such contravention by the Act, be 
punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees. If the person 
committing any offence under the Act is a company, every person who at the time 
the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company 
for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly. No such person will be liable to punishment, if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.
 


Any director, manager, 
secretary or other officer of the company with whose consent or connivance an 
offence has been committed is liable to be proceeded against and punished under 
the Act.
 


  Note.—(a)  
“company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
individuals,
 


              (b)  
“director” in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.]
 


XI. Minimum Rates of 
Wages Fixed
 


Name 
of undertaking...................................
 


                 Serial 
No.                                      Category of employees                                       Minimum 
Wages
 


       
...................................                             ...................................                                   
...................................
 


 
 


XII. Name and address of 
Inspector(s)
 



Name                                                                                         
Address
 



...................................                                                               
...................................]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins by S.R.O. 2727, 
dated 11th August, 1954, published in Fort St Geo. Gazette 9-6-1954, Supp. to 
Pt. I, p. 223.
 


   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 109, 
dated 14th January, 1959.
 


   3.  Ins. by G.S.R. 109, 
dated 14th January, 1959.
 


   4. Ins. by G.S.R. 109, 
dated 14th January, 1959.
 


   5. Subs. by G.S.R. 918, 
dated 29th July, 1960.
 


   6. Sub. by G.S.R. 213, 
dated 7th February, 1962.
 


   7. Subs. by G.S.R. 213, 
dated 7th February, 1962.
 


   8. Ins. by G.S.R. 109, 
dated 14th January, 1959.
 


   9. Subs. by G.S.R. 109, 
dated 14th January, 1959. 
 


  10. Ins by G.S.R 213, 
dated 7th February, 1962.
 


  11. Ins. by G.S.R. 213, 
dated 7th February, 1962.
 


  12. Subs. by G.S.R. 213, 
dated 7th February, 1962.
 


  13. Subs. by G.S.R. 109, 
dated 14th January, 1959.
 


  14. Subs. by G.S.R. 213, 
dated 7th February, 1962.
 


  15. Subs. by G.S.R. 109, 
dated 14th January, 1959.
 


 
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 109, dated 14th January, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 659, dated 26th July, 1958.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 717, dated 15th June, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by S.R.O. 298, dated 23rd January, 1957.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 627, dated 22nd April, 1961.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 676, dated 7th June, 1980. Earlier item (xiii) was inserted by G.S.R. 945, dated 23rd May, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Corrected by G.S.R. 463 (E), dated 2nd August, 1980.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 676, dated 7th June, 1980.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 1060, dated 3rd September, 1980.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 1060, dated 3rd September, 1980.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 1542, dated 8th November, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by S.R.O. 2574, dated 2nd August, 1954.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Ins. by 
S.R.O. 2727, dated 11th August, 1954.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 918, dated 29th July, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 918, dated 29th July, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 1324, dated 2nd August, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 1324, dated 2nd August, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Sub-rule (5) omitted by G.S.R. 158, dated 10th January, 1979 (w.e.f. 27-1-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>Sub-rule (6) renumbered as sub-rule (5) thereof by G.S.R. 158, dated 10th January, 1979 (w.e.f. 27-1-1979).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Ins. by S.R.O. 3304, 
dated 2nd October, 1954.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>  Added by S.R.O. 
1932, dated 6th October, 1954.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 158, 
dated 10th January, 1979.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1060, dated 3rd September, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1473, dated 17th September, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 139, 
dated 16th January, 1974. Earlier sub-rule (1A) was inserted by G.S.R. 1473, 
dated 17th September, 1966.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 721, 
dated 5th May, 1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 139, 
dated 16th January, 1974.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>  Sub-rule (6) omitted 
by G.S.R. 1213, dated 9th July, 1963. Earlier sub-rule (6) was inserted by G.S.R. 
1512, dated 15th December, 1961.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 1060, 
dated 3rd September, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 1523, 
dated 16th December, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 255, 
dated 20th February, 1967. Earlier rule 26B was inserted by G.S.R. 1523, dated 
16th December, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>  Ins. by 
G.S.R. 1213, dated 9th July, 1963.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 846, dated 19th July, 1984.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1301, dated 28th October, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 1301, 
dated 28th October, 1960.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>Subs. by S.R.O. 463, dated 28th February, 1955.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>