<act><tid>1303562</tid>
<title>THE IRON AND STEEL COMPANIES AMALGAMATION ACT, <year>1952</year></title>

ACT NO. 79 OF <year>1952</year>
[ 29th December, <year>1952</year>.]

An Act to make special provision, in the interests of the general 
public and the Union, for the amalgamation of certain companies 
closely connected with each other in the manufacture and 
production of iron and steel, and for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

WHEREAS for the purpose of securing, in the interest of the 
general public and the Union, the efficient and economical expansion 
and working of the iron and steel industry in India, it is essential 
that the Steel Corporation of Bengal, Limited, and the Indian Iron and 
Steel Company, Limited, which are engaged in the manufacture and 
production of iron and steel, should be amalgamated;

AND WHEREAS to give effect to the scheme of the Central 
Government for the expansion of the iron and steel industry and to 
make available further resources for such expansion, it is necessary 
that the said companies should be amalgamated with as little delay as 
possible;

AND WHEREAS the amalgamation of the said companies is also in 
pursuance of successive recommendations made by the Tariff Board and 
the Tariff Commission;

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--





<article><tid>1013001</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>87397</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Iron and Steel Companies Amalgamation Act, <year>1952</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1307394</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 29th day of 
October, <year>1952</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1122661</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>561981</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of January, <year>1953</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>332759</tid>
<number>b</number>" the dissolved company" means the Steel Corporation of 
Bengal, Limited, formed and registered under the Indian 
Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7 of <year>1913</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>942906</tid>
<number>c</number>" the Iron and Steel Company" means the Indian Iron and 
Steel Company, Limited, formed and registered under the 
Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7 of <year>1913</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>842355</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>987744</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amalgamation of certain companies engaged in the iron and 
steel industry.
<section><tid>671343</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day, the undertaking of the  
Steel Corporation of Bengal, Limited, shall be transferred to and 
shall vest in the Iron and Steel Company.

</section>

<section><tid>186594</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertaking of the dissolved company shall be deemed to 
include all rights, powers, authorities and privileges and all 
property, movable or immovable, including cash balances, reserves, 
revenue balances, investments and all other interests and rights in or 
arising out of such property as may belong to, or be in the possession 
of, the dissolved company immediately before the appointed day, and 
all books, accounts and documents relating thereto, and shall also be 
deemed to include all debts, liabilities and obligations of whatever 
kind then existing of the dissolved company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>693558</tid>
<number>4</number>Special provision for the transfer of certain items of 
property. For the purposes of this Act, all the profits of the 
dissolved company for the year <year>1952</year> and the revenue reserves of the 
dissolved company, when transferred to the Iron and Steel Company 
under the provisions of this Act, shall be deemed to be respectively 
the profits of the Iron and Steel Company for the said year and 
revenue reserves of the said Company:
Provided that nothing in this section shall entitle a director or 
a managing agent of the Iron and Steel Company to any commission or 
other remuneration in respect of any profits so transferred.



</article>



<article><tid>1456549</tid>
<number>5</number>Saving of contracts, etc., to which the dissolved company is a 
party. Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, all 
contracts, deeds, bonds, agreements and other instruments of whatever 
nature to which the dissolved company is a party, subsisting or having 
effect immediately before the appointed day, shall be of as full force 
and effect against or in favour of the Iron and Steel Company, as the 
case may be, and may be enforced as fully and effectually as if, 
instead of the dissolved company, the Iron and Steel Company had been 
a party thereto.


</article>



<article><tid>155513</tid>
<number>6</number>Saving of legal proceedings to which the dissolved company is 
a party. If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other legal 
proceeding of whatever nature by or against the dissolved company is 
pending, the same shall not abate, be discontinued or be in any way 
prejudicially affected by reason of the transfer to the Iron and Steel 
Company of the undertaking of the dissolved company or of anything 
contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the Iron and Steel 
Company, in the same manner and to the same extent as it would or may 
be continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the dissolved 
company if this Act had not been passed.


</article>



<article><tid>175691</tid>
<number> 7</number> Terms of transfer as respects shareholders in the dissolved 
company.
<section><tid>1338165</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Iron and  
Steel Company shall, subject to the rules, if any, made in this 
behalf,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>123</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

allot to every person registered as a shareholder in the dissolved 
company immediately before the appointed day,--


<subsection><tid>1861249</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is the holder of preference shares, as many 
preference shares in the Iron and Steel Company as are 
equivalent in number and value to the preference shares 
held by him in the dissolved company immediately before 
the appointed day, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1126998</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is the holder of ordinary shares, four ordinary 
shares for rupees ten each in the Iron and Steel 
Company for every five ordinary shares for rupees ten 
each held by him in the dissolved company immediately 
before the appointed day, being the relative values of 
the two shares as determined by the Tariff Commission 
established under the Tariff Commission Act, <year>1951</year> (50  
  of <year>1951</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1927932</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the 
time being in force, any report made by the Tariff Commission before 
the commencement of this Act respecting the value of ordinary shares 
in the Iron and Steel Company in relation to the value of ordinary 
shares in the dissolved company shall be deemed to have been validly 
made and shall not be called in question in any Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1409010</tid>
<number>3</number>Every shareholder in the dissolved company to whom a 
preference share has been allotted under this section shall be 
entitled--

<subsection><tid>27841</tid>
<number>i</number>to receive a fixed cumulative preferential dividend at 
the rate of five per cent. per annum as from the 1st 
day of January, <year>1953</year>, on the capital for the time being 
paid up or credited as having been fully paid up 
thereon without deduction of Indian income- tax paid by 
the company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>476046</tid>
<number>ii</number>subject to the provisions of clause (i), to rank for 
dividend equally with the holders of preference shares 
in the Iron and Steel Company immediately before the 
appointed day, and in priority to all other 
shareholders in that company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1546154</tid>
<number>iii</number>to be repaid, in the winding up of the Iron and Steel 
Company, the amounts paid up or credited as having been 
fully paid up thereon, together with any arrears of 
dividends (whether earned or not), calculated to the 
date of repayment of capital, equally with the holders 
of preference shares in the Iron and Steel Company 
immediately, before the appointed day, and in priority 
to all other shareholders in that company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776602</tid>
<number>iv</number>to exercise the same voting rights at general meetings 
of the Iron and Steel Company as are conferred on the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

holders of preference shares in that company 
immediately before the appointed day.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1219576</tid>
<number>4</number>The Iron and Steel Company shall cause a notice to be 
published in the Gazette of India and shall also send by post to every 
person whose name was entered immediately before the appointed day in 
the register of shareholders in the dissolved company, a notice giving 
particulars of the terms hereinbefore set out as to the allotment of 
new shares and the disposal in the prescribed manner of fractional 
shares and an allotment letter for the new shares which shall also 
contain a statement of the fractional shares (if any) to which a 
shareholder would be entitled if fractional shares are to be allotted.

</section>

<section><tid>549051</tid>
<number>5</number>Every shareholder in the dissolved company whose name appears 
in the register of the dissolved company immediately before the 
appointed day shall be entitled, on presentation within the prescribed 
period of the allotment letter and the share certificate in respect of 
the shares held by him in the dissolved company, to receive in due 
course share certificates of the Iron and Steel Company in accordance 
with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1072501</tid>
<number>6</number>Any rights specified in sub- section (5) shall, during the 
period beginning with the appointed day and ending with the day on 
which the Iron and Steel Company issues fresh share certificates to 
the shareholders of the dissolved company, be transferable in like 
manner as the shares in the Iron and Steel Company themselves are 
transferable, and the transferees of such rights shall be entitled, 
upon submission of the letter of allotment, the relative share 
certificate in the dissolved company and the document of transfer to 
share certificates in the same manner and to the same extent as the 
transferors would have been entitled.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>304104</tid>
<number>8</number>Priority as between secured creditors of the dissolved company 
and secured creditors of the Iron and Steel Company. Creditors of the 
dissolved company whose debts are secured by a mortgage, charge or 
lien on the property of the dissolved company or any part thereof 
shall, with reference to similar secured creditors of the Iron and 
Steel Company, have such priority in the repayment of the debts as may 
be determined by agreement between the Iron and Steel Company and the 
secured creditors of the dissolved company:
Provided that in the absence of any such agreement the matter 
shall be referred by the Iron and Steel Company to the determination 
of such person as may be appointed by the Central Government in this 
behalf, and the decision of such person shall be final and binding on 
the Iron and Steel Company and the secured creditors concerned.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>125</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1504895</tid>
<number> 9</number> Provisions with respect to taxation.
<section><tid>457344</tid>
<number>1</number>The Iron and Steel  
Company shall be taxable in respect of the profits and gains of the 
business carried on by the dissolved company before the appointed day 
to the same extent as the dissolved company would have been taxable if 
this Act had not been passed, and the Iron and Steel Company shall, in 
its assessment, be entitled to claim all such allowances under sub- 
section (2) of section 10 of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of  
  <year>1922</year>) as the dissolved company could have claimed in its assessment if 
this Act had not been passed.

</section>

<section><tid>143873</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of any law relating to taxation on income, 
the original cost to the Iron and Steel Company of the buildings, 
machinery, plant or furniture of the dissolved company transferred to 
it by virtue of this Act shall be deemed to be the written down value 
thereof, as reduced by the initial depreciation permitted by sub- 
section (2) of section 10 of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of  
  <year>1922</year>), which has been or could have been computed by the dissolved 
company on the appointed day if this Act had not been passed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>997798</tid>
<number> 10</number> Payment of interim dividends to shareholders in the dissolved 
company. If the profits of the dissolved company warrant such a 
course, the directors of the dissolved company may, at any time before 
the appointed day, declare the following dividends as being payable--
<section><tid>1086990</tid>
<number>a</number>to the holders of preference shares immediately before 
the appointed day, a dividend at the rate of five per 
cent. per annum on the amount paid up without deduction 
of Indian income- tax payable by the dissolved company 
for the period commencing on the 1st day of June, <year>1952</year>, 
and ending with the 31st day of December, <year>1952</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>952033</tid>
<number>b</number>to the holders of ordinary shares whose names appear on 
the register of the company on the date of such 
payment, an interim dividend not exceeding two and half 
per cent. on the amount paid up or credited as having 
been fully paid up thereon without deduction of Indian 
income- tax payable by the dissolved company for the 
period commencing on the 1st day of January, <year>1952</year>, and 
ending with the 31st day of December, <year>1952</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>351472</tid>
<number>11</number>Provisions respecting existing officers and other employees 
of the dissolved company. Every officer or other employee (including  
within that expression auditors but excluding therefrom directors, 
  managing agents and London Committee Members) employed immediately 
before the appointed day in the dissolved company shall, as from the 
appointed day, become an officer or other employee, as the case may 
be, of the Iron and Steel Company and shall hold his office or service 
therein by the same tenure and upon the same terms and conditions and 
with the same rights and privileges as to pension or gratuity as he 
would have held the same under the dissolved company if this Act had 
not been passed, and shall continue to do so unless and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>126</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

until he is duly removed from his employment in the Iron and Steel 
Company or until his terms and conditions of employment are duly 
altered by that company.



</article>



<article><tid>855135</tid>
<number>12</number>Position of directors of the dissolved company. Every 
director of the dissolved company holding office as such immediately 
before the appointed day shall become, as from the appointed day, a 
director of the Iron and Steel Company, in addition to the other 
directors of the Iron and Steel Company holding office as such before 
the appointed day, and shall, subject to the provisions of the 
articles of association of the Iron and Steel Company, hold his office 
and act in all respects as if he had been duly appointed under the 
said articles.


</article>



<article><tid>379651</tid>
<number> 13</number> Dissolution of the Steel Corporation of Bengal, Limited. As 
from the appointed day--
<section><tid>247407</tid>
<number>a</number>the Steel Corporation of Bengal, Limited, shall be 
dissolved and thereafter no person shall make, assert 
or take any claims, demands or proceedings against the 
dissolved company or against a director or officer 
thereof in his capacity as such director or officer, 
except in so far as may be necessary, for enforcing the 
provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>356760</tid>
<number>b</number>the right of every shareholder to or in respect of any 
share in the dissolved company shall be extinguished, 
and thereafter no such shareholder shall make, assert 
or take any claims or demands or proceedings in respect 
of any such share except as provided in this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>401857</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to make rules for facilitating amalgamation. The 
Central Government may, by rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> published in the Official Gazette, 
make such incidental, consequential or supplementary provisions as in 
its opinion are necessary for fully and effectually carrying out the 
purposes of this Act, and without prejudice to the generality of such 
power, provision may be made in such rules--
<section><tid>232533</tid>
<number>a</number>for the allotting or appropriation by the Iron and Steel 
Company of any shares, debentures, policies or other 
like interests in that company which are to be allotted 
or appropriated under this Act by that company to or 
from any person;

</section>

<section><tid>678771</tid>
<number>b</number>for the disposal of shares in the dissolved company 
which do not represent one fully paid up share in the 
Iron and Steel Company under clause (b) of sub- section 
 (1) of section 7, whether by the surrender to the Iron 
and Steel
<pagefootnote><pagenum>127</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For the Works, Provident Funds (Amalgamation) Rules, <year>1953</year>, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1953</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 245.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Company of the fractional certificates relating thereto 
with other fractional certificates so as to represent 
in all one fully paid up share, or, at the option of 
the shareholder, by the surrender of the fractional 
certificates to the Iron and Steel Company for sale by 
the Company on his account;


</section>

<section><tid>1196349</tid>
<number>c</number>for fixing the period within which any action required 
to be taken under this Act may be taken;

</section>

<section><tid>226612</tid>
<number>d</number>for the alteration, notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
 (7 of <year>1913</year>), of the memorandum or articles of 
association of the Iron and Steel Company for the 
purpose of increasing the capital of the company or the 
borrowing powers of the directors thereof or for the 
purpose of securing the representation of the Central 
Government on the Board of Directors of the company or 
for any other purpose;

</section>

<section><tid>1487688</tid>
<number>e</number>for requiring any person concerned with the keeping of 
the register of the holders of any shares, securities 
or investments now transferred to and vesting in the 
Iron and Steel Company to forthwith register the name 
of the Iron and Steel Company therein, and to issue to 
the Iron and Steel Company the appropriate documents of 
title relating to the shares, securities or investments 
transferred to and vesting in it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1696541</tid>
<number>15</number>[ Repeal of Ordinance 8 of <year>1952</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1957</year> (36 of <year>1957</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>128</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>