<act><title>


THE ARBITRATION AND CONCILIATION
Act, 1996</title> 

 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India:
 
Provided that Parts I, III 
and IV shall extend to the State of Jammu and Kashmir only in so far as they 
relate to international commercial arbitration or, as the case may be, 
international commercial conciliation.
 
Explanation.—In 
this sub-section, the expression “international commercial conciliation” shall 
have the same meaning as the expression “international commercial arbitration” 
in clause (f) of sub-section (1) of section 2, subject to the modification that 
for the word “arbitration” occurring therein, the word “conciliation” shall be 
substituted.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date1 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, appoint.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In this Part, unless the context 
otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “arbitration” means any arbitration whether or not administered by 
  permanent arbitral institution; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “arbitration agreement” means an agreement referred to in section 7; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “arbitral award” includes an interim award; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “arbitral tribunal” means a sole arbitrator or a panel of arbitrators; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “Court” means the principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction in a 
  district, and includes the High Court in exercise of its ordinary original 
  civil jurisdiction, having jurisdiction to decide the questions forming the 
  subject-matter of the arbitration if the same had been the subject-matter of a 
  suit, but does not include any civil court of a grade inferior to such 
  principal Civil Court, or any Court of Small Causes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “international commercial arbitration” means an arbitration relating to 
  disputes arising out of legal relationships, whether contractual or not, 
  considered as commercial under the law in force in India and where at least 
  one of the parties is— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> an individual who is a national of, or habitually resident in, any 
    country other than India ; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> a body corporate which is incorporated in any country other than 
    India ; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> a company or an association or a body of individuals whose central 
    management and control is exercised in any country other than India ; or 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> the Government of a foreign country; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “legal representative” means a person who in law represents the estate 
  of a deceased person, and includes any person who intermeddles with the estate 
  of the deceased, and, where a party acts in a representative character, the 
  person on whom the estate devolves on the death of the party so acting; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “party” means a party to an arbitration agreement. </subsection>
 Scope 
 </section><section><number>2</number> This Part shall apply where the place of arbitration is in India . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> This Part shall not affect any other law for the time being in force by 
virtue of which certain disputes may not be submitted to arbitration. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> This Part except sub-section (1) of section 40, sections 41 and 43 shall 
apply to every arbitration under any other enactment for the time being in 
force, as if the arbitration were pursuant to an arbitration agreement and as if 
that other enactment were an arbitration agreement, except in so far as the 
provisions of this Part are inconsistent with that other enactment or with any 
rules made thereunder. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section (4), and save in so far as is 
otherwise provided by any law for the time being in force or in any agreement in 
force between India and any other country or countries, this Part shall apply to 
all arbitrations and to all proceedings relating thereto. 
 Construction of references 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where this Part, except section 28, leaves the parties free to determine 
a certain issue, that freedom shall include the right of the parties to 
authorise any person including an institution, to determine that issue. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> An arbitral award made under this Part shall be considered as a domestic 
award. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Where this Part— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> refers to the fact that the parties have agreed or that they may agree, 
or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> in any other way refers to an agreement of the parties, 
 that agreement shall include any arbitration rules referred to in that 
agreement. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>9</number> Where this Part, other than clause (a) of section 25 or clause (a) of 
sub-  section (2) of section 32, refers to a claim, it shall also apply to a 
counter-claim, and where it refers to a defence, it shall also apply to a 
defence to that counter-claim. 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Receipt of written 
communications.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless otherwise agreed by the parties,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> any written 
communication is deemed to have been received if it is delivered to the 
addressee personally or at his place of business, habitual residence or mailing 
address, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> if none of the 
places referred to in clause (a) can be found after making a reasonable inquiry, 
a written communication is deemed to have been received if it is sent to the 
addressee’s last known place of business, habitual residence or mailing address 
by registered letter or by any other means which provides a record of the 
attempt to deliver it.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The communication is 
deemed to have been received on the day it is so delivered.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> This section does not 
apply to written communications in respect of proceedings of any judicial 
authority.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Waiver of right to object. </title>—A party who knows that— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> any provision of this Part from which the parties may derogate, or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> any requirement under the arbitration agreement, has not been complied 
  with and yet proceeds with the arbitration without stating his objection to 
  such non-compliance without undue delay or, if a time limit is provided for 
  stating that objection, within that period of time, shall be deemed to have 
  waived his right to so object. </section>

</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Extent of judicial 
intervention.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, in matters 
governed by this Part, no judicial authority shall intervene except where so 
provided in this Part.




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Administrative 
assistance.—In 
order to facilitate the conduct of the arbitral proceedings, the parties, or the 
arbitral tribunal with the consent of the parties, may arrange for 
administrative assistance by a suitable institution or person.
 
 
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Arbitration agreement. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In this Part, “arbitration agreement” means an agreement by the parties to submit to arbitration all or certain disputes which have arisen or which may arise between them in respect of a defined legal relationship, whether contractual or not. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An arbitration agreement may be in the form of an arbitration clause in a contract or in the form of a separate agreement. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An arbitration agreement shall be in writing. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An arbitration agreement is in writing if it is contained in— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a document signed by the parties; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> an exchange of letters, telex, telegrams or other means of telecommunication which provide a record of the agreement; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> an exchange of statements of claim and defence in which the existence of the agreement is alleged by one party and not denied by the other. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> The reference in a contract to a document containing an arbitration clause constitutes an arbitration agreement if the contract is in writing and the reference is such as to make that arbitration clause part of the contract. 









</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Power to refer parties to 
arbitration where there is an arbitration agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> A judicial authority before 
which an action is brought in a matter which is the subject of an arbitration 
agreement shall, if a party so applies not later than when submitting his first 
statement on the substance of the dispute, refer the parties to 
arbitration.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application referred to in 
sub-section (1) shall not be entertained unless it is accompanied by the 
original arbitration agreement or a duly certified copy thereof.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding that an 
application has been made under sub-section (1) and that the issue is pending 
before the judicial authority, an arbitration may be commenced or continued and 
an arbitral award made.












</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Interim measures, 
etc. by Court.—A 
party may, before or during arbitral proceedings or at any time after the making 
of the arbitral award but before it is enforced in accordance with section 36, 
apply to a court—
 <section>
        <number>i</number>  for the 
appointment of a guardian for a minor or a person of unsound mind for the 
purposes of arbitral proceedings; or
 </section><section>
        <number>ii</number> for an 
interim measure of protection in respect of any of the following matters, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number> the 
preservation, interim custody or sale of any goods which are the subject-matter 
of the arbitration agreement;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number> securing 
the amount in dispute in the arbitration;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>c</number> the 
detention, preservation or inspection of any property or thing which is the 
subject-matter of the dispute in arbitration, or as to which any question may 
arise therein and authorising for any of the aforesaid purposes any person to 
enter upon any land or building in the possession of any party, or authorising 
any samples to be taken or any observation to be made, or experiment to be 
tried, which may be necessary or expedient for the purpose of obtaining full 
information or evidence;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>d</number> interim 
injunction or the appointment of a receiver;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>e</number> such other 
interim measure of protection as may appear to the court to be just and 
convenient,
 
and the Court shall have 
the same power for making orders as it has for the purpose of, and in relation 
to, any proceedings before it.








</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Number of 
arbitrators.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The parties are free to determine the number of arbitrators, provided that such 
number shall not be an even number.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Failing the 
determination referred to in sub-section (1), the arbitral tribunal shall 
consist of a sole arbitrator.





</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Appointment of arbitrators. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A person of any 
nationality may be an arbitrator, unless otherwise agreed by the parties. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to sub-section (6), the parties are free to agree on a procedure 
for appointing the arbitrator or arbitrators. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Failing any agreement referred to in sub-section (2), in an arbitration 
with three arbitrators, each party shall appoint one arbitrator, and the two 
appointed arbitrators shall appoint the third arbitrator who shall act as the 
presiding arbitrator. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the appointment procedure in sub-section (3) applies and— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a party fails to appoint an arbitrator within thirty days from the 
  receipt of a request to do so from the other party; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the two appointed arbitrators fail to agree on the third arbitrator 
  within thirty days from the date of their appointment, the appointment shall 
  be made, upon request of a party, by the Chief Justice or any person or 
  institution designated by him. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> Failing any agreement referred to in sub-section (2), in an arbitration 
with a sole arbitrator, if the parties fail to agree on the arbitrator within 
thirty days from receipt of a request by one party from the other party to so 
agree the appointment shall be made, upon request of a party, by the Chief 
Justice or any person or institution designated by him. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where, under an appointment procedure agreed upon by the parties,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a party fails to act as required under that procedure; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the parties, or the two appointed arbitrators, fail to reach an 
  agreement expected of them under that procedure; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a person, including an institution, fails to perform any function 
  entrusted to him or it under that procedure, a party may request the Chief 
  Justice or any person or institution designated by him to take the necessary 
  measure, unless the agreement on the appointment procedure provides other 
  means for securing the appointment. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>7</number> A decision on a matter entrusted by sub-section (4) or sub-section (5) or 
sub-section (6) to the Chief Justice or the person or institution designated by 
him is final. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Chief Justice or the person or institution designated by him, in 
appointing an arbitrator, shall have due regard to— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> any qualifications required of the arbitrator by the agreement of the 
  parties; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> other considerations as are likely to secure the appointment of an 
  independent and impartial arbitrator. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>9</number> In the case of appointment of sole or third arbitrator in an 
international commercial arbitration, the Chief Justice of India or the person 
or institution designated by him may appoint an arbitrator of a nationality 
other than the nationalities of the parties where the parties belong to 
different nationalities. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The Chief Justice may make such scheme<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as he may deem 
appropriate for dealing with matters entrusted by sub-section (4) or sub-section 
(5) or sub-section (6) to him. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> Where more than one request has been made under sub-section (4) or 
sub-section (5) or sub-section (6) to the Chief Justices of different High 
Courts or their designates, the Chief Justice or his designate to whom the 
request has been first made under the relevant sub-section shall alone be 
competent to decide on the request. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> (a) Where the matters referred to in sub-sections (4), (5), (6), (7), 
(8) and (10) arise in an international commercial arbitration, the reference to 
‘‘Chief Justice'' in those sub-sections shall be construed as a reference to the 
‘‘Chief Justice of India''. 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where the matters referred to in sub-sections (4), (5), (6), (7), (8) 
  and (10) arise in any other arbitration, the reference to “Chief Justice” in 
  those sub-sections shall be construed as a reference to the Chief Justice of 
  the High Court within whose local limits the principal Civil Court referred to 
  in clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 2 is situate and, where the High 
  Court itself is the Court referred to in that clause, to the Chief Justice of 
  that High Court. </subsection>






</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>12</number> Grounds for 
challenge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a person is approached in connection with his possible appointment as an 
arbitrator, he shall disclose in writing any circumstances likely to give rise 
to justifiable doubts as to his independence or impartiality.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An arbitrator, from 
the time of his appointment and throughout the arbitral proceedings, shall, 
without delay, disclose to the parties in writing any circumstances referred to 
in sub-section (1) unless they have already been informed of them by him.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An arbitrator may be 
challenged only if—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  circumstances 
exist that give rise to justifiable doubts as to his independence or 
impartiality, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  he does not 
possess the qualifications agreed to by the parties.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> A party may challenge 
an arbitrator appointed by him, or in whose appointment he has participated, 
only for reasons of which he becomes aware after the appointment has been made.
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Challenge 
procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to sub-section (4), the parties are free to agree on a procedure for 
challenging an arbitrator.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Failing any agreement 
referred to in sub-section (1), a party who intends to challenge an arbitrator 
shall, within fifteen days after becoming aware of the constitution of the 
arbitral tribunal or after becoming aware of any circumstances referred to in 
sub-section (3) of section 12, send a written statement of the reasons for the 
challenge to the arbitral tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Unless the arbitrator 
challenged under sub-section (2) withdraws from his office or the other party 
agrees to the challenge, the arbitral tribunal shall decide on the challenge.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If a challenge under 
any procedure agreed upon by the parties or under the procedure under 
sub-section (2) is not successful, the arbitral tribunal shall continue the 
arbitral proceedings and make an arbitral award.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where an arbitral 
award is made under sub-section (4), the party challenging the arbitrator may 
make an application for setting aside such an arbitral award in accordance with 
section 34.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where an arbitral 
award is set aside on an application made under sub-section (5), the Court may 
decide as to whether the arbitrator who is challenged is entitled to any fees.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>14</number> Failure or impossibility to 
act.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
mandate of an arbitrator shall terminate if—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number> he becomes de jure or de facto unable to perform his functions 
or for other reasons fails to act without undue delay; and
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number> he withdraws from his office or the parties agree to the termination of his 
mandate.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If a controversy remains 
concerning any of the grounds referred to inclause (a) of sub-section (1), a 
party may, unless otherwise agreed by the parties, apply to the Court to decide 
on the termination of the mandate.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If, under this section or 
sub-section (3) of section 13, an arbitrator withdraws from his office or a 
party agrees to the termination of the mandate of an arbitrator, it shall not 
imply acceptance of the validity of any ground referred to in this section or 
sub-section (3) of section 12.
  </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Termination of 
mandate and substitution of arbitrator.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In addition to the circumstances referred to in section 13 or section 14, the 
mandate of an arbitrator shall terminate—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> where he 
withdraws from office for any reason; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> by or pursuant 
to agreement of the parties.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the mandate of 
an arbitrator terminates, a substitute arbitrator shall be appointed according 
to the rules that were applicable to the appointment of the arbitrator being 
replaced.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, where an arbitrator is replaced under sub-section (2), 
any hearings previously held may be repeated at the discretion of the arbitral 
tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, an order or ruling of the arbitral tribunal made prior to 
the replacement of an arbitrator under this section shall not be invalid solely 
because there has been a change in the composition of the arbitral tribunal.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Competence of 
arbitral tribunal to rule on its jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The arbitral tribunal may rule on its own jurisdiction, including ruling on any 
objections with respect to the existence or validity of the arbitration 
agreement, and for that purpose,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> an arbitration 
clause which forms part of a contract shall be treated as an agreement 
independent of the other terms of the contract; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> a decision by 
the arbitral tribunal that the contract is null and void shall not entail 
ipso jure the invalidity of the arbitration clause.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A plea that the 
arbitral tribunal does not have jurisdiction shall be raised not later than the 
submission of the statement of defence; however, a party shall not be precluded 
from raising such a plea merely because that he has appointed, or participated 
in the appointment of, an arbitrator.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A plea that the 
arbitral tribunal is exceeding the scope of its authority shall be raised as 
soon as the matter alleged to be beyond the scope of its authority is raised 
during the arbitral proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The arbitral tribunal 
may, in either of the cases referred to in sub-section (2) or sub-section (3), 
admit a later plea if it considers the delay justified.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The arbitral tribunal 
shall decide on a plea referred to in sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) and, 
where the arbitral tribunal takes a decision rejecting the plea, continue with 
the arbitral proceedings and make an arbitral award.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A party aggrieved by 
such an arbitral award may make an application for setting aside such an 
arbitral award in accordance with section 34.






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Interim measures 
ordered by arbitral tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless otherwise agreed by the parties, the arbitral tribunal may, at the 
request of a party, order a party to take any interim measure of protection as 
the arbitral tribunal may consider necessary in respect of the subject-matter of 
the dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The arbitral tribunal 
may require a party to provide appropriate security in connection with a measure 
ordered under sub-section (1).
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>18</number> Equal treatment of 
parties.—The 
parties shall be treated with equality and each party shall be given a full 
opportunity to present his case.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Determination of 
rules of procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The arbitral tribunal shall not be bound by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 
of 1908) or the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to this Part, 
the parties are free to agree on the procedure to be followed by the arbitral 
tribunal in conducting its proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Failing any agreement 
referred to in sub-section (2), the arbitral tribunal may, subject to this Part, 
conduct the proceedings in the manner it considers appropriate.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The power of the 
arbitral tribunal under sub-section (3) includes the power to determine the 
admissibility, relevance, materiality and weight of any evidence.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Place of 
arbitration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The parties are free to agree on the place of arbitration.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Failing any agreement 
referred to in sub-section (1), the place of arbitration shall be determined by 
the arbitral tribunal having regard to the circumstances of the case, including 
the convenience of the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the arbitral tribunal may, unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, meet at any place it considers appropriate for 
consultation among its members, for hearing witnesses, experts or the parties, 
or for inspection of documents, goods or other property.




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Commencement of 
arbitral proceedings.—Unless 
otherwise agreed by the parties, the arbitral proceedings in respect of a 
particular dispute commence on the date on which a request for that dispute to 
be referred to arbitration is received by the respondent.




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Language.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The parties are free to agree upon the language or languages to be used in the 
arbitral proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Failing any agreement 
referred to in sub-section (1), the arbitral tribunal shall determine the 
language or languages to be used in the arbitral proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The agreement or 
determination, unless otherwise specified, shall apply to any written statement 
by a party, any hearing and any arbitral award, decision or other communication 
by the arbitral tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The arbitral tribunal 
may order that any documentary evidence shall be accompanied by a translation 
into the language or languages agreed upon by the parties or determined by the 
arbitral tribunal.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Statement of claim 
and defence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Within the period of time agreed upon by the parties or determined by the 
arbitral tribunal, the claimant shall state the facts supporting his claim, the 
points at issue and the relief or remedy sought, and the respondent shall state 
his defence in respect of these particulars, unless the parties have otherwise 
agreed as to the required elements of those statements.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The parties may submit 
with their statements all documents they consider to be relevant or may add a 
reference to the documents or other evidence they will submit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, either party may amend or supplement his claim or defence 
during the course of the arbitral proceedings, unless the arbitral tribunal 
considers it inappropriate to allow the amendment or supplement having regard to 
the delay in making it.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Hearings and 
written proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless otherwise agreed by the parties, the arbitral tribunal shall decide 
whether to hold oral hearings for the presentation of evidence or for oral 
argument, or whether the proceedings shall be conducted on the basis of 
documents and other materials:
 
Provided that the arbitral 
tribunal shall hold oral hearings, at an appropriate stage of the proceedings, 
on a request by a party, unless the parties have agreed that no oral hearing 
shall be held.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The parties shall be 
given sufficient advance notice of any hearing and of any meeting of the 
arbitral tribunal for the purposes of inspection of documents, goods or other 
property.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All statements, 
documents or other information supplied to, or applications made to the arbitral 
tribunal by one party shall be communicated to the other party, and any expert 
report or evidentiary document on which the arbitral tribunal may rely in making 
its decision shall be communicated to the parties.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Default of a party.—Unless 
otherwise agreed by the parties, where, without showing sufficient cause,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> the claimant 
fails to communicate his statement of claim in accordance with sub-section (1) 
of section 23, the arbitral tribunal shall terminate the proceedings;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> the respondent 
fails to communicate his statement of defence in accordance with sub-section (1) 
of section 23, the arbitral tribunal shall continue the proceedings without 
treating that failure in itself as an admission of the allegations by the 
claimant;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> a party fails 
to appear at an oral hearing or to produce documentary evidence, the arbitral 
tribunal may continue the proceedings and make the arbitral award on the 
evidence before it.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Expert appointment 
by arbitral tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless otherwise agreed by the parties, the arbitral tribunal may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> appoint one or 
more experts to report to it on specific issues to be determined by the arbitral 
tribunal, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> require a party 
to give the expert any relevant information or to produce, or to provide access 
to, any relevant documents, goods or other property for his inspection.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, if a party so requests or if the arbitral tribunal 
considers it necessary, the expert shall, after delivery of his written or oral 
report, participate in an oral hearing where the parties have the opportunity to 
put questions to him and to present expert witnesses in order to testify on the 
points at issue.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, the expert shall, on the request of a party, make 
available to that party for examination all documents, goods or other property 
in the possession of the expert with which he was provided in order to prepare 
his report.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Court assistance in 
taking evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The arbitral tribunal, or a party with the approval of the arbitral tribunal, 
may apply to the Court for assistance in taking evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application shall 
specify—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the names and 
addresses of the parties and the arbitrators;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the general 
nature of the claim and the relief sought;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> the evidence to 
be obtained, in particular,—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number> the name 
and address of any person to be heard as witness or expert witness and a 
statement of the subject-matter of the testimony required;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number> the 
description of any document to be produced or property to be inspected.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court may, within 
its competence and according to its rules on taking evidence, execute the 
request by ordering that the evidence be provided directly to the arbitral 
tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Court may, while 
making an order under sub-section (3), issue the same processes to witnesses as 
it may issue in suits tried before it.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Persons failing to 
attend in accordance with such process, or making any other default, or refusing 
to give their evidence, or guilty of any contempt to the arbitral tribunal 
during the conduct of arbitral proceedings, shall be subject to the like 
disadvantages, penalties and punishments by order of the Court on the 
representation of the arbitral tribunal as they would incur for the like 
offences in suits tried before the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In this section the 
expression “Processes” includes summonses and commissions for the examination of 
witnesses and summonses to produce documents.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Rules applicable to 
substance of dispute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the place of arbitration is situate in India,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> in an 
arbitration other than an international commercial arbitration, the arbitral 
tribunal shall decide the dispute submitted to arbitration in accordance with 
the substantive law for the time being in force in India;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> in 
international commercial arbitration,—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number> the 
arbitral tribunal shall decide the dispute in accordance with the rules of law 
designated by the parties as applicable to the substance of the dispute;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number> any 
designation by the parties of the law or legal system of a given country shall 
be construed, unless otherwise expressed, as directly referring to the 
substantive law of that country and not to its conflict of laws rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number> failing 
any designation of the law under clause (a) by the parties, the arbitral 
tribunal shall apply the rules of law it considers to be appropriate given all 
the circumstances surrounding the dispute.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The arbitral tribunal 
shall decide ex aequo et bono or as amiable compositeur only if 
the parties have expressly authorised it to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In all cases, the 
arbitral tribunal shall decide in accordance with the terms of the contract and 
shall take into account the usages of the trade applicable to the transaction.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Decision making by 
panel of arbitrators.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless otherwise agreed by the parties, in arbitral proceedings with more than 
one arbitrator, any decision of the arbitral tribunal shall be made by a 
majority of all its members.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
sub-section (1), if authorised by the parties or all the members of the arbitral 
tribunal, questions of procedure may be decided by the presiding arbitrator.




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Settlement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It is not incompatible with an arbitration agreement for an arbitral tribunal to 
encourage settlement of the dispute and, with the agreement of the parties, the 
arbitral tribunal may use mediation, conciliation or other procedures at any 
time during the arbitral proceedings to encourage settlement.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, during arbitral 
proceedings, the parties settle the dispute, the arbitral tribunal shall 
terminate the proceedings and, if requested by the parties and not objected to 
by the arbitral tribunal, record the settlement in the form of an arbitral award 
on agreed terms.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An arbitral award on 
agreed terms shall be made in accordance with section 31 and shall state that it 
is an arbitral award.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An arbitral award on 
agreed terms shall have the same status and effect as any other arbitral award 
on the substance of the dispute.




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Form and contents 
of arbitral award.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An arbitral award shall be made in writing and shall be signed by the members of 
the arbitral tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of 
sub-section (1), in arbitral proceedings with more than one arbitrator, the 
signatures of the majority of all the members of the arbitral tribunal shall be 
sufficient so long as the reason for any omitted signature is stated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The arbitral award 
shall state the reasons upon which it is based, unless—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the parties 
have agreed that no reasons are to be given, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the award is an 
arbitral award on agreed terms under section 30.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The arbitral award 
shall state its date and the place of arbitration as determined in accordance 
with section 20 and the award shall be deemed to have been made at that place.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> After the arbitral 
award is made, a signed copy shall be delivered to each party.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The arbitral tribunal 
may, at any time during the arbitral proceedings, make an interim arbitral award 
on any matter with respect to which it may make a final arbitral award.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> (a) Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, where and in so far as an arbitral award is for the 
payment of money, the arbitral tribunal may include in the sum for which the 
award is made interest, at such rate as it deems reasonable, on the whole or any 
part of the money, for the whole or any part of the period between the date on 
which the cause of action arose and the date on which the award is made.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> A sum directed to be 
paid by an arbitral award shall, unless the award otherwise directs, carry 
interest at the rate of eighteen per centum per annum from the date of the award 
to the date of payment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the costs of an 
arbitration shall be fixed by the arbitral tribunal;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the arbitral 
tribunal shall specify—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number> the party 
entitled to costs,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number> the party 
who shall pay the costs,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number> the 
amount of costs or method of determining that amount, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>iv</number> the manner 
in which the costs shall be paid.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purpose of clause (a), “costs” means reasonable costs relating to—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>i</number> the fees and 
expenses of the arbitrators and witnesses,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number> legal fees 
and expenses,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iii</number> any 
administration fees of the institution supervising the arbitration, and 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iv</number> any other 
expenses incurred in connection with the arbitral proceedings and the arbitral 
award.




</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Termination of 
proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The arbitral proceedings shall be terminated by the final arbitral award or by 
an order of the arbitral tribunal under sub-section (2).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The arbitral tribunal 
shall issue an order for the termination of the arbitral proceedings where—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the claimant 
withdraws his claim, unless the respondent objects to the order and the arbitral 
tribunal recognises a legitimate interest on his part in obtaining a final 
settlement of the dispute,
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the parties 
agree on the termination of the proceedings, or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> the arbitral 
tribunal finds that the continuation of the proceedings has for any other reason 
become unnecessary or impossible.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to section 33 
and sub-section (4) of section 34, the mandate of the arbitral tribunal shall 
terminate with the termination of the arbitral proceedings.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Correction and 
interpretation of award; additional award.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Within thirty days from the receipt of the arbitral award, unless another period 
of time has been agreed upon by the parties—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> a party, with 
notice to the other party, may request the arbitral tribunal to correct any 
computation errors, any clerical or typographical errors or any other errors of 
a similar nature occurring in the award;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> if so agreed by 
the parties, a party, with notice to the other party, may request the arbitral 
tribunal to give an interpretation of a specific point or part of the award.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the arbitral 
tribunal considers the request made under sub-section (1) to be justified, it 
shall make the correction or give the interpretation within thirty days from the 
receipt of the request and the interpretation shall form part of the arbitral 
award.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The arbitral tribunal 
may correct any error of the type referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (1), 
on its own initiative, within thirty days from the date of the arbitral award.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Unless otherwise 
agreed by the parties, a party with notice to the other party, may request, 
within thirty days from the receipt of the arbitral award, the arbitral tribunal 
to make an additional arbitral award as to claims presented in the arbitral 
proceedings but omitted from the arbitral award.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the arbitral 
tribunal considers the request made under sub-section (4) to be justified, it 
shall make the additional arbitral award within sixty days from the receipt of 
such request.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The arbitral tribunal 
may extend, if necessary, the period of time within which it shall make a 
correction, give an interpretation or make an additional arbitral award under 
sub-section (2) or sub-section (5).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Section 31 shall apply 
to a correction or interpretation of the arbitral award or to an additional 
arbitral award made under this section.




</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>34</number> Application for setting aside arbitral award. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> 
Recourse to a Court against an arbitral award may be made only by an application 
for setting aside such award in accordance with sub-section (2) and sub-section 
(3). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An arbitral award may be set aside by the Court only if— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the party making the application furnishes proof that— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> a party was under some incapacity, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the arbitration agreement is not valid under the law to which the 
    parties have subjected it or, failing any indication thereon, under the law 
    for the time being in force; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> the party making the application was not given proper notice of the 
    appointment of an arbitrator or of the arbitral proceedings or was otherwise 
    unable to present his case; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> the arbitral award deals with a dispute not contemplated by or not 
    falling within the terms of the submission to arbitration, or it contains 
    decisions on matters beyond the scope of the submission to arbitration: 
  </subsubsection>
 Provided that, if the decisions on matters submitted to arbitration can be 
  separated from those not so submitted, only that part of the arbitral award 
  which contains decisions on matters not submitted to arbitration may be set 
  aside; or 
 
 <subsubsection><number>v</number> the composition of the arbitral tribunal or the arbitral procedure 
    was not in accordance with the agreement of the parties, unless such 
    agreement was in conflict with a provision of this Part from which the 
    parties cannot derogate, or, failing such agreement, was not in accordance 
    with this Part; or </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Court finds that— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> the subject-matter of the dispute is not capable of settlement by 
    arbitration under the law for the time being in force, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the arbitral award is in conflict with the public policy of India . 
    </subsubsection></subsection>
 Explanation. —Without prejudice to the generality of sub-clause (ii) 
it is hereby declared, for the avoidance of any doubt, that an award is in 
conflict with the public policy of India if the making of the award was induced 
or affected by fraud or corruption or was in violation of section 75 or section 
81. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An application for setting aside may not be made after three months have 
elapsed from the date on which the party making that application had received 
the arbitral award or, if a request had been made under section 33, from the 
date on which that request had been disposed of by the arbitral tribunal: 
 Provided that if the Court is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by 
sufficient cause from making the application within the said period of three 
months it may entertain the application within a further period of thirty days, 
but not thereafter. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of an application under sub-section (1), the Court may, where 
it is appropriate and it is so requested by a party, adjourn the proceedings for 
a period of time determined by it in order to give the arbitral tribunal an 
opportunity to resume the arbitral proceedings or to take such other action as 
in the opinion of arbitral tribunal will eliminate the grounds for setting aside 
the arbitral award. 










</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Finality of 
arbitral awards.—Subject 
to this Part an arbitral award shall be final and binding on the parties and 
persons claiming under them respectively.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Enforcement.—Where 
the time for making an application to set aside the arbitral award under section 
34 has expired, or such application having been made, it has been refused, the 
award shall be enforced under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) in 
the same manner as if it were a decree of the Court.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Appealable orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall lie from the following orders (and from no others) to the Court 
authorised by law to hear appeals from original decrees of the Court passing the 
order, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> granting or 
refusing to grant any measure under section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> setting aside 
or refusing to set aside an arbitral award under  
section 34.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal shall also 
lie to a Court from an order granting of the arbitral tribunal.—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  accepting the 
plea referred in sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) of section 16; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  granting or 
refusing to grant an interim measure under section 17.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No second appeal shall 
lie from an order passed in appeal under this section, but nothing in this 
section shall affect or take away any right to appeal to the Supreme Court.






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The arbitral tribunal may fix the amount of the deposit or supplementary 
deposit, as the case may be, as an advance for the costs referred to in 
sub-section (8) of section 31, which it expects will be incurred in respect of 
the claim submitted to it:
 
Provided that where, apart 
from the claim, a counter-claim has been submitted to the arbitral tribunal, it 
may fix separate amount of deposit for the claim and counter-claim.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The deposit referred 
to in sub-section (1) shall be payable in equal shares by the parties:
 
Provided that where one 
party fails to pay his share of the deposit, the other party may pay that share:
 
Provided further that 
where the other party also does not pay the aforesaid share in respect of the 
claim or the counter-claim, the arbitral tribunal may suspend or terminate the 
arbitral proceedings in respect of such claim or counter-claim, as the case may 
be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Upon termination of 
the arbitral proceedings, the arbitral tribunal shall render an accounting to 
the parties of the deposits received and shall return any unexpended balance to 
the party or parties, as the case may be.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Lien on arbitral 
award and deposits as to costs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2) and to any provision to the 
contrary in the arbitration agreement, the arbitral tribunal shall have a lien 
on the arbitral award for any unpaid costs of the arbitration.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If in any case an 
arbitral tribunal refuses to deliver its award except on payment of the costs 
demanded by it, the Court may, on an application in this behalf, order that the 
arbitral tribunal shall deliver the arbitral award to the applicant on payment 
into Court by the applicant of the costs demanded, and shall, after such 
inquiry, if any, as it thinks fit, further order that out of the money so paid 
into Court there shall be paid to the arbitral tribunal by way of costs such sum 
as the Court may consider reasonable and that the balance of the money, if any, 
shall be refunded to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An application under 
sub-section (2) may be made by any party unless the fees demanded have been 
fixed by written agreement between him and the arbitral tribunal, and the 
arbitral tribunal shall be entitled to appear and be heard on any such 
application.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Court may make 
such orders as it thinks fit respecting the costs of the arbitration where any 
question arises respecting such costs and the arbitral award contains no 
sufficient provision concerning them.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Arbitration 
agreement not to be discharged by death of party thereto.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An arbitration agreement shall not be discharged by the death of any party 
thereto either as respects the deceased or as respects any other party, but 
shall in such event be enforceable by or against the legal representative of the 
deceased.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The mandate of an 
arbitrator shall not be terminated by the death of any party by whom he was 
appointed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this 
section shall affect the operation of any law by virtue of which any right of 
action is extinguished by the death of a person.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Provisions in case 
of insolvency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where it is provided by a term in a contract to which an insolvent is a party 
that any dispute arising thereout or in connection therewith shall be submitted 
to arbitration, the said term shall, if the receiver adopts the contract, be 
enforceable by or against him so far as it relates to any such dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a person who has 
been adjudged an insolvent had, before the commencement of the insolvency 
proceedings, become a party to an arbitration agreement, and any matter to which 
the agreement applies is required to be determined in connection with, or for 
the purposes of, the insolvency proceedings, then, if the case is one to which 
sub-section (1) does not apply, any other party or the receiver may apply to the 
judicial authority having jurisdiction in the insolvency proceedings for an 
order directing that the matter in question shall be submitted to arbitration in 
accordance with the arbitration agreement, and the judicial authority may, if it 
is of opinion that, having regard to all the circumstances of the case, the 
matter ought to be determined by arbitration, make an order accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In this section the 
expression “receiver” includes an Official Assignee.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Jurisdiction.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained elsewhere in this Part or in any other law for the time being 
in force, where with respect to an arbitration agreement any application under 
this Part has been made in a Court, that Court alone shall have jurisdiction 
over the arbitral proceedings and all subsequent applications arising out of 
that agreement and the arbitral proceedings shall be made in that Court and in 
no other Court.






</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Limitations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), shall apply to arbitrations as it applies 
to proceedings in Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of 
this section and the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), an arbitration shall be 
deemed to have commenced on the date referred in section 21.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an arbitration 
agreement to submit future disputes to arbitration provides that any claim to 
which the agreement applies shall be barred unless some step to commence 
arbitral proceedings is taken within a time fixed by the agreement, and a 
dispute arises to which the agreement applies, the Court, if it is of opinion 
that in the circumstances of the case undue hardship would otherwise be caused, 
and notwithstanding that the time so fixed has expired, may on such terms, if 
any, as the justice of the case may require, extend the time for such period as 
it thinks proper.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the Court orders 
that an arbitral award be set aside, the period between the commencement of the 
arbitration and the date of the order of the Court shall be excluded in 
computing the time prescribed by the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), for the 
commencement of the proceedings (including arbitration) with respect to the 
dispute so submitted.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Definition.—In 
this Chapter, unless the context otherwise requires, “foreign award” means an 
arbitral award on differences between persons arising out of legal 
relationships, whether contractual or not, considered as commercial under the 
law in force in India, made on or after the 11th day of October, 1960—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> in pursuance of 
an agreement in writing for arbitration to which the Convention set forth in the 
First Schedule applies, and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> in one of such 
territories as the Central Government, being satisfied that reciprocal 
provisions have been made may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare 
to be territories to which the said Convention applies.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>45</number> Power of judicial authority to refer parties to arbitration. 
</title>—Notwithstanding anything contained in Part I or in the Code of Civil 
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), a judicial authority, when seized of an action in a 
matter in respect of which the parties have made an agreement referred to in 
section 44, shall, at the request of one of the parties or any person claiming 
through or under him, refer the parties to arbitration, unless it finds that the 
said agreement is null and void, inoperative or incapable of being performed. 







</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> When foreign award 
binding.—Any 
foreign award which would be enforceable under this Chapter shall be treated as 
binding for all purposes on the persons as between whom it was made, and may 
accordingly be relied on by any of those persons by way of defence, set off or 
otherwise in any legal proceedings in India and any references in this Chapter 
to enforcing a foreign award shall be construed as including references to 
relying on an award.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The party applying for the enforcement of a foreign award shall, at the time of 
the application, produce before the court—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the original 
award or a copy thereof, duly authenticated in the manner required by the law of 
the country in which it was made;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the original 
agreement for arbitration or a duly certified copy thereof; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> such evidence 
as may be necessary to prove that the award is a foreign award.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the award or 
agreement to be produced under sub-section (1) is in a foreign language, the 
party seeking to enforce the award shall produce a translation into English 
certified as correct by a diplomatic or consular agent of the country to which 
that party belongs or certified as correct in such other manner as may be 
sufficient according to the law in force in India.
 
Explanation.—In 
this section and all the following sections of this Chapter, “Court” means the 
principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction in a district, and includes the 
High Court in exercise of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction, having 
jurisdiction over the subject-matter of the award if the same had been the 
subject-matter of a suit, but does not include any civil court of a grade 
inferior to such principal Civil Court, or any Court of Small Causes.




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> Conditions for 
enforcement of foreign awards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Enforcement of a foreign award may be refused, at the request of the party 
against whom it is invoked, only if that party furnishes to the court proof 
that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the parties to 
the agreement referred to in section 44 were, under the law applicable to them, 
under some incapacity, or the said agreement is not valid under the law to which 
the parties have subjected it or, failing any indication thereon, under the law 
of the country where the award was made; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the party 
against whom the award is invoked was not given proper notice of the appointment 
of the arbitrator or of the arbitral proceedings or was otherwise unable to 
present his case; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> the award deals 
with a difference not contemplated by or not falling within the terms of the 
submission to arbitration, or it contains decisions on matters beyond the scope 
of the submission to arbitration:
 
                   
Provided that, if the decisions on matters submitted to arbitration can be 
separated from those not so submitted, that part of the award which contains 
decisions on matters submitted to arbitration may be enforced; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> the composition 
of the arbitral authority or the arbitral procedure was not in accordance with 
the agreement of the parties, or, failing such agreement, was not in accordance 
with the law of the country where the arbitration took place; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number> the award has 
not yet become binding on the parties, or has been set aside or suspended by a 
competent authority of the country in which, or under the law of which, that 
award was made.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Enforcement of an 
arbitral award may also be refused if the Court finds that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the 
subject-matter of the difference is not capable of settlement by arbitration 
under the law of India; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the enforcement 
of the award would be contrary to the public policy of India.
 
Explanation.—Without 
prejudice to the generality of clause (b) of this section, it is hereby 
declared, for the avoidance of any doubt, that an award is in conflict with the 
public policy of India if the making of the award was induced or affected by 
fraud or corruption.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If an application for 
the setting aside or suspension of the award has been made to a competent 
authority referred to in clause (e) of sub-section (1) the Court may, if it 
considers it proper, adjourn the decision on the enforcement of the award and 
may also, on the application of the party claiming enforcement of the award, 
order the other party to give suitable security.








</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>49</number> Enforcement of 
foreign awards.—Where 
the Court is satisfied that the foreign award is enforceable under this Chapter, 
the award shall be deemed to be a decree of that Court.




</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Appealable orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall lie from the order refusing to—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> refer the 
parties to arbitration under section 45;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> enforce a 
foreign award under section 48,
 
to the court authorised by 
law to hear appeals from such order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No second appeal shall 
lie from an order passed in appeal under this section, but nothing in this 
section shall affect or take away any right to appeal to the Supreme Court.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Saving.—Nothing 
in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights which any person would have had of 
enforcing in India of any award or of availing himself in India of any award if 
this Chapter had not been enacted.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Chapter II not to 
apply.—Chapter 
II of this Part shall not apply in relation to foreign awards to which this 
Chapter applies.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Interpretation.—In 
this Chapter “foreign award” means an arbitral award on differences relating to 
matters considered as commercial under the law in force in India made after the 
28th day of July, 1924,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> in pursuance of 
an agreement for arbitration to which the Protocol set forth in the Second 
Schedule applies, and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> between persons 
of whom one is subject to the jurisdiction of some one of such Powers as the 
Central Government, being satisfied that reciprocal provisions have been made, 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be parties to the 
Convention set forth in the Third Schedule, and of whom the other is subject to 
the jurisdiction of some other of the Powers aforesaid, and
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> in one of such 
territories as the Central Government, being satisfied that reciprocal 
provisions have been made, may, by like notification, declare to be territories 
to which the said Convention applies,
 
and for the purposes of 
this Chapter an award shall not be deemed to be final if any proceedings for the 
purpose of contesting the validity of the award are pending in the country in 
which it was made.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> Power of judicial 
authority to refer parties to arbitration.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in Part I or in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
1908), a judicial authority, on being seized of a dispute regarding a contract 
made between persons to whom section 53 applies and including an arbitration 
agreement, whether referring to present or future differences, which is valid 
under that section and capable of being carried into effect, shall refer the 
parties on the application of either of them or any person claiming through or 
under him to the decision of the arbitrators and such reference shall not 
prejudice the competence of the judicial authority in case the agreement or the 
arbitration cannot proceed or becomes inoperative.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Foreign awards when 
binding.—Any 
foreign award which would be enforceable under this Chapter shall be treated as 
binding for all purposes on the persons as between whom it was made, and may 
accordingly be relied on by any of those persons by way of defence, set off or 
otherwise in any legal proceedings in India and any references in this Chapter 
to enforcing a foreign award shall be construed as including references to 
relying on an award.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Evidence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The party applying for the enforcement of a foreign award shall, at the time of 
application, produce before the Court—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the original 
award or a copy thereof duly authenticated in the manner required by the law of 
the country in which it was made;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> evidence 
proving that the award has become final; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> such evidence 
as may be necessary to prove that the conditions mentioned in clauses (a) and 
(c) of sub-section (1) of section 57 are satisfied.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any document 
requiring to be produced under sub-section (1) is in a foreign language, the 
party seeking to enforce the award shall produce a translation into English 
certified as correct by a diplomatic or consular agent of the country to which 
that party belongs or certified as correct in such other manner as may be 
sufficient according to the law in force in India.
 
Explanation.—In 
this section and all the following sections of this Chapter, “Court” means the 
principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction in a district, and includes the 
High Court in exercise of its ordinary original civil jurisdiction, having 
jurisdiction over the subject-matter of the award if the same had been the 
subject-matter of a suit, but does not include any civil court of a grade 
inferior to such principal Civil Court, or any Court of Small Causes.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Conditions for 
enforcement of foreign awards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In order that a foreign award may be enforceable under this Chapter, it shall be 
necessary that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the award has 
been made in pursuance of a submission to arbitration which is valid under the 
law applicable thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the 
subject-matter of the award is capable of settlement by arbitration under the 
law of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> the award has 
been made by the arbitral tribunal provided for in the submission to arbitration 
or constituted in the manner agreed upon by the parties and in conformity with 
the law governing the arbitration procedure;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> the award has 
become final in the country in which it has been made, in the sense that it will 
not be considered as such if it is open to opposition or appeal or if it is 
proved that any proceedings for the purpose of contesting the validity of the 
award are pending;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number> the enforcement 
of the award is not contrary to the public policy or the law of India.
 
Explanation.—Without 
prejudice to the generality of clause (e), it is hereby declared, for the 
avoidance of any doubt, that an award is in conflict with the public policy of 
India if the making of the award was induced or affected by fraud or corruption.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Even if the conditions 
laid down in sub-section (1) are fulfilled, enforcement of the award shall be 
refused if the Court is satisfied that—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the award has 
been annulled in the country in which it was made;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the party 
against whom it is sought to use the award was not given notice of the 
arbitration proceedings in sufficient time to enable him to present his case; or 
that, being under a legal incapacity, he was not properly represented;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> the award does 
not deal with the differences contemplated by or falling within the terms of the 
submission to arbitration or that it contains decisions on matters beyond the 
scope of the submission to arbitration:
 
Provided that if the award 
has not covered all the differences submitted to the arbitral tribunal, the 
Court may, if it thinks fit, postpone such enforcement or grant it subject to 
such guarantee as the Court may decide.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the party against 
whom the award has been made proves that under the law governing the arbitration 
procedure there is a ground, other than the grounds referred to in clauses (a) 
and (c) of sub-section (1) and clauses (b) and (c) of sub-section (2) entitling 
him to contest the validity of the award, the Court may, if it thinks fit, 
either refuse enforcement of the award or adjourn the consideration thereof, 
giving such party a reasonable time within which to have the award annulled by 
the competent tribunal.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Enforcement of 
foreign awards.—Where 
the Court is satisfied that the foreign award is enforceable under this Chapter, 
the award shall be deemed to be a decree of the Court.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> Appealable orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall lie from the order refusing—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> to refer the 
parties to arbitration under section 54; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> to enforce a 
foreign award under section 57,
 
to the court authorised by 
law to hear appeals from such order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No second appeal shall 
lie from an order passed in appeal under this section, but nothing in this 
section shall affect or take away any right to appeal to the Supreme Court.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> Saving.—Nothing 
in this Chapter shall prejudice any rights which any person would have had of 
enforcing in India of any award or of availing himself in India of any award if 
this Chapter had not been enacted.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> Application and 
scope.—
<section><number>1</number> Save 
as otherwise provided by any law for the time being in force and unless the 
parties have otherwise agreed, this Part shall apply to conciliation of disputes 
arising out of legal relationship, whether contractual or not and to all 
proceedings relating thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> This Part shall not 
apply where by virtue of any law for the time being in force certain disputes 
may not be submitted to conciliation.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> Commencement of 
conciliation proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The party initiating conciliation shall send to the other party a written 
invitation to conciliate under this Part, briefly identifying the subject of the 
dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Conciliation 
proceedings shall commence when the other party accepts in writing the 
invitation to conciliate.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the other party 
rejects the invitation, there will be no conciliation proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the party 
initiating conciliation does not receive a reply within thirty days from the 
date on which he sends the invitation, or within such other period of time as 
specified in the invitation, he may elect to treat this as a rejection of the 
invitation to conciliate and if he so elects, he shall inform in writing the 
other party accordingly.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> Number of 
conciliators.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be one conciliator unless the parties agree that there shall be two 
or three conciliators.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where there is more 
than one conciliator, they ought, as a general rule, to act jointly.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> Appointment of 
conciliators.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to sub-section (2),—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> in conciliation 
proceedings with one conciliator, the parties may agree on the name of a sole 
conciliator;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> in conciliation 
proceedings with two conciliators, each party may appoint one conciliator;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> in conciliation 
proceedings with three conciliators, each party may appoint one conciliator and 
the parties may agree on the name of the third conciliator who shall act as the 
presiding conciliator.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Parties may enlist the 
assistance of a suitable institution or person in connection with the 
appointment of conciliators, and in particular,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> a party may 
request such an institution or person to recommend the names of suitable 
individuals to act as conciliator; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the parties may 
agree that the appointment of one or more conciliators be made directly by such 
an institution or person:
 
Provided that in 
recommending or appointing individuals to act as conciliator, the institution or 
person shall have regard to such considerations as are likely to secure the 
appointment of an independent and impartial conciliator and, with respect to a 
sole or third conciliator, shall take into account the advisability of 
appointing a conciliator of a nationality other than the nationalities of the 
parties.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> Submission of 
statements to conciliator.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The conciliator, upon his appointment, may request each party to submit to him a 
brief written statement describing the general nature of the dispute and the 
points at issue. Each party shall send a copy of such statement to the other 
party.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The conciliator may 
request each party to submit to him a further written statement of his position 
and the facts and grounds in support thereof, supplemented by any documents and 
other evidence that such party deems appropriate. The party shall send a copy of 
such statement, documents and other evidence to the other party.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At any stage of the 
conciliation proceedings, the conciliator may request a party to submit to him 
such additional information as he deems appropriate.
 
Explanation.—In 
this section and all the following sections of this Part, the term “conciliator” 
applies to a sole conciliator, two or three conciliators as the case may be.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>66</number> Conciliator not bound by 
certain enactments.—The conciliator is not bound by 
the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) or the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 
(1 of 1872).
  </article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> Role of 
conciliator.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The conciliator shall assist the parties in an independent and impartial manner 
in their attempt to reach an amicable settlement of their dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The conciliator shall 
be guided by principles of objectivity, fairness and justice, giving 
consideration to, among other things, the rights and obligations of the parties, 
the usages of the trade concerned and the circumstances surrounding the dispute, 
including any previous business practices between the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The conciliator may 
conduct the conciliation proceedings in such a manner as he considers 
appropriate, taking into account the circumstances of the case, the wishes the 
parties may express, including any request by a party that the conciliator hear 
oral statements, and the need for a speedy settlement of the dispute.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The conciliator may, 
at any stage of the conciliation proceedings, make proposals for a settlement of 
the dispute. Such proposals need not be in writing and need not be accompanied 
by a statement of the reasons therefor.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> Administrative 
assistance.—In 
order to facilitate the conduct of the conciliation proceedings, the parties, or 
the conciliator with the consent of the parties, may arrange for administrative 
assistance by a suitable institution or person.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>69</number> Communication 
between conciliator and parties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The conciliator may invite the parties to meet him or may communicate with them 
orally or in writing. He may meet or communicate with the parties together or 
with each of them separately.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Unless the parties 
have agreed upon the place where meetings with the conciliator are to be held, 
such place shall be determined by the conciliator, after consultation with the 
parties, having regard to the circumstances of the conciliation proceedings.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> Disclosure of 
information.—When 
the conciliator receives factual information concerning the dispute from a 
party, he shall disclose the substance of that information to the other party in 
order that the other party may have the opportunity to present any explanation 
which he considers appropriate:
 
Provided that when a party 
gives any information to the conciliator subject to a specific condition that it 
be kept confidential, the conciliator shall not disclose that information to the 
other party.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>71</number> Co-operation of 
parties with conciliator.—The 
parties shall in good faith co-operate with the conciliator and, in particular, 
shall endeavour to comply with requests by the conciliator to submit written 
materials, provide evidence and attend meetings.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> Suggestions by 
parties for settlement of dispute.—Each 
party may, on his own initiative or at the invitation of the conciliator, submit 
to the conciliator suggestions for the settlement of the dispute.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> Settlement 
agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When it appears to the conciliator that there exist elements of a settlement 
which may be acceptable to the parties, he shall formulate the terms of a 
possible settlement and submit them to the parties for their observations. After 
receiving the observations of the parties, the conciliator may reformulate the 
terms of a possible settlement in the light of such observations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the parties reach 
agreement on a settlement of the dispute, they may draw up and sign a written 
settlement agreement. If requested by the parties, the conciliator may draw up, 
or assist the parties in drawing up, the settlement agreement.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the parties sign 
the settlement agreement, it shall be final and binding on the parties and 
persons claiming under them respectively.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The conciliator shall 
authenticate the settlement agreement and furnish a copy thereof to each of the 
parties.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>74</number> Status and effect 
of settlement agreement.—The 
settlement agreement shall have the same status and effect as if it is an 
arbitral award on agreed terms on the substance of the dispute rendered by an 
arbitral tribunal under section 30.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> Confidentiality.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the conciliator 
and the parties shall keep confidential all matters relating to the conciliation 
proceedings. Confidentiality shall extend also to the settlement agreement, 
except where its disclosure is necessary for purposes of implementation and 
enforcement.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Termination of 
conciliation proceedings.—The 
conciliation proceedings shall be terminated—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> by the signing 
of the settlement agreement by the parties on the date of the agreement; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> by a written 
declaration of the conciliator, after consultation with the parties, to the 
effect that further efforts at conciliation are no longer justified, on the date 
of the declaration; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> by a written 
declaration of the parties addressed to the conciliator to the effect that the 
conciliation proceedings are terminated, on the date of the declaration; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number> by a written 
declaration of a party to the other party and the conciliator, if appointed, to 
the effect that the conciliation proceedings are terminated, on the date of the 
declaration.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> Resort to arbitral 
or judicial proceedings.—The 
parties shall not initiate, during the conciliation proceedings, any arbitral or 
judicial proceedings in respect of a dispute that is the subject-matter of the 
conciliation proceedings except that a party may initiate arbitral or judicial 
proceedings where, in his opinion, such proceedings are necessary for preserving 
his rights.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Costs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Upon termination of the conciliation proceedings, the conciliator shall fix the 
costs of the conciliation and give written notice thereof to the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of 
sub-section (1), “costs” means reasonable costs relating to—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the fee and 
expenses of the conciliator and witnesses requested by the conciliator with the 
consent of the parties;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> any expert 
advice requested by the conciliator with the consent of the parties;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> any assistance 
provided pursuant to clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 64 and section 68;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> any other 
expenses incurred in connection with the conciliation proceedings and the 
settlement agreement.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The costs shall be 
borne equally by the parties unless the settlement agreement provides for a 
different apportionment. All other expenses incurred by a party shall be borne 
by that party.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> Deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The conciliator may direct each party to deposit an equal amount as an advance 
for the costs referred to in sub-section (2) of section 78 which he expects will 
be incurred.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> During the course of 
the conciliation proceedings, the conciliator may direct supplementary deposits 
in an equal amount from each party.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the required 
deposits under sub-sections (1) and (2) are not paid in full by both parties 
within thirty days, the conciliator may suspend the proceedings or may make a 
written declaration of termination of the proceedings to the parties, effective 
on the date of that declaration.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Upon termination of 
the conciliation proceedings, the conciliator shall render an accounting to the 
parties of the deposits received and shall return any unexpended balance to the 
parties.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> Role of conciliator 
in other proceedings.—Unless 
otherwise agreed by the parties,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> the conciliator 
shall not act as an arbitrator or as a representative or counsel of a party in 
any arbitral or judicial proceeding in respect of a dispute that is the subject 
of the conciliation proceedings;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> the conciliator 
shall not be presented by the parties as a witness in any arbitral or judicial 
proceedings.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> Admissibility of 
evidence in other proceedings.—The 
parties shall not rely on or introduce as evidence in arbitral or judicial 
proceedings, whether or not such proceedings relate to the dispute that is the 
subject of the conciliation proceedings,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> views expressed 
or suggestions made by the other party in respect of a possible settlement of 
the dispute;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> admissions made 
by the other party in the course of the conciliation proceedings;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> proposals made 
by the conciliator;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number> the fact that 
the other party had indicated his willingness to accept a proposal for 
settlement made by the conciliator.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> Power of High Court 
to make rules.—The 
High Court may make rules consistent with this Act as to all proceedings before 
the Court under this Act.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> Removal of 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no such 
order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the date of 
commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each 
House of Parliament.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>84</number> Power to make 
rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for 
carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every rule made by the 
Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be, after it is 
made before each House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total period 
of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>85</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Arbitration (Protocol and Convention) Act, 1937 (6 of 1937), the Arbitration 
Act, 1940 (10 of 1940) and the Foreign Awards (Recognition and Enforcement) Act, 
1961 (45 of 1961) are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the provisions 
of the said enactments shall apply in relation to arbitral proceedings which 
commenced before this Act came into force unless otherwise agreed by the parties 
but this Act shall apply in relation to arbitral proceedings which commenced on 
or after this Act comes into force;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> all rules made 
and notifications published, under the said enactments shall, to the extent to 
which they are not repugnant to this Act, be deemed respectively to have been 
made or issued under this Act.






</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>86</number> Repeal of Ordinance 
27 of 1996 and Saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Arbitration and Conciliation (Third) Ordinance, 1996 (27 of 1996) is hereby 
repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, any order, rule, notification or scheme made or anything done or any 
action taken in pursuance of any provision of the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been made, done or taken under the corresponding provisions of 
this Act.
 
 
</section></article><form>
 




THE ARBITRATION AND CONCILIATION 

Act, 1996
 


 
 


THE FIRST SCHEDULE
 


(See section 44)
 


CONVENTION ON THE 
RECOGNITION AND ENFORCEMENT  

OF FOREIGN ARBITRAL AWARDS
 


ARTICLE I
 


1. This Convention shall 
apply to the recognition and enforcement of arbitral awards made in the 
territory of a State other than the State where the recognition and enforcement 
of such awards are sought, and arising out of differences between persons, 
whether physical or legal. It shall also apply to arbitral awards not considered 
as domestic awards in the State where their recognition and enforcement are 
sought.
 


2. The term “arbitral 
awards” shall include not only awards made by arbitrators appointed for each 
case but also those made by permanent arbitral bodies to which the parties have 
submitted.
 


3. When signing, ratifying 
or acceding to this Convention, or notifying extension under article X hereof, 
any State may on the basis of reciprocity declare that it will apply the 
Convention to the recognition and enforcement of awards made only in the 
territory of another Contracting State. It may also declare that it will apply 
the Convention only to differences arising out of legal relationships, whether 
contractual or not, which are considered as commercial under the national law of 
the State making such declaration.
 


ARTICLE II
 


1. Each Contracting State 
shall recognise an agreement in writing under which the parties undertake to 
submit to arbitration all or any differences which have arisen or which may 
arise between them in respect of defined legal relationship, whether contractual 
or not, concerning a subject-matter capable of settlement by arbitration.
 


2. The term “agreement in 
writing” shall include an arbitral clause in a contract or an arbitration 
agreement, signed by the parties or contained in an exchange of letters or 
telegrams.
 


3. The court of a 
Contracting State, when seized of an action in a matter in respect of which the 
parties have made an agreement within the meaning of this article, shall, at the 
request of one of the parties, refer the parties to arbitration, unless it finds 
that the said agreement is null and void, inoperative and incapable of being 
performed.
 


ARTICLE III
 


Each Contracting State 
shall recognize arbitral awards as binding and enforce them in accordance with 
the rules of procedure of the territory where the award is relied upon, under 
the conditions laid down in the following articles. There shall not be imposed 
substantially more onerous conditions or higher fees or charges on the 
recognition or enforcement of arbitral awards to which this Convention applies 
than are imposed on the recognition or enforcement of domestic arbitral awards.
 


ARTICLE IV
 


1. To obtain the 
recognition and enforcement mentioned in the preceding article, the party 
applying for recognition and enforcement shall, at the time of the application, 
supply—
 


        (a) the duly 
authenticated original award or a duly certified copy thereof;
 


        (b) the original 
agreement referred to in article II or a duly certified copy thereof.
 


2. If the said award or 
agreement is not made in an official language of the country in which the award 
is relied upon, the party applying for recognition and enforcement of the award 
shall produce a translation of these documents into such language. The 
translation shall be certified by an official or sworn translator or by a 
diplomatic or consular agent.
 


ARTICLE V
 


1. Recognition and 
enforcement of the award may be refused, at the request of the party against 
whom it is invoked, only if that party furnishes to the competent authority 
where the recognition and enforcement is sought, proof that—
 


        (a) the parties to 
the agreement referred to in article II were, under the law applicable to them, 
under some incapacity, or the said agreement is not valid under the law to which 
the parties have subjected it or, failing any indication thereon, under the law 
of the country where the award was made; or
 


        (b) the party 
against whom the award is invoked was not given proper notice of the appointment 
of the arbitrator or of the arbitration proceedings or was otherwise unable to 
present his case; or
 


        (c) the award deals 
with a difference not contemplated by or not falling within the terms of the 
submission to arbitration, or it contains decisions on matters beyond the scope 
of the submission to arbitration; provided that, if the decisions on matters 
submitted to arbitration can be separated from those not so submitted, that part 
of the award which contains decisions on matters submitted to arbitration may be 
recognised and enforced; or
 


        (d) the composition 
of the arbitral authority or the arbitral procedure was not in accordance with 
the agreement of the parties, or, failing such agreement, was not in accordance 
with the law of the country where the arbitration took place; or
 


        (e) the award has 
not yet become binding on the parties, or has been set aside or suspended by a 
competent authority of the country in which, or under the law of which, that 
award was made.
 


2. Recognition and 
enforcement of an arbitral award may also be refused if the competent authority 
in the country where recognition and enforcement is sought finds that—
 


        (a) the 
subject-matter of the difference is not capable of settlement by arbitration 
under the law of that country; or
 


        (b) the recognition 
or enforcement of the award would be contrary to the public policy of that 
country.
 


ARTICLE VI
 


If an application for the 
setting aside or suspension of the award has been made to a competent authority 
referred to in article V(1)(e), the authority before which the award is sought 
to be relied upon may, if it considers it proper, adjourn the decision on the 
enforcement of the award and may also, on the application of the party claiming 
enforcement of the award, order the other party to give suitable security.
 


ARTICLE VII
 


1. The provisions of the 
present Convention shall not affect the validity of multilateral or bilateral 
agreements concerning the recognition and enforcement of arbitral awards entered 
into by the Contracting States nor deprive any interested party of any right he 
may have to avail himself of an arbitral award in the manner and to the extent 
allowed by the law or the treaties of the country where such award is sought to 
be relied upon.
 


2. The Geneva Protocol on 
Arbitration Clauses of 1923 and the Geneva Convention on the Execution of 
Foreign Arbitral Awards of 1927 shall cease to have effect between Contracting 
States on their becoming bound and to the extent that they become bound by this 
Convention.
 


ARTICLE VIII
 


1. This Convention shall be 
open until 31st December, 1958 for signature on behalf of any Member of the 
United Nations and also on behalf of any other State which is or hereafter 
becomes member of any specialised agency of the United Nations, or which is or 
hereafter becomes a party to the Statute of the International Court of Justice, 
or any other State to which an invitation has been addressed by the General 
Assembly of the United Nations.
 


2. This Convention shall be 
ratified and the instrument of ratification shall be deposited with the 
Secretary-General of the United Nations.
 


ARTICLE IX
 


1. This Convention shall be 
open for accession to all States referred to in article VIII.
 


2. Accession shall be 
effected by the deposit of an instrument of accession with the Secretary-General 
of the United Nations.
 


ARTICLE X
 


1. Any State may, at the 
time of signature, ratification or accession, declare that this Convention shall 
extend to all or any of the territories for the international relations of which 
it is responsible. Such a declaration shall take effect when the Convention 
enters into force for the State concerned.
 


2. At any time thereafter 
any such extension shall be made by notification addressed to the 
Secretary-General of the United Nations and shall take effect as from the 
ninetieth day after the day of receipt by the Secretary-General of the United 
Nations of this notification, or as from the date of entry into force of the 
Convention for the State concerned, whichever is the later.
 


3. With respect to those 
territories to which this Convention is not extended at the time of signature, 
ratification or accession, each State concerned shall consider the possibility 
of taking the necessary steps in order to extend the application of this 
Convention to such territories, subject, where necessary for constitutional 
reasons, to the consent of the Governments of such territories.
 


ARTICLE XI
 


In the case of a federal or 
non-unitary State, the following provisions shall apply:—
 


        (a) with respect of 
those articles of this Convention that come within the legislative jurisdiction 
of the federal authority, the obligations of the federal Government shall to 
this extent be the same as those of Contracting States which are not federal 
States;
 


        (b) with respect to 
those articles of this Convention that come within the legislative jurisdiction 
of constituent States or provinces which are not, under the constitutional 
system of the federation, bound to take legislative action, the federal 
Government shall bring such articles with a favourable recommendation to the 
notice of the appropriate authorities of constituent States or provinces at the 
earliest possible moment;
 


        (c) a federal State 
Party to this Convention shall, at the request of any other Contracting State 
transmitted through the Secretary-General of the United Nations, supply a 
statement of the law and practice of the federation and its constituent units in 
regard to any particular provision of this Convention, showing the extent to 
which effect has been given to that provision by legislative or other action.
 


ARTICLE XII
 


1. This Convention shall 
come into force on the ninetieth day following the date of deposit of the third 
instrument of ratification or accession.
 


2. For each State ratifying 
or acceding to this Convention after the deposit of the third instrument of 
ratification or accession, this Convention shall enter into force on the 
ninetieth day after deposit by such State of its instrument of ratification or 
accession.
 


ARTICLE XIII
 


1. Any Contracting State 
may denounce this Convention by a written notification to the Secretary-General 
of the United Nations. Denunciation shall take effect one year after the date of 
receipt of the notification by the Secretary-General.
 


2. Any State which has made 
a declaration or notification under article X may, at any time thereafter, by 
notification to the Secretary-General of the United Nations, declare that this 
Convention shall cease to extend to the territory concerned one year after the 
date of the receipt of the notification by the Secretary-General.
 


3. This Convention shall 
continue to be applicable to arbitral awards in respect of which recognition or 
enforcement proceedings have been instituted before the denunciation takes 
effect.
 


ARTICLE XIV
 


A Contracting State shall 
not be entitled to avail itself of the present Convention against other 
Contracting States except to the extent that it is itself bound to apply the 
Convention. 
 


ARTICLE XV
 


The Secretary-General of 
the United Nations shall notify the States contemplated in article VIII of the 
following:—
 


        (a) signatures and 
ratifications in accordance with article VIII;
 


        (b) accessions in 
accordance with article IX;
 


        (c) declarations 
and notifications under articles I, X and XI;
 


        (d) the date upon 
which this Convention enters into force in accordance with article XII;
 


        (e) denunciations 
and notifications in accordance with article XIII.
 


ARTICLE XVI
 


1. This Convention, of 
which the Chinese, English, French, Russian and Spanish texts shall be equally 
authentic, shall be deposited in the archives of the United Nations.
 


2. The Secretary-General of 
the United Nations shall transmit a certified copy of this Convention to the 
States contemplated in article XIII.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE ARBITRATION AND CONCILIATION 

Act, 1996
 


 
 


 
 


THE SECOND SCHEDULE
 


(See section 53)
 


PROTOCOL ON ARBITRATION 
CLAUSES
 


The undersigned, being duly 
authorised, declare that they accept, on behalf of the countries which they 
represent, the following provisions:—
 


          1. Each of the 
Contracting States recognises the validity of an agreement whether relating to 
existing or future differences between parties subject respectively to the 
jurisdiction of different Contracting States by which the parties to a contract 
agree to submit to arbitration all or any differences that may arise in 
connection with such contract relating to commercial matters or to any other 
matter capable of settlement by arbitration, whether or not the arbitration is 
to take place in a country to whose jurisdiction none of the parties is subject.
 


              Each 
Contracting State reserves the right to limit the obligation mentioned above to 
contracts which are considered as commercial under its national law. Any 
Contracting State which avails itself of this right will notify the 
Secretary-General of the League of Nations in order that the other Contracting 
States may be so informed.
 


          2. The arbitral 
procedure, including the constitution of the Arbitral Tribunal, shall be 
governed by the will of the parties and by the law of the country in whose 
territory the arbitration takes place.
 


              The 
Contracting States agree to facilitate all steps in the procedure which require 
to be taken in their own territories, in accordance with the provisions of their 
law governing arbitral procedure applicable to existing differences.
 


          3. Each 
Contracting State undertakes to ensure the execution by its authorities and in 
accordance with the provisions of its national laws of arbitral awards made in 
its own territory under the preceding articles.
 


          4. The Tribunals 
of the Contracting Parties, on being seized of a dispute regarding a contract 
made between persons to whom Article I applies and including an Arbitration 
Agreement whether referring to present or future differences which is valid in 
virtue of the said article and capable of being carried into effect, shall refer 
the parties on the application of either of them to the decision of the 
Arbitrators.
 


              Such 
reference shall not prejudice the competence of the judicial tribunals in case 
the agreement or the arbitration cannot proceed or becomes inoperative.
 


          5. The present 
Protocol, which shall remain open for signature by all States, shall be 
ratified. The ratification shall be deposited as soon as possible with the 
Secretary-General of the League of Nations, who shall notify such deposit to all 
the Signatory States.
 


          6. The present 
Protocol will come into force as soon as two ratifications have been deposited. 
Thereafter it will take effect, in the case of each Contracting State, one month 
after the notification by the Secretary-General of the deposit of its 
ratification.
 


          7. The present 
Protocol may be denounced by any Contracting State on giving one year’s notice. 
Denunciation shall be effected by a notification addressed to the 
Secretary-General of the League, who will immediately transmit copies of such 
notification to all the other Signatory States and inform them of the date on 
which it was received. The denunciation shall take effect one year after the 
date on which it was notified to the Secretary-General, and shall operate only 
in respect of the notifying State.
 


          8. The 
Contracting States may declare that their acceptance of the present Protocol 
does not include any or all of the under-mentioned territories: that is to say, 
their colonies, overseas possessions or territories, protectorates or the 
territories over which they exercise a mandate.
 


The said States may 
subsequently adhere separately on behalf of any territory thus excluded. The 
Secretary-General of the League of Nations shall be informed as soon as possible 
of such adhesions. He shall notify such adhesions to all Signatory States. They 
will take effect one month after the notification by the Secretary-General to 
all Signatory States.
 


The Contracting States may 
also denounce the Protocol separately on behalf of any of the territories 
referred to above. Article 7 applies to such denunciation.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE ARBITRATION AND CONCILIATION 

Act, 1996
 


 
 


THE THIRD SCHEDULE
 


(See section 53)
 


CONVENTION OF THE 
EXECUTION OF FOREIGN ARBITRAL AWARDS
 


Article 1.—(1) 
In the territories of any High Contracting Party to which the present Convention 
applies, an arbitral award made in pursuance of an agreement, whether relating 
to existing or future differences (hereinafter called “a submission to 
arbitration”) covered by the Protocol on Arbitration Clauses opened at Geneva on 
September 24th, 1923, shall be recognised as binding and shall be enforced in 
accordance with the rules of the procedure of the territory where the award is 
relied upon, provided that the said award has been made in a territory of one of 
the High Contracting Parties to which the present Convention applies and between 
persons who are subject to the jurisdiction of one of the High Contracting 
Parties.
 


(2) To obtain such 
recognition or enforcement, it shall, further, be necessary—
 


        (a) that the award 
has been made in pursuance of a submission to arbitration which is valid under 
the law applicable thereto;
 


        (b) that the 
subject-matter of the award is capable of settlement by arbitration under the 
law of the country in which the award is sought to be relied upon;
 


        (c) that the award 
has been made by the Arbitral Tribunal provided for in the submission to 
arbitration or constituted in the manner agreed upon by the parties and in 
conformity with the law governing the arbitration procedure;
 


        (d) that the award 
has become final in the country in which it has been made, in the sense that it 
will not be considered as such if it is open to opposition, appeal or pourvoi 
en cassation (in the countries where such forms of procedure exist) or if it 
is proved that any proceedings for the purpose of contesting the validity of the 
award are pending;
 


        (e) that the 
recognition or enforcement of the award is not contrary to the public policy or 
to the principles of the law of the country in which it is sought to be relied 
upon.
 


Article 2.—Even 
if the conditions laid down in Article 1 hereof are fulfilled, recognition and 
enforcement of the award shall be refused if the court is satisfied—
 


        (a) that the award 
has been annulled in the country in which it was made;
 


        (b) that the party 
against whom it is sought to use the award was not given notice of the 
arbitration proceedings in sufficient time to enable him to present his case; or 
that, being under a legal incapacity, he was not properly represented;
 


        (c) that the award 
does not deal with the differences contemplated by or falling within the terms 
of the submission to arbitration or that it contains decisions on matters beyond 
the scope of the submission to arbitration.
 


If the award has not 
covered all the questions submitted to the arbitral tribunal, the competent 
authority of the country where recognition or enforcement of the award is sought 
can, if it thinks fit, postpone such recognition or enforcement or grant it 
subject to such guarantee as that authority may decide.
 


Article 3.—If 
the party against whom the award has been made proves that, under the law 
governing the arbitration procedure, there is a ground, other than the grounds 
referred to in Article 1(a) and (c), and Article 2(b) and (c), entitling him to 
contest the validity of the award in a Court of Law, the Court may, if it thinks 
fit, either refuse recognition or enforcement of the award or adjourn the 
consideration thereof, giving such party a reasonable time within which to have 
the award annulled by the competent tribunal.
 


Article 4.—The 
party relying upon an award or claiming its enforcement must supply, in 
particular—
 


        (1) the original 
award or a copy thereof duly authenticated, according to the requirements of the 
law of the country in which it was made;
 


        (2) documentary or 
other evidence to prove that the award has become final, in the sense defined in 
Article 1(d), in the country in which it was made;
 


        (3) when necessary, 
documentary or other evidence to prove that the conditions laid down in Article 
1, paragraph (1) and paragraph (2) (a) and (c), have been fulfilled.
 


A translation of the award 
and of the other documents mentioned in this Article into the official language 
of the country where the award is sought to be relied upon may be demanded. Such 
translations must be certified correct by a diplomatic or consular agent of the 
country to which the party who seeks to rely upon the award belongs or by a 
sworn translator of the country where the award is sought to be relied upon.
 


Article 5.—The 
provisions of the above Articles shall not deprive any interested party of the 
right of availing himself of an arbitral award in the manner and to the extent 
allowed by the law or the treaties of the country where such award is sought to 
be relied upon.
 


Article 6.—The 
present Convention applies only to arbitral awards made after the coming into 
force of the Protocol on Arbitration Clauses opened at Geneva on September 24th, 
1923.
 


Article 7.—The 
present Convention, which will remain open to the signature of all the 
signatories of the Protocol of 1923 on Arbitration Clauses, shall be ratified.
 


It may be ratified only on 
behalf of those Members of the League of Nations and Non-Member States on whose 
behalf the Protocol of 1923 shall have been ratified.
 


Ratification shall be 
deposited as soon as possible with the Secretary-General of the League of 
Nations, who will notify such deposit to all the signatories.
 


Article 8.—The 
present Convention shall come into force three months after it shall have been 
ratified on behalf of two High Contracting Parties. Thereafter, it shall take 
effect, in the case of each High Contracting Party, three months after the 
deposit of the ratification on its behalf with the Secretary-General of the 
League of Nations.
 


Article 9.—The 
present Convention may be denounced on behalf of any Member of the League or 
Non-Member State. Denunciation shall be notified in writing to the 
Secretary-General of the League of Nations, who will immediately send a copy 
thereof, certified to be in conformity with the notifications, to all the other 
Contracting Parties, at the same time informing them of the date on which he 
received it.
 


The denunciation shall come 
into force only in respect of the High Contracting Party which shall have 
notified it and one year after such notification shall have reached the 
Secretary-General of the League of Nations.
 


The denunciation of the 
Protocol on Arbitration Clauses shall entail, ipso facto, the 
denunciation of the present Convention.
 


Article 10.—The 
present Convention does not apply to the colonies, protectorates or territories 
under suzerainty or mandate of any High Contracting Party unless they are 
specially mentioned.
 


The application of this 
Convention to one or more of such colonies, protectorates or territories to 
which the Protocol on Arbitration Clauses opened at Geneva on September 24th, 
1923, applies, can be effected at any time by means of a declaration addressed 
to the Secretary-General of the League of Nations by one of the High Contracting 
Parties.
 


Such declaration shall take 
effect three months after the deposit thereof.
 


The High Contracting 
Parties can at any time denounce the Convention for all or any of the Colonies, 
Protectorates or territories referred to above. Article 9 hereof applied to such 
denunciation.
 


Article 11.—A 
certified copy of the present Convention shall be transmitted by the 
Secretary-General of the League of Nations to every Member of the League of 
Nations and to every Non-Member State which signs the same.
 


 
 


—————
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  See  Appointment of Arbitrators by the Chief Justice 
of India Scheme, 1996, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 
1, dated 16th May, 1996 .</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>