<act><title>


    THE EMBLEMS AND NAMES (PREVENTION OF IMPROPER USE) RULES, 19821</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Emblems and Names (Prevention of Improper Use) 
    Rules, 1982.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the 
    Emblems and Names (Prevention of Improper Use) Act, 1950 (12 of 1950); 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Committee” 
    means the Committee appointed by the Central Government under rule 4; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “designated 
    officer” means an officer designated by the Central Government under rule 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Schedule” means 
    Schedule to the Act. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Appointment of 
    designated officer.—The 
    Central Government may, for purposes of these rules designate an officer who 
    shall not be below the rank of a Group ‘A’ officer of the Central
    government as designated 
    officer. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Appointment of 
    Committee.—The 
    Central Government may appoint a Committee for purposes of these rules 
    consisting of,— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    an officer of 
    the Central government 
    not            
    below the rank of a Joint Secretary to the            
    Government of India in the Ministry/                 
    Department of that Government which is          
    administratively concerned with the   
    administration of the Act                            
    —Chairman;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   an officer of 
    the Ministry of Law, Justice             
    and Company Affairs in the Department           
    of legal Affairs                                         
    —Member;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> an officer of 
    the Ministry of Home Affairs       —Member.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Co-option of 
    Members of the Committee.—The 
    Committee may, at its discretion co-opt any person or persons of 
    eminence/erudation not exceeding two at a time as its members for 
    considering any proposal or classes of proposals for the consideration of 
    which such persons’ views are considered valuable by the Committee. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Processing of 
    proposals.—Any 
    proposal for making additions or alterations to the Schedule received by the 
    Central Government from any State Government, local authority or any other 
    source, shall be referred to the designated officer who shall, after 
    examining the same and after classifying the said proposals in appropriate 
    classes wherever possible, submit them for consideration by the Committee. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Recommendation 
    of the Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Committee shall, after considering the proposal submitted by the 
    designated officer, make appropriate recommendations as to the desirability 
    or otherwise of including any particular proposal or classes of proposals in 
    the Schedule. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The designated 
    officer shall, on receipt of the recommendations from the Committee, submit 
    the same to the Central Government whose decision thereon shall be final. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Use of emblems 
    and names contained in the Schedule.—No 
    person shall use or continue to use, for the purpose of any trade, business, 
    calling or profession, or in the title of any patent, or in any trademark or 
    design, any name or emblem specified in the Schedule or any colourable 
    imitation thereof without the previous permission of the Central Government 
    or of such officer of Government as may be authorised in this behalf by the 
    Central Government except in the following cases, namely:— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>   the use thereof 
    by the agencies, bodies or persons to whom the name or emblem belongs; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   the use thereof 
    by the Central Government or any State Government to whom the name or emblem 
    belongs; 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   issue of postal 
    stamps, coins or other commemorative items brought out by the Central 
    Government or a State Government in honour of any of the persons or 
    institutions whose names are included in the Schedule; 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   the use of the 
    names of persons included in the Schedule by bodies set up by the Central
    government or State Government 
    for propogation of the ideals for which they stood and lived; 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   the authorship, 
    production, publication, exhibition or transmission by any medium for 
    academic, artistic, biographical, cultural, educational, scientific or 
    spiritual purposes with the previous permission of the Central Government 
    and subject to such conditions as the Central Government may lay down while 
    granting such permission. 
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>