<act><title>

The 
    Limitation Act, 1963</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Limitation Act, 1963.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India except, the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “applicant” includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    a petitioner; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any person from or through whom an 
    applicant derives his right to apply; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    any person whose estate is 
    represented by the applicant as executor, administrator or other 
    representative; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    “application” includes a petition; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “bill of exchange” includes a hundi and 
    a cheque; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “bond “ includes any instrument whereby 
    a person obliges himself to pay money to another, on condition that the 
    obligation shall be void if a specified act is performed, or is not 
    performed, as the case may be; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “defendant” includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any person from or through whom a 
    defendant derives his liability to be sued; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any person whose estate is represented 
    by the defendant as executor, administrator or other representative; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>    “easement” includes a right not arising 
    from contract, by which one person is entitled to remove and appropriate for 
    his own profit any part of the soil belonging to another or anything growing 
    in, or attached to, or subsisting upon, the land of another; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “foreign country” means any country 
    other than India; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “good faith”— nothing shall be deemed 
    to be done in good faith which is not done with due care and attention; 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “plaintiff” includes— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    any person from or through whom a 
    plaintiff derives his right to sue; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    any person whose estate is represented 
    by the plaintiff as executor, administrator or other representative; 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>j</number>    “period of limitation” means the period 
    of limitation prescribed for any suit, appeal or application by the 
    Schedule, and “prescribed period” means the period of limitation computed in 
    accordance with the provisions of this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>    “promissory note” means any instrument 
    whereby the maker engages absolutely to pay a specified sum of money to 
    another at a time therein limited, or on demand, or at sight; 
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>    “suit” does not include an appeal or an 
    application; 
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>    “tort” means a civil wrong which is not 
    exclusively the breach of a contract or the breach of a trust; 
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>    “trustee” does not include a 
    benamidar, a mortgagee remaining in possession after the mortgage has 
    been satisfied or a person in a wrongful possession without title. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>3</number>
Bar of limitation.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to the provisions contained in sections 4 to 24 (inclusive), every suit
instituted, appeal preferred, and application made after the prescribed period
shall be dismissed, although limitation has not been set up as a defence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
For the purposes of this Act— (2) For the purposes of this
Act—"

 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> 
a suit is instituted— 	(a) 	a suit is
instituted—"

 


 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>
in an ordinary case, when the plaint is presented to the proper officer;  	(i) 	in an ordinary case,
when the plaint is presented to the proper officer; "

 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>
in the case of a pauper, when his application for leave to sue as a pauper is
made; and 	(ii) 	in the case of a
pauper, when his application for leave to sue as a pauper is made; and"

 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>
in the case of a claim against a company which is being wound up by the court,
when the claimant first sends in his claim to the official liquidator; 	(iii) 	in the case of a
claim against a company which is being wound up by the court, when the claimant
first sends in his claim to the official liquidator;"

 


 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
any claim by way of a set off or a counter claim, shall be treated as a
separate suit and shall be deemed to have been instituted— 	(b) 	any claim by way of a set off or a counter
claim, shall be treated as a separate suit and shall be deemed to have been
instituted—"

 


 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>
in the case of a set off, on the same date as the suit in which the set off is
pleaded; 	(i) 	in the case of a set
off, on the same date as the suit in which the set off is pleaded;"

 


 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>
in the case of a counter claim, on the date on which the counter claim is made
in court; 	(ii) 	in the case of a
counter claim, on the date on which the counter claim is made in court;"

 


 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> an application by notice of
motion in a High Court is made when the application is presented to the proper
officer of that court. 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>4</number> Expiry 
    of prescribed period when court is closed.—Where 
    the prescribed period for any suit, appeal or application expires on a day 
    when the court is closed, the suit, appeal or application may be instituted, 
    preferred or made on the day when the court reopens. 
 

    Explanation.— A court shall be 
    deemed to be closed on any day within the meaning of this section if during 
    any part of its normal working hours it remains closed on that day. 
 

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Extension of prescribed period in certain cases. </title>—Any 
appeal or any application, other than an application under any of the provisions 
of Order XXI of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), may be admitted 
after the prescribed period, if the appellant or the applicant satisfies the 
court that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal or making the 
application within such period. <title></title>
 Explanation.— The fact that the appellant or the applicant was 
misled by any order, practice or judgment of the High Court in ascertaining or 
computing the prescribed period may be sufficient cause within the meaning of 
this section. 




















</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Legal 
    disability.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a person 
    entitled to institute a suit or make an application for the execution of a 
    decree is, at the time from which the prescribed period is to be reckoned, a 
    minor or insane, or an idiot, he may institute the suit or make the 
    application within the same period after the disability has ceased, as would 
    otherwise have been allowed from the time specified therefor in the third 
    column of the Schedule. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where such 
    person is, at the time from which the prescribed period is to be reckoned, 
    affected by two such disabilities, or where, before his disability has 
    ceased, he is affected by another disability, he may institute the suit or 
    make the application within the same period after both disabilities have 
    ceased, as would otherwise have been allowed from the time so specified. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    disability continues up to the death of that person, his legal 
    representative may institute the suit or make the application within the 
    same period after the death, as would otherwise have been allowed from the 
    time so specified. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the 
    legal representative referred to in sub-section (3) is, at the date of the 
    death of the person whom he represents, affected by any such disability, the 
    rules contained in sub-sections (1) and (2) shall apply. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a 
    person under disability dies after the disability ceases but within the 
    period allowed to him under this section, his legal representative may 
    institute the suit or make the application within the same period after the 
    death, as would otherwise have been available to that person had he not 
    died. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section, ‘minor’ includes a child in the womb. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Disability of one of several persons.—Where 
    one of several persons jointly entitled to institute a suit or make an 
    application for the execution of a decree is under any such disability, and 
    a discharge can be given without the concurrence of such person, time will 
    run against them all; but, where no such discharge can be given, time will 
    not run as against any of them until one of them becomes capable of giving 
    such discharge without the concurrence of the others or until the disability 
    has ceased. 
 
Explanation 
    I.— This section applies to a 
    discharge from every kind of liability, including a liability in respect of 
    any immovable property. 
 
Explanation 
    II.— For the purposes of this 
    section, the manager of a Hindu undivided family governed by the Mitakshara 
    law shall be deemed to be capable of giving a discharge without the 
    concurrence of the other members of the family only if he is in management 
    of the joint family property. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Special 
    exceptions.— Nothing in 
    section 6 or in section 7 applies to suits to enforce rights of pre-emption, 
    or shall be deemed to extend, for more than three years from the cessation 
    of the disability or the death of the person affected thereby, the period of 
    limitation for any suit or application. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>9</number> 
    Continuous running of time.—Where 
    once time has begun to run, no subsequent disability or inability to 
    institute a suit or make an application stops it:
 
Provided that 
    where letters of administration to the estate of a creditor have been 
    granted to his debtor, the running of the period of limitation for a suit to 
    recover the debt shall be suspended while the administration continues.
 
 
 
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>10</number> Suits 
    against trustees and their representatives.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this Act, no suit against 
    a person in whom property has become vested in trust for any specific 
    purpose, or against his legal representatives or assigns (not being assigns 
    for valuable consideration), for the purpose of following in his or their 
    hands such property, or the proceeds thereof, or for an account of such 
    property or proceeds, shall be barred by any length of time. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section any property comprised in a Hindu, Muslim or Buddhist religious 
    or charitable endowment shall be deemed to be property vested in trust for a 
    specific purpose and the manager of the property shall be deemed to be the 
    trustee thereof. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article> <number>11</number> Suits on contracts entered into 
      outside the territories to which the Act extends.—
<section><number>1</number> Suits instituted in the territories to 
      which this Act extends on contracts entered into in the State of Jammu and 
      Kashmir or in a foreign country shall be subject to the rules of 
      limitation contained in this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No rule of limitation in force in the State 
      of Jammu and Kashmir or in a foreign country shall be a defence to a suit 
      instituted in the said territories on a contract entered into in that 
      State or in a foreign country unless— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    the rule has 
      extinguished the contract; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    the parties were 
      domiciled in that State or in the foreign country during the period 
      prescribed by such rule. 
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>12</number> 
    Exclusion of time in legal proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In computing the period of limitation for any suit, appeal or application, 
    the day from which such period is to be reckoned, shall be excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    computing the period of limitation for an appeal or an application for leave 
    to appeal or for revision or for review of a judgment, the day on which the 
    judgment complained of was pronounced and the time requisite for obtaining a 
    copy of the decree, sentence or order appealed from or sought to be revised 
    or reviewed shall be excluded. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where a decree or order is appealed from or sought to be revised or 
    reviewed, or where an application is made for leave to appeal from a decree 
    or order, the time requisite for obtaining a copy of the judgment 


    1[***] shall also be 
    excluded. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    computing the period of limitation for an application to set aside an award, 
    the time requisite for obtaining a copy of the award shall be excluded. 
 

    Explanation.—In computing under 
    this section the time requisite for obtaining a copy of a decree or an 
    order, any time taken by the court to prepare the decree or order before an 
    application for a copy thereof is made shall not be excluded. 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Exclusion of time in cases where leave to sue or appeal as a pauper is 
    applied for.—In computing the 
    period of limitation prescribed for any suit or appeal in any case where an 
    application for leave to sue or appeal as a pauper has been made and 
    rejected, the time during which the applicant has been prosecuting in good 
    faith his application for such leave shall be excluded, and the court may, 
    on payment of the court fees prescribed for such suit or appeal, treat the 
    suit or appeal as having the same force and effect as if the court fees had 
    been paid in the first instance. 

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Exclusion of time of proceeding bona fide in 
court without jurisdiction. </title>— 
<section><number>1</number> In computing the period of limitation 
for any suit the time during which the plaintiff has been prosecuting with due 
diligence another civil proceeding, whether in a court of first instance or of 
appeal or revision, against the defendant shall be excluded, where the 
proceeding relates to the same matter in issue and is prosecuted in good faith 
in a court which, from defect of jurisdiction or other cause of a like nature, 
is unable to entertain it. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In computing the period of limitation for any application, the time 
during which the applicant has been prosecuting with due diligence another civil 
proceeding, whether in a court of first instance or of appeal or revision, 
against the same party for the same relief shall be excluded, where such 
proceeding is prosecuted in good faith in a court which, from defect of 
jurisdiction or other cause of a like nature, is unable to entertain it. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 2 of Order XXIII of the Code 
of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), the provisions of sub-section (1) shall 
apply in relation to a fresh suit instituted on permission granted by the court 
under rule 1 of that Order where such permission is granted on the ground that 
the first suit must fail by reason of a defect in the jurisdiction of the court 
or other cause of a like nature. 
 Explanation.— For the purposes of this section,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> in excluding the time during which a former civil proceeding was 
  pending, the day on which that proceeding was instituted and the day on which 
  it ended shall both be counted; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a plaintiff or an applicant resisting an appeal shall be deemed to be 
  prosecuting a proceeding; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> misjoinder of parties or of causes of action shall be deemed to be a 
  cause of a like nature with defect of jurisdiction. </subsection>








</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Exclusion of time in certain other cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In computing the period of limitation of any suit or application for the 
    execution of a decree, the institution or execution of which has been stayed 
    by injunction or order, the time of the continuance of the injunction or 
    order, the day on which it was issued or made, and the day on which it was 
    withdrawn, shall be excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    computing the period of limitation for any suit of which notice has been 
    given, or for which the previous consent or sanction of the Government or 
    any other authority is required, in accordance with the requirements of any 
    law for the time being in force, the period of such notice or, as the case 
    may be, the time required for obtaining such consent or sanction shall be 
    excluded. 
 

    Explanation.—In excluding the 
    time required for obtaining the consent or sanction of the Government or any 
    other authority, the date on which the application was made for obtaining 
    the consent or sanction and the date of receipt of the order of the 
    Government or other authority shall both be counted. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    computing the period of limitation for any suit or application for execution 
    of a decree by any receiver or interim receiver appointed in 
    proceedings for the adjudication of a person as an insolvent or by any 
    liquidator or provisional liquidator appointed in proceedings for the 
    winding up of a company, the period beginning with the date of institution 
    of such proceeding and ending with the expiry of three months from the date 
    of appointment of such receiver or liquidator, as the case may be, shall be 
    excluded. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    computing the period of limitation for a suit for possession by a purchaser 
    at a sale in execution of a decree, the time during which a proceeding to 
    set aside the sale has been prosecuted shall be excluded. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    computing the period of limitation for any suit the time during which the 
    defendant has been absent from India and from the territories outside India 
    under the administration of the Central Government, shall be excluded. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Effect 
    of death on or before the accrual of the right to sue.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a person who would, if he were living, have a right to institute a 
    suit or make an application dies before the right accrues, or where a right 
    to institute a suit or make an application accrues only on the death of a 
    person, the period of limitation shall be computed from the time when there 
    is a legal representative of the deceased capable of instituting such suit 
    or making such application. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    person against whom, if he were living, a right to institute a suit or make 
    an application would have accrued dies before the right accrues, or where a 
    right to institute a suit or make an application against any person accrues 
    on the death of such person, the period of limitation shall be computed from 
    the time when there is a legal representative of the deceased against whom 
    the plaintiff may institute such suit or make such application. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in 
    sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) applies to suits to enforce rights of 
    pre-emption or to suits for the possession of immovable property or of a 
    hereditary office. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Effect 
    of fraud or mistake.—
<section><number>1</number> Where, 
    in the case of any suit or application for which a period of limitation is 
    prescribed by this Act,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the suit or application is based upon 
    the fraud of the defendant or respondent or his agent; or  
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the knowledge of the right or title on 
    which a suit or application is founded is concealed by the fraud of any such 
    person as aforesaid; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the suit or application is for relief 
    from the consequences of a mistake; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    where any document necessary to 
    establish the right of the plaintiff or applicant has been fraudulently 
    concealed from him, 
 
the period of limitation shall not begin to 
    run until plaintiff or applicant has discovered the fraud or the mistake or 
    could, with reasonable diligence, have discovered it; or in the case of a 
    concealed document, until the plaintiff or the applicant first had the means 
    of producing the concealed document or compelling its production: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall enable any suit to be instituted or 
    application to be made to recover or enforce any charge against, or set 
    aside any transaction affecting, any property which— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    in the case of fraud, has been 
    purchased for valuable consideration by a person who was not a party to the 
    fraud and did not at the time of the purchase know, or have reason to 
    believe, that any fraud had been committed, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    in the case of mistake, has been 
    purchased for valuable consideration subsequently to the transaction in 
    which the mistake was made, by a person who did not know, or have reason to 
    believe, that the mistake had been made, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    in the case of a concealed document, 
    has been purchased for valuable consideration by a person who was not a 
    party to the concealment and, did not at the time of purchase know, or have 
    reason to believe, that the document had been concealed. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    judgment-debtor has, by fraud or force, prevented the execution of a decree 
    or order within the period of limitation, the court may, on the application 
    of the judgment-creditor made after the expiry of the said period extend the 
    period for execution of the decree or order: 
 
Provided that 
    such application is made within one year from the date of the discovery of 
    the fraud or the cessation of force, as the case may be. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Effect 
    of acknowledgment in writing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where, before the expiration of the prescribed period for a suit of 
    application in respect of any property or right, an acknowledgment of 
    liability in respect of such property or right has been made in writing 
    signed by the party against whom such property or right is claimed, or by 
    any person through whom he derives his title or liability, a fresh period of 
    limitation shall be computed from the time when the acknowledgment was so 
    signed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    writing containing the acknowledgment is undated, oral evidence may be given 
    of the time when it was signed; but subject to the provisions of the Indian 
    Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), oral evidence of its contents shall not be 
    received. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an acknowledgment may be sufficient 
    though it omits to specify the exact nature of the property or right, or 
    avers that the time for payment, delivery, performance or enjoyment has not 
    yet come or is accompanied by a refusal to pay, deliver, perform or permit 
    to enjoy, or is coupled with a claim to set-off, or is addressed to a person 
    other than a person entitled to the property or right; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the word “signed” means signed either 
    personally or by an agent duly authorised in this behalf; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    an application for the execution of a 
    decree or order shall not be deemed to be an application in respect of any 
    property or right. 
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>19</number>
Effect of payment on account of debt or of interest on legacy.—Where
payment on account of a debt or of interest on a legacy is made before the
expiration of the prescribed period by the person liable to pay the debt or
legacy or by his agent duly authorised in this behalf, a fresh period of
limitation shall be computed from the time when the payment was made: 19. Effect of payment on account of
debt or of interest on legacy.—Where payment on account of a debt
or of interest on a legacy is made before the expiration of the prescribed
period by the person liable to pay the debt or legacy or by his agent duly
authorised in this behalf, a fresh period of limitation shall be computed from
the time when the payment was made\:"

 


 Provided
that, save in the case of payment of interest made before the 1st day of
January, 1928, an acknowledgment of the payment appears in the handwriting of,
or in a writing signed by, the person making the payment. Provided that, save in the case of
payment of interest made before the 1st day of January, 1928, an acknowledgment
of the payment appears in the handwriting of, or in a writing signed by, the
person making the payment."

 


 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section,—  Explanation.—For the
purposes of this section,— "

 


 <section>
<number>a</number> 
where mortgaged land is in the possession of the mortgagee, the receipt
of the rent or produce of such land shall be deemed to be a payment; 	(a) 	where mortgaged land
is in the possession of the mortgagee, the receipt of the rent or produce of
such land shall be deemed to be a payment;"

 


 </section><section> <number>b</number> 
“debt” does not include money payable under a decree or order of a
court
 . 	(b) 	“debt” does not
include money payable under a decree or order of a court."

 
















</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Effect 
    of acknowledgment or payment by another person.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The expression “agent duly authorised in this behalf” in sections 18 and 19 
    shall, in the case of a person under disability, include his lawful 
    guardian, committee or manager or an agent duly authorised by such guardian, 
    committee or manager to sign the acknowledgment or make the payment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in 
    the said sections renders one of several joint contractors, partners, 
    executors or mortgagees chargeable by reason only of a written 
    acknowledgment signed by, or of a payment made by, or by the agent, of, any 
    other or others of them. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purposes of the said sections,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an acknowledgment signed or a payment 
    made in respect of any liability by or by the duly authorised agent of, any 
    limited owner of property who is governed by Hindu law, shall be a valid 
    acknowledgment or payment, as the case may be, against a reversioner 
    succeeding to such liability; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where a liability has been incurred by 
    or on behalf of a Hindu undivided family as such, an acknowledgment or 
    payment made by, or by the duly authorised agent of, the manager of the 
    family for the time being shall be deemed to have been made on behalf of the 
    whole family. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 

    


 <article><number>21</number>
Effect of substituting or adding new plaintiff or defendant.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where after the institution of a suit, a new plaintiff or, defendant is
substituted or added, the suit shall, as regards him, be deemed to have been
instituted when he was so made a party: 21. Effect of substituting or
adding new plaintiff or defendant.—(1) Where after the
institution of a suit, a new plaintiff or, defendant is substituted or added,
the suit shall, as regards him, be deemed to have been instituted when he was
so made a party\:"

 


 Provided
that where the court is satisfied that the omission to include a new plaintiff
or defendant was due to a mistake made in good faith it may direct that the suit
as regards such plaintiff or defendant shall be deemed to have been instituted
on any earlier date. 


   


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Nothing in sub-section (1) shall apply to a case where a party is added or
substituted owing to assignment or devolution of any interest during the
pendency of a suit or where a plaintiff is made a defendant or a defendant is
made a plaintiff. (2) Nothing
in sub-section (1) shall apply to a case where a party is added or substituted
owing to assignment or devolution of any interest during the pendency of a suit
or where a plaintiff is made a defendant or a defendant is made a
plaintiff."

 









</section></article> 

   


  


 <article><number>22</number>
Continuing breaches and torts.—In
the case of a continuing breach of contract or in the case of a continuing tort,
a fresh period of limitation begins to run at every moment of the time during
which the breach or the tort, as the case may be, continues. 22. Continuing breaches and torts.—In the
case of a continuing breach of contract or in the case of a continuing tort, a
fresh period of limitation begins to run at every moment of the time during
which the breach or the tort, as the case may be, continues."

 





</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>23</number> Suits for compensation for acts not 
      actionable without special damage.—In the case of a suit for compensation for an 
      act which does not give rise to a cause of action unless some specific 
      injury actually results therefrom, the period of limitation shall be 
      computed from the time when the injury results. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Computation of time mentioned in instruments.—All 
    instruments shall for the purposes of this Act be deemed to be made with 
    reference to the Gregorian calendar. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Acquisition of easement by prescription.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the access and use of light or air to and for any building have been 
    peaceably enjoyed therewith as an easement, and as of right, without 
    interruption, and for twenty years, and where any way or watercourse or the 
    use of any water or any other easement (whether affirmative or negative) has 
    been peaceably and openly enjoyed by any person claiming title thereto as an 
    easement and as of right without interruption and for twenty years, the 
    right to such access and use of light or air, way, watercourse, use of 
    water, or other easement shall be absolute and indefeasible. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each of 
    the said periods of twenty years shall be taken to be a period ending within 
    two years next before the institution of the suit wherein the claim to which 
    such period relates is contested. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    property over which a right is claimed under sub-section (1) belongs to the 
    Government that sub-section shall be read as if for the words “twenty years” 
    the words “thirty years” were substituted. 
 

    Explanation.—Nothing is an 
    interruption within the meaning of this section, unless where there is an 
    actual discontinuance of the possession or enjoyment by reason of an 
    obstruction by the act of some person other than the claimant, and unless 
    such obstruction is submitted to or acquiesced in for one year after the 
    claimant has notice thereof and of the person making or authorising the same 
    to be made. 
 
 
State Amendment
 <subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—Section 
      25 is repealed.  
 
[Vide Orissa Act 
      24 of 1967, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 31-8-1967)]. tc 
      "[Vide Orissa Act 24 of 1967, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 31-8-1967)]." 
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Exclusion in favour of reversioner of servient tenement.—Where 
    any land or water upon, over or from, which any easement has been enjoyed or 
    derived has been held under or by virtue of any interest for life or in 
    terms of years exceeding three years from the granting thereof the time of 
    the enjoyment of such easement during the continuance of such interest or 
    term shall be excluded in the computation of the period to twenty years in 
    case the claim is, within three years next after the determination of such 
    interests or term resisted by the person entitled on such determination to 
    the said land or water. 
 
 
State Amendment
 <section>
<number>Orissa</number>—Section 
      26 is repealed.  
 
[Vide Orissa Act 
      24 of 1967, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 31-8-1967)]. tc 
      "[Vide Orissa Act 24 of 1967, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 31-8-1967)]." 
</section>

 
  


</article> 

   


 <article><number>27</number>
Extinguishment of right to property.—At
the determination of the period hereby limited to any person for instituting a
suit for possession of any property, his right to such property shall be
extinguished. 27. Extinguishment of right to
property.—At the determination of the period hereby limited to any
person for instituting a suit for possession of any property, his right to such
property shall be extinguished."

 





</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Amendment of certain Acts.—[Rep. 
    by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1974 (56 of 1974), sec. 2 and First Sch.] 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Savings.—
<section><number>1</number> Nothing in this Act 
    shall affect section 25 of the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872). 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    special or local law prescribes for any suit, appeal or application a period 
    of limitation different from the period prescribed by the Schedule, the 
    provisions of section 3 shall apply as if such period were the period 
    prescribed by the Schedule and for the purpose of determining any period of 
    limitation prescribed for any suit, appeal or application by any special or 
    local law, the provisions contained in sections 4 to 24 (inclusive) shall 
    apply only in so far as, and to the extent to which, they are not expressly 
    excluded by such special or local law. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided in any law for the time being in force with respect to 
    marriage and divorce, nothing in this Act shall apply to any suit or other 
    proceeding under any such law. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Sections 
    25 and 26 and the definition of “easement” in section 2 shall not apply to 
    cases arising in the territories to which the Indian Easements Act, 1882 (5 
    of 1882), may for the time being extend. 
  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Provision for suits, etc ., for which the prescribed 
period is shorter than the period prescribed by the Indian Limitation Act, 1908. 
</title>—Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> any suit for which the period of limitation is shorter than the period 
  of limitation prescribed by the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908), may 
  be instituted within a period of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[seven years] next after the 
  commencement of this Act or within the period prescribed for such suit by the 
  Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908), whichever period expires earlier: 
</section>
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Provided that if in respect of any such suit, the said period of 
seven years expires earlier than period of limitation prescribed therefor under 
the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908) and the said period of seven years 
together with so much of the period of limitation in respect of such suit under 
the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908), as has already expired before the 
commencement of this Act is shorter than the period prescribed for such suit 
under this Act, then, the suit may be instituted within the period of limitation 
prescribed therefor under this Act;] 
 <section><number>b</number> any appeal or application for which the period of limitation is shorter 
than the period of limitation prescribed by the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 
of 1908), may be preferred or made within a period of ninety days next after the 
commencement of this Act or within the period prescribed for such appeal or 
application by the Indian Limitation Act, 1908, whichever period expires 
earlier. 
 <title>State Amendment </title>
 (Modification under Article 371F of the Constitution of India ) 

 <subsection><title><number>Sikkim</number> </title>—For section 30, substitute the following section, 
namely:— 
 “30. Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, any suit, appeal or 
application, which could be instituted, preferred or made before the 
commencement of this Act and for which the period of limitation is shorter than 
the period provided therefor by the law in Sikkim immediately before such 
commencement, may be instituted, preferred or made within the period provided by 
such law.” 
 [ Vide Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), p. 4 (No. 329), 
dated 29th July, 1983 (w.e.f. 22-7-1983).] 


</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number> Provisions as to barred or pending suits, 
etc:-</title>Nothing in this Act shall,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> enable any suit, appeal or application to be instituted, preferred or 
  made, for which the period of limitation prescribed by the Indian Limitation 
  Act, 1908 (9 of 1908), expired before the commencement of this Act; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> affect any suit, appeal or application instituted, preferred or made 
  before, and pending at, such commencement. </section>
 <title>State Amendment </title><title></title>
 (Modification under Article 371F of the Constitution of India ) 

 <section><title><number>Sikkim</number> </title>—In section 31, in clause (a), for the words “Indian 
Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 1908), expired before the commencement of this Act”, 
substitute the words “law in force in Sikkim immediately before the commencement 
of this Act, expired before such commencement”. 
 [ Vide Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), p. 4 (No. 329), 
dated 29th July, 1983 (w.e.f. 22-7-1983).] </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>32</number> 
    Repeal.—[Rep. by the Repealing 
    and Amending Act, 1974 (56 of 1974), sec. 2 and First Sch.]
  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 1969, sec. 2(a), for “five years” 
(w.r.e.f. 1-1-1964).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 10 of 1969, sec. 2(b) (w.e.f. 26-3-1969).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>