<act><tid>132057</tid>
<title>THE BANKING COMPANIES (LEGAL PRACTITIONERS' CLIENTS' ACCOUNTS) 
ACT, <year>1949</year></title>

ACT NO. 46 OF <year>1949</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
[ 8th December, <year>1949</year>.]
An Act to restrict the liability of banking companies in connection 
with certain transactions by legal practitioners.




<article><tid>1841325</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1205494</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Banking Companies (Legal Practitioners' Clients' Accounts) 
Act, <year>1949</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>525484</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.]

</section>

<section><tid>953572</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force in the Presidency- town of Bombay at 
once, and in the rest of the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State of Maharashtra] or any part 
thereof or <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> in any other State or in any part of such State] on such 
date or dates <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>984066</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1607207</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>" banking company" means any banking company as 
defined in section 5 of the Banking Companies Act, 
 <year>1949</year> (1 of <year>1949</year>), and includes the State Bank of India 
 <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> a corresponding
<pagefootnote><pagenum>98</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and 
Sch. I; Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I, Goa, Daman 
and Diu by Reg. 11 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. and Laccadive, Minicoy 
and Amindivi Islands by Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section. 
3. The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
62 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
4. Subs. by the Bombay Reorganisation (Adaptation of Laws on Union  
  subjects) Order, <year>1961</year>, for" State of Bombay" (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1960</year>). 
5. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" in any other Province or any 
Acceding State or any Part of such Province or State". 
6. The Act was brought into force in Orissa on 1st August, <year>1950</year>, 
vide Notification No. S. R. O. 270, dated the 12th July, <year>1950</year>, 
Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 278, and in the State of 
Punjab on the 1st October, <year>1951</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. 1431, 
dated 18th September, <year>1951</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 
1597. 
7. Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1959</year>, s. 64 and Sch. III, for cl. (a)  (w. e. f.  
  10- 9- <year>1959</year>). 
8. Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1970</year>, s. 20, for" and any subsidiary bank" 
 (w. e. f. 19- 7- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking 
Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) 
Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1970</year>), <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a Regional Rural Bank 
established under section 3 of the Regional Rural Banks 
Act, <year>1976</year> (21 of <year>1876</year>) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a corresponding new bank 
constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies 
 (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1980</year> 
 (40 of <year>1980</year>) and any subsidiary bank] as defined in 
the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> 
 (38 of <year>1959</year>);]


</section>

<section><tid>640042</tid>
<number>b</number>" legal practitioner" has the same meaning as in the 
Legal Practitioners Act, <year>1879</year> (18 of <year>1879</year>).


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1434005</tid>
<number> 3</number> Restriction of liability of banking companies in certain 
cases.-
<section><tid>1120702</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, under any law or rules having the force of law, a  
legal practitioner keeping an account in a banking company for 
clients' moneys may only operate on such account for specified 
purposes, then, neither the banking company with which such an account 
is kept nor any other banking company shall, in connection with any 
transaction relating to such account, incur any liability, or be under 
any obligation to make any enquiry, or be deemed to have any knowledge 
of any right of any person to any money paid or credited to such 
account, which it would not incur, or be under, or be deemed to have, 
in the case of an account kept by a person entitled absolutely to all 
the money paid or credited to the account:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall--


<subsection><tid>1284208</tid>
<number>i</number>apply to the case of an account kept by a legal 
practitioner as trustee for a specified beneficiary, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1613632</tid>
<number>ii</number>relieve a banking company from any liability or 
obligation which it would incur or be under, apart from 
this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>151639</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), a 
banking company in which a legal practitioner keeps an account for 
clients' moneys shall not, in respect of any liability of such 
practitioner to the banking company, not being a liability in 
connection with that account, have or obtain any recourse or right, 
whether by way of set- off, counter- claim, charge or otherwise, against 
moneys standing to the credit of that account.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>99</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1976</year>, s. 33, for certain words (w. e. f. 26- 9-  
  <year>1975</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1980</year>, s. 20, for" any subsidiary bank" (w. e. f.  
  15- 4- <year>1980</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>