<act><title>


    The 
BEEDI 
    AND CIGAR WORKERS (CONDITIONS OF EMPLOYMENT) ACT, 1966</title> 
 
 
  
 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Beedi and cigar Workers (Conditions of 
    Employment) Act, 1966.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in a State on such date* as the State Government may, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different dates may be 
    appointed by the State Government for different areas and for different 
    provisions of this Act.


 
 
 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 


 







  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>  “adult” means a person who has 
    completed eighteen years of age;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  “child” means a person who has not 
    completed fourteen years of age;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  “competent authority” means 
    any authority authorised by the State Government by notification in the 
    Official Gazette to perform all or any of the functions of the competent 
    authority under this Act and for such areas as may be specified therein;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>  “contractor” means a person 
    who, in relation to a manufacturing process, undertakes to produce a given 
    result by executing the work through contract labour or who engages labour 
    for any manufacturing process in a private dwelling house and includes a 
    sub-contractor, agent, munshi, thekedar or sattedar.”
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>  “contract labour” means any 
    person engaged or employed in any premises by or through a contractor, with 
    or without the knowledge of the employer, in any manufacturing process;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>  “employee” means a person 
    employed directly or through any agency, whether for wages or not, in any 
    establishments 
1[or 
    godown] to do any work skilled, unskilled, manual or clerical, and includes—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  any labour who is given raw 
    materials by an employer or a contractor for being made into beedi or cigar 
    or both at home (herein after referred to in this Act as “home worker”), and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>  any person not employed by 
    an employer or a contractor but working with the permission of, or under 
    agreement with, the employer or contractor 
1[or 
    both];
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> “employer” means,—
 
 
 </section><section>
<number>a</number> in relation to contract labour, the principal employer; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> in relation to other labour, the person who has the ultimate control over the affairs of any 
    establishment or who has, by reason of his advancing money, supplying goods 
    or otherwise, a substantial interest in the control of the affairs of any 
    establishment, and includes any other person to whom the affairs of the 
    establishment are entrusted, whether such other person is called the 
    managing agent, manager, superintendent or by any other name;
</section><section>
<number>h</number>  “establishment” means any 
    place or premises including the precincts thereof in which or in any part of 
    which any manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi or cigar 
    or both is being, or is ordinarily, carried on and includes an industrial 
    premises;
 
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[‘(hh)  
    “godown” means any warehouse or other place, by whatever name called, used 
    for the storage of—
 
 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>  any article substance 
    required for any manufacturing process; or
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>  beedi or cigar or 
    both;]
</subsection></section><section>
<number>i</number> “industrial premises” means 
    any place or premises (not being a private dwelling house), including the 
    precincts thereof, in which or in any part of which any industry or 
    manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi or cigar or both is 
    being or is ordinarily carried on with or without the aid of power <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[and 
    includes a godown attached thereto];
 </section><section>
<number>j</number> “Inspector” means an Inspector appointed 
    under sub-section (1) of section 6;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number> “manufacturing process” means 
    any process for, or incidental to, making, finishing or packing or otherwise 
    treating any article or substance with a view to its use, sale, transport, 
    delivery or disposal as beedi or cigar or both;
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made by the State Government under this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>  “principal employer” means a 
    person for whom or on whose behalf any contract labour is engaged or 
    employed in an establishment;
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>  “private dwelling house” means 
    a house in which persons engaged in the manufacture of beedi or cigar or 
    both reside;
 </section><section>
<number>o</number> “State Government” in relation to a Union 
    territory, means the Administrator thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>  “week” means a period of seven days, 
    beginning at midnight on Saturday;
 </section><section>
<number>q</number> “young person” means a person who has 
    completed fourteen years of age but has not completed eighteen years of age.
</section>






  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>3</number> Industrial premises to 
    be licensed.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in this Act, no employer shall use or allow to be used 
    any place or premises as an industrial premises unless he holds a valid 
    licence issued under this Act and no such premises shall be used except in 
    accordance with the terms and conditions of such licence.
 





  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Licences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person who intends to use or allows to be used any place or premises as 
    industrial premises shall make an application in writing to the competent 
    authority, in such form on payment of such fees as may be prescribed, for a 
    licence to use, or allow to be used, such premises as an industrial 
    premises.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application shall 
    specify the maximum number of employees proposed to be employed at any time 
    of the day in the place or premises and shall be accompanied by a plan of 
    the place or premises prepared in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The competent authority 
    shall, in deciding whether to grant or refuse a licence, have regard to the 
    following matters:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  the suitability of the place 
    or premises which is proposed to be used for the manufacture of beedi or 
    cigar or both;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  the previous experience of the 
    applicant;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  the financial resources of 
    the applicant including his financial capacity to meet the demands arising 
    out of the provisions of the laws for the time being in force relating to 
    welfare of labour;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  whether the application is 
    made bona fide on behalf of the applicant himself or in benami of any 
    other person;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>  welfare of the labour in the 
    locality, the interest of the public generally and such other matters as may 
    be prescribed.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (a) A licence granted 
    under this section shall not be valid beyond the financial year in which it 
    is granted but may be renewed from financial year to financial year.
 
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> An application for the 
    renewal of a licence granted under this Act shall be made at least thirty 
    days before the expiry of the period thereof, on payment of such fees as may 
    be prescribed, and where such an application has been made, the licence 
    shall be deemed to continue, notwithstanding the expiry of the period 
    thereof, until the renewal of the licence, or, as the case may be, the 
    rejection of the application for the renewal thereof.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The competent authority 
    shall, in deciding whether to renew a licence or to refuse a renewal 
    thereof, have regard to the matters specified in sub-section (3). 

</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The competent authority 
    shall not grant a renew a licence unless it is satisfied that the provisions 
    of this Act and the rules made thereunder have been substantially complied 
    with.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The competent authority 
    may, after giving the holder of a licence an opportunity of being heard, 
    cancel or suspend any licence granted or renewed under this Act if it 
    appears to it that such licence has been obtained by misrepresentation or 
    fraud or that the licensee has contravened or failed to comply with any of 
    the provisions of this Act or the rules made thereunder or any of the terms 
    or conditions of the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The State Government 
    may issue in writing to a competent authority such directions of a general 
    character as that Government may consider necessary in respect of any matter 
    relating to the grant or renewal of licences under this section.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Subject to the 
    foregoing provisions of this section, the competent authority may grant or 
    renew licences under this Act on such terms and conditions as it may 
    determine and where the competent authority refuses to grant or renew any 
    licence, it shall do so by an order communicated to the applicant, giving 
    the reasons in writing for such refusal.
  




  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>5</number> Appeals.—Any 
    person aggrieved by the decision of the competent authority refusing to 
    grant or renew a licence or cancelling or suspending a licence may, within 
    such time and on payment of such fees, not exceeding twenty rupees, as may 
    be prescribed, appeal to such authority as the State Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf, and such 
    authority may by order confirm, modify or reverse any order refusing to 
    grant or renew a licence or cancelling or suspending a licence.

  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    such of its officers or such officers of any local authority as it thinks 
    fit to be Inspectors for the purposes of this Act and may assign to them 
    such local limits as it may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint any person to be a 
    Chief Inspector who shall exercise the powers of an Inspector throughout the 
    State. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every Chief Inspector 
    and Inspector shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of 
    section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Powers of Inspectors. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to any rules by the State Government in this behalf, an Inspector may, within the local limits for which he is appointed,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> make such examination and hold such inquiry as may be necessary for ascertaining whether the provisions of this Act have been or are being complied within any place or premises: 
 Provided that no person shall be compelled under this section to answer any question or to give any evidence which may tend to incriminate himself: 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> require the production of any prescribed register and any other document relating to the manufacture of beedi or cigar or both; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> enter, with such assistants as he thinks fit, at all times any place or premises including the residences of employees if he has reasonable grounds for suspecting that any manufacturing process is being carried on or is ordinarily carried on in any such place or premises; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> exercise such other powers as may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If an Inspector has reasonable grounds for suspecting that any manufacturing process is being carried on in any establishment in contravention of the provisions of this Act, he may, after giving due notice to the employer or, in the absence of the employer, to the occupier, enter such establishment with such assistants, if any, as he may think fit. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every employer or occupier shall accord to the chief Inspector or the Inspector, as the case may be, all reasonable facilities in the discharge of his duties under this Act. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> <title>[<number>7A</number> Inspector not to disclose the source of any complaint, etc. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No Inspector shall disclose the source of any complaint made to him regarding the contravention of any of the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No Inspector shall, while making an inspection under this Act in pursuance of a complaint received by him, disclose to the employer or contractor concerned or any of his representatives that the inspection is being made in pursuance of a complaint: 
 Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to any case in which the person who has made the complaint has consented to disclose his name.] 


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Cleanliness.—Every 
    industrial premises shall be kept clean and free from effluvia arising from 
    any drain, privy or other nuisance and shall also maintain such standard of 
    cleanliness including white washing, colour washing, varnishing or painting, 
    as may be prescribed.
  



  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Ventilation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of preventing injury to the health of the persons working 
    therein, every industrial premises shall maintain such standards of 
    lighting, ventilation and temperature, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Wherever dust or fume 
    or other impurity of such a nature and to such an extent as is likely to be 
    injurious or offensive to the persons employed in any industrial premises is 
    given off by reason of the manufacturing process carried on in such 
    premises, the competent authority may require the employer to take such 
    effective measures as may prevent the inhalation of such dust, fume or other 
    impurity and accumulation thereof in any work room.
  





  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Overcrowding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No room in any industrial premises shall be overcrowded to an extent 
    injurious to the health of the persons employed therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
    the generality of sub-section (1) there shall be in any work room of such 
    premises at least four and a quarter cubic metres of space for every person 
    employed therein, and for the purposes of this sub-section, no account shall 
    be taken of any space which is more than three metres above the level of the 
    floor of the work room.
  




  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Drinking water.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The employer shall make in every industrial premises effective arrangements 
    to provide and maintain at suitable points conveniently situated for all 
    persons employed therein, a sufficient supply of wholesome drinking water.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All such points shall 
    be legibly marked “drinking water” in language understood by the majority of 
    the persons employed in the industrial premises and no such point shall be 
    situated within six metres of any washing place, urinal or latrine except 
    with the prior approval in writing of the competent authority.
 
 





  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Latrines and urinals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In every industrial premises, sufficient latrine and urinal accommodation of 
    such types as may be prescribed shall be provided and shall be so 
    conveniently situated as may be accessible to the employees at all times 
    while they are in the industrial premises: 
 
Provided that it shall not 
    be necessary to provide separate urinals in industrial premises where less 
    than fifty persons are employed or where the latrines are connected to a 
    water-borne sewage system.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
    may specify the number of latrines and urinals which shall be provided in 
    any industrial premises in proportion to any number of male and female 
    employees ordinarily employed therein, and may provide for such further 
    matters in respect of sanitation in the industrial premises including 
    obligation of the employees in this regard as it may consider necessary in 
    the interest of the health of the persons employed therein.
  




  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Washing facilities.—In 
    every industrial premises, where blending or sieving or both of tobacco or 
    warming of beedi in hot ovens is carried on, the employer shall provide such 
    washing facilities for the use of the employees, as may be prescribed.
  




  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Creches.—In 
    every industrial premises wherein more than 
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[thirty]
female employees are 
    ordinarily employed, there shall be provided and maintained a suitable room 
    or rooms for the use of children under the age of six years of such female 
    employees.
 <section>
<number>2</number> Such rooms shall—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  provide adequate accommodation;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  be adequately lighted and 
    ventilated;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  be maintained in a clean and 
    sanitary condition;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  be under the charge of women trained 
    in the care of children and infants.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The State Government 
    may make rules—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  prescribing the location and the 
    standards in respect of construction, accommodation, furniture and other 
    equipment of rooms to be provided under this section.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  requiring the provision in any 
    industrial premises to which this section applies, of additional facilities 
    for the care of children belonging to female employees, including suitable 
    provisions of facilities for washing and changing their clothing;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  requiring the provision in any 
    industrial premises of free milk or refreshment or both for such children;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  requiring that facilities shall be 
    given in any industrial premises for the mothers of such children to feed 
    them at necessary intervals.
  
 
COMMENTS
 
Where more than thirty female employees are 
ordinarily employed, a suitable room or rooms are to be provided for the use of 
children under the age of six years of such female employees.
</subsection>







  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> First aid.—Every 
    industrial premises shall provide such first aid facilities as may be 
    prescribed.
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Canteens.—The 
    State Government may, by rules, require the employer to provide and maintain 
    in every industrial premises wherein not less than two hundred and fifty 
    employees are ordinarily employed, a canteen for the use of the employees.
  




  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Working hours.—No 
    employee shall be required or allowed to work in any industrial premises for 
    more than nine hours in any day or for more than forty-eight hours in any 
    week:
 
Provided that any adult 
    employee may be allowed to work in such industrial premises for any period 
    in excess of the limit fixed under this section subject to the payment of 
    overtime wages if the period of work including overtime work, does not 
    exceed ten hours in any day and in the aggregate fifty-four hours in any 
    week.
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Wages for overtime 
    work.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    any employee employed in any industrial premises is required to work 
    overtime, he shall be entitled in respect of such overtime work, to wages at 
    the rate of twice his ordinary rate of wages.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the employees in 
    an industrial premises are paid on a piece rate basis, the overtime rate 
    shall be calculated, for the purposes of this section, at the time rates 
    which shall be as nearly as possible equivalent to the daily average of 
    their full time earnings for the days on which they had actually worked 
    during the week immediately preceding the week in which the overtime work 
    has been done.
 
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Explanation.—Where 
    an employee had not worked on any day of the week immediately preceding the 
    week in which the overtime work has been done, any week preceding such week 
    in which he had actually worked shall be taken into account in calculating 
    the overtime rate for the purposes of this sub-section.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the purposes of 
    this section, “ordinary rates of wages” means the basic wages plus such 
    allowance, including the cash equivalent of the advantage accruing through 
    the concessional sale to the employees of foodgrains and other articles as 
    the employee is for the time being entitled to but does not include bonus.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The cash equivalent of 
    the advantage accruing through the concessional sale to an employee of 
    foodgrains and other articles shall be computed as often as may be 
    prescribed on the basis of the maximum quantity of foodgrains and other 
    articles admissible to a standard family.
 
Explanation I.—“Standard 
    family” means a family consisting of the employee, his or her spouse and two 
    children requiring in all three adult consumption units.
 
Explanation II.—“Adult 
    consumption units” means the consumption unit of a male above the age of 
    fourteen years; and the consumption unit of a female above the age of 
    fourteen years and that of a child shall be calculated at the rate of 
    eight-tenths and six-tenths, respectively, of one adult consumption unit.





  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Interval for rest.—The 
    periods of work for employees in an industrial premises each day shall be so 
    fixed that no period shall exceed five hours and that no employee shall work 
    for more than five hours before he has an interval for rest of at least half 
    an hour.
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Spread over.—The 
    periods of work of an employee in an industrial premises shall be so 
    arranged that inclusive of his intervals for rest under section 19, they 
    shall not spread over more than ten and a half hours in any day:
 
Provided that the Chief 
    Inspector may, for reasons to be specified in writing, increase the spread 
    over to twelve hours.
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Weekly holidays.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every industrial premises shall remain entirely closed, except for wetting 
    of beedi or tobacco leaves, on one day in the week which day shall be 
    specified by the employer in a notice exhibited in a conspicuous place in 
    the industrial premises and the day so specified shall not be altered by the 
    employer more often than once in three months and except with the previous 
    written permission of the Chief Inspector.
 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[Provided that a 
    copy of every such notice shall be sent to the Inspector having jurisdiction 
    over the industrial premises within two weeks from the date on which such 
    notice is exhibited in the industrial premises.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), an employee employed in the said 
    premises for wetting of beedi or tobacco leaves on the day on which it 
    remains closed in pursuance of sub-section (1), shall be allowed a 
    substituted holiday on one of the three days immediately before or after the 
    said day.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For a holiday under 
    this section, an employee shall be paid, notwithstanding any contract to the 
    contrary, at the rate equal to the daily average of his total full time 
    earnings for the days on which he had worked during the week immediately 
    preceding the holiday exclusive of any overtime earnings and bonus but 
    inclusive of dearness and other allowances.
 
Explanation.—The 
    expression “total full time earnings” shall have the meaning assigned to it 
    in section 27.





  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> Notice of periods of 
    work.—
<section><number>1</number> There 
    shall be displayed and correctly maintained in every industrial premises a 
    notice of periods of work in such form and in such manner as may be 
    prescribed, showing clearly for every day the periods during which the 
    employees may be required to work.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) A copy of the 
    notice referred to in sub-section (1) shall be sent in triplicate to the 
    Inspector having jurisdiction over the industrial premises within two weeks 
    from the date of the grant of a licence for the first time under this Act, 
    in the case of any industrial premises carrying on work at the commencement 
    of this Act, and in the case of any industrial premises beginning work after 
    such commencement, before the day on which the work is begun in the 
    industrial premises.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Any proposed change in 
    the system of work which will necessitate a change in the notice referred to 
    in sub-section (1) shall be notified to the Inspector in triplicate before 
    the change is made and except with the previous sanction of the Inspector, 
    no such change shall be made until one week has elapsed since the last 
    change.
 


  





 
    .

</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>23</number> Hours of work to 
    correspond with notice under section 22.—No 
    employee shall be employed in any industrial premises otherwise than in 
    accordance with the notice of work displayed in the premises under section 
    22.

  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> Prohibition of 
    employment of children.—No 
    child shall be required or allowed to work in any industrial premises.
  




  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> Prohibition of 
    employment of women or young persons during certain hours.—No 
    woman or young person shall be required or allowed to work in any industrial 
    premises except between 6 a.m. and 7 p.m.




  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> Annual leave with 
    wages.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    employee in an establishment shall be allowed in a calendar year leave with 
    wages—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number> in the case of an adult, at 
    the rate of one day for every twenty days of work performed by him during 
    the previous calendar year;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> in the case of a young person at the rate 
    of one day for every fifteen days of work performed by him during the 
    previous calendar year.
 
Explanation.—The 
    leave admissible under this sub-section shall be exclusive of all holidays 
    whether occuring during, or at the beginning or at the end of, the period of 
    leave.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If an employee is 
    discharged or dismissed from service or quits employment during the course 
    of the year, he shall be entitled to leave with wages at the rate laid down 
    in sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In calculating leave 
    under this section, any fraction of leave of half a day or more shall be 
    treated as one full day’s leave and any fraction of less than half a day 
    shall be omitted.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any employee does 
    not, in any calendar year take the whole of the leave allowed to him under 
    sub-section (1), the leave not taken by him shall be added to the leave to 
    be allowed to him in the succeeding calendar year:
 
Provided that the total 
    number of days of leave that may be carried forward to a succeeding year 
    shall not exceed thirty in the case of an adult or forty in the case of a 
    young person.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An application of an 
    employee for the whole or any portion of the leave allowed under sub-section 
    (1) shall be in writing and ordinarily shall have to be made sufficiently in 
    advance of the day on which he wishes the leave to begin.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If the employment of an 
    employee who is entitled to leave under sub-section (1) is terminated by the 
    employer before he has taken the entire leave to which he is entitled, or if 
    having applied for leave, he has not been granted such leave, or if the 
    employee quits his employment before he has taken the leave, the employer 
    shall pay him the amount payable under section 27 in respect of leave not 
    taken and such payment shall be made, where the employment of the employee 
    is terminated by the employer, before the expiry of the second working day 
    after such termination and where the employee quits his employment, on or 
    before the next pay day.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The leave not availed 
    of by an employee shall not be taken into consideration in computing the 
    period of any notice required to be given before discharge or dismissal.
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Wages during leave 
    period.—
<section><number>1</number> For 
    the leave allowed to him under section 26, an employee shall be paid at the 
    rate equal to the daily average of his total full time earnings for the days 
    on which he had worked during the month immediately preceding his leave 
    exclusive of any overtime earnings and bonus but inclusive of dearness and 
    other allowances.
 
Explanation I.—In 
    this sub-section, the expression “total full time earnings”
    includes the cash equivalent of the advantage accruing through the 
    concessional sale to employees of foodgrains and other articles, as the 
    employee is for the time being entitled to, but does not include bonus.
 
Explanation II.—For 
    the purposes of determining the wages payable to a home worker during leave 
    period or for the purpose of payment of maternity benefit to a woman home 
    worker, “day” shall mean any period during which such home worker was 
    employed during a period of twenty-four hours commencing at midnight, for 
    making beedi or cigar or both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An employee who has 
    been allowed leave for not less than four days in the case of an adult and 
    five days in the case of a young person, shall, before his leave begins, be 
    paid wages due for the period of the leave allowed.
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> Application of the 
    Payment of Wages Act, 1936 to industrial
    premises.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 
    1936) (hereinafter referred to in this section as the said Act), the State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that all or 
    any of the provisions of the said Act or the rules made thereunder shall 
    apply to all or any class of employees in establishment or class of 
    establishments to which this Act applies and on such application of the 
    provisions of the said Act, an Inspector appointed under this Act shall be 
    deemed to be the Inspector for the purposes of the enforcement of such 
    provisions of the said Act within the local limits of his jurisdiction.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government 
    may, by a like notification, cancel or vary any notification issued under 
    sub-section (1).
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> Special provisions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may permit the wetting or cutting of beedi or tobacco 
    leaves by employees outside the industrial premises on an application made 
    to it by the employer on behalf of such employees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The employer shall 
    maintain in the prescribed form a record of the work permitted under 
    sub-section (1) to be carried on outside the industrial premises.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Save as otherwise 
    provided in this section, no employer shall require or allow any 
    manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi or cigar or both to 
    be carried on outside the industrial premises:
 
Provided that nothing in 
    this sub-section shall apply to any labour who is given raw material by an 
    employer or a contractor for being made into beedi or cigar or both at home.
  




  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> Onus as to age.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When any act or omission would, if a person were under a certain age, be an 
    offence punishable under this Act and such person is, in the opinion of the 
    court, prima facie under such age, the burden shall be on the accused 
    to prove that such person is not under such age.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A declaration in 
    writing by a medical officer not below the rank of a Civil Assistant Surgeon 
    relating to an employee that he has personally examined him and believes him 
    to be under the age stated in such declaration, shall, for the purposes of 
    this Act and the rules made thereunder, be admissible as evidence of the age 
    of that employee.
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> Notice of dismissal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No employer shall dispense with the services of an employee who has been 
    employed for a period of six months or more, except for a reasonable cause, 
    and without giving such employee at least one month’s notice or wages in 
    lieu of such notice:
 
Provided that such notice 
    shall not be necessary if the services of such employee are dispensed with 
    on a charge of misconduct supported by satisfactory evidence recorded at an 
    inquiry held by the employer for the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The employee 
    discharged, dismissed or retrenched may appeal to such authority and within 
    such time as may be prescribed either on the ground that there was no 
    reasonable cause for dispensing with his services or on the ground that he 
    had not been guilty of misconduct as held by the employer or on the ground 
    that such punishment of discharge or dismissal was severe.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The appellate authority 
    may, after giving notice in the prescribed manner to the employer and the 
    employee, dismiss the appeal or direct the reinstatement of the employee 
    with or without wages for the period during which he was kept out of 
    employment or direct payment of compensation without reinstatement or grant 
    such other relief as it deems fit in the circumstances of the case.
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> The appellate 
    authority shall have the same powers as vested in a civil court under the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, (5 of 1908) when trying a suit, in respect of 
    the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  enforcing the attendance of 
    any person and examining him on oath; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  compelling the production of 
    documents and material objects.]
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The decision of the 
    appellate authority shall be final and binding on both the parties and be 
    given effect to within such time as may be specified in the order of the 
    appellate authority.
  










  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> Penalty for obstructing 
    Inspector.—Whoever 
    obstructs the Chief Inspector or an Inspector in the exercise of any powers 
    conferred on him by or under this Act, or fails to produce on demand by the 
    Chief Inspector or an Inspector any register or other document kept in his 
    custody in pursuance of this Act or of any rules made thereunder, or 
    conceals or prevents any employee in an industrial premises from appearing 
    before or being examined by the Chief Inspector or an Inspector, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[six months] which 
    may extend to <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[five thousand 
    rupees], or with both.







  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> General penalty for 
    offence.—Save as 
    otherwise expressly provided in this Act, any person who contravenes any of 
    the provisions of this Act or of any rule made thereunder, or fails to wages 
    or compensation in accordance with any order of the appellate authority 
    passed under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 31, shall, be 
    punishable, for the first offence, with fine which may extend to two hundred 
    and fifty rupees and for a second or any subsequent offence with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one month or more than 
    six months or with fine which shall not be less than one hundred rupees or 
    more than five hundred rupees or with both.
 <section>
<number>2</number> (a) Any employer who 
    fails to reinstate any employee in accordance with the order of the 
    appellate authority passed under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 
    31, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred and fifty 
    rupees.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Any employer, who, 
    after having been convicted under clause (a), continues, after the date of 
    such conviction, to fail to reinstate an employee in accordance with the 
    order mentioned in that clause, shall be punishable, for each day of such 
    default, with fine which may extend to twenty rupees.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Any court trying an 
    offence punishable under this sub-section may direct that the whole or any 
    part of the fine, if realised, shall be paid, by way of compensation, to the 
    person, who, in its opinion, has been injured by such failure.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936) with regard 
    to the definition of wages, any compensation required to be paid by an 
    employer under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 31 but not paid by 
    him shall be recoverable as delayed wages under the provisions of that Act.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> It shall be no defence 
    in a prosecution of any person for the contravention of the provisions of 
    section 3 that any manufacturing process connected with the making of beedi 
    or cigar or both was carried on by such person himself of by any member of 
    his family or by any other person living with or dependant on such person.
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who, at the time the offence was committed was incharge of, and was 
    responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing 
    contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
    punishment provided in this Act if he proves that the offence was committed 
    without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has 
    been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been 
    committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any 
    neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of 
    the company, such director, manager; secretary or other officer shall also 
    deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
    against and punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm, and other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> “director”, in relation to a firm, means a 
    partner in the firm.
</subsection>
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Indemnity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person 
    for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
    Act or any rule or order made thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No suit or other legal 
    proceedings shall lie against the Government for any damage caused or likely 
    to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
    in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> Cognizance of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act 
    except upon a complaint made by, or with the previous sanction in writing of 
    the Chief Inspector or an Inspector within three months of the date on which 
    the alleged commission of the offence came to the knowledge of the 
    Inspector:
 
Provided that where the 
    offence consists of disobeying a written order made by the competent 
    authority, the Chief Inspector or an Inspector, complaint thereof may be 
    made within six months of the date on which the offence is alleged to have 
    been committed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No Court inferior to 
    that of a presidency magistrate or a magistrate of the first class shall try 
    any offence punishable under this Act.
  

  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> Application of the 
    Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 and the Maternity Benefit 
    Act, 1961.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provisions of the Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 (20 
    of 1946) shall apply to every industrial premises wherein fifty or more 
    persons are employed or were employed on any one day of the preceding twelve 
    months as if such industrial premises were an industrial establishment to 
    which that Act has been applied by a notification under sub-section (3) of 
    section 1 thereof, and as if the employee in the said premises were a 
    workman within the meaning of that Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1) the State Government may, after giving 
    not less than two months’ notice of its intention so to do, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, apply all or any of the provisions of the 
    Industrial Employment (Standing Orders) Act, 1946 (20 of 1946), to any 
    industrial premises wherein less than fifty employees are employed or were 
    employed on any one day of the preceding twelve months as if such industrial 
    premises were an industrial establishment to which Act has been applied by a 
    notification under sub-section (3) of section 1 thereof, and as if the 
    employee in the said premises were a workman within the meaning of that Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961 (53 of 1961), the 
    provisions of that Act shall apply to every establishment as if such 
    establishment were an establishment to which that Act has been applied by a 
    notification under sub-section (1) of section 2 thereof:
 
Provided that the said Act 
    shall, in its application to a home worker, apply subject to the following 
    modifications, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  in section 5, in the
    Explanation to sub-section (1), the words “or one rupee a day, 
    whichever is higher” shall be omitted; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> sections 8 and 10 shall 
    be omitted.
</subsection>
  

  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> Certain provisions not 
    to apply to industrial premises.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Chapter IV and section 85 of the Factories Act, 1948 (62 of 1948) shall 
    apply to an industrial premises and the rest of the provisions in that Act 
    shall not apply to any industrial premises.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
    any law relating to the regulation of the conditions of work of workers in 
    shops or commercial establishments shall apply to any establishment to which 
    this Act applies.
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> Application of the 
    Industrial Disputes Act, 1947.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provisions of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) shall apply 
    to matters arising in respect of every industrial premises.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), a dispute between an employer and 
    employee relating to—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the issue by the employer of 
    raw materials to the employees,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the rejection by the employer 
    of beedi or cigar or both made by an employee,
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the payment of wages for the beedi or cigar or both rejected by the employer, 
 
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[shall be referred 
    for settlement within such time and by such authority as the State 
    Government may, by rules, specify in this behalf and such rules may also 
    provide for the summary manner in which such dispute shall be settled.]
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person aggrieved by 
    a settlement made by the authority specified under sub-section (2) may 
    prefer an appeal to such authority and within such time as the State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this 
    behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The decision of the 
    authority specified under sub-section (3) shall be final.





  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Effect of law and 
    agreements inconsistent with this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    inconsistent therewith contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force or in the terms of any award, agreement or contract of service whether 
    made before or after the commencement of this Act.
 
Provided that where under 
    any such award, agreement, contract of service or otherwise an employee is 
    entitled to benefits in respect of any matters which are more favourable to 
    him than those to which he will be entitled to under this Act, the employee 
    shall continue to be entitled to the more favourable benefits in respect of 
    that matter notwithstanding that he receives benefits in respect of other 
    matters under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
    this Act shall be construed as precluding any employee from entering into an 
    agreement with an employer for granting him rights or privileges in respect 
    of any matter which are more favourable to him than those to which he would 
    be entitled under this Act.
  




  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Power to exempt.­—The 
    State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt, 
    subject to such conditions and restrictions as it may impose, any class of 
    industrial premises or class of employers or employees from all or any of 
    the provisions of this Act or of any rules made thereunder:
 
Provided that nothing in 
    this section shall be constructed as empowering the State Government to 
    grant any exemption in respect of any woman employee from any of the 
    provisions of this Act or any rules made thereunder relating to annual leave 
    with wages, maternity benefits, creches, wages, rejection of beedi or cigar 
    and night work.
  

  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Powers of Central 
    Government to give directions.—The 
    Central Government may give directions to a State Government as to the 
    carrying into execution of the provisions of this Act.
  

  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>43</number> Act not to apply to 
    self-employed persons in private dwelling houses.— 
    Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to the owner or occupier of a 
    private dwelling house who carries on any manufacturing process in such 
    private dwelling house with the assistance of the members of his family 
    living with him in such dwelling house and dependant on him:
 
Provided that the owner or 
    occupier thereof is not an employee of an employer to whom this Act applies.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “family” means the spouse and children of the 
    owner or occupier.
  
  

  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
    without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
    provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the terms and conditions 
    subject to which a licence may be granted or renewed under this Act and the 
    fees to be paid in respect of such licence;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> the form of application for a licence under this Act and the documents and plans to be submitted together 
    with such application;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> other matters which are to be 
    taken into consideration by the competent authority for granting or refusing 
    a licence;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> the time within which, the fees 
    on payment of which and the authority to which, appeals may be preferred 
    against any order granting or refusing to grant a licence;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> the submission of a monthly 
    return by an employer to the competent authority specifying the quantity of 
    tobacco released by the Central Excise Department and the number of beedi or 
    cigar or both manufactured by him;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> the powers which may be conferred on the 
    Inspectors under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> the standards of cleanliness required to 
    be maintained under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> the standards of lighting, ventilation and 
    temperature required to be maintained under this Act; 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> the types of urinals and 
    latrines required to be provided under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> the washing facilities which are to be 
    provided under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number> canteens;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number> the form and manner of notice regarding 
    the periods of work;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>  the form in which records of work 
    done outside an establishment shall be maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number> the authority to which and the 
    time within which an appeal may be filed by a dismissed, discharged or 
    retrenched employee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>  the manner in which the cash 
    equivalent of the advantage accruing through the concessional sale to an 
    employee of foodgrains and other articles shall be computed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number> the records and registers that 
    shall be maintained in an establishment for the purpose of securing 
    compliance with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number> the maintenance of first aid 
    boxes or cupboards and the contents thereof and the persons in whose charge 
    such boxes shall be placed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number> the manner in which sorting or 
    rejection of beedi or cigar or both and disposal of rejected beedi or cigar 
    or both shall be carried out; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number> the fixation of maximum limit 
    of the percentage of rejection of beedi or cigar or both manufactured by an 
    employee;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number> specifying the place at which 
    wages shall be paid to persons who receive directly or through an agent raw 
    materials for the manufacture of beedi or cigar or both at home;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>  supervision by the Inspectors 
    over distribution of raw materials including beedi and tobacco leaves to the 
    employees;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number> precautions to be taken 
    against fire for the safety of workers;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>w</number>  
<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[the 
    time within which a dispute specified in sub-section (2) of section 39 shall 
    be referred for settlement, the authority by which and the summary manner in 
    which such dispute shall be settled] and the authority to which an appeal 
    shall be from the settlement made by the first-mentioned authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>  any matter which is required 
    to be, or may be, prescribed.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All rules made under 
    this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette and shall be subject to 
    the condition of previous publication; and the dates to be specified under 
    clause (3) of section 23 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), 
    shall not be less than three months from the date on which draft of the 
    proposed rules was published.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every rule made under 
    this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
    house of the State Legislature, where it consists of two Houses, or where 
    such Legislature consists of one house, before that House, while it is in 
    session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the 
    session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following the 
    Legislatures agree in making any modification in the rule or the 
    Legislatures agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
    thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the 
    case may be; so however, that any such modification or annulment, shall be 
    without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that 
    rule.






  







</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>             Ins. by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>             Added by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>             Subs. by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 4, for “fifty”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>             Ins. by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 5.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> 
                Added by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 6.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>    Ins. by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 7.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> 
 Subs. by Act 41 of 
    1993, sec. 8, for “three months”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> 
 Subs. by Act 
    41 of 1993, sec. 8, for “five hundred rupees”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>             Subs. by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 9 for certain words.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>             Subs. by Act 41 of 1993, sec. 10 for certain words.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>