<act><title>

the 
    Electricity Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules shall be called the Electricity Rules, 2005.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    These rules shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
    Official Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise, requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Electricity Act, 2003 
    (36 of 2003); 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the words and expressions used and not 
    defined herein but defined in the Act shall have the meaning assigned to 
    them in the Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Requirements of Captive Generating Plant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No power plant shall qualify as a ‘Captive Generating Plant’ under section 9 
    read with clause (8) of section 2 of the Act unless— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in case of a power plant— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    not less than twenty six per cent. of 
    the ownership is held by the captive user(s), and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    not less than fifty one per cent. of 
    the aggregate electricity generated in such plant, determined on an annual 
    basis, is consumed for the captive use: 
 
Provided that in case of power plant set up by 
    registered co-operative society, the conditions mentioned under paragraphs (i) 
    and (ii) above shall be satisfied collectively by the members of the 
    co-­operative society:
 
Provided further that in case of association 
    of persons, the captive user(s) shall hold not less than twenty six per 
    cent. of the ownership of the plant in aggregate and such captive user(s) 
    shall consume not less than fifty one per cent. of the electricity 
    generated, determined on an annual basis, in proportion to their shares in 
    ownership of the power plant within a variation not exceeding ten per cent.; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in case of a generating station owned 
    by a company formed as special purpose vehicle for such generating station, 
    a unit or units of such generating station identified for captive use and 
    not the entire generating station satisfy(ies) the conditions contained in 
    paragraphs (i) and (ii) of sub-­clause (a) above including— 
 
Explanation.—(1) 
    The electricity required to be consumed by captive users shall be determined 
    with reference to such generating unit or units in aggregate identified for 
    captive use and not with reference to generating station as a whole; and 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The equity shares to be held by the 
    captive user(s) in the generating station shall not be less than twenty six 
    per cent. of the proportionate of the equity of the company related to the 
    generating unit or units identified as the captive generating plant. 
  
 


    Illustration
 
In a 
    generating station with two units of 50 MW each namely Units A and B, one 
    unit of 50 MW namely Unit A may be identified as the Captive Generating 
    Plant. The captive users shall hold not less than thirteen per cent. of the 
    equity shares in the company (being the twenty six per cent. proportionate 
    to Unit A of 50 MW) and not less than fifty one per cent. of the electricity 
    generated in Unit A determined on an annual basis is to be consumed by the 
    captive users. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall be the obligation of the captive users to ensure that the consumption 
    by the captive users at the percentages mentioned in sub‑clauses (a) and (b) 
    of sub­-rule (1) above is maintained and in case the minimum percentage of 
    captive use is not complied with in any year, the entire electricity 
    generated shall be treated as if it is a supply of electricity by a 
    generating company. 
 

    Explanation.—(1) 
    For the purpose of this rule,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “annual basis” 
    shall be determined based on a financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “captive user” 
    shall mean the end user of the electricity generated in a Captive Generating 
    Plant and the term “captive use” shall be construed accordingly; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “ownership” in 
    relation to a generating station or power plant set up by a company or any 
    other body corporate shall mean the equity share capital with voting rights. 
    In other cases ownership shall mean proprietary interest and control over 
    the generating station or power plant; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “Special Purpose 
    Vehicle” shall mean a legal entity owning, operating and maintaining a 
    generating station and with no other business or activity to be engaged in 
    by the legal entity. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Distribution system.—The 
    distribution system of a distribution licensee in terms of sub‑section (19) 
    of section 2 of the Act shall also include electric line, sub‑station and 
    electrical plant that are primarily maintained for the purpose of 
    distributing electricity in the area of supply of such distribution licensee 
    notwithstanding that such line, sub‑station or electrical plant are high 
    pressure cables or overhead lines or associated with such high pressure 
    cables or overhead lines; or used incidentally for the purposes of 
    transmitting electricity for others.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Compliance with the directions by transmission licensee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The National Load Despatch Centre, Regional Load Despatch Centre, as the 
    case may be, or the State Load Despatch Centre, may, under section 26, 
    sub­-section (3) of section 28, sub‑section (1) of section 29, sub‑section 
    (2) of section 32 and sub‑section (1) of section 33 read with clause (b) of 
    section 40 of the Act, give such directions, as it may consider appropriate 
    for maintaining the availability of the transmission system of a 
    Transmission Licensee and the Transmission Licensee shall duly comply with 
    all such directions. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Appropriate Commission, on an application filed by the National Load 
    Despatch Centre, the Regional Load Despatch Centre or the State Load 
    Despatch Centre and after hearing the Transmission Licensee, if satisfied 
    that the Transmission Licensee has persistently failed to maintain the 
    availability of the transmission system, may issue such directions to the 
    National Load Despatch Centre, the Regional Load Despatch Centre or the 
    State Load Despatch Centre to take control of the operations of the 
    transmission system of such Transmission Licensee for such period and on 
    such terms, as the Commission may decide. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    direction under sub‑rules (1) and (2) above shall be without prejudice to 
    any other action which may be taken against the Transmission Licensee under 
    other provisions of the Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    The surcharge under section 38.—The 
    surcharge on transmission charges under section 38, the manner of 
    progressive reduction of such surcharge and the manner of payment and 
    utilization of such surcharge to be specified by the Central Commission 
    under sub‑clause (ii) of clause (d) of sub‑section (2) of section 38 shall 
    be in accordance with surcharge on the charges for wheeling, the manner of 
    progressive reduction of such surcharge and the manner of payment and 
    utilization of such surcharge as may be specified by the Appropriate 
    Commission of the State in which the consumer is located under sub‑section 
    (2) of section 42 of the Act. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Consumer Redressal Forum and Ombudsman.—1[
<section><number>1</number> The distribution licensee shall establish 
    a Forum for Redressal of Grievances of Consumers under sub‑section (5) of 
    section 42 which shall consist of officers of the licensee. The Appropriate 
    Commission shall nominate one independent member who is familiar with the 
    consumer affairs:
 
Provided 
    that the manner of appointment and the qualification and experience of the 
    persons to be appointed as member of the Forum and the procedure of dealing 
    with the grievances of the consumers by the Forum and other similar matters 
    would be as per the guidelines specified by the State Commission.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Ombudsman to be appointed or designated by the State Commission under 
    sub‑section (6) of section 42 of the Act shall be such person as the State 
    Commission may decide from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Ombudsman shall consider the representations of the consumers consistent 
    with the provisions of the Act, the Rules and Regulations made hereunder or 
    general orders or directions given by the Appropriate Government or the 
    Appropriate Commission in this regard before settling their grievances.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (a) 
    The Ombudsman shall prepare a report on a six monthly basis giving details 
    of the nature of the grievances of the consumer dealt by the Ombudsman, the 
    response of the Licensees in the redressal of the grievances and the opinion 
    of the Ombudsman on the Licensee’s compliance of the standards of 
    performance as specified by the Commission under section 57 of the Act 
    during the preceding six months.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    report under sub‑clause (a) above shall be forwarded to the State Commission 
    and the State Government within 45 days after the end of the relevant period 
    of six months.
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Tariffs of generating companies under section 79.—The 
    tariff determined by the Central Commission for generating companies under 
    clause 
<section><number>a</number> or (b) of sub‑section (1) of section 79 of the Act shall not be 
    subject to re‑determination by the State Commission in exercise of functions 
    under clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number> or (b) of sub‑section (1) of section 86 of the Act and 
    subject to the above the State Commission may determine whether a 
    Distribution Licensee in the State should enter into Power Purchase 
    Agreement or procurement process with such generating companies based on the 
    tariff determined by the Central Commission. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Inter‑State trading licence.—A 
    licence issued by the Central Commission under section 14 read with clause 
    (e) of sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 79 of the Act to an electricity trader for 
    inter‑state operations shall also entitle such electricity trader to 
    undertake purchase of electricity from a seller in a State and resell such 
    electricity to a buyer in the same State, without the need to take a 
    separate licence for intra‑State trading from the State Commission of such 
    State. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Appeal to the Appellate Tribunal.—In 
    terms of sub‑section (2) of section 111 of the Act, the appeal against the 
    orders passed by the adjudicating officer or the appropriate commission 
    after the coming into force of the Act may be filed within forty-five days 
    from the date, as notified by the Central Government, on which the Appellate 
    Tribunal comes into operation. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Jurisdiction of the courts.—The 
    jurisdiction of courts other than the special courts shall not be barred 
    under sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 154 till such time the special court is 
    constituted under sub‑section (1) of section 153 of the Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Cognizance of the offence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The police shall take cognizance of the offence punishable under the Act on 
    a complaint in writing made to the police by the Appropriate Government or 
    the Appropriate Commission or any of their officer authorized by them in 
    this regard or a Chief Electrical Inspector or an Electrical Inspector or an 
    authorized officer of Licensee or a generating company, as the case may be. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    police shall investigate the complaint in accordance with the general law 
    applicable to the investigation of any complaint. For the purposes of 
    investigation of the complaint the police shall have all the powers as 
    available under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    police shall, after investigation, forward the report along with the 
    complaint filed under sub‑clause (1) to the court for trial under the Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub‑clauses (1), (2) and (3) above, 
    the complaint for taking cognizance of an offence punishable under the Act 
    may also be filed by the Appropriate Government or the Appropriate 
    Commission or any of their officer authorized by them or a Chief Electrical 
    Inspector or an Electrical Inspector or an authorized officer of Licensee or 
    a generating company, as the case may be directly in the appropriate court. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, 
    every special court may take cognizance of an offence referred to in 
    sections 135 to 139 of the Act without the accused being committed to it for 
    trial. 
 </section><section>
 <number>6</number> The 
    cognizance of the offence under the Act shall not in any way prejudice the 
    actions under the provisions of the Indian Penal Code. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number> Issue of orders and practice directions.—The Central Government may from 
      time to time issue orders and practice directions in regard to the 
      implementation of these rules and matters incidental or ancillary thereto 
      as the Central Government may consider 
      appropriate. 
  
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>