<act><title>

THE PREVENTION OF CORRUPTION ACT, 1988</title> 

  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir and it applies also to all citizens 
of India outside India.
  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “election” means any election, by whatever means 
held under any law for the purpose of selecting members of Parliament or of any 
Legislature, local authority or other public authority;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “public duty” means a duty in the discharge of 
which the State, the public or the community at large has an interest.
                  Explanation.—In this clause “State” 
includes a corporation established by or under a Central, Provincial or State 
Act, or an authority or a body owned or controlled or aided by the Government or 
a Government company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 
1956);
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> “public servant” means,—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number> any person in the service or pay of the 
Government or remunerated by the Government by fees or commission for the 
performance of any public duty;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number> any person in the service or pay of a local 
authority;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number> any person in the service or pay of a 
corporation established by or under a Central, Provincial or State Act, or an 
authority or a body owned or controlled or aided by the Government or a 
Government company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 
1956);
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number> any Judge, including any person empowered by 
law to discharge, whether by himself or as a member of any body of persons, any 
adjudicatory functions;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>v</number> any person authorised by a court of justice 
to perform any duty, in connection with the administration of justice, including 
a liquidator, receiver or commissioner appointed by such court;
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>vi</number>  any arbitrator or other person to whom any 
cause or matter has been referred for decision or report by a court of justice 
or by a competent public authority;
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>vii</number>  any person who holds an office by virtue 
of which he is empowered to prepare, publish, maintain or revise an electoral 
roll or to conduct an election or part of an election;
 </subsection><subsection>          <number>viii</number>  any person who holds an office by virtue 
of which he is authorised or required to perform any public duty;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ix</number>  any person who is the president, secretary 
or other office-bearer of a registered co-operative society engaged in 
agriculture, industry, trade or banking, receiving or having received any 
financial aid from the Central Government or a State Government or from any 
corporation established by or under a Central, Provincial or State Act, or any 
authority or body owned or controlled or aided by the Government or a Government 
company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956  
(1 of 1956);
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>x</number>  any person who is a chairman, member or 
employee of any Service Commission or Board, by whatever name called, or a 
member of any selection committee appointed by such Commission or Board for the 
conduct of any examination or making any selection on behalf of such Commission 
or Board;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>xi</number>  any person who is a Vice-Chancellor or 
member of any governing body, professor, reader, lecturer or any other teacher 
or employee, by whatever designation called, of any University and any person 
whose services have been availed of by a University or any other public 
authority in connection with holding or conducting examinations;
 </subsection></section><section>           <number>xii</number>  any person who is an office-bearer or an 
employee of an educational, scientific, social, cultural or other institution, 
in whatever manner established, receiving or having received any financial 
assistance from the Central Government or any State Government, or local or 
other public authority.
 Explanation 1.—Persons 
falling under any of the above sub-clauses are public servants, whether 
appointed by the Government or not.
 Explanation 2.—Wherever 
the words “public servant” occur, they shall be understood of every person who 
is in actual possession of the situation of a public servant, whatever legal 
defect there may be in his right to hold that situation.









</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Power to appoint special 
Judges.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government or 
the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint as 
many special Judges as may be necessary for such area or areas or for such case 
or group of cases as may be specified in the notification to try the following 
offences, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> any offence punishable under this Act; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> any conspiracy to commit or any attempt to commit 
or any abetment of any of the offences specified in clause (a).
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment as a special Judge under this Act unless he is or has 
been a Sessions Judge or an Additional Sessions Judge or an Assistant Sessions 
Judge under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Cases triable by special 
Judges.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), or in any other 
law for the time being in force, the offences specified in sub-section (1) of 
section 3 shall be tried by special Judges only.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every offence specified in 
sub-section (1) of section 3 shall be tried by the special Judge for the area 
within which it was committed, or, as the case may be, by the special Judge 
appointed for the case, or, where there are more special Judges than one for 
such area, by such one of them as may be specified in this behalf by the Central 
Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> When trying any case, a 
special Judge may also try any offence, other than an offence specified in 
section 3, with which the accused may, under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
1973 (2 of 1974), be charged at the same trial.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), a special Judge 
shall, as far as practicable, hold the trial of an offence on day-to-day basis.







</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Procedure and powers of 
special Judge.—
<section><number>1</number> A special Judge 
may take cognizance of offences without the accused being committed to him for 
trial and, in trying the accused persons, shall follow the procedure prescribed 
by the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), for the trial of warrant 
cases by the Magistrates.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A special Judge may, with a 
view to obtaining the evidence of any person supposed to have been directly or 
indirectly concerned in, or privy to, an offence, tender a pardon to such person 
on condition of his making a full and true disclosure of the whole circumstances 
within his knowledge relating to the offence and to every other person 
concerned, whether as principal or abettor, in the commission thereof and any 
pardon so tendered shall, for the purposes of sub-sections (1) to (5) of section 
308 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), be deemed to have been 
tendered under section 307 of that Code.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Save as provided in 
sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the provisions of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), shall, so far as they are not inconsistent with 
this Act, apply to the proceedings before a special Judge; and for purposes of 
the said provisions, the Court of the special Judge shall be deemed to be a 
Court of Session and the person conducting a prosecution before a special Judge 
shall be deemed to be a public prosecutor.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In particular and without 
prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in sub-section (3), the 
provisions of sections 326 and 475 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974), shall, so far as may be, apply to the proceedings before a special Judge 
and for the purposes of the said provisions, a special Judge shall be deemed to 
be a Magistrate.
 </section><section><number>5</number> A special Judge may pass 
upon any person convicted by him any sentence authorised by law for the 
punishment of the offence of which such person is convicted.
 </section><section><number>6</number> A special Judge, while 
trying an offence punishable under this Act, shall exercise all the powers and 
functions exercisable by a District Judge under the Criminal Law Amendment 
Ordinance, 1944 (Ord. 38 of 1944).



</section></article> 

   
 <article><number>6</number> Power to try summarily.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a special Judge tries any offence specified in sub-section (1) of section 
3, alleged to have been committed by a public servant in relation to the 
contravention of any special order referred to in sub-section (1) of section 12A 
of the Essential Commodities Act, 1955 (10 of 1955) or of an order referred to 
in clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) of that section, then, notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1) of section 5 of this Act or section 260 of the Code 
of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), the special Judge shall try the offence 
in a summary way, and the provisions of sections 262 to 265 (both inclusive) of 
the said Code shall, as far as may be, apply to such trial:
 Provided that, in the case of 
any conviction in a summary trial under this section, it shall be lawful for the 
special Judge to pass a sentence of imprisonment for a term not exceeding one 
year:
 Provided further that when at 
the commencement of, or in the course of, a summary trial under this section, it 
appears to the special Judge that the nature of the case is such that a sentence 
of imprisonment for a term exceeding one year may have to be passed or that it 
is, for any other reason, undesirable to try the case summarily, the special 
Judge shall, after hearing the parties, record an order to that effect and 
thereafter recall any witnesses who may have been examined and proceed to hear 
or re-hear the case in accordance with the procedure prescribed by the said Code 
for the trial of warrant cases by Magistrates.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything to 
the contrary contained in this Act or in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 
of 1974), there shall be no appeal by a convicted person in any case tried 
summarily under this section in which the special Judge passes a sentence of 
imprisonment not exceeding one month, and of fine not exceeding two thousand 
rupees whether or not any order under section 452 of the said Code is made in 
addition to such sentence, but an appeal shall lie where any sentence in excess 
of the aforesaid limits is passed by a special Judge.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>7</number> Public servant taking 
gratification other than legal remuneration in respect of an official act.—Whoever, 
being, or expecting to be a public servant, accepts or obtains or agrees to 
accept or attempts to obtain from any person, for himself or for any other 
person, any gratification whatever, other than legal remuneration, as a motive 
or reward for doing or forbearing to do any official act or for showing or 
forbearing to show, in the exercise of his official functions, favour or 
disfavour to any person or for rendering or attempting to render any service or 
disservice to any person, with the Central Government or any State Government or 
Parliament or the Legislature of any State or with any local authority, 
corporation or Government company referred to in clause (c) of  
section 2, or with any public servant, whether named or otherwise, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment which shall be not less than six months but which 
may extend to five years and shall also be liable to fine.
 <section><number>Explanations</number>—(a) 
“Expecting to be a public servant”. If a person not expecting to be in office 
obtains a gratification by deceiving others into a belief that he is about to be 
in office, and that he will then serve them, he may be guilty of cheating, but 
he is not guilty of the offence defined in this section.
 <subsection><number>b</number> “Gratification”. The word 
“gratification” is not restricted to pecuniary gratifications or to 
gratifications estimable in money.
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “Legal remuneration”. The 
words “legal remuneration” are not restricted to remuneration which a public 
servant can lawfully demand, but include all remuneration which he is permitted 
by the Government or the organisation, which he serves, to accept.
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “A motive or reward for 
doing”. A person who receives a gratification as a motive or reward for doing 
what he does not intend or is not in a position to do, or has not done, comes 
within this expression.
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Where a public servant 
induces a person erroneously to believe that his influence with the Government 
has obtained a title for that person and thus induces that person to give the 
public servant, money or any other gratification as a reward for this service, 
the public servant has committed an offence under this section.










</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Taking gratification, in 
order, by corrupt or illegal means, to influence public servant.—Whoever 
accepts or obtains, or agrees to accept, or attempts to obtain, from any person, 
for himself or for any other person, any gratification whatever as a motive or 
reward for inducing, by corrupt or illegal means, any public servant, whether 
named or otherwise, to do or to forbear to do any official act, or in the 
exercise of the official functions of such public servant to show favour or 
disfavour to any person, or to render or attempt to render any service or 
disservice to any person with the Central Government or any State Government or 
Parliament or the Legislature of any State or with any local authority, 
corporation or Government company referred to in clause (c) of  
section 2, or with any public servant, whether named or otherwise, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall be not less than six months 
but which may extend to five years and shall also be liable to fine.



</article> 

   
 <article><number>9</number> Taking gratification, for 
exercise of personal influence with public servant.—Whoever 
accepts or obtains or agrees to accept or attempts to obtain, from any person, 
for himself or for any other person, any gratification whatever, as a motive or 
reward for inducing, by the exercise of personal influence, any public servant 
whether named or otherwise to do or to forbear to do any official act, or in the 
exercise of the official functions of such public servant to show favour or 
disfavour to any person, or to render or attempt to render any service or 
disservice to any person with the Central Government or any State Government or 
Parliament or the Legislature of any State or with any local authority, 
corporation or Government company referred to in clause (c) of section 2, or 
with any public servant, whether named or otherwise, shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which shall be not less than six months but which may 
extend to five years and shall also be liable to fine.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Punishment for abetment 
by public servant of offences defined in section 8 or 9.—Whoever, 
being a public servant, in respect of whom either of the offences defined in 
section 8 or section 9 is committed, abets the offence, whether or not that 
offence is committed in consequence of that abetment, shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which shall be not less than six months but which may 
extend to five years and shall also be liable to fine.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>11</number> Public servant obtaining 
valuable thing, without consideration from person concerned in proceeding or 
business transacted by such public servant.—Whoever, 
being a public servant, accepts or obtains or agrees to accept or attempts to 
obtain for himself, or for any other person, any valuable thing without 
consideration, or for a consideration which he knows to be inadequate, from any 
person whom he knows to have been, or to be, or to be likely to be concerned in 
any proceeding or business transacted or about to be transacted by such public 
servant, or having any connection with the official functions of himself or of 
any public servant to whom he is subordinate, or from any person whom he knows 
to be interested in or related to the person so concerned, shall be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which shall be not less than six months but which 
may extend to five years and shall also be liable to fine.




</article> 

   
 <article><number>12</number> Punishment for abetment 
of offences defined in section 7 or 11.—Whoever 
abets any offence punishable under section 7 or section 11 whether or not that 
offence is committed in consequence of that abetment, shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which shall be not less than six months but which may 
extend to five years and shall also be liable to fine.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>13</number> Criminal misconduct by a 
public servant.—
<section><number>1</number> A public servant 
is said to commit the offence of criminal misconduct,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> if he habitually accepts or obtains or agrees to 
accept or attempts to obtain from any person for himself or for any other person 
any gratification other than legal remuneration as a motive or reward such as is 
mentioned in section 7; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> if he habitually accepts or obtains or agrees to 
accept or attempts to obtain for himself or for any other person, any valuable 
thing without consideration or for a consideration which he knows to be 
inadequate from any person whom he knows to have been, or to be, or to be likely 
to be concerned in any proceeding or business transacted or about to be 
transacted by him, or having any connection with the official functions of 
himself or of any public servant to whom he is subordinate, or from any person 
whom he knows to be interested in or related to the person so concerned; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> if he dishonestly or fraudulently misappropriates 
or otherwise converts for his own use any property entrusted to him or under his 
control as a public servant or allows any other person so to do; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number> if he,—
 <subsubsection>             <number>i</number> by corrupt or illegal means, obtains for 
himself or for any other person any valuable thing or pecuniary advantage; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number> by abusing his position as a public 
servant, obtains for himself or for any other person any valuable thing or 
pecuniary advantage; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>iii</number> while holding office as a public servant, 
obtains for any person any valuable thing or pecuniary advantage without any 
public interest; or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number> if he or any person on his behalf, is in 
possession or has, at any time during the period of his office, been in 
possession for which the public servant cannot satisfactorily account, of 
pecuniary resources or property disproportionate to his known sources of income.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section, “known sources of income” means income received 
from any lawful source and such receipt has been intimated in accordance with 
the provisions of any law, rules or orders for the time being applicable to a 
public servant.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any public servant who 
commits criminal misconduct shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which shall be not less than one year but which may extend to seven years and 
shall also be liable to fine.















</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>14</number> Habitual committing of 
offence under sections 8, 9 and 12.—Whoever 
habitually commits,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> an offence punishable under section 8 or section 
9; or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> an offence punishble under section 12,
 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall be not 
less than two years but which may extend to seven years and shall also be liable 
to fine.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>15</number> Punishment for attempt.—Whoever 
attempts to commit an offence referred to in clause (c) or clause (d) of 
sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 13 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to three years and with fine.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>16</number> Matters to be taken into 
consideration for fixing fine.—Where 
a sentence of fine is imposed under sub-section (2) of section 13 or section 14, 
the court is fixing the amount of the fine shall take into consideration the 
amount or the value of the property, if any, which the accused person has 
obtained by committing the offence or where the conviction is for an offence 
referred to in clause (e) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 13, the pecuniary 
resources or property referred to in that clause for which the accused person is 
unable to account satisfactorily.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>17</number> Persons authorised to 
investigate.—Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), no police officer 
below the rank,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> in the case of the Delhi Special Police 
Establishment, of an Inspector of Police; 
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> in the metropolitan areas of Bombay, Calcutta, 
Madras and Ahmedabad and in any other metropolitan area notified as such under 
sub-section (1) of section 8 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974), of an Assistant Commissioner of Police;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> elsewhere, of a Deputy Superintendent of Police 
or a police officer of equivalent rank,
 shall investigate any offence punishable under this Act without the 
order of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Magistrate of the first class, as the 
case may be, or make any arrest therefor without a warrant:
 Provided that if a police 
officer not below the rank of an Inspector of Police is authorised by the State 
Government in this behalf by general or special order, he may also investigate 
any such offence without the order of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Magistrate 
of the first class, as the case may be, or make arrest therefor without a 
warrant:
 Provided further that an offence 
referred to in clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 13 shall not be 
investigated without the order of a police officer not below the rank of a 
Superintendent of Police.








</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>18</number> Power to inspect bankers’ 
books.—If from information received 
or otherwise, a police officer has reason to suspect the commission of an 
offence which he is empowered to investigate under section 17 and considers that 
for the purpose of investigation or inquiry into such offence, it is necessary 
to inspect any bankers’ books, then notwithstanding anything contained in any 
law for the time being in force, he may inspect any bankers’ books in so far as 
they relate to the accounts of the persons suspected to have committed that 
offence or of any other person suspect to be holding money on behalf of such 
person, and take or cause to be taken certified copies of the relevant entries 
therefrom, and the bank concerned shall be bound to assist the police officer in 
the exercise of his powers under this section:
 Provided that no power under 
this section in relation to the accounts of any person shall be exercised by a 
police officer below the rank of a Superintendent of Police, unless he is 
specially authorised in this behalf by a police officer of or above the rank of 
a Superintendent of Police.
 Explanation.—In 
this section, the expressions “bank” and “bankers’ books” shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Bankers’ Books Evidence Act, 1891 
(18 of 1891).
</article> 

  
 <article><number>18</number> Power to inspect bankers’ 
books.—If from information received 
or otherwise, a police officer has reason to suspect the commission of an 
offence which he is empowered to investigate under section 17 and considers that 
for the purpose of investigation or inquiry into such offence, it is necessary 
to inspect any bankers’ books, then notwithstanding anything contained in any 
law for the time being in force, he may inspect any bankers’ books in so far as 
they relate to the accounts of the persons suspected to have committed that 
offence or of any other person suspect to be holding money on behalf of such 
person, and take or cause to be taken certified copies of the relevant entries 
therefrom, and the bank concerned shall be bound to assist the police officer in 
the exercise of his powers under this section:
 Provided that no power under 
this section in relation to the accounts of any person shall be exercised by a 
police officer below the rank of a Superintendent of Police, unless he is 
specially authorised in this behalf by a police officer of or above the rank of 
a Superintendent of Police.
 Explanation.—In 
this section, the expressions “bank” and “bankers’ books” shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Bankers’ Books Evidence Act, 1891 
(18 of 1891).
</article> 

  
 <article><number>19</number> Previous sanction 
necessary for prosecution.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under sections 7, 10, 11, 
13 and 15 alleged to have been committed by a public servant, except with the 
previous sanction,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> in the case of a person who is employed in 
connection with the affairs of the Union and is not removable from his office 
save by or with the sanction of the Central Government, of that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> in the case of a person who is employed in 
connection with the affairs of a State and is not removable from his office save 
by or with the sanction of the State Government, of that Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> in the case of any other person, of the authority 
competent to remove him from his office.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where for any reason 
whatsoever any doubt arises as to whether the previous sanction as required 
under sub-section (1) should be given by the Central Government or the State 
Government or any other authority, such sanction shall be given by that 
Government or authority which would have been competent to remove the public 
servant from his office at the time when the offence was alleged to have been 
committed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974),—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> no finding, sentence or order passed by a special 
Judge shall be reversed or altered by a court in appeal, confirmation or 
revision on the ground of the absence of, or any error, omission or irregularity 
in, the sanction required under sub-section (1), unless in the opinion of that 
court, a failure of justice has in fact been occasioned thereby;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> no court shall stay the proceedings under this 
Act on the ground of any error, omission or irregularity in the sanction granted 
by the authority, unless it is satisfied that such error, omission or 
irregularity has resulted in a failure of justice;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> no court shall stay the proceedings under this 
Act on any other ground and no court shall exercise the powers of revision in 
relation to any interlocutory order passed in any inquiry, trial, appeal or 
other proceedings.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> In determining under 
sub-section (3) whether the absence of, or any error, omission or irregularity 
in, such sanction has occasioned or resulted in a failure of justice the court 
shall have regard to the fact whether the objection could and should have been 
raised at any earlier stage in the proceedings.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> error includes competency of the authority to 
grant sanction;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> a sanction required for prosecution includes 
reference to any requirement that the prosecution shall be at the instance of a 
specified authority or with the sanction of a specified person or any 
requirement of a similar nature.







</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>20</number> Presumption where public 
servant accepts gratification other than legal remuneration.—
<section><number>1</number> Where, in any trial of an offence punishable 
under section 7 or section 11 or clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> or clause (b) of sub-section (1) of 
section 13 it is proved that an accused person has accepted or obtained or has 
agreed to accept or attempted to obtain for himself, or for any other person, 
any gratification (other than legal remuneration) or any valuable thing from any 
person, it shall be presumed, unless the contrary is proved, that he accepted or 
obtained or agreed to accept or attempted to obtain that gratification or that 
valuable thing, as the case may be, as a motive or reward such as is mentioned 
in section 7 or, as the case may be, without consideration or for a 
consideration which he knows to be inadequate.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where in any trial of an 
offence punishable under section 12 or under clause (b) of section 14, it is 
proved that any gratification (other than legal remuneration) or any valuable 
thing has been given or offered to be given or attempted to be given by an 
accused person, it shall be presumed, unless the contrary is proved, that he 
gave or offered to give or attempted to give that gratification or that valuable 
thing, as the case may be, as a motive or reward such as is mentioned in section 
7, or as the case may be, without consideration or for a consideration which he 
knows to be inadequate.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-sections (1) and (2), the court may decline to draw the 
presumption referred to in either of the said sub-sections, if the gratification 
or thing aforesaid is, in its opinion, so trivial that no interference of 
corruption may fairly be drawn.










</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>21</number> Accused person to be a 
competent witness.—Any person charged 
with an offence punishable under this Act, shall be a competent witness for the 
defence and may give evidence on oath in disproof of the charges made against 
him or any person charged together with him at the same trial:
 Provided that—
 <section>       <number>a</number> he shall not be called as a witness except at his 
own request;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> his failure to give evidence shall not be made 
the subject of any comment by the prosecution or give rise to any presumption 
against himself or any person charged together with him at the same trial;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> he shall not be asked, and if asked shall not be 
required to answer, any question tending to show that he has committed or been 
convicted of any offence other than the offence with which he is charged, or is 
of bad character, unless—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number> the proof that he has committed or been 
convicted of such offence is admissible evidence to show that he is guilty of 
the offence with which he is charged, or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number> he has personally or by his pleader asked 
any question of any witness for the prosecution with a view to establish his own 
good character, or has given evidence of his good character, or the nature or 
conduct of the defence is such as to involve imputations on the character of the 
prosecutor or of any witness for the prosecution, or
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number> he has given evidence against any other 
person charged with the same offence.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>22</number> The Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 to apply subject to certain modifications.—The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
1973 (2 of 1974), shall in their application to any proceeding in relation to an 
offence punishable under this Act have effect as if,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> in sub-section (1) of 
section 243, for the words “The accused shall then be called upon”, the words 
“The accused shall then be required to give in writing at once or within such 
time as the court may allow, a list of the persons (if any) whom he proposes to 
examine as his witnesses and of the documents (if any) on which he proposes to 
rely and he shall then be called upon” had been substituted;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> in sub-section (2) of 
section 309, after the third proviso, the following proviso had been inserted, 
namely:—
                  
“Provided also that the proceeding shall not be adjourned or postponed merely on 
the ground that an application under section 397 has been made by a party to the 
proceeding.”;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> after sub-section (2) 
of section 317, the following sub-section had been inserted, namely:—
                  
“(3) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) or sub- section 
(2), the Judge may, if he thinks fit and for reasons to be recorded by him, 
proceed with enquiry or trial in the absence of the accused or his pleader and 
record the evidence of any witness subject to the right of the accused to recall 
the witness for cross-examination.”;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number> in sub-section (1) of 
section 397, before the Explanation, the following proviso had been 
inserted, namely:—
                  
“Provided that where the powers under this section are exercised by a court on 
an application made by a party to such proceedings, the court shall not 
ordinarily call for the record of the proceedings,—
 </section><section>            
<number>a</number> without giving the other party an opportunity of showing cause why the 
record should not be called for; or
 </section><section>            
<number>b</number> if it is satisfied that an examination of the record of the proceedings may 
be made from the certified copies.”.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>23</number> Particulars in a charge in 
relation to an offence under section 13
<section><number>1</number>(c).—Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), when an accused is charged with an offence 
under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 13, it shall be sufficient to 
describe in the charge the property in respect of which the offence is alleged 
to have been committed and the dates between which the offence is alleged to 
have been committed, without specifying particular items or exact dates, and the 
charge so framed shall be deemed to be a charge of one offence within the 
meaning of section 219 of the said Code:
 Provided that the time included 
between the first and last of such dates shall not exceed one 
year.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>24</number> Statement by bribe giver 
not to subject him to prosecution.—Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the 
time being in force, a statement made by a person in any proceeding against a 
public servant for an offence under sections 7 to 11 or under section 13 or 
section 15, that he offered or agreed to offer any gratification (other than 
legal remuneration) or any valuable thing to the public servant, shall not 
subject such person to a prosecution under section 12.</article> 

  
 <article><number>25</number> Military, Naval and Air 
Force or other law not to be affected.— 
<section><number>1</number> Nothing in this Act shall affect the 
jurisdiction exercisable by, or the procedure applicable to, any court or other 
authority under the Army Act, 1950 (45 of 1950), the Air Force Act, 1950 (46 of 
1950), the Navy Act, 1957 (62 of 1957), the Border Security Froce Act, 1968 (47 
of 1968), the Coast Guard Act, 1978 (30 of 1978) and the National Security Guard 
Act, 1986 (47 of 1986).
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the removal of doubts, it 
is hereby declared that for the purposes of any such law as is referred to in 
sub-section (1), the court of a special Judge shall be deemed to be a court of 
ordinary criminal justice.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>26</number> Special Judges appointed 
under Act 46 of 1952 to be special Judges appointed under this 
Act.—Every special Judge appointed 
under the Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1952 for any area or areas and is holding 
office on the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be a special Judge 
appointed under section 3 of this Act for that area or areas and, accordingly, 
on and from such commencement, every such Judge shall continue to deal with all 
the proceedings pending before him on such commencement in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act.</article> 

  
 <article><number>27</number> Appeal and 
revision.—Subject to the provisions 
of this Act, the High Court may exercise, so far as they may be applicable, all 
the powers of appeal and revision conferred by the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
1973 (2 of 1974) on a High Court as if the court of the special Judge were a 
Court of Session trying cases within the local limits of the High 
Court.</article> 

  
 <article><number>28</number> Act to be in addition to 
any other law.—The provisions of this 
Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other law for the 
time being in force, and nothing contained herein shall exempt any public 
servant from any proceeding which might, apart from this Act, be instituted 
against him.</article> 

  
 <article><number>29</number> Amendment of the Ordinance 
38 of 1944.—In the Criminal Law 
Amendment Ordinance, 1944,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> in sub-section (1) of 
section 3, sub-section (1) of section 9, clause (a) of section 10, sub-section 
(1) of section 11 and sub-section (1) of section 13, for the words “State 
Government”, wherever they occur, the words “State Government or, as the case 
may be, the Central Government” shall be substituted;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> in section 10, in 
clause (a), for the words “three months”, the words “one year” shall be 
substituted;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> in the Schedule,—
 <subsection>             
<number>i</number> paragraph 1 shall be omitted;
 </subsection><subsection>            
<number>ii</number> in paragraphs 2 and 4,—
 <subsubsection>                 
<number>a</number> after the words “a local authority”, the words and figures “or a corporation 
established by or under a Central, Provincial or State Act, or an authority or a 
body owned or controlled or aided by Government or a Government company as 
defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or a society aided 
by such corporation, authority, body or Government company” shall be 
inserted;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                 
<number>b</number> after the words “or authority”, the words “or corporation or body or 
Government company or society” shall be inserted;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>            
<number>iii</number> for paragraph 4A, the following paragraph shall be substituted, 
namely:—
                       
“4A. An offence punishable under the Prevention of Corruption Act, 1988.”;
 </subsection><subsection>           
<number>iv</number> in paragraph 5, for the words and figures “items 2, 3 and 4”, the words, 
figures and letter “items 2, 3, 4 and 4A” shall be 
substituted.</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>30</number> Repeal and 
saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Prevention of 
Corruption Act, 1947 (2 of 1947) and the Criminal Law Amendment Act, 1952 (46 of 
1952) are hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, 
but without prejudice to the application of section 6 of the General Clauses 
Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), anything done or any action taken or purported to have 
been done or taken under or in pursuance of the Acts so repealed shall, in so 
far as it is not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have 
been done or taken under or in pursuance of the corresponding provision of this 
Act.</section></article> 

  
 <article>*<number>31</number> Omission of certain 
sections of Act 45 of 1860.—Sections 
161 to 165A (both inclusive) of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860) shall 
be omitted, and section 6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall 
apply to such omission as if the said sections had been repealed by a Central 
Act.
  

</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>