<act><title>


THE 
    DEPOSITORIES (APPEAL TO THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT) RULES, 19981</title> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Depositories (Appeal to the Central 
    Government) Rules, 1998.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the 
    Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “authorised 
    representative” means,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   in relation to an 
    appellant, a person duly authorized by the appellant to present an appeal on 
    his behalf to the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   in relation to the 
    Board, a person duly appointed by the Board by notification in the Official 
    Gazette as authorised representative to appear, plead and act for such 
    authority in any such appeal and any other person acting on behalf of the 
    person so appointed;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Board” means the 
    Securities and Exchange Board of India established under section 3 of the 
    Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Form” means the 
    Form appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “regulations” means 
    the regulations made by the Board under the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “rules” means the 
    rules made under the Act.  
  

 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Form of appeal.—Any 
    person aggrieved by an order of the Board made under the Act or the 
    Regulations made thereunder, may prefer an appeal to the Central Government 
    in the Form.  
  

 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Time within which appeal is to be preferred.—
<section><number>1</number>
An appeal shall be preferred by the aggrieved person within a period of 
    thirty days from the date of communication to him of the order of the Board 
    made under the Act or Regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    When the appeal is preferred after the expiry of the period of thirty days 
    specified in sub‑rule (1), it shall be accompanied by an application 
    supported by an affidavit setting forth the facts on which the appellant 
    relies to satisfy the Central Government that he has sufficient cause for 
    not preferring the appeal within the said period of thirty days:
 

    Provided that if the Central Government is satisfied that the appellant had 
    sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within the aforesaid period, 
    it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, admit the appeal after the 
    aforesaid period but before the expiry of forty‑five days from the date of 
    communication to him of the order of the Board.
 


 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Payment of fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every appeal shall be accompanied by fee of rupees five thousand only.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    The amount of fees shall be deposited in any Government Treasury or any 
    branch of the State Bank of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    The amount of the fees shall be deposited under the head “065—Other Admn. 
    Services—Other Services—Other Receipts”.

 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Contents of appeal.— 
    Every appeal filed under rule 3 shall be written in English or Hindi and 
    shall set forth concisely under distinct heads, the grounds of appeal 
    without any argument or narrative and such grounds shall be numbered 
    consecutively.
  

 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    What to accompany Form.—Every 
    appeal shall be filed in the Form in duplicate and shall be accompanied by 
    two copies (at least one of which shall be a certified copy) of the order of 
    the Board appealed against and other documents to support the grounds of 
    objection mentioned in the appeal.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this rule “certified copy” includes the copy which was 
    originally supplied to the appellant as well as a photocopy thereof duly 
    authenticated by the appellant or his authorized representative as a true 
    copy.
  

 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Filing of affidavits.—Where 
    a fact which cannot be borne out by, or is contrary to, the records is 
    alleged, it shall be stated clearly and concisely and supported by a duly 
    sworn affidavit.
  

 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Rights of appellant to appear before the Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every appellant may appear before the Central Government in person or 
    through his authorised representative.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    appellant may, by writing, authorise—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   an advocate, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a Chartered 
    Accountant, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   a Cost and Works 
    Accountant, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   a Company 
    Secretary, having prescribed qualifications under clause (45) of section 2 
    of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956),
 
to function as authorised 
    representative of such party.
  

 
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Authorising a representative to appear.—In 
    an appeal any appellant, where the Form is signed by his authorised 
    representative, the appellant shall append to the Form documents authorising 
    the authorised representative to appear for him and the said document shall 
    state what his relationship is with the appellant.
  

 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Authorisation to be filed.—An 
    authorised representative appearing for the appellant at the hearing of an 
    appeal shall, unless the document referred to in rule 10 has been appended, 
    file such a document before the commencement of the hearing.
 


 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Procedure for filing appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An appeal shall be preferred by the appellant or his authorised 
    representative to the Central Government in person or be sent by Registered 
    Post addressed to the Secretary to the Government of India, Department of 
    Economic Affairs, Ministry of Finance, New Delhi.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    appeal sent by post under sub‑rule (1) shall be deemed to have been 
    preferred to the Central Government on the day on which it is received in 
    the office of the Secretary to the Government of India, Department of 
    Economic Affairs, Ministry of Finance, at Delhi.
  

 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Furnishing of information and documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, before considering the appeal, require the 
    appellant or the Board or both to furnish such further information and 
    documents as it considers necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Parties concerned shall furnish such information and documents within thirty 
    days of such order.
  

 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Date and place of hearing of appeal to be communicated.—The 
    Central Government shall communicate, before considering the appeal, to the 
    appellant or the Board or both the date and place of the hearing of the 
    appeal and may send a copy of the appeal to the Board either before or with 
    such communication.
  

 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Hearing of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On the day fixed or on any other day to which the hearing may be adjourned, 
    the appellant shall be heard in support of the appeal. The Central 
    Government shall, then, if necessary, hear the Board or its authorised 
    representa­tive against the appeal, and in such case the appellant shall be 
    entitled to reply.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    case the appellant does not appear in person or through an authorised 
    representative when the appeal is called for hearing, the Central Government 
    may dispose of the appeal on merits:
 

    Provided that where an appeal has been disposed of as provided above and the 
    appellant appears afterwards and satisfies the Central Government that there 
    was sufficient cause for his non‑appearance, when the appeal was called for 
    hearing, the Central Government shall make an order setting aside the order 
    and restore the appeal.
  

 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Order by Central Government.—The 
    Central Government shall,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   after considering 
    the appeal preferred to it under rule 3,
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   after considering 
    further documentary evidence referred to in rule 13, and
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   after giving 
    hearing under rule 15,
 
pass such orders or give 
    such directions as may be necessary or expedient to give effect to, or in 
    relation to, its orders.
  

 
 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Order to be signed and dated.—The 
    orders of the Central Government shall be in writing and shall be signed and 
    dated.
  

 
 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Order to be communicated to the party.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, after the order is signed, cause it to be 
    communicated to the appellant and the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Any person other than appellant or the Board may obtain a copy of the order 
    on depositing a sum of one hundred rupees under the head “065—Other Admn. 
    Services—Other Services—Other Receipts”.
 


 
 


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 


 
 




THE 
    DEPOSITORIES (APPEAL TO THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT) RULES, 1998
 

 
 


FORM
 


THE DEPOSITORIES 
    (APPEAL TO THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT) RULES, 1998
 


[See rule 2(d) 
    and rule 3]
 

 
 



Form of Appeal
 


From
 


(Mention the name and 
    address of the appellant here)
 


To,
 


The Secretary to the 
    Government of India,
 


Department of Economic 
    Affairs,
 


Ministry of Finance, 
    North Block,  
 


New Delhi.
 


Sir,
 


The appellant named 
    above, begs to prefer this appeal under section 23 of the Depositories Act, 
    1996 (22 of 1996) against Order No. .................................. dated 
    ............................. passed by the Securities and Exchange Board of 
    India under the said Act, and the Securities and Exchange Board of India 
    (Depositories and Participants) Regulations, 1996 on the following facts and 
    grounds:
 


FACTS
 


(Mention briefly the 
    fact of the case here. Enclose copy of the order passed by the Board and 
    copies of letters written by the appellant to Board and copies of other 
    relevant documents, if any.)*
 


GROUNDS
 


(Mention here the 
    grounds on which the appeal is made.)
 


PRAYER
 


In the light of what is 
    stated above, the appellant prays that he/she/it may be granted the 
    following relief.
 


RELIEF SOUGHT
 


(Specify the relief 
    sought)
 


The amount of rupees 
    five thousand as fees for this appeal has been deposited in 
    .................................. vide receipt No. 
    .................................... dated ..............................  
 

 
 

 
 



    Place:.............................
 



    Date:..............................
 


(Signature of the 
    Appellant or  

    his authorised representative)
 


--------------------
 


      
    * Indicate the relevant regulation if it is different than that mentioned 
    above.
 


         
    List of documents attached:
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


.
 


.
 


n
 


(Signature of the 
    Appellant or  

    his authorised representative) 

 

 
 




</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>