<act><tid>1337815</tid>
<title>[ THE CIVIL COURTS AMINS ACT, <year>1856</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1856</year> 
[ 9th May, <year>1856</year>.]
An Act to amend the Law respecting the employment of Amins by the 
Civil Courts in the Presidency of Fort William.

Preamble.-- Whereas the law by which the Civil Courts are 
authorize 1 to employ Amins upon local investigations is defective, 
and requires amendment; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It is enacted as follows:-




<article><tid>919129</tid>
<number>1</number>[ Repeal of Regulations.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1870</year> (14  
  of <year>1870</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>576403</tid>
<number>2</number>Appointment of Amins.-- In each district, officers to be 
designated Civil Court Amins shall be appointed for the purposes of 
this Act, and shall be remunerated by fixed monthly salaries.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The number of Amins to be employed in each district shall be 
determined by the State Government.]



</article>



<article><tid>1681776</tid>
<number>3</number>Amins by whom appointed and to what Courts attached.-- The 4 
[ District Judge shall from time to time attach the Civil Court 
Amins] to the several Courts of the district according as the state of 
business may require:
Provided that an Amin attached to any particular Court may, with 
the sanction of the Judge be employed occasionally by any other Court.


</article>



<article><tid>689618</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Declaration to be made by Civil Court Amins.] Rep. by the 
Indian Oaths act, <year>1873</year> (10 of <year>1873</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>192926</tid>
<number> 5</number> Duties of Amins.-- <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> The Civil Court Amins may be employed 
in any of the following duties:--
<section><tid>173134</tid>
<number>i</number>in investigating or adjusting accounts in any suit or other 
judicial proceeding;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>50</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Amending Act, <year>1897</year> (5 of <year>1897</year>).

This Act was declared, by the Laws Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year>, 
 (15 of <year>1874</year>), s. 7, to be in force in the former North- Western 
Provinces except the Scheduled Districts.

It has been declared, by notifiation under the Scheduled 
Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the scheduled 
portion of the Mirzapur District and in Jaunsar Bawar- see Gazette 
of India, <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, pp. 382- 383.

This Act has been extended to Union Territory of Pondichery 
by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Certain words were rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for the original paragraph.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The words" Subject to such general directions and restrictions as 
may from time to time be prescribed by the" Sudder Court" were 
rep. by Act 12 of <year>1873</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1295010</tid>
<number>ii</number>in making local investigations when the Court may deem 
investigation on the spot to be requisite and proper for the purpose 
of elucidating the matters in dispute, or of ascertaining the amount 
of mense profits or damages, in any suit or other judicial proceeding;

</section>

<section><tid>1759610</tid>
<number>iii</number>in delivering over possession of lands, houses and other 
immovable property, in execution of decrees or orders of Court;

</section>

<section><tid>766848</tid>
<number>iv</number>in the sale of movable property, and of houses, gardens and 
other immovable property of the kind described <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in section 3, 
Regulation 7, <year>1825</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1382235</tid>
<number>v</number>in ascertaining the sufficiency of sureties and the means of 
persons suing in forma pauperis.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>501953</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Procedure in referring accounts to Civil Court Amins.] Rep. 
by Act 10 of <year>1861</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>1180425</tid>
<number>7</number>[ Procedure in cases of local enquiry.] Rep., ibid.


</article>



<article><tid>1260842</tid>
<number>8</number>Expense of Amins how charged.-- Whenever a Civil Court Amin may 
be employed on any duty connected with a pending suit, or the 
execution of a decree, except the sale of property, the Court shall 
estimate the time which the duty may be expected to occupy, and shall 
charge for the expense of the Amin such fixed rate per diem as may be 
determined by the Sudder Court.
The amount shall be paid into Court by the party at whose 
instance or for whose benefit the Amin is deputed, and shall be added 
to the costs of suit.



</article>



<article><tid>12307</tid>
<number>9</number>When employed to sell property, deduction from proceeds.-- When 
a Civil Court Amin shall be employed to sell property, a deduction at 
the rate of one anna in the rupee shall be made from the proceeds of 
the sale.
Expenses, if no sale takes place.-- If no sale takes place by 
reason of the claim being satisfied, or for any other cause, a charge 
shall be made for the expenses of the Amin according to the time he 
may be employed.

A deposit to meet this charge, calculated in the manner 
prescribed in the preceding section, shall be made before the Amin is 
deputed, and shall be returned to the depositor if the sale takes 
place.

All sums paid for the employment of Amins, and all sums deducted 
from the proceeds of sales, shall be credited to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the revenues of 
the States].



</article>



<article><tid>1744211</tid>
<number>10</number>Poert og Civil Court, North- Western Provinces, to employ 
Revenue officers.-- Nothing contained in this Act shall be held to 
prohibit the Civil Courts in the North- Western Provinces of the 
Presidency of Fort William from making use of the agency of the 
Revenue- officer in investigations and adjustments of accounts 
connected with land paying revenue to Government <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>51</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>That is" orchards, or small portions of lakhiraj land". Ben. Reg. 
7 of <year>1825</year> was repealed by the Repealing Act, <year>1874</year> (16 of <year>1874</year>), 
but not so as to affect the provisions referred to here, see s. 
1, para, 2 of that Act.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Govt".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" under such general directions as may from time to time 
be prescribed by the" Sudder Court" were rep. by Act 12 of <year>1873</year>, 
and the words" Whenver a Tuhseeldare, a Naib Tuhseeldar of a 
Peshkar shall be employed in any such investigation or adjustment 
under the orders of a Civil Court he shall possess all the powers 
vested in Civil Court Amins by section 7 of this Act; and the 
provisions of the said section shall be applicable to the 
proceedings held by such officer" with which the section 
concluded were rep. by Act 12 of <year>1891</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>