<act><title>

The
Railway Protection Force Act, 1957 </title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called The Railway Protection Force Act, 1957. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India. 
 </section><section><number>3</number>
 It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

  
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>]
In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
 “Force” means
the Railway Protection Force constituted under
section 3;

 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>b</number>
“Director-General” means the Director-General of the Force appointed
under sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ba</number>
 “enrolled member
of the Force” means any subordinate officer, under officer or any other member
of the Force of a rank lower than that of under officer;
 </subsection><subsection><number>bb</number>
 “Force
custody” means the arrest or confinement of a member of the Force in
accordance with rules made under this Act;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “member of the Force” means a person appointed
to the Force under this Act;
 
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***];

 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>ca</number>
"passenger" shall have the meaning assigned to it in the
Railways Act, 1989 (24 of 1989);
 </subsection><subsection><number>cb</number>
"passenger area" shall include railway platform, train, yard
and such other area as is frequently visited by passengers;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
 “prescribed” means prescribed by rules
made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 “railway property” includes any goods,
money or valuable security, or animal, belonging to, or in the charge or
possession of, a railway administration;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>ea</number>
“subordinate officer” means a person appointed to the Force as an
Inspector, a Sub-Inspector or an Assistant Sub-Inspector;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
 “superior
officer” means any of the officers appointed under section 4 and includes any
other officer appointed by the Central Government as a superior officer of the
Force;
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>fa</number>
“under officer” means a person appointed to the Force as a Head
Constable or Naik;]
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
 words and
expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in the Indian Railways
Act, 1890 (9 of 1890), shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them
under that Act.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
Any reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in any area shall, in
relation to that area, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law, if
any, in force in that area.]
   












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Constitution of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number>
There shall be constituted and maintained by the Central Government 1[an
armed force of the Union] to be called the Railway Protection Force for the
better protection and security of railway property. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Force shall be constituted in such manner, shall consist of such number of <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[superior
officers, subordinate officers, under officers and other enrolled members] of
the Force and shall receive such pay and other remuneration as may prescribed. 
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Appointment and powers of superior officers.—1[
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may appoint a person to be the Director-General of the
Force and may appoint other persons to be Inspector-General, Additional
Inspectors-General, Deputy Inspectors-General, Assistant Inspectors-General,
Senior Commandants, Commandants or Assistant Commandants of the Force.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Director-General]
and every other superior officer so appointed shall possess and exercise such
powers and authority over the members of the Force under their respective
commands as is provided by or under this Act.  


   








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 
[***] 


  





 



 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>6</number>
Appointment of members of the Force.—The appointment of enrolled members
of the Force shall rest with the Inspector-General, Additional Inspector-General
or Deputy Inspector-General, who shall exercise that power in accordance with
rules made under this Act: 
 Provided
that the power of appointment under this section may also be exercised by other
superior officer as the Inspector-General, Additional Inspector-General, or
Deputy Inspector-General concerned may, by order, specify in this behalf.] 
  









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Certificates to members of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every member of the Force shall receive on his appointment a certificate in the
form specified in the Schedule, under the seal of the <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Inspector-General,
Additional Inspector-General or Deputy Inspector-General] or such other superior
officer as the <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Inspector-General,
Additional Inspector-General or Deputy Inspector-General] may specify in this
behalf, by virtue of which the person holdings such certificate shall be vested
with the powers of a member of the Force. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Such certificate shall cease to have effect whenever the person named in it
ceases for any reason to be a member of the Force <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[***].
 


   








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>8</number>
Superintendence and administration of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> The superintendence
of the Force shall vest in the Central Government, and subject thereto and to
the provisions of this Act and of any rules made thereunder, the command,
supervision and administration of the Force shall vest in the Director-General. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (1), the administration of the Force,
within such local limits in relation to a railway as may be prescribed shall be
carried on by an Inspector-General, an Additional Inspector-General or a Deputy
Inspector-General in accordance with the provisions of this Act and of any rules
made thereunder and they shall, subject to any direction that may be given by
the Central Government or the Director-General in this behalf discharge his
functions under the general supervision of the General Manager of the Railway.] 
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
Dismissal, removal, etc., of members of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to the provisions of article 311 of the Constitution and to such rules
as the Central Government may make under this Act, any superior officer may—
 <subsection><number>i</number>
 dismiss, suspend
or reduce in rank any <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[enrolled
member] of the Force whom he shall think remiss or negligent in the discharge of
his duty, or unfit for the same; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
 award any one or
more of the following punishments to any 4[enrolled
member] of the Force who discharges his duty in a careless or negligent manner,
or who by any act of his own renders himself unfit for the discharge thereof,
namely:—
 <subsubsection><number>a</number>
fine to any amount not exceeding seven days’ pay or reduction in pay scale; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number>
confinement to quarters for a period not exceeding fourteen days with or without
punishment, drill, extra guard, fatigue or other duty; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number>
removal from any office of distinction or deprivation of any special emolument. 
  
















 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>10</number>
Officers and members of the force to be deemed to be railway servants.—<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[Director-General
and every member of the Force] shall for all purposes be regarded as railway
servants within the meaning of the Indian Railways Act, 1890 (9 of 1890) other
than Chapter VIA thereof, and shall be entitled to exercise the powers conferred
on railway servants by or under that Act.

  
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>11</number>
Duties of members of Force.—It shall
be the duty of every superior officer and member of the Force—
 <section><number>a</number>
 promptly to
execute all orders lawfully issued to him by his superior authority; 
 </section><section><number>b</number>
 to protect and safeguard
railway property, passenger area and passengers; 
 </section><section><number>c</number>
 to remove any obstruction in
the movement of railway property or passenger area; and 
 </section><section><number>d</number>
 to do any other act conducive
to the better protection and security of railway property, passenger area and
passengers.]
  
  









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>12</number>
Power to arrest without warrant.—Any member of the Force may, without an
order from a Magistrate and without a warrant, arrest—
 <section><number>i</number>
 any person who voluntarily
causes hurt to, or attempts voluntarily to cause hurt to, or wrongfully
restrains or attempts wrongfully to restrain, or assaults, threatens to assault,
or uses, or threatens or attempts to use, criminal force to him or any other
member of the Force in the execution of his duty as such member, or with intent
to prevent or to deter him from discharging his duty as such member, or in
consequence of anything done or attempted to be done by him in the lawful
discharge of his duty as such member; or
 </section><section><number>ii</number>
 any person who has been
concerned in, or against whom a reasonable suspicion exists of his having been
concerned in, or who is found taking precautions to conceal his presence under
circumstances which afford reason to believe that he is taking such precautions
with a view to committing a cognizable offence which relates to <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[railway
property, passenger area and passengers]; or 
 </section><section><number>iii</number>
any person found taking precautions to conceal his presence within the
railway limits under circumstances which afford reason to believe that he is
taking such precautions with a view to committing theft of, or damage to,<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[railway property, passenger area and passengers]; or 
 </section><section><number>iv</number>
any person who commits or attempts to commit a cognizable offence which
involves or which is likely to involve imminent danger to the life of any person
engaged in carrying on any work relating to <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[railway
property, passenger area and passengers].]
   








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>13</number>
Power to search without warrant.—
<section><number>1</number>
Whenever <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[***]
any member of the Force, not below the rank of a Senior Rakshak, has reason to
believe that any such offence as is referred to in section 12 has been or is
being committed and that a search warrant cannot be obtained without affording
the offender an opportunity of escaping or of concealing evidence of the
offence, he may detain him and search his person and belongings forthwith and,
if he thinks proper, arrest any person whom he has reason to believe to have
committed the offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The provisions of the <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[Code
of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], relating to searches under that Code
shall, so far as may be, apply to searches under this section.
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>14</number>
Procedure to be followed after arrest.—Any
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[***]
member of the Force making an arrest under this Act, shall, without unnecessary
delay, make over the person so arrested <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[to
a police officer together with a detailed report of the circumstances leading to
the arrest of such person], or, in the absence of a police officer, take such
person or cause him to be taken to the nearest police station.  


   








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>15</number>
Officers and members of the Force to be considered always on duty and liable to
be employed in any part of the Railways.—<footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>
Every member of the Force shall, for the purposes of this Act, be considered to
be always on duty, and shall, at any time, be liable to be employed at any place
within India]. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[***]
member of the Force shall engage himself in any employment or office other than
his duties under this Act.  


  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>15A</number>
Restrictions respecting right to form association, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> No member of
the Force shall, without the previous sanction in writing of the Central
Government or of the prescribed authority,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
 be a member of, or be
associated in any way with, any trade union, labour union, political association
or with any class of trade unions, labour unions or political associations; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 be a member of, or be
associated in any way with, any other society, institution, association or
organisation that is not recognised as part of the Force or is not of a purely
social, recreational or religious nature; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 communicate with
the press or publish or cause to be published any book, letter or other document
except where such communication or publication is in the bona fide
discharge of his duties or is of a purely literary, artistic or scientific
character or is of a prescribed nature. 
 Explanation.—If
any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or
organisation is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature under
clause (b) of this sub-section, the decision of the Central Government thereon
shall be final.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
No member of the Force shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take
part in any demonstration organised by any body of persons for any political
purposes or for such other purposes as may be prescribed.]
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>16</number>
Responsibilities of members of the Force during suspension.—A
member of the Force shall not by reason of his suspension from office cease to
be a member of the force; and he shall, during that period, be subject to the
same responsibilities, discipline and penalties to which he would have been
subject if he were on duty. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[<number>16A</number>
Surrender of certificate, arms, etc., by persons ceasing to be members of
the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> Every person who for any reason ceases to be a member of
the Force, shall forthwith surrender to any superior officer empowered to
receive the same, his certificate of appointment, the arms, accoutrements,
clothing and other articles which have been furnished to him for the performance
of his duties as a member of the Force. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any person who wilfully neglects or refuses to surrender his certificate of
appointment, the arms, accoutrements, clothing and other articles furnished to
him, as required by sub-section (1), shall, on conviction, be punished with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one month, or with fine which may
extend to two hundred rupees, or with both. 
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Nothing in this section shall be deemed to apply to any article, which, under
the orders of the Director-General, has become the property of the person to
whom the same was furnished.] 
   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<number>17</number>
Penalties for neglect of duty, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Without prejudice to the
provisions contained in section 9, every enrolled member of the Force who shall
be guilty of any violation of duty or wilful breach or neglect of any rule or
lawful order made by a superior officer, or who shall withdraw from duties of
his office without permission, or who, being absent on leave, fails, without
reasonable cause, to report himself for duty on the expiration of the leave, or
who engages himself without authority for any employment other than his duty as
an enrolled member of the Force, or who shall be guilty of cowardice may be
taken into Force custody and shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment
which may extend to one year. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
1974), an offence punishable under this section shall be cognizable and non-bailable.

 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
1974), the Central Government may invest Assistant Inspector-General, Senior
Commandant or Commandant with the powers of a Magistrate of any class for the
purpose of inquiring into or trying any offence committed by an enrolled member
of the Force and punishable under this Act, or any offence committed by an
enrolled member of the Force against the person or property of another member of
the Force : 
 Provided
that—
 <subsection><number>i</number>
 when the offender
is on leave or absent from duty; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
 when the offence
is not connected with the offender’s duties as an enrolled member of the
Force; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
 when it is a petty
offence even if connected with the offender’s duties as an enrolled member of
the Force; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
 when, for reasons
to be recorded in writing, it is not practicable for the Commandant invested
with the powers of a Magistrate to inquire into or to try the offence, 
 the
offence may, if the prescribed authority within the limits of whose jurisdiction
the offence has been committed so requires, be inquired into or tried by an
ordinary criminal court having jurisdiction in the matter.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
Nothing contained in this section shall be construed to prevent any enrolled
member of the Force from being prosecuted under any other law for any offence
made punishable by that law, or for being liable under any such law to any other
or higher penalty or punishment than is provided for such offence by this
section : 
 Provided
that no person shall be punished twice for the same offence.]  


   








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>18</number>
Application of Act 22 of 1922 to members of the Force.—The
Police (Incitement to Disaffection) Act, 1922 shall apply to members of the
Force as it applies to members of a police force. 
   



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>19</number>
Certain Acts not to apply to members of the Force.—Nothing contained in
the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936) or the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947
(14 of 1947) or the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948) or any corresponding law
relating to investigation and settlement of industrial dispute in force in a
state shall apply to members of the Force.]  


  
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>20</number>
Protection of acts of members of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number>
In any suit or proceeding against any <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[***]
member of the Force for any act done by him in the discharge of his duties, it
shall be lawful for him to plead that such act was done by him under the orders
of a competent authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any such plea may be proved by the production of the order directing the act,
and if it is so proved, the <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[***]
member of the Force shall thereupon be discharged from any liability in respect
of that act so done by him, notwithstanding any defect in the jurisdiction of
the authority which issued such order. 
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force,
any legal proceeding, whether civil or criminal, which may lawfully be brought
against any <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[***]
member of the Force for anything done or intended to be done under the powers
conferred by, or in pursuance of, any provisions of this Act or the rules
thereunder shall be commenced within three months after the act complained of
shall have been committed and not otherwise; and notice in writing of such
proceeding and of the cause thereof shall be given to the person concerned and
his superior officer at least one month before the commencement of such
proceeding.  


   









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>21</number>
Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules
for carrying out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers,
such rules may provide for—
 <subsection> <number>a</number>
 regulating the
classes and grades and the pay and remuneration of <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[***] members of
the Force and their conditions of service in the Force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 regulating the
powers and duties of <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[***]
members of the Force authorised to exercise any functions by or under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
 fixing the period
of service for <footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[***] members of the Force; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>
prescribing the description and quantity of arms, accoutrements, clothing
and other necessary articles to be furnished to the members of the Force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
 prescribing the
places of residence of the member of the force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
 institution,
management and regulation of any fund for any purpose connected with the
administration of the force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
 regulating the
punishments and prescribing authorities to whom appeal shall be preferred from
orders of punishment, or remission of fines, or other punishments and the
procedure to be followed for the disposal of such appeals; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
 regulating matters
with respect to Force custody under this Act, including the procedure to be
followed for taking persons into such custody; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
 regulating matters
with respect to disposal of cases relating to offences under this Act and
specifying the places in which persons convicted under this Act may be confined;

 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
 any other matter which has to
be, or may be, imposed, or in respect of which rules are required to be made
under this Act.] 
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done
under that rule.]  


   











 



</section></article><form>
 

RAILWAYS PROTECTION FORCE ACT, 1957
 

 
 

THE SCHEDULE 
 
 

(See Section 7)  
 

A. B. 
has been appointed a member of the Railway Protection Force under the Railway 
Protection Force Act, 1957, and is vested with the powers, functions and 
privileges of a member of the Force.  
 

   </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Came into force on 10-9-1959, vide Notification No.
58—Security/116/9D, dated 10th September, 1959, published in the Gazette of
India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(1), dated 10th September, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Renumbered by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985). tc
"	4.	Renumbered by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985). tc
"	5. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
The words “other than a superior officer” omitted by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>
Ins. by Act 52 of 2003, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004). tc
"	7.	Ins. by Act 52 of 2003, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> 
Ins. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985). tc
"	8. 	Ins. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> 
Ins. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985). tc
"	1. 	Ins. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> 
Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985). tc
"	2. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> 
Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985). tc
"	3. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> 
Section 5 omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> 
Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> 
Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  The words “and on 
his ceasing to be a member of the Force shall be forthwith surrendered by him to 
any superior officer empowered to receive the same” omitted by Act 60 of 1985, 
sec. 8 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>
Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> 
Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985). tc
"	4. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>
 Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 18 and
Sch. (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).  tc "	2. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 18 and Sch. (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>
Subs. by Act 52 of 2003, sec. 4, for section "11. Duties of
members of the Force.—It shall be the duty of every superior officer and
member of the Force—  tc "	3.	Subs. by Act 52 of 2003,
sec. 4, for section \"11. Duties of members of the Force.—It shall
be the duty of every superior officer and member of the Force—"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>
 Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 11 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).  tc "	1. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 11 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>
Subs. by Act 52 of 2003, sec. 5, for "railway property" (w.e.f.
1-7-2004).  tc "	2.	Subs. by Act 52 of 2003,
sec. 5, for \"railway property\" (w.e.f. 1-7-2004)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>
 The words “any superior officer,
or” omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 18 and Sch. (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).  tc "	3. 	The words “any superior
officer, or” omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 18 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>
 Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 18 and
Sch. (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).  tc "	4. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 18 and Sch. (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>
 The words “superior officer or”
omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 18 and Sch. (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>
Subs. by Act 52 of 2003, sec. 6, for "to a police officer"
(w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>
 Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 12 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).  tc "	3. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 12 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>
The words “superior officer or” omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 12 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>
 Ins. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 13 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).  tc "	5. 	Ins. by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 13 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>
Ins. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).  tc "	6.	 Ins. by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 14 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>
 Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 15 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).  tc "	1. 	Subs. by Act 60 of 1985,
sec. 15 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>
 Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 16 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>
 The words “superior officers
and” omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 18 and Sch. (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>
The words “superior officer or” omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 17 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>
 The words “superior officers
and” omitted by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 20-9-1985).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>
 Subs. by Act 60 of 1985, sec. 17 (w.e.f.
20-9-1985).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>