<act><tid>1353429</tid>
<title>THE RESERVE BANK (TRANSFER TO PUBLIC OWNERSHIP) ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 62 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 23rd September <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to bring the share capital of the Reserve Bank of India into 
public ownership and to make consequential amendments in the Reserve 
Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year>.





<article><tid>714389</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Reserve Bank (Transfer  
  to Public Ownership) Act, <year>1948</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1862823</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act,--
<section><tid>1919718</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means such day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint;

</section>

<section><tid>961755</tid>
<number>b</number>" Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India as constituted by 
the principal Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>1334668</tid>
<number>c</number>" principal Act" means the Reserve Bank of India Act, 
<year>1934</year>. (2 of <year>1934</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1500290</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer of Bank shares.-
<section><tid>727053</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day-- 

<subsection><tid>263501</tid>
<number>a</number>all shares in the capital of the Bank shall by virtue of 
this Act be deemed to be transferred free of all 
trusts, liabilities and encumbrances to the Central 
Government, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1964902</tid>
<number>b</number>as full compensation therefor, the Central Government 
shall issue to every person who, immediately before the 
appointed day, is registered as the holder of any such 
shares, an amount calculated at the rate of one hundred 
and eighteen rupees and ten annas per share, in 
promissory notes of the Central Government bearing 
interest at the rate of three per centum per annum 
repayable at par on such date as may be specified in 
this behalf by the Central Government:
Provided that where the amount so calculated is 
not an exact multiple of one hundred rupees the amount 
in excess of the nearest lower multiple of one hundred 
rupees shall be paid by cheque drawn on the Bank:

Provided further that in respect of any share 
obtained at par from the Central Government by any 
Director of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st January, <year>1949</year>, see Notification No. F 3 (43)- F. I 48, dated the 
18th October, <year>1948</year> Gazette of India, <year>1948</year>, Extraordinary, p. 1657.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the Bank in pursuance of sub- section (8) of section 4 
of the principal Act as in force immediately before the 
appointed day, the said amount shall be calculated at 
the rate of one hundred rupees per share.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>339311</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the transfer of shares effected by this 
section any shareholder who, immediately before the appointed day, is 
entitled to payment of dividend on the shares held by him shall be 
entitled to receive from the Bank--

<subsection><tid>1763307</tid>
<number>a</number>all dividends accruing due on his shares in respect of 
the year ending on the 30th day of June, <year>1948</year>, or any 
preceding year remaining unpaid on the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>929939</tid>
<number>b</number>dividends calculated at the rate of four rupees per 
annum per share in respect of the period from the 1st 
day of July, <year>1948</year>, to the appointed day.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1879985</tid>
<number>4</number>Vacation of office by existing office bearers.- On the 
appointed day any person who immediately before that day was holding 
office as a Director of the Central Board otherwise than as Governor 
or Deputy Governor or as a member of a Local Board of the Bank shall 
vacate his office, and the Central Board and the Local Boards of the 
Bank shall thereafter be constituted in the manner prescribed by 
sections 8 and 9 of the principal Act as amended by this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1672491</tid>
<number>5</number>Interim arrangements.- Pending the constitution of the Central 
Board under section 8 of the principal Act as amended by this Act, the 
Governor of the Bank, or in his absence a Deputy Governor of the Bank 
duly nominated by him in this behalf, may, subject to such 
restrictions and conditions as may from time to time be imposed by the 
Central Government, exercise all powers, and do all acts and things 
which may be exercised or done by the Bank.


</article>



<article><tid>1622047</tid>
<number> 6</number> Rule- making power.-
<section><tid>1156742</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 1 for the purpose of 
giving effect to the objects of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>411535</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide--

<subsection><tid>655521</tid>
<number>a</number>for the manner in which and the authority by which 
compensation shall be paid under section 3; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1026601</tid>
<number>b</number>for the determination of persons to whom compensation is 
so payable.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1228089</tid>
<number>7</number>[ Amendment to Act II of <year>1934</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and 
Amending Act, <year>1950</year> (35 of <year>1950</year>).

</article>



 </act>