<act><title>

    THE SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE BOARD OF INDIA ACT, 1992</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall be deemed to have come into force on the 30th day of January, 1992.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “Board” means the Securities and 
    Exchange Board of India established under section 3;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “Chairman” means the Chairman of 
    the Board;  
 

1[(ba)    
    “collective investment scheme” means any scheme or arrangement which 
    satisfies the conditions specified in section 11AA;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “existing Securities and Exchange 
    Board” means the Securities and Exchange Board of India constituted under 
    the Resolution of the Government of India in the Department of Eco­nomic 
    Affairs No. 1(44)SE/86, dated the 12th day of April, 1988;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “Fund” means the Fund constituted 
    under section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “member” means a member of the 
    Board and includes the Chairman;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “notification” means a 
    notification published in the Official Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    “regulations” means the 
    regulations made by the Board under this Act;
 

2[(ha)    
    “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve Bank of India constituted under section 3 
    of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    “securities” has the meaning 
    assigned to it in section 2 of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 
    1956.
 


    3 [(2) Words and 
    expression used and not defined in this Act but defined in 

    4[the Securities 
    Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956) or the Depositories Act, 1996 
    (22 of 1996)] shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that 
    Act.]
 
 








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Establishment and incorporation of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> With effect from such date as 
      the Central Government may, by notification, appoint, there shall be 
      established, for the purposes of this Act, a Board by the name of the 
      Securities and Exchange Board of India.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, 
      having perpetual succession and a common seal, with power sub­ject to 
      the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property, both 
      movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall, by the said name, sue 
      or be sued.  
 </section><section><number>3</number>   The head office of the Board shall be at 
      Bombay.  
 </section><section><number>4</number>   The Board may establish offices at other places in 
      India.  
 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Management of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a Chairman;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    two members from 
    amongst the officials of the 
1[Minis­try] 
    of the Central Government dealing with Finance 
2[and 
    administration of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956)];  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    one member from 
    amongst the officials of 
3[the 
    Reserve Bank];  
 

4[(d)    
    five other members of whom at least three shall be the whole-time members,]  
 
to be 
    appointed by the Central Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs of the 
    Board shall vest in a Board of members, which may exercise all powers and do 
    all acts and things which may be exercised or done by the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Save 
    as otherwise determined by regulations, the Chairman shall also have powers 
    of general superintendence and direction of the affairs of the Board and may 
    also exercise all powers and do all acts and things which may be exercised 
    or done by that Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Chairman and members referred to in clauses (a) and (d) of sub-section (1) 
    shall be appointed by the Central Government and the members referred to in 
    clauses (b) and (c) of that sub-section shall be nominated by the Central 
    Government and the 

    5[Reserve Bank] 
    respectively.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Chairman and the other members referred to in clauses (a) and (d) of 
    sub-section (1) shall be persons of ability, integrity and standing who have 
    shown capacity in dealing with problems relating to securities market or 
    have special knowledge or ex­perience of law, finance, economics, 
    accountancy, administration or in any other discipline which, in the opinion 
    of the Central Government, shall be useful to the Board.  
 
 
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Term of office and conditions of service of Chairman and members 
      of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The term of office and other condi­tions of service of 
      the Chairman and the members referred to in clause (d) of sub-section (1) 
      of section 4 shall be such as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the 
      Central Government shall have the right to terminate the services of the 
      Chairman or a member appointed under clause (d) of sub-section (1) of 
      section 4, at any time before the expiry of the period prescribed under 
      sub-section (1), by giving him notice of not less than three months in 
      writing or three months’ salary and allowances in lieu thereof, and the 
      Chairman or a member, as the case may be, shall also have the right to 
      relinquish his office, at any time before the expiry of the period 
      prescribed under sub-section (1), by giving to the Central Government 
      notice of not less than three months in writing.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Removal of member from office.—1 [***] 
    The Central Government shall remove a member from office if he—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    is, or at any time has been, 
    adjudicated as insolvent;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    is of unsound mind and stands so 
    declared by a compe­tent court;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    has been convicted of an offence 
    which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves a moral turpitude;  
 

2[***]  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    has, in the opinion of the 
    Central Government, so abused his position as to render his continuation in 
    office detrimental to the public interest:  
 
Provided that no member shall be removed 
    under this clause unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
    heard in the matter.  
 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall meet at such times and places, and shall observe such rules 
    of procedure in regard to the trans­action of business at its meetings 
    (including quorum at such meetings) as may be provided regulation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairman or, if for any reason, he is unable to attend a meeting of the 
    Board, any other member chosen by the members present from amongst 
    themselves at the meeting shall preside at the meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    questions which come up before any meeting of the Board shall be decided by 
    a majority votes of the members present and voting, and, in the event of an 
    equality of votes, the Chairman or in his absence, the person presiding, 
    shall have a second or casting vote.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>7A</number> Member not to participate in 
      meetings in certain cases.—Any member, who is a director of 
      a company and who as such director has any direct or indirect pecuniary 
      interest in any matter coming up for consideration at a meeting of the 
      Board, shall, as soon as possible after relevant circumstances have come 
      to his knowledge, disclose the nature of his interest at such meeting and 
      such disclosure shall be recorded in the proceedings of the Board, and the 
      member shall not take any part in any deliberation or decision of the 
      Board with respect to that mat­ter.]  
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Vacancies etc., not to invalidate proceedings of 
      Board.—No 
      act or proceeding of the Board shall be invalid merely by reason 
      of—  
 <section><number>a</number>    any 
      vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Board; or  
 </section><section><number>b</number>    any 
      defect in the appointment of a person acting as a member of the Board; 
      or  
 </section><section><number>c</number>    any 
      irregularity in the procedure of the Board not affecting the merits of the 
      case.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Officers and employees of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board may ap­point 
      such other officers and employees as it considers necessary for the 
      efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The term and other conditions of service of officers and 
      employees of the Board appointed under sub-section (1) shall be such as 
      may be determined by regulations.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Transfer of assets, liabilities, etc., of existing Securities and Exchange 
    Board to the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On and from the date of establishment of the Board,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any reference to the existing 
    Securities and Exchange Board in any law other than this Act or in any 
    contract or other instrument shall be deemed as a reference to the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all properties and assets, 
    movable and immovable, of, or belonging to, the existing Securities and 
    Exchange Board, shall vest in the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all rights and liabilities of the 
    existing Securities and Exchange Board shall be transferred to, and be the 
    rights and liabilities of, the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    without prejudice to the 
    provisions of clause (c), all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, 
    all contracts en­tered into and all matters and things engaged to be done 
    by, with or for the existing Securities and Exchange Board immediately 
    before that date, for or in connection with the purpose of the said existing 
    Board shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into or engaged to be 
    done by, with or for, the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    all sums of money due to the 
    existing Securities and Exchange Board immediately before that date shall be 
    deemed to be due to the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    all suits and other legal 
    proceedings instituted or which could have been instituted by or against the 
    existing Securities and Exchange Board immediately before that date may be 
    continued or may be instituted by or against the Board; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    every employee holding any office 
    under the existing Securities and Exchange Board immediately before that 
    date shall hold his office in the Board by the same tenure and upon the same 
    terms and conditions of service as respects remuneration, leave, provident 
    fund, retirement and other terminal benefits as he would have held such 
    office if the Board had not been established and shall continue to do so as 
    an employee of the Board or until the expiry of the period of six months 
    from that date if such employee opts not to be the employee of the Board 
    within such period.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 
    of 1947), or in any other law for the time being in force, absorption of any 
    employee by the Board in its regular service under this section shall not 
    entitle such employee to any compen­sation under that Act or other law and 
    no such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other 
    authority.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Functions of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, it shall be the duty of the Board to 
    protect the interests of investors in securities and to promote the 
    development of, and to regulate the securities market, by such measures as 
    it thinks fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provi­sions, the 
    measures referred to therein may provide for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    regulating the 
    business in stock exchanges and any other securities markets;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    registering and 
    regulating the working of stock brokers, sub-brokers, share transfer agents, 
    bankers to an issue, trustees of trust deeds, registrars to an issue, 
    merchant ban­kers, underwriters, portfolio managers, investment advisers and 
    such other intermediaries who may be associated with securities markets in 
    any manner;  
 

1[(ba)    
    registering and regulating the working of the 
2[deposi­tories, 
    participants, custodians] of securities, foreign institutional inves­tors, 
    credit rating agencies and such other intermediaries as the Board may, by 
    notification specify in this behalf;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    registering and 
    regulating the working of 
3[venture 
    capital funds and collective investment schemes], including mutual funds;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    promoting and regulating 
    self-regulatory organisations;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    prohibiting fraudulent 
    and unfair trade practices relat­ing to securities markets;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    promoting investors’ 
    education and training of inter­mediaries of securities markets;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    prohibiting 
    insider trading in securities;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    regulating substantial 
    acquisition of shares and take-over of companies;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    calling for 
    information from, undertaking inspection, conducting inquiries and audits of 
    the 4[stock 
    exchanges, mutual funds, other persons associated with the securities 
    market] intermediar­ies and self-regulatory organisations in the securities 
    market;
 

5[(ia)    
    calling for information and record from any bank or any other authority or 
    board or corporation established or constituted by or under any Central, 
    State or Provincial Act in respect of any transaction in securities which is 
    under investigation or inquiry by the Board;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    performing such 
    functions and exercising such powers under the provisions of 
6[***] 
    and the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956), as may be 
    delegated to it by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    levying fees or other 
    charges for carrying out the purposes of this section;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    conducting research for 
    the above purposes;
 

7[(la)    
    calling from or furnishing to any such agencies, as may be specified by the 
    Board, such information as may be considered necessary by it for the 
    efficient discharge of its functions;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    performing such other 
    functions as may be prescribed.
 


    8[(2A) Without 
    prejudice to the provisions contained in sub-section (2), the Board may take 
    measures to undertake inspection of any book, or register, or other document 
    or record of any listed public company or a public company (not being 
    intermediaries referred to section 12) which intends to get its securities 
    listed on any recognized stock exchange where the Board has reasonable 
    grounds to believe that such company has been indulging in insider trading 
    or fraudulent and unfair trade practices relating to securities market.]  
 


    7[(3) Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law for the time being in force while 
    exercising the powers under 

    9[clause (i) or clause 
    (ia) of sub-section (2) or sub-section (2A)], the Board shall have the same 
    powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
    1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, 
    namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the discovery and 
    production of books of account and other documents, at such place and such 
    time as may be specified by the Board;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    summoning and 
    enforcing the attendance of persons and examine them on oath;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    inspection of 
    any books, registers and other documents of any person referred to in 
    section 12, at any place.]  
 

8[(iv)    
    inspection of any book, or register, or other document or record of the 
    company referred to in section (2A);  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    issuing 
    commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents.]  
 


    8[(4) Without 
    prejudice to the provisions contained in sub-sections (1), (2), (2A) and (3) 
    and section 11B, the Board may, by an order, for reasons to be recorded in 
    writing, in the interests of investors or securities market, take any of the 
    following measures, either pending investigation or inquiry or on completion 
    of such investigation or inquiry, namely:—  
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>    suspend the 
    trading of any security in a recognized stock exchange;  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>    restrain persons 
    from accessing the securities market and prohibit any person associated with 
    securities market to buy, sell or deal in securities;  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>c</number>    suspend any 
    office-bearer of any stock exchange or self-regulatory organisation from 
    holding such position;  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>d</number>    impound and retain 
    the proceeds or securities in respect of any transaction which is under 
    investigation;  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>e</number>    attach after 
    passing of an order on an application made for approval, by the Judicial 
    Magistrate of first class having jurisdiction, for a period not exceeding 
    one month, one or more bank account or accounts of any intermediary or any 
    person associated with the securities market in any manner involved in 
    violation of any of the provisions of this Act, or the rules or the 
    regulations made thereunder:  
 
Provided that only the bank account or 
    accounts or any transaction entered therein, so far as it relates to the 
    proceeds actually involved in violation of any of the provisions of this 
    Act, or the rules or the regulations made thereunder shall be allowed to be 
    attached.  
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>f</number>    direct any 
    intermediary or any person associated with the securities market in any 
    manner not to dispose of or alienate an asset forming part of any 
    transaction which is under investigation:  
 
Provided that the Board may, without 
    prejudice to the provisions contained in sub-section (2) or sub-section 
    (2A), take any of the measures specified in clause (d) or clause (e) or 
    clause (f), in respect of any listed public company or a public company (not 
    being intermediaries referred to in section 12) which intends to get its 
    securities listed on any recognised stock exchange where the Board has 
    reasonable grounds to believe that such company has been indulging in 
    insider trading or fraudulent and unfair trade practices relating to 
    securities market:  
 
Provided further that the Board shall, 
    either before or after passing such orders, give an opportunity of hearing 
    to such intermediaries or persons concerned.]  
 
 
 












 



</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11A</number> Board to 
    regulate or prohibit issue of prospectus, offer document or advertisement 
    soliciting money for issue of securities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), 
    the Board may, for the protection of investors,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    specify, by regulations—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the matters relating to issue of 
    capital, transfer of securities and other matters incidental thereto; and
    
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the manner in which such matters 
    shall be disclosed by the companies;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    by general or special orders—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    prohibit any company from issuing 
    of prospectus, any offer document, or advertisement soliciting money from 
    the public for the issue of securities;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    specify the conditions subject 
    to which the prospectus, such offer document or advertisement, if not 
    prohibited, may be issued.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the provisions of section 21 of the Securities Contracts 
    (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956), the Board may specify the requirements 
    for listing and transfer of securities and other matters incidental 
    thereto.]
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11AA</number> Collective 
    investment scheme.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any scheme or ar­rangement which satisfies the conditions referred to in 
    sub-section (2) shall be a collective investment scheme.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    scheme or arrangement made or offered by any company under which,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the contributions, or payment 
    made by the investors, by whatever name called, are pooled and utilized for 
    the purposes of the scheme or arrangement;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the contributions or payments 
    are made to such scheme or arrangement by the investors with a view to 
    receive profits, income, produce or property, whether movable or immovable, 
    from such scheme or arrangement;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the property, contribution or 
    investment forming part of scheme or arrangement, whether identifiable or 
    not, is managed on behalf of the investors;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    the investors do not have 
    day-to-day control over the management and operation of the scheme or 
    arrangement.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (2), any scheme or 
    arrangement—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    made or offered by a co-operative 
    society registered under the Co-operative Societies Act, 1912 (2 of 1912) or 
    a society being a society registered or deemed to be registered under any 
    law relating to co-operative societies for the time being in force in any 
    State;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    under which deposits are 
    accepted by non-banking finan­cial companies as defined in clause (f) of 
    section 45-I of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    being a contract of insurance 
    to which the In­surance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938), applies;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    providing for any scheme, 
    pension scheme or the in­surance scheme framed under the Employees’ 
    Provident Funds and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1952 (19 of 1952);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    under which deposits are accepted 
    under section 58A of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>    under which deposits are 
    accepted by a company declared as a Nidhi or a Mutual Benefit Society 
    under section 620A of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    falling within the meaning of 
    chit business as defined in clause (e) of section 2 of the Chit Funds Act, 
    1982 (40 of 1982);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>    under which contributions made 
    are in the nature of subscription to a mutual fund,  
 
shall not be 
    collective investment scheme.]
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11B</number> Power to 
    issue directions.—Save as otherwise provided in section 11, if after 
    making or causing to be made an enquiry, the Board is satisfied that it is 
    necessary—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    in the interest of 
    investors, or orderly development of securities market; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    to prevent the 
    affairs of any intermediary or other persons referred to in section 12 being 
    conducted in a manner detrimental to the interests of investors or 
    securities market; or  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    to secure the 
    proper management of any such inter­mediary or person,  
 
it may 
    issue such directions,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to any person or 
    class of persons referred to in sec­tion 12, or associated with the 
    securities market; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to any company in 
    respect of matters specified in section 11A,  
 
as may 
    be appropriate in the interests of investors in securities and the 
    securities market.]  
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11C</number> 
    Investigation.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Board has reasonable ground to believe 
    that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the transactions 
    in securities are being dealt with in a manner detrimental to the investors 
    or the securities market; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any intermediary 
    or any person associated with the securities market has violated any of the 
    provisions of this Act or the rules or the regulations made or directions 
    issued by the Board thereunder,  
 
it may, 
    at any time by order in writing, direct any person (hereafter in this 
    section referred to as the Investigating Authority) specified in the order 
    to investigate the affairs of such intermediary or persons associated with 
    the securities market and to report thereon to the Board.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of sections 235 to 241 of the Companies 
    Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), it shall be the duty of every manager, managing 
    director, officer and other employee of the company and every intermediary 
    referred to in section 12 or every person associated with the securities 
    market to preserve and to produce to the Investigating Authority or any 
    person authorized by him in this behalf, all the books, registers, other 
    documents and record of, or relating to, the company or, as the case may be, 
    of or relating to, the intermediary or such person, which are in their 
    custody or power.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Investigating Authority may require any intermediary or any person 
    associated with securities market in any manner to furnish such information 
    to, or produce such books, or registers, or other documents, or record 
    before him or any person authorised by it in this behalf as it may consider 
    necessary if the furnishing of such information or the production of such 
    books, or registers, or other documents, or record is relevant or necessary 
    for the purposes of its investigation.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Investigating Authority may keep in its custody any books, registers, other 
    documents and record produced under sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) for 
    six months and thereafter shall return the same to any intermediary or any 
    person associated with securities market by whom or on whose behalf the 
    books, registers, other documents and record are produced:  
 
Provided 
    that the Investigating Authority may call for any book, register, other 
    document and record if they are needed again:  
 
Provided 
    further that if the person on whose behalf the books, registers, other 
    documents and records are produced requires certified copies of the books, 
    registers, other documents and record produced before the Investigating 
    Authority, it shall give certified copies of such books, registers, other 
    documents and record to such person or on whose behalf the books, registers, 
    other documents and records were produced.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    person, directed to make an investigation under sub-section (1),  may 
    examine on oath, any manager, managing director, officer and other employee 
    of any intermediary or any person associated with securities market in any 
    manner, in relation to the affairs of his business and may administer an 
    oath accordingly and for that purpose may require any of those persons to 
    appear before him personally.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If 
    any person fails without reasonable cause or refuses—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to produce to the 
    Investigating Authority or any person authorised by it in this behalf any 
    book, register, other document and record which is in his duty under 
    sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) to produce; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to furnish any 
    information which is his duty under sub-section (3) to furnish; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to appear before 
    the Investigating Authority personally when required to do so under 
    sub-section (5) or to answer any question which is put to him by the 
    Investigating Authority in pursuance of that sub-section; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    to sign the notes 
    of any examination referred to in sub-section (7),  
 
he shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or 
    with fine, which may extend to one crore rupees, or with both, and also with 
    a further fine which may extend to five lakh rupees for every day after the 
    first during which the failure or refusal continues.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Notes of any examination under sub-section (5) shall be taken down in 
    writing and shall be read over to, or by, and signed by, the person 
    examined, and may thereafter be used in evidence against him.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> 
    Where in the course of investigation, the Investigating Authority has 
    reasonable ground to believe that the books, registers, other documents and 
    record of, or relating to, any intermediary or any person associated with 
    securities market in any manner, may be destroyed, mutilated, altered, 
    falsified or secreted, the Investigating Authority may make an application 
    to the Judicial Magistrate of the first class having jurisdiction for an 
    order for the seizure of such books, registers, other documents and record.  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> 
    After considering the application and hearing the Investigating Authority, 
    if necessary, the Magistrate may, by order, authorise the Investigating 
    Authority—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to enter, with 
    such assistance, as may be required, the place or places where such books, 
    registers, other documents and record are kept;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to search that 
    place or those places in the manner specified in the order; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to seize books, 
    registers, other documents and record, it considers necessary for the 
    purposes of the investigation:  
 
Provided 
    that the Magistrate shall not authorise seizure of books, registers, other 
    documents and record, of any listed public company or a public company (not 
    being the intermediaries specified under section 12) which intends to get 
    its securities listed on any recognised stock exchange unless such company 
    indulges in insider trading or market manipulation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    Investigating Authority shall keep in its custody the books, registers, 
    other documents and record seized under this section for such period not 
    later than the conclusion of the investigation as it considers necessary and 
    thereafter shall return the same to the company or the other body corporate, 
    or, as the case may be, to the managing director or the manager or any other 
    person, from whose custody or power they were seized and inform the 
    Magistrate of such return:  
 
Provided 
    that the Investigating Authority may, before returning such books, 
    registers, other documents and record as aforesaid, place identification 
    marks on them or any part thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided in this section, every search or seizure made 
    under this section shall be carried out in accordance with the provisions of 
    the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) relating to searches or 
    seizures made under that Code.]  
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>11D</number> Cease and 
    desist proceedings.—If the Board finds, after causing an inquiry to be 
    made, that any person has violated, or is likely to violate, any provisions 
    of this Act, or any rules or regulations made thereunder, it may pass an 
    order requiring such person to cease and desist from committing or causing 
    such violation:  
 
Provided that 
    the Board shall not pass such order in respect of any listed public company 
    or a public company (other than the intermediaries specified under section 
    12) which intends to get its securities listed on any recognised stock 
    exchange unless the Board has reasonable grounds to believe that such 
    company has indulged in insider trading or market manipulation.]
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Registration of stock-brokers, sub-brokers, share transfer agents, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No stock-broker, sub-broker, share transfer agent, banker to an issue, 
    trustee of trust deed, registrar to an issue, merchant banker, underwriter, 
    portfolio manager, investment advi­ser and such other intermediary who may 
    be associated with secu­rities market shall buy, sell or deal in securities 
    except under, and in accordance with, the conditions of a certificate of 
    regis­tration obtained from the Board in accordance with the 

    1[regula­tions] made 
    under this Act:  
 
Provided 
    that a person buying or selling securities or otherwise dealing with the 
    securities market as a stock-broker, sub-broker, share transfer agent, 
    banker to an issue, trustee of trust deed, registrar to an issue, merchant 
    banker, underwriter, portfolio manager, investment adviser and such other 
    intermediary who may be associated with securities market immediately before 
    the establishment of the Board for which no registration certificate was 
    necessary prior to such establishment, may continue to do so for a period of 
    three months from such establishment or, if he has made an application for 
    such registration within the said period of three months, till the disposal 
    of such application:  
 


    2[Provided further 
    that any certificate of registration, ob­tained immediately before the 
    commencement of the Securities Laws (Amendment) Act, 1995, shall be deemed 
    to have been obtained from the Board in accordance with the regulations 
    providing for such registration.]  
 


    2[(1A) No 


    3[depository, 
    participant, custodian] of securities, foreign institutional investor, 
    credit rating agency or any other intermediary associated with the 
    securities market as the Board may by notification in this behalf specify, 
    shall buy or sell or deal in securities except under and in accordance with 
    the condi­tions of a certificate of registration obtained from the Board in 
    accordance with the regulations made under this Act:  
 
Provided 
    that a person buying or selling securities or otherwise dealing with the 
    securities market as a 

    3[depository, 
    participant, custodian] of securities, foreign institutional investor or 
    credit rating agency immediately before the commencement of the Securities 
    Laws (Amendment) Act, 1995, for which no certificate of registration was 
    required prior to such commencement, may continue to buy or sell securities 
    or otherwise deal with the securities market until such time regulations are 
    made under clause (d) of sub-section (2) of section 30.  
 </section><section>
<number>1B</number> No 
    person shall sponsor or cause to be sponsored or carry on or cause to be 
    carried on any venture capital funds or collective investment scheme 
    including mutual funds, unless he obtains a certificate of registration from 
    the Board in accordance with the regulations:  
 
Provided 
    that any person sponsoring or cause to be sponsored, carrying or causing to 
    be carried on any venture capital funds or collective investment scheme 
    operating in the securities market immediately before the commencement of 
    the Securities Laws (Amend­ment) Act, 1995 for which no certificate of 
    registration was required prior to such commencement, may continue to 
    operate till such time regulations are made under clause (d) of sub-section 
    (2) of section 30.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every application for registration shall be in such manner and on payment of 
    such fees as may be determined by regulations.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Board may, by order, suspend or cancel a certificate of registration in such 
    manner as may be determined by regulations:  
 
Provided that 
    no order under this sub-section shall be made unless the person concerned 
    has been given a reasonable opportun­ity of being heard.
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>12A</number> 
    Prohibition of manipulative and deceptive devices, insider trading and 
    substantial acquisition of securities or control.—No 
    person shall directly or indirectly—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    use or employ, in 
    connection with the issue, purchase or sale of any securities listed or 
    proposed to be listed on a recognised stock exchange, any manipulative or 
    deceptive device or contrivance in contravention of the provisions of this 
    Act or the rules or the regulations made thereunder;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    employ any device, 
    scheme or artifice to defraud in connection with issue or dealing in 
    securities which are listed or proposed to be listed on a recognised stock 
    exchange;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    engage in any act, 
    practice, course of business which operates or would operate as fraud or 
    deceit upon any person, in connection with the issue, dealing in securities 
    which are listed or proposed to be listed on a recognised stock exchange, in 
    contravention of the provisions of this Act or the rules or the regulations 
    made thereunder;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    engage in insider 
    trading;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    deal in securities 
    while in possession of material or non-public information or communicate 
    such material or non-public information to any other person, in a manner 
    which is in contravention of the provisions of this Act or the rules or the 
    regulations made thereunder;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    acquire control of 
    any company or securities more than the percentage of equity share capital 
    of a company whose securities are listed or proposed to be listed on a 
    recognised stock exchange in contravention of the regulations made under 
    this Act.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Grants by the Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, make to the Board grants of such sums of money as that 
    Government may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be constituted a Fund to be called the Securities and Exchange 
    Board of India General Fund and there shall be credited thereto—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all grants, fees and charges 
    received by the Board under this Act; 
1[***]  
 

2[***]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all sums received by the Board 
    from such other sources as may be decided upon by the Central Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Fund shall be applied for meeting—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the salaries, allowances and 
    other remuneration of the members, officers, and other employees of the 
    Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the expenses of the Board in the 
    discharge of its functions under section 11;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the expenses on objects and for 
    purposes authorised by this Act.  
 
 
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by 
    the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Board shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India at such intervals as may be speci­fied by him and 
    any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by 
    the Board to the Comptroller and Audi­tor-General of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any other person appointed by 
    him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the Board shall have the 
    same rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit as 
    the Comptroller and Auditor-General generally has in connection with the 
    audit of the Government accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to 
    demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other 
    documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the Board as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of 
    India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf together with the 
    audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government 
    and that Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House of 
    Parliament.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15A</number> 
    Penalty for failure to furnish information, return, etc.—If 
    any person, who is required under this Act or any rules or regu­lations made 
    thereunder,—  
 <section>
               
    <number>a</number>    to furnish any document, return or report to the 
    Board, fails to furnish the same, he shall be liable to 
1[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less];  
 </section><section>
               
    <number>b</number>    to file any return or furnish any information, books 
    or other documents within the time specified therefor in the regula­tions, 
    fails to file return or furnish the same within the time specified therefor 
    in the regulations, he shall be liable to 
2[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less];  
 </section><section>
               
    <number>c</number>    to maintain books of account or records, fails to 
    maintain the same, he shall be liable to 
3[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less].  
 
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15B</number> 
    Penalty for failure by any person to enter into agreement with clients.—If 
    any person, who is registered as an intermedi­ary and is required under this 
    Act or any rules or regulations made thereunder to enter into an agreement 
    with his client, fails to enter into such agreement, he shall be liable to
    

    1[a penalty of one 
    lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore 
    rupees, whichever is less].
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    *1[<number>15C</number> Penalty for 
    failure to redress investors’ grievances.—If any listed company or any 
    person who is registered as an intermediary, after having been called upon 
    by the Board in writing, to redress the grievances of investors, fails to 
    redress such grievances within the time specified by the Board, such company 
    or intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day 
    during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.]
 
 
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    *1[<number>15C</number> Penalty for 
    failure to redress investors’ grievances.—If any listed company or any 
    person who is registered as an intermediary, after having been called upon 
    by the Board in writing, to redress the grievances of investors, fails to 
    redress such grievances within the time specified by the Board, such company 
    or intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day 
    during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.]
 
 
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15D</number> 
    Penalty for certain defaults in case of mutual funds.—If 
    any person, who is—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    required under 
    this Act or any rules or regulations made thereunder to obtain a certificate 
    of registration from the Board for sponsoring or carrying on any collective 
    investment scheme, including mutual funds, sponsors or carries on any 
    collective investment scheme, including mutual funds, without obtaining such 
    certificate of registration, he shall be liable to 
1[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which he sponsers or carries 
    on any collective investment scheme including mutual funds or one crore 
    rupees, whichever is less];  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    registered with 
    the Board as a collective investment scheme, including mutual funds, for 
    sponsoring or carrying on any investment scheme, fails to comply with the 
    terms and conditions of certificate of registration, he shall be liable to
    2[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less];  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    registered with 
    the Board as a collective investment scheme including mutual funds, fails to 
    make an application for listing of its schemes as provided for in the 
    regulation govern­ing such listing, he shall be liable to 
3[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less];  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    registered as a 
    collective investment scheme, including mutual funds, fails to despatch unit 
    certificates of any scheme in the manner provided in the regulation 
    governing such despatch, he shall be liable to 
4[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less];  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    registered as a 
    collective investment scheme, including mutual funds, fails to refund the 
    application monies paid by the investors within the period specified in the 
    regulations, he shall be liable to 
4[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less];  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    registered as a 
    collective investment scheme, including mutual funds, fails to invest money 
    collected by such collective investment schemes in the manner or within the 
    period specified in the regulations, he shall be liable to 
5[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less].  
 
 

  











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15E</number> 
    Penalty for failure to observe rules and regulations by an asset management 
    company.—Where 
    any asset management company of a mutual fund registered under this Act 
    fails to comply with any of the regulations providing for restrictions on 
    the activities of the asset management companies, such asset management 
    company shall be liable to 

    1[a penalty of one 
    lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore 
    rupees, whichever is less].  
 
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15F</number> 
    Penalty for default in case of stock brokers.—If 
    any person, who is registered as a stock broker under this Act,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    fails to issue 
    contract notes in the form and manner specified by the stock exchange of 
    which such broker is a member, he shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding 
    five times the amount for which the contract note was required to be issued 
    by that broker;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    fails to deliver 
    any security or fails to make payment of the amount due to the investor in 
    the manner within the period specified in the regulations, he shall be 
    liable to 
1[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
    or one crore rupees, whichever is less].  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    charges an amount 
    of brokerage which is in excess of the brokerage specified in the 
    regulations, he shall be liable to 
2[a 
    penalty of one lakh rupees] or five times the amount of brokerage charged in 
    excess of the specified brokerage, whichever is higher.  
 
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15G</number> 
    Penalty for insider trading.—If 
    any insider who,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    either on his own 
    behalf or on behalf of any other person, deals in securities of a body 
    corporate listed on any stock exchange on the basis of any unpublished price 
    sensitive information; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    communicates any 
    unpublished price sensitive informa­tion to any person, with or without his 
    request for such informa­tion except as required in the ordinary course of 
    business or under any law; or  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    counsels, or 
    procures for any other person to deal in any securities of any body 
    corporate on the basis of unpub­lished price sensitive information,  
 
shall be 
    liable to a penalty 

    1[of twenty-five crore 
    rupees or three times the amount of profits made out of insider trading, 
    whichever is higher].  
 
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15H</number> 
    Penalty for non-disclosure of acquisition of shares and take-overs.—If 
    any person, who is required under this Act or any rules or regulations made 
    thereunder, fails to—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    disclose the 
    aggregate of his share holding in the body corporate before he acquires any 
    shares of that body corporate; or  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    make a public 
    announcement to acquire shares at a minimum price,  
 

1[(iii)    
    make a public offer by sending letter of offer to the shareholders of the 
    concerned company; or  
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    make payment of 
    consideration to the shareholders who sold their shares pursuant to letter 
    of offer,]  
 
he shall be liable to a penalty 
2[of 
    twenty-five crore rupees or three times the amount of profits made out of 
    such failure, whichever is higher].  
 


 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>15HA</number> Penalty for 
    fraudulent and unfair trade practices.—If any person indulges in 
    fraudulent and unfair trade practices relating to securities, he shall be 
    liable to a penalty of twenty-five crore rupees or three times the amount of 
    profits made out of such practices, whichever is higher.]
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>15HB</number> Penalty for 
    contravention where no separate penalty has been provided.—Whoever fails 
    to comply with any provision of this Act, the rules or the regulations made 
    or directions issued by the Board thereunder for which no separate penalty 
    has been provided, shall be liable to a penalty which may extend to one 
    crore rupees.]  
 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    *<number>15-I</number> Power to adjudicate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of adjudging under sections 15A, 15B, 15C, 15D, 15E, 15F, 
    15G 

    1[15H, 15HA and 15HB], 
    the Board shall appoint any officer not below the rank of a Division Chief 
    to be an adjudicating officer for holding an inquiry in the prescribed 
    manner after giving any person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being 
    heard for the purpose of imposing any penal­ty.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    While holding an inquiry the adjudicating officer shall have power to summon 
    and enforce the attendance of any person ac­quainted with the facts and 
    circumstances of the case to give evidence or to produce any document which 
    in the opinion of the adjudicating officer, may be useful for or relevant to 
    the sub­ject matter of the inquiry and if, on such inquiry, he is satis­fied 
    that the person has failed to comply with the provisions of any of the 
    sections specified in sub-section (1), he may impose such penalty as he 
    thinks fit in accordance with the provisions of any of those sections.
 
 
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15J</number> 
    Factors to be taken into account by the adjudicating offi­cer.—While 
    adjudging the quantum of penalty under section 15-I, the adjudicating 
    officer shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the amount of 
    disproportionate gain or unfair advan­tage, wherever quantifiable, made as a 
    result of the default;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the amount of loss 
    caused to an investor or group of investors as a result of the default;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    the repetitive 
    nature of the default.]  
 
 
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>15JA</number> Crediting 
    sums realised by way of penalties to Consolidated Fund of India.—All 
    sums realised by way of penalties under this Act shall be credited to the 
    Consolidated Fund of India.]
 
 







 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>15K</number> Establishment of Securities Appellate Tribunals. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall by notification, establish one or more Appellate Tribunals to be known as the Securities Appellate Trib­unal to exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority con­ferred on such Tribunal by or under this Act <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[or any other law for the time being in force]. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall also specify in the notification referred to in sub-section (1) the matters and places in rela­tion to which the Securities Appellate Tribunal may exercise jurisdiction. ]



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[</title> <title><number>15L</number> Composition of Securities Appellate Tribunal. </title>—A Securities Appellate Tribunal shall consist of a Presiding Officer and two other members, to be appointed, by notification, by the Central Government: 
 Provided that the Securities Appellate Tribunal, consisting of one person only, established before the commencement of the Securities and Exchange Board of India (Amendment) Act, 2002, shall continue to exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on it by or under this Act or any other law for the time being in force till two other Members are appointed under this section.]] 



 
 <section><number>a</number> is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; or
 </section><section><number>b</number> has been a member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in Grade 
    I of that Service for at least three years; or
 </section><section><number>c</number> has held office as the Presiding Officer of a Tribunal for at least three years.” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002).
</section>
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    *1[<number>15M</number> 
    Qualification for appointment as Presiding Officer or Member of Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> A person shall not be qualified for appointment 
    as the Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate Tribunal unless he is a 
    sitting or retired Judge of the Supreme Court or a sitting or retired Chief 
    Justice of a High Court:  
 
Provided 
    that the Presiding Officer of the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall be 
    appointed by the Central Government in consultation with the Chief Justice 
    of India or his nominee.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as Member of a Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal unless he is a person of ability, integrity and standing 
    who has shown capacity in dealing with problems relating to securities 
    market and has qualification and experience of corporate law, securities 
    laws, finance, economics or accountancy:  
 
Provided that 
    a member of the Board or any person holding a post at senior management 
    level equivalent to Executive Director in the Board shall not be appointed 
    as Presiding Officer or Member of a Securities Appellate Tribunal during his 
    service or tenure as such with the Board or within two years from the date 
    on which he ceases to hold office as such in the Board.]
 
 
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    *1[<number>15N</number> Tenure of 
    office of Presiding Officer and other Members of Securities Appellate 
    Tribunal.—The Presiding Officer and every other Member of a Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal shall hold office for a term of five years from the date 
    on which he enters upon his office and shall be eligible for re-appointment:  
 
Provided 
    that no person shall hold office as the Presiding Officer of the Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal after he has attained the age of sixty-eight years:  
 
Provided 
    further that no person shall hold office as a Member of the Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal after he has attained the age of sixty-two years.]  
 
 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

    *<number>15-O</number> Salary and allowances and other terms and conditions of service of 
    Presiding Officer—The 
    salary and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of 
    service (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, the
    

    1[Presiding Officer 
    and other Members of a Securities Appellate Tribunal] shall be such as may 
    be pre­scribed:  
 
Provided 
    that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the 

    2[Presiding Officer 
    and other Members of a Securities Appellate Tribunal] shall be varied to 
    their disadvantage after appointment.
 
 
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15P</number> 
    Filling up of vacancies.—If, 
    for reason other than tempo­rary absence, any vacancy occurs in 


    1[the office of the 
    Presiding Officer or any other Member,] of a Securities Appellate Tribunal, 
    then the Central Government shall appoint another person in accordance with 
    the provisions of this Act to fill the vacancy and the proceedings may be 
    continued before the Securities Appellate Tribunal from the stage at which 
    the vacancy is filled.
 
 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15Q</number> 
    Resignation and removal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The 

    1[Presiding Officer or 
    any other Member of a Securities Appellate Tribunal] may, by notice in 
    writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government, resign his 
    office:  
 
Provided 
    that 

    2[the Presiding 
    Officer or any other Member] shall, unless he is permitted by the Central 
    Government to relinquish his office sooner, continue to hold office until 
    the expiry of three months from the date of receipt of such notice or until 
    a person duly appointed as his successor enters upon his office or until the 
    expiry of his term of office, whichever is the earliest.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The
    

    3[Presiding Officer or 
    any other Member] of a Securities Appellate Tribunal shall not be removed 
    from his office except by an order by the Central Government on the ground 
    of proved misbehaviour or inca­pacity after an inquiry made by a Judge of 
    the Supreme Court, in which the 

    3[Presiding Officer or 
    any other Member] concerned has been informed of the charges against him and 
    given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of these charges.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for the 
    investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of 

    4[the Presiding 
    Officer or any other Member].  
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15R</number> 
    Orders constituting Appellate Tribunal to be final and not to invalidate its 
    proceedings.—No 
    order of the Central Govern­ment appointing any person as the 

    1[Presiding Officer or 
    a Member] of a Securi­ties Appellate Tribunal shall be called in question in 
    any manner, and no act or proceeding before a Securities Appellate Tribunal 
    shall be called in question in any manner on the ground merely of any defect 
    in the constitution of a Securities Appellate Tribun­al.
 
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>*<number>15S</number> Staff of the Securities Appellate 
      Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall provide the Securities Appellate 
      Tribunal with such officers and employees as that Government may think 
      fit.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> The officers and employees of the Securities Appellate 
      Trib­unal shall discharge their functions under general 
      superinten­dence of the Presiding Officer.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of 
      the officers and employees of the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall be 
      such as may be prescribed.
  



 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>*<number>15T</number> Appeal to the Securities Appellate 
      Tribunal.—1[
<section><number>1</number> Save as provided in 
      sub-section (2), any person aggrieved,—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>    by an 
      order of the Board made, on and after the com­mencement of the 
      Securities Laws (Second Amendment) Act, 1999, under this Act, or the rules 
      or regulations made thereunder, or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    by an 
      order made by an adjudicating officer under this Act, 
 
 may prefer an appeal to a Securities Appellate Tribunal having 
      jurisdiction in the matter.]  
 2 [(2) No appeal shall lie to the 
      Securities Appellate Tribunal from an order made—  
 </subsection><subsection><number>a</number>    by the Board 
      on and after the commencement of the Secu­rities Laws (Second 
      Amendment) Act, 1999;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    by an 
      adjudicating officer,  
 with the consent of the parties.]  
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal under sub-section (1) shall be filed within a 
      period of forty-five days from the date on which 3[a copy of the order made by the 
      Board or the adjudicating officer, as the case may be,] is received by him 
      and it shall be in such form and be accompanied by such fee as may be 
      prescribed:
 Provided that the Securities Appellate Tribunal may entertain an 
      appeal after the expiry of the said period of forty-five days if it is 
      satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing it within that 
      period.  
 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of an appeal under sub-section (1), the Securities 
      Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the appeal, an 
      opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, 
      confirming, modifying or setting aside the order appealed 
      against.  
 </section><section><number>5</number>   The Securities Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy 
      of every order made by it to the 4[Board, the parties] to the appeal 
      and to the concerned adjudicating officer.  
 </section><section><number>6</number>   The appeal filed before the Securities Appellate 
      Tribunal under sub-section (1) shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously 
      as possible and endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the appeal 
      finally within six months from the date of receipt of the 
      appeal.  
 
  







 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>15U</number> Procedure and Powers of the Securities Appellate 
Tribunal:</title>— 
<section><number>1</number> The Securities Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by 
the procedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1980), but 
shall be guided by the principles of natural justice and, subject to the other 
provisions of this Act and of any rules, the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall 
have powers to regulate their own procedure including the places at which they 
shall have their sittings. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Securities Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of 
discharging their functions 4 [under this Act or any other law for the time 
being in force], the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code 
of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely:— 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining 
    him on oath; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> requiring the discovery and production of documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> receiving evidence on affidavits; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents; 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> reviewing its decisions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> dismissing an application for default or deciding it ex parte 
    ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> setting aside any order of dismissal of any application for default 
    or any order passed by it ex parte ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> any other matter which may be prescribed. </subsection>
 </section><section>  <number>3</number> Every proceeding before the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall be 
deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228, 
and for the purposes of section 196, of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and 
the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for all 
the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
1973 (2 of 1974).]





</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>*1[<number>15V</number> Right to legal 
      representation.—The appellant may either appear in person or authorise 
      one or more chartered accountants or company secretaries or cost 
      accountants or legal practitioners or any of its officers to present his 
      or its case before the Securities Appellate Tribunal.  
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
      section,—  
 <section><number>a</number>    “chartered 
      accountant” means a chartered accountant as defined in clause (b) of 
      sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 
      1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) 
      of section 6 of that Act;
 </section><section><number>b</number>    “company 
      secretary” means a company secretary as de­fined in clause (c) of 
      sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Company Secretaries Act, 1980 (56 of 
      1980) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) 
      of section 6 of that Act;
 </section><section><number>c</number>    “cost 
      accountant” means a cost accountant as defined in clause (b) of 
      sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 
      (23 of 1959) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under 
      sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;  
 </section><section><number>d</number>    “legal 
      practitioner” means an advocate, vakil or an attorney of any High 
      Court, and includes a pleader in practice.]  
  
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>15W</number> 
    Limitation.—The 
    provisions of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), shall as far as may be, 
    apply to an appeal made to a Securities Ap­pellate Tribunal.
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
*<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>15X</number> 
    Presiding Officer, Members and Staff of Securities Appellate Tribunals to be 
    public servants.—The Presiding Officer, Members and other officers and 
    employees of a Securities Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be public 
    servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Panel Code (45 of 
    1860).]
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>*<number>15Y</number> Civil court not to have jurisdiction.—No civil court shall have 
      jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in respect of any matter 
      which an adjudicating officer appointed under this Act or a Securities 
      Appellate Tribunal constituted under this Act is empowered by or under 
      this Act to determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court or 
      other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance 
      of any power conferred by or under this Act.  
 
  



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
*<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>15Z</number> 
    Appeal to Supreme Court.—Any person aggrieved by any decision or order 
    of the Securities Appellate Tribunal may file an appeal to the Supreme Court 
    within sixty days from the date of communication of the decision or order of 
    the Securities Appellate Tribunal to him on any question of law arising out 
    of such order:
 
Provided 
    that the Supreme Court may, if it is satisfied that the applicant was 
    prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, 
    allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days.]
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Power to Central Government to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[this Act or 
    the Deposi­tories Act, 1996], the Board shall, in exercise of its powers or 
    the performance of its functions under this Act, be bound by such directions 
    on questions of policy as the Central Government may give in writing to it 
    from time to time:  
 
Provided 
    that the Board shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity to 
    express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of policy or 
    not shall be final.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Power of Central Government to supersede the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time the Central Government is of opinion—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that on account of 
    grave emergency, the Board is unable to discharge the functions and duties 
    imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the Board has 
    persistently made default in comply­ing with any direction issued by the 
    Central Government under this Act or in the discharge of the functions and 
    duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act and as a result 
    of such default the financial position of the Board or the administra­tion 
    of the Board has deteriorated; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that circumstances 
    exist which render it necessary in the public interest so to do,  
 
the 
    Central Government may, by notification, supersede the Board for such 
    period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified in the notification.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the 
    Board,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all the members 
    shall, as from the date of superses­sion, vacate their offices as such;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all the powers, 
    functions and duties which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, be 
    exercised or discharged by or on behalf of the Board, shall until the Board 
    is reconstituted under sub-section (3), be exercised and discharged by such 
    person or persons as the Central Government may direct; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all property owned 
    or controlled by the Board shall, until the Board is reconstituted under 
    sub-section (3), vest in the Central Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification 
    issued under sub-section (1), the Central Gov­ernment may reconstitute the 
    Board by a fresh appointment and in such case any person or persons who 
    vacated their offices under clause (a) of sub-section (2), shall not be 
    deemed disqualified for appointment:  
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may, at any time, before the expiration of the 
    period of supersession, take action under this sub-section.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Central Government shall cause a notification issued under sub-section (1) 
    and a full report of any action taken under this section and the 
    circumstances leading to such action to be laid before each House of 
    Parliament at the earliest.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Returns and reports.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall furnish to the Central Government at such time and in such 
    form and manner as may be prescribed or as the Central Government may 
    direct, such returns and statements and such particulars in regard to any 
    proposed or existing programme for the promotion and development of the 
    securities market, as the Central Government may, from time to time, 
    require.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), the Board shall, 
    within 

    1[ninety days] after 
    the end of each finan­cial year, submit to the Central Government a report 
    in such form, as may be prescribed, giving a true and full account of its 
    activities, policy and programmes during the previous financial year.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    copy of the report received under sub-section (2) shall be laid, as soon as 
    may be after it is received, before each House of Parliament.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Delegation.—The 
    Board may, by general or special order in writing delegate to any member, 
    officer of the Board or any other person subject to such conditions, if any, 
    as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and functions under 
    this Act (except the powers under section 29) as it may deem necessary.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by 

    1[an order of the 
    Board made, before the commencement of the Securities Laws (Second 
    Amendment) Act, 1999,] under this Act, or the rules or regula­tions made 
    thereunder may prefer an appeal to the Central Govern­ment within such time 
    as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    appeal shall be admitted if it is preferred after the expiry of the period 
    prescribed therefor:  
 
Provided 
    that an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the period prescribed 
    therefor if the appellant satisfies the Central Government that he had 
    sufficient cause for not prefer­ring the appeal within the prescribed 
    period.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every appeal made under this section shall be made in such form and shall be 
    accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against and by such fees as may 
    be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    procedure for disposing of an appeal shall be such as may be prescribed:  
 
Provided that 
    before disposing of an appeal, the appellant shall be given a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>


    1[<number>20A</number> Bar of 
    jurisdiction.—No order passed by the 

    2[Board or the 
    adju­dicating officer] under this Act shall be appealable except as provided 
    in 

    3[section 15T or 
    section 20] and no civil court shall have jurisdiction in respect of any 
    matter which the 

    2[Board or the 
    adjudicating officer] is empowered by, or under, this Act to pass any order 
    and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in 
    respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any order passed 
    by the 

    2[Board or the 
    adjudicating officer] by, or under this Act.]  
 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Savings.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall exempt any person from any suit or other proceedings which 
    might, apart from this Act, be brought against him.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Members, officers and employees of the Board to be public servants.—All 
    members, officers and other employees of the Board shall be deemed, when 
    acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this 
    Act, to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian 
    Penal Code (45 of 1860).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecu­tion or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central 
    Government 

    1[or Board] or any 
    officer of the Central Government or any member, officer or other employee 
    of the Board for any­thing which is in good faith done or intended to be 
    done under this Act or the rules or regulations made thereunder.  
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>24</number> Offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to any award of penalty by the adjudicating officer under 
    this Act, if any person contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the 
    contravention of the provi­sions of this Act or of any rules or regulations 
    made thereunder, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to 

    2[ten years, or with 
    fine,  which may extend to twenty-five crore rupees or with both].  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    any person fails to pay the penalty imposed by the adjudi­cating officer or 
    fails to comply with any of his directions or orders, he shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one month but 
    which may extend to 

    3[ten years or with 
    fine, which may extend to twenty-five crore rupees or with both].]  
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>


    1[<number>24A</number> Composition 
    of certain offences.—Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), any offence punishable under this Act, 
    not being an offence punishable with imprisonment only, or with imprisonment 
    and also with fine, may either before or after the institution of any 
    proceeding, be compounded by a Securities Appellate Tribunal or a court 
    before which such proceedings are pending.]
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>


    1[<number>24B</number> Power to 
    grant immunity.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, on recommendation by the 
    Board, if the Central Government is satisfied, that any person, who is 
    alleged to have violated any of the provisions of this Act or the rules or 
    the regulations made thereunder, has made a full and true disclosure in 
    respect of the alleged violation, grant to such person, subject to such 
    conditions as it may think fit to impose, immunity from prosecution for any 
    offence under this Act, or the rules or the regulations made thereunder or 
    also from the imposition of any penalty under this Act with respect to the 
    alleged violation:  
 
Provided 
    that no such immunity shall be granted by the Central Government in cases 
    where the proceedings for the prosecution for any such offence have been 
    instituted before the date of receipt of application for grant of such 
    immunity:  
 
Provided 
    further that recommendation of the Board under this sub-section shall not be 
    binding upon the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    immunity granted to a person under sub-section (1) may, at any time, be 
    withdrawn by the Central Government, if it is satisfied that such person 
    had, in the course of the proceedings, not complied with the condition on 
    which the immunity was granted or had given false evidence, and thereupon 
    such person may be tried for the offence with respect to which the immunity 
    was granted or for any other offence of which he appears to have been guilty 
    in connection with the contravention and shall also become liable to the 
    imposition of any penalty under this Act to which such person would have 
    been liable, had not such immunity been granted.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Exemption from tax on wealth and income.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Wealth-tax Act, 1957 (27 of 1957), the Income-tax 
    Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), or any other enactment for the time being in force 
    relating to tax on wealth, income, profits or gains—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the Board;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the existing 
    Securities and Exchange Board from the date of its constitution to the date 
    of establishment of the Board,  
 
shall 
    not be liable to pay wealth-tax, income-tax or any other tax in respect of 
    their wealth income, profits or gains derived.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Cognizance of offences by courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act or 
    any rules or regulations made thereunder, save on a complaint made by the 
    Board 

    1[***].  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    court inferior to that of 

    2[a court of session] 
    shall try any offence punishable under this Act.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Offences by Companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every 
    person who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was 
    responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, 
    as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
    shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accord­ingly:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he proves that the offence 
    was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due 
    diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other 
    officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable 
    to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “company” means 
    any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; 
    and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “director”, in 
    relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Power to exempt.—[Rep. 
    by the Securities Laws (Amendment) Act, 1995 (9 of 1995), sec. 15 (w.r.e.f.
    
    25-1-1995).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
    purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the term of office 
    and other conditions of service of the Chairman and the members under 
    sub-section (1) of section 5;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the additional 
    functions that may be performed by the Board under section 11;  
 


    1[***]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the manner in 
    which the accounts of the Board shall be maintained under section 15;  
 

2[(da)    
    the manner of inquiry under sub-section (1) of section 15-I;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>db</number>    the salaries and 
    allowances and other terms and condi­tions of service of the 
3[Presiding 
    Officers, Members] and other officers and employees of the Securities, 
    Appellate Tribunal under section 15-O and sub-section (3) of section 15S;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dc</number>    the procedure for 
    the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the 
3[Presiding 
    Officers or other Members] of the Securities Appellate Tribunals under 
    sub-section (3) of section 15Q;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dd</number>    the form in which 
    an appeal may be filed before the securities Appellate Tribunal under 
    section 15T and the fees payable in respect of such appeal;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the form and the 
    manner in which returns and report to be made to the Central Government 
    under section 18;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    any other matter 
    which is to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which provision is 
    to be, or may be, made by rules.  
 
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Power to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board may, 

    1[***] by 
    notification, make regulations consistent with this Act and the rules made 
    thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the forgoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the times and 
    places of meetings of the Board and the procedure to be followed at such 
    meetings under sub-section (1) of section 7 including quorum necessary for 
    the transaction of business;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the term and other 
    conditions of service of officers and employees of the Board under 
    sub-section (2) of section 9;  
 

2[(c)    
    the matters relating to issue of capital, transfer of securities and other 
    matters incidental thereto and the manner in which such matters shall be 
    disclosed by the companies under section 11A;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the conditions 
    subject to which certificate of registration is to be issued, the amount of 
    fee to be paid for certificate of registration and the manner of suspension 
    or cancellation of certificate of registration under section 12.]  
 
 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
    regulation or both Houses agree that the rule or regulation should not be 
    made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule or regulation.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Application of other laws not barred.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, 
    the provi­sions of any other law for the time being in force.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Amendment of certain enactments.—The 
    enactments specified in Parts I and II of the Schedule to this Act shall be 
    amended in the manner specified therein and such amendments shall take 
    effect on the date of establishment of the Board.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Power to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty:  
 
Provided 
    that no order shall be made, under this section after the expiry of five 
    years from the commencement of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
    it is made, before each House of Parliament.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Securities and Exchange Board of India Ordinance, 1992 (Ord. 5 of 1992), 
    is hereby repealed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
    said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
    corresponding provisions of this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

The Schedule
 
(See section 33)
 

Amendment of Certain Enactments
  
 
Part I
 

Amendment to the Capital Issues (Control) Act, 1947
 

    (29 of 
    1947)
  
 
In section 10, for “to that Government” 
    substitute “to that Government or the Securities and Exchange Board of 
    India”.
  
 
Part 
    II
 

Amendments to the Securities Contracts  
    (Regulations) Act, 1956
 

    (42 of 
    1956)
 <article>
<number>1</number> Section 2, in clause (h), for sub-clause 
    (ii), substitute the following:—
 
“(ii)   Government securities;  
 <section>
<number>iia</number>   such other instruments 
    as may be declared by the Central Government to be securities; and”.  
 </section></article><article>
<number>2</number> Section 6,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   in sub-section (1), for 
    “Central Government”, substitute “Securities and Exchange Board of India”;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   in sub-section (2), for 
    “by the Central Government”, substitute “by the Securities and Exchange 
    Board of India”;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   in sub-section (3), 
    for “Central Government”, wherever it occurs, substitute “Securities and 
    Exchange Board of India”;  
 </section></article><article>
<number>3</number> Section 9, for “Central Government” 
    wherever it occurs, substitute “Securities and Exchange Board of India”;  
 </article><article>
<number>4</number> Section 10, for “Central Government” 
    wherever it occurs, substitute “Securities and Exchange Board of India”;  
 </article><article>
<number>5</number> Section 17, in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number>, for 
    “licence granted by the Central Government”, substitute “licence granted by 
    the Securities and Exchange Board of India”;  
 </section></article><article>
<number>6</number> Section 21, for “Central Government”, 
    substitute “Securities and Exchange Board of India”;  
 </article><article>
<number>7</number> Section 22A, in sub-section (3), for 
    clause (b), substitute the following:—  
 
“(b)   that the transfer of 
    the securities is in contravention of any law or rules made thereunder or 
    any administrative instructions or conditions of listing agreement laid down 
    in pursuance of such laws or rules;”;  
 </article><article>
<number>8</number> In sub-section (2) of section 23, for 
    “Central Government under section 21 or section 22”, substitute “Securities 
    and Exchange Board of India under section 21 or the Central Government under 
    section 22”;  
 </article><article>
<number>9</number> After section 29, insert the 
    following:—  
 
“29A. Power of delegate.—The 
    Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, direct 
    that the powers exercisable by it under any provision of this Act shall, in 
    relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any as may be 
    specified in the order, by exercisable also by the Securities and Exchange 
    Board of India.”.  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  15K ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 9. (w.r.e.f. 
25-1-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 32 of 1999, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 16-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  15L ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 9. (w.r.e.f. 
25-1-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 20, for section “15M. Qualifications for appointment as Presiding Officer of the Securities Appellate Tribunal.—A person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate Tribunal unless he—</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by Act 59 of 
    2002, sec. 20, for section “15M. Qualifications for appointment as 
    Presiding Officer of the Securities Appellate Tribunal.—A person shall 
    not be qualified for appointment as the Presiding Officer of a Securities 
    Appellate Tribunal unless he— tc 
    " 5. Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 20, 
    for section “15M. Qualifications for appointment as Presiding Officer of 
    the Securities Appellate Tribunal.—A person shall not be qualified for 
    appointment as the Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate Tribunal 
    unless he—"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   
    Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 21, for section “15N. Terms of office.—The 
    Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate Tribunal shall hold office for a 
    term of five years from the date on which he enters upon his office or until 
    the attains the age of sixty five years, whichever is earlier.” (w.r.e.f. 
    29-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 22, for “Presiding Officer of a 
    Securities Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 22, 
    for “Presiding Officer of a Securities Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 
    29-10-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 22, for “said Presiding 
    Officers” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002). tc 
    " 3. Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 22, 
    for “said Presiding Officers” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   
    Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 23, for “office of the Presiding Officer” (w.r.e.f. 
    29-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 22, for “Presiding Officer of a 
    Securities Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 24, for “the said Presiding 
    Officer” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 24, for “Presiding Officer” (w.r.e.f. 
    29-10-2002). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 24, 
    for “Presiding Officer” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by 
      Act 32 of 1999, sec. 9, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 16-12-1999). tc 
    " 4. Subs. by Act 32 of 1999, sec. 9, 
    for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 16-12-1999)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by 
      Act 32 of  1999, sec. 9, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 
      16-12-1999). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 32 of  1999, sec. 
    9, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 16-12-1999)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Chapter VIA (containing sections 15U) ins. by Act 9 of 
1995, sec. 8 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by 
      Act 32 of 1999, sec. 10, for section 15V (w.e.f. 16-12-1999). tc 
    "  1. Subs. by Act 32 of 1999, sec. 
    10, for section 15V (w.e.f. 16-12-1999)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  
    Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 26, for section “15X. Presiding Officer and 
    staff of Securities Appellate Tribunals to be public servants.—The 
    Presiding Officer and other officers and employees of a Securities Appellate 
    Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 
    21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  
    Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 27, for section “15Z. Appeal to High Court.—Any 
    person aggrieved by any decision or order of the Securities Appellate 
    Tribunal may file an appeal to the High Court within sixty days from the 
    date of communication of the decision or order of the Securities Appellate 
    Tribunal to him on any question of fact or law arising out of such order:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Subs. by Act 22 
    of 1996, sec. 30 and Sch., for “this Act” (w.r.e.f. 20-9-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 10, for “sixty days” (w.r.e.f. 
    25-1-1995). tc 
    "  1. Subs. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 
    10, for “sixty days” (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   
    Subs. by Act 32 of 1999, sec. 11, for “an order of the Board made” (w.e.f. 
    16-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   Ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 11 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995). tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 11 (w.r.e.f. 
    25-1-1995)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   Subs. by Act  32 of 1999, sec. 12, for “Board” (w.e.f. 
    16-12-1999). tc 
    "  4. Subs. by Act  32 of 
    1999, sec. 12, for “Board” (w.e.f. 16-12-1999)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 12 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995). tc 
    "  1. Ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 
    12 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Subs. by 
    Act 9 of 1995, sec. 13, for section 24  (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995). tc 
    "  2. Subs. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 
    13, for section 24  (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Subs. by Act 59 
    of 2002, sec. 28, for “one year, or with fine, or with both” (w.r.e.f. 
    29-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Ins. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 29 (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002). tc 
    " 5. Ins. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 29 (w.r.e.f. 
    29-10-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Ins. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 29 (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002). tc 
    " 5. Ins. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 29 (w.r.e.f. 
    29-10-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   
    The words, “with the previous sanction of the Central Government” omitted by 
    Act 9 of 1995, sec. 14 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   
    Subs. by Act 59 of 2002, sec. 30 for “a Metropolitan Magistrate or a 
    Judicial Magistrate of the first class” (w.r.e.f. 29-10-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Clause (c) omitted by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 16 (w.r.e.f. 
    25-1-1995). tc 
    "  1. Clause (c) omitted by Act 9 
    of 1995, sec. 16 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   Ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 16 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995). tc 
    "  2. Ins. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 
    16 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   
    The words “with the previous approval of the Central Government” omitted by 
    Act 9 of 1995, sec. 17 (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   
    Subs. by Act 9 of 1995, sec. 17, for clause (c)  (w.r.e.f. 25-1-1995).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>