<act><tid>136639</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN COUNCIL OF WORLD AFFAIRS 
 (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 5 OF <year>2004</year>
[ 7th January, <year>2004</year>.]

An Act to amend the Indian Council of World Affairs Act, <year>2001</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1587354</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Indian Council of World 
Affairs (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>627528</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 7.- In section 7 of the Indian Council of World 
Affairs Act, <year>2001</year> (29 of <year>2001</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), in sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>866948</tid>
<number>i</number>the words and figures" which shall not be later than three months 
from the date of assent by the President of the Indian Council of 
World Affairs Bill, <year>2001</year>" shall be omitted and shall be deemed always 
to have been omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1730154</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), for the words" as may be nominated by the Council", 
the words, brackets and figure" to be nominated, in the first instance 
by the Council constituted under sub- section (1) and thereafter by the 
Council constituted under this sub- section" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1521036</tid>
<number>iii</number>for clause (c), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (c) Director- General, ex officio Member- Secretary;"; 
 (iv) in clause (e), for the words" to be nominated by the Council", the 
words, brackets and figure" to be nominated, in the first instance by 
the Council constituted under sub- section (1) and thereafter by the 
Council constituted under this sub- section" shall be substituted;


</section>

<section><tid>369460</tid>
<number>v</number>in clause (f), for the words" to be nominated by the Council", the 
words, brackets and figure" to be nominated, in the first instance by 
the Council constituted under sub- section (1) and thereafter by the 
Council constituted under this sub- section" shall be substituted,

</section>

<section><tid>679854</tid>
<number>vi</number>in clause (g),-

<subsection><tid>1775886</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" either media personalities or representatives of 
organisations", the words" either media personalities or persons from 
organisations" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>869185</tid>
<number>b</number>for the word" selected", the word" nominated" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>441079</tid>
<number>vii</number>in clause (h), for the words" who are representatives of Business 
or", the words" from Business or" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1089669</tid>
<number>viii</number>in clause (i), the words", to be nominated by the Chairperson 
of the Governing Body" shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1987574</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 15.- In section 15 of the principal Act, for 
sub- sections
<section><tid>1475821</tid>
<number>1</number>and (2), the following sub- sections shall be  
substituted, namely:-
" (1) There shall be a Director- General of the Council who shall, before 
a Council is constituted under sub- section (2) of section 7, be 
appointed by the Council constituted under sub- section (1) of that 
section and thereafter during the tenure of a Council constituted under 
sub- section (2) of section 7, by that Council.


</section>

<section><tid>956640</tid>
<number>1A</number>Every appointment of the Director- General under sub- section (1) 
shall be made from a panel of at least two names recommended by the 
Government of India in the Ministry of External Affairs.

</section>

<section><tid>165754</tid>
<number>1B</number>The Director- General shall be the chief executive officer of the 
Council.

</section>

<section><tid>483032</tid>
<number>1C</number>The Director- General shall be at least equivalent to the rank of 
Additional Secretary to the Government of India and shall have a tenure 
not exceeding three years.

</section>

<section><tid>1469506</tid>
<number>2</number>The Director- General shall act as ex officio Member- Secretary to 
the Council, its Governing Body and other bodies and Committees 
thereof.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1079189</tid>
<number>4</number>Insertion of new section 23A.- After section 23 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
Transitory provision.

" 23A. Transitory provision.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby 
declared that till the constitution of a Council in terms of sub- 
section (2) of section 7, the Council referred to in sub- section (1) 
thereof shall be deemed to have been a Council for the purposes of this 
Act notwithstanding anything contrary contained in any provision of 
this Act:

Provided that anything done or any action taken or any proceeding 
initiated under any provision of this Act or rules or regulations made 
thereunder shall not be called in question before any court or other 
authority because of non- existence of a Council in terms of sub- section 
 (2) of section 7.".



</article>



<article><tid>612956</tid>
<number> 5</number> Insertion of new section 28A.- After section 28 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
Power to remove difficulties.

" 28A. Power to remove difficulties.- (1) If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of the Indian Council of World Affairs 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>, the Central Government may, by order, do 
anything not inconsistent with such provisions for the purpose of 
removing the difficulty:

Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period 
of two years from the commencement of the Indian Council of World 
Affairs (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

<section><tid>1141160</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.".
T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>