<act><tid>1368282</tid>
<title>THE MARRIAGE LAWS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 49 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 24th September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Indian Divorce Act, <year>1869</year>, the Parsi 
Marriage and Divorce Act, <year>1936</year>, the Special Marriage Act, <year>1954</year> and the 
Hindu Marriage Act, <year>1955</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>872257</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Marriage Laws (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2001</year>.
CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE INDIAN DIVORCE ACT, <year>1869</year>

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENTS TO THE INDIAN DIVORCE ACT, <year>1869</year>



</article>



<article><tid>860381</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 36.- In section 36 of the Indian Divorce Act, 
 <year>1869</year> (4 of <year>1869</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the Divorce  
  Act),-
<section><tid>864119</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" the wife may present a petition for alimony pending 
the suit", the words" the wife may present a petition for expenses of 
the proceedings and alimony pending the suit" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1110999</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" for payment to the wife of alimony pending the 
suit", the words" for payment to the wife of the expenses of the 
proceedings and alimony pending the suit" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1052184</tid>
<number>c</number>after the proviso, the following proviso shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" Provided further that the petition for the expenses of the 
proceedings and alimony pending the suit shall, as far as possible, be 
disposed of within sixty days of service of such petition on the 
husband.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>603385</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 41.- In section 41 of the Divorce Act, the 
following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the application with respect to the maintenance and 
education of the minor children pending the suit, shall, as far as 
possible, be disposed of within sixty days from the date of service of 
notice on the respondent.".

CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE PARSI MARRIAGE AND DIVORCE ACT, <year>1936</year>

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENTS TO THE PARSI MARRIAGE AND DIVORCE ACT, <year>1936</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1756337</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 39.- In section 39 of the Parsi Marriage and 
Divorce Act, <year>1936</year> (3 of <year>1936</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to  
  as the Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act), the following proviso shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the application for the payment of the expenses of the 
suit and such weekly or monthly sum during the suit, shall, as far as 
possible, be disposed of within sixty days from the date of service of 
notice on the wife or the husband, as the c se may be.".



</article>



<article><tid>1010382</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 49.- In section 49 of the Parsi Marriage and 
Divorce Act, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the application with respect to the maintenance and 
education of such children during the suit, shall, as far as possible, 
be disposed of within sixty days from the date of service of notice on 
the respondent.".

CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE SPECIAL MARRIAGE ACT, <year>1954</year>

CHAPTER IV

AMENDMENTS TO THE SPECIAL MARRIAGE ACT, <year>1954</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1909323</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 36.- In section 36 of the Special Marriage 
Act, <year>1954</year> (43 of <year>1954</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the  
  Special Marriage Act), the following proviso shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" Provided that the application for the payment of the expenses of the 
proceeding and such weekly or monthly sum during the proceeding under 
Chapter V or Chapter VI, shall, as far as possible, be disposed of 
within sixty days from the date of service of n tice on the husband.".



</article>



<article><tid>1299935</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 38.- In section 38 of the Special Marriage 
Act, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the application with respect to the maintenance and 
education of the minor children, during the proceeding, under Chapter 
V or Chapter VI shall, as far as possible, be disposed of within sixty 
days from the date of service of notice on the respondent.".

CHAP

AMENDMENTS TO THE HINDI MARRIAGE ACT, <year>1955</year>

CHAPTER V

AMENDMENTS TO THE HINDU MARRIAGE ACT, <year>1955</year>



</article>



<article><tid>1142371</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 24.- In section 24 of the Hindu Marriage Act, 
 <year>1955</year> (25 of <year>1955</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the Hindu  
  Marriage Act), the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the application for the payment of the expenses of the 
proceeding and such monthly sum during the proceeding, shall, as far 
as possible, be disposed of within sixty days from the date of service 
of notice on the wife or the husband, as the case may be.".



</article>



<article><tid>290897</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of section 26.- In section 26 of the Hindu Marriage Act, 
the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the application with respect to the maintenance and 
education of the minor children, pending the proceeding for obtaining 
such decree shall, as far as possible, be disposed of within sixty 
days from the date of service of notice on the res ondent.".


</article>



 </act>