<act><tid>1370000</tid>
<title>THE FOREIGN AIRCRAFT (EXEMPTION FROM TAXES AND DUTIES ON FUEL  
  AND LUBRICANTS) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 36 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 11th June, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to implement Agreements entered into by India with other 
countries in pursuance of the Convention on International Civil 
Aviation opened for signatures at Chicago on the 7th December, <year>1944</year>.

WHEREAS a Convention on International Civil Aviation was signed by 
India on the 7th December, <year>1944</year>;

AND WHEREAS India, having signed the said Convention, entered into 
Agreements with the parties to the said Convention to exempt the taxes 
and duties on fuel and lubricants supplied in India to the aircraft of 
the contracting parties.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>972877</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1719975</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Foreign  
Aircraft (Exemption from Taxes and Duties on Fuel and Lubricants) Act, 
<year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>56981</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>869304</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1858878</tid>
<number>a</number>" Agreements" means the Air Services Agreements or Air Transport 
Agreements entered into by India with parties to the Convention;

</section>

<section><tid>1224693</tid>
<number>b</number>" Convention" means the Convention on International Civil Aviation 
opened for signatures at Chicago on the 7th December, <year>1944</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1923185</tid>
<number>3</number>Exemption from levy of taxes and duties on fuel and lubricants 
supplied to aircraft of other countries.- Where, in pursuance of the 
Convention or Agreement with any other country or countries, it is 
necessary to grant exemption from levy of taxes and d ties on fuel and 
lubricants filled into receptacles forming part of any aircraft of any 
other country or countries under any law of a State or Union territory 
in India, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make such provi ions as may be necessary for giving effect to 
the said Convention or Agreement and thereupon the said provision 
shall apply accordingly and, notwithstanding anything contrary 
contained in any other law, shall in such application have the force 
of law in ndia.
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>