<act><title>QUALITY OF SERVICE (CODE OF PRACTICE FOR METERING AND BILLING ACCURACY) REGULATION, 20061</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> This regulation shall be called Quality of Service (Code of Practice for Metering and Billing Accuracy) Regulation, 2006 (5 of 2006) (hereinafter called the Regulation). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> This regulation shall be applicable to all the Basic Service Providers, Unified Access Service Providers and Cellular Mobile Telephone Service Providers, including Mahanagar Telephone Nigam Limited and Bharat Sanchar Nigam Limited. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> This regulation shall come into effect from the date of its publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In this regulation, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Act means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Basic Telecommunication Services means services derived from a Public Switched Telephone Network (PSTN) and as specified in the licence; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Cellular Mobile Telephone Services means services derived from a Public Land Mobile Network (PLMN) and as specified in the license. This includes both Cellular Mobile Telephone Services provided through GSM and CDMA Technology; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> Quality of Service is the main indicator of the performance of a telephone network and of the degree to which the network conforms to the stipulated norms; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> Words and expressions used in this regulation and not defined here shall bear the same meaning as assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Purpose of laying down the Code of Practice for metering and billing accuracy. </title>The purpose of laying down the Code of Practice for metering and billing accuracy is to: 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Bring uniformity and transparency in the procedures being followed by service providers with regard to metering and billing; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> Prescribe standards relating to accuracy of measurement and reliability of billing; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Measure the accuracy of billing provided by the Service Providers from time to time and to compare them with the norms so as to assess the level of performance; 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> Minimize the incidences of billing complaints; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> Protect the interest of consumers of telecommunication services. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Code of Practice for metering and billing accuracy. </title>The service provider is required to comply with the Code of Practice for metering and billing accuracy as laid down in Annexure 1. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Review. </title>The Code of Practice for metering and billing accuracy as given in Regulation 4 above may be reviewed by the Authority from time to time. The Authority, on reference from any affected party, and for good and sufficient reasons, may review and modify this regulation. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Auditing of Metering and Billing System. </title>The Authority shall notify the panel of auditors to certify the Metering and Billing System of service providers. The service providers shall arrange audit of their Metering and Billing System in compliance with this regulation on an annual basis through any one of the auditors as may be notified by the Authority and an audit certificate thereof shall be furnished to the Authority not later than 30th June of every year. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Explanatory Memorandum. </title>This regulation contains at Annexure 2, an explanatory memorandum, which explains the background and reasons for its issuance. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Interpretation. </title>In case of any doubt regarding interpretation of any of the provisions of this regulation, the decision of the Authority shall be final and binding. 


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>