<act><tid>1385811</tid>
<title>THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 21 OF <year>1996</year>
[ 1st August, <year>1996</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-

An Act further to amend the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> 
and 
the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year>.

CHAP

PRILIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1474052</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>106366</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Representation of the People (Amendment) Act, <year>1996</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>454795</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

AMENDMENT OF THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENT OF THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1721265</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 32. In the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1950</year>, in section 32, in sub- section 1, for the words" with fine 
which may extend to five hundred rupees', the words" with imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than three months but which may 
extend to two years and with fine" shall be substituted.
CHAP

AMENDMENT OF THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE ACT, <year>1951</year>

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENT OF THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE ACT, <year>1951</year>



</article>



<article><tid>913059</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 8. In the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>) hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the 
1951-Act, in section 8, in sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>1366541</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (j), the word" or" shall be added at the 
end;

</section>

<section><tid>1906888</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (j), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (k) section 2 (offence of insulting the Indian National  
  Flag or the Constitution of India) or section 3 (offence  
  of preventing singing of National Anthem) of the 
Prevention of Insults to National Honour Act, <year>1971</year>;". 
 (69 of <year>1971</year>).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1658269</tid>
<number>4</number>Insertion of new section 20B. After section 20A of the <year>1951</year>- 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-


</article>



<article><tid>1983381</tid>
<number> 20B</number> Observers.
<section><tid>1445889</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission may nominate an  
Observer who shall be an officer of Government to watch the conduct of 
election or elections in a constituency or a group of constituencies 
and to perform such other functions as may be entrusted to him by the 
Election Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>618180</tid>
<number>2</number>The Observer nominated under subsection (1) shall have the 
power to direct the returning officer for the constituency or for any 
of the constituencies for which he has been nominated, to stop the 
counting of votes at any time before the declaration of the result or 
not to declare the result if in the opinion of the Observer booth 
capturing has taken place at a large number of polling stations or at 
places fixed for the poll or counting of votes or any ballot papers 
used at a polling station or at a place fixed for the poll are 
unlawfully taken out of the custody of the returning officer or are 
accidentally or intentionally destroyed or lost or are damaged or 
tampered with to such an extent that the result of the poll at that 
polling station or place cannot be ascertained.

</section>

<section><tid>1995429</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an Observer has directed the returning officer under 
this section to stop counting of votes or not to declare the result, 
the Observer shall forthwith report the matter to the Election 
Commission and thereupon the Election Commission shall, after taking 
all material circumstances into account, issue appropriate directions 
under section 58 A or section 64A or section 66.
Explanation.- For the purposes of sub- section (2) and subsection 
 (3)," Observer" shall include a Regional Commissioner or any such 
officer of the Election Commission as has been assigned under this 
section the duty of watching the conduct of election or elections in a 
constituency or group of constituencies by the Commission.".


<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>826311</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 30. In section 30 of the 1951-Act, in 
clause (d), for the words" twentieth day," the words" fourteenth day" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>851638</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 33. In section 33 of the <year>1951</year> Act,-
<section><tid>918660</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the provisos, the following provisos 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" Provided that a candidate not set up by a recognised political 
party, shall not be deemed to be duly nominated for election from a 
constituency unless the nomination paper is subscribed by ten 
proposers being electors of the constituency:

Provided further that no nomination paper shall be delivered to 
the returning officer on a day which is a public holiday:

Provided also that in the case of a local authorities' 
constituency, graduates' constituency or teachers' constituency, the 
reference to" an elector of the constituency as proposer" shall be 
construed as a reference to ten per cent. of the electors of the con- 
stituency or ten such electors, whichever is less, as proposers";


</section>

<section><tid>1327347</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (6), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1895860</tid>
<number>7</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (6) or in 
any other provisions of this Act, a person shall not be nominated as a 
candidate for election,-

<subsubsection><tid>1793473</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a general election to the House of the People 
 (whether or not held simultaneously from all Parliamentary  
  constituencies), from more than two Parliamentary constituencies;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1835073</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a general election to the Legislative 
Assembly of a State (whether or not held simultaneously from all  
  Assembly constituencies), from more than two Assembly constituencies 
in that State;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1740341</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a biennial election to the Legislative 
Council of a State having such Council, from' more than two Council 
constituencies in the State;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>41352</tid>
<number>d</number>in the case of a biennial election to the Council of States 
for filling two or more seats allotted to a State, for filling more 
than two such seats;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>72352</tid>
<number>e</number>in the case of bye- elections to the House of the People from 
two or more Parliamentary constituencies which are held 
simultaneously, from more than two such Parliamentary constituencies;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>229420</tid>
<number>f</number>in the case of bye- elections to the Legislative Assembly of 
a State from two or more Assembly constituencies which are held 
simultaneously, from more than two such Assembly constituencies;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1445929</tid>
<number>g</number>in the case of bye- elections to the Council of States for 
filling two or more seats allotted to a State, which are held 
simultaneously, for filling more than two such seats;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1284191</tid>
<number>h</number>in the case of bye- elections to the Legislative Council of a 
State having such Council from two or more Council constituencies 
which are held simultaneously, from more than two such Council 
constituencies.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, two or more 
bye- elections shall be deemed to be held simultaneously where the 
notification calling such bye- elections are issued, by the Election 
Commission under section 147, 149, 150 or, as the case may be, 151 on 
the same date.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>969006</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 34. In section 34 of the <year>1951</year> Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following subsection shall be substituted 
namely:-
<section><tid>1479258</tid>
<number>1</number>A candidate shall not be deemed to be duly nominated for 
election from a constituency unless he deposits or causes to be 
deposited,-

<subsection><tid>909676</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an election from a Parliamentary 
constituency, a sum of ten thousand rupees or where the candidate is a 
member of a Scheduled Caste or Scheduled Tribe, a sum of five thousand 
rupees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>607569</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of an election from an Assembly or Council 
constituency, a sum. of five thousand rupees or where the candidate is 
a member of a Scheduled Caste or Scheduled Tribe, a sum of two 
thousand five hundred rupees:
Provided that where a candidate has been nominated by more than 
one nomination paper for election in the same constituency, not more 
than one deposit shall be required of him under this sub- section.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>895887</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of section 38. In section 38 of the 1951-Act, for 
sub- section (2), the following sub- sections shall be substituted, 
namely:-
<section><tid>580757</tid>
<number>2</number>for the purpose of listing the names under sub- section (1), 
the candidates shall be classified as follows, namely:-

<subsection><tid>331957</tid>
<number>i</number>candidates of recognised political parties;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1155467</tid>
<number>ii</number>candidates of registered political parties other 
than those mentioned in clause (i);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>245663</tid>
<number>iii</number>other candidates.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>597020</tid>
<number>3</number>The categories mentioned in sub- section (2) shall be 
arranged in the order specified therein and the names of candidates in 
each category shall be arranged in alphabetical order and the 
addresses of the contesting candidates as given in the nomination 
papers together with such other particulars as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1307214</tid>
<number>9</number>Substitution of new section for section 52. Death of 
candidate of recognised political party before poll. For section 52 
of the 1951-Act, the following section shall be substituted namely:-


</article>



<article><tid>1647542</tid>
<number> 52</number> Death of candidate of recognised political party before poll.

<section><tid>842719</tid>
<number>1</number>If a candidate set up by a recognised political party,- 

<subsection><tid>1513980</tid>
<number>a</number>dies at any time after 11. 00 A. M. on the last date for 
making nominations and his nomination is found valid on scrutiny under 
section 36; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>425287</tid>
<number>b</number>whose nomination has been found valid on scrutiny under 
section 36 and who has not withdrawn his candidature under section 37 
dies,
and in either case, a report of his death is received at any time 
before the publication of the list of contesting candidates under 
section 38; or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518279</tid>
<number>c</number>dies as a contesting candidate and a report of his death is 
received before the commencement of the poll,
the returning officer shall, upon being satisfied about the fact 
of the death of the candidate, by order, announce an adjournment of 
the poll to a date to be notified later and report the fact to the 
Election Commission and also to the appropriate authority:

Provided that no order for adjourning a poll should be made in a 
case referred to in clause (a) except after the scrutiny of all the 
nominations including the nomination of the deceased candidate.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1726249</tid>
<number>2</number>The' Election Commission shall, on receipt of a report from 
the returning officer- under sub- section (1), call upon the recognised 
political party, whose candidate has died, to nominate another 
candidate for the said poll within seven days of issue such notice to 
such recognised political party and the provisions of sections 30 to 
 37 shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to such nomination as 
they would apply to other nominations:
Provided that no person who has given a notice of withdrawal of 
his candidature under sub- section (1) of section 37 before the 
adjournment of the poll shall be ineligible for being nominated as a 
candidate for the election after such adjournment.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>331737</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a list of contesting, candidates had been published 
under section 38 before the adjournment of the poll under sub- section 
 (1), the returning officer shall again prepare and publish a fresh 
list of contesting candidates under that section so as to include the 
name of the candidate who has been validly nominated under sub- section 
 (2).
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, sections 33 and 
38," recognised political party" means a political party recognised by 
the Election Commission under the Election Symbols (Reservation and  
  Allotment) Order, <year>1968</year>.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>961490</tid>
<number>10</number>Substitution of new section for section 126. For section 126 
of the 1951-Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-


</article>



<article><tid>1462243</tid>
<number> 126</number> Prohibition of public meetings during period of forty- eight 
hours ending with four fixed for conclusion of poll.
<section><tid>147372</tid>
<number>1</number>No person  
shall-

<subsection><tid>769454</tid>
<number>a</number>convene, hold, attend, join or address any public meeting or 
procession in connection with an election; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1761407</tid>
<number>b</number>display to the public any election matter by means of 
cinematograph, television or other similar apparatus; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1535332</tid>
<number>c</number>propagate any election matter to the public by holding, or 
by arranging the holding of, any musical concert or any theatrical 
performance or any other entertainment or amusement with a view to 
attracting the members of the public thereto,
in any polling area during the period of forty- eight hours ending with 
the hour fixed for the conclusion of the poll for any election in that 
polling area.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1364241</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1) 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>1866539</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section, the expression" election matter" means any 
matter intended or calculated to influence or affect the result of an 
election.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>277663</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amendment of section 127. In section 127 of the 1951-Act,-
<section><tid>1722327</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" three months or with fine 
which may extend to one thousand rupees", the words" six months or 
with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1324825</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (1A) An offence punishable under sub- section (1) shall be 
cognizable.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1326960</tid>
<number>12</number>Substitution of new section for section 133. For section 133 
of the 1951-Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-


</article>



<article><tid>1162903</tid>
<number>133</number>Penalty for illegal hiring or procuring of conveyance at 
election. If any person is guilty of any such corrupt practice as is 
specified in clause (5) of section 123 at or in connection with an 
election, he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to 
three months and with fine."


</article>



<article><tid>879919</tid>
<number> 13</number> Insertion of new section 134B. After section 134A of the 
1951-Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>134B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Prohibition of going armed to or near a polling station.

" 134B. Prohibition of going armed to or near a polling station. 
 (1) No person, other than the returning officer, the presiding 
officer, any police officer and any other person appointed to maintain 
peace and order, at a polling station who is on duty at the polling 
station, shall, on a polling day, go armed with arms, as defined in 
the Arms Act, <year>1959</year> (54 of <year>1959</year>), of any kind within the neighbourhood 
of a polling station.

<section><tid>1522330</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1), 
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to two years, or with fine, or with both.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1376467</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Arms Act, <year>1959</year> (54  
  of <year>1959</year>), where a person is convicted of an offence under this 
section, the arms as defined in the said Act found in his possession 
shall be liable to confirmation and the licence granted in relation to 
such arms shall be deemed to have been revoked under section 17 of 
that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>944031</tid>
<number>4</number>An offence punishable under sub- section (2) shall be 
cognizable.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>682983</tid>
<number>14</number>Amendment of section 135. In section 135 of the <year>1951</year>- Act, 
in sub- section 1, for the word" fraudulently", the word 
" unauthorisedly" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1161401</tid>
<number> 15</number> Amendment of section 135 A. Section 135A of the 1951-Act 
shall be renumbered as sub- section
<section><tid>1323691</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof and,- 

<subsection><tid>825574</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1) as so renumbered,-

<subsubsection><tid>701392</tid>
<number>a</number>for the portion beginning with the words" shall 
not be less than six months" and ending with the words 
" extend to three years and with fine' the following shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" shall not be less than one year but which may extend 
to three years and with fine, and where such offence is 
committed by a person in the service of the Government, he 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall 
not be less than three years but which may extend to five 
years and with fine;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>337658</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Explanation,-

<subsubsubsection><tid>1485601</tid>
<number>A</number>for the words" this section", occurring in the 
opening portion, the words, figures and letter" this sub- 
section and section 20B" shall be substituted;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1881176</tid>
<number>B</number>in clause (b), for the words" prevent others from 
voting", the words prevent others from free exercise of their 
right to vote' shall be substituted;

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>614773</tid>
<number>C</number>in clause (c), for the word" threatening', the 
words" coercing or intimidating or threatening directly or 
indirectly", shall be substituted,

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>125113</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (1) as so renumbered and the 
Explanation thereto, the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (2) An offence punishable under sub- section (1), shall be 
cognizable.".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1566930</tid>
<number> 16</number> Insertion of new sections 135 B and 135 C. After section 
 135A of the 1951-Act, the following sections shall be inserted, 
namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>135B</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Grant of paid holiday to employees on the day of poll.

" 135B. Grant of paid holiday to employees on the 
day of poll. (1) Every person employed in any business, 
trade, industrial undertaking or any other establishment and 
entitled to vote at an election to the House of the People or 
the Legislative Assembly of a State shall, on the day of 
poll, be granted a holiday.

<section><tid>565541</tid>
<number>2</number>No deduction or abatement of the wages of any such person 
shall be made on account of a holiday having been granted in 
accordance with sub- section (1) and if such person is employed on the 
basis that he would not ordinarily receive wages for such a day, he 
shall nonetheless be paid for such day the wages he would have drawn 
had not a holiday been granted to him on that day.

</section>

<section><tid>542106</tid>
<number>3</number>If an employer contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1) 
or sub- section (2), then such employer shall be punishable with fine 
which may extend to five hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>284536</tid>
<number>4</number>This section shall no apply to any elector whose absence may 
cause danger or substantial loss in respect of the employment in which 
he is engaged.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>135C</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Liquor not to be sold given or distributed on polling day.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>100231</tid>
<number> 135C</number> Liquor not to be sold given or distributed on polling day.

<section><tid>1472681</tid>
<number>1</number>No spirituous, fermented or intoxicating liquors or other  
substances of a like nature shall be sold, given or distributed at a 
hotel, eating house, tavern, shop or any other place, public or 
private, within a polling area during the period of forty- eight hours 
ending with the hour fixed for the conclusion of the poll for any 
election in that polling area.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>355564</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub- section 
 (1), shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to six months, or with fine, which may extend to two thousand rupees, 
or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>562331</tid>
<number>3</number>Where a person is convicted of an offence under this 
section, the spirituous, fermented or intoxicating liquors or other 
substances of a like nature found in this possession shall be liable 
to confiscation and the same shall be disposed of in such manner as 
may be prescribed.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>341031</tid>
<number>17</number>Insertion of new section 151A. After section 151 of the 
1951-Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>151A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Time limit for filling vacancies referred to in sections 147, 149, 150 and 151.

</article>



<article><tid>1574524</tid>
<number> 151A</number> Time limit for filling vacancies referred to in 
sections 147, 149, 150 and 151. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 147, section 149, section 150 and 
section 151, a bye- election for filling any vacancy referred 
to in any of the said sections shall be held within a period 
of six months from the date of the occurrence of the vacancy:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply 
if-

<section><tid>1381438</tid>
<number>a</number>the remainder of the term of a member in relation 
to a vacancy is less than one year; or

</section>

<section><tid>1357862</tid>
<number>b</number>The Election Commission in consultation with the 
Central Government certifies that it is difficult to hold the 
bye- election within the said period.".
K. L. MOHANPURIA,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>