<act><title>


    The Unlawful Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[1. Short title, 
    extent and application.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the Unlawful 
    Activities (Prevention) Act, 1967. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    person shall be liable to punishment under this Act for every act or 
    omission contrary to the provisions thereof, of which he is held guilty in 
    India.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any 
    person, who commits an offence beyond India, which is punishable under this 
    Act, shall be dealt with according to the provisions of this Act in the same 
    manner as if such act had been committed in India.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    provisions of this Act apply also to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    citizens of India outside India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    persons in the service of the 
    Government, wherever they may be; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    persons on ships and aircrafts, 
    registered in India, wherever they may be.]
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, unless the 
context otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “association” means any combination or body of individuals; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “cession of a part of the territory of India ” includes admission of 
  the claim of any foreign country to any such part; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “Code” means the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “court” means a criminal court having jurisdiction, under the Code, to 
  try offences under this Act <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[and includes a special court 
  constituted under section 11 or under section 21 of the National Investigation 
  Agency Act, 2008 (34 of 2008);] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “Designated Authority” means such officer of the Central Government not 
  below the rank of Joint Secretary to that Government, or such officer of the 
  State Government not below the rank of Secretary to that Government, as the 
  case may be, as may be specified by the Central Government or the State 
  Government, by notification published in the Official Gazette; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ea</number> “Order” means the Prevention and Suppression of Terrorism 
  (Implementation of Security Council Resolutions) Order, 2007, as may be 
  amended from time to time;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “proceeds of terrorism” means all kinds of properties which have been 
  derived or obtained from commission of any terrorist act or have been acquired 
  through funds traceable to a terrorist act, irrespective of person in whose 
  name such proceeds are standing or in whose possession they are found, and 
  includes any property which is being used, or is intended to be used, for the 
  purpose of a terrorist organisation <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[or terrorist gang]; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>h</number> “property” means property and assets of every description, 
  whether corporeal or incorporeal, movable or immovable, tangible or intangible 
  and legal documents, deeds and instruments in any form including electronic or 
  digital, evidencing title to, or interest in, such property or assets by means 
  of bank credits, travellers' cheques, bank cheques, money orders, shares, 
  securities, bonds, drafts, letters of credit, cash and bank account including 
  fund, however acquired; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ha</number> “Schedule” means the Schedule to this Act;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “secession of a part of the territory of India from the Union ” 
  includes the assertion of any claim to determine whether such part will remain 
  a part of the territory of India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> “State Government”, in relation to a Union territory, means the 
  Administrator thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> “terrorist act” has the meaning assigned to it in section 15, and the 
  expressions “terrorism” and “terrorist” shall be construed accordingly; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> “terrorist gang” means any association, other than terrorist 
  organisation, whether systematic or otherwise, which is concerned with, or 
  involved in, terrorist act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> “terrorist organisation” means an organisation listed in the Schedule 
  or an organisation operating under the same name as an organisation so listed; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> “Tribunal” means the Tribunal constituted under section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> “unlawful activity”, in relation to an individual or association, means 
  any action taken by such individual or association (whether by committing an 
  act or by words, either spoken or written, or by signs or by visible 
  representation or otherwise),— 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> which is intended, or supports any claim, to bring about, on any ground 
  whatsoever, the cession of a part of the territory of India or the secession 
  of a part of the territory of India from the Union, or which incites any 
  individual or group of individuals to bring about such cession or secession; 
  or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> which disclaims, questions, disrupts or is intended to disrupt the 
  sovereignty and territorial integrity of India; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> which causes or is intended to cause disaffection against India ; 

 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>p</number> “unlawful association” means any association,— 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> which has for its object any unlawful activity, or which encourages or 
  aids persons to undertake any unlawful activity, or of which the members 
  undertake such activity; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> which has for its object any activity which is punishable under 
  section 153A or section 153B of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860), or which 
  encourages or aids persons to undertake any such activity, or of which the 
  members undertake any such activity: 
 Provided that nothing contained in sub-clause (ii) shall apply to the State 
  of Jammu and Kashmir ; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>q</number> words and expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in 
  the Code shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Code. 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any reference in this Act to any enactment or any provision thereof 
shall, in relation to an area in which such enactment or such provision is not 
in force, be construed as a reference to the corresponding law or the relevant 
provision of the corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.] 






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Declaration of an association as unlawful.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Central Government is of opinion that any association is, or has 
    become, an unlawful association, it may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, declare such association to be unlawful.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such 
    notification shall specify the grounds on which it is issued and such other 
    particulars as the Central Government may consider necessary:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this sub-section shall require the Central Government to disclose 
    any fact which it considers to be against the public interest to disclose.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No such 
    notification shall have effect until the Tribunal has, by an order made 
    under section 4, confirmed the declaration made therein and the order is 
    published in the Official Gazette:  
 
Provided that 
    if the Central Government is of opinion that circumstances exist which 
    render it necessary for that Government to declare an association to be 
    unlawful with immediate effect, it may, for reasons to be stated in writing, 
    direct that the notification shall, subject to any order that may be made 
    under section 4, have effect from the date of its publication in the 
    Official Gazette.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every such 
    notification shall, in addition to its publication in the Official Gazette, 
    be published in not less than one daily newspaper having circulation in the 
    State in which the principal office, if any, of the association affected is 
    situated, and shall be served on such association in such manner as the 
    Central Government may think fit and all or any of the following modes may 
    be followed in effecting such service, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    by affixing a copy of the notification 
    to some conspicuous part of the office, if any of the association; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    by serving a copy of the notification, 
    where possible, on the principal office-bearers, if any of the association; 
    or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    by proclaiming by beat of drum or by 
    means of loudspeakers, the contents of the notification in the area in which 
    the activities of the association are ordinarily carried on; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    in such other manner as may be 
    prescribed.
 
 

  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Reference to Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
    any association has been declared unlawful by a notification issued under 
    sub-section (1) of section 3, the Central Government shall, within thirty 
    days from the date of the publication of the notification under the said 
    sub-section, refer the notification to the Tribunal for the purpose of 
    adjudicating whether or not there is sufficient cause for declaring the 
    association unlawful.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of a reference under sub-section (1), the Tribunal shall call upon the 
    association affected by notice in writing to show cause, within thirty days 
    from the date of the service of such notice, why the association should not 
    be declared unlawful.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After 
    considering the cause, if any, shown by the association or the 
    office-bearers or members thereof, the Tribunal shall hold an inquiry in the 
    manner specified in section 9 and after calling for such further information 
    as it may consider necessary from the Central Government or from any 
    office-bearer or member of the association, it shall decide whether or not 
    there is sufficient cause for declaring the association to be unlawful and 
    make, as expeditiously as possible and in any case within a period of six 
    months from the date of the issue of the notification under sub-section (1) 
    of section 3, such order as it may deem fit either confirming the 
    declaration made in the notification or cancelling the same.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The order 
    of the Tribunal made under sub-section (3) shall be published in the 
    Official Gazette.  
 

  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute, as and 
    when necessary, a Tribunal to be known as the “Unlawful Activities 
    (Prevention) Tribunal” consisting of one person, to be appointed by the 
    Central Government:  
 
Provided that 
    no person shall be so appointed unless he is a Judge of a High Court.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, for 
    any reason, a vacancy (other than a temporary absence) occurs in the office 
    of the presiding officer of the Tribunal, then, the Central Government shall 
    appoint another person in accordance with the provisions of this section to 
    fill the vacancy and the proceedings may be continued before the Tribunal 
    from the stage at which the vacancy is filled.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government shall make available to the Tribunal such staff as may be 
    necessary for the discharge of its functions under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    expenses incurred in connection with the Tribunal shall be defrayed out of 
    the Consolidated Fund of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of section 9, the Tribunal shall have power to regulate its 
    own procedure in all matters arising out of the discharge of its functions 
    including the place or places at which it will hold its sittings.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Tribunal shall, for the purpose of making an inquiry under this Act, have 
    the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit, in respect of the following 
    matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the summoning and enforcing the 
    attendance of any witness and examining him on oath;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the discovery and production of any 
    document or other material object producible as evidence;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the reception of evidence on 
    affidavits;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the requisitioning of any public record 
    from any court or office;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the issuing of any commission for the 
    examination of witnesses.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> Any 
    proceeding before the Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding 
    within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
    1860) and the Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes 
    of section 195 and 

    1[Chapter XXVI] of the
    

    2[Code.]
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Period 
    of operation and cancellation of notification.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), a notification issued under 
    section 3 shall, if the declaration made therein is confirmed by the 
    Tribunal by an order made under section 4, remain in force for a period of 
    two years from the date on which the notification becomes effective.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central 
    Government may, either on its own motion or on the application of any person 
    aggrieved, at any time, cancel the notification issued under section 3 
    whether or not the declaration made therein has been confirmed by the 
    Tribunal.  
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power to 
    prohibit the use of funds of an unlawful association.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an association has been declared unlawful by a notification issued 
    under section 3 which has become effective under sub-section (3) of that 
    section and the Central Government is satisfied, after such inquiry as it 
    may think it, that any person has custody of any moneys, securities or 
    credits which are being used or are intended to be used for the purpose of 
    the unlawful association, the Central Government may, by order in writing, 
    prohibit such person from paying, delivering, transferring or otherwise 
    dealing in any manner whatsoever with such moneys, securities or credits or 
    with any other moneys, securities  or credits which may come into his 
    custody after the making of the order save in accordance with the written 
    orders of the Central Government and a copy of such order shall be served 
    upon the person so prohibited in the manner specified in sub-section (3).  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may endorse a copy of the prohibitory order made under 
    sub-section (1) for investigation to any Gazetted Officer of the Government 
    it may select, and such copy shall be a warrant whereunder such officer may 
    enter in or upon any premises of the person to whom the order is directed, 
    examine the books of such person, search for moneys, securities or credits, 
    and make inquiries from such person or any officer, agent or servant of such 
    person, touching the origin of any dealings in any moneys, securities or 
    credits which the Investigating Officer may suspect are being used or are 
    intended to be used for the purpose of the unlawful association.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    copy of an order made under this section shall be served in the manner 
    provided in the 

    1[Code], for the 
    service of a summons, or where the person to be served is a corporation, 
    company, bank or other association, it shall be served on any secretary, 
    director or other officer or person concerned with the management thereof; 
    or by leaving it or sending it by post addressed to the corporation, 
    company, bank or other association at its registered office, or where there 
    is no registered office, at the place where it carries on business. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person 
    aggrieved by a prohibitory order made under sub-section (1) may, within 
    fifteen days from the date of the service of such order, make an application 
    to the Court of the District Judge within the local limits of whose 
    jurisdiction such person voluntarily resides  or carries on business or 
    personally works for gain, to establish that the moneys, securities or 
    credits in respect of which the prohibitory order has been made are not 
    being used or are not intended to be used for the purpose of the unlawful 
    association and the Court of the District Judge shall decide the question.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Except so 
    far as is necessary for the purposes of any proceedings under this section, 
    no information obtained in the course of any investigation made under 
    sub-section (2) shall be divulged by any gazetted officer of the Government, 
    without the consent of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In this 
    section, “security” includes a document whereby any person acknowledges that 
    he is under a legal liability to pay money, or whereunder any person obtains 
    a legal right to the payment of money.
 
 



 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power to 
    notify places used for the purpose of an unlawful association.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an association has been declared unlawful by a notification issued 
    under section 3 which has become effective under sub-section (3) of that 
    section, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, notify any place which in its opinion is used for the purpose of 
    such unlawful association.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub-section, “place” includes a house or building, or part thereof, or 
    a tent or vessel.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the 
    issue of notification under sub-section (1), the District Magistrate within 
    the local limits of whose jurisdiction such notified place is situate or any 
    officer authorised by him in writing in this behalf shall make a list of all 
    movable properties (other than wearing apparel, cooking vessels, beds and 
    beddings, tools of artisans, implements of husbandry, cattle, grain and 
    food-stuffs and such other articles as he considers to be of a trivial 
    nature) found in the notified place in the presence of two respectable 
    witnesses.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, in the 
    opinion of the District Magistrate, any articles specified in the list are 
    or may be used for the purpose of the unlawful association, he may make an 
    order prohibiting any person from using the articles save in accordance with 
    the written orders of the District Magistrate.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    District Magistrate may, thereupon make an order that no person who at the 
    date of the notification was not a resident in the notified place shall, 
    without the permission of the District Magistrate, enter, or be on or in, 
    the notified place:  
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this sub-section shall apply to any near relative of any person 
    who was a resident in the notified place at the date of the notification.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where in 
    pursuance of sub-section (4), any person is granted permission to enter, or 
    to be on or in, the notified place, that person shall, while acting under 
    such permission, comply with such orders for regulating his conduct as may 
    be given by the District Magistrate.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any police 
    officer, not below the rank of a sub-inspector, or any other person 
    authorised in this behalf by the Central Government may search any person 
    entering, or seeking to enter, or being on or in the notified place and may 
    detain any such person for the purpose of searching him:  
 
Provided that 
    no female shall be searched in pursuance of this sub-section except by a 
    female.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If any 
    person is in the notified place in contravention of an order made under 
    sub-section (4), then, without prejudice to any other proceedings which may 
    be taken against him, he may be removed therefrom by any officer or by any 
    other person authorised in this behalf by the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Any person 
    aggrieved by a notification issued in respect of a place under, sub-section 
    (1) or by an order made under sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) may, within 
    thirty days from the date of the notification or order, as the case may be, 
    make an application to the Court of the District Judge within the local 
    limits of whose jurisdiction such notified place is situate—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for declaration that the place has not 
    been used for the purpose of the unlawful association; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    for setting aside the order made under 
    sub-section (3) or sub-section (4), and on receipt of the application the 
    Court of the District Judge shall, after giving the parties an opportunity 
    of being heard, decide the question.  

 
  


  
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Procedure to be followed in the disposal of applications under this Act.—Subject 
    to any rules that may be made under this Act, the procedure to be followed 
    by the Tribunal in holding any inquiry under sub-section (3) of section 4 or 
    by a Court of the District Judge in disposing of any application under 
    sub-section (4) of section 7 or sub-section (8) of section 8 shall, so far 
    as may be, be the procedure laid down in the 

    1[Code]; for the 
    investigation of claims and the decision of the Tribunal or the Court of the 
    District Judge, as the case may be, shall be final.
 
 




 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>10</number> Penalty for 
    being member of an unlawful association, etc.—Where 
    an association is declared unlawful by a notification issued under section 3 
    which has become effective under sub­-section (3) of that section,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    a person, who­—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    is and continues to be a member of such 
    association; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    takes part in meetings of such 
    association; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    contributes to, or receives or 
    solicits any contri­bution for the purpose of, such association; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    in any way assists the operations of 
    such association,  
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to two years, and shall also be liable to fine; and  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>    a person, who is or continues to be a 
    member of such association, or voluntarily does an act aiding or promoting 
    in any manner the objects of such association and in either case is in 
    possession of any unlicensed firearms, ammunition, explosive or other 
    instrument or substance capable of causing mass destruction and commits any 
    act resulting in loss of human life or grievous injury to any person or 
    causes significant damage to any property,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    and if such act has resulted in the 
    death of any person, shall be punishable with death or imprisonment for 
    life, and shall also be liable to fine;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in any other case, shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years but 
    which may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to 
    fine.]
 
 




 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Penalty for dealing with funds of an unlawful association.—If 
    any person on whom a prohibitory order has been served under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> 
    of section 7 in respect of any moneys, securities or credits pays, delivers, 
    transfers or otherwise deals in any manner whatsoever with the same in 
    contravention of the prohibitory order, he shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or with fine, or 
    with both, and notwithstanding anything contained in the 

    1[Code], the court 
    trying such contravention may also impose on the person convicted an 
    additional fine to recover from him the amount of the moneys or credits or 
    the market value of the securities in respect of which the prohibitory order 
    has been contravened or such part thereof as the court may deem fit.
 
 




 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Penalty 
    for contravention of an order made in respect of a notified place.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever uses any article in contravention of a prohibitory order in respect 
    thereof made under sub-section (3) of section 8 shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, and shall also be 
    liable to fine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever 
    knowingly and wilfully is in, or effects or attempts to effect entry into, a 
    notified place in contravention of an order made under sub-section (4) of 
    section 8 shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
    to one year, and shall also be liable to fine.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Punishment for unlawful activities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    takes part in or commits, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    advocates, abets, advises or incites 
    the commission of, any unlawful activity, shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years, and shall also be 
    liable to fine.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever, 
    in any way, assists any unlawful activity of any association declared 
    unlawful under section 3, after the notification by which it has been so 
    declared has become effective under sub-section (3) of that section, shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, 
    or with fine, or with both.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in 
    this section shall apply to any treaty, agreement or convention entered into 
    between the Government of India and the Government of any other country or 
    to any negotiations therefor carried on by any person authorised in this 
    behalf by the Government of India  
 

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Offences to be cognizable.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the 

    1[Code], an offence 
    punishable under this Act shall be cognizable.
 






 




</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>14</footcitenum><title>[<number>15</number> Terrorist act. </title>—Whoever does 
any act with intent to threaten or likely to threaten the unity, integrity, 
security or ­sovereignty of India or with intent to strike terror or likely 
to strike terror in the people or any section of the people in India or in any 
foreign country,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> by using bombs, dynamite or other explosive substances or inflammable 
  substances or firearms or other lethal weapons or poisonous or noxious gases 
  or other chemicals or by any other substances (whether biological radioactive, 
  nuclear or otherwise) of a hazardous nature or by any other means of whatever 
  nature to cause or likely to cause— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> death of, or injuries to, any person or persons; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> loss of, or damage to, or destruction of, property; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> disruption of any supplies or services essential to the life of the 
    community in India or in any foreign country; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> damage or destruction of any property in India or in a foreign 
    country used or intended to be used for the defence of India or in 
    connection with any other purposes of the Government of India, any State 
    Government or any of their agencies; or </subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> overawes by means of criminal force or the show of criminal force or 
  attempts to do so or causes death of any public functionary or attempts to 
  cause death of any public functionary; or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> detains, kidnaps or abducts any person and threatens to kill or injure 
  such person or does any other act in order to compel the Government of India, 
  any State Government or the Government of a foreign country or any other 
  person to do or abstain from doing any act, </section>
 commits a terrorist act. 
 Explanation. —For the purpose of this section, public functionary 
means the constitutional authorities and any other functionary notified in the 
Official Gazette by the Central Government as a public functionary.] 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Punishment for terrorist act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever commits a terrorist act shall,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if such act has resulted in the death 
    of any person, be punishable with death or imprisonment for life, and shall 
    also be liable to fine;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in any other case, be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years but which 
    may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine.  

 
  


  
</subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>16</footcitenum><title>[<number>16A</number> Punishment for making demands of 
radioactive substances, nuclear devices, etc. </title>—Whoever intentionally, 
by use of force or threat of use of force or by any other means, demands any 
bomb, dynamite or other explosive substance or inflammable substances or 
firearms or other lethal weapons or poisonous or noxious or other chemicals or 
any biological, radiological, nuclear material or device, with the intention of 
aiding, abetting or committing a terrorist act, shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years, and shall also be liable 
to fine.]] 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>18</footcitenum><title>[</title><title><number>17</number> Punishment for raising 
funds for terrorist act. </title>—Whoever, in India or in a foreign country, 
directly or indirectly, raises or collects funds or provides funds to any person 
or persons or attempts to provide funds to any person or persons, knowing that 
such funds are likely to be used by such person or persons to commit a terrorist 
act, notwithstanding whether such funds were actually used or not for commission 
of such act, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be 
less than five years but which may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall 
also be liable to fine.] 




</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Punishment for conspiracy, etc.—Whoever 
    conspires or attempts to commit, or advocates, abets, advises or incites or 
    knowingly facilitates the commission of, a terrorist act or any act 
    preparatory to the commission of a terrorist act, shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years but which 
    may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine.  

 
  


  
</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>20</footcitenum><title>[</title><title><number>18A</number> Punishment for 
organising of terrorist camps. </title>—Whoever organizes or causes to be 
organized any camp or camps for imparting training in terrorism shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than five years 
but which may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to 
fine.] 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>22</footcitenum><title>[</title><title><number>18B</number> Punishment for 
recruiting of any person or persons for terrorist act. </title>—Whoever 
recruits or causes to be recruited any person or persons for commission of a 
terrorist act shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not 
be less than five years but which may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall 
also be liable to fine.] <title>]</title>


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Punishment for harbouring, etc.—Whoever 
    voluntarily harbours or conceals, or attempts to harbour or conceal any 
    person knowing that such person is a terrorist shall be punishable with 
    imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three years but which 
    may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall also be liable to fine:  
 
Provided that 
    this section shall not apply to any case in which the harbour or concealment 
    is by the spouse of the offender.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>20</number> Punishment for being member of terrorist 
      gang or organisation.—Any 
      person who is a member of a terrorist gang or a terrorist organisation, 
      which is involved in terrorist act, shall be punishable with imprisonment 
      for a term which may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall also be 
      liable to fine.  
 
  
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Punishment for holding proceeds of terrorism.—Whoever 
    knowingly holds any property derived or obtained from commission of any 
    terrorist act or acquired through the terrorist fund shall be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to imprisonment for life, and 
    shall also be liable to fine.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Punishment for threatening witness.—Whoever 
    threatens any person who is a witness or any other person in whom such 
    witness may be interested, with violence, or  wrongfully restrains or 
    confines the witness, or any other person in whom the witness may be 
    interested, or does any other unlawful act with intent to cause any of the 
    said acts, shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three 
    years, and shall also be liable to fine.  

 
  


  
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Enhanced penalties. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[If any person with 
intent to aid any terrorist or a terrorist organisation or a terrorist gang 
contravenes] any provision of, or any rule made under the Explosives Act, 1884 
(4 of 1884­) or the Explosive Substances Act, 1908 (6 of 1908) or the 
Inflammable Substances Act, 1952 (20 of 1952) or the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 
1959), or is in unauthorised possession of any bomb, dynamite or hazardous 
explosive substance or other lethal weapon or substance capable of mass 
destruction or biological or chemical substance of warfare, he shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in any of the aforesaid Acts or the rules 
made thereunder, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be 
less than five years but which may extend to imprisonment for life, and shall 
also be liable to fine. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[Any person who with the intent to aid any terrorist, or a 
terrorist organisation or a terrorist gang] attempts to contravene or abets, or 
does any act preparatory to contravention of any provision of any law or rule 
specified in sub-section (1), shall be deemed to have contravened that provision 
under sub-section (1) and the provisions of that sub-section in relation to such 
person, have effect subject to the modification that the reference to 
“imprisonment for life” therein shall be construed as a reference to 
“imprisonment for ten years”. 



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<title><number>24</number> Forfeiture of proceeds of terrorism. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall hold or be in possession of any proceeds of terrorism. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Proceeds of terrorism, whether held by a terrorist or 
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[terrorist organisation or terrorist gang or] by any other person 
and whether or not such terrorist or other person is prosecuted or convicted for 
any offence under Chapter IV or Chapter VI, shall be liable to be forfeited to 
the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, in the 
manner provided under this Chapter.


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[<title><number>25</number> Powers of investigating officer and Designated 
Authority and appeal against order of Designated Authority. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> If an 
officer investigating an offence committed under Chapter IV or Chapter VI, has 
reason to believe that any property in relation to which an investigation is 
being conducted, represents proceeds of terrorism, he shall, with the prior 
approval in writing of the Director General of the Police of the State in which 
such property is situated, make an order seizing such property and where it is 
not practicable to seize such property, make an order of attachment directing 
that such property shall not be transferred or otherwise dealt with except with 
the prior permission of the officer making such order, or of the Designated 
Authority before whom the property seized or attached is produced and a copy of 
such order shall be served on the person concerned. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The investigating officer shall duly inform the Designated Authority 
within forty-eight hours of the seizure or attachment of such property. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Designated Authority before whom the seized or attached property is 
produced shall either confirm or revoke the order of seizure or attachment so 
issued within a period of sixty days from the date of such production: 
 Provided that an opportunity of making a representation by the person whose 
property is being seized or attached shall be given. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the case of immovable property attached by the investigating officer, 
it shall be deemed to have been produced before the Designated Authority, when 
the investigating officer notifies his report and places it at the disposal of 
the Designated Authority. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The investigating officer may seize and detain any cash to which this 
Chapter applies if he has reasonable grounds for suspecting that— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> it is intended to be used for the purposes of terrorism; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> it forms the whole or part of the resources of a terrorist 
  organisation: </subsection>
 Provided that the cash seized under this sub-section by the investigating 
officer shall be released within a period of forty-eight hours beginning with 
the time when it is seized unless the matter involving the cash is before the 
Designated Authority and such Authority passes an order allowing its retention 
beyond forty-eight hours. 
 Explanation .—For the purposes of this sub-section, “cash” means— 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> coins or notes in any currency; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> postal orders; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> traveller's cheques; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>ca</number> credit or debit cards or cards that serve a similar 
  purpose;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> banker's drafts; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> such other monetary instruments as the Central Government or, as the 
  case may be, the State Government may specify by an order made in writing. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> Any person aggrieved by an order made by the Designated Authority may 
prefer an appeal to the court within a period of thirty days from the date of 
receipt of the order, and the court may either confirm the order of attachment 
of property or seizure so made or revoke such order and release the property. ] 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number>  Court 
    to order forfeiture of proceeds of terrorism.—Where 
    any property is seized or attached on the ground that it constitutes 
    proceeds of terrorism and the court confirms the order in this regard under 
    sub‑section (6) of section 25, it may order forfeiture of such property, 
    whether or not the person from whose possession it is seized or attached, is 
    prosecuted in a court for an offence under Chapter IV or Chapter VI.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number>  Issue 
    of show cause notice before forfeiture of proceeds of terrorism.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No order forfeiting any proceeds of terrorism shall be made under section 26 
    unless the person holding or in possession of such proceeds is given a 
    notice in writing informing him of the grounds on which it is proposed to 
    forfeit the proceeds of terrorism and such person is given an opportunity of 
    making a representation in writing within such reasonable time as may be 
    specified in the notice against the grounds of forfeiture and is also given 
    a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No order 
    of forfeiture shall be made under sub‑section (1), if such person 
    establishes that he is a bona fide transferee of such proceeds for 
    value without knowing that they represent proceeds of terrorism.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    be competent for the court to make an order in respect of the property 
    seized or attached,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    directing it to be sold if it is a 
    perishable property and the provisions of section 459 of the Code shall, as 
    nearly as may be practicable, apply to the net proceeds of such sale;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    nominating any officer of the Central 
    Government or the State Government, in the case of any other property, to 
    perform the function of the Administrator of such property subject to such 
    conditions as may be specified by the court.  

 
  


  
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of forfeiture under section 26 may, within 
    one month from the date of the receipt of such order, appeal to the High 
    Court within whose jurisdiction, the court, which passed  the order appealed 
    against, is situated.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    order under section 26 is modified or annulled by the High Court or where in 
    a prosecution instituted for any offence under Chapter IV or Chapter VI, the 
    person against whom an order of forfeiture has been made under section 26 is 
    acquitted, such property shall be returned to him and in either case if it 
    is not possible for any reason to return the forfeited property, such person 
    shall be paid the price therefor as if the property had been sold to the 
    Central Government with reasonable interest calculated from the day of 
    seizure of the property and such price shall be determined in the manner 
    prescribed.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Order 
    of forfeiture not to interfere with other punishments.—The 
    order of forfeiture made under this Chapter by the court, shall not prevent 
    the infliction of any other punishment to which the person affected thereby 
    is liable under Chapter IV or Chapter VI.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Claims 
    by third party.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any 
    claim is preferred or any objection is made to the seizure or attachment of 
    any property under section 25 on the ground that such property is not liable 
    to seizure or attachment, the Designated Authority before whom such property 
    is produced, shall proceed to investigate the claim or objection:  
 
Provided that 
    no such investigation shall be made where the Designated Authority considers 
    that the claim or objection is designed to cause unnecessary delay.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    appeal has been preferred under sub‑section (6) of section 25 and any 
    claimant or objector establishes that the property specified in the notice 
    issued under section 27 is not liable to be forfeited under this Chapter, 
    the said notice shall be withdrawn or modified accordingly.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Powers 
    of Designated Authority.—The 
    Designated Authority, acting under the provisions of this Chapter, shall 
    have  all the powers of a civil court required for making a full and fair 
    inquiry into the matter before it.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number>  
    Certain transfers to be null and void.—Where, 
    after the issue of an order under section 25 or issue of a notice under 
    section 27, any property referred to in the said order or notice is 
    transferred by any mode whatsoever, such transfer shall, for the purpose of 
    the proceedings under this Chapter, be ignored and if such property is 
    subsequently forfeited, the transfer of such property shall be deemed to be 
    null and void.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Forfeiture of property of certain persons.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any person is accused of an offence under Chapter IV or Chapter VI, it 
    shall be open to the court to pass an order that all or  any of the 
    properties, movable or immovable or both, belonging to him, shall, during 
    the period of such trial, be attached, if not already attached under this 
    Chapter.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    person has been convicted of any offence punishable under Chapter IV or 
    Chapter VI, the court may, in addition to awarding any punishment, by order 
    in writing, declare that any property, movable or immovable or both, 
    belonging to the accused and specified in the order, shall stand forfeited 
    to the Central Government or the State Government, as the case may be, free 
    from all encumbrances.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Company 
    to transfer shares to Government.—Where 
    any share in a company stands forfeited to the Central Government or the 
    State Government, as the case may be, under this Chapter, then, the company 
    shall, on receipt of the order of the court, notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or  the articles of 
    association of the company, forthwith register the Central Government or the 
    State Government, as the case may be, as the transferee of such share.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Amendment of Schedule, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by order, in the Official Gazette,­—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    add an organisation in the Schedule;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    add also an organisation to the 
    Schedule, which is identified as a terrorist organisation in a resolution 
    adopted by the Security Council under Chapter VII of the Charter of the 
    United Nations, to combat international terrorism;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    remove an organisation from the 
    Schedule;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    amend the Schedule in some other way.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government shall exercise its power under clause (a) of sub‑section 
    (1) in respect of an organisation only if it believes that it is involved in 
    terrorism.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purposes of sub‑section (2), an organisation shall be deemed to be involved 
    in terrorism if it—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    commits or participates in acts of 
    terrorism, or   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    prepares for terrorism, or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    promotes or encourages terrorism, or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is otherwise involved in terrorism.  

 
  


  
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Denotification of a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application may be made to the Central Government for the exercise of its 
    power under clause (c) of sub‑section (1) of section 35 to remove an 
    organisation from the Schedule.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    application under sub‑section (1) may be made by—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the organisation, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any person affected by inclusion of the 
    organisation in the Schedule as a terrorist organisation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may prescribe the procedure for admission and disposal of 
    an application made under this section.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where an 
    application under sub‑section (l) has been rejected the applicant may apply 
    for a review to the Review Committee constituted by the Central Government 
    under sub‑section (1) of section 37 within one month from the date of 
    receipt of the order of such refusal by the applicant.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Review 
    Committee may allow an application for review against rejection to remove an 
    organisation from the Schedule, if it considers that the decision to reject 
    was flawed when considered in the light of the principles applicable on an 
    application for judicial review.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where the 
    Review Committee allows review under sub‑section (5) by or in respect of an 
    organisation, it may make an order to such effect.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where an 
    order is made under sub‑section (6), the Central Government shall, as soon 
    as the certified copy of the order is received by it, make an order removing 
    the organisation from the Schedule.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Review 
    Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government shall constitute one or more Review Committees for the purposes 
    of section 36.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such 
    Committee shall consist of a Chairperson and such other members not 
    exceeding three and possessing such qualifications as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    Chairperson of the Committee shall be a person who is, or has been, a Judge 
    of a High Court, who shall be appointed by the Central Government and in the 
    case of appointment of a sitting Judge, the concurrence of the Chief Justice 
    of the concerned High Court shall be obtained.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Offence 
    relating to membership of a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person, who associates himself, or professes to be associated, with a 
    terrorist organisation with intention to further its activities, commits an 
    offence relating to membership of a terrorist organisation:  
 
Provided that 
    this sub‑section shall not apply where the person charged is able to prove—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the organisation was not declared 
    as a terrorist organisation at the time when he became a member or began to 
    profess to be a member; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that he has not taken part in the 
    activities of the organisation at any time during its inclusion in the 
    Schedule as a terrorist organisation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person, 
    who commits the offence relating to membership of a terrorist organisation 
    under sub-section (1), shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term not 
    exceeding ten years, or with fine, or with both.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Offence 
    relating to support given to a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person commits the offence relating to support given to a terrorist 
    organisation,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    who, with intention to further the 
    activity of a terrorist organisation,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    invites support for the terrorist 
    organisation, and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the support is not or is not 
    restricted to provide money or other property within the meaning of section 
    40; or  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    who, with intention to further the 
    activity of a terrorist organisation, arranges, manages or assists in 
    arranging or managing a meeting which he knows is­—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    to support the terrorist organisation, 
    or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    to further the activity of the 
    terrorist organisation, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    to be addressed by a person who 
    associates or professes to be associated with the terrorist organisation; or  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    who, with intention to further the 
    activity of a terrorist organisation, addresses a meeting for the purpose of 
    encouraging support for the terrorist organisation or to further its 
    activity.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person, 
    who commits the offence relating to support given to a terrorist 
    organisation under sub‑section (1), shall be punishable with imprisonment 
    for a term not exceeding ten years, or with fine, or with both.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Offence 
    of raising fund for a terrorist organisation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person commits the offence of raising fund for a terrorist organisation, 
    who, with intention to further the activity of a terrorist organisation,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    invites another person to provide money 
    or other property, and intends that it should be used, or has reasonable 
    cause to suspect that it might be used, for the purposes of terrorism; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    receives money or other property, and 
    intends that it should be used, or has reasonable cause to suspect that it 
    might be used, for the purposes of terrorism; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    provides money or other property, and 
    knows, or has reasonable cause to suspect, that it would or might be used 
    for the purposes of terrorism.  
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this sub‑section, a reference to provide money or other property includes of 
    its being given, lent or otherwise made available, whether or not for 
    consideration.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A person, 
    who commits the offence of raising fund for a terrorist organisation under 
    sub‑section (1), shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term not 
    exceeding fourteen years, or with fine, or with both.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Continuance of association.—An 
    association shall not be deemed to have ceased to exist by reason only of 
    any formal act of its dissolution or change of name but shall be deemed to 
    continue so long as any actual combination for the purposes of such 
    association continues between any members thereof.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Power 
    to delegate.—The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that all or 
    any of the powers which may be exercised by it under section 7, or section 
    8, or both, shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if any, 
    as may be specified in the notification, be exercised also by any State 
    Government and the State Government may, with the previous approval of the 
    Central Government, by order in writing, direct that any power which has 
    been directed to be exercised by it shall, in such circumstances and under 
    such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the direction, be exercised 
    by any person subordinate to the State Government as may be specified 
    therein.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Officers competent to investigate offences under Chapters IV and VI.— 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, no police officer,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in the case of the Delhi Special Police 
    Establishment, constituted under sub‑section (1) of section 2 of the Delhi 
    Special Police Establishment Act, 1946, (25 of 1946), below the rank of a 
    Deputy Superintendent of Police or a police officer of equivalent rank;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in the metropolitan areas of Mumbai, 
    Kolkata, Chennai and Ahmedabad and any other metropolitan area notified as 
    such under sub‑section (1) of section 8 of the Code, below the rank of an 
    Assistant Commissioner of Police;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    in any case not relatable to clause (a) 
    or clause (b), below the rank of a Deputy Superintendent of Police or a 
    police officer of an equivalent rank,  
 
shall investigate any offence punishable under 
    Chapter IV or Chapter VI.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[<title><footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[<number>43A</number> Power to arrest, search, etc. 
</title>—Any officer of the Designated Authority empowered in this behalf, by 
general or special order of the Central Government or the State Government, as 
the case may be, knowing of a design to commit any offence under this Act or has 
reason to believe from personal knowledge or information given by any person and 
taken in writing that any person has committed an offence punishable under this 
Act or from any document, article or any other thing which may furnish evidence 
of the commission of such offence or from any illegally acquired property or any 
document or other article which may furnish evidence of holding any illegally 
acquired property which is liable for seizure or freezing or forfeiture under 
this Chapter is kept or concealed in any building, conveyance or place, may 
authorise any officer subordinate to him to arrest such a person or search such 
building, conveyance or place whether by day or by night or himself arrest such 
a person or search a such building, conveyance or place.] 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<title><footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>43B</number> Procedure of arrest, 
seizure, etc. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any officer arresting a person under section 43A 
shall, as soon as may be, inform him of the grounds for such arrest. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every person arrested and article seized under section 43A shall be 
forwarded without unnecessary delay to the officer in charge of the nearest 
police station. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The authority or officer to whom any person or article is forwarded under 
sub-section (2) shall, with all convenient dispatch, take such measures as may 
be necessary in accordance with the provisions of the Code.] 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[<title><footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>43C</number> Application of 
provisions of Code. </title>—The provisions of the Code shall apply, insofar as 
they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, to all arrests, 
searches and seizures made under this Act.] <title>]</title>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<title><footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>43D</number> Modified application 
of certain provisions of the Code. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code or any other law, every offence punishable under this Act 
shall be deemed to be a cognizable offence within the meaning of clause (c) of 
section 2 of the Code, and “cognizable case” as defined in that clause shall be 
construed accordingly. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Section 167 of the Code shall apply in relation to a case involving an 
offence punishable under this Act subject to the modification that in 
sub-section (2),— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the references to “fifteen days”, “ninety days” and “sixty days”, 
  wherever they occur, shall be construed as references to “thirty days”, 
  “ninety days” and “ninety days” respectively; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> after the proviso, the following provisos shall be inserted, namely:— 
  </subsection>
 “Provided further that if it is not possible to complete the investigation 
within the said period of ninety days, the Court may if it is satisfied with the 
report of the Public Prosecutor indicating the progress of the investigation and 
the specific reasons for the detention of the accused beyond the said period of 
ninety days, extend the said period up to one hundred and eighty days: 
 Provided also that if the police officer making the investigation under this 
Act, requests, for the purposes of investigation, for police custody from 
judicial custody of any person in judicial custody, he shall file an affidavit 
stating the reasons for doing so and shall also explain the delay, if any, for 
requesting such police custody.”. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Section 268 of the Code shall apply in relation to a case involving an 
offence punishable under this Act subject to the modification that— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the reference in sub-section (1) thereof— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> to “the State Government” shall be construed as a reference to “the 
    Central Government or the State Government”, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> to “order of the State Government” shall be 
    construed as a reference to “order of the Central Government or the State 
    Government, as the case may be”; and </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the reference in sub-section (2) thereof, to “the 
  State Government” shall be construed as a reference to “the Central Government 
  or the State Government, as the case may be”. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Nothing in section 438 of the Code shall apply in relation to any case 
involving the arrest of any person accused of having committed an offence 
punishable under this Act. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, no person accused of an 
offence punishable under Chapters IV and VI of this Act shall, if in custody, be 
released on bail or on his own bond unless the Public Prosecutor has been given 
an opportunity of being heard on the application for such release: 
 Provided that such accused person shall not be released on bail or on his own 
bond if the Court, on a perusal of the case diary or the report made under 
section 173 of the Code is of the opinion that there are reasonable grounds for 
believing that the accusation against such person is prima facie true. 

 </section><section><number>6</number> The restrictions on granting of bail specified in sub-section (5) is in 
addition to the restrictions under the Code or any other law for the time being 
in force on granting of bail. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-sections (5) and (6), no bail 
shall be granted to a person accused of an offence punishable under this Act, if 
he is not an Indian citizen and has entered the country unauthorisedly or 
illegally except in very exceptional circumstances and for reasons to be 
recorded in writing.]] 


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>39</footcitenum><title>[<number>43E</number> Presumption as to offences under 
section 15. </title>—In a prosecution for an offence under section 15, if it is 
proved— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> that the arms or explosives or any other substances specified in the 
  said section were recovered from the possession of the accused and there is 
  reason to believe that such arms or explosives or other substances of a 
  similar nature were used in the commission of such offence; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> that by the evidence of the expert the finger-prints of the accused or 
  any other definitive evidence suggesting the involvement of the accused in the 
  offence were found at the site of the offence or on anything including arms 
  and vehicles used in connection with the commission of such offence, 
  </section>
 the Court shall presume, unless the contrary is shown, that the accused has 
committed such offence.]]


</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[<title><footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>43F</number> Obligation to furnish 
information. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, 
the officer investigating any offence under this Act, with the prior approval in 
writing of an officer not below the rank of a Superintendent of Police, may 
require any officer or authority of the Central Government or a State Government 
or a local authority or a bank, or a company, or a firm or any other 
institution, establishment, organisation or any individual to furnish 
information in his or their possession in relation to such offence, on points or 
matters, where the investigating officer has reason to believe that such 
information will be useful for, or relevant to, the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The failure to furnish the information called for under sub-section (1), 
or deliberately furnishing false information shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine or with 
both. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, an offence under 
sub-­ section (2) shall be tried as a summary case and the procedure 
prescribed in Chapter XXI of the said Code [except sub-section (2) of section 
262] shall be applicable thereto.]<title>]</title>


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Protection of witnesses.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, the proceedings under this 
    Act may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, be held in camera if 
    the court so desires.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A court, 
    if on an application made by a witness in any proceeding before it or by the 
    Public Prosecutor in relation to such witness or on its own motion, is 
    satisfied that the life of such witness is in danger, it may, for reasons to 
    be recorded in writing, take such measures as it deems fit for keeping the 
    identity and address of such witness secret.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of 
    sub-section (2), the measures which a court may take under that sub-section 
    may include—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the holding of the proceedings at a 
    place to be decided by the court;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the avoiding of the mention of the name 
    and address of the witness in its orders or judgments or in any records of 
    the case accessible to public;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the issuing of any directions for 
    securing that the identity and address of the witness are not disclosed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a decision that it is in the public 
    interest to order that all or any of the proceedings pending before such a 
    court shall not be published in any manner.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Any 
    person, who contravenes any decision or direction issued under sub-section 
    (3), shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    three years, and shall also be liable to fine.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>42</footcitenum>[<title><number>45</number> Cognizance of offences. </title>— <footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] 
No court shall take cognizance of any offence— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> under Chapter III without the previous sanction of the Central 
  Government or any officer authorised by the Central Government in this behalf; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> under Chapters IV and VI without the previous sanction of the Central 
  Government or, as the case may be, the State Government, and where such 
  offence is committed against the Government of a foreign country without the 
  previous sanction of the Central Government. </subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Sanction for prosecution under sub-section (1) shall be 
given within such time as may be prescribed only after considering the report of 
such authority appointed by the Central Government or, as the case may be, the 
State Government which shall make an independent review of the evidence gathered 
in the course of investigation and make a recommendation within such time as may 
be prescribed to the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State 
Government.] 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Admissibility of evidence collected through the interception of 
    communications.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or any other 
    law for the time being in force, the evidence collected through the 
    interception of wire, electronic or oral communication under the provisions 
    of the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885) or the Information Technology 
    Act, 2000 (21 of 2000) or any other law for the time being in force, shall 
    be admissible as evidence against the accused in the court during the trial 
    of a case:  
 
Provided that 
    the contents of any wire, electronic or oral communication intercepted or 
    evidence derived therefrom shall not be received in evidence or otherwise 
    disclosed in any trial, hearing or other proceeding in any court unless each 
    accused has been furnished with a copy of the order of the competent 
    authority under the aforesaid law, under which the interception was 
    directed, not less than ten days before trial, hearing or proceeding:  
 
Provided 
    further that the period of ten days may be waived by the judge trying the 
    matter, if he comes to the conclusion that it was not possible to furnish 
    the accused with such order ten days before the trial, hearing or proceeding 
    and that the accused shall not be prejudiced by the delay in receiving such 
    order.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Bar of 
    jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as 
    otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no proceeding taken under this Act 
    by the Central Government or the District Magistrate or any officer 
    authorised in this behalf by the Central Government or the District 
    Magistrate, shall be called in question in any civil court in any suit or 
    application or by way of appeal or revision, and no injunction shall be 
    granted by any civil court or other authority in respect of any action taken 
    or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), no civil court or 
    other authority shall have, or be entitled to exercise, any jurisdiction, 
    powers or authority in relation to the matters referred to in section 36.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>48</number> Effect 
    of Act and rules, etc., inconsistent with other enactments.—The 
    provisions of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder shall have 
    effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any 
    enactment other than this Act or any instrument having effect by virtue of 
    any enactment other than this Act.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the Central Government or a State 
    Government or any officer or authority of the Central Government or State 
    Government or District Magistrate or any officer authorised in this behalf 
    by the Government or the District Magistrate or any other authority on whom 
    powers have been conferred under this Act, for anything which is in good 
    faith done or purported to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or 
    order made thereunder; and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any serving or retired member of the 
    armed forces or para-military forces in respect of any action taken or 
    purported to be taken by him in good faith, in the course of any operation 
    directed towards combating terrorism.  

 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Saving.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall affect the jurisdiction exercisable by, or the procedure 
    applicable to, any court or other authority under any law relating to the 
    navy, army or air force or other armed forces of the Union.  

 
  


  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Impounding of passport and arms licence of person charge-sheeted under the 
    Act.—Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in any other law for the time being in force, the passport and the 
    arms licence of a person, who is charge-sheeted for having committed any 
    offence under this Act, shall be deemed to have been impounded for such 
    period as the court may deem fit.  

 
  


  
</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>46</footcitenum><title>[<number>51A</number> Certain powers of the Central 
Government. </title>—For the prevention of, and for coping with terrorist 
activities, the Central Government shall have power to— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> freeze, seize or attach funds and other financial assets or economic 
  resources held by, on behalf of or at the direction of the individuals or 
  entities listed in the Schedule to the Order, or any other person engaged in 
  or suspected to be engaged in terrorism; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> prohibit any individual or entity from making any funds, financial 
  assets or economic resources or related services available for the benefit of 
  the individuals or entities listed in the Schedule to the Order or any other 
  person engaged in or suspected to be engaged in terrorism; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> prevent the entry into or the transit through India of individuals 
  listed in the Schedule to the Order or any other person engaged in or 
  suspected to be engaged in terrorism.] </section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[<title><number>52</number> Power to make rules. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, makes rules for 
carrying out the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the service of notices or orders issued or made under this Act and the 
  manner in which such notices or orders may be served, where the person to be 
  served is a corporation, company, bank or other association; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the procedure to be followed by the Tribunal or a District Judge in 
  holding any inquiry or disposing of any application under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> determination of the price of the forfeited property under sub-section 
  (2) of section 28; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the procedure for admission and disposal of an application under 
  sub-section (3) of section 36; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the qualifications of the members of the Review Committee under 
  sub-section (2) of section 37; and </subsection>
 <subsection><footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[<number>ee</number> the time within which sanction for prosecution and 
recommendation to the Central Government shall be given under sub-section (2) of 
section 45; and] 


</subsection></section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[<title><number>53</number> Orders and rules to be laid before both Houses of 
Parliament. </title>— <footcitenum>50</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>] Every order and every rule made by the 
Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the order or rule or both Houses agree that the order 
or rule should not be made, the order or rule shall thereafter have effect only 
in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
anything previously done under that order or rule. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>51</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The Order referred to in entry 33 of the Schedule and every 
amendment made to that Order shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made 
before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 30 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions.] 



</section></article><form>
 

THE UNLAWFUL ACTIVITIES (PREVENTION) ACT, 1967 
 

 
 

THE SCHEDULE 
 

[ See sections 2(l)(m) and 35] 
 

TERRORIST ORGANISATIONS 
 

1. Babbar Khalsa International. 
 

2. Khalistan Commando Force. 
 

3. Khalistan Zindabad Force. 
 

4. International Sikh Youth Federation. 
 

5. Lashkar-E-Taiba/Pasban-E-Ahle Hadis. 
 

6. Jaish-E-Mohammed/Tahrik-E-Furqan. 
 

7. Harkat-Ul-Mujahideen/Harkat-Ul-Ansar/Harkat-Ul-Jehad-E-Islami 
 

8. Hizb-Ul-Mujahideen/Hizb-Ul-Mujahideen Pir Panjal Regiment. 
 

9. Al-Umar-Mujahideen. 
 

10. Jammu and Kashmir Islamic Front. 
 

11. United Liberation Front of Assam (ULFA). 
 

12. National Democratic Front of Bodoland (NDFB). 
 

13. People's Liberation Army (PLA). 
 

14. United National Liberation Front (UNLF). 
 

15. People's Revolutionary Party of Kangleipak (PREPAK). 
 

16. Kangleipak Communist Party (KCP). 
 

17. Kanglei Yaol Kanba Lup (KYKL). 
 

18. Manipur People's Liberation Front (MPLF). 
 

19. All Tripura Tiger Force. 
 

20. National Liberation Front of Tripura. 
 

21. Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam (LTTE). 
 

22. Students Islamic Movement of India . 
 

23. Deendar Anjuman. 
 

24. Communist Party of India (Marxist-Leninist)—People's War, All Its 
Formations and Front Organisations. 
 

25. Maoist Communist Centre (MCC), All its Formations and Front 
Organisations. 
 

26. Al Badr. 
 

27. Jamiat-Ul-Mujahidden. 
 

28. Al-Qaida. 
 

29. Dukhtaran-E-Millat (DEM). 
 

30. Tamil Nadu Liberation Army (TNLA). 
 

31. Tamil National Retrieval Troops (TNRT). 
 

32. Akhil Bharat Nepali Ekta Samaj (ABNES).] 
 

1[33. Organisations listed in the Schedule to the U.N. Prevention 
and Suppression of Terrorism (Implementation of Security Council Resolutions) 
Order, 2007 made under section 2 of the United Nations (Security Council) Act, 
1947 (43 of 1947) and amended from time to time.] 
 

---------- 
 

1. Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 17.</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by Act 29 of 2004, sec. 4, for sections 1, 2 and 2A 
(w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 3(i).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 3(ii).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 3(iii).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 3(iv), for clause (h). Clause 
(h), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    2004, sec. 5, for “Chapter XXXV” (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    2004, sec. 3, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.r.e.f. 
    21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    2004, sec. 3, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.r.e.f. 
    21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    2004, sec. 3, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.r.e.f. 
    21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    2004, sec. 6, for section 10 (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    2004, sec. 3, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.r.e.f. 
    21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 29 of 
    2004, sec. 3, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.r.e.f. 
    21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> sections 15 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Act 35 of 2008, section 4, for section 15. Section 
15, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> sections 16A subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 5.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> sections 17 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by Act 35 of 2008, section 6, for section 17. Section 
17, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> sections 18A subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 8.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> sections 18B subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 8.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> sections 23 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Subs. by Act 35 of 2008, section 9(a), for “If any person 
with intent to aid any terrorist contravenes”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Subs. by Act 35 of 2008, section 9(b), for “Any person who, 
with intent to aid any terrorist,”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> sections 24 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 10.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> sections 25 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 11.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> sections 43A subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 12.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> sections 43B subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 12.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number> sections 43C subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 12.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> sections 43D subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 12.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> sections 43E subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 12.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number> sections 43F subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 12.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number> sections 45 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number> Section 45 re-numbered as sub-section (1) thereof, by Act 35 
of 2008, sec. 13.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 13.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number> sections 45 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 14.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number> sections 52 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 15.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number> sections 53 subs. by Act 29 of 2004, (w.r.e.f. 21-9-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>Section 53 re-numbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 35 
of 2008, sec. 16.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number> Ins. by Act 35 of 2008, sec. 16.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>