<act><title>THE NATIONAL LEGAL SERVICES AUTHORITY (LOK 
ADALATS) REGULATIONS, 20091</title> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> These regulations may 
be called The National Legal Services Authority (Lok Adalats) Regulations, 2009. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-In these regulations, unless the context 
otherwise requires,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> 'Act' means the Legal Services Authorities Act, 1987 (39 of 1987); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> 'Lok Adalats' means Lok Adalats to be organised under section 19 of the 
  Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> all other words and expressions used but not defined in these 
  regulations and defined in the Legal Services Authorities Act, 1987 (39 of 
  1987) or the National Legal Services Authority Rules, 1995 shall have the 
  meanings respectively assigned to them in the said Act or rules. 
</section>


</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>3</number> Procedure for organising Lok Adalats. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Lok Adalats 
may be organised by the State Authorities or District Authorities or Supreme 
Court Legal Services Committee or High Court Legal Services Committee or, as the 
case may be, the Taluk Legal Services Committees at regular intervals and such 
Lok Adalats shall be organised for a definite geographical area as the aforesaid 
Authorities or Committees think fit: 
 Provided that, special Lok Adalats shall be organised for all Family Courts 
at regular intervals. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Member-Secretary or Secretary of the High Court Legal Services 
Committee or District Authority or, as the case may be, the Chairman of the 
Taluk Legal Services Committee may associate the members of the legal 
profession, college students, social organisations, charitable and philanthropic 
institutions and other similar organisations for organising the Lok Adalats. 



</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>4</number> Intimation to the State Authority. </title>-The Secretary of the 
High Court Legal Services Committee or District Authority or Chairman of the 
Taluk Legal Services Committee, as the case may be, shall inform the State 
Authority about the proposal to organise the Lok Adalat, well before the date on 
which the Lok Adalat is proposed to be organised, and furnish the following 
information to the State Authority, namely:- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> the place and the date on which the Lok Adalat is proposed to be 
  organised; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> whether any of the organisations as referred to in sub-regulation (2) 
  of regulation 3 above have agreed to associate themselves with Lok Adalat; 

 </section><section><number>iii</number> categories and nature of cases, viz ., pending cases or 
  pre-litigation disputes, proposed to be placed before the Lok Adalat; 
 </section><section><title></title><number>iv</number> number of cases proposed to be brought before the Lok 
  Adalat in each category; 
 </section><section><number>v</number> any other information relevant to the convening and organising of the 
  Lok Adalat. </section>


</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>5</number> Notice to parties concerned. </title>-The Member-Secretary or 
Secretary of the High Court Legal Services Committee or District Authority or, 
as the case may be, the Chairman of the Taluk Legal Services Committee convening 
and organising the Lok Adalat shall inform every party concerned whose case is 
referred to the Adalat, well in time so as to afford him an opportunity to 
prepare himself for the Lok Adalat: 
 Provided that such notice may be dispensed with, if the court while referring 
the case to the Lok Adalat fixes or informs the date and time of the Lok Adatat, 
in the presence of the parties or their advocates: 
 Provided further that if a party is not willing to refer their case to Lok 
Adalat, the case may be considered on its merits by the court concerned. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>6</number> Composition of Lok Adalat. </title>- 
 
 <section><title></title><number>a</number> At State Authority Level.-The Member-Secretary 
  organising the Lok Adalat shall constitute benches of the Lok Adalats, each 
  bench comprising of a sitting or retired Judge of the High Court or a serving 
  or retired judicial officer and any one or both of the following:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a member from the legal profession; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a social worker of repute who is engaged in the upliftment of the 
    weaker sections of the people, including the Scheduled Castes, the Scheduled 
    Tribes, women, children, rural and urban labour and interested in the 
    implementation of legal services schemes or programmes. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> At High Court Level.-The Secretary of the High Court Legal Services 
  Committee organising the Lok Adalat shall constitute benches of the Lok 
  Adalats, each bench comprising of a sitting or retired Judge of the High Court 
  or a serving or retired judicial officer and any one or both of the 
  following:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a member from the legal profession; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a social worker belonging to the category as mentioned in item (ii) 
    of sub-para (a) above. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>c</number> At District Level.-The Secretary of the District Authority organising 
  the Lok Adalats shall constitute benches of the Lok Adalats, each bench 
  comprising of a sitting or retired judicial officer and any one or both of the 
  following:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a member from the legal profession; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a social worker belonging to the category as mentioned in item (ii) 
    of sub-para (a) above or a person engaged in para-legal activities of the 
    area, preferably a woman. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>d</number> At Taluk Level.-The Chairman of the Taluk Legal Services Committee 
  organising the Lok Adalat shall constitute benches of the Lok Adalat, each 
  bench comprising of a sitting or retired judicial officer and any one or both 
  of the following:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a member from the legal profession; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a social worker belonging to the category as mentioned in item (ii) 
    of sub-para (a) above or a person engaged in para-legal activities of the 
    area, preferably a woman. </subsection></section>

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>7</number> Allotment of cases to Lok Adalats. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The 
Member-Secretary, the Secretary of the High Court Legal Services Committee, the 
District Authority or Chairman of the Taluk Legal Services Committee, as the 
case may be, shall assign specific cases to each bench of the Lok Adalat. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Member-Secretary, the Secretary of the High Court Legal Services 
Committee or the District Authority or Chairman of the Taluk Legal Services 
Committee, as the case may be, may prepare a cause list for each bench of the 
Lok Adalat and intimate the same to all concerned at least two days before the 
date of holding of the Lok Adalat. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every bench of the Lok Adalat shall make sincere efforts to bring about a 
conciliated settlement in every case put before it without bringing about any 
kind of coercion, threat, undue influence, allurement or misrepresentation. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>8</number> Holding of Lok Adalats. </title>-Lok Adalats may be organised at 
such time and place and on such days, including holidays as the State Authority, 
the High Court Legal Services Committee, the District Authority or the Taluk 
Legal Services Committee, as the case may be, organising the Lok Adalat deems 
appropriate. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>9</number> Jurisdiction of Lok Adalats. </title>-Lok Adalats shall have the 
power only to help the parties to arrive at a compromise or settlement between 
the parties to a dispute and, while so doing, it shall not issue any direction 
of order in respect of such dispute between the parties. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>10</number> Reference of cases and matters. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Lok Adalat shall 
get jurisdiction to deal with a case only when a court of competent jurisdiction 
orders the case to be referred in the manner prescribed in section 20 of the Act 
or under section 89 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 ( 5 of 1908). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A mechanical reference of pending cases to Lok Adalat shall be avoided 
and the referring court shall, prima facie satisfy itself that there 
are chances of settlement of the case through Lok Adalat and the case is 
appropriate to be referred to Lok Adalat: 
 Provided that matters relating to divorce and criminal cases which are not 
compoundable under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) shall not be 
referred to Lok Adalat. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In a pending case where only one of the parties had made application to 
the court for referring, the case to Lok Adalat, or where the court suo motu 
is satisfied that the case is appropriate to take cognizance by Lok Adalat, 
the case shall not be referred to the Lok Adalat except after giving a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard to the parties. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>11</number> Summoning of records and responsibility for its safe custody. 
</title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Member-Secretary, the Secretary of the High Court Legal 
Services Committee, the District Authority or, as the case may be, the Chairman 
of the Taluk Legal Services Committee may call for the judicial records of 
pending cases which are referred to the Lok Adalat under section 20 of the Act 
from the courts concerned. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The officer duly authorised by the Member Secretary, the Secretary of the 
High Court Legal Services Committee, the District Authority or the Chairman of 
the Taluk Legal Services Committee, as the case may be, shall be responsible for 
the safe custody of records from receiving of the same from court till they are 
returned. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The judicial records shall be returned within ten days of the Lok Adalat 
irrespective of whether or not the case is settled by the Lok Adalat with an 
endorsement about the result of proceedings: 
 Provided that wherever it is appropriate, the court concerned from where the 
records are called may permit the records to be retained beyond the period of 
ten days. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every judicial authority is expected to co-operate in transmission of the 
judicial records. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>12</number> Pre-litigation matters. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In a pre-litigation matter 
it may be ensured that the court for which a Lok Adalat is organised has 
territorial jurisdiction to adjudicate in the matter. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Before referring a pre-litigation matter to Lok Adalat the Authority 
concerned or Committee, as the case may be, shall give a reasoanble hearing to 
the parties concerned: 
 Provided that the version of each party, shall be obtained by the Authority 
concerned or, as the case may be, the Committee for placing it before the Lok 
Adalat. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An award based on settlement between the parties can be challenged only 
on violation or procedure prescribed in section 20 of the Act by filing a 
petition under articles 226 and 227 of the Constitution of India. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>13</number> Procedure in Lok Adalats. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Members of Lok Adalat 
have the role of statutory conciliators only and have no judicial role and they, 
mutatis mutandis, may follow the procedure laid down in sections 67 to 
76 of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996 (26 of 1996). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Members of Lok Adalat shall not pressurise or coerce any of the parties, 
to compromise or settle cases or matters, either directly or indirectly. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In a Lok Adalat the members shall discuss the subject matter with the 
parties for arriving at a just settlement or compromise and such members of Lok 
Adalat shall assist the parties in an independent and impartial manner in their 
attempt to reach amicable settlement of their dispute: 
 Provided that if it is found necessary the assistance of an independent 
person or a trained mediator may also be availed by the Lok Adalat. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Members of Lok Adalat shall be guided by principles of natural justice, 
equity, fairplay, objectivity, giving consideration to, among other things, the 
rights and obligations of the parties, custom and usages and the circumstances 
surrounding the dispute. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Lok Adalat may conduct the proceedings in such a manner as it 
considers appropriate taking into account the circumstances of the case, wishes 
of the parties including any request by a party to the Lok Adalat to hear oral 
statements, and the need for a speedy settlement of the dispute. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Lok Adalat shall not determine a reference, at its own instance, but 
shall determine only on the basis of a compromise or settlement between the 
parties by making an award in terms of the compromise or settlement arrived at: 

 Provided that no Lok Adalat has the power to hear the parties to adjudicate 
their dispute as a regular court: 
 Provided further that the award of the Lok Adalat is neither a verdict nor an 
opinion arrived at by any decision making process. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>14</number> Administrative assistance. </title>-Administrative assistance 
for facilitating Lok Adalat proceedings may be arranged by suitable institutions 
or persons engaged in providing legal services. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>15</number> Formulating compromise or settlements. </title>-The Lok Adalat 
may, at any stage of the proceedings, make proposal for a settlement of the 
dispute and such proposal need not be accompanied by a statement of the reasons 
therefor. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>16</number> Communication between Lok Adalat and parties. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> A Lok 
Adalat may invite the parties to meet it or may communicate with it orally or in 
writing and it may meet or communicate with the parties together or with each of 
them separately. The factual information concerning the dispute received from a 
party may be disclosed to the other party in order that the other party may have 
the opportunity to present any explanation: 
 Provided that the Lok Adalat shall not disclose any information, if one of 
the party desires to keep it confidential. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Each party may on its own initiative or at the invitation of the Lok 
Adalat, submit suggestions for settlement of the dispute. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> When it appears to the Lok Adalat that there exists elements of a 
settlement which may be acceptable to the parties, the terms of a possible 
settlement may be formulated by the Lok Adalat and given to the parties for 
their observations and modifications, if any, suggested by the parties can be 
taken into consideration and terms of a possible settlement may be re-formulated 
by the Lok Adalat. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the parties reach a compromise or settlement of the dispute, the Lok 
Adalat may draw up or assist the parties in drawing up the terms of such 
compromise or settlement. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>17</number> Award. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Drawing up of the award is merely an 
administrative act by incorporating the terms of settlement or compromise agreed 
by the parties under the guidance and assistance from Lok Adalat. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When both parties sign or affix their thumb impression and the members of 
the Lok Adalat countersign it, it becomes an award (see a specimen at 
 Appendix I) Every award of the Lok Adalat shall be categorical and lucid and 
shall be written in regional language used in the local courts or in English. It 
shall also contain particulars of the case, viz ., case number, name of 
court and names of parties, date of receipt, register number assigned to the 
case in the permanent register (maintained as provided under regulation 20) and 
date of settlement. Wherever the parties are represented by counsel, they should 
also be required to sign the settlement or award before the members of the Lok 
Adalat affix their signature. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In cases referred to Lok Adalat from a court, it shall be mentioned in 
the award that the plaintiff or petitioner is entitled to refund of the court 
fees remitted. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the parties are not accompanied or represented by counsel, the 
members of the Lok Adalat shall also verify the identity of parties, before 
recording the settlement. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Member of the Lok Adalat shall ensure that the parties affix their 
signatures only after fully understanding the terms of settlement arrived at and 
recorded. The members of the Lok Adalat shall also satisfy themselves about the 
following before affixing their signatures:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> that the terms of settlement are not unreasonable or illegal or 
  one-sided; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> that the parties have entered into the settlement voluntarily and not 
  on account of any threat, coercion or undue influence. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> Members of the Lok Adalat should affix their signatures only in 
settlement reached before them and should avoid affixing signatures to 
settlement reached by the parties outside the Lok Adalat with the assistance of 
some third parties, to ensure that the Lok Adalats are not used by unscrupulous 
parties to commit fraud, forgery, etc. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Lok Adalat shall not grant any bail or a divorce by mutual consent. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The original award shall form part of the judicial records (in 
pre-litigation matter, the original award may be kept with the Legal Services 
Authority or Committee, concerned) and a copy of the award shall be given to 
each of the parties duly certifying them to be true by the officer designated by 
the Member-Secretary or Secretary of the High Court Legal Services Committee or 
District Legal Services Authority or, as the case may be, the Chairman of Taluk 
Legal Services Committees free of cost and the official seal of the Authority 
concerned or Committee shall be affixed on all awards. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>18</number> Confidentiality. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The members of the Lok Adalat and 
the parties shall keep confidential all matters relating to the proceedings in 
the Lok Adalat and the members of the Lok Adalat shall not be compelled to 
disclose the matters which took place in the Lok Adalat proceedings before any 
court of law, except where such disclosure is necessary for purposes of 
implementation and enforcement of the award. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The views expressed and discussions made by parties during the 
proceedings of Lok Adalat in respect of the possible settlement of a dispute and 
the proposals made by the members of Lok Adalat or admission made by any party 
or the conduct of the parties in the course of the proceeding before Lok Adalat 
shall not be brought in evidence or made use of in other court or arbitral 
proceedings. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Members of the Lok Adalat shall not record the statement of any of the 
parties or record any conduct of the parties or express any opinion in such a 
manner as it would prejudice such party in any other proceedings before a court 
or arbitrator. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If any member of the Lok Adalat violates the confidentiality and the 
ethical concerns which are akin to any other judicial proceedings, such member 
shall be removed from the panel of members of Lok Adalat. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>19</number> Failure of Lok Adalat proceedings. </title>-If a pre-litigation 
matter is not settled in the Lok Adalat, the parties may be advised to resort to 
other Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR) techniques or to approach a court of 
law and in appropriate- cases they may be advised about the availability of 
legal aid. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>20</number> Compilation of results. </title>-At the conclusion of session of 
the Lok Adalat, the officer designated by the Member-Secretary, the Secretary of 
the High Court Legal Services Committee, the District Authority or the Chairman 
of the Taluk Legal Services Committee, as case may be, shall compile the results 
for submission to the State Authority in the proforma given in Appendix-II 
. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>21</number> Maintenance of panel of names of Lok Adalat members. 
</title>-The Member Secretary or Secretary of the High Court Legal Services 
Committee or District Authority or, as the case may be, the Chairman of the 
Taluk Legal Services Committee shall maintain a panel of names of retired 
judicial officers, advocates and social workers to work in Lok Adalats. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>22</number> Procedure for maintaining record of cases referred under section 
20 of the Act or otherwise. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The officer designated by the 
Member-Secretary, the Secretary of the High Court Legal Services committee, the 
District Authority or the Chairman of the Taluk Legal Services Committee, as the 
case may be, shall maintain a permanent register wherein all the cases and 
pre-litigation matters received by him by way of reference to the Lok Adalat 
shall be entered giving particulars of:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> date of receipt; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> nature of the case or pre-litigation matter; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> other particulars, if any; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> date of compromise or settlement and the manner in which the case or 
  matter was finally disposed of; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> date of return of the case file. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> A copy of the award, if passed, duly certified in the manner stated in 
regulation 17 shall be kept in the office of the Authority or Committee, as the 
case may be, as a permanent record. (3) Records other than the original of 
the awards of pre-litigation Lok Adalats may be destroyed after a period of 
three years from the date of disposal of the matter by Lok Adalat. 

</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>23</number> Appearance of lawyers and the procedure to be followed in the 
cases before Lok Adalats. </title>-The appearance of lawyers on behalf of the 
parties at the Lok Adalat shall not be barred and an effort shall be made to 
encourage the parties to be present personally. The lawyers may be advised to 
avoid wearing their robes and bands during the proceedings before the Lok 
Adalat. 

</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title><title> </title>
 <article><title><number>24</number> Application of regulations. </title>-The above regulations shall 
be applicable in the same manner with appropriate changes to the Lok Adalats 
organised by the National Legal Services Authority and the Supreme Court Legal 
Services Committee. 

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Came into force on 20-10-2009.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>