<act><title>

The Contempt of 
    Courts Act, 1971</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Contempt of Courts Act, 1971.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India:
 
Provided 
    that it shall not apply to the State of Jammu and Kashmir except to the 
    extent to which the provisions of this Act relate to contempt of the Supreme 
    Court.
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “contempt of court” means civil contempt 
    or criminal contempt;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “civil contempt” means wilful 
    disobedience to any judgment, decree, direction, order, writ or other 
    process of a court or wilful breach of an undertaking given to a court;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “criminal contempt” means the 
    publication (whether by words, spoken or written, or by signs, or by visible 
    representation, or otherwise) of any matter or the doing of any other act 
    whatsoever which—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   scandalises or tends to scandalise, or 
    lowers or tends to lower the authority of, any court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   prejudices, or interferes or tends to 
    interfere with, the due course of any judicial proceeding; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   interferes or tends to interfere with, 
    or obstructs or tends to obstruct, the administration of justice in any 
    other manner;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>   “High Court” means the High Court for a 
    State or a Union territory, and includes the court of the Judicial 
    Commissioner in any Union territory.
  










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Innocent publication and distribution of matter not contempt.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person shall not be guilty of contempt of court on the ground that he has 
    published (whether by words, spoken or written, or by signs, or by visible 
    representations, or otherwise) any matter which interferes or tends to 
    interfere with, or obstructs or tends to obstruct, the course of justice in 
    connection with any civil or criminal proceeding pending at that time of 
    publication, if at that time he had no reasonable grounds for believing that 
    the proceeding was pending. —(1) 
    A person shall not be guilty of contempt of court on the ground that he has 
    published (whether by words, spoken or written, or by signs, or by visible 
    representations, or otherwise) any matter which interferes or tends to 
    interfere with, or obstructs or tends to obstruct, the course of justice in 
    connection with any civil or criminal proceeding pending at that time of 
    publication, if at that time he had no reasonable grounds for believing that 
    the proceeding was pending." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in this Act or any other 
    law for the time being in force, the publication of any such matter as is 
    mentioned in sub-section (1) in connection with any civil or criminal 
    proceeding which is not pending at the time of publication shall not be 
    deemed to constitute contempt of court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    person shall not be guilty of contempt of court on the ground that he has 
    distributed a publication containing any such matter as is mentioned in 
    sub-section (1), if at the time of distribution he had no reasonable grounds 
    for believing that it contained or was likely to contain any such matter as 
    aforesaid:
 
Provided 
    that this sub-section shall not apply in respect of the distribution of—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   any publication which is a book or paper 
    printed or published otherwise than in conformity with the rules contained 
    in section 3 of the Press and Registration of Books Act, 1867 (25 of 1867);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any publication which is a newspaper 
    published otherwise than in conformity with the rules contained in section 5 
    of the said Act.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, a judicial proceeding—
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   is said to be pending—
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>A</number>   in the case of a civil proceeding, when 
    it is instituted by the filing of a plaint or otherwise,
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>B</number>   in the case of a criminal proceeding 
    under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, or any 
    other law—
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   where it relates to the commission of an 
    offence, when the charge-sheet or challan is filed, or when the court 
    issues summons or warrant, as the case may be, against the accused, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   in any other case, when the court takes 
    cognizance of the matter to which the proceeding relates, and
 
      in the case of 
    a civil or criminal proceeding, shall be deemed to continue to be pending 
    until it is heard and finally decided, that is to say, in a case where an 
    appeal or revision is competent, until the appeal or revision is heard and 
    finally decided or, where no appeal or revision is preferred, until the 
    period of limitation prescribed for such appeal or revision has expired;
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   which has been heard and finally decided 
    shall not be deemed to be pending merely by reason of the fact that 
    proceedings for the execution of the decree, order or sentence passed 
    therein are pending.
  










 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Fair and accurate report of judicial proceeding not contempt.—Subject 
    to the provisions contained in section 7, a person shall not be guilty of 
    contempt of court for publishing a fair and accurate report of a judicial 
    proceeding or any stage thereof. —Subject 
    to the provisions contained in section 7, a person shall not be guilty of 
    contempt of court for publishing a fair and accurate report of a judicial 
    proceeding or any stage thereof." 
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Fair criticism of judicial act not 
      contempt.—A 
      person shall not be guilty of contempt of court for publishing any fair 
      comment on the merits of any case which has been heard and finally 
      decided. —A 
    person shall not be guilty of contempt of court for publishing any fair 
    comment on the merits of any case which has been heard and finally decided." 
  


 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Complaint against presiding officers of subordinate courts when not 
    contempt.—A 
    person shall not be guilty of contempt of court in respect of any statement 
    made by him in good faith concerning the presiding officer of any 
    subordinate court to—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   any other subordinate court, or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the High Court,
 
to which it is subordinate.
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this section, “subordinate court” means any court subordinate to a High 
    Court.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Publication of information relating to proceedings in chambers or in 
    camera not contempt except in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, a person shall not be guilty 
    of contempt of court for publishing a fair and accurate report of a judicial 
    proceeding before any court sitting in chambers or in camera except 
    in the following cases, that is to say,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   where the publication is contrary to the 
    provisions of any enactment for the time being in force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   where the court, on grounds of public 
    policy or in exercise of any power vested in it, expressly prohibits the 
    publication of all information relating to the proceeding or of information 
    of the description which is published;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   where the court sits in chambers or 
    in camera for reasons connected with public order or the security of the 
    State, the publication of information relating to those proceedings;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   where the information relates to a 
    secret process, discovery or invention which is an issue in the proceedings.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions contained in sub-section (1), a person 
    shall not be guilty of contempt of court for publishing the text or a fair 
    and accurate summary of the whole, or any part, of an order made by a court 
    sitting in chambers or in camera, unless the court has expressly 
    prohibited the publication thereof on grounds of public policy, or for 
    reasons connected with public order or the security of the State, or on the 
    ground that it contains information relating to a secret process, discovery 
    or invention, or in exercise of any power vested in it.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Other defences not affected.—Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall be construed as implying that any other defence 
    which would have been a valid defence in any proceedings for contempt of 
    court has ceased to be available merely by reason of the provisions of this 
    Act. —Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall be construed as implying that any other defence 
    which would have been a valid defence in any proceedings for contempt of 
    court has ceased to be available merely by reason of the provisions of this 
    Act." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Act not to imply enlargement of scope of 
      contempt.—Nothing contained in this Act shall be 
      construed as implying that any disobedience, breach, publication or other 
      act is punishable as contempt of court which would not be so punishable a 
      part from this Act. —Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall be construed as implying that any disobedience, 
    breach, publication or other act is punishable as contempt of court which 
    would not be so punishable a part from this Act." 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Power of High Court to punish contempts of subordinate courts.—Every 
    High Court shall have and exercise the same jurisdiction, powers and 
    authority, in accordance with the same procedure and practice, in respect of 
    contempts of courts subordinate to it as it has and exercises in respect of 
    contempts of itself: —Every 
    High Court shall have and exercise the same jurisdiction, powers and 
    authority, in accordance with the same procedure and practice, in respect of 
    contempts of courts subordinate to it as it has and exercises in respect of 
    contempts of itself\:" 
 
Provided 
    that no High Court shall take cognizance of a contempt alleged to have been 
    committed in respect of a court subordinate to it where such contempt is an 
    offence punishable under the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Power of High Court to try offences committed or offenders found outside 
    jurisdiction.—A 
    High Court shall have jurisdiction to inquire into or try a contempt of 
    itself or of any court subordinate to it, whether the contempt is alleged to 
    have been committed within or outside the local limits of its jurisdiction, 
    and whether the person alleged to be guilty of contempt is within or outside 
    such limits. —A 
    High Court shall have jurisdiction to inquire into or try a contempt of 
    itself or of any court subordinate to it, whether the contempt is alleged to 
    have been committed within or outside the local limits of its jurisdiction, 
    and whether the person alleged to be guilty of contempt is within or outside 
    such limits." 
  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Punishment for contempt of court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act or in any other law, a 
    contempt of court may be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand 
    rupees, or with both: —(1) 
    Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act or in any other law, a 
    contempt of court may be punished with simple imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand 
    rupees, or with both\:" 
 
Provided 
    that the accused may be discharged or the punishment awarded may be remitted 
    on apology being made to the satisfaction of the court.
 

    Explanation.—An 
    apology shall not be rejected merely on the ground that it is qualified or 
    conditional if the accused makes it bona fide.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force, no court shall impose a sentence in excess of that specified in 
    sub-section (1) for any contempt either in respect of itself or of a court 
    subordinate to it.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, where a person is found 
    guilty of a civil contempt, the court, if it considers that a fine will not 
    meet the ends of justice and that a sentence of imprisonment is necessary 
    shall, instead of sentencing him to simple imprisonment, direct that he be 
    detained in a civil prison for such period not exceeding six months as it 
    may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where the person found guilty of contempt of court in respect of any 
    undertaking given to a court is a company, every person who, at the time the 
    contempt was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
    company for the conduct of business of the company, as well as the company, 
    shall be deemed to be guilty of the contempt and the punishment may be 
    enforced, with the leave of the court, by the detention in civil prison of 
    each such person:
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to such punishment if he proves that the contempt was committed 
    without his knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent its 
    commission.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (4), where the contempt of 
    court referred to therein has been committed by a company and it is proved 
    that the contempt has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or 
    is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, 
    secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the contempt and the 
    punishment may be enforced, with the leave of the court, by the detention in 
    civil prison of such director, manager, secretary or other officer.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of sub-sections (4) and (5),—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body 
    corporate and includes a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a 
    firm, means a partner in the firm.
  









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>13</number> 
    Contempts not punishable in certain cases.—Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in any law for the time being in force,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   no court shall impose a 
    sentence under this Act for a contempt of court unless it is satisfied that 
    the contempt is of such a nature that it substantially interferes, or tends 
    substantially to interfere with the due course of justice;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the court may permit, in any 
    proceeding for contempt of court, justification by truth as a valid defence 
    if it is satisfied that it is in public interest and the request for 
    invoking the said defence is bona fide.]
  












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Procedure where contempt is in the face of the Supreme Court or a High 
    Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When it is alleged, or appears to the Supreme Court or the High Court upon 
    its own view, that a person has been guilty of contempt committed in its 
    presence or hearing, the Court may cause such person to be detained in 
    custody, and, at any time before the rising of the Court, on the same day, 
    or as early as possible thereafter, shall— —(1) 
    When it is alleged, or appears to the Supreme Court or the High Court upon 
    its own view, that a person has been guilty of contempt committed in its 
    presence or hearing, the Court may cause such person to be detained in 
    custody, and, at any time before the rising of the Court, on the same day, 
    or as early as possible thereafter, shall—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   cause him to be informed in 
    writing of the contempt with which he is charged;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   afford him an opportunity to 
    make his defence to the charge;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   after taking such evidence as 
    may be necessary or as may be offered by such person and after hearing him, 
    proceed, either forthwith or after adjournment, to determine the matter of 
    the charge; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   make such order for the 
    punishment or discharge of such person as may be just.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where a person 
    charged with contempt under that sub-section applies, whether orally or in 
    writing, to have the charge against him tried by some Judge other than the 
    Judge or Judges in whose presence or hearing the offence is alleged to have 
    been committed, and the Court is of opinion that it is practicable to do so 
    and that in the interests of proper administration of justice the 
    application should be allowed, it shall cause the matter to be placed, 
    together with a statement of the facts of the case, before the Chief Justice 
    for such directions as he may think fit to issue as respects the trial 
    thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, in any trial of a 
    person charged with contempt under sub-section (1) which is held, in 
    pursuance of a direction given under sub-section (2), by a Judge other than 
    the Judge or Judges in whose presence or hearing the offence is alleged to 
    have been committed, it shall not be necessary for the Judge or Judges in 
    whose presence or hearing the offence is alleged to have been committed to 
    appear as a witness and the statement placed before the Chief Justice under 
    sub-section (2) shall be treated as evidence in the case.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Pending the determination of the charge, the Court may direct that a person 
    charged with contempt under this section shall be detained in such custody 
    as it may specify:
 
Provided 
    that he shall be released on bail, if a bond for such sum of money as the 
    Court thinks sufficient is executed with or without sureties conditioned 
    that the person charged shall attend at the time and place mentioned in the 
    bond and shall continue to so attend until otherwise directed by the Court:
 
Provided 
    further that the Court may, if it thinks fit, instead of taking bail from 
    such person, discharge him on his executing a bond without sureties for his 
    attendance as aforesaid.
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Cognizance of criminal contempt in other cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the case of a criminal contempt, other than a contempt referred to in 
    section 14, the Supreme Court or the High Court may take action on its own 
    motion or on a motion made by—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the Advocate-General, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   any other person, with the 
    consent in writing to the Advocate-General, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[or]
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>c</number>   in relation to 
    the High Court for the Union territory of Delhi, such Law Officer as the 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
    this behalf, or any other person, with the consent in writing of such Law 
    Officer.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the case of any criminal contempt of a subordinate court, the High Court may 
    take action on a reference made to it by the subordinate court or on a 
    motion made by the Advocate-General or, in relation to a Union territory, by 
    such Law Officer as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every motion or reference made under this section shall specify the contempt 
    of which the person charged is alleged to be guilty.
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this section, the expression “Advocate-General” means—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in relation to the Supreme 
    Court, the Attorney-General or the Solicitor-General;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in relation to the High Court, 
    the Advocate-General of the State or any of the States for which the High 
    Court has been established;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   in relation to the Court of a 
    Judicial Commissioner, such Law Officer as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.
  














 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>16</number> Contempt by Judge, Magistrate or other person acting 
      judicially.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of any law for 
      the time being in force, a Judge, Magistrate or other person acting 
      judicially shall also be liable for contempt of his own court or of any 
      other court in the same manner as any other individual is liable and the 
      provisions of this Act shall, so far as may be, apply 
      accordingly. —(1) 
    Subject to the provisions of any law for the time being in force, a Judge, 
    Magistrate or other person acting judicially shall also be liable for 
    contempt of his own court or of any other court in the same manner as any 
    other individual is liable and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as 
    may be, apply accordingly." 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing in this section shall apply to any observations or 
      remarks made by a Judge, Magistrate or other person acting judicially, 
      regarding a subordinate court in an appeal or revision pending before such 
      Judge, Magistrate or other person against the order or judgment of the 
      subordinate court.
  






 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Procedure after cognizance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notice of every proceeding under section 15 shall be served personally on 
    the person charged, unless the court for reasons to be recorded directs 
    otherwise. —(1) 
    Notice of every proceeding under section 15 shall be served personally on 
    the person charged, unless the court for reasons to be recorded directs 
    otherwise." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    notice shall be accompanied—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the case of proceedings 
    commenced on a motion, by a copy of the motion as also copies of the 
    affidavits, if any, on which such motion is founded; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in case of proceedings 
    commenced on a reference by a subordinate court, by a copy of the reference.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Court may, if it is satisfied that a person charged under section 15 is 
    likely to abscond or keep out of the way to avoid service of the notice, 
    order the attachment of his property of such value or amount as it may deem 
    reasonable.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every attachment under sub-section (3) shall be effected in the manner 
    provided in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908)<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>, 
    for the attachment of property in execution of a decree for payment of 
    money, and if, after such attachment, the person charged appears and shows 
    to the satisfaction of the court that he did not abscond or keep out of the 
    way to avoid service of the notice, the Court shall order the release of his 
    property from attachment upon such terms as to costs or otherwise as it may 
    think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any 
    person charged with contempt under section 15 may file an affidavit in 
    support of his defence, and the court may determine the matter of the charge 
    either on the affidavits filed or after taking such further evidence as may 
    be necessary, and pass such order as the justice of the case requires.
  













 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Hearing of cases of criminal contempt to be by Benches.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every case of criminal contempt under section 15 shall be heard and 
    determined by a Bench of not less than two Judges.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Sub-section (1) shall not apply to the Court of a Judicial Commissioner.
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An appeal shall lie as of right from any order or decision of High Court in 
    the exercise of its jurisdiction to punish for contempt— —(1) 
    An appeal shall lie as of right from any order or decision of High Court in 
    the exercise of its jurisdiction to punish for contempt—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   where the order or decision is 
    that of a single Judge, to a Bench of not less than two Judges of the Court;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   where the order or decision is 
    that of a Bench, to the Supreme Court:
 
Provided 
    that where the order or decision is that of the Court of the Judicial 
    Commissioner in any Union territory, such appeal shall lie to the Supreme 
    Court.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Pending any appeal, the appellate Court may order that—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the execution of the 
    punishment or order appealed against be suspended;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if the appellant is in 
    confinement, he be released on bail; and   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the appeal be heard 
    notwithstanding that the appellant has not purged his contempt.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where any person aggrieved by any order against which an appeal may be filed 
    satisfies the High Court that he intends to prefer an appeal, the High Court 
    may also exercise all or any of the powers conferred by sub-section (2).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An 
    appeal under sub-section (1) shall be filed—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the case of an appeal to a 
    Bench of the High Court, within thirty days;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in the case of an appeal to 
    the Supreme Court, within sixty days,
 
from the date of the order appealed against.
  







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>20</number> Limitation for actions for contempt.—No court shall initiate any 
      proceedings of contempt, either on its own motion or otherwise, after the 
      expiry of a period of one year from the date on which the contempt is 
      alleged to have been committed. —No 
    court shall initiate any proceedings of contempt, either on its own motion 
    or otherwise, after the expiry of a period of one year from the date on 
    which the contempt is alleged to have been committed." 
  












 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>21</number> Act not to apply to Nyaya Panchayats or other village 
      courts.—Nothing contained in this Act shall apply in 
      relation to contempt of Nyaya Panchayats or other village courts, 
      by whatever name known, for the administration of justice, established 
      under any law. —Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall apply in relation to contempt of Nyaya 
    Panchayats or other village courts, by whatever name known, for the 
    administration of justice, established under any law." 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>22</number> Act to be in addition to, and not in derogation of, other laws 
      relating to contempt.—The provisions of this Act shall be in addition 
      to, and not in derogation of the provisions of any other law relating to 
      contempt of courts. —The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of the 
    provisions of any other law relating to contempt of courts." 
  



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Power of Supreme Court and High Courts to make rules.—The 
    Supreme Court or, as the case may be, any High Court, may make rules, not 
    inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, providing for any matter 
    relating to its procedure.
 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Repeal.—The 
    Contempt of Courts Act, 1952 (32 of 1952), is hereby repealed. 
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Now see Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by Act 6 of 
    2006, sec. 2, for section 13 (w.e.f. 17-3-2006). Section 13, before 
    substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   
    Ins. by Act 45 of 1976, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 30-3-1976).  tc 
    "  1. Ins. by 
    Act 45 of 1976, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 30-3-1976)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>    Now see Code of  Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>