<act><title>

    THE INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT BANK OF INDIA  ACT, 1964</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Board” means the Board of 
    Directors of the Development Bank;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Development Bank” means the 
    Industrial Development Bank of India established under section 3;  
 

1[(c)    
    “industrial concern” means any concern engaged or to be engaged in,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the manufacture, preservation or 
    processing of goods;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    shipping;  
 

2[(iii)    
    mining included development of mines;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    the hotel industry;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    the transport of passengers or 
    goods by road or by water or 
3[by 
    air or by ropeway or by lift];  
 

4[(vi)    
    the generation, storage or distribution of electricity or any other form of 
    energy;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>    the maintenance, repair, 
    testing or servicing of 
5[machinery 
    or equivalent] of any description or vehicles or vessels or motor 
    boats or trailers or tractors; 
1[machinery 
    or equivalent] of any description or vehicles or vessels or motor 
    boats or trailers or tractors;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>    assembling, repairing or 
    packing any article with the aid of machinery or power;  
 

6[(ix)    
    the setting up of, or development of, an industrial area or an industrial 
    estate;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>    fishing or providing shore 
    facilities for fishing or maintenance thereof;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>    providing special or technical 
    knowledge or other services for the promotion of industrial growth; or  
 

7[(xii)    
    providing engineering, technical, financial management, marketing or other 
    services or facilities for industry;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>xiii</number>    service industry such as 
    altering, ornamenting, polishing, finishing, oiling, washing, cleaning or 
    otherwise treating or adapting any article or substance with a view of its 
    use, sale, transport, delivery or disposal;  
 </section><section>
<number>xiv</number>    providing medical, health or 
    other allied services;  
 </section><section>
<number>xv</number>    providing services relating to 
    infromation technology, telecommunication or electronics;  
 </section><section>
<number>xvi</number>    leasing, sub-leasing or giving 
    on hire or hire purchase of industrial plants, equipments, machinery or 
    other assets including vehicles, ships and aircraft;  
 </section><section>
<number>xvii</number>    such other activity as the 
    Central Government may, having regard to the objects of this Act, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf; or  
 </section><section>
<number>xviii</number>    the research and development 
    of any concept, technology design, process or product whether in relation to 
    any of the matters aforesaid, including any activities specified under 
    sub-clause (xvii), or any other matter.  
 
Explanation.— The expression 
    "processing of goods" includes any art or process for producing, preparing 
    or making an article by subjecting any material to a manual, mechanical, 
    chemical electrical or any other like operation;]  
 

8[(d)    
    “Industrial Finance Corporation” means the Industrial Finance Corporation of 
    India Limited formed and registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 
    1956);]  
 

9[(da) 
       “nationalised bank” means a corresponding new bank specified   in the 
    First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or a corresponding new bank specified in 
    the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertaking) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980);]  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    regulations made under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve 
    Bank of India constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 
    1934);  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “scheduled bank” means a bank for 
    the time being included in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of India 
    Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);  
 

10[(ga)    
    “State Bank” means the State Bank of India constituted under the  State Bank 
    of                 India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955);  
 </section><section>
<number>gb</number>    “subsidiary bank” has the 
    meaning assigned to it in the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 
    1959 (38 of 1959);]  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> "State Co-operative Bank” 
    has the same meaning as in the Reserve Bank of  India Act, 1934 (2 of 
    1 934);  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “State Financial Corporation” 
    means a financial corporation established under section 3 or section 3A of 
    the State Financial Corporation Act, 1951 (63 of 1951) and includes the
    11[Tamil 
    Nadu] Industrial Investment Corporation Limited; 
2[Tamil 
    Nadu] Industrial Investment Corporation Limited;" 
 

10[(j)    
    “Unit Trust” means the Unit Trust of India established under section 3 of 
    the Unit Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 of 1963).]
 
 
















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Establishment and incorporation of Industrial Development Bank of India.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in 
    the Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be established for the purposes 
    of this Act, a corporation to be known as the Industrial Development Bank of 
    India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Development Bank shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid having 
    perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to the provisions 
    of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property and to contract, and 
    may, by that name sue or be sued.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    head office of the Development Bank shall be at Bombay or at such other 
    place as the 

    1[Central Government] 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Development Bank may establish offices, branches or agencies at any other 
    place in or outside India.  
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[2[<number>4</number> 
    Authorised capital.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The authorised capital of the Development Bank shall be two thousand crores 
    of rupees divided into one hundred and fifty crores fully paid up equity 
    shares of rupees ten each and subject to the provisions of section 4E, fifty 
    crores of fully paid-up redeemable preference shares of rupees ten each. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Development Bank may, from time to time, by a resolution in general meeting, 
    increase the authorised capital to an amount not exceeding five thousand 
    crores of rupees consisting of such number of equity shares and redeemable 
    preference shares as it deems fit.]]
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>4A</number> Transfer of 
    capital to Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The issued capital of the Development Bank which has been subscribed by the 
    Reserve Bank as on the date immediately preceding the commencement of 
    section 5 of the Public Financial Institutions Laws (Amendment) Act,1975 
    (hereinafter referred to as the “appointed day”), shall, on such 
    commencement, stand transferred to, and vested in the Central Government.]  
 


    2[***]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>4B</number> Payment of 
    amount.—
The Reserve Bank shall be given by the Central Government, in cash, for 
    the transfer to, and vesting in, the Central Government of the issued 
    capital of the Development Bank which has been subscribed by the Reserve 
    Bank, an amount equal to the face value of the said subscribed capital.]
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>4C</number> Issued 
    capital.—
<section><number>1</number> The issued capital of the Development Bank of seven hundred 
    and fifty-three crores of rupees which stands fully vested in and subscribed 
    by the Central Government immediately before the commencement of the 
    Industrial Development Bank of India (Amendment) Act, 1995 shall, on such 
    commencement, stand divided into seventy-five crores and thirty lakh equity 
    shares of rupees ten each.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board may, from time to time, increase the issued equity share capital of 
    the Development Bank by allotment of shares to such persons and on such 
    terms and conditions as the Board may determine:  
 
Provided 
    that no increase in the issued equity capital shall be made in such a manner 
    that the Central Government holds at any time less than fifty-one per cent 
    of the issued equity capital of the Development Bank.]  
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>4D</number> Reduction of 
    share capital.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank may, by a resolution passed in a general meeting of the 
    shareholders to, reduce its share capital in any way.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, the share 
    capital may be reduced by:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    extinguishing or reducing the 
    liability on any of its equity shares in respect of share capital not paid-up;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    either with or without 
    extinguishing or reducing liability on any of its equity shares, cancelling 
    any paid-up share capital which is lost, or is unrepresented by available 
    assets; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    either with or without 
    extinguishing or reducing liability on any of its equity shares, paying off 
    any paid-up share capital which is in excess of the wants of the Development 
    Bank.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    any general meeting referred to in sub-section (1), the resolution for 
    reduction of share capital shall be passed by shareholders entitled to vote, 
    voting in person, or, where proxies are allowed by proxy, and the votes cast 
    in favour of the resolution are not less than three times the number of the 
    votes, if any, cast against the resolution by shareholders so entitled and 
    voting.]  
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>4E</number> Conversion of 
    equity shares into redeemable preference shares.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, at any time after the commencement of the 
    Industrial Development Bank of India (Amendment) Act,1995 and by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, convert such number of equity shares 
    held by it not exceeding fifty crores as it may decide into redeemable 
    preference shares.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    redeemable preference shares referred to in sub-section (1) shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    carry such fixed rate of dividend 
    as the Central Government may specify at the time of such conversion, and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    neither be transferable nor carry 
    any voting rights.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    redeemable preference shares referred to in sub-section (1) shall be 
    redeemable by the Development Bank within three years from the date of such 
    conversion in such instalments and in such manner as the Board may 
    determine.]  
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Management.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and 
    business of the Development Bank shall vest in a Board of Directors which 
    may exercise all powers and do all such acts and things, as may be exercised 
    or done by the Development Bank and are not by this Act expressly directed 
    or required to be done by the Development Bank in general meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board may direct that any power exercisable by it under this Act shall also 
    be exercisable in such cases and subject to such conditions, if any, as may 
    be specified by it, by the chairman, managing director or the whole-time 
    director.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Board in discharging its 
    functions shall act on business principles with due regard to public 
    interest.  
 


    2[***]  
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>6</number>Constitution of 
    Board.—2[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall consist of the following, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a chairman and a managing 
    director appointed by the Central Government:  
 
Provided that the same person may be 
    appointed to function both as chairman and as managing director;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    one whole-time director appointed 
    by the Central Government on the recommendation of the Board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    two directors who shall be 
    officials of the Central Government nominated by the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    three directors from amongst 
    persons having special knowledge of, and professional experience in science, 
    technology, economics, industry, banking, industrial co-operatives, law, 
    industrial finance, investment, accountancy, marketing or any other matter, 
    the special knowledge of, and professional experience in, which would, in 
    the opinion of the Central Government, be useful to the Development Bank, 
    nominated by the Central Government; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    such number of directors elected, 
    in the prescribed manner, by shareholders other than the Central Government, 
    whose names are entered on the register of shareholders of the Development 
    Bank ninety days before the date of the meeting in which such election takes 
    place on the following basis, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    where the total amount of equity 
    share capital issued to such shareholders is ten per cent. or less of the 
    total issued equity capital, two directors;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    where the total amount of equity 
    share capital issued to such shareholders is more than ten per cent. but 
    less than twenty-five per cent. of the total issued equity capital, three 
    directors; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    where the total equity share 
    capital issued to such shareholders is twenty-five per cent. or more of the 
    total issued equity capital, four directors:  
 
Provided that until the assumption of 
    charge by the elected directors under this clause, the Central Government 
    may at any time nominate such number of directors, not exceeding four, from 
    amongst persons having special knowledge of, and professional experience in 
    science, technology, economics, industry, banking, industrial co-operatives, 
    law, industrial finance, investment, accountancy, marketing or any other 
    matter, the special knowledge of, and professional experience in, which 
    would, in the opinion of the Central Government, be useful to the 
    Development Bank for carrying out its functions.]  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number>
    

    3[The chairman, the 
    managing director and the whole-time director] shall hold office for such 
    term not exceeding five years as the Central Government may specify in this 
    behalf and any person so appointed shall be eligible for re-appointment.  
 


    4[(2A) Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central Government shall have the 
    right to terminate the term of office of 

    5[the chairman, 
    managing director or the whole-time director], as the case may be, at any 
    time before the expiry of the term specified under sub-section (2) by giving 
    him notice of not less than three months in writing or three months’ salary 
    and allowances in lieu of such notice; and 

    5[the chairman, 
    managing director or the whole-time director], as the case may be, shall 
    also have the right to relinquish his office at any time before the expiry 
    of the term specified under sub-section (2) by giving to the Central 
    Government notice of not less than three months in writing.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    3[The chairman, 
    managing director and the whole-time director] shall receive such salary and 
    allowances as may be determine by the Central Government.  
 
 4[(3A) 
    The Central Government may, at any time, remove 

    5[the chairman, 
    managing director or the wholetime director], as the case may be, from 
    office:  
 
Provided 
    that no person shall be removed from his office, under this sub-section, 
    unless he has been given an opportunity of showing cause against his 
    removal.]  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    nominated director shall hold office during the pleasure of the authority 
    nominating him.  
 


    6[(4A) Subject to the 
    provisions of sub-section (4)—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    every director nominated under 
    clause (d) of sub-section (1) shall hold office for such term not exceeding 
    three years as the Central Government may specify in this behalf and 
    thereafter until his successor assumes office, and shall be eligible for re-nomination:  
 
Provided that no such director shall 
    hold office continuously for a period exceeding six years; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    every director elected under 
    clause (e) of sub-section (1) shall hold office for three years and 
    thereafter until his successor assumes office, and shall be eligible for re-election:  
 
Provided 
    that no such director shall hold office continuously for a period exceeding 
    six years.]  
 


    7[4B) The 
    shareholders, other than the Central Government, may, after giving to the 
    director a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the manner as may be 
    prescribed, by resolution passed by majority of the votes of such 
    shareholders holding in the aggregate not less than one-half of the share 
    capital held by such shareholders, remove any director elected under clause 
    (e) of sub-section (1) and elect another director in his place to fill the 
    vacancy so caused.]  
 


    8[(5) (i) A meeting of 
    the Board shall be held at least once every three months and at least four 
    meetings shall be held every year and the meetings may be held at such 
    places as may be prescribed.  
 <subsubsection>
 <number>ii</number> 
    Notice of every meeting of the Board shall be given in writing to every 
    director for the time being in India, and at his usual address in India to 
    every other director.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>5A</number> 
    Subject to the provisions contained in this Chapter, the Board may meet at 
    such times and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to 
    transaction of its business including the manner of adoption of resolutions 
    as may be prescribed.]  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    chairman, or, if for any reason he is unable to attend a meeting of the 
    Board, the managing director or, in the event of both the chairman and the 
    managing director being unable to attend a meeting, any other director 
    nominated by the chairman in this behalf and in the absence of such 
    nomination any director elected by the directors from among themselves, 
    shall preside at the meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> All 
    questions which come up before any meeting of the Board shall be decided by 
    a majority of votes of the directors present and voting, and in the event of 
    an equality of votes, the chairman, or in his absence, the managing 
    director, or in the absence of both the chairman and the managing director, 
    the person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Save 
    as provided in sub-section (7), every director of the Board shall have one 
    vote.]  
 
 
 











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>6A</number> Financial 
    Institution.—[Rep. by the Industrial Development Bank of 
India (Amendment) 
    Act, 1995 (5 of 1995), sec. 8 (w.r.e.f. 12-10-1994).]]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>6B</number> 
    Disqualification of directors.—
<section><number>1</number> A person shall not be eligible for 
    being elected as a director under clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 
    6, if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    has been found to be of unsound 
    mind by a court of competent jurisdiction and the finding is in force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    is an undischarged insolvent;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    has applied to be adjudicated as 
    an insolvent and his application is pending;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    has been convicted by a court of 
    any offence involving moral turpitude and sentenced in respect thereof to 
    imprisonment for not less than six months and a period of five years has not 
    elapsed from the date of expiry of the sentence; or " 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    has not paid any call in respect 
    of shares of the Development Bank held by him, whether along or jointly with 
    others, and six months have elapsed from the last day fixed for the payment 
    of the call.]  
  
  






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6C</number> 
    Vacation of office by director.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The office of a director shall become vacant if he—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    becomes subject to any of the 
    disqualifications mentioned in section 6B; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    resigns his office by giving 
    notice in writing under his hand and the resignation is accepted; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    absents himself from three 
    consecutive meetings of the Board without obtaining leave of absence from 
    the Board;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything in clause (a) of sub-section (1), the 
    disqualifications referred to in that clause shall not take effect—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    for thirty days from the date of 
    the adjudication, sentence or order;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where any appeal or petition is 
    preferred within thirty days aforesaid against the adjudication, sentence or 
    conviction resulting in the sentence or order until the expiry of seven days 
    from the date on which such appeal or petition is disposed of; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    where within the seven days 
    aforesaid, any further appeal or petition is preferred in respect of the 
    adjudication, sentence, conviction or order and the appeal or petition, if 
    allowed, would result in the removal of the disqualification, until such 
    further appeal or petition is disposed of.
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Executive Committee and other committees.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board shall constitute an Executive Committee consisting of the 
    chairman, the managing director, the whole-time director and such other 
    directors as it may deem fit.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Executive Committee shall discharge such functions as may be prescribed or 
    as may be delegated to it by the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Board may constitute such other committees whether consisting wholly of 
    directors or wholly of other persons or partly of directors and partly of 
    other persons for such purpose or purposes as it may think fit.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Executive Committee or any other committee constituted under this section 
    shall meet at such times and places and shall observe such rules of 
    procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings as may be 
    prescribed.  
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Fees and allowances of directors and members of committees.—The 
    directors and the members of a committee shall be paid such fees and 
    allowances as may be prescribed for attending the meetings of the Board or 
    of any committee constituted in pursuance of this Act and for attending to 
    any other work of the Development Bank:  
 


    1[Provided that no 
    fees shall be payable to the chairman, if he is appointed whole-time, or to 
    the managing director or to the whole time director or to any other director 
    who is an official of the Government.]
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Business of Development Bank.—
<section><number>1</number>
    

    1[The Development Bank 
    shall function as the principal financial institution for co-ordinating the 
    working of institutions engaged in financing, promoting or developing 
    industry and for assisting the development of such institutions in such 
    manner as it may deem appropriate and may] carry on and transact any of the 
    following kinds of business, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    granting loans and advances to—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the Industrial Finance 
    Corporation, any State Financial Corporation or any other financial 
    institution 
2[which 
    may be approved by the Board in this behalf] by way of refinance of any 
    loans or advances granted to industrial concerns 
3[***] 
    by such Corporation or institution which are repayable 
4[within 
    a period not exceeding twenty-five years]; 
1[which 
    may be approved by the Board in this behalf] by way of refinance of any 
    loans or advances granted to industrial concerns 
2[***] 
    by such Corporation or institution which are repayable 
3[within 
    a period not exceeding twenty-five years];" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    any scheduled bank or State 
    Co-operative Bank, by way of refinance of any loans or advances granted to 
    industrial concerns 
3[***] 
    by such bank which are repayable 
5[within 
    a period not exceeding fifteen years]; 
2[***] 
    by such bank which are repayable 
4[within 
    a period not exceeding fifteen years];" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    any scheduled bank or State 
    Co-operative Bank or the Industrial Finance Corporation or any State 
    Financial Corporation or any other financial institution which may be 
    notified by the Central Government in this behalf, by way of refinance of 
    any loans or advances granted to industrial concerns 
3[***] 
    or group of industrial concerns by such bank or institution which are for 
    the purpose of, or in connection with, the export of capital goods, 
    commodities or merchandise from India 
    6[or the execution of any turnkey project outside 
    India by any industrial concern as aforesaid or by any person in India, and, 
    in any case, are repayable—  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    within a period not exceeding 
    twelve years in the case of persons outside India, and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    within a period not exceeding 
    fifteen years in the other cases];  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    subject to such conditions as may 
    be prescribed, accepting, discounting, or re-discounting bills of exchange 
    and 7[promissory 
    notes made, drawn, accepted or endorsed by industrial concerns or by any 
    person selling capitals goods manufactured by one industrial concern]; 
6[promissory 
    notes made, drawn, accepted or endorsed by industrial concerns or by any 
    person selling capitals goods manufactured by one industrial concern];" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    subscribing to or purchasing 
    stocks, shares, bonds or debentures of the Industrial Finance Corporation, 
    any State Financial Corporation or 
8[any 
    other financial institution whether within or outside India].9[which 
    may be approved by the Board in this behalf ];  
 

10[(ca)    
    granting letters of credit or loans and advances to the Industrial 
    Finance Corporation, any State Financial Corporation or any other financial 
    institution 
9[which 
    may be approved by the Board in this behalf], for the purpose of any 
    business of such Corporation or institution];  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    granting loans and advances to 
    any industrial concern or subscribing to, or purchasing, or underwriting the 
    issue of, stocks, shares, bonds or debentures of any industrial concern:  
 
Provided that nothing contained in this 
    clause shall be deemed to preclude the Development Bank from granting loans 
    or advances to, or subscribing to debentures of, industrial concern, 
11[the 
    amounts outstanding thereon may be convertible at the option of the 
    Development Bank] into stocks or shares of that concern within the period 
    the loan, advance or debenture is repayable; 
4[the 
    amounts outstanding thereon may be convertible at the option of the 
    Development Bank] into stocks or shares of that concern within the period 
    the loan, advance or debenture is repayable;" 
 
[Explanation.—In this clause, the 
    expression "the amounts outstanding thereon" used in relation to any loan or 
    advance, shall mean the principal, interest and other charges payable on 
    such loan or advance as at the time when the amounts are sought to be 
    converted into stocks or shares.] 
 
 

12[(da)    
    granting loan and advances-—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    to any person exporting products 
    of industrial concerns; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    to any person outside India, in 
    connection with the export of  capital goods from India; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    for the execution of turn-key 
    projects outside India by any industrial concern or by any person in India;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>db</number>    transferring for consideration 
    any instrument relating to loans and advances granted by it to industrial 
    concerns;]  
 

13[(dc)    
    granting loans and advances to any person for purposes of investment in any 
    industrial concern;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    guaranteeing deferred payments 
    due from any industrial concern;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    guaranteeing—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    loans raised by industrial 
    concerns which are floated in the public market; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    loans raised by industrial 
    concerns from any scheduled bank or State Co-operative Bank or the 
    Industrial Finance Corporation or any State Financial Corporation or any 
    other financial institution 
14[which 
    may be approved by the Board in this behalf]; 
1[which 
    may be approved by the Board in this behalf];" 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    guaranteeing the obligations of 
    any scheduled bank or State Co-operative Bank or the Industrial Finance 
    Corporation or any State Financial Corporation or any other financial 
    institution 
14[ 
    which may be approved by the Board in this behalf] arising out of, or in 
    connection with, underwriting the issue of stocks, shares, bonds or 
    debentures of any industrial concern;
 

15[(ga) 
       granting, opening, issuing, confirming or endorsing letters of credit and 
    negotiating or collecting bills and other documents drawn thereunder;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>gb</number>    providing consultancy and 
    merchant banking services in or outside India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>gc</number>    acting as the trustee for the 
    holders of debentures or other securities;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>gd</number>    acquiring, with the approval of 
    the Central Government, the undertaking, including the business, assets and 
    liabilities of any institution the principal object of which is the 
    promotion or development of industry in India, or the grant of financial 
    assistance for such promotion or development;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    undertaking research and surveys 
    for evaluating or dealing with marketing or investments and undertaking and 
    carrying on techno-economic studies in connection with the development of 
    industry;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    providing technical 
15[, 
    legal, marketing] and administrative assistance to any industrial concern or 
    any person for promotion, management or expansion of any industry; 
2[, 
    legal, marketing] and administrative assistance to any industrial concern or 
    any person for promotion, management or expansion of any industry;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    planning, promoting and 
    developing industries to fill up gaps in the industrial structure in India;  
 

16[(k)    
    promoting, forming or conducting or associating in the promotion, formation 
    or conduct of companies, subsidiaries, societies, trusts or such other 
    associations of persons as it may deem fit;]  
 

17[(ka)    
    acting as agent of—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the Central Government or of the 
    Reserve Bank, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    such other Government or person 
    as the Central Government 
18[In 
    consultation with] the Reserve Bank, may authorise;] 5[In 
    consultation with] the Reserve Bank, may authorise;]" 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    performing functions entrusted 
    to, or required of, the Development Bank by this Act or by any other law for 
    the time being in force;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    doing any other kind of business 
    which the Central Government, 
19[***] 
    may authorise; 1[***] 
    may authorise;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    generally doing such other acts 
    and things as may be incidental to, or consequential upon, the exercise of 
    its powers or the discharge of its duties under this Act or any other law 
    for the time being in force including sale or transfer of any of its assets.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Development Bank may receive in consideration of any of the services 
    mentioned in sub-section (1) such commission, brokerage, interest, 
    remuneration or fees as may be agreed upon.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Development Bank shall not grant any loan or advance or other financial 
    accommodation on the security of its own bonds or debentures.  
 
 
 






















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>9A</number> Prohibited 
    business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank shall not enter into any kind of business with any 
    industrial concern, of which any of the directors of the Development Bank is 
    a proprietor, partner, director, manager, agent, employee or guarantor, or 
    in which one or more directors of the Development Bank together hold 
    substantial interest:  
 
Provided 
    that this sub-section shall not apply to any industrial concern if any 
    director of the Development Bank—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    is nominated as a director of the 
    Board of such concern by Government, or a Government company as defined in 
    section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or by a Corporation 
    established by any other law; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    is elected on the Board of such 
    concern by virtue of shares held in the concern by Government, or a 
    Government company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 
    of 1956) or by a Corporation established by any other law,  
 
by reason, only of such nomination or election 
    as the case may be.
 

    Explanation.—"Substantial 
    interest”, in relation to an industrial concern, means the beneficial 
    interest held by one or more of the directors of the Development Bank or by 
    any relative as defined in clause (41) of section 2 of the Companies Act, 
    1956 (1 of 1956), of such director, whether singly or taken together, in the 
    shares of the industrial concern, the aggregate amount paid-up on which 
    either exceeds five lakhs of rupees or five per cent. of the paid up share 
    capital of the industrial concern, whichever is the lesser.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of sub-section (1)—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    shall not apply to any industrial 
    concern as specified therein if the Development  Bank is satisfied that it 
    is necessary in the public interest to enter into business with that 
    concern, and entering into any kind of business with such industrial concern 
    shall be in accordance with and subject to such conditions and limitations 
    as may be prescribed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    shall not apply to any 
    transaction relating to the business entered into prior to the commencement 
    of the Industrial Development Bank of India (Amendment) Act, 1972, and all 
    such business and any transaction in relation thereto may be implemented or 
    continued as if that Act had not come into force;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    shall apply only so long as the 
    conditions precedent to such disability as set out in the said sub-section 
    continue.]  
 
 

 






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Loans by Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf, advance to the Development Bank—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    an interest free loan of ten 
    crores of rupees repayable in fifteen equal annual instalments, commencing 
    on the expiry of a period of fifteen years from the date of the receipt of 
    the loan; and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    such further sums of money by way 
    of loan on such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon:  
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may, on a request being made to it by the 
    Development Bank, increase the number of instalments or alter the amount of 
    any instalment or vary the date on which any instalment is payable under 
    clause (a).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Borrowings and acceptance of deposits by Development Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank may, for the purpose of carrying out its functions 
    under this Act,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    issue and sell bonds and 
    debentures with or without the guarantee of the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    borrow money from the Reserve 
    Bank—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    repayable on demand or on the 
    expiry of fixed periods not exceeding ninety days from the date on which the 
    money is so borrowed against the security of stocks, funds and securities 
    (other than immovable property) in which a trustee is authorised to invest 
    trust money by any law for the time being in force in India;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    against bills of exchange or 
    promissory notes arising out of bona fide commercial or trade 
    transactions, bearing two or more good signatures and maturing within five 
    years from the date of the borrowing;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    out of the National Industrial 
    Credit (Long Term Operations) Fund established under section 46C of the 
    Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) for any of the purposes 
    specified in that section;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    borrow money from such other 
    authority, organisation or institution in India as may be generally or 
    specially approved by 
1[the 
    Board]; 
1[the 
    Board];" 
 

1[(d)    
    accept deposits on such terms as may be approved by the Board.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, on a request being made to it by the Development 
    Bank, guarantee the bonds and debentures issued by that bank as to the 
    repayment of principal and the payment of interest at such rate as may be 
    fixed by that Government.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>11A</number> Power to 
    transfer rights.—The 
    rights and interests of the Development Bank (including any other rights and 
    incidental thereto) in relation to any loan or advance granted, or any 
    amount recoverable, by it may be transferred by the Development Bank, either 
    in whole or in part, by the execution or issue of any instrument or by the 
    transfer of any instrument by endorsement, or in any other manner in which 
    the rights and interests in relation to such loan or advance may be lawfully 
    transferred, and the Development Bank may, notwithstanding such transfer, 
    act as the trustee for the transferee.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>11B</number> Power to 
    acquire rights.—The Development Bank shall have the right to acquire, by 
    transfer or assignment, the rights and interests of any public financial 
    institution as defined in section 4A of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) 
    (including any other rights incidental thereto) in relation to any loan or 
    advances granted, or any amount recoverable by such institution, either in 
    whole or in part, by the execution or issue of any instrument or by the 
    transfer of any instrument or in any other manner.]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Loans in foreign currency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 
    1947 (7 of 1947) or in any other enactment for the time being in force 
    relating to foreign exchange, the Development Bank may, for the purpose of 
    granting loans and advances under this Act, borrow, with the previous 
    consent of the Central Government, foreign currency from any bank or 
    financial institution in any foreign country or otherwise.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may, where necessary, guarantee any loan taken by the 
    Development Bank under sub-section (1) or any part thereof as to the 
    repayment of principal and the payment of interest and other incidental 
    charges.  
 


    1[***]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Grants donations, etc., to Development Bank.— 
    The Development Bank may receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions 
    from Government or any other source.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
*<number>13A</number> 
    Free transferability of shares.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (2), the equity shares of the 
    Development Bank shall be freely transferable.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Nothing contained in sub-section (1) shall entitle the Central Government to 
    transfer any shares held by it in the Development Bank if such transfer will 
    result in reducing the equity shares held by it to less than fifty-one per 
    cent. of the issued equity capital of the Development Bank. 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
*<number>13B</number> 
    Register of shareholders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank shall keep at its head office a register, in one or 
    more books, of the shareholders and shall enter therein the following 
    particulars so far as they may be available, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the names, addresses and 
    occupations, if any, of the shareholders and a statement of the shares held 
    by each shareholder distinguishing each share by its denoting number;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the date on which each person is 
    so entered as a shareholder;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the date on which any person 
    ceases to be a shareholder; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    such other particulars as may be 
    prescribed:  
 


    1[Provided that 
    nothing in this sub-section shall apply to the shares held with a 
    depository.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), it shall be lawful 
    for the Development Bank to keep the register of the shareholders in 
    computer floppies or diskettes subject to such safeguards as may be 
    prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 
    1872), a copy of, or extract from, the register of shareholders, certified 
    to be a true copy under the hand of an officer of the Development Bank 
    authorised in this behalf, shall, in all legal proceedings, be admissible in 
    evidence.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>13BA</number> Register of 
    beneficial owners.—The 
    register of beneficial owners maintained by a depository under section 11 of 
    the Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996) shall be deemed to be a register of 
    the shareholders for the purpose of this Act.]  
 
 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
*<number>13C</number> 
    Trust not to be entered on the register of shareholders.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 13B, no notice of any trust, express implied 
    or constructive, shall be entered on the register of shareholders or be 
    receivable by the Development Bank:  
 


    1[Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall apply to a depository in respect of shares 
    held by it as a registered owner on behalf of a beneficial owner.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of section 13B, section 13BA and this section, the expression 
    “beneficial owner" ,“depository” and “registered owner” shall have the 
    meaning respectively assigned to them in clauses 
<section><number>a</number>, (e) and (j) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Depositories Act, 1996 (22 of 1996).]  
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
*<number>13D</number> 
    Board’s right to refuse registration of transfer of shares.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board may refuse to register the transfer of any shares in the name of 
    the transferee on any one or more of the following grounds, and on no other 
    ground, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the transfer of the shares is in 
    contravention of the provisions of this Act or regulations made thereunder 
    or any other law;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the transfer of the shares, in 
    the opinion of the Board is prejudicial to the interests of the Development 
    Bank or to the public interest;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the transfer of shares is 
    prohibited by an order of a court, tribunal or any other authority under any 
    law for the time being in force.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall, before the expiry of two months from the date on which the 
    instrument of transfer of shares of Development Bank is lodged with it for 
    the purpose of registration of such transfer, not only form, in good faith, 
    its opinion as to whether such registration ought not or ought to be refused 
    on any of the grounds referred to in sub-section (1) but also,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if it has formed the opinion that 
    such registration ought not to be refused, effect such registration; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if it has formed the opinion that 
    such registration ought to be refused on any of the grounds mentioned in 
    sub-section (1), intimate the transferor and the transferee by notice in 
    writing.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    appeal against the order of refusal of the Board under sub-section (2) shall 
    lie to the Central Government and the procedure for filing and hearing of 
    such appeal shall be in accordance with the rules made by the Central 
    Government in this behalf. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>*<number>13E</number> Shares to be securities under the Indian Trusts Act, 
      1882.— 
      Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 
      1882), the shares of the Development Bank shall be deemed to be included 
      among the securities enumerated in section 20 of the said 
      Act.]
  



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
*<number>13F</number> 
    Annual general meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank shall in each year hold, in addition to any other 
    meetings, a general meeting as its annual general meeting and shall specify 
    the meeting as such in the notices calling it; and not more than fifteen 
    months shall elapse between the date of one annual general meeting and that 
    of the next:  
 
Provided 
    that the Development Bank may hold the first annual general meeting within a 
    period of six months from the date on which it allots shares for the first 
    time to public for subscription:  
 
Provided 
    further that the Central Government may extend the time within which any 
    annual general meeting shall be held by a period not exceeding three months.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every annual general meeting shall be called for a time during business 
    hours, on a day that is not a public holiday, and shall be held either at 
    head office or at some other place within the city or town in which the head 
    office is situate.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “public holiday” means a public holiday within 
    the meaning of the Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (26 of 1981):  
 
Provided 
    that no Sunday shall be deemed to be such a holiday in relation to any 
    meeting:  
 
Provided 
    further that no day declared by the Central Government to be a public 
    holiday shall be deemed to be such a holiday, in relation to any meeting, 
    unless the declaration was notified before the issue of the notice convening 
    such meeting. 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
*<number>13G</number> 
    Restriction on exercising of voting right.—Every 
    shareholder of the Development Bank holding equity shares shall have a right 
    to vote in respect of such shares on every resolution and his voting right 
    on a poll shall be in proportion to his share of the paid-up equity capital 
    of the Development Bank:  
 

    Provided, however, that no shareholder other than the Central Government, 
    shall be entitled to exercise voting rights in respect of any equity shares 
    held by him in excess of ten per cent. of the issued equity capital. 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
*<number>13H</number> 
    Matters to be discussed and procedure in annual general meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The shareholders present at an annual general meeting shall be entitled to 
    discuss and adopt—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the balance sheet and profit and 
    loss account of the Development Bank made up to the date on which its 
    accounts are closed and balanced;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the report of working of the 
    Development Bank for the period covered by the accounts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the auditor’s report on the 
    balance sheet and accounts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    proposals for declaration of 
    dividend and capitalisation of reserves.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    shareholders present at an annual general meeting may also discuss any other 
    matter to be transacted at such meetings in accordance with the provisions 
    of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    matters relating to—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the manner in which annual 
    general meeting or other meetings are held under this Act and the procedure 
    to be followed thereat;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the manner in which voting rights 
    may be exercised and resolutions may be passed; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the procedure for transaction of 
    business at such meetings and related matters,  
 
shall be such as may be prescribed.]




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Development Assistance Fund.—With 
    effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, appoint the Development Bank shall establish a special 
    fund to be called the Development Assistance Fund.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Credits to Development Assistance Fund.— 
    To the Development Assistance Fund shall be credited—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    all amount 
    received for the purposes of that fund by way of loans, gifts, grants, 
    donations or benefactions from Government or any other source;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    repayments or 
    recoveries in respect of loans, advances or other facilities granted from 
    the fund;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    income or profits 
    from investments made from the fund; and  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    income accruing or 
    arising to the fund, by way of interest or otherwise, on account of the 
    application of the fund in accordance with the provisions of section 16.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Utilisation of Development Assistance Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Development Bank considers it necessary or desirable so to do, it 
    may, subject to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), disburse or 
    spend from the Development Assistance Fund any amount on account or in 
    consequence of the grant of any loan or advance, or on account or in 
    consequence of entering into any arrangement, under clause (d) or clause (e) 
    or clause (f) or clause (g) of sub-section (1) of section 9:  
 
Provided 
    that before granting any such loan or advance to an industrial concern or 
    entering into any such arrangement with or in relation to an industrial 
    concern, the Development Bank shall obtain the prior approval of the Central 
    Government.  
 


    1[(1A) Where the 
    Development Bank considers it necessary or desirable so to do, it may, 
    subject to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), disburse or spend 
    from the Development Assistance Fund any amount for one or more of the 
    purposes specified in clause (l) or clause (m) of sub-section (1) of section 
    9.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Before seeking the approval of the Central Government under sub-section (1), 
    the Development Bank shall satisfy itself that banking or other financial 
    institutions or other agencies are not likely to grant such loan or advance 
    to the industrial concern or to enter into any such arrangement with or in 
    relation to the industrial concern in the ordinary course of business.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government, before giving its approval, shall satisfy itself that 
    such loan, advance or arrangement is necessary as a matter of priority in 
    the interests of the industrial development of the country.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For 
    the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that nothing contained in this 
    section shall be deemed to preclude the Development Bank from granting any 
    loan or advance or from entering into any arrangement under clause (d) or 
    clause (e) or clause (f) or clause (g) of sub-section (1) of section 9 
    without the approval of the Central Government, if no amount in respect 
    thereof is to be disbursed or spent from the Development Assistance Fund.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Debits to Development Assistance Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    To the Development Assistance Fund shall be debited—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    such amounts as 
    may from time to time be disbursed or spent under sub-sections (1) to (3) of 
    section 16;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such amount as may 
    be required for discharging the liabilities in respect of loans received for 
    the purposes of that fund;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any loss arising 
    on account of investment made out of that fund; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    such expenditure 
    arising out of, or in connection with, the administration and applicaion of 
    the fund as may be determined by the Board.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    amount shall be debited to the Development Assistance Fund except as 
    provided for in sub-section (1).  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Accounts and Audit of Development Assistance Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The balance-sheet and accounts of the Development Assistance Fund shall be 
    prepared in such form and manner as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall cause the books and accounts of the fund to be closed and 
    balanced as on the 30th day of June each year 

    1[or such other date, 
    as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint]:  
 


    2[Provided that with a 
    view to facilitating the transmission from one period of accounting to 
    another period of accounting under this sub-section, the Central Government 
    may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions as it 
    considers necessary or expedient for the closing and balancing of, or for 
    other matters relating to, the books or accounts in respect of the concerned 
    years.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    fund shall be audited by one or more auditors appointed by the 


    3[Development Bank] 
    under section 23 who shall make a separate report therein.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    provisions of sub-sections (2), (3), (4) and (6) of section 23 shall, so far 
    as may be, apply in relation to the audit of the Development Assistance 
    Fund.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Development Bank shall furnish to the Central Government 

    4[***] within four 
    months from the date on which the accounts of the fund are closed and 
    balanced, a copy of the balance sheet and accounts together with a copy of 
    the auditors' report and a report on the operation of the fund during the 
    relevant year and 

    5[the Central 
    Government shall, as soon as may be after they are received by it, cause the 
    same to be laid before each House of Parliament].  
 
 
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Liquidation of Development Assistance Fund.— 
    The Development Assistance Fund shall not be closed or wound up save by 
    order of the Central Government and in such manner as that Government may 
    direct.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    General Fund.— 
    All receipts of the Development Bank other than those which are to be 
    credited the Development Assistance Fund under this Act shall be credited to 
    a fund to be called the General Fund and all payments by the Development 
    Bank, other than those which are to be debited to the Development Assistance 
    Fund, shall be made out of the General Fund.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Preparation of accounts and balance-sheet.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The balance-sheet and accounts of the Development Bank shall be prepared in 
    such form and manner as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall cause the books and accounts of the Development Bank to be 
    closed and balanced as on the 30th day of June each year 

    1[or such other date, 
    as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint]:  
 


    2[Provided that with a 
    view to facilitating the transition from one period of accounting to another 
    period of accounting under this sub-section, the Central Government may, by 
    order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions as it consider 
    necessary or expedient for the closing and balancing of, or for other 
    matters relating to, the books or accounts in respect of the concerned 
    years.]  
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Disposal of profits accruing to General Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank may establish a reserve fund to which may be 
    transferred such sums as that bank may deem fit out of the annual profits 
    accruing to the General Fund.  
 


    1[(2) After making 
    provision for bad and doubtful debts, depreciation of assets and for all 
    other matters for which provision is necessary or expedient or which is 
    usually provided for by bankers and for the reserve fund referred to in 
    sub-section (1), and after transferring a part of the profits to such other 
    reserves or funds as may be considered appropriate, the Board may, out of 
    its net profits declare a dividend.]  
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Audit.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The accounts of the Development Bank shall be audited by auditors duly 
    qualified to act as auditors under sub-section (1) of section 226 of the 
    Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) who shall be appointed by the Development 
    Bank in general meeting of the shareholders out of the panel of auditors 
    approved by the Reserve Bank for such term and on such remuneration as the 
    Reserve Bank may fix.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    auditors shall be supplied with a copy of the annual balance sheet of the 
    Development Bank and it shall be their duty to examine it together with the 
    accounts and vouchers relating thereto and they shall have a list delivered 
    to them of all books kept by the Development Bank and shall at all 
    reasonable times have excess to the books, accounts, vouchers and other 
    documents of the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    auditors may, in relation to such accounts, examine any director or any 
    officer or other employee of the Development Bank and shall be entitled to 
    require from the Board of officer or other employees of the Development Bank 
    such information and explanation as they may think necessary for the 
    performance of their duties.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    auditors shall make a report to the Development Bank upon the annual 
    balance-sheet and accounts examined by them and in every such report they 
    shall state whether in their opinion the balance-sheet is a full and fair 
    balance-sheet containing all necessary particulars and properly drawn up so 
    as to exhibit a true and fair view of the state of affairs of the 
    Development Bank and in case they had called for any explanation or 
    information from the Board or any officer or other employee of the 
    Development Bank whether it has been given and whether it is satisfactory.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Development Bank shall furnish to the 

    2[Central Government]
    

    3[within one month 
    from the date on which the annual general meeting is held] a copy of its 
    balance-sheet and accounts together with a copy of the auditors’ report and 
    a report of the working of the Development Bank during the relevant year, 
    and 

    4[the Central 
    Government shall, as soon as may be after they are received by it, cause the 
    same to be laid before each House of Parliament]; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Without prejudice to anything contained in the preceding sub-sections, the 
    Central Government may at any time appoint the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India to examine and report upon the accounts of the 
    Development Bank and any expenditure incurred by him in connection with such 
    examination and report shall be payable by the Development Bank to the 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India.  
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Saving.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in sub-section (4) of section 18, nothing contained in 
    this Chapter shall apply to the Development Assistance Fund.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Transfer of assets and liabilities of Refinance Corporation for Industry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, appoint, the entire undertaking of the Refinance Corporation for 
    Industry, Limited (hereinafter in this Chapter referred to as “the company”) 
    including all business, property, assets and liabilities, rights, interests, 
    privileges and obligations of whatever nature, shall stand transferred to 
    and vest in the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As 
    compensation for the transfer of the undertaking of the company to the 
    Development Bank under sub-section (1), the Development Bank shall pay in 
    cash to the company an amount equal to the total paid up capital of the 
    company for the purpose of being distributed to the shareholders of the 
    company in proportion to their contribution to such paid up capital.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    contracts, deeds, bonds, agreements, powers of attorney, grants of legal 
    representation and other instruments of whatever nature subsisting or having 
    effect immediately before the date referred to in sub-section (1) and to 
    which the company is a party or which are in favour of that company shall be 
    of full force and effect against or in favour of the Development Bank, as 
    the case may be, and may be enforced or acted upon as fully and effectually 
    as if instead of the company of the Development Bank had been a party 
    thereto or as if they had been issued in favour of the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    on the date referred to in sub-section (1) any suit, appeal or other legal 
    proceeding of whatever nature, is pending by or against the company, the 
    same shall not abate, be discontinued or be in any way prejudicially 
    affected by reason of the transfer to the Development Bank of the 
    undertaking of the company or of anything contained in this Act, but the 
    suit, appeal or other proceeding may be continued, prosecuted and enforced 
    by or against the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Central Government may appoint, whether on or after the date referred to in 
    sub-section (1), a suitable person to take over the management of the 
    company for the purpose of winding up its affairs and distributing its 
    assets and simultaneously with such appointment the Central Government may 
    issue directions to be followed by the person in the management of the 
    company for the purpose aforesaid and thereupon—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the provisions of the Companies 
    Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or any other law for the time being in force or any 
    instrument having effect by virtue of any such Act or other law; insofar as 
    they are inconsistent with such directions, shall cease to apply to, or in 
    relation to, the company;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all persons in charge of the 
    management, including any person holding office as manager or director; of 
    the company immediately before the issue of such directions, shall be deemed 
    to have vacated their office as such; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the person appointed to take over 
    the management of the company shall, in accordance with those directions, 
    take all such steps as may be necessary to facilitate the winding up of its 
    affairs and the distribution of its assets.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Central Government, when satisfied that nothing further requires to be done 
    in order to wind up the affairs of the company, may, by order in writing, 
    direct that as from such date as may be specified therein, the company shall 
    stand dissolved and thereupon any such direcion shall have effect 
    accordingly.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    provisions of this section shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the Companies Act,1956 (1 of 1956) or any other law or any 
    instrument having force by virtue of such Act or other law.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Staff of Development Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank may appoint such number of officers and employees as it 
    considers necessary or desirable for the efficient performance of its 
    functions and determine the terms and conditions of their appointment and 
    service.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), it shall be lawful 
    for the Development Bank to utilise, and for the Reserve Bank to make 
    available the services of, such staff of the Reserve Bank on such terms and 
    conditions as may be agreed upon between the Development Bank and the 
    Reserve Bank.  
 


    1[(3) Every member of 
    the staff—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    whose services are being, 
    immediately before the appointed day, utilised by the Development Bank under 
    sub-section (2), or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    whose services, having been made 
    available to the Development Bank, stand immediately before the appointed 
    day, deputed by that Bank to any other organisation,  
 
shall, on and from the appointed day, be 
    deemed to be appointed by the Development Bank under sub-section (1) on the 
    same salary, emoluments and other terms and conditions of service to which 
    he was entitled immediately before the appointed day:
 
Provided 
    that every member of the staff aforesaid other than those recruited 
    specifically for utilisation in the Development Bank, may, before the expiry 
    of a period of eighteen months from the appointed day, elect to go back to 
    the Reserve Bank by exercising an option in writing to that effect, the 
    option once exercised being final, and on the exercise of such option, the 
    Reserve Bank shall, before the expiration of a period of thirty months from 
    the appointed day, take back such member of the staff and on such member 
    being taken back by the Reserve Bank, he shall become a member of the staff 
    of the Reserve Bank and shall cease to be a member of the staff of the 
    Development Bank.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    on the appointed day or at any time thereafter any of the functions of the 
    Reserve Bank is transferred to the Development Bank, it shall be lawful for 
    the Development Bank to appoint, with the previous approval of the Reserve 
    Bank, such of the members of the staff of the Reserve Bank whose services 
    were, immediately before the transfer aforesaid, being utilised by the 
    Reserve Bank in connection with any of the said functions, and every member 
    of the staff so appointed shall be released by the Reserve Bank and be 
    deemed to be appointed by the Development Bank under sub-section (1) on the 
    same salary, emoluments and other terms and conditions of service to which 
    he was entitled immediately before the date of his appointment:  
 
Provided 
    that every member of the staff aforesaid may, before the expiry of a period 
    of eighteen months from the appointed day, elect to go back to the Reserve 
    Bank by exercising an option in writing to that effect, the option once 
    exercised being final and on the exercise of such option, the Reserve Bank 
    shall, before the expiration of a period of thirty months from the appointed 
    day, take back such member of the staff and on such member being taken back 
    by the Reserve Bank he shall become a member of the staff of the Reserve 
    Bank and shall cease to be a member of the staff of the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act or in any other law 
    or in any contract, for the time being in force, for a temporary period, not 
    being a period exceeding eighteen months from the appointed day or the date 
    notified under section 4A of the Unit Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 of 1963), 
    whichever is earlier, if the Reserve Bank in consultation with the 
    Development Bank or the Unit Trust considers it necessary, in the interest 
    of any of the said institutions to promote any member of the staff of any of 
    the said institutions to a post in either of the other two institutions, it 
    shall be lawful, for the Reserve Bank to transfer on promotion any such 
    member of staff to that other institution and on such transfer each such 
    member of the staff shall be deemed to be a member of the staff of the other 
    institution to which he is so transferred and shall be entitled to the same 
    salary, emoluments and other conditions of service to which he was entitled 
    immediately before the date of such transfer, including benefits, if any, 
    arising directly out of such promotion:  
 
Provided 
    that every member of the staff aforesaid may, before the expiry of a period 
    of eighteen months from the appointed day or the date notified under section 
    4A of the Unit Trust of India Act,1963 (52 of 1963), whichever is earlier, 
    elect to go back to the institution from which he was so transferred by 
    exercising an option in writing to that effect, the option once exercised 
    being final, and on the exercise of such option, that institution shall, 
    before the expiration of a period of thirty months from the appointed day or 
    the date notified under section 4A of the Unit Trust of India Act, 1963, 
    whichever is earlier, take back such member of the staff and on such member 
    being taken back by that institution, he shall become a member of its staff 
    and shall cease to be a member of the staff of the institution to which he 
    was earlier transferred.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law or in any agreement, for 
    the time being in force, no member of the staff shall be entitled to claim 
    any compensation for, or in relation to any matter concerning his transfer, 
    appointment, or as the case may be, return, under sub-sections (3) to (5) 
    and no claim in respect thereof shall be entertained by any court, tribunal 
    or other authority.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Delegation of powers.—The 
    Board may, by general or special order, delegate to any committee of 
    directors constituted under section 7 or to any director or any officer or 
    other employee of the Development Bank, subject to such conditions and 
    limitations, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers 
    and duties under this Act as it may deem necessary.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Returns.—The 
    Development Bank shall furnish, from time to time, to the Central Government 
    and the Reserve Bank such returns as the Central Government or, as the case 
    may be, the Reserve Bank, may require.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Obligation as to fidelity and secrecy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank shall not, except as otherwise required by this Act or 
    any other law, divulge any information relating to or the affairs of, its 
    constituents except in circumstances in which it is, in accordance with the 
    law or practice and usage customary among bankers, necessary or appropriate 
    for the Development Bank to divulge such information.  
 


    1[(1A) The Development 
    Bank may, for the purpose of the efficient discharge of its functions under 
    this Act, collect from or furnish to the Central Government, the State Bank, 
    any subsidiary bank, nationalised bank or other scheduled bank, State 
    Co-operative Bank, State Financial Corporation or such other financial 
    institution, as may be notified by the Central Government in this behalf, 
    credit information or other information as it may consider useful for the 
    purpose, in such manner and at such times, as it may think fit.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this sub-section, the expression “credit information” shall 
    have the same meaning as in clause (c) of section 45A of the Reserve Bank of 
    India Act,1934 (2 of 1934), subject to the modification that “banking 
    company” referred to therein shall mean the State Bank, any subsidiary bank, 
    nationalised bank or other scheduled bank, State Co-operative Bank, State 
    Financial Corporation or other financial institution as aforesaid.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every director, member of a committee, auditor or officer or other employee 
    of the Development Bank or for the Reserve Bank, whose services are utilised 
    by the Development Bank under the provision of this Act, shall, before 
    entering upon his duties, make a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the 
    form set out in the First Schedule to this Act.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>30</number> Defects in appointments not to invalidate acts, 
      etc.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
      act or proceeding of the Board or of any committee of the Development Bank 
      shall be questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy 
      in, or defect in the constitution of, the Board or the committee, as the 
      case may be.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> No act done by any person acting in good faith as a director 
      shall be deemed to be invalid merely on the ground that he was 
      disqualified to be a director or that there was any other defect in this 
      appointment.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>30A</number> Arrangement 
    with Development Bank on appointment of directors to prevail.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any arrangement entered into by the Development Bank with an 
    industrial concern provides for the appointment by the Development Bank of 
    one or more directors of such industrial concern, such provision and any 
    appointment of directors made in pursuance thereof shall be valid and 
    effective notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the 
    Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or in any other law for the time being in 
    force or in the memorandum, articles of association or any other instrument 
    relating to the industrial concern, and any provision regarding share 
    qualification, age-limit, number of directorships, removal from office of 
    directors and such like conditions contained in any such law or instrument 
    aforesaid, shall not apply to any director appointed by the Development Bank 
    in pursuance of the arrangement as aforesaid.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    director appointed as aforesaid shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    hold office during the pleasure 
    of the Development Bank and may be removed or substituted by any person by 
    order in writing of the Development Bank.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    not incur any obligation or 
    liability by reason only of his being a director or for anything done or 
    omitted to be done in good faith in the discharge of his duties as a 
    director or anything in relation thereto;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    not be liable to retirement by 
    rotation and shall not be taken into account for computing the number of 
    directors liable to such retirement.]  
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Indemnity of directors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every director shall be indemnified by the Development Bank against all 
    losses and expenses incurred by him in, or in relation to, the discharge of 
    his duties, except such as are caused by his own wilful act or default.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    director shall not be responsible for any other director or for any officer 
    or other employee of the Development Bank or for any loss or expenses 
    resulting to the Development Bank from the insufficiency or deficiency of 
    the value of, or title to, any property or security acquired or taken on 
    behalf of the Development Bank of the insolvency or wrongful act of any 
    debtor or any person under obligation to the Development Bank or anything 
    done in good faith in the execution of the duties of his office or in 
    relation thereto.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Protection of action taken under this Act.—No 
    suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Development Bank or any 
    director or any officer or other employee of the Development Bank or any 
    other person authorised by the Development Bank to discharge any functions 
    under this Act for any loss or damage caused or likely to be caused by 
    anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of 
    this Act or any other law or provision having the force of law.  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>32A</number> Nomination 
    in respect of deposits, bonds, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
    force, where a nomination in respect of any deposits, bonds or other 
    securities is made in the prescribed manner, the amount due on such deposits 
    bonds or securities shall, on the death of the depositor or holder thereof, 
    vest in, and be payable to, the nominee subject to any right, title or 
    interest of any other person to such deposits, bonds or securities.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    payment by the Development Bank in accordance with the provisions of 
    sub-section (1) shall constitute a full discharge to the Development Bank of 
    its liability in respect of such deposits, bonds or securities.]
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>33</number> Act 18 of 
      1891 to apply in relation to Development Bank.—The Banker’s Books Evidence Act, 
      1891 shall apply in relation to the Development Bank as if it were a bank 
      as defined in section 2 of that Act.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>34</number> Act 10 of 1949 not to apply to 
      Development Bank.—Nothing contained in the Banking Regulation Act, 1949, except 
      section 34A and section 36AD thereof, shall apply to the Development 
      Bank.]  
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>35</number> Act 43 of 1961 and 14 of 1963 not to apply to Development 
      Bank.—Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the 
      Income-tax Act, 1961, the Super Profits Tax Act, 1963 or in any other 
      enactment for the time being in force relating to income-tax, super-tax or 
      super profits tax, or any other tax on income, profits or gains, the 
      Development Bank shall not be liable to pay income-tax; super-tax, super 
      profits tax or any other tax in respect of—  
 <section><number>a</number>    any 
      income, profits or gains accruing or arising to the Development Assistance 
      Fund or any amount received in that fund; and  
 </section><section><number>b</number>    any 
      income, profits or gains derived or any amount received by the Development 
      Bank.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Liquidation of Development Bank.—No 
    provision of law relating to the winding up of companies or corporations 
    shall apply to the Development Bank and the Development Bank shall not be 
    placed in liquidation save by order of the Central Government and in such 
    manner as it may direct.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Power to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Board may, with the previous approval of the 

    1[Central Government] 
    make regulations not inconsistent with this Act to provide for all matters 
    for which provision is necessary or expedient for the purpose of giving 
    effect to the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the times and places of the 
    meetings of the Board or of any committee constituted under this Act and the 
    procedure to be followed at such meetings including the quorum necessary for 
    the transaction of business 
2[and 
    the manner of adoption of resolutions]; 4[and 
    the manner of adoption of resolutions];" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the 
3[***] 
    functions of the Executive Committee; 
5[***] 
    functions of the Executive Committee;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the fees and allowances that may 
    be paid to the directors and the members of a committee;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the conditions which the 
    Development Bank may impose in granting loans or advances or entering into 
    any other arrangements;  
 

4[(da) 
       entering into business with industrial concerns specified in sub-section 
    (1) of section 9A and the conditions and limitations in regard thereto;]  
 

5[(db) 
       the manner in which and the conditions subject to which shares may be 
    held and transferred;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dc</number>    matters relating to the rights 
    of shareholders;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dd</number>    the maintenance of share 
    registers and the particulars to be entered therein;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>de</number>    the safeguards to be observed in 
    the maintenance of register of shareholders on computer floppies or 
    diskettes;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>df</number>    the inspection and closure of 
    the registers and all other matters connected therewith;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dg</number>    the holding and conduct of 
    elections of directors under this Act and the determination of disputes, 
    regarding the qualification of directors;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dh</number>    the manner in which general 
    meetings shall be convened, the procedure to be followed, thereat, the 
    manner in which voting rights may be exercised, resolutions passed and 
    business transacted in such meetings and other matters relating to meetings;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>di</number>    the manner in which notices may 
    be served on shareholders or other persons;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>dj</number>    the manner in which nomination 
    may be made in terms of section 32A;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the conditions on which the 
    Development Bank may accept, discount or rediscount bills of exchange or 
    promissory notes;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the investment (whether by way of 
    deposit in bank or otherwise) of the amounts in the Development Assistance 
    Fund or the General Fund which are not for the time being required for the 
    transaction of business;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the form and manner in which the 
    balance-sheet and the accounts of the Development Assistance Fund and the 
    Development Bank shall be prepared;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the forms of returns and 
    statements required under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the duties and conduct, salaries, 
    allowances and conditions of service of officers and other employees of the 
    Development Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the establishment and maintenance 
    of provident or other benefit funds for officers and other employees of the 
    Development Bank;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    generally, the efficient conduct 
    of the affairs of the Development Bank; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    any other manner which is to be, 
    or may be, prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    regulation which may be made by the Board under this Act may be made by the 
    Reserve Bank within three months of the establishment of the Development 
    Bank; and any regulation so made may be altered and rescinded by the Board 
    in the exercise of its powers under this Act.  
 


    6[(4) Every regulation 
    or rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
    more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or rule or both 
    Houses agree that the regulation or rule should not be made, the regulation 
    or rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
    effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
    annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously 
    done under that regulation or rule.]  
 
 
 
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>38</number> Amendment of certain enactments.—The enactments specified in Parts 
      I to IV of the Second Schedule to this Act shall be amended in the manner 
      directed in the first column thereof and such amendments shall take effect 
      on the dates specified in the second column of that 
Schedule.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>39</number> Power to remove 
    difficulty.—If 
    any difficulty arises in giving effect to
    the provisions of this Act, as amended by the Public Financial Institutions 
    Laws (Amendment) Act, 1975, the Central Government may, by order, do 
    anything, not inconsistent with such provisions, for the purpose of removing 
    the difficulty:
 
Provided 
    that no such order shall be made after the expiration of three years from 
    the date of commencement of the said Amendment Act.]  
 







 



</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT BANK OF INDIA  ACT, 1964
 



 



 




    THE FIRST SCHEDULE
 




    [See section 29(2)]
 




    Declaration of fidelity and secrecy
 




    I,...................................................., do hereby declare 
    that I will faithfully, truly and to the best of my skill and ability 
    execute and perform the duties required of me as director, member 
    of...........................................committee, auditor, officer or 
    other employee (as the case may be) of the Industrial Development Bank of 
    India and which properly relate to the office or position held by me in or 
    in relation to the said Development Bank. tc 
    "I,...................................................., 
    do hereby declare that I will faithfully, truly and to the best of my skill 
    and ability execute and perform the duties required of me as director, 
    member of...........................................committee, auditor, 
    officer or other employee (as the case may be) of the Industrial Development 
    Bank of India and which properly relate to the office or position held by me 
    in or in relation to the said Development Bank." 
 




    I further declare that I will not communicate or allow to be communicated to 
    any person not legally entitled there to any information relating to the 
    affairs of the Industrial Development Bank of India or to the affairs of any 
    person having any dealing with the said Development Bank, nor will I allow 
    any such person to inspect or have access to any book or documents belonging 
    to or in the possession of the said Development Bank and relating to the 
    business of the said Development Banks or the business of any person having 
    any dealing with the said Development Bank. tc 
    "I 
    further declare that I will not communicate or allow to be communicated to 
    any person not legally entitled there to any information relating to the 
    affairs of the Industrial Development Bank of India or to the affairs of any 
    person having any dealing with the said Development Bank, nor will I allow 
    any such person to inspect or have access to any book or documents belonging 
    to or in the possession of the said Development Bank and relating to the 
    business of the said Development Banks or the business of any person having 
    any dealing with the said Development Bank." 
 




            (Signature)
 




    Signed before me.
 




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>