<act><tid>1414105</tid>
<title>THE INLAND WATERWAYS AUTHORITY OF INDIA (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 40 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 11th September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Inland Waterways Authority of India Act, 
<year>1985</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1957069</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>596358</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Inland Waterways Authority of India (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>412613</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1829033</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 3.- In the Inland Waterways Authority of India 
Act, <year>1985</year> (82 of <year>1985</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), 
in section 3, for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (3) The Authority shall consist of the following members, namely:-

<section><tid>1505629</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>1696904</tid>
<number>b</number>a Vice- Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>770686</tid>
<number>c</number>not more than three full- time members; and

</section>

<section><tid>1983538</tid>
<number>d</number>not more than three part- time members, to be appointed by the 
Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>156161</tid>
<number> 3</number> Insertion of new section 4A.- After section 4 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 4A. Disqualifications for appointment as member.- A person shall be 
disqualified for being appointed as a member, if he-

<section><tid>281387</tid>
<number>a</number>has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence 
which, in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral 
turpitude; or

</section>

<section><tid>1573147</tid>
<number>b</number>is an undischarged insolvent; or

</section>

<section><tid>1737103</tid>
<number>c</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>771503</tid>
<number>d</number>has been removed or dismissed from the service of the Government 
or a company owned or controlled by the Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>516322</tid>
<number>e</number>has, in the opinion of the Central Government, such financial or 
other interest in the Authority as is likely to affect prejudicially 
the discharge by him of his functions as a member.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>704969</tid>
<number> 4</number> Insertion of new section 5A.- After section 5 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 5A. Meetings.- (1) The Authority shall meet at such times and places 
and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction 
of business at its meetings, including the quorum thereat, as may be 
provided by regulations.

<section><tid>715171</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or in his absence, the Vice- Chairman, or in the 
absence of both, such other member as is chosen by the members present 
at the meeting of the Authority shall preside at the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1575369</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions which come up before any meeting of the Authority 
shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members present and 
voting, and in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairman or in 
his absence, the Vice- Chairman, or in the absence f both, the person 
presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>142659</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 14.- In section 14 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after clause (j), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (k) enter into joint ventures concerning inland shipping by way of 
equity participation.".



</article>



<article><tid>1220658</tid>
<number>6</number>Insertion of new section 18A.- After section 18 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 18A. Borrowing powers of the Authority.- The Authority may, in such 
manner and subject to such terms and conditions as may be determined 
by regulations, borrow money from any source by the issue of bonds, 
debentures or other instruments as it may think f t for discharge of 
all or any of its functions under the Act.".



</article>



<article><tid>1823463</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 35.- In section 35 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), after clause (j), the following clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (k) the terms and conditions for issue of bonds, debentures or other 
instruments;

<section><tid>1233747</tid>
<number>l</number>the time, place and the rules of procedure with regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings including the quorum under 
sub- section (1) of section 5A.".
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>