<act><title>


    The 

    BIRTH, DEATH AND MARRIAGES REGISTRATION ACT, 1886</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Births, Deaths and Marriages Registration Act, 
    1886; and
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall come into 
    force on such day<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as 
    the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette directs.
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]





  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Extent.—This 
    Act extends2 to 
    the whole of India except 

    3[the territories 
    which immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B 
    States].]







  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless there is something repugnant in the subject or context,—
 
“sign” includes mark, when 
    the person making the mark is unable to write his name;
 
“prescribed” means 
    prescribed by a rule made <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***] under this 
    Act; and
 
“Registrar of Births and 
    Deaths” means a Registrar of Births and Deaths appointed under this Act.





  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Saving of local laws.—Nothing 
    in this Act, or in any rule made under this Act, shall affect any law 
    heretofore or hereafter passed providing for the registration of births and 
    deaths within particular local areas.
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Power exercisable from 
    time to time.—All 
    powers conferred by this Act may be exercised from time to time as occasion 
    requires.
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Establishment of general 
    registry offices and appointment of Registrars General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Each State Government—
 <subsection>
          <number>a</number>   shall establish a general 
    registry office for keeping such certified copies of registers of births and 
    deaths registered under this Act, or marriages registered under Act III of 
    1872<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>
(to provide a form of marriage in 
    certain cases) or the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (15 of 1872), or, 
    beyond the local limits of the ordinary original civil jurisdiction of the 
    High Court of Judicature at Bombay, under the Parsi Marriage and Divorce 
    Act, 1865 (15 of 1865)<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>, 
    as may be sent to it under this Act, or under any of the three 
    last-mentioned Acts, as amended by this Act; and
 </subsection><subsection>
          <number>b</number>   may appoint to the charge of 
    that office an officer, to be called the Registrar General of Births, Deaths 
    and Marriages, for the territories under its administration:
 <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[***]









  







</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Indexes to be kept at 
    general registry office.—Each 
    Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages shall cause indexes of all 
    the certified copies of registers sent to his office under this Act or under 
    Act III of 18721, 
    or the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (15 of 1872), or the Parsi 
    Marriage and Divorce Act, 1865 (15 of 1865)<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>, 
    as amended by this Act, to be made and kept in his office in the prescribed 
    form.







  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Indexes to be open to 
    inspection.—Subject 
    to the payment of the prescribed fees the indexes so made shall be at all 
    reasonable time open to inspection by any person applying to inspect them, 
    and copies of entries in the certified copies of the registers to which the 
    indexes relate shall be given to all persons applying for them.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Copies of entries to be 
    admissible in evidence.—A 
    copy of an entry given under the last foregoing section shall be certified 
    by the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages, or by an officer 
    authorized in this behalf by the State Government and shall be admissible in 
    evidence for the purpose of proving the birth, death or marriage to which 
    the entry relates.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Superintendence of 
    Registrars by Registrar General.—Each 
    Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages shall exercise a general 
    superintendence over the Registrars of Births and Deaths in the territories 
    for which he is appointed.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Persons whose births 
    and deaths are registrable.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The persons whose births and deaths shall, in the first instance, be 
    registrable under this Chapter are the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in 
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[the 
    territories to which this Act extends] the members of every race, sect or 
    tribe to which the Indian Succession Act, 1865 (10 of 1865)<footcitenum>11</footcitenum> applies, 
    and in respect of which an order under section 332 of that Act is not for 
    the time being in force, and all persons professing the Christian religion;
 
<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[***]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> But the State 
    Government by notification in the Official Gazette, may <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[***] extend the 
    operation of this Chapter to any other class of persons either generally or 
    in any local area.











  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Power for State 
    Government to appoint Registrars for its territories.—The 
    State Government may appoint, either by name or by virtue of their office, 
    so many persons as it thinks necessary to be Registrars of Births and Deaths 
    for such local areas within the territories under its administration as it 
    may define and, if it sees fit, for any class of persons within any part of 
    those territories.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Power for Central 
    Government to appoint Registrars for Indian States.—[Repealed 
    by the A.O. 1950.]
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Registrar to be deemed 
    a public servant.—Every 
    Registrar of Births and Deaths shall be deemed to be a public servant within 
    the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Power to remove 
    Registrars.—[Rep. 
    by the A.O. 1937.]
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Office and attendance 
    of Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Registrar of Births and Deaths shall have an office in the local area, 
    or within the part of the territories or dominions for which he is 
    appointed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Registrar of 
    Births and Deaths to whom the State Government may direct this sub-section 
    to apply shall attend at his office for the purpose of registering births 
    and deaths on such days and at such hours as the Registrar General of 
    Births, Deaths and Marriages may direct, and shall cause to be placed in 
    some conspicuous place on or near the outer door of his office his name, 
    with the addition of Registrar of Births and Deaths for the local area or 
    class for which he is appointed, and the days and hours of his attendance.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Absence of Registrar or 
    vacancy in his office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When any Registrar of Births and Deaths to whom the State Government may 
    direct this section to apply<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>, 
    not being a Registrar of Births and Deaths for a local area in the town of 
    Calcutta, Madras or Bombay is absent, or when his office is temporarily 
    vacant, any person whom the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and 
    Marriages appoints in this behalf, or, in default of such appointment the 
    Judge of the District Court within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
    the Registrar’s office is situate, or such other officer as the State 
    Government appoints in this behalf, shall be the Registrar of Births and 
    Deaths during such absence or until the State Government fills the vacancy.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When any such Registrar 
    of Births and Deaths for a local area in the town of Calcutta, Madras or 
    Bombay is absent, or when his office is temporarily vacant, any person whom 
    the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages appoints in this 
    behalf shall be the Registrar of Births and Deaths during such absence or 
    until the State Government fills the vacancy.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Registrar General 
    of Births, Deaths and Marriages shall report to the State Government all 
    appointments made by him under this section.








  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Register books to be 
    supplied and preservation of records to be provided for.—The 
    State Government shall every Registrar of Births and Deaths with a 
    sufficient number of register books of births and of register books of 
    deaths, and shall make suitable provision for the preservation of the 
    records connected with the registration of births and deaths.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Duty of Registrar to 
    register births and deaths of which notice is given.—Every 
    Registrar of Births and Deaths of notice of a birth or death within the 
    local area or among the class for which he is appointed, shall, if the 
    notice is given within the prescribed time and in the prescribed mode by a 
    person authorized by this Act to give the notice, forthwith make an entry of 
    the birth or death in the proper register book:
 
Provided that—
 <section>
          <number>a</number>   if he has reason to believe 
    the notice to be in any respect false, he may refuse to register the birth 
    or death until he receives an order from the Judge of the District Court 
    directing him to make the entry and prescribing the manner in which the 
    entry is to be made; and
 </section><section>
          <number>b</number>   he shall not enter in the 
    register the name of any person as father of an illegitimate child, unless 
    at the request of the mother and of the person acknowledging himself to be 
    the father of the child.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Persons authorized to 
    give notice of birth.—Any 
    of the following persons may give notice of a birth, namely:—
 <section>
          <number>a</number>   the father or mother of the 
    child;
 </section><section>
          <number>b</number>   any person present at the 
    birth;
 </section><section>
          <number>c</number>   any person occupying, at the 
    time of the birth, any part of the house wherein the child was born and 
    having knowledge of the child having been born in the house;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>   any medical practitioner in 
    attendance after the birth and having personal knowledge of birth occurred;
 </section><section>
          <number>e</number>   any person having charge of 
    the child.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Persons authorized to 
    give notice of death.—Any 
    of the following persons may give notice of a death, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   any relative of the deceased 
    having knowledge of any of the particulars required to be registered 
    concerning the death;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   any person present at the 
    death;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   any person occupying, at the 
    time of the death, any part of the house wherein the death occurred and 
    having knowledge of the deceased having died in the house; 

 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   any person in attendance 
    during the last illness of the deceased:
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   any person who has seen the 
    body of the deceased after death.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> Entry of birth or death 
    to be signed by person giving notice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When an entry of a birth or death has been made by the Registrar of Births 
    and Deaths under section 19, the person giving notice of the birth or death 
    must sign the entry in the register in the presence of the Registrar:
 
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Provided that it 
    shall not be necessary for the person giving notice to attend before the 
    Registrar or to sign the entry in the register if he has given such notice 
    in writing and has furnished to the satisfaction of the Registrar such 
    evidence of his identity as may be required by any rules made by the State 
    Government in this behalf.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Until the entry has 
    been so signed, 

    1[or the conditions 
    specified in the proviso to sub-section (1) have been complied with] the 
    birth or death shall not be deemed to be registered under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the birth of an 
    illegitimate child is registered, and the mother and the person 
    acknowledging himself to be the father of the child jointly request that 
    person may be registered as the father, the mother and that person must both 
    sing the entry in the register in the presence of the Registrar.








  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Grant of certificate of 
    Registration of Birth or Death.—The 
    Registrar of Births and Deaths shall, on application made at the time of 
    registering any birth or death by the person giving notice of the birth or 
    death, and on payment by him of the prescribed fee, give to the applicant a 
    certificate in the prescribed form signed by the Registrar, of having 
    registered the birth or death.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> Duty of Registrars as 
    to sending certified copies of entries in register books to Registrar 
    General.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Registrar of Birth and Deaths in <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[the territories to 
    which this Act extends] shall send to the Registrar General of Birth, Deaths 
    and Marriages for the territories within which the local area or class for 
    which he is appointed is situate or resides, at the prescribed intervals, a 
    true copy certified by him, in the prescribed form, of all the entries of 
    births and deaths in the register book kept by him since the last of those 
    intervals:
 
Provided that in the case 
    Registrars of Births and Deaths who are clergymen of the Churches of 
    England, Rome and Scotland the Registrar may, if so directed by his 
    ecclesiastical superior, send the certified copies in the first instance to 
    that superior, who shall send them to the proper Registrar General of 
    Births, Deaths and Marriages.
 
In this sub-section “Church 
    of England” and “Church of Scotland” means the Church of England and the 
    Church of Scotland as by law established respectively; and “Church of Rome” 
    means the Church which regards the Pope of Rome as its spiritual head.
 
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[***]
 
<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[***]










  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> Searches and copies of 
    entries in register books.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Registrar of Births and Deaths shall, on payment of the prescribed 
    fees, at all reasonable times, allow searches to be made in the register 
    books kept by him, and give a copy of any entry in the same.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every copy of an entry 
    in a register book given under this section shall be certified by the 
    Registrar of Births and Deaths, and shall be admissible in evidence for the 
    purpose of proving the birth or death to which the entry relates.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> Exceptional provision 
    for registration of certain births and deaths.—Notwithstanding 
    anything in section 19, the <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    may make <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[rules] authorizing 
    Registrars of Births and Deaths, on conditions and in circumstances to be 
    specified in the rules, to register births and deaths occurring outside the 
    local areas or classes for which they are appointed.
  









  







</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Penalty for wilfully 
    giving false information.—If 
    any person wilfully makes, or causes to be made, for the purpose of being 
    inserted in any register of births or deaths, any false statement in 
    connection with any notice of a birth or death under this Act, he shall be 
    punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years, or 
    with fine, or with both.
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> Correction of entry in 
    register of births or deaths.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If it is proved to the satisfaction of a Registrar of Births and Deaths that 
    any entry of a birth or death in any register kept by him under this Act is 
    erroneous in form or substance, he may, subject to such <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[rules] as may be 
    made by the <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[State Government] 
    with respect to the conditions and circumstances on and in which errors may 
    be corrected, correct the error by entry in the margin, without any 
    alteration of the original entry, and shall sign the marginal entry and add 
    thereto the date of the correction.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a certified copy of 
    the entry has already been sent to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths 
    and Marriages, the Registrar of Births and Deaths shall make and send a 
    separate certified copy of the original erroneous entry and of the marginal 
    correction therein made.










  







</section></article> 

  
  <title>Sections 29. </title>—[ Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch.]  
 

  
  <title>Sections 30. </title>—[ Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch.]  
 

  
  <title>Sections 31. </title>—[ Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch.]  
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> Permission to persons 
    having custody of certain records to send them within one year to Registrar 
    General.—If any 
    person in <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[the territories to 
    which this Act extends] has for the time being the custody of any register 
    or record of birth, baptism, naming, dedication, death or burial of any 
    persons of the classes referred to in section 11, sub-section 
<section><number>1</number>, or, of 
    any register or record of marriage of any persons of the classes to which 
    Act III of 1872<footcitenum>24</footcitenum> or 
    the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872 (15 of 1872) or the Parsi Marriage 
    and Divorce Act, 1865 (15 of 1865)<footcitenum>25</footcitenum> applies, 
    and if such register or record has been made otherwise than in performance 
    of a duty specially enjoined by the law of the country in which the register 
    or record was kept, he may, <footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[at any time before 
    the first day April, 1891,] send the register or record to the office of the 
    Registrar General or Births, Deaths and Marriages for the territories within 
    which he resides, <footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[***]













  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> Appointment of 
    Commissioners to examine registers.—<footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>Any 
    State Government in the case of registers or records sent under section 32 
    to the Registrar General for the territories under its administration, <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[***] may appoint 
    so many persons as it <footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[***] thinks fit to 
    be Commissioner for examining such registers or records.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Commissioners so 
    appointed shall hold office for such period as the <footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[authority 
    appointing them], by the order of appointment, or any subsequent order, 
    directs.












  







</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> Duties of 
    Commissioners.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commissioners appointed under the last foregoing section shall enquire 
    into the state, custody and authenticity of every such register or record as 
    may be sent to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages under 
    section 32;
 
and shall deliver to the 
    Registrar General a descriptive list or descriptive lists of all such 
    registers or records, or portions of registers or records, as they find to 
    be accurate and faithful.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The list or lists shall 
    contain the prescribed particulars and refer to the registers or records, or 
    to the portions of the registers or records, in the prescribed manner.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Commissioners, 
    shall also certify in writing, upon some part of every separate book or 
    volume containing any such register or record, or portion of a register or 
    record, as is referred to in any list or lists made by the Commissioners, 
    that it is one of the registers or records, or portions of registers or 
    records, referred to in the said list or lists.
  
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Searches of lists 
    prepared by Commissioners and grant of certified copies of entries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the payment of the prescribed fees, the descriptive list or lists 
    of registers or records, or portions of registers or records, delivered by 
    the Commissioners to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages 
    shall be, at all reasonable times, open to inspection by any person applying 
    to inspect it or them, and copies of entries in those registers or records 
    shall be given to all persons applying for them.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of an entry 
    given under this section shall be certified by the Registrar General of 
    Births, Deaths and Marriages, or by an officer or person authorized in this 
    behalf by the State Government and shall be admissible in evidence for the 
    purpose of proving the birth, baptism, naming, dedication, death, burial or 
    marriage to which the entry relates.
  







 






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>35A</number> 
    Constitution of additional Commissions for purposes of this Chapter.—
<section><number>1</number>
    <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[***] The State 
    Government <footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[may by 
    notification in the Official Gazette] appoint more Commissions<footcitenum>35</footcitenum> than 
    one for the purposes of section 33, each such Commission consisting of so 
    many and such members, and having its functions restricted to the disposal, 
    under this Act and the rules thereunder, of such registers and records sent 
    under section 32 to the Registrar General, as may be specified in the 
    notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If more Commissions 
    than one are appointed in exercise of the power conferred by sub-section 
    (1), then references in this Act to the Commissioners shall be construed as 
    references to the members constituting a Commission so appointed.]







 






</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[<number>36</number> Rules.—<footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government, for each State <footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[***] may make 
    rules to carry out the purpose of this Act.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
    without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   fix the fees payable under 
    this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   prescribe the forms required 
    for the purposes of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   prescribe the time within 
    which, and the mode in which, persons authorized under this Act to give 
    notice of a birth or death to a Registrar of Births and Deaths must give the 
    notice;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   prescribe the evidence of 
    identity to be furnished to a Registrar of Birth and Deaths by persons 
    giving notice of a birth or death in cases where personal attendance before 
    such Registrar is dispensed with;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   prescribe the registers to be 
    kept and the form and manner in which Registrars of Births and Deaths are to 
    register births and deaths under this Act, and the intervals at which they 
    are to send to the Registrar General of Births, Deaths and Marriages true 
    copies of the entries of births and deaths in the registers kept by them;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   prescribe the conditions and 
    circumstances on and in which Registers of Births and Deaths may correct 
    entries of births and deaths in registers kept by them;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   prescribe the particulars 
    which the descriptive list or lists to be prepared by the Commissioner 
    appointed under Chapter V are to contain, and the manner in which they are 
    to refer to the registers or records, or portions of registers or records, 
    to which they relates; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   prescribe the custody in which 
    those registers or records are to kept.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every power to make 
    rules conferred by this Act is subject to the condition of the rules being 
    made after previous publication.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All rules made under 
    this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette and on such publication 
    shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.]
 












 






</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> Procedure for making 
    and publication of rules.—[Rep., 
    by the Births, Deaths and Marriages Registration (Amendment) Act, 1911 (9 of 
    1911) sec. 5.]  
  
  
  
 


  





 
    .

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Came 
    into force on 1st October, 1888, See Gazette of India, 1888, Pt. I, 
    p. 336.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Sub-section 
    (3) rep. by Act 12 of 1891, sec. 2 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for the former section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
 It has been 
    declared in force in the Santhal Parganas by sec. 3 of the Santhal Parganas
    
    Settlement Regulation, 1872 (III of 1872). It has also been partially 
    extended to Berar by the Berar Laws Act 1941 (4 of 1941).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>             The words 
    “by the G.G. in C.” rep. by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> 
 See 
now the Special Marriage Act, 1954 (43 of 
    1954).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> 
 See 
now the Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act, 1936 
    (3 of 1936).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> 
 Sub-section (2) 
    rep. by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>
 See
    now the Special Marriage Act, 1954 
    (43 of 1954).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> 
 Subs. by the A.O. 
    (No. 2) 1956, for “a Part A State or a Part C State”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> 
 See 
    now the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), section 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> 
 Clause (b) rep. by 
    the A.O. 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>    
    T he words “with the 
    previous approval of the G.G. in C” were omitted by the Act 38 of 1920, sec. 
    2 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> 
 The section has 
    been declared by the Government of Madras to apply to all Registrars 
    appointed by that Government under section 12, See Mad. R and O.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>             Ins. by 
    Act 9 of 1911, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> 
 Subs. by the A.O. 
    (No. 2), 1956, for “Part A States or Part C States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> 
 Sub-section (2) 
    rep. by the A.O. 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> 
 The proviso to 
    sub-section (2) ins. by Act 38 of 1920, sec. 2 and sch. I, and rep. by the 
    A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> 
 Subs. by Act 9 of 
    1911, sec. 3 for “G.G. in C”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   For rules made 
    under section 26 conjointly with sections 28 and 36, see Gazette of 
    India, 1888, Pt. I, p. 336, and different local Rules and Orders. All rules 
    made by the G.G. in C. under this Act, before 1911, shall be deemed to have 
    been made by the State Governments, see section  6 of Act 9 of 1911.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> 
 For rules made 
    under section 26 cojointly with sections 28 and 36, see Gazette of India, 
    1888, pt. 1, p. 336 and different local Rules and orders. All rules made by 
    the G.G. in C. under this Act, before 1911, shall be deemed to have been 
    made by the State Government, see section 6 of Act 9 of 1911.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> 
 Subs. by Act 9 of 
    1911, sec. 3 for “G.G. in C”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> 
 Subs. by the A.O. 
    (No. 2) 1956, for “a Part A State or a Part C State.”</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> 
 See. now the 
    Special Maggiage Act, 1954 (43 of 1954).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> 
 See. now the 
    Parsi Marriage and Divorce Act, 1936 (3 of 1936).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> 
 Subs. by Act 16 
    of 1890, sec. 1, for “within one year from the date on which this  Act coms 
    into force”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> 
 Certain words 
    including the proviso which was ins. by Act 38 of 1920, sec. 2 and sch. 
    omitted by the A.O. 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> 
 Subs. by Act 38 
    of 1920, sec. 2 and Sch. 1, for the original sub-section (1).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> 
 Certain words 
    rep. by the A.O. 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> 
 The words “or he, 
    as the case may be”, rep. by the A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> 
 Subs. by Act 38 of 
    1920, sec. 2 and Sch. I, for “G.G. in C”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> 
 Section 35A was 
    added by the Births, Death and Marriages Registration Act, (1886) Amendment 
    Act, 1890 (16 of 1890), sec. 2, which was repealed by the Devolution Act, 
    1920 (38 of 1920), sec. 3 and Sch. II. The present sub-section (1) was subs. 
    for the original sub-section by the Devolution Act, 1920 (38 of 1920), sec. 
    2, Sch. I, and sub-section (2), was inserted by the Repealing and Amending 
    Act, 1934 (24 of 1934), sec. 2 and Sch. I.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number> 
 The words “The 
    Central Goverment or” rep. by the A.O. 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number> 
 Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for “if he or it thinks fit, may by notification in the Gazette of 
    India or the local official Gazette, as the case may be”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> 
 For Commissioners 
    appointed under this section, see Gazette of India, 1890, Pt. I, p. 
    744.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   Subs. by Act 9 of 
    1911, sec. 4, for the original section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for the original sub-section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number>   The words “and 
    the Central Government for British subjects in Indian States” rep. by the 
    A.O. 1950.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>