<act><tid>1432853</tid>
<title>THE UNITED NATIONS (PRIVILEGES AND IMMUNITIES) ACT, <year>1947</year></title>

ACT NO. 46 OF <year>1947</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[]

An Act to give effect to the Convention on the Privileges and 
Immunities of the United Nations.

WHEREAS it is expedient to give effect to the Convention on the 
Privileges and Immunities of the United Nations, and to enable similar 
privileges and immunities to be enjoyed by other international 
organisations and their representatives and officials:--

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>228804</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the United Nations 
 (Privileges and Immunities) Act, <year>1947</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1601788</tid>
<number> 2</number> Conferment on United Nations and its representatives and 
officers of certain privileges and immunities.-
<section><tid>1796866</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything to the contrary contained in any other law, the provisions 
set out in the Schedule to this Act of the Convention on the 
Privileges and Immunities, adopted by the General Assembly of the 
United Nations on the 13th day of February, <year>1946</year>, shall have the force 
of law in India.

</section>

<section><tid>743409</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, amend the Schedule in conformity 
with any amendments, duly made and adopted, of the provisions of the 
said Convention set out therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>121060</tid>
<number>3</number>Power to confer certain privileges and immunities on other 
international organisation and their representatives and officers.- 
Where in pursuance of any international agreement, convention or other 
instrument it is necessary to accord to any international organisation 
and its representatives and officers privileges and immunities in 
India similar to those contained in the provisions set out in the 
Schedule, the Central Government may, by notification <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, 
s. 3 and Schedule. 
2. Extended to the State of Sikkim (w. e. f. 12. 1. <year>1976</year>) vide Notifer 
No. G. S. R. 19 (E), dt. 12. 1. <year>1976</year>.


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Provisions set out in the Schedule have been extended with 
certain modifications to the following organisations by various 
notifications:--

(1) International Civil Aviation Organisation.

(2) World Health Organisation.

(3) International Labour Organisation.

(4) Food and Agriculture Organisation of the United Nations.

(5) United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural 
Organisation.

(6) International Monetary Fund.

(7) International Bank of Reconstruction and Development.

(8) Universal Postal Union.

(9) International Telecommunication Union.

(10) World Meteorological Organisation.

(11) Permanent Central Opium Board.

(12) International Hydregraphic Bureau (vide Notifen. No. S. 2480  
dt. 10. 10. 60 Gazetta of India, Pt II Sec 3 (ii) P. 3001.

(13) Commissioner for India Watns Govt. of Pakistan and to his 
Advisers and Assistants (Artich IV) bide.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


in the Official Gazette, declare that the provisions set out in the 
Schedule shall, subject to such modifications, if any, as it may 
consider necessary or expedient for giving effect to the said 
agreement, convention or other instrument, apply mutatis mutandis to 
the international organisation specified in the notification and its 
representatives and officers, and thereupon the said provisions shall 
apply accordingly and, notwithstanding anything to the contrary 
contained in any other law, shall in such application have the force 
of law in India.



</article>



<article><tid>1527827</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to make rules.- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>772065</tid>
<number>1</number>] The Central Government may <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>,  
by notification in the Official Gazette,] make rules for carrying out 
the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>730919</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]

</section>

</article>



 </act>