<act><tid>1435091</tid>
<title>THE CHIEF ELECTION COMMISSIONER AND OTHER ELECTION 
COMMISSIONERS (CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) ACT, <year>1991</year></title>

NO. 11 OF <year>1991</year> 
[ 25th January, <year>1991</year>.]
An Act to determine the conditions of service of the Chief Election 
Commissioner and other Election Commissioners <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and to provide for 
the procedure for transaction of business by the Election Commission 
and for matters"] connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- first Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>79718</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Election 
Commission (Conditions of Service of Election Commissioners and  
  Transaction of Business)"] Act, <year>1991</year>.

</article>



<article><tid>742821</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1736411</tid>
<number>a</number>" Chief Election Commissioner" means the Chief Election 
Commissioner appointed under article 324 of the Constitution;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (b)" Election Commission" means the Election Commission 
referred to in article 324 of the Constitution;'.]


</section>

<section><tid>1039394</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>]" Election Commissioner" means any other Election 
Commissioner appointed under article 324 of the Constitution.
CHAP 
SALARY AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF THE CHIEF 
ELECTIONCOMMISSIONER AND ELECTION COMMISSIONERS

CHAPTER II

SALARY AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF THE CHIEF ELECTION 
COMMISSIONER AND ELECTION COMMISSIONERS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1749922</tid>
<number> 3</number> Salary.
<section><tid>1936256</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be paid to the Chief Election  
Commissioner a salary which is equal to the salary of a Judge of the 
Supreme Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1995181</tid>
<number>2</number>There shall be paid to an Election Commissioner a salary 
which is equal to the salary of a Judge of a High Court:
Provided that if a person who, immediately before the date of 
assuming office as the Chief Election Commissioner or, as the case may 
be, an Election Commissioner, was in receipt of, or, being eligible so 
to do, had election to draw, a pension (other than a disability or  
  wound pension) in respect of any previous service under the Government 
of the Union or under the Government of a State, his salary in respect 
of service as the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 4 of <year>1994</year>, S. 2 (w. e. f 1- 10- <year>1993</year>) 
2 Subs by S. 3 ibid (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1993</year>) 
3 Re- lettered and ins. by S. 4, ibid (w. e. f 1- 10- <year>1993</year>) 
4 Omitted and ins by S. 5, ibid (w. e. f 1- 10- <year>1993</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Chief Election Commissioner or, as the case may be, an Election 
Commissioner shall be reduced--


<subsection><tid>1633900</tid>
<number>a</number>by the amount of that pension; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776048</tid>
<number>b</number>if he had, before assuming office, received, in lieu of 
a portion of the pension due to him in respect of such previous 
service, the commuted value thereof, by the amount of that 
portion of the pension.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>455675</tid>
<number>4</number>Term of office. The Chief Election Commissioner or an Election 
Commissioner shall hold office for a term of six years from the date 
on which he assumes his office:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that where the Chief Election Commissioner or an 
Election Commissioner attains the age of sixty- five years before the 
expiry of the said term of six years, he shall vacate his office on 
the date on which he attains the said age:".]

Provided further that the Chief Election Commissioner or an 
Election Commissioner may, at any time, by writing under his hand 
addressed to the President, resign his office.

Explanation.-- For the purpose of this section, the term of six 
years in respect of the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election 
Commissioner holding office immediately before the commencement of 
this Act, shall be computed from the date on which he had assumed 
office.


</article>



<article><tid>37665</tid>
<number> 5</number> Leave.
<section><tid>376806</tid>
<number>1</number>A person who, immediately before the date of  
assuming office as the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election 
Commissioner, was in service of Government may be granted during his 
tenure of office but not thereafter, leave in accordance with the 
rules for the time being applicable to the Service to which he 
belonged before such date and he shall be entitled to carry forward 
the amount of leave standing at his credit on such date, 
notwithstanding anything contained in section 6.

</section>

<section><tid>129071</tid>
<number>2</number>Any other person who is appointed as the Chief Election 
Commissioner or an Election Commissioner may be granted leave in 
accordance with such rules as are for the time being applicable to a 
member of the Indian Administrative Service.

</section>

<section><tid>1568855</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to grant or refuse leave to the Chief Election 
Commissioner or an Election Commissioner and to revoke or curtail 
leave granted to him, shall vest in the President.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>834499</tid>
<number> 6</number> Pension payable to Election Commissioners.
<section><tid>255319</tid>
<number>1</number>A person who,  
immediately before the date of assuming office as the Chief Election 
Commissioner or an Election Commissioner was in service of Government, 
shall be deemed to have retired from service on the date on which he 
enters upon office as the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election 
Commissioner but his subsequent service as the Chief Election 
Commissioner or an Election Commissioner shall be reckoned as 
continuing approved service counting for pension in Service to which 
he belonged.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs by Act 4 of <year>1994</year>, S. 6 (w. e. f 1- 10- <year>1993</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>527270</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Chief Election Commissioner demits office[ whether 
in any manner specified in sub- section (4) or by resignation], he 
shall, on such demission be entitled to--

<subsection><tid>1933155</tid>
<number>a</number>a pension which is equal to the pension payable to a 
Judge of the Supreme Court in accordance with the provisions of 
Part III of the Schedule to the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions  
  of Service) Act, <year>1958</year>, (41 of <year>1958</year>.) as amended from time to 
time; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>662099</tid>
<number>b</number>such pension (including commutation of pension), family 
pension and gratuity as are admissible to a Judge of the Supreme 
Court under the said Act and the rules made thereunder, as 
amended from time to time.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1067207</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] Except where the Chief Election Commissioner or an 
Election Commissioner demits office by resignation, he shall be 
deemed, for the purpose of this Act, to have demitted his office if, 
and only if,--

<subsection><tid>1094106</tid>
<number>a</number>he has completed the term of office specified in section 
4, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1998739</tid>
<number>b</number>he has attained the age of sixty- five years, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> xxx or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>144244</tid>
<number>c</number>his demission of office is medically certified to be 
necessitated by ill- health.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>507006</tid>
<number>7</number>Right to subscribe to General Provident Fund. Every person 
holding office as the Chief Election Commissioner or an Election 
Commissioner shall be entitled to subscribe to the General Provident 
Fund (Central Services).

</article>



<article><tid>387448</tid>
<number>8</number>Other conditions of service. Save as otherwise provided in 
this Act, the conditions of service relating to travelling allowance, 
provision of rent- free residence and exemption from payment of income- 
tax on the value of such rent- free residence, conveyance facilities, 
sumptuary allowance, medical facilities and such other conditions of 
service as are, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for the time being, applicable to a Judge of the 
Supreme Court under Chapter IV of the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions  
  of Service) Act, <year>1958</year> (41 of <year>1958</year>) and the rules made thereunder, 
shall, so far as may be, apply to the Chief Election Commissioner and 
other Election Commissioners"]
CHAP 
TRANSACTION OF BUSINESS OF ELECTION COMMISSION

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> CHAPTER III

TRANSACTION OF BUSINESS OF ELECTION COMMISSION]


</article>



<article><tid>494164</tid>
<number>9</number>Transaction of business of Election Commission. The business 
of the Election Commission shall be transacted in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>390370</tid>
<number> 10</number> Disposal of business by Election Commission.
<section><tid>844340</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election  
Commission may, by unanimous decision, regulate the procedure for 
transaction of its business as also allocation of its business amongst 
the Chief Election Commissioner and other Election Commissioners.

</section>

<section><tid>1629161</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as provided in sub- section (1), all business of the 
Election Commission shall, as far as possible, be transacted 
unanimously.

</section>

<section><tid>1237729</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), if the Chief 
Election Commissioner and other Election Commissioners differ in 
opinion on any matter, such matter shall be decided according to the 
opinion of the majority."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. Subs, omitteds and renumbered by Act 4 of <year>1994</year>, S. 7 (w. e. f 1-  
  10- 93) 
2 Subs by S. 8, ibid (w. e. f 1- 10- <year>1993</year>) 
3 Ins. by S. 9, ibid (w. e. f 1- 10- <year>1993</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>