<act><tid>1439698</tid>
<title>THE PART B STATES (LAWS) ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 22nd February, <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to provide for the extension of certain laws to Part B 
States.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--





<article><tid>114920</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1295623</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Part B States (Laws) Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1443712</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1818930</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," appointed day" means the date on 
which this Act comes into force.


</article>



<article><tid>1472974</tid>
<number>3</number>Extension and amendment of certain Acts and Ordinances. The 
Acts and Ordinances specified in the Schedule shall be amended in the 
manner and to the extent therein specified, and the territorial extent 
of each of the said Acts and Ordinances shall, as from the appointed 
day and in so far as any of the said Acts or Ordinances or any of the 
provisions contained therein relates to matters with respect to which 
Parliament has power to make laws, be as stated in the extent clause 
thereof as so amended.


</article>



<article><tid>1983980</tid>
<number>4</number>Construction of references to laws not in force in Part B 
States. Any reference in any Act or Ordinance specified in the 
Schedule to a law which is not in force in a Part B State shall, in 
relation to that State, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law, if any, in force in that State.


</article>



<article><tid>875642</tid>
<number>5</number>Construction of references to authorities where new 
authorities have been constituted. Any reference, by whatever form of 
words, in any law for the time being in force in a Part B State to any 
authority competent at the date of the passing of that law to exercise 
any powers or discharge any functions in that State shall, where a 
corresponding new authority has been constituted by or under any Act 
or Ordinance now extended to that State, have effect as if it were a 
reference to that new authority.


</article>



<article><tid>189796</tid>
<number> 6</number> Repeals and savings. If immediately before the appointed day, 
there is in force in any Part B State any law corresponding to any of 
the Acts or Ordinances now extended to that State, that law shall, 
save as otherwise expressly provided in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> this Act] stand repealed:
Provided that the repeal shall not affect--

<section><tid>1602277</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of any law so repealed or 
anything duly done or suffered thereunder, or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>132</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st April, <year>1951</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1951</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 354. 
2. Subs. by Act 48 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" the Act".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>417964</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, 
accrued or incurred under any law so repealed, or

</section>

<section><tid>1021508</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against any law so 
repealed, or

</section>

<section><tid>327818</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect 
of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, 
penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid;
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed:

Provided further that, subject to the preceding proviso, anything 
done or any action taken (including any appointment or delegation  
made, notification, order, instruction or direction issued, rule, 
regulation, form, bye- law or scheme framed, certificate obtained, 
  patent, permit or licence granted or registration effected) under any 
such law shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provision of the Act or Ordinace as now extended to that 
State, and shall continue to be in force accordingly, unless and until 
superseded by anything done or any action taken under the said Act or 
Ordinance.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1300269</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>1054388</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect in any Part B State to the provisions of any Act or 
Ordinance now extended to that State, the Central Government may, by 
order notified in the Official Gazette, make such provisions or give 
such directions as appear to it to be necessary for the removal of the 
difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1023567</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, any such notified order may--

<subsection><tid>1265908</tid>
<number>a</number>specify the corresponding authorities within the meaning 
of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>780888</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for the transfer of any matter pending before 
any Court, tribunal or other authority, immediately 
before the appointed day, to any corresponding Court, 
tribunal or other authority for disposal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>800604</tid>
<number>c</number>specify the areas or circumstances in which, or the 
extent to which or the conditions subject to which, 
anything done or any action taken including any of the 
matters specified in the second proviso to section (6) 
under any law repealed by that section shall be 
recognised or given effect to under the corresponding 
provision of the Act or Ordinance as now extended.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>133</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>