<act><title>


Aircraft (Carriage of Dangerous 
    Goods) Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Aircraft (Carriage of Dangerous Goods) Rules, 
    2003.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    extend to whole of India and apply also—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to aircraft registered in India or 
    aircraft operated by an operator who has his principal place of business or 
    permanent place of residence in India, wherever they may be;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to all aircraft for the time being in 
    or over India; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to persons operating air transport 
    services to, from, within and over India, shippers of dangerous goods or 
    their agents.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their final publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions and interpretation.—In
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context—
 


 <section> <number>1</number>
“aerodrome” means any definite or limited ground or water area
intended to be used, either wholly or in part, for the landing or departure of
aircraft, and includes all buildings, sheds, vessels, piers and other structures
thereon or appertaining thereto: 
 
 


 </section><section> <number>2</number>
“aircraft” means any machine which can derive support in the
atmosphere from reactions of the air other than reactions of the air against the
earth’s surface and includes balloons whether fixed or free, airships, kites,
gliders and flying machines: 
 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
“cargo aircraft” means any aircraft, other than a passenger aircraft, which
is carrying goods or property;
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
“crew member” means a person assigned by an operator to duty on an
aircraft during a flight duty period; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>5</number> “dangerous
goods” means articles or substances which are capable of posing a risk to
health, safety, property or the environment and which are listed as such in the
Technical Instructions or which are classified according to the Technical
Instructions <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***]; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>6</number> “dangerous goods
accident” means an occurrence associated with and related to the transport of
dangerous goods by air which results in fatal or serious injury to a person or
major property damage; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>7</number> “dangerous goods
incident” means an occurrence, other than a dangerous goods accident,
associated with and related to the transport of dangerous goods by air, not
necessarily occurring on board an aircraft, which results in injury to a person,
damage to property, fire, breakage, spillage, leakage of fluid or radiation or
other evidence that the integrity of the packaging has not been maintained and
also includes any occurrence relating to the transport of dangerous goods which
seriously jeopardizes the aircraft or its occupants; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>8</number> “Director-General”
means Director General of Civil Aviation; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>9</number> “flight crew
member” means a licensed crew member charged with duties essential to the
operation of an aircraft during a flight duty period: 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>10</number> “operator”
means a person, organisation or enterprise engaged in or offering to engage in
an aircraft operation; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>11</number> “overpack”
means an enclosure used by a single shipper to contain one or more packages and
to form one handling unit for convenience of handling and stowage; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>12</number> “package” means
the complete product of the packing operation consisting of the packaging and
its contents prepared for transport; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>13</number> “packaging”
means receptacles and any other components or materials necessary for the
receptacle to perform its conainment function; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>14</number> “passenger
aircraft” means an aircraft that carries any person other than a crew member,
an operator’s employee in an official capacity, an authorized representative
of an appropriate national authority or a person accompanying a consignment or
other cargo; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>15</number> “pilot-in-command”
means the pilot designated by the operator, or in the case of general aviation
by the owner, as being in command and charged with the safe conduct of a flight; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>16</number> “serious
injury” means an injury which is sustained by a person in an accident and
which; 
 
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number> requires hospitalization for
more than 48 hours, commencing within seven days from the date the injury was
received; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>b</number>
results in a fracture of any bone (except simple fractures of fingers,
toes or nose); or  
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> involves lacerations which cause
severe haemorrhage, nerve, muscle or tendon damage; or  
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> involves injury to any internal
organ; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> involves second or third degree
burns, or any burns affecting more than five per cent. of the body surface; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> involves verified exposure to
infectious substances or injurious radiation; 
 
 


 
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[16A)
“State of origin” means the State in the territory of which the
dangerous goods were first loaded on an aircraft;] 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>17</number> “State of the
operator” means the State in which the operator’s principal place of
business is located or, if there is no such place of business, the operator’s
permanent place of residence; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>18</number> “Technical
Instructions” means the Technical Instructions for the Safe Transport of
Dangerous Goods by Air issued by the International Civil Aviation Organisation; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>19</number> “UN number” means the
four-digit number assigned by the United Nations Committee of Experts on the
Transport of Dangerous Goods to indentify a substance or a particular group of
substances; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>20</number>“Unit
load device” means any type of freight container, aircraft container or
aircraft pallet with a net, but excluding an overpack, designed for loading on
an aircraft. 


   

  








</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Carriage of dangerous goods by air.—
<section><number>1</number>
No operator shall engage in the carriage of dangerous goods unless it has been
certified by the aeronautical authority of the State of the operator to carry
the dangerous goods. (2) No operator shall carry and no person shall cause or
permit to be carried in any aircraft to, from, within or over India or deliver
or cause to be delivered for loading on such aircraft any dangerous goods,
except in accordance with and subject to the requirements specified in the
Technical Instructions:
 


 Provided
that where dangerous goods classified as radioactive material are to be carried
in any aircraft to, from or within India, the operator shall ensure that the
consignor or the consignee, as the case may be, has written consent of the
Central Government to carry such goods under section 16 of the Atomic Energy
Act, 1962 (33 of 1962):
 


 Provided
further that where there is extreme emergency such as national or international
crisis or natural calamities or otherwise necessitating transportation by air of
such goods and full compliance with the requirements specified in the Technical
Instructions may adversely affect the public interest, the Director-General or
any other officer authorised in this behalf by the Central Government may, by
general or special order in writing, grant exemption from complying with these
requirements provided that he is satisfied that every effort has been made to
achieve an overall level of safety in the transportation of such goods which is
equivalent to the level of safety specified in the Technical Instructions.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (2), the articles and substances
that are specifically identified by name or by generic description in the
Technical Instructions as being forbidden for transport by air under any
circumstances, shall not be carried on any aircraft.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2) shall not apply to—
 


 <subsection> <number>a</number>
the articles and substances classified as dangerous goods but otherwise
required to be on board the aircraft in accordance with the pertinent
airworthiness requirements and the operating regulations, or for such
specialised purposes as are identified in the Technical Instructions; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection> <number>b</number>
specific articles and substances carried by passengers or crew members to
the extent specified in the Technical Instructions. 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number>
Where dangerous goods are carried under sub-rule (2), it shall be the duty of
the shipper, the operator and every person concerned with packing, marking,
labelling, acceptance, handling, loading, unloading, storage, transportation or
any other process connected directly or indirectly with carriage of such
dangerous goods, to take all precautions to avoid danger to the aircraft or to
the persons on board or to any other person or property.] 


    




















</section></article> 
 

Aircraft 
(Carriage of Dangerous  
Goods) Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>4</number> Custody of unauthorized 
dangerous goods.—Where any officer 
authorised in this behalf by the Central Government has reason to believe that 
the provisions of this rule are, or are about to be, contravened, he may cause 
the dangerous goods in question to be placed under his custody pending detailed 
examination of the nature of the goods or pending a decision regarding the 
action, if any, to be taken in the matter.
  
</article> 

   


  
 <article><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number>
Classification of dangerous goods.— The
dangerous goods shall be classified in accordance with the provisions of the
Technical Instructions.] 

 





</article> 
 

Aircraft 
(Carriage of Dangerous  
Goods) Rules, 2003
  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Packing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Dangerous goods shall be packed in accordance with the requirements specified in 
the Technical Instructions in addition to the provisions of this rule.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall be ensured that no 
harmful quantity of a dangerous substance adheres to the outside of the 
packagings used for the transport of the dangerous goods.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Packagings used for the 
transport of dangerous goods by air shall be of good quality and shall be 
constructed and securely closed so as to prevent leakage which might be caused 
in normal conditions of transport by changes in temperature, humidity or 
pressure, or by vibration.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The packagings shall be 
suitable for the contents and the packagings in direct contact with dangerous 
goods shall be resistant to any chemical or other action of such goods.
 

1[(4A) Packagings shall meet the material 
and construction specifications contained in the Technical Instructions.
 </section><section><number>4B</number> Packagings shall be tested 
in accordance with the provisions of the Technical Instructions.
 </section><section><number>4C</number> Packagings for which 
retention of a liquid is a basic function, shall be capable of withstanding, 
without leaking, the pressure specified in the Technical Instructions.]
 </section><section><number>5</number> Inner packagings used for 
the transport of the dangerous goods shall be packed, secured or cushioned in 
such a manner that no breakage or leakage shall be caused and these shall also 
control the movement of the dangerous goods within the outer packaging (s) 
during normal conditions of air transport and also the cushioning and absorbent 
materials shall not react dangerously with the contents of the receptacles.
 </section><section><number>6</number> No packaging used for the 
transport of the dangerous goods shall be re-used unless,—
 <subsection>             <number>a</number>  it has been inspected and found free from 
corrosion or other damage; and
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>b</number>  all necessary precautions have been taken 
to prevent contamination of subsequent contents:
 Provided that where it is not 
possible to properly clean a packaging already used for the transport of 
dangerous goods, then such an uncleaned empty packaging shall be transported by 
air following the same procedure as laid down for the transport of the dangerous 
goods for which such packagings has been used earlier.
  




</subsection></section></article> 
 

Aircraft 
(Carriage of Dangerous  
Goods) Rules, 2003
  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Labelling.—Unless 
otherwise provided in the Technical Instructions each package of dangerous goods 
shall be labelled in accordance with the requirements specified in the Technical 
Instructions.
  
</article> 

   


 <article> <number>7</number>
Marking.—
<section><number>1</number>
Save as otherwise provided in the Technical Instructions, each package of
dangerous goods shall be marked with the proper shipping name of its contents
and, when assigned; the UN number and such other markings as may be specified in
those Instructions.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Save as otherwise provided in the Technical Instructions, each packaging
manufactured to the specifications of the Technical Instructions shall be marked
in accordance with the provisions of the Technical Instructions and no other
packagings shall be so marked.
 


 </section><section>[<number>3</number>
In addition to the languages required by the State of origin, English shall also
be used for the markings related to dangerous goods.] 


   




1.
Ins. by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006 (w.e.f. 28-9-2006).
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>8</number>
Shipper’s responsibilities.—
<section><number>1</number>
No shipper or his agent shall offer any package or overpack of dangerous goods
for transport by air unless he has ensured that such dangerous goods are not
forbidden for transport by air and are properly classified, packed, marked and
labelled in accordance with the requirements specified in the Technical
Instructions.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Unless otherwise provided in these rules, no shipper or his agent shall offer
dangerous goods for transport by air unless he has completed, signed and
provided to the operator a dangerous goods transport document, as specified in
the Technical Instructions.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The dangerous goods transport document shall bear a declaration <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[signed
by the shipper or his agent] indicating that the dangerous goods are fully and
accurately described by their proper shipping names and that they are
classified, packed, marked, labelled and in proper condition for transport by
air as per requirements of the Technical Instructions.
 


 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>
In addition to the languages required by the State of origin, English shall also
be used in the dangerous goods transport document.] 


   





</section></article> 
 

Aircraft 
(Carriage of Dangerous  
Goods) Rules, 2003
  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Operator’s 
responsibilities.—
<section><number>1</number> No operator 
shall accept dangerous goods for transport by air unless,—
 <subsection>             <number>a</number>  the dangerous goods are accompanied by a 
completed dangerous goods transport document, except where the Technical 
Instructions specify that such a document is not required; and
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>b</number>  the package, overpack or freight container 
containing the dangerous goods has been inspected in accordance with the 
acceptance procedures specified in the Technical Instructions.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The operator shall ensure 
that an acceptance check-list as required by the Technical Instructions has been 
developed and is being used by his acceptance staff.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Packages and overpacks 
containing dangerous goods and freight containers containing radioactive 
materials shall be inspected for evidence of leakage or damage before loading on 
an aircraft or into a unit load device and such packages, overpacks or freight 
containers shall be loaded and stowed on an aircraft in accordance with the 
requirements specified in the Technical Instructions.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The operator shall ensure 
that no leaking or damaged packages, overpacks or freight containers containing 
dangerous goods shall be loaded on an aircraft.
 </section><section><number>5</number> A unit load device shall not 
be loaded aboard an aircraft unless the device has been inspected and found free 
from any evidence of leakage from, or damage to, any dangerous goods contained 
therein.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where any package of 
dangerous goods loaded on an aircraft appears to be damaged or leaking, the 
operator shall remove such package from the aircraft, or arrange for its removal 
by an appropriate authority or organisation, as the case may be, and thereafter 
shall ensure that the remainder of the consignment is in a proper condition for 
transport by air and that no other package has been contaminated. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Packages or overpacks 
containing dangerous goods freight containers containing radioactive materials 
shall be inspected for signs of damage or leakage upon unloading from the 
aircraft or unit load device and if evidence of damage or leakage is found, the 
area where the dangerous goods or unit load device were stowed on the aircraft 
shall be inspected for damage or contamination.
 </section><section><number>8</number> No dangerous goods shall be 
carried in an aircraft cabin occupied by passengers or on the flight deck of an 
aircraft, except those specified in sub-rule (2) of rule 3.
 </section><section><number>9</number> Any hazardous contamination 
found on an aircraft as a result of leakage or damage to dangerous goods shall 
be removed without delay.
 </section><section><number>10</number> An aircraft which has been 
contaminated by radioactive materials shall immediately be taken out of service 
and not returned to service until the radiation level at any accessible surface 
and the non-fixed contamination are not more than the values specified in the 
Technical Instructions. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> Packages containing 
dangerous goods which might react dangerously with one another shall not be 
stowed on an aircraft next to each other or in a position that would allow 
interaction between them in the event of leakage.
 </section><section><number>12</number> Packages of toxic and 
infectious substances shall be stowed on an aircaft in accordance with the 
requirements specified in the Technical Instructions.
 </section><section><number>13</number> Packages of radioactive 
materials shall be stowed on an aircraft so that they are separated from 
persons; live animals and undeveloped film, in accordance with the requirements 
specified in the Technical Instructions.
 </section><section><number>14</number> Subject to the provisions 
of these rules, when dangerous goods are loaded in an aircraft, the operator 
shall protect the dangerous goods from being damaged, and shall secure such 
goods in the aircraft in such a manner that will prevent any movement-in-flight 
which would change the orientation of the packages. For packages containing 
radioactive materials, the securing shall be adequate to ensure that the 
separation requirements of sub-rule (13) are met at all times.
 </section><section><number>15</number> Except as otherwise 
provided in the Technical Instructions, packages of dangerous goods bearing the 
“Cargo aircraft only” label shall be loaded in such a manner that a crew member 
or other authorised person can see, handle and, where size and weight permit, 
separate such packages from other cargo in flight. 
  
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>10</number>
Provision of information.—
<section><number>1</number>
The operator of the aircraft in which dangerous goods are to be carried shall
provide information in writing to the pilot-in-command as early as practicable
before departure of the aircraft as required by the Technical Instructions.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The operator shall provide such information in the Operations Manual so as to
enable the flight crew member to carry out their responsibilities with regard to
the transport of dangerous goods and shall also provide instructions as to the
action to be taken in the event of emergencies arising involving dangerous
goods.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Operators shall ensure that information is promulgated in such a manner that
passengers are warned as to the types of goods which they are forbidden from
transporting aboard an aircraft as provided in the Technical Instructions.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Operators, shippers or other organizations involved in the transport of
dangerous goods by air shall provide such information to their personnel so as
to enable them to carry out their responsibilities with regard to the transport
of dangerous goods and shall also provide instructions as to the action to be
taken in the event of emergencies arising involving dangerous goods.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
If an in-flight emergency occurs, the pilot-in command shall, as soon as the
situation permits, inform the appropriate air traffic services unit, for the
information of aerodrome authorities, of any dangerous goods on board the
aircraft, as provided in the Technical Instructions.
 


 1(6)
In the event of an aircraft accident or a serious incident where dangerous goods
carried as cargo are involved, the operator of the aircraft shall provide
information, without delay, to the emergency services responding to the accident
or serious incident, and, as soon as possible, to the appropriate authorities of
the State of the operator and the State in which the accident or serious
incident occurred, about the dangerous goods on board, as shown on the written
information to the pilot-in-command.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
In the event of an aircraft incident, the operator of an aircraft carrying
dangerous goods as cargo shall, upon request, provide information, without
delay, to the emergency services responding to the incident and also to the
appropriate authority of the State in which the incident occurred, about the
dangerous goods on board, as shown on the written information to the
pilot-in-command.] 


   

 

 







</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>10A</number>
Inspection.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Director-General or any other officer authorised in this behalf by the
Central Government by general or special order in writing, may, at any
reasonable time, enter any place to which access in necessary and inspect any
services, equipment, documents and records.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The operator, shipper, training establishment and every other person concerned
with carriage of dangerous goods shall allow the person so authorised, access to
any part of the aircraft, building or any facility including equipment, records,
documents and personnel, and shall co-operate in exercising his powers or
carrying out his duties under these rules.]
 


   





</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>11</number>
Dangerous goods accidents and incidents.—
<section><number>1</number>
In the event of a dangerous goods accident or dangerous goods incident, as the
case may be, the pilot-in-command of the aircraft and the operator of the
aircraft or of the aerodrome, as the case may be, shall submit a report in
writing to the Director-General on such accident or incident.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The report under sub-rule (1) shall, in addition to any other relevant
information, contain the following information, namely:—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the type, nationality and registration marks of aircraft; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the name of the owner, operator and hirer of the aircraft; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the name of the pilot-in-command of the aircraft; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
the nature and purpose of the flight; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
the date and time of the dangerous goods accident or incident; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
the place where the accident occurred; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>
the last point of departure and the next point of intended landing of the
aircraft; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>
the details of the dangerous goods on board the aircraft viz.
their proper shipping name, UN number, quantity, etc.; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>
the known cause of the dangerous goods accident or incident; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>
details of other cargo on board the aircraft; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>
the extent of known damage to the aircraft, other property and persons on
board the aircraft; 
 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>
any other information required to be included by the Director-General. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
On receipt of the report under sub-rule (1), the Director-General may, if
considered necessary, order an investigation to determine the causes of such
accident or incident and take preventive measures to avoid re-occurrence of such
accident or incident.] 


 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> Requirement of Training. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall engage himself in any manner in the transport of dangerous goods unless he has undergone proper training commensurate with his responsibilities. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The training shall be provided or verified upon the employment of a person in a position involving the transport of dangerous goods and recurrent training shall take place within twenty-four months of the previous training.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>13</footcitenum></title>[<number>3</number> The period of validity of the training referred to in sub-rule (2) shall be twenty-four months from the date of successful completion of the training.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>13</footcitenum></title>[<number>4</number> In case of the recurrent training, the period of validity of the training shall commence from the date of expiry of the previous training subject to the condition that the recurrent training has been successfully completed within a period of not more than three months prior to the date of expiry of the previous training.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>13</footcitenum></title>[<number>5</number> In cases other than those referred to in sub-rule (4), the period of validity of the recurrent training shall commence from the date of successful completion of the recurrent training.] 





 
 <subsection><number>a</number> shippers of dangerous goods including packers and persons or organisations undertaking the responsibilities of the shipper; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> operators; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> ground handling agencies which perform, on behalf of the operator, the act of accepting, handling, loading, unloading, transferring or other processing of cargo; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> ground handling agencies located at an airport which perform, on behalf of the operator, the act of processing passengers. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> agencies, not located at an airport, which perform, on behalf of the operator, the act of checking in passengers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> freight forwarders; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> agencies engaged in the security screening of passengers and their baggage, and cargo.] 
</subsection>

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> general familiarization training aimed at providing familiarity with the general provisions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> function-specific training providing detailed training in the requirements applicable to the function for which that person is responsible; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> safety training covering the hazards presented by dangerous goods, safe handling and emergency response procedures. 
</subsection>



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> Requirement of Training. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall engage himself in any manner in the transport of dangerous goods unless he has undergone proper training commensurate with his responsibilities. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The training shall be provided or verified upon the employment of a person in a position involving the transport of dangerous goods and recurrent training shall take place within twenty-four months of the previous training.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>16</footcitenum></title>[<number>3</number> The period of validity of the training referred to in sub-rule (2) shall be twenty-four months from the date of successful completion of the training.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>16</footcitenum></title>[<number>4</number> In case of the recurrent training, the period of validity of the training shall commence from the date of expiry of the previous training subject to the condition that the recurrent training has been successfully completed within a period of not more than three months prior to the date of expiry of the previous training.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>16</footcitenum></title>[<number>5</number> In cases other than those referred to in sub-rule (4), the period of validity of the recurrent training shall commence from the date of successful completion of the recurrent training.] 





 
 <subsection><number>a</number> shippers of dangerous goods including packers and persons or organisations undertaking the responsibilities of the shipper; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> operators; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> ground handling agencies which perform, on behalf of the operator, the act of accepting, handling, loading, unloading, transferring or other processing of cargo; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> ground handling agencies located at an airport which perform, on behalf of the operator, the act of processing passengers. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> agencies, not located at an airport, which perform, on behalf of the operator, the act of checking in passengers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> freight forwarders; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> agencies engaged in the security screening of passengers and their baggage, and cargo.] 
</subsection>

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> general familiarization training aimed at providing familiarity with the general provisions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> function-specific training providing detailed training in the requirements applicable to the function for which that person is responsible; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> safety training covering the hazards presented by dangerous goods, safe handling and emergency response procedures. 
</subsection>



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Directions by Director-General. </title>— <title><footcitenum>18</footcitenum></title>[
<section><number>1</number>] The Director-General may, through Aeronautical Information Circulars (AICs) and publication entitled Civil Aviation Requirements (CARs), issue special directions, not inconsistent with the provisions of the Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 1934), the Aircraft Rules, 1937 or these rules, relating to packing, marking, labelling, acceptance, handling, loading, unloading, storage, training and any other process or procedure connected directly or indirectly with the carriage of dangerous goods by air. 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>19</footcitenum></title>[<number>2</number> The Civil Aviation Requirements under sub-rule (1) shall be issued after placing the draft on the website of the Directorate General of Civil Aviation for a period of thirty days for inviting objections and suggestions from all persons likely to be affected thereby: 
 Provided that the Director-General may, in public interest and by order in writing, dispense with the requirement of inviting such objections and suggestions.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>19</footcitenum></title>[<number>3</number> Every direction issued under sub-rule (1) shall be complied with by the person or persons to whom such direction is issued.] 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>19</footcitenum></title>[<number>4</number> If any person fails to comply with any direction issued under sub- 
  rule (1), he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or with fine which may extend to two lakh rupees, or with both.] 




</section></article> 
 

Aircraft 
(Carriage of Dangerous  
Goods) Rules, 2003
  
  
 <article><number>14</number> General power to exempt.—The 
Central Government may, by general or special order in writing, exempt any 
aircraft or class of aircraft or any person or class of persons from the 
operation of these rules, either wholly or partially, subject to such 
conditions, if any, as may be specified in that order.
  
  
  
</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>15</number> Cancellation or suspension of licence, certificate and approval. </title>—Where <title><footcitenum>22</footcitenum></title>[the Director-General or any officer authorised in this behalf by the Central Government], after giving an opportunity of being heard, is satisfied that any person <title><footcitenum>23</footcitenum></title>[has contravened or failed to comply with the provisions of these rules or any direction issued under rule 13, he may], for reasons to be recorded in writing, cancel or suspend any licence, certificate or approval issued under these rules or under the Aircraft Rules, 1937.] 





</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> The words “, and also includes arms, military stores, implements of
war and munitions of war” omitted by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006 (w.e.f.
28-9-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Ins. by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006 (w.e.f. 28-9-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006, for rule 3 (w.e.f.
28-9-2006). Rule 3, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>
Ins. by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006 (w.e.f. 28-9-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>    Ins. by G.S.R. 434(E), dated 19th July, 
2006 (w.e.f. 20-7-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 600,
dated 27th September, 2006, for “signed by the shipper” (w.e.f.28-9-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by G.S.R.
600, dated 27th September, 2006 (w.e.f. 28-9-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006, for sub-rules (6) and
(7) (w.e.f. 28-9-2006). Sub-rules (6) and (7), before substitution, stood as
under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>Ins.
by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006 (w.e.f. 28-9-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>
Subs. by G.S.R. 600, dated 27th September, 2006, for rule 11 (w.e.f.
28-9-2006). Rule 11, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Vide G.S.R. 206(E) dated 5th March, 2003, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (i), dated 7th March, 2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 823(E), dated 12th November, 2009, for rule 12 (w.e.f. 13-11-2009). Earlier</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 928(E), dated 29th November, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-11-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Vide G.S.R. 206(E) dated 5th March, 2003, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (i), dated 7th March, 2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 823(E), dated 12th November, 2009, for rule 12 (w.e.f. 13-11-2009). Earlier</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 928(E), dated 29th November, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-11-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Vide G.S.R. 206(E) dated 5th March, 2003, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (i), dated 7th March, 2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Rule 13 re-numbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by G.S.R. 928(E), dated 29th November, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-11-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 928(E), dated 29th November, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-11-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Vide G.S.R. 206(E) dated 5th March, 2003, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (i), dated 7th March, 2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 600(E), dated 27th September, 2006 (w.e.f. 28-9-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 823(E), dated 12th November, 2009, for “the Director-General” (w.e.f.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 928(E), dated 29th November, 2010, for “has contravened or failed to comply with the provisions of these rules, he may” (w.e.f. 29-11-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>