<act><title>THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (EXPORT AND IMPORT OF CURRENCY) REGULATIONS, 20001</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>i</number> These regulations may be called the Foreign Exchange Management (Export and Import of Currency) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> They shall come into effect on 1st day of June, 2000. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these regulations, unless the context requires otherwise, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> Act' means Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (42 of 1999); 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> the words and expressions used and not defined in these regulations but defined in the Act have meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Export and import of Indian currency and currency notes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided in these regulations, any person resident in India , 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> may take outside India (other than to Nepal and Bhutan) currency notes of Government of India and Reserve Bank of India notes upto an amount not exceeding <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Rs. 7500 (Rupees Seven Thousand Five Hundred only)] per person; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> may take or send outside India (other than to Nepal and Bhutan ) commemorative coins not exceeding two coins each. 
</subsection>
 Explanation .commemorative coin' includes coin issued by Government of India Mint to commemorate any specific occasion or event and expressed in India currency; 
 
 <subsection><number>c</number> who had gone out of India on a temporary visit, may bring into India at the time of his return from any place outside India (other than from Nepal and Bhutan), currency notes of Government of India and Reserve Bank of India notes upto an amount not exceeding  
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Rs. 7500 (Rupees Seven Thousand Five Hundred only)] per person. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-regulation (1), Reserve Bank may, on application made to it and on being satisfied that it is necessary to do so, allow a person to take or send out of India or bring into India currency notes of Government of India and/or of Reserve Bank of India subject to such terms and conditions as the Bank may stipulate.] 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Prohibition on Export of Indian coins. </title>No person shall take or send out of India the Indian coins which are covered by the Antique and Art Treasure Act, 1972. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Prohibition on export and import of foreign currency. </title>Except as otherwise provided in these regulations, no person shall, without the general or special permission of the Reserve Bank, export or send out of India, or import or bring into India, any foreign currency. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Import of foreign exchange into India. </title>A person may 
 
 <section><number>a</number> send into India without limit foreign exchange in any form other than currency notes, bank notes and travellers cheques; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> bring into India from any place outside India without limit foreign exchange (other than unissued notes): 
</section>
 Provided that bringing of foreign exchange into India under clause (b) shall be subject to the condition that such person makes, on arrival in India, a declaration to the customs authorities in Currency Declaration Form (CDF) annexed to these Regulations: 
 Provided further that it shall not be necessary to make such declaration where the aggregate value of the foreign exchange in the form of currency notes, bank notes or traveller's cheques brought in by such person at any one time does not exceed US $ 10,000 (US Dollars ten thousands) or its equivalent and/or the aggregate value of foreign currency notes brought in by such person at any time does not exceed US $ 5,000 (US Dollars five thousands) or its equivalent. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Export of foreign exchange and currency notes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> An authorised person may send out of India foreign currency acquired in normal course of business. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person may take or send out of India , 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> cheques drawn on foreign currency account maintained in accordance with Foreign Exchange Management (Foreign Currency Accounts by a Person Resident in India ) Regulations, 2000; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> foreign exchange obtained by him by drawal from an authorised person in accordance with the provisions of the Act or the rules or regulations or directions made or issued thereunder; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> currency in the safes of vessels or aircrafts which has been brought into India or which has been taken on board a vessel or aircraft with the permission of the Reserve Bank. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any person may take out of India , 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> foreign exchange possessed by him in accordance with the Foreign Exchange Management (Possession and Retention of Foreign Currency) Regulations, 2000; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> unspent foreign exchange brought back by him to India while returning from travel abroad and retrained in accordance with the Foreign Exchange Management (Possession and Retention of Foreign Currency) Regulations, 2000. 
</subsection>
(4) Any person resident outside India may take out of India unspent foreign exchange not exceeding the amount brought in by him and declared in accordance with the proviso to clause (b) of regulation 6, on his arrival in India .


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 548(E), dated 7th July, 2009, for Rs. 5000 (w.e.f. 24-7-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 201(E), dated 27th February, 2001 (w.e.f. 27-2-2001).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>