<act><tid>1441671</tid>
<title>THE ANDHRA PRADESH AND MADRAS (ALTERATION OF BOUNDARIES) ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 56 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 24th December, <year>1959</year>]

An Act to provide for the alteration of boundaries of the States of 
Andhra Pradesh and Madras and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>47226</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>91866</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1535353</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1298801</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>886276</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date appointed under sub- 
section (2) of section 1 for the coming into force of 
this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>97880</tid>
<number>b</number>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and 
" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as 
in the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>475536</tid>
<number>c</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument having the force of law in the whole or in 
any part of Andhra Pradesh or Madras;

</section>

<section><tid>1334935</tid>
<number>d</number>" notified order" means an order published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1721487</tid>
<number>e</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of a State, means a 
person who, immediately before the appointed day, is a 
member of that House;

</section>

<section><tid>494409</tid>
<number>f</number>" transferred territories" means--

<subsection><tid>908387</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the State of Andhra 
Pradesh, the territories specified in the Second 
Schedule and transferred from that State to 
Madras, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>532</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st April <year>1960</year>. See Notification No. S. O. 2863, dated 29th 
December, <year>1959</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, <year>1959</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3 
 (ii), p. 611.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>148365</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to the State of Madras, the 
territories specified in the First Schedule and 
transferred from that State to Andhra Pradesh;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>922283</tid>
<number>g</number>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury;

</section>

<section><tid>401525</tid>
<number>h</number>any reference to a district, taluk, firka, village or 
other territorial division of a State shall be 
construed as a reference to the area comprised within 
that territorial division on the 1st day of July, <year>1957</year>.
PART

TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES

PART II

TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>652934</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer of territories. As from the appointed day, there 
shall be added--
<section><tid>441085</tid>
<number>a</number>to the State of Andhra Pradesh, the territories 
specified in the First Schedule which shall thereupon 
cease to form part of the State of Madras; and

</section>

<section><tid>95895</tid>
<number>b</number>to the State of Madras, the territories specified in the 
Second Schedule which shall thereupon cease to form 
part of the State of Andhra Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1146606</tid>
<number> 4</number> Changes of territorial divisions in Andhra Pradesh.
<section><tid>742988</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
territories specified in Part I of the First Schedule shall be 
included in, and form part of, Chittoor district; and the said 
territories, together with the territories comprised in the villages 
of Puttur taluk specified in the Third Schedule and the territories 
which immediately before the appointed day were comprised in 
Kanakammachatram and Tiruttani firkas of Tiruttani taluk but are not 
transferred by virtue of section 3 to the State of Madras, shall form 
a taluk to be known as Sathyavedu taluk in Chittoor district.

</section>

<section><tid>1929582</tid>
<number>2</number>The territories which immediately before the appointed day 
were comprised in Pallipattu and Erumbi firkas of Tiruttani taluk but 
are not transferred by virtue of section 3 to the State of Madras 
shall be included in, and form part of, Puttur taluk.

</section>

<section><tid>1565252</tid>
<number>3</number>The territories which immediately before the appointed day 
were comprised in Melpadi firka of Chittoor taluk but are not 
transferred by virtue of section 3 to the State of Madras shall be 
included in, and form part of, Chittoor firka of Chittoor taluk.

</section>

<section><tid>1698226</tid>
<number>4</number>The territories specified in Part II of the First Schedule 
shall be included in, and form part of, Kuppam West firka of Palmaner 
taluk in Chittoor district.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>533</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>758618</tid>
<number> 5</number> Changes of territorial divisions in Madras.
<section><tid>1224586</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
territories which immediately before the appointed day were comprised 
in Sathyavedu firka of Ponneri taluk and Uttukkottai firka of 
Tiruvallur taluk but are not transferred by virtue of section 3 to the 
State of Andhra Pradesh shall be included in, and form part of, 
Gummidipundi firka of Ponneri taluk.

</section>

<section><tid>1712455</tid>
<number>2</number>The territories specified in Parts I and II of the Second 
Schedule shall be included in and form a separate taluk to be known as 
Tiruttani taluk of Chingleput district; and in that taluk, the 
territories specified in Part II of that Schedule shall form a 
separate firka to be known as Kanakammachatram firka.

</section>

<section><tid>1686824</tid>
<number>3</number>The territories specified in Parts III, IV, V, VI, VII and 
VIII of the Second Schedule shall respectively be included in, and 
form part of,--

<subsection><tid>185581</tid>
<number>a</number>Mappedu firka of Tiruvallur taluk of Chingleput 
district,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>807331</tid>
<number>b</number>Parangi firka of Arkonam taluk of North Arcot district,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475364</tid>
<number>c</number>Arkonam firka of Arkonam taluk of North Arcot district,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>396104</tid>
<number>d</number>Ranipet firka of Walajapet taluk of North Arcot 
district,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1961187</tid>
<number>e</number>Gudiyattam East firka of Gudiyattam taluk of North Arcot 
district, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1225773</tid>
<number>f</number>Vaniyambadi firka of Tiruppattur taluk of North Arcot 
district.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1559381</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under the 
heading" I. THE STATES",--
<section><tid>703883</tid>
<number>a</number>for the entry against" 1. Andhra Pradesh", the following 
shall be substituted, namely:--
" The territories specified in sub- section (1) 
of section 3 of the Andhra State Act, <year>1953</year>, sub- 
section (1) of section 3 of the States 
Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>, and the First Schedule 
to the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of  
  Boundaries) Act, <year>1959</year>, but excluding the 
territories specified in the Second Schedule to 
the last mentioned Act,"; and


</section>

<section><tid>37678</tid>
<number>b</number>in the entry against" 7. Madras",--

<subsection><tid>1835701</tid>
<number>i</number>after the words and figures" section 4 of 
the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>", the words, 
brackets and figures" and the Second Schedule to 
the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration of  
  Boundaries) Act, <year>1959</year>," shall be inserted; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>534</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>175226</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words, brackets, letters and 
figures" and the territories specified in clause 
 (b) of sub- section (1) of section 5, section 6 and 
clause (d) of sub- section (1) of section 7 of the 
States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>", the following 
shall be substituted namely:--
" the territories specified in clause (b) of 
sub- section (1) of section 5, section 6 and 
clause (d) of sub- section (1) of section 7 of 
the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> and the 
territories specified in the First Schedule 
to the Andhra Pradesh and Madras (Alteration  
  of Boundaries) Act, <year>1959</year>".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>435305</tid>
<number>7</number>Saving powers of State Governments. Nothing in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part shall be deemed to affect the power of the 
State Government of Andhra Pradesh or Madras to alter after the 
appointed day the name, extent or boundaries of any district, taluk, 
firka or village in the State.
PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

The Council of States



</article>



<article><tid>390775</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of Fourth Schedule to the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the 
second column of the Table,--
<section><tid>1981026</tid>
<number>a</number>for the figures" 17" against Madras, the figures" 18" 
shall be substituted; and

</section>

<section><tid>857613</tid>
<number>b</number>for the figures" 220", the figures" 221" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1756804</tid>
<number> 9</number> Bye- election to fill the additional seat.
<section><tid>1095156</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may  
be after the appointed day, a bye- election shall be held to fill the 
additional seat allotted to the State of Madras in the Council of 
States by virtue of section 8.

</section>

<section><tid>1079055</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of the member elected to the Council of 
States in pursuance of this section shall expire on the 2nd day of 
April, <year>1962</year>.
The House of the People




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1133612</tid>
<number>10</number>Amendment of First Schedule to the Delimitation Order. The 
First Schedule to the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly 
Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>, shall have effect subject to the 
modifications specified in the Fourth Schedule to this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>535</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>374848</tid>
<number>11</number>Provision as to sitting members. Every sitting member of the 
House of the People representing a constituency the extent of which is 
altered by virtue of section 10 shall be deemed to have been elected 
to the said House by that constituency as so altered.
The Legislative Assemblies



</article>



<article><tid>770006</tid>
<number>12</number>Strength of Legislative Assemblies. The total number of seats 
in the Legislative Assembly of Andhra Pradesh to be filled by persons 
chosen by direct election shall be reduced from 301 to 300 and that in 
the Legislative Assembly of Madras shall be increased from 205 to 206; 
and, accordingly, in the Second Schedule to the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), for the figures" 301" against" Andhra 
Pradesh", the figures" 300" shall be substituted, and for the figures 
" 205" against" Madras", the figures" 206" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1634905</tid>
<number>13</number>Amendment of Second Schedule to Delimitation Order. The 
Second Schedule to the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly 
Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>, shall have effect subject to the 
modifications specified in the Fifth Schedule to this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>73982</tid>
<number>14</number>Amendment of Delimitation Commission' s Final Order No. 19. 
The Delimitation Commission' s Final Order No. 19, dated the 4th 
October, <year>1954</year>, shall have effect subject to the modifications 
specified in the Sixth Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>36841</tid>
<number> 15</number> Provisions as to certain sitting members.
<section><tid>596425</tid>
<number>1</number>The sitting  
members of the Legislative Assembly of Andhra Pradesh representing the 
Vadamalpet, Vepanjeri, Chittoor and Kuppam constituencies shall, 
notwithstanding the alteration in the extent thereof by the provisions 
of this Act, be deemed to have been respectively elected to the said 
Assembly by the said constituencies as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>1038231</tid>
<number>2</number>The sitting members of the Legislative Assembly of Madras 
representing the Gummidipundi, Tiruvallur, Arkonam, Sholinghur, 
Ranipet, Gudiyattam, Vaniyambadi and Uddanpalli constituencies shall, 
notwithstanding the alteration in the extent thereof by the provisions 
of this Act, be deemed to have been respectively elected to the said 
Assembly by the said constituencies as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>1069026</tid>
<number>3</number>The sitting members of the Legislative Assembly of Andhra 
Pradesh representing the Tiruttani constituency shall, as from the 
appointed day, be deemed to have been elected to that Assembly by the 
Sathyavedu Constituency in the State of Andhra Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>307815</tid>
<number>4</number>The sitting member of the Legislative Assembly of Andhra 
Pradesh representing the Ramakrishnarajupet constituency shall, as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>536</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

from the appointed day, cease to be a member of that Assembly and be 
deemed to have been elected to the Legislative Assembly of Madras from 
the Tiruttani constituency in the State of Madras.

The Legislative Councils




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>959360</tid>
<number> 16</number> Extent of Council constituencies.
<section><tid>1645571</tid>
<number>1</number>Any reference in the  
Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Andhra Pradesh) Order, <year>1957</year>, 
to the State of Andhra Pradesh or to Chittoor district shall be 
construed as excluding the territories transferred from that State or 
district, as the case may be, to the State of Madras and as including 
the territories transferred to that State or district, as the case may 
be, from the State of Madras.

</section>

<section><tid>1920351</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference in the Delimitation of Council Constituencies 
 (Madras) Order, <year>1951</year>, to the State of Madras or to Chingleput, North 
Arcot or Salem district shall be construed as excluding the 
territories transferred from that State or district, as the case may 
be, to the State of Andhra Pradesh, and as including the territories 
transferred to that State or district, as the case may be, from the 
State of Andhra Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1362373</tid>
<number>17</number>Sitting members. Every sitting member of the Legislative 
Council of Andhra Pradesh or of Madras representing a Council 
constituency the extent of which is altered by virtue of section 16 
shall, as from the appointed day, be deemed to have been elected to 
the said Council by that constituency as so altered.
PART

HIGH COURTS

PART IV

HIGH COURTS



</article>



<article><tid>1580667</tid>
<number> 18</number> Extension of jurisdiction of, and transfer of proceedings to, 
Andhra Pradesh High Court.
<section><tid>64869</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided,-- 

<subsection><tid>1134201</tid>
<number>a</number>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Andhra Pradesh 
shall, as from the appointed day, extend to the 
territories specified in the First Schedule; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>197283</tid>
<number>b</number>the High Court at Madras shall, as from that day, have 
no jurisdiction in respect of the said territories.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>425844</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court at Madras 
immediately before the appointed day as are certified by the Chief 
Justice of that High Court, having regard to the place of accrual of 
the cause of action and other circumstances, to be proceedings which 
ought to be heard and decided by the High Court of Andhra Pradesh 
shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be transferred to 
the High Court of Andhra Pradesh.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>537</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>383168</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2), but save as hereinafter provided, the High Court at Madras shall 
have, and the High Court of Andhra Pradesh shall not have, 
jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of appeals, applications 
for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review and 
other proceedings, where any such proceedings seek any relief in 
respect of any order passed by the High Court at Madras before the 
appointed day:
Provided that if, after such proceedings have been entertained by 
the High Court at Madras, it appears to the Chief Justice of that High 
Court that they ought to be transferred to the High Court of Andhra 
Pradesh, he shall order that they shall be so transferred, and such 
proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>12047</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court at Madras--

<subsection><tid>106965</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day in any proceedings transferred 
to the High Court of Andhra Pradesh by virtue of sub- 
section (2), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>885126</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court 
at Madras retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- section 
 (3),
shall, for all purposes, have effect, not only as an order of the 
High Court at Madras, but also as an order made by the High Court of 
Andhra Pradesh.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1510748</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to any rule made or direction given by the High Court 
of Andhra Pradesh, any such person who immediately before the 
appointed day is an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at 
Madras as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief Justice of the 
High Court of Andhra Pradesh having regard to the transfer of 
territories from the State of Madras to the State of Andhra Pradesh, 
shall be recognised as an advocate entitled to practise in the High 
Court of Andhra Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>18679</tid>
<number> 19</number> Extension of jurisdiction of, and transfer of proceedings to, 
Madras High Court.
<section><tid>1126929</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided,-- 

<subsection><tid>507078</tid>
<number>a</number>the jurisdiction of the High Court at Madras shall, as 
from the appointed day, extend to the territories 
specified in the Second Schedule; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1900783</tid>
<number>b</number>the High Court of Andhra Pradesh shall, as from that 
day, have no jurisdiction in respect of the said 
territories.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1420801</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court of andhra Pradesh 
immediately before the appointed day as are certified by

<pagefootnote><pagenum>538</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Chief Justice of that High Court, having regard to the place of 
accrual of the cause of action and other circumstances, to be 
proceedings which ought to be heard and decided by the High Court at 
Madras shall, as soon as may be after such certification, be 
transferred to the High Court at Madras.


</section>

<section><tid>898872</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2), but save as hereinafter provided, the High Court of Andhra 
Pradesh shall have, and the High Court at Madras shall not have, 
jurisdiction to entertain, hear or dispose of appeals, applications 
for leave to appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review and 
other proceedings, where any such proceedings seek any relief in 
respect of any order passed by the High Court of Andhra Pradesh before 
the appointed day:
Provided that if, after such proceedings have been entertained by 
the High Court of Andhra Pradesh, it appears to the Chief Justice of 
that High Court that they ought to be transferred to the High Court at 
Madras, he shall order that they shall be so transferred, and such 
proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>1724599</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court of Andhra Pradesh--

<subsection><tid>895300</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day in any proceedings transferred 
to the High Court at Madras by virtue of sub- section 
 (2), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>732934</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court 
of Andhra Pradesh retains jurisdiction by virtue of 
sub- section (3),
shall, for all purposes, have effect, not only as an order of the High 
Court of Andhra Pradesh, but also as an order made by the High Court 
of Madras.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>867798</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to any rule made or direction given by the High Court 
at Madras, any such person who immediately before the appointed day is 
an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Andhra Pradesh 
as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief Justice of the High 
Court at Madras having regard to the transfer of territories from the 
State of Andhra Pradesh to the State of Madras, shall be recognised as 
an advocate entitled to practise in the High Court at Madras.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>71141</tid>
<number>20</number>Right to appear or act in any proceedings transferred under 
section 18 or section 19. Any person who immediately before the 
appointed day is an advocate entitled to practise, or an attorney 
entitled to act, in the High Court of Andhra Pradesh or the High Court 
at Madras and was authorised to appear or to act in any proceedings 
transferred under section 18 or section 19 shall have the right to 
appear, or to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>539</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

act, as the case may be, in the High Court to which the proceedings 
have been transferred, in relation to those proceedings.



</article>



<article><tid>1547219</tid>
<number> 21</number> Interpretation. For the purposes of sections 18 and 19,--
<section><tid>1378115</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High 
Court of Andhra Pradesh or the High Court at Madras 
until that Court has disposed of all issues between the 
parties, including any issue with respect to the 
taxation of the costs of the proceedings and shall 
include appeals, applications for leave to appeal to 
the Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions 
for revision and petitions for writs;

</section>

<section><tid>1815774</tid>
<number>b</number>references to the High Court of Andhra Pradesh or the 
High Court at Madras shall be construed as including 
references to a Judge or division court thereof, and 
references to an order made by a court or a Judge shall 
be construed as including references to a sentence, 
judgment or decree passed or made by that court or 
Judge.
PART

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE

PART V

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1539345</tid>
<number> 22</number> Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred 
territories under existing appropriation Acts.
<section><tid>410167</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the  
appointed day, any Act passed by the Legislature of the State of 
Andhra Pradesh or Madras before that day for the appropriation of any 
moneys out of the Consolidated Fund of the State to meet any 
expenditure in respect of any part of the financial year <year>1959</year>- 60 shall 
have effect also in relation to the territories transferred to that 
State by the provisions of Part II and it shall be lawful for the 
State Government to spend any amount in those territories out of the 
amount authorised by such Act to be expended for any service in that 
State.

</section>

<section><tid>269780</tid>
<number>2</number>The Governor of Andhra Pradesh or of Madras may, after the 
appointed day, authorise such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund 
of the State as he deems necessary for any purpose or service in the 
territories transferred to that State for a period of not more than 
three months beginning with the appointed day pending the sanction of 
such expenditure by the Legislature of the State.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1343751</tid>
<number>23</number>Reports relating to the accounts of Andhra Pradesh and 
Madras. The reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India 
referred to in clause (2) of article 151 of the Constitution relating 
to the accounts of the State of Andhra Pradesh or Madras in respect of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>540</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

any period prior to the appointed day shall be submitted to the 
Governor of each of the States of Andhra Pradesh and Madras who shall 
cause them to be laid before the Legislature of the State.



</article>



<article><tid>430411</tid>
<number>24</number>Distribution of revenues. Section 3 of the Union Duties of 
Excise (Distribution) Act, <year>1957</year> (55 of <year>1957</year>), sections 3 and 5 of the 
Estate Duty and Tax on Railway Passenger Fares (Distribution) Act, 
 <year>1957</year> (57 of <year>1957</year>), section 4 of and the Second Schedule to the 
Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> 
 (58 of <year>1957</year>), and paragraphs 3 and 5 of the Constitution (Distribution  
  of Revenues) No. 2 Order, <year>1957</year>, shall, as from the appointed day, have 
effect subject to such modifications as the President may, by order 
published in the Official Gazette, specify having regard to the 
transfer of territories effected by the provisions of Part II of this 
Act.
PART

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

PART VI

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES



</article>



<article><tid>874458</tid>
<number> 25</number> Land and goods.
<section><tid>1933251</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions of this  
Part, all land and all stores, articles and other goods, including 
cash balances in all treasuries in the territories specified in the 
First Schedule or the Second Schedule shall, as from the appointed 
day, pass to the State to which the territories are transferred.

</section>

<section><tid>15287</tid>
<number>2</number>In this section, the expression" land" includes immovable 
property of every kind and any rights in or over such property.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1448130</tid>
<number>26</number>Arrears of taxes. The right of Andhra Pradesh or Madras to 
recover arrears of any tax or duty on property situate in the 
transferred territories, including land revenue, or to recover arrears 
of any other tax or duty in any case where the place of assessment of 
that tax or duty is in the transferred territories shall belong to the 
State to which the territories are transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>842088</tid>
<number>27</number>Right to recover loans and advances. The right to recover any 
loans or advances made before the appointed day by Andhra Pradesh or 
Madras to any local body, society, agriculturist or other person in 
the transferred territories shall belong to the State to which the 
territories are transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>1929563</tid>
<number>28</number>Refund of taxes collected in excess. The liability of Andhra 
Pradesh or Madras to refund any tax or duty on property situate in the 
transferred territories, including land revenue, collected in excess 
shall be the liability of the State to which the territories are 
transferred, and the liability of Andhra Pradesh or Madras to refund 
any other tax or duty collected in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>541</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

excess in any case where the place of assessment of that tax or duty 
is in the transferred territories shall also be the liability of the 
State to which those territories are transferred.



</article>



<article><tid>1820657</tid>
<number>29</number>Deposits. The liability of Andhra Pradesh or Madras in 
respect of any civil deposit or local fund deposit made in the 
transferred territories shall, as from the appointed day, be the 
liability of the State to which the territories are transferred.


</article>



<article><tid>94178</tid>
<number>30</number>Provident funds. The liability of Andhra Pradesh or Madras in 
respect of the provident fund account of a Government servant in 
service on the appointed day shall, as from that day, be the liability 
of the State to which the Government servant is permanently allotted.


</article>



<article><tid>277936</tid>
<number>31</number>Pensions. The liability of Andhra Pradesh or Madras in 
respect of pensions shall be apportioned between those States in such 
manner as may be agreed upon between them or, in default of such 
agreement, in such manner as the President may, by notified order, 
specify having regard to the transfer of territories effected by this 
Act and the principles underlying the provisions of the Fifth Schedule 
to the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1373776</tid>
<number> 32</number> Contracts.
<section><tid>616428</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, before the appointed day, the State of  
Andhra Pradesh or Madras has made any contract in the exercise of its 
executive power for any purposes of the State, that contract shall be 
deemed to have been made in the exercise of the executive power,--

<subsection><tid>1719454</tid>
<number>a</number>if such purposes are, as from that day, purposes 
relatable exclusively to the transferred territories, 
of the State to which the territories are transferred; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>406764</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, of the State which made the contract;
and all rights and liabilities which have accrued, or may accrue, 
under any such contract shall, to the extent to which they are rights 
or liabilities of the State which made the contract, be rights or 
liabilities of the State specified in clause (a) or clause (b) 
above.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>859961</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, there shall be deemed to be 
included in the liabilities which have accrued or may accrue under any 
contract--

<subsection><tid>1473012</tid>
<number>a</number>any liability to satisfy an order or award made by any 
court or other tribunal in proceedings relating to the 
contract; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>542</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1214353</tid>
<number>b</number>any liability in respect of expenses incurred in or in 
connection with any such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1626280</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall have effect subject to the other 
provisions of this Part relating to the apportionment of liabilities 
in respect of loans, guarantees and other financial obligations; and 
bank balances and securities shall, notwithstanding that they partake 
of the nature of contractual rights, be dealt with under those 
provisions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>881399</tid>
<number> 33</number> Liability in respect of actionable wrong. Where, immediately 
before the appointed day, the State of Andhra Pradesh or Madras is 
subject to any liability in respect of an actionable wrong, other than 
breach of contract, that liability shall,--
<section><tid>553911</tid>
<number>a</number>if the cause of action arose wholly within the 
transferred territories, be a liability of the State to 
which they are transferred; and

</section>

<section><tid>899991</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, continue to be a liability of the 
State which, immediately before that day, was subject 
to such liability.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>695787</tid>
<number> 34</number> Liability as guarantor of co- operative societies. Where, 
immediately before the appointed day, the State of Andhra Pradesh or 
Madras is liable as guarantor in respect of any liability of a 
registered co- operative society, that liability shall,--
<section><tid>620358</tid>
<number>a</number>if the area of the society' s operations is limited to 
the transferred territories, be a liability of the 
State to which the territories are transferred; and

</section>

<section><tid>1505889</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, continue to be a liability of the 
State which, immediately before that day, was subject 
to such liability.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>200307</tid>
<number>35</number>Items in suspense. If any item in suspense is ultimately 
found to affect an asset or liability of the nature referred to in any 
of the foregoing provisions of this Part, it shall be dealt with in 
accordance with that provision.


</article>



<article><tid>728437</tid>
<number>36</number>Power of Central Government to order allocation or adjustment 
in certain cases. Where either Andhra Pradesh or Madras becomes 
entitled to any property or obtains any benefits or becomes subject to 
any liability, and the Central Government, on a reference made within 
a period of three years from the appointed day by either of the 
States, is of opinion that it is just and equitable that that property 
or those benefits should be transferred to, or shared with, the other 
State or that a contribution towards that liability should be made by 
the other State, the said property or benefits shall be allocated in 
such manner between the two States, or the other State shall make to 
the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>543</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

State subject to the liability such contribution in respect thereof, 
as the Central Government may, after consultation with the two State 
Governments, by order determine.



</article>



<article><tid>1714415</tid>
<number>37</number>Certain expenditure to be charged on the Consolidated Fund. 
All sums payable by either Andhra Pradesh or Madras to the other State 
by virtue of the provisions of this Part shall be charged on the 
Consolidated Fund of the State by which such sums are payable.
PART

ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS

PART VII

ADMINISTRATIVE PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>823831</tid>
<number> 38</number> Provisions as to certain Financial Corporations.
<section><tid>1477185</tid>
<number>1</number>As from  
the appointed day, the Financial Corporation constituted under the 
State Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>), for the State of 
Andhra Pradesh shall be deemed to have been constituted for that State 
with its area as altered by the provisions of Part II of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1546223</tid>
<number>2</number>As from the appointed day, the Madras Industrial Investment 
Corporation constituted for the State of Madras shall be deemed to 
have been constituted for that State with its area as altered by the 
provisions of Part II of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>627329</tid>
<number>39</number>Amendment of Act 6 of <year>1942</year>. In the Multi- Unit Co- operative 
Societies Act, <year>1942</year>, in section 5A, in sub- section 1, for the words 
and figures" any co- operative society which, immediately before the 
 1st day of November, <year>1956</year>", the words" or any other enactment relating 
to reorganisation of States, any co- operative society which, 
immediately before the day on which the reorganisation takes place" 
shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1962423</tid>
<number> 40</number> Provision as to State Electricity Boards and apportionment of 
their assets and liabilities.
<section><tid>494619</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day, the State  
Electricity Boards constituted under the Electricity (Supply) Act, 
 <year>1948</year> (54 of <year>1948</year>), for the States of Andhra Pradesh and Madras shall 
be deemed to have been constituted for those States with their areas 
as altered by the provisions of Part II of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>101626</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertakings and assets of a State Electricity Board 
referred to in sub- section (1), situated in the territories specified 
in the First Schedule or, as the case may be, the Second Schedule 
shall, as from the appointed day, pass to the State to which the 
territories are transferred.

</section>

<section><tid>887073</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), the assets and 
liabilities of the State Electricity Boards referred to in sub- section 
 (1) shall be apportioned between them in such manner as may be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>544</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

agreed upon between the Governments of Andhra Pradesh and Madras 
within one year from the appointed day, or in default of such 
agreement, as the Central Government may by order determine.


</section>

<section><tid>1540999</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the 
arrangement which, immediately before the appointed day, was in force 
in regard to the generation or supply of electric power for the 
territories specified in the First Schedule or the Second Schedule 
shall continue to be in force after the appointed day on such terms 
and conditions and for such period as may be agreed upon between the 
Governments of Andhra Pradesh and Madras, or, in default of such 
agreement, as the Central Government may by order direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1431707</tid>
<number> 41</number> Special provisions with regard to Araniar Project.
<section><tid>541403</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, all rights and 
liabilities of the State of Madras in relation to the Araniar Project 
or the administration thereof shall, on the appointed day, be the 
rights and liabilities of the State of Andhra Pradesh and Madras, 
subject to such adjustments as may be made by agreement entered into 
by the said States or, if no such agreement is entered into within a 
period of one year from the appointed day, as the Central Government 
may by order determine having regard to the purposes of the Project, 
and any such order may provide for the management of the Project 
jointly by the said States or otherwise:
Provided that the order so made by the Central Government may be 
varied by any subsequent agreement entered into by the States of 
Andhra Pradesh and Madras.


</section>

<section><tid>1006993</tid>
<number>2</number>An agreement or order referred to in sub- section (1) shall 
provide also for the rights and liabilities of the States of Andhra 
Pradesh and Madras in relation to any extension or further development 
of the Project after the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1785166</tid>
<number>3</number>The rights and liabilities referred to in sub- sections (1) 
and (2) shall include--

<subsection><tid>1528106</tid>
<number>a</number>the rights to receive and to utilise water which may be 
available for distribution as a result of the Project; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1019971</tid>
<number>b</number>the rights and liabilities in respect of the 
administration of the Project and the construction, 
maintenance and operation thereof,
but shall not include the rights and liabilities under any contract 
entered into before the appointed day by the Government of Madras.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1792581</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may, from time to time, give such 
directions as may appear to it necessary generally in regard to any of 
the matters specified in the foregoing provisions of this section

<pagefootnote><pagenum>545</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and in particular, for the completion of the Project and its operation 
and maintenance thereafter:

Provided that no such direction shall be issued or have effect 
after an agreement has been entered into by the States of Andhra 
Pradesh and Madras under sub- section (1) or after an order has been 
made by the Central Government under that sub- section, whichever is 
earlier.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>710185</tid>
<number>42</number>Temporary provisions as to the continuance of certain 
existing road transport permits. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
section 63 of the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year> (4 of <year>1939</year>), a permit 
granted by the State Transport Aut hority of Andhra Pradesh or Madras 
or by any Regional Transport Authority in such State shall, if such 
permit was immediately before the appointed day valid and effective in 
any area within the transferred territories, be deemed to continue to 
be valid and effective in that area after that day subject to the 
provisions of that Act as for the time being in force in that area; 
and it shall not be necessary for any such permit to be countersigned 
by the State Transport Authority or any Regional Transport Authority 
in the State to which the territories are transferred for the purpose 
of validating it for use in such area:
Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with 
the State Governments, add to, amend or vary the conditions attached 
to the permit by the authority by which the permit was granted.



</article>



<article><tid>255823</tid>
<number> 43</number> Provisions relating to services.
<section><tid>1439596</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who,  
immediately before the appointed day, is serving in connection with 
the affairs of Andhra Pradesh or Madras shall, as from that day, 
continue so to serve, unless he is required by general or special 
order of the Central Government to serve provisionally in connection 
with the affairs of the other State.

</section>

<section><tid>278263</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Central 
Government shall, by general or special order, determine the State to 
which every person provisionally allotted to Andhra Pradesh or Madras 
shall be finally allotted for service and the date from which such 
allotment shall take effect or be deemed to have taken effect.

</section>

<section><tid>744601</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person who is finally allotted under the provisions of 
sub- section (2) to Andhra Pradesh or Madras shall, if he is not 
already serving therein, be made available for serving in that State 
from such date as may be agreed upon between the two State Governments 
or in default of such agreement, as may be determined by the Central 
Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>546</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1612832</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect, after the 
appointed day, the operation of the provisions of Chapter I of Part 
XIV of the Constitution in relation to the determination of the 
conditions of service of persons serving in connection with the 
affairs of Andhra Pradesh or Madras:
Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately 
before the appointed day to the case of any person provisionally or 
finally allotted to Andhra Pradesh or Madras under this section shall 
not be varied to his disadvantage except with the previous approval of 
the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>633879</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may at any time before or after the 
appointed day give such directions to either State Government as may 
appear to it to be necessary for the purpose of giving effect to the 
foregoing provisions of this section and the State Government shall 
comply with such directions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1126301</tid>
<number>44</number>Provisions as to the continuance of officers in the same 
posts. Every person who, immediately before the appointed day, is 
holding or discharging the duties of any post or office in connection 
with the affairs of Andhra Pradesh or Madras in any area which on that 
day falls within the other State shall continue to hold the same post 
or office in the State in which such area is included on that day and 
shall be deemed as from that day to have been duly appointed to that 
post or office by the Government of, or other appropriate authority 
in, such State:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
the competent authority, after the appointed day, from passing in 
relation to such person any order affecting his continuance in such 
post or office.

PART

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART VIII

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>285854</tid>
<number>45</number>Territorial extent of laws. The provisions of section 3 shall 
not be deemed to have effected any change in the territories to which 
any law in force immediately before the appointed day extends or 
applies, and territorial references in any such law to Andhra Pradesh 
or Madras shall, until otherwise provided by a competent legislature 
or other competent authority, be construed as meaning the territories 
within that State immediately before the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>1804150</tid>
<number>46</number>Power to adapt laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application of any law in relation to Andhra Pradesh or Madras, the 
appropriate Government may, before the expiration of one year from the 
appointed day, by

<pagefootnote><pagenum>547</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

order make such adaptations and modifications of the law, whether by 
way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient, and 
thereupon every such law shall have effect subject to the adaptations 
and modifications so made until altered, repealed or amended by a 
competent authority or competent legislature.

Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate 
Government" means, as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated 
in the Union List, the Central Government, and as respects any other 
law, the State Government.



</article>



<article><tid>7388</tid>
<number>47</number>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or 
insufficient provision has been made for the adaptation of a law made 
before the appointed day, any court, tribunal or authority, required 
or empowered to enforce such law may, for the purpose of facilitating 
its application in relation to Andhra Pradesh or Madras, construe the 
law in such manner, without affecting the substance, as may be 
necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the court, tribunal 
or authority.


</article>



<article><tid>1497297</tid>
<number>48</number>Power to name authorities, etc., for exercising statutory 
functions. The Government of the State of Andhra Pradesh or Madras, as 
respects any territory transferred to that State by the provisions of 
Part II, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify the 
authority, officer or person who, as from the appointed day, shall be 
competent to exercise such functions exercisable under any law in 
force on that day as may be mentioned in that notification, and such 
law shall have effect accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1225346</tid>
<number>49</number>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed 
day, the State of Andhra Pradesh or Madras is a party to any legal 
proceedings with respect to any property, rights or liabilities 
transferred to the other State under this Act, the other State shall 
be deemed to be substituted for the State from which such property, 
rights or liabilities are transferred as a party to those proceedings, 
or added as a party thereto, as the case may be, and the proceedings 
may continue accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1640045</tid>
<number> 50</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>1853155</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before a court (other than a High  
  Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that day 
falls within the State of Andhra Pradesh or Madras shall, if it is a 
proceeding relatable exclusively to any part of the territories which 
as from that day are the territories of the other State, stand 
transferred to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer 
in the other State.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>548</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>894999</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should 
stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the 
High Court having jurisdiction in respect of the area in which the 
court, tribunal, authority or officer before which, or before whom, 
such proceeding is pending on the appointed day, is functioning and 
the decision of that High Court shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1378163</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section,--

<subsection><tid>1687644</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>544284</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in 
a State means--

<subsubsection><tid>1889065</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer 
in which, or before whom, the proceeding would 
have lain if the proceeding had been instituted 
after the appointed day, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>849187</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, 
authority or officer in that State as may be 
determined after the appointed day by the 
Government of that State, or before the appointed 
day by the Government of the other State, to be 
the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or 
officer.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1830194</tid>
<number>51</number>Right of pleaders to practise in certain courts. Any person 
who, immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader 
entitled to practise in any subordinate courts in the transferred 
territories shall, for a period of six months from that day, continue 
to be entitled to practise in those courts, notwithstanding that the 
whole or any part of the territories within the jurisdiction of those 
courts has been transferred to another State.


</article>



<article><tid>1716410</tid>
<number>52</number>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.


</article>



<article><tid>42448</tid>
<number>53</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may by 
order do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears 
to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the 
difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>667190</tid>
<number> 54</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>346905</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1160170</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>549</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.





</section>

</article>



 </act>