<act><tid>1449261</tid>
<title>THE PATENTS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 38 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 25th June, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Patents Act, <year>1970</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1688861</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>817464</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Patents (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>450308</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any 
reference in any such provision to the commencem nt of this Act shall 
be construed as a reference to the coming into force of that 
provision.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1789474</tid>
<number>2</number>Substitution of certain words for the words" High Court" and 
" Court".- In the Patents Act, <year>1970</year> (39 of <year>1970</year>)  (hereinafter referred  
  to as the principal Act), for the words" High Court" wherever they 
occur in sections 21, 43 and 71 and the word" Court" o curring in 
sections 21 and 71, the words" Appellate Board" and" Board" shall 
respectively be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1931666</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>95110</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (a), the following clauses shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (a)" Appellate Board" means the Appellate Board referred to in 
section 116;


</section>

<section><tid>1781455</tid>
<number>ab</number>" assignee" includes an assignee of the assignee and the legal 
representative of a deceased assignee and references to the assignee 
of any person include references to the assignee of the legal 
representative or assignee of that person;

</section>

<section><tid>1169153</tid>
<number>ac</number>" capable of industrial application", in relation to an invention, 
means that the invention is capable of being made or used in an 
industry;';

</section>

<section><tid>90151</tid>
<number>b</number>for clause (d), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (d)" convention country" means a country or a country which is member 
of a group of countries or a union of countries or an 
Inter- governmental organisation notified as such under sub- section (1) 
of section 133;';


</section>

<section><tid>365767</tid>
<number>c</number>for clause (g), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (g)" food" means any article of nourishment for human consumption and 
also includes any substance intended for the use of infants, invalids 
or convalescents as an article of food or drink;';


</section>

<section><tid>884694</tid>
<number>d</number>in clause (i),-

<subsection><tid>1067205</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- clause (i), for the words" Union territory of Delhi", the 
words" National Capital Territory of Delhi" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1526711</tid>
<number>ii</number>for sub- clause (ii), the following sub- clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (ii) in relation to the State of Arunachal Pradesh and the State of 
Mizoram, the Gauhati High Court (the High Court of Assam, Nagaland,  
  Meghalaya, Manipur, Tripura, Mizoram and Arunachal Pradesh);";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>389376</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- clause (v), for the words" Union territory of Goa, Daman 
and Diu", the words" State of Goa, the Union territory of Daman and 
Diu" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>977322</tid>
<number>e</number>after clause (i), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (ia)" international application" means an application for patent made 
in accordance with the Patent Cooperation Treaty;';


</section>

<section><tid>427640</tid>
<number>f</number>for clause (j), the following clauses shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (j)" invention" means a new product or process involving an inventive 
step and capable of industrial application;


</section>

<section><tid>647582</tid>
<number>ja</number>" inventive step" means a feature that makes the invention not 
obvious to a person skilled in the art;';

</section>

<section><tid>560487</tid>
<number>g</number>for clause (m), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (m)" patent" means a patent granted under this Act;';


</section>

<section><tid>948763</tid>
<number>h</number>after clause (o), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (oa)" Patent Cooperation Treaty" means the Patent Cooperation Treaty 
done at Washington on the 19th day of June, <year>1970</year> as amended and 
modified from time to time;';


</section>

<section><tid>1357121</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (u), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (u)" prescribed" means,-


<subsection><tid>1733386</tid>
<number>A</number>in relation to proceedings before a High Court, prescribed by 
rules made by the High Court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1183003</tid>
<number>B</number>in relation to proceedings before the Appellate Board, prescribed 
by rules made by the Appellate Board; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1694563</tid>
<number>C</number>in other cases, prescribed by rules made under this Act.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1148989</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1638691</tid>
<number>a</number>for clause (b), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
'' (b) an invention the primary or intended use or commercial 
exploitation of which would be contrary to public order or morality or 
which causes serious prejudice to human, animal or plant life or 
health or to the environment;";


</section>

<section><tid>1974197</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (c), after the words" an abstract theory", the words" or 
discovery of any living thing or non- living substance occurring in 
nature" shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>1395863</tid>
<number>c</number>clause (g) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>985510</tid>
<number>d</number>in clause (i),-

<subsection><tid>367534</tid>
<number>i</number>after the word" prophylactic", the words" diagnostic, therapeutic" 
shall be inserted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>97941</tid>
<number>ii</number>the words" or plants" shall be omitted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1939739</tid>
<number>e</number>after clause (i), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (j) plants and animals in whole or any part thereof other than 
micro- organisms but including seeds, varieties and species and 
essentially biological processes for production or propagation of 
plants and animals;


</section>

<section><tid>1450529</tid>
<number>k</number>a mathematical or business method or a computer programme per se 
or algorithms;

</section>

<section><tid>1467380</tid>
<number>l</number>a literary, dramatic, musical or artistic work or any other 
aesthetic creation whatsoever including cinematographic works and 
television productions;

</section>

<section><tid>1932975</tid>
<number>m</number>a mere scheme or rule or method of performing mental act or method 
of playing game;

</section>

<section><tid>502140</tid>
<number>n</number>a presentation of information;

</section>

<section><tid>530788</tid>
<number>o</number>topography of integrated circuits;

</section>

<section><tid>288731</tid>
<number>p</number>an invention which, in effect, is traditional knowledge or which 
is an aggregation or duplication of known properties of traditionally 
known component or components.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1188010</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, after 
sub- section (2), the following Explanation shall be inserted, namely:-
' Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," chemical processes" 
includes biochemical, biotechnological and microbiological 
processes.'.



</article>



<article><tid>1083511</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 7.- In section 7 of the principal Act, after 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (1A) Every international application under the Patent Cooperation 
Treaty for a patent, as may be filed designating India, shall be 
deemed to be an application under this Act, if a corresponding 
application has also been filed before the Controller in I dia.".



</article>



<article><tid>413898</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 8.- In section 8 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>827358</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>166690</tid>
<number>i</number>in the opening portion, after the words" he shall file along with 
his application", the words" or subsequently within such period as the 
Controller may, for good and sufficient reasons, allow" shall be 
inserted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>533762</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (a), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (a) a statement setting out detailed particulars of such application; 
and";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>566179</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (b), for the words" details of the nature referred to 
in", the words" detailed particulars as required under" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>720100</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2) At any time after an application for patent is filed in India and 
till the grant of patent or refusal to grant of patent is made 
thereon, the Controller may also require the applicant to furnish 
details, as may be prescribed, relating to the proces ing of the 
application in a country outside India, and in that event the 
applicant shall furnish information available to him to the Controller 
within thirty days from the date of receipt of the communication 
requiring such furnishing of information or w thin such further period 
as the Controller may, for good and sufficient reasons, allow.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1031008</tid>
<number> 8</number> Amendment of section 10.- In section 10 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>376259</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (4), after clause (c), the following clause shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (d) be accompanied by an abstract to provide technical information on 
the invention:

Provided that-


<subsection><tid>1909433</tid>
<number>i</number>the Controller may amend the abstract for providing better 
information to third parties; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>671407</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the applicant mentions a biological material in the 
specification which may not be described in such a way as to satisfy 
clauses (a) and (b), and if such material is not available to the 
public, the application shall be completed by depositing t e material 
to an authorised depository institution as may be notified by the 
Central Government in the Official Gazette and by fulfilling the 
following conditions, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>1537177</tid>
<number>A</number>the deposit of the material shall be made not later than the date 
of the patent application in India;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>302983</tid>
<number>B</number>all the available characteristics of the material required for it 
to be correctly identified or indicated are included in the 
specification including the name, address of the depository 
institution and the date and number of the deposit of the materi l at 
the institution;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1545717</tid>
<number>C</number>access to the material is available in the depository institution 
only after the date of the application for patent in India or if a 
priority is claimed after the date of the priority;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1962856</tid>
<number>D</number>disclose the source and geographical origin of the biological 
material in the specification, when used in an invention.";

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1251041</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (4), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (4A) In case of an international application designating India,-


<subsection><tid>615692</tid>
<number>i</number>the title, description, drawings, abstract and claims filed with 
the application shall be taken as the complete specification for the 
purposes of this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>502327</tid>
<number>ii</number>the filing date of the application and its complete 
specification, processed by the patent office as designated office or 
elected office, shall be the international filing date accorded under 
the Patent Cooperation Treaty.";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1933439</tid>
<number>c</number>for sub- section (5), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (5) The claim or claims of a complete specification shall relate to a 
single invention, or to a group of inventions linked so as to form a 
single inventive concept, shall be clear and succinct and shall be 
fairly based on the matter disclosed in the spe ification.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>338722</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of Chapter IV.- In Chapter IV of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1215196</tid>
<number>a</number>for the Chapter heading" EXAMINATION OF APPLICATIONS", the 
following Chapter heading shall be substituted, namely:-
" PUBLICATION AND EXAMINATION OF APPLICATIONS";


</section>

<section><tid>1962518</tid>
<number>b</number>before section 12, the following sections shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" 11A. Publication of applications.- (1) Applications for patents shall 
not be open to the public for a period of eighteen months from the 
date of filing or date of priority, whichever is earlier.


<subsection><tid>615352</tid>
<number>2</number>Except when a secrecy direction is given under section 35, every 
application for a patent shall, on the expiry of the period as 
specified in sub- section (1), be published.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1850105</tid>
<number>3</number>The publication of every application for a patent shall be 
notified in the Official Gazette.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>74657</tid>
<number>4</number>In case a secrecy direction has been given in respect of an 
application under section 35, then, it shall be published after the 
expiry of the period of eighteen months or when the secrecy direction 
has ceased to operate, whichever is later.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>360767</tid>
<number>5</number>The publication of every application under this section shall 
include the particulars of the date of application, number of 
application, name and address of the applicant identifying the 
application and an abstract.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1291874</tid>
<number>6</number>Upon publication of an application for a patent under this 
section-

<subsubsection><tid>1967606</tid>
<number>a</number>the depository institution shall make the biological material 
mentioned in the specification available to the public;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1512871</tid>
<number>b</number>the patent office may, on payment of such fee as may be 
prescribed, make the specification and drawings, if any, of such 
application available to the public.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>283422</tid>
<number> 11B</number> Request for examination.-
<section><tid>928894</tid>
<number>1</number>No application for a patent shall  
be required to be examined unless the applicant or any other 
interested person makes a request in the prescribed manner for such 
examination within forty- eight months from the date of fi ing of the 
application for patent.

</section>

<section><tid>1578635</tid>
<number>2</number>In case of an application filed before the commencement of the 
Patents (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, a request in the prescribed manner for 
examination shall be made by the applicant or any other interested 
person within a period of twelve months from the d te of such 
commencement or within forty- eight months from the date of the 
application, whichever is later.

</section>

<section><tid>1094149</tid>
<number>3</number>In case of an application in respect of a claim for a patent 
covered under sub- section (2) of section 5, a request in the 
prescribed manner for examination shall be made by the applicant or 
any other interested person within a period of twelve months from the 
 31st day of December, <year>2004</year> or within forty- eight months from the date 
of the application, whichever is later.

</section>

<section><tid>1026750</tid>
<number>4</number>In case the applicant or any other interested person does not make 
a request for examination of the application for a patent within the 
period as specified under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) or 
sub- section (3), the application shall be treate as withdrawn by the 
applicant: Provided that-

<subsection><tid>186786</tid>
<number>i</number>the applicant may, at any time after the filing of the application 
but before the grant of the patent, withdraw the application made by 
him; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1367857</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case where a secrecy direction has been issued under section 
35, the request for examination may be made within forty- eight months 
from the date of revocation of the secrecy direction.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1740994</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of section 12.- In section 12 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1398853</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>134331</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" When the complete specification has been filed in 
respect of an application for a patent, the application and 
specification relating thereto", the words, brackets, figures and 
letter" When a request for examination has been made in res ect of an 
application for a patent in the prescribed manner under sub- section 
 (1) or sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) of section 11B, the 
application and specification and other documents relating thereto" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>72183</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (a), for the words" specification relating thereto", 
the words" specification and other documents relating thereto" shall 
be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1325230</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" specification relating 
thereto", the words" specification and other documents relating 
thereto" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1333534</tid>
<number>11</number>Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), the words" as the Controller may direct" shall be 
omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>4075</tid>
<number>12</number>Substitution of new section for section 15.- For section 15 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 15. Power of Controller to refuse or require amended applications, 
etc., in certain cases.- Where the Controller is satisfied that the 
application or any specification or any other document filed in 
pursuance thereof does not comply with the requirements of this Act or 
of any rules made thereunder, the Controller may require the 
application, specification or other document, as the case may be, to 
be amended to his satisfaction before he proceeds with the application 
or refuse the application on failure o do so.".



</article>



<article><tid>1145297</tid>
<number>13</number>Amendment of section 17.- In section 17 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (2) Where an application or specification (including drawings) or any 
other document is required to be amended under section 15, the 
application or specification or other document shall, if the 
Controller so directs, be deemed to have been made on the d te on 
which the requirement is complied with or where the application or 
specification or other document is returned to the applicant, on the 
date on which it is refiled after complying with the requirement.".



</article>



<article><tid>433536</tid>
<number> 14</number> Amendment of section 21.- In section 21 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1962552</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the portion beginning with the words 
" fifteen months" and ending with the words" of this section", the 
words" twelve months from the date on which the first statement of 
objections to the application or complete specificati n or other 
documents relating thereto is forwarded to the applicant by the 
Controller," shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>449898</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- section (2) shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>84520</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (3),-

<subsection><tid>1291161</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words, brackets and figure" fifteen months specified in 
sub- section (1) or the extended period", the words" twelve months" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>775119</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" fifteen months or the extended period, as the case 
may be", the words" twelve months" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1990359</tid>
<number>d</number>in sub- section (4), for the words" fifteen months, or as the case 
may be, the extended period, until the expiration of", the words 
" twelve months to" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>439341</tid>
<number>15</number>Amendment of section 22.- In section 22 of the principal Act, in 
the proviso, for the words" eighteen months", the words" twelve 
months" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1617145</tid>
<number>16</number>Amendment of section 23.- In section 23 of the prinicpal Act, for 
the words" filed in pursuance thereof", the words" as accepted by the 
Controller along with other documents filed by the applicant in 
pursuance thereof" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>822449</tid>
<number> 17</number> Amendment of section 24C.- In section 24C of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1004726</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (c), for the word and figures" section 85", the word and 
figures" section 84" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1997969</tid>
<number>b</number>for clause (d), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (d) clause (e) of sub- section (7) of section 84 shall be omitted.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1973769</tid>
<number> 18</number> Amendment of section 25.- In section 25 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>904926</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), after clause (i), the following clauses shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (j) that the complete specification does not disclose or wrongly 
mentions the source or geographical origin of biological material used 
for the invention;


</section>

<section><tid>1366748</tid>
<number>k</number>that the invention so far as claimed in any claim of the complete 
specification is anticipated having regard to the knowledge, oral or 
otherwise, available within any local or indigenous community in India 
or elsewhere,";

</section>

<section><tid>1259026</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" shall give", the words" may, if 
so desired, give" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>192512</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (3), after the words" shall be taken of any", the 
words" personal document or secret trial or" shall be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1837417</tid>
<number>19</number>Amendment of section 35.- In section 35 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, the words" to any person or class of persons 
specified in the directions" shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1401282</tid>
<number>20</number>Amendment of section 36.- In section 36 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) The question whether an invention in respect of which directions 
have been given under section 35 continues to be relevant for defence 
purposes shall be reconsidered by the Central Government at intervals 
of twelve months or on a request made by the applicant which is found 
to be reasonable by the Controller and if, on such reconsideration it 
appears to the Central Government that the publication of the 
invention would no longer be prejudicial to the defence of India or in 
case of an application fi ed by a foreign applicant it is found that 
the invention is published outside India, it shall forthwith give 
notice to the Controller to revoke the direction and the Controller 
shall thereupon revoke the directions previously given by him.".



</article>



<article><tid>1700378</tid>
<number> 21</number> Insertion of new section 39.- After section 38 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 39. Prohibition to apply, under certain circumstances, for patents 
relevant for defence purposes, etc.- (1) No person shall, except under 
the authority of a written permit granted by or on behalf of the 
Controller, make or cause to be made any applicatio outside India for 
the grant of a patent for an invention relevant for defence purposes 
or related to atomic energy unless-

<section><tid>140098</tid>
<number>a</number>an application for a patent for the same invention has been made 
in India, not less than six weeks before the application outside 
India; and

</section>

<section><tid>1954788</tid>
<number>b</number>either no direction has been given under sub- section (1) of 
section 35 in relation to the application in India, or all such 
directions have been revoked.

<subsection><tid>439323</tid>
<number>2</number>The Controller shall not grant written permission to any person to 
make any application outside India without the prior consent of the 
Central Government.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1659521</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall not apply in relation to an invention for which 
an application for protection has first been filed in a country 
outside India by a person resident outside India.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>774090</tid>
<number>22</number>Amendment of section 40.- In section 40 of the principal Act, 
after the words and figures" under section 35", the words and figures 
" or makes or causes to be made an application for grant of a patent 
outside India in contravention of section 39" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>158968</tid>
<number> 23</number> Amendment of section 43.- In section 43 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1,-
<section><tid>213313</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (c), the word" or" shall be inserted at the end;

</section>

<section><tid>1924972</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (c), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (d) the application has not been found to be in contravention of any 
of the provisions of the Act,".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>177150</tid>
<number>24</number>Amendment of section 45.- In section 45 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
'' (1) Subject to the other provisions contained in this Act, every 
patent shall be dated as of the date on which the application for 
patent was filed.''.



</article>



<article><tid>1686008</tid>
<number> 25</number> Substitution of new section for section 48.- For section 48 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 48. Rights of patentees.- Subject to the other provisions contained 
in this Act and the conditions specified in section 47, a patent 
granted under this Act shall confer upon the patentee-

<section><tid>1123021</tid>
<number>a</number>where the subject matter of the patent is a product, the exclusive 
right to prevent third parties, who do not have his consent, from the 
act of making, using, offering for sale, selling or importing for 
those purposes that product in India;

</section>

<section><tid>1387983</tid>
<number>b</number>where the subject matter of the patent is a process, the exclusive 
right to prevent third parties, who do not have his consent, from the 
act of using that process, and from the act of using, offering for 
sale, selling or importing for those purposes he product obtained 
directly by that process in India: Provided that the product obtained 
is not a product in respect of which no patent shall be granted under 
this Act.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1392167</tid>
<number>26</number>Amendment of section 50.- In section 50 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for the words" make, use, exercise and sell the 
patented invention", the words and figures" the rights conferred by 
section 48'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1815882</tid>
<number> 27</number> Amendment of section 53.- In section 53 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1873681</tid>
<number>a</number>for sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
'' (1) Subject to the provisions of this Act, the term of every patent 
granted, after the commencement of the Patents (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, 
and the term of every patent which has not expired and has not ceased 
to have effect, on the date of such commence ent, under this Act, 
shall be twenty years from the date of filing of the application for 
the patent.'';


</section>

<section><tid>991157</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (4) Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, on cessation of the patent right due to non- payment of 
renewal fee or on the expiry of the term of patent, the subject matter 
covered by the said patent shall not be en itled to any protection.''.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>26942</tid>
<number> 28</number> Amendment of section 57.- In section 57 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1263008</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), after the word" specification" at both the 
places where it occurs, the words" or any document relating thereto" 
shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>1509616</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" or a specification", the 
words" or a complete specification or any document relating thereto" 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>316714</tid>
<number>c</number>for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (3) Any application for leave to amend an application for a patent or 
a complete specification or a document relating thereto under this 
section made after the acceptance of the complete specification and 
the nature of the proposed amendment may be adve tised in the Official 
Gazette if the amendment, in the opinion of the Controller, is 
substantive.";


</section>

<section><tid>1845996</tid>
<number>d</number>in sub- section (6),-

<subsection><tid>1060767</tid>
<number>i</number>after the words" amend his specification", the words" or any 
document relating thereto" shall be inserted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488256</tid>
<number>ii</number>after the words" acceptance of the complete specification", the 
words" along with other documents filed by the applicant" shall be 
inserted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1000169</tid>
<number> 29</number> Amendment of section 59.- In section 59 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1766205</tid>
<number>i</number>for sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (1) No amendment of an application for a patent or a complete 
specification or any document relating thereto shall be made except by 
way of disclaimer, correction or explanation, and no amendment thereof 
shall be allowed, except for the purpose of incor oration of actual 
fact, and no amendment of a complete specification shall be allowed, 
the effect of which would be that the specification as amended would 
claim or describe matter not in substance disclosed or shown in the 
specification before the amend ent, or that any claim of the 
specification as amended would not fall wholly within the scope of a 
claim of the specification before the amendment.";


</section>

<section><tid>1243935</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>1182426</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" complete specification, any amendment of the 
specification", the words" complete specification along with other 
documents relating thereto, any amendment of the specification or any 
other document relating thereto" shall be substituted

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1335153</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (a), for the word" specification", the words 
" specification along with other documents relating thereto" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1753215</tid>
<number>c</number>in clause (b), for the word" specification", the words 
" specification or any other document relating thereto" shall be 
substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>591129</tid>
<number> 30</number> Amendment of section 60.- In section 60 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1880815</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" one year", the words" eighteen 
months" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>434948</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- section (2) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>858819</tid>
<number> 31</number> Amendment of section 64.- In section 64 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>844982</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1970467</tid>
<number>i</number>the proviso to clause (b) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1204259</tid>
<number>ii</number>the proviso to clause (e) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1319615</tid>
<number>iii</number>the proviso to clause (f) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>828120</tid>
<number>iv</number>in clause (n), after the words and figures" under section 35", 
the words and figures" or made or caused to be made an application for 
the grant of a patent outside India in contravention of section 39" 
shall be inserted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>116898</tid>
<number>v</number>after clause (o), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (p) that the complete specification does not disclose or wrongly 
mentions the source or geographical origin of biological material used 
for the invention;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1161213</tid>
<number>q</number>that the invention so far as claimed in any claim of the complete 
specification was anticipated having regard to the knowledge, oral or 
otherwise, available within any local or indigenous community in India 
or elsewhere.";

</section>

<section><tid>8125</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), in clause (a), for the words" secret use", the 
words" personal document or secret trial or secret use" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1853769</tid>
<number> 32</number> Amendment of section 67.- In section 67 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (4), the following sub- sections shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (4) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), it shall 
be lawful for the Controller to keep the register of patents or any 
part thereof in computer floppies, diskettes or any other electronic 
form subject to such safeguards as may be prescr bed.

<section><tid>1164323</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, 
 <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>), a copy of, or extracts from, the register of 
patents, certified to be a true copy under the hand of the Controller 
or any officer duly authorised by the Controller in th s behalf shall, 
in all legal proceedings, be admissible in evidence.

</section>

<section><tid>1514006</tid>
<number>6</number>In the event the register is kept wholly or partly in computer 
floppies, diskettes or any other electronic form,-

<subsection><tid>654405</tid>
<number>a</number>reference in this Act to an entry in the register shall be deemed 
to include reference to a record of particulars kept in computer 
floppies, diskettes or any other electronic form and comprising the 
register or part of the register;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1120141</tid>
<number>b</number>references in this Act to particulars being registered or entered 
in the register shall be deemed to include references to the keeping 
of record of those particulars comprising the register or part of the 
register in computer floppies, diskettes or a y other electronic form; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1759004</tid>
<number>c</number>references in this Act to the rectification of the register are to 
be read as including references to the rectification of the record of 
particulars kept in computer floppies, diskettes or any other 
electronic form and comprising the register or part of the register.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>171806</tid>
<number>33</number>Amendment of section 68.- In section 68 of the principal Act, for 
the words" the Controller within six months from the commencement of 
this Act or the execution of the document, whichever is later or 
within such further period", the words" the Control er within six 
months from the execution of the document or within such further 
period" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>545816</tid>
<number>34</number>Amendment of section 72.- In section 72 of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (3) If the record of particulars is kept in computer floppies or 
diskettes or in any other electronic form, sub- sections (1) and (2) 
shall be deemed to have been complied with if the public is given 
access to such computer floppies, diskettes or any oth r electronic 
form or printouts of such record of particulars for inspection.".



</article>



<article><tid>946580</tid>
<number>35</number>Amendment of section 73.- In section 73 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the words and figures" section 4 of the Trade and 
Merchandise Marks Act, <year>1958</year> (43 of <year>1958</year>)", the words and figures 
" section 3 of the Trade Marks Act, <year>1999</year> (47 of 199)" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1775154</tid>
<number> 36</number> Amendment of section 76.- In section 76 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1143328</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" Central Government", the words" Central Government 
or Appellate Board" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>125777</tid>
<number>b</number>in clauses (a) and (b), the words and figures" or under the Indian 
Patents and Designs Act, <year>1911</year> (2 of <year>1911</year>)" shall respectively be 
omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>824906</tid>
<number>37</number>Amendment of section 78.- In section 78 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, after the words" complete specifications", the words 
" or other documents relating thereto" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>775534</tid>
<number>38</number>Amendment of section 80.- In section 80 of the principal Act, the 
following proviso shall be inserted at the end, namely:-
" Provided that the party desiring a hearing makes the request for such 
hearing to the Controller at least ten days in advance of the expiry 
of the time- limit specified in respect of the proceeding.".



</article>



<article><tid>587971</tid>
<number>39</number>Substitution of new Chapter for Chapter XVI.- For Chapter XVI of 
the principal Act, the following Chapter shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' CHAPTER XVI

WORKING OF PATENTS, COMPULSORY LICENCES AND REVOCATION

</article>



<article><tid>436777</tid>
<number> 82</number> Definitions of" patented articles" and" patentee".- In this 
Chapter, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1650338</tid>
<number>a</number>" patented article" includes any article made by a patented 
process; and

</section>

<section><tid>1631480</tid>
<number>b</number>" patentee" includes an exclusive licensee.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>925879</tid>
<number> 83</number> General principles applicable to working of patented 
inventions.- Without prejudice to the other provisions contained in 
this Act, in exercising the powers conferred by this Chapter, regard 
shall be had to the following general considerations, namely:
<section><tid>1261416</tid>
<number>a</number>that patents are granted to encourage inventions and to secure 
that the inventions are worked in India on a commercial scale and to 
the fullest extent that is reasonably practicable without undue delay;

</section>

<section><tid>757088</tid>
<number>b</number>that they are not granted merely to enable patentees to enjoy a 
monopoly for the importation of the patented article;

</section>

<section><tid>1818821</tid>
<number>c</number>that the protection and enforcement of patent rights contribute to 
the promotion of technological innovation and to the transfer and 
dissemination of technology, to the mutual advantage of producers and 
users of technological knowledge and in a manne conducive to social 
and economic welfare, and to a balance of rights and obligations;

</section>

<section><tid>31117</tid>
<number>d</number>that patents granted do not impede protection of public health and 
nutrition and should act as instrument to promote public interest 
specially in sectors of vital importance for socio- economic and 
technological development of India;

</section>

<section><tid>720601</tid>
<number>e</number>that patents granted do not in any way prohibit Central Government 
in taking measures to protect public health;

</section>

<section><tid>866520</tid>
<number>f</number>that the patent right is not abused by the patentee or person 
deriving title or interest on patent from the patentee, and the 
patentee or a person deriving title or interest on patent from the 
patentee does not resort to practices which unreasonably estrain trade 
or adversely affect the international transfer of technology; and

</section>

<section><tid>949356</tid>
<number>g</number>that patents are granted to make the benefit of the patented 
invention available at reasonably affordable prices to the public.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>187660</tid>
<number> 84</number> Compulsory licences.-
<section><tid>1191645</tid>
<number>1</number>At any time after the expiration of  
three years from the date of the sealing of a patent, any person 
interested may make an application to the Controller for grant of 
compulsory licence on patent on any of the following groun s, namely:-

<subsection><tid>564815</tid>
<number>a</number>that the reasonable requirements of the public with respect to the 
patented invention have not been satisfied, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>916058</tid>
<number>b</number>that the patented invention is not available to the public at a 
reasonably affordable price, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1294873</tid>
<number>c</number>that the patented invention is not worked in the territory of 
India.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>712105</tid>
<number>2</number>An application under this section may be made by any person 
notwithstanding that he is already the holder of a licence under the 
patent and no person shall be estopped from alleging that the 
reasonable requirements of the public with respect to the p tented 
invention are not satisfied or that the patented invention is not 
worked in the territory of India or that the patented invention is not 
available to the public at a reasonably affordable price by reason of 
any admission made by him, whether in su h a licence or otherwise or 
by reason of his having accepted such a licence.

</section>

<section><tid>1250400</tid>
<number>3</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall contain a statement 
setting out the nature of the applicant' s interest together with such 
particulars as may be prescribed and the facts upon which the 
application is based.

</section>

<section><tid>1607235</tid>
<number>4</number>The Controller, if satisfied that the reasonable requirements of 
the public with respect to the patented invention have not been 
satisfied or that the patented invention is not worked in the 
territory of India or that the patented invention is not av ilable to 
the public at a reasonably affordable price, may grant a licence upon 
such terms as he may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>894523</tid>
<number>5</number>Where the Controller directs the patentee to grant a licence he 
may, as incidental thereto, exercise the powers set out in section 88.

</section>

<section><tid>493463</tid>
<number>6</number>In considering the application filed under this section, the 
Controller shall take into account,-

<subsection><tid>1922061</tid>
<number>i</number>the nature of the invention, the time which has elapsed since the 
sealing of the patent and the measures already taken by the patentee 
or any licensee to make full use of the invention;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>48859</tid>
<number>ii</number>the ability of the applicant to work the invention to the public 
advantage;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1943727</tid>
<number>iii</number>the capacity of the applicant to undertake the risk in providing 
capital and working the invention, if the application were granted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>625803</tid>
<number>iv</number>as to whether the applicant has made efforts to obtain a licence 
from the patentee on reasonable terms and conditions and such efforts 
have not been successful within a reasonable period as the Controller 
may deem fit: Provided that this clause shall not be applicable in 
case of national emergency or other circumstances of extreme urgency 
or in case of public non- commercial use or on establishment of a 
ground of anti- competitive practices adopted by the patentee,
but shall not be required to take into account matters subsequent to 
the making of the application.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>943366</tid>
<number>7</number>For the purposes of this Chapter, the reasonable requirements of 
the public shall be deemed not to have been satisfied-

<subsection><tid>1823973</tid>
<number>a</number>if, by reason of the refusal of the patentee to grant a licence or 
licences on reasonable terms,-

<subsubsection><tid>937863</tid>
<number>i</number>an existing trade or industry or the development thereof or the 
establishment of any new trade or industry in India or the trade or 
industry of any person or class of persons trading or manufacturing in 
India is prejudiced; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>554311</tid>
<number>ii</number>the demand for the patented article has not been met to an 
adequate extent or on reasonable terms; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>700731</tid>
<number>iii</number>a market for export of the patented article manufactured in 
India is not being supplied or developed; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1687325</tid>
<number>iv</number>the establishment or development of commercial activities in 
India is prejudiced; or

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>702554</tid>
<number>b</number>if, by reason of conditions imposed by the patentee upon the grant 
of licences under the patent or upon the purchase, hire or use of the 
patented article or process, the manufacture, use or sale of materials 
not protected by the patent, or the establ shment or development of 
any trade or industry in India, is prejudiced; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>410361</tid>
<number>c</number>if the patentee imposes a condition upon the grant of licences 
under the patent to provide exclusive grant back, prevention to 
challenges to the validity of patent or coercive package licensing, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>65619</tid>
<number>d</number>if the patented invention is not being worked in the territory of 
India on a commercial scale to an adequate extent or is not being so 
worked to the fullest extent that is reasonably practicable, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>493132</tid>
<number>e</number>if the working of the patented invention in the territory of India 
on a commercial scale is being prevented or hindered by the 
importation from abroad of the patented article by-

<subsubsection><tid>1402866</tid>
<number>i</number>the patentee or persons claiming under him; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1893841</tid>
<number>ii</number>persons directly or indirectly purchasing from him; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1113183</tid>
<number>iii</number>other persons against whom the patentee is not taking or has not 
taken proceedings for infringement.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>484033</tid>
<number> 85</number> Revocation of patents by the Controller for non- working.-
<section><tid>1711042</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where, in respect of a patent, a compulsory licence has been granted, 
the Central Government or any person interested may, after the 
expiration of two years from the date of the order grant ng the first 
compulsory licence, apply to the Controller for an order revoking the 
patent on the ground that the patented invention has not been worked 
in the territory of India or that reasonable requirements of the 
public with respect to the patented i vention has not been satisfied 
or that the patented invention is not available to the public at a 
reasonably affordable price.

</section>

<section><tid>569773</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall contain such 
particulars as may be prescribed, the facts upon which the application 
is based, and, in the case of an application other than by the Central 
Government, shall also set out the nature of the pplicant' s interest.

</section>

<section><tid>205551</tid>
<number>3</number>The Controller, if satisfied that the reasonable requirements of 
the public with respect to the patented invention have not been 
satisfied or that patented invention has not been worked in the 
territory of India or that the patented invention is not vailable to 
the public at a reasonably affordable price, may make an order 
revoking the patent.

</section>

<section><tid>1360979</tid>
<number>4</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall ordinarily be 
decided within one year of its being presented to the Controller.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>733348</tid>
<number> 86</number> Power of Controller to adjourn applications for compulsory 
licences, etc., in certain cases.-
<section><tid>1626863</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an application under  
section 84 or section 85, as the case may be, is made on the grounds 
that the patented invention has not been worked in the te ritory of 
India or on the ground mentioned in clause (d) of sub- section (7) of 
section 84 and the Controller is satisfied that the time which has 
elapsed since the sealing of the patent has for any reason been 
insufficient to enable the invention to be orked on a commercial scale 
to an adequate extent or to enable the invention to be so worked to 
the fullest extent that is reasonably practicable, he may, by order, 
adjourn the further hearing of the application for such period not 
exceeding twelve month in the aggregate as appears to him to be 
sufficient for the invention to be so worked:
Provided that in any case where the patentee establishes that the 
reason why a patented invention could not be worked as aforesaid 
before the date of the application was due to any State or Central Act 
or any rule or regulation made thereunder or any order of the 
Government imposed otherwise than by way of a condition for the worki 
g of the invention in the territory of India or for the disposal of 
the patented articles or of the articles made by the process or by the 
use of the patented plant, machinery, or apparatus, then, the period 
of adjournment ordered under this sub- section hall be reckoned from 
the date on which the period during which the working of the invention 
was prevented by such Act, rule or regulation or order of Government 
as computed from the date of the application, expires.


</section>

<section><tid>409567</tid>
<number>2</number>No adjournment under sub- section (1) shall be ordered unless the 
Controller is satisfied that the patentee has taken with promptitude 
adequate or reasonable steps to start the working of the invention in 
the territory of India on a commercial scale a d to an adequate 
extent.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>73641</tid>
<number> 87</number> Procedure for dealing with applications under sections 84 and 
85.-
<section><tid>1206464</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Controller is satisfied, upon consideration of an  
application under section 84, or section 85, that a prima facie case 
has been made out for the making of an order, he s all direct the 
applicant to serve copies of the application upon the patentee and any 
other person appearing from the register to be interested in the 
patent in respect of which the application is made, and shall 
advertise the application in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1907490</tid>
<number>2</number>The patentee or any other person desiring to oppose the 
application may, within such time as may be prescribed or within such 
further time as the Controller may on application (made either before  
  or after the expiration of the prescribed time) allow, give to the 
Controller notice of opposition.

</section>

<section><tid>1059094</tid>
<number>3</number>Any such notice of opposition shall contain a statement setting 
out the grounds on which the application is opposed.

</section>

<section><tid>576625</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any such notice of opposition is duly given, the Controller 
shall notify the applicant, and shall give to the applicant and the 
opponent an opportunity to be heard before deciding the case.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>392378</tid>
<number> 88</number> Powers of Controller in granting compulsory licences.-
<section><tid>563693</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
the Controller is satisfied on an application made under section 84 
that the manufacture, use or sale of materials not protected by the 
patent is prejudiced by reason of conditions impos d by the patentee 
upon the grant of licences under the patent, or upon the purchase, 
hire or use of the patented article or process, he may, subject to the 
provisions of that section, order the grant of licences under the 
patent to such customers of the pplicant as he thinks fit as well as 
to the applicant.

</section>

<section><tid>1716157</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an application under section 84 is made by a person being 
the holder of a licence under the patent, the Controller may, if he 
makes an order for the grant of a licence to the applicant, order the 
existing licence to be cancelled, or may, if he hinks fit, instead of 
making an order for the grant of a licence to the applicant, order the 
existing licence to be amended.

</section>

<section><tid>1472825</tid>
<number>3</number>Where two or more patents are held by the same patentee and an 
applicant for a compulsory licence establishes that the reasonable 
requirements of the public have not been satisfied with respect to 
some only of the said patents, then, if the Controlle is satisfied 
that the applicant cannot efficiently or satisfactorily work the 
licence granted to him under those patents without infringing the 
other patents held by the patentee and if those patents involve 
important technical advancement of considerab e economic significance 
in relation to the other patents, he may, by order, direct the grant 
of a licence in respect of the other patents also to enable the 
licensee to work the patent or patents in regard to which a licence is 
granted under section 84.

</section>

<section><tid>1249228</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the terms and conditions of a licence have been settled by 
the Controller, the licensee may, at any time after he has worked the 
invention on a commercial scale for a period of not less than twelve 
months, make an application to the Controller or the revision of the 
terms and conditions on the ground that the terms and conditions 
settled have proved to be more onerous than originally expected and 
that in consequence thereof the licensee is unable to work the 
invention except at a loss: Provided that no such application shall 
be entertained a second time.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>780953</tid>
<number> 89</number> General purposes for granting compulsory licences.- The powers of 
the Controller upon an application made under section 84 shall be 
exercised with a view to securing the following general purposes, that 
is to say,-
<section><tid>802901</tid>
<number>a</number>that patented inventions are worked on a commercial scale in the 
territory of India without undue delay and to the fullest extent that 
is reasonably practicable;

</section>

<section><tid>1996649</tid>
<number>b</number>that the interests of any person for the time being working or 
developing an invention in the territory of India under the protection 
of a patent are not unfairly prejudiced.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1589480</tid>
<number> 90</number> Terms and conditions of compulsory licences.-
<section><tid>479393</tid>
<number>1</number>In settling the  
terms and conditions of a licence under section 84, the Controller 
shall endeavour to secure-

<subsection><tid>77379</tid>
<number>i</number>that the royalty and other remuneration, if any, reserved to the 
patentee or other person beneficially entitled to the patent, is 
reasonable, having regard to the nature of the invention, the 
expenditure incurred by the patentee in making the inventi n or in 
developing it and obtaining a patent and keeping it in force and other 
relevant factors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>139149</tid>
<number>ii</number>that the patented invention is worked to the fullest extent by 
the person to whom the licence is granted and with reasonable profit 
to him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>824217</tid>
<number>iii</number>that the patented articles are made available to the public at 
reasonably affordable prices;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1987564</tid>
<number>iv</number>that the licence granted is a non- exclusive licence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1396665</tid>
<number>v</number>that the right of the licensee is non- assignable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1385865</tid>
<number>vi</number>that the licence is for the balance term of the patent unless a 
shorter term is consistent with public interest;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1104516</tid>
<number>vii</number>that the licence is granted with a predominant purpose of 
supplying in Indian market and in the case of semi- conductor 
technology, the licence granted is to work the invention for public 
non- commercial use and in the case, the licence granted to re edy a 
practice determined after judicial or administrative process to be 
anti- competitive, licensee shall be permitted to export the patented 
product.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1545133</tid>
<number>2</number>No licence granted by the Controller shall authorise the licensee 
to import the patented article or an article or susbtance made by a 
patented process from abroad where such importation would, but for 
such authorisation, constitute an infringement of the rights of the 
patentee.

</section>

<section><tid>1596859</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the Central 
Government may, if in its opinion it is necessary so to do, in the 
public interest, direct the Controller at any time to authorise any 
licensee in respect of a patent to import the pa ented article or an 
article or substance made by a patented process from abroad (subject  
to such conditions as it considers necessary to impose relating among 
other matters to the royalty and other remuneration, if any, payable 
to the patentee, the quant m of import, the sale price of the imported 
  article and the period of importation), and thereupon the Controller 
shall give effect to the directions.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1207017</tid>
<number> 91</number> Licensing of related patents.-
<section><tid>810970</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the other provisions of this Chapter, at any time after 
the sealing of a patent, any person who has the right to work any 
other patented invention either as patentee or as licens e thereof, 
exclusive or otherwise, may apply to the Controller for the grant of a 
licence of the first- mentioned patent on the ground that he is 
prevented or hindered without such licence from working the other 
invention efficiently or to the best advant ge possible.

</section>

<section><tid>1142379</tid>
<number>2</number>No order under sub- section (1) shall be made unless the Controller 
is satisfied-

<subsection><tid>351700</tid>
<number>i</number>that the applicant is able and willing to grant, or procure the 
grant to the patentee and his licensees if they so desire, of a 
licence in respect of the other invention on reasonable terms; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1967329</tid>
<number>ii</number>that the other invention has made a substantial contribution to 
the establishment or development of commercial or industrial 
activities in the territory of India.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>411668</tid>
<number>3</number>When the Controller is satisfied that the conditions mentioned in 
sub- section (1) have been established by the applicant, he may make an 
order on such terms as he thinks fit granting a licence under the 
first- mentioned patent and a similar order unde the other patent if so 
requested by the proprietor of the first- mentioned patent or his 
licensee:
Provided that the licence granted by the Controller shall be 
non- assignable except with the assignment of the respective patents.


</section>

<section><tid>915735</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of sections 87, 88, 89 and 90 shall apply to 
licences granted under this section as they apply to licences granted 
under section 84.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1368833</tid>
<number> 92</number> Special provision for compulsory licences on notifications by 
Central Government.-
<section><tid>969705</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is satisfied, in  
respect of any patent in force in circumstances of national emergency 
or in circumstances of extreme urgency or in case o public 
non- commercial use, that it is necessary that compulsory licences 
should be granted at any time after the sealing thereof to work the 
invention, it may make a declaration to that effect, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, and thereupon the ollowing provisions shall 
have effect, that is to say,-

<subsection><tid>969320</tid>
<number>i</number>the Controller shall, on application made at any time after the 
notification by any person interested, grant to the applicant a 
licence under the patent on such terms and conditions as he thinks 
fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1000734</tid>
<number>ii</number>in settling the terms and conditions of a licence granted under 
this section, the Controller shall endeavour to secure that the 
articles manufactured under the patent shall be available to the 
public at the lowest prices consistent with the patentee deriving a 
reasonable advantage from their patent rights.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1019477</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 83, 87, 88, 89 and 90 shall apply in 
relation to the grant of licences under this section as they apply in 
relation to the grant of licences under section 84.

</section>

<section><tid>1366827</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), where the 
Controller is satisfied on consideration of the application referred 
to in clause (i) of sub- section (1) that it is necessary in-

<subsection><tid>595723</tid>
<number>i</number>a circumstance of national emergency; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1717738</tid>
<number>ii</number>a circumstance of extreme urgency; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1758843</tid>
<number>iii</number>a case of public non- commercial use, which may arise or is 
required, as the case may be, including public health crises, relating 
to Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome, human immunodeficiency virus, 
tuberculosis, malaria or other epidemics, he shall not apply any 
procedure specified in sec ion 87 in relation to that application for 
grant of licence under this section:
Provided that the Controller shall, as soon as may be practicable, 
inform the patentee of the patent relating to the application for such 
non- application of section 87.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1805756</tid>
<number>93</number>Order for licence to operate as a deed between parties 
concerned.- Any order for the grant of a licence under this Chapter 
shall operate as if it were a deed granting a licence executed by the 
patentee and all other necessary parties embodying the ter s and 
conditions, if any, settled by the Controller.
</article>



<article><tid>799740</tid>
<number> 94</number> Termination of compulsory licence.-
<section><tid>116311</tid>
<number>1</number>On an application made by  
the patentee or any other person deriving title or interest in the 
patent, a compulsory licence granted under section 84 may be 
terminated by the Controller, if and when the circumstanc s that gave 
rise to the grant thereof no longer exist and such circumstances are 
unlikely to recur:
Provided that the holder of the compulsory licence shall have the 
right to object to such termination.


</section>

<section><tid>799719</tid>
<number>2</number>While considering an application under sub- section (1), the 
Controller shall take into account that the interest of the person who 
had previously been granted the licence is not unduly prejudiced.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1816492</tid>
<number>40</number>Amendment of section 99.- In section 99 of the principal Act, 
sub- section (2) shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>733375</tid>
<number> 41</number> Amendment of section 100.- In section 100 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>366758</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (3), for the proviso, the following proviso shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" Provided that in case of any such use of any patent, the patentee 
shall be paid not more than adequate remuneration in the circumstances 
of each case, taking into account the economic value of the use of the 
patent.";


</section>

<section><tid>1313482</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (5), for the words" unless it appears to the 
Government that it would be contrary to the public interest so to do", 
the words" except in case of national emergency or other circumstances 
of extreme urgency or for non- commercial use" sh ll be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>15304</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (6), for the words" right to sell the goods", the 
words" right to sell, on non- commercial basis, the goods" shall be 
substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>963408</tid>
<number> 42</number> Amendment of section 101.- In section 101 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>727406</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>580600</tid>
<number>i</number>the words", whether before or after the commencement of this 
Act," shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>743807</tid>
<number>ii</number>the brackets and words" (including payments by way of minimum  
  royalty)" shall be omitted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>339905</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), the brackets and words" (including payments by  
  way of minimum royalty)" shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>9266</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (3), in clause (b), the words" including payments 
by way of minimum royalty" shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1696700</tid>
<number> 43</number> Insertion of new section 104A.- After section 104 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 104A. Burden of proof in case of suits concerning infringement.- (1) 
In any suit for infringement of a patent, where the subject matter of 
patent is a process for obtaining a product, the court may direct the 
defendant to prove that the process used by h m to obtain the product, 
identical to the product of the patented process, is different from 
the patented process if,-

<section><tid>922449</tid>
<number>a</number>the subject matter of the patent is a process for obtaining a new 
product; or

</section>

<section><tid>757048</tid>
<number>b</number>there is a substantial likelihood that the identical product is 
made by the process, and the patentee or a person deriving title or 
interest in the patent from him, has been unable through reasonable 
efforts to determine the process actually used:
Provided that the patentee or a person deriving title or interest in 
the patent from him, first proves that the product is identical to the 
product directly obtained by the patented process.


<subsection><tid>443086</tid>
<number>2</number>In considering whether a party has discharged the burden imposed 
upon him by sub- section (1), the court shall not require him to 
disclose any manufacturing or commercial secrets, if it appears to the 
court that it would be unreasonable to do so.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>136863</tid>
<number> 44</number> Insertion of new section 107A.- After section 107 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 107A. Certain acts not to be considered as infringement.- For the 
purposes of this Act,-

<section><tid>638472</tid>
<number>a</number>any act of making, constructing, using or selling a patented 
invention solely for uses reasonably relating to the development and 
submission of information required under any law for the time being in 
force, in India, or in a country other than India that regulates the 
manufacture, construction, use or sale of any product;

</section>

<section><tid>1254432</tid>
<number>b</number>importation of patented products by any person from a person who 
is duly authorised by the patentee to sell or distribute the product, 
shall not be considered as an infringement of patent rights.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1602678</tid>
<number> 45</number> Amendment of section 108.- Section 108 of the principal Act shall 
be numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>764262</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof, and after sub- section (1) as  
so numbered, the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) The court may also order that the goods which are found to be 
infringing and materials and implement, the predominant use of which 
is in the creation of infringing goods shall be seized, forfeited or 
destroyed, as the court deems fit under the circu stances of the case 
without payment of any compensation.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1876207</tid>
<number>46</number>Omission of section 112.- Section 112 of the principal Act shall 
be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>226158</tid>
<number>47</number>Substitution of new Chapter for Chapter XIX.- For Chapter XIX of 
the principal Act, the following Chapter shall be substituted, 
namely:-
'' CHAPTER XIX

APPEALS TO THE APPELLATE BOARD

</article>



<article><tid>1163084</tid>
<number> 116</number> Appellate Board.-
<section><tid>185642</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the  
Appellate Board established under section 83 of the Trade Marks Act, 
 <year>1999</year> (47 of <year>1999</year>) shall be the Appellate Board for the purposes of 
this Act and the said Appellate Board shall exerc se the jurisdiction, 
power and authority conferred on it by or under this Act:
Provided that the Technical Member of the Appellate Board for the 
purposes of this Act shall have the qualifications specified in 
sub- section (2).


</section>

<section><tid>1562593</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a Technical 
Member for the purposes of this Act unless he-

<subsection><tid>1710703</tid>
<number>a</number>has, at least five years, held the post of Controller under this 
Act or has exercised the functions of the Controller under this Act 
for at least five years; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1742926</tid>
<number>b</number>has, for at least ten years, functioned as a Registered Patent 
Agent and possesses a degree in engineering or technology or a masters 
degree in science from any University established under law for the 
time being in force or equivalent; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1165373</tid>
<number>c</number>has, for at least ten years, been an advocate of a proven 
specialised experience in practising law relating to patents and 
designs.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1458865</tid>
<number> 117</number> Staff of Appellate Board.-
<section><tid>1430720</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall  
determine the nature and categories of the officers and other 
employees required to assist the Appellate Board in the discharge of 
its functions under this Act and provide the Appellate Boar with such 
officers and other employees as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1387080</tid>
<number>2</number>The salaries and allowances and conditions of service of the 
officers and other employees of the Appellate Board shall be such as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>454153</tid>
<number>3</number>The officers and other employees of the Appellate Board shall 
discharge their functions under the general superintendence of the 
Chairman of the Appellate Board in the manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1334806</tid>
<number> 117A</number> Appeals to Appellate Board.-
<section><tid>777730</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise expressly  
provided in sub- section (2), no appeal shall lie from any decision, 
order or direction made or issued under this Act by the Central 
Government, or from any act or order of the Controller f r the purpose 
of giving effect to any such decision, order or direction.

</section>

<section><tid>1547856</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal shall lie to the Appellate Board from any decision, 
order or direction of the Controller or Central Government under 
section 15, section 16, section 17, section 18, section 19, section 
20, section 25, section 27, section 28, section 51, sec ion 54, 
section 57, section 60, section 61, section 63, section 66, 
sub- section (3) of section 69, section 78, sub- sections (1) to (5) of 
section 84, section 85, section 88, section 91, section 92 and section 
94.

</section>

<section><tid>1055066</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under this section shall be in the prescribed form 
and shall be verified in such manner as may be prescribed and shall be 
accompanied by a copy of the decision, order or direction appealed 
against and by such fees as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1261064</tid>
<number>4</number>Every appeal shall be made within three months from the date of 
the decision, order or direction, as the case may be, of the 
Controller or the Central Government or within such further time as 
the Appellate Board may, in accordance with the rules mad by it, 
allow.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>76717</tid>
<number>117B</number>Procedure and powers of Appellate Board.- The provisions of 
sub- sections (2) to (6) of section 84, section 87, section 92, section 
 95 and section 96 of the Trade Marks Act, <year>1999</year> (47 of <year>1999</year>) shall 
apply to the Appellate Board in the discharge of its functions under 
this Act as they apply to it in the discharge of its functions under 
the Trade Marks Act, <year>1999</year>.
</article>



<article><tid>402384</tid>
<number>117C</number>Bar of jurisdiction of courts, etc.- No court or other authority 
shall have or, be entitled to, exercise any jurisdiction, powers or 
authority in relation to the matters referred to in sub- section (2) of 
section 117A or section 117D.
</article>



<article><tid>256450</tid>
<number> 117D</number> Procedure for application for rectification, etc., before 
Appellate Board.-
<section><tid>1321897</tid>
<number>1</number>An application for rectification of the register  
made to the Appellate Board under section 71 shall be in such form as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1772886</tid>
<number>2</number>A certified copy of every order or judgment of the Appellate Board 
relating to a patent under this Act shall be communicated to the 
Controller by the Board and the Controller shall give effect to the 
order of the Board and shall, when so directed, am nd the entries in, 
or rectify, the register in accordance with such order.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1516232</tid>
<number> 117E</number> Appearance of Controller in legal proceedings.-
<section><tid>1969459</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Controller shall have the right to appear and be heard-

<subsection><tid>378865</tid>
<number>a</number>in any legal proceedings before the Appellate Board in which the 
relief sought includes alteration or rectification of the register or 
in which any question relating to the practice of the patent office is 
raised;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>897707</tid>
<number>b</number>in any appeal to the Appellate Board from an order of the 
Controller on an application for grant of a patent-

<subsubsection><tid>1418345</tid>
<number>i</number>which is not opposed, and the application is either refused by the 
Controller or is accepted by him subject to any amendments, 
modifications, conditions or limitations, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>810983</tid>
<number>ii</number>which has been opposed and the Controller considers that his 
appearance is necessary in the public interest, and the Controller 
shall appear in any case if so directed by the Appellate Board.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1070348</tid>
<number>2</number>Unless the Appellate Board otherwise directs, the Controller may, 
in lieu of appearing, submit a statement in writing signed by him, 
giving such particulars as he thinks proper of the proceedings before 
him relating to the matter in issue or of the g ounds of any decision 
given by him or of the practice of the patent office in like cases, or 
of other matters relevant to the issues and within his knowledge as 
the Controller may deem it necessary, and such statement shall be 
evidence in the proceeding.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1634834</tid>
<number>117F</number>Costs of Controller in proceedings before Appellate Board.- In 
all proceedings under this Act before the Appellate Board, the costs 
of the Controller shall be in the discretion of the Board, but the 
Controller shall not be ordered to pay the costs o any of the parties.
</article>



<article><tid>1612182</tid>
<number>117G</number>Transfer of pending proceedings to Appellate Board.- All cases 
of appeals against any order or decision of the Controller and all 
cases pertaining to rectification of register, pending before any High 
Court, shall be transferred to the Appellate Boa d from such date as 
may be notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette and 
the Appellate Board may proceed with the matter either de novo or from 
the stage it was so transferred.
</article>



<article><tid>1206002</tid>
<number>117H</number>Power of Appellate Board to make rules.- The Appellate Board may 
make rules consistent with this Act as to the conduct and procedure in 
respect of all proceedings before it under this Act.".


</article>



<article><tid>821997</tid>
<number>48</number>Amendment of section 118.- In section 118 of the principal Act, 
after the words and figures'' under section 35'', the words and 
figures'' or makes or causes to be made an application for the grant 
nserted.


</article>



<article><tid>774391</tid>
<number>49</number>Amendment of section 120.- In section 120 of the principal Act, 
for the words'' five hundred rupees'', the words'' ten thousand 
rupees'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>72256</tid>
<number>50</number>Amendment of section 122.- In section 122 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the words'' one thousand rupees'', the words 
'' twenty thousand rupees'' shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1598148</tid>
<number> 51</number> Amendment of section 123.- In section 123 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1015947</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words'' five hundred rupees'', the words'' ten thousand 
rupees'' shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1061862</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words'' two thousand rupees'', the words'' forty thousand 
rupees'' shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1269206</tid>
<number> 52</number> Substitution of new section for section 125.- For section 125 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 125. Register of patent agents.- (1) The Controller shall maintain a 
register to be called the register of patent agents in which shall be 
entered the names, addresses and other relevant particulars, as may be 
prescribed, of all persons qualified to have their names so entered 
under section 126.

<section><tid>594556</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), it shall be 
lawful for the Controller to keep the register of patent agents in 
computer floppies, diskettes or any other electronic form subject to 
such safeguards as may be prescribed.''.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>429187</tid>
<number> 53</number> Amendment of section 126.- In section 126 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>917231</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1797203</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (c),-

<subsubsection><tid>1460365</tid>
<number>A</number>for the words'' degree from any University'', the words'' degree 
in science, engineering or technology from any University established 
under law for the time being in force'' shall be substituted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1176633</tid>
<number>B</number>in sub- clause (ii), the word'' or'' shall be inserted at the end;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>922510</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- clause (ii), the following sub- clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (iii) has, for a total period of not less than ten years, functioned 
either as an examiner or discharged the functions of the Controller 
under section 73 or both, but ceased to hold any such capacity at the 
time of making the application for registratio;'';


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>624559</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
'' (2) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), a person 
who has been registered as a patent agent before the commencement of 
the Patents (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year> shall be entitled to continue to be, 
or when required to be re- registered, as a p tent agent, on payment of 
the fees as may be prescribed.''.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1156265</tid>
<number> 54</number> Amendment of section 128.- In section 128 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>288978</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), the words'' Subject to the provisions 
contained in sub- section (2) and to any rules made under this Act,'' 
shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>725783</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- section (2) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1152125</tid>
<number> 55</number> Amendment of section 130.- In section 130 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1247423</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words'' Central Government'' wherever they occur, the word 
'' Controller'' shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>735815</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (1), for the word'' it'' at both the places where 
it occurs, the word'' he'' shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1927767</tid>
<number> 56</number> Amendment of section 132.- In section 132 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>942332</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (a), the words'' or any person, not being a patent 
agent, who is duly authorised by the applicant'' shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>657874</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (b), for the words'' proceedings under this Act, 
otherwise than by way of drafting any specification'', the words 
'' hearing before the Controller on behalf of a party who is taking 
part in any proceeding under this Act'' shall be substitute.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1015084</tid>
<number>57</number>Amendment of section 133.- In section 133 of the principal Act, 
the following Explanation shall be inserted at the end, namely:-
' Explanation.- For the purposes of this Chapter'' country'' includes a 
group or union of countries or Inter- governmental organisation.'.



</article>



<article><tid>546376</tid>
<number> 58</number> Amendment of section 138.- In section 138 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>112714</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), after the words'' shall furnish,'', the words 
'' when required by the Controller,'' shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>1112364</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words'' annexed to the specification 
or document'', the words'' furnished when required by the Controller'' 
shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>980106</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (3), the following sub- sections shall be 
inserted, namely:-
'' (4) An international application filed under the Patent Cooperation 
Treaty designating India shall have effect of filing an application 
for patent under section 7, section 54 and section 135, as the case 
may be, and the title, description, claim and ab tract and drawings, 
if any, filed in the international application shall be taken as 
complete specification for the purposes of this Act.


<subsection><tid>1261563</tid>
<number>5</number>The filing date of an application for patent and its complete 
specification processed by the patent office as designated office 
shall be the international filing date accorded under the Patent 
Cooperation Treaty.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>737714</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment, if any, proposed by the applicant for an international 
application designating India or designating and electing India before 
international searching authority or preliminary examination authority 
shall, if the applicant so desires, be tak n as an amendment made 
before the patent office.''.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>444827</tid>
<number> 59</number> Amendment of section 140.- In section 140 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>463417</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), in clause (iii), after sub- clause (c), the 
following sub- clause shall be inserted, namely:-
'' (d) to provide exclusive grant back, prevention to challenges to 
validity of patent and coercive package licensing,'';


</section>

<section><tid>1833528</tid>
<number>b</number>sub- section (5) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1352365</tid>
<number>60</number>Amendment of section 141.- In section 141 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, the words,'' whether made before or after the 
commencement of this Act,'' shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1835858</tid>
<number> 61</number> Amendment of section 142.- In section 142 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1666391</tid>
<number>a</number>for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
'' (3) Where a fee is payable in respect of the filing of a document at 
the patent office, the fee shall be paid along with the document or 
within the prescribed time and the document shall be deemed not to 
have been filed at the office if the fee has not been paid within such 
time.'';


</section>

<section><tid>1604745</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (4), the words'' or within the extended period not 
later than nine months from the date of recording'' shall be inserted 
at the end.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>445169</tid>
<number>62</number>Amendment of section 143.- In section 143 of the principal Act, 
for the words" or be open to public inspection at any time before the 
date of advertisement of acceptance of the application", the words 
" before eighteen months from the date of applicati n or the priority 
date of the application or before the same is open to public 
inspection" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1656206</tid>
<number> 63</number> Substitution of new section for section 157A.- For section 157A of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' 157A. Protection of security of India.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act, the Central Government shall-

<section><tid>1823430</tid>
<number>a</number>not disclose any information relating to any patentable invention 
or any application relating to the grant of patent under this Act, 
which it considers prejudicial to the interest of the security of 
India;

</section>

<section><tid>462467</tid>
<number>b</number>take any action including the revocation of any patent which it 
considers necessary in the interest of the security of India by issue 
of a notification in the Official Gazette to that effect.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, the expression 
" security of India" includes any action necessary for the security of 
India which-


<subsection><tid>1891013</tid>
<number>i</number>relates to fissionable materials or the materials from which they 
are derived; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1636838</tid>
<number>ii</number>relates to the traffic in arms, ammunition and implements of war 
and to such traffic in other goods and materials as is carried on 
directly or indirectly for the purpose of supplying a military 
establishment; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>679218</tid>
<number>iii</number>is taken in time of war or other emergency in international 
relations.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1821851</tid>
<number> 64</number> Amendment of section 159.- In section 159 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>1913536</tid>
<number>a</number>after clause (i), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ia) the details to be furnished by the applicant under sub- section 
 (2) of section 8;


</section>

<section><tid>294721</tid>
<number>ib</number>the manner of making the request for examination of an 
application for patent under sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) of section 
11B;";

</section>

<section><tid>1595614</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (iii), after the word" manner", the words" and time" 
shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>164669</tid>
<number>c</number>in clause (ix), after the word" patents", the words" and the 
safeguards to be observed in the maintenance of such register in 
computer floppies, diskettes or any other electronic form" shall be 
inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>830240</tid>
<number>d</number>after clause (xii), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (xiia) the salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of 
the officers and other employees of the Appellate Board under 
sub- section (2), and the manner in which the officers and other 
employees of the Appellate Board shall discharge their fu ctions under 
sub- section (3), of section 117;


</section>

<section><tid>1770697</tid>
<number>xiib</number>the form of making an appeal, the manner of verification and 
the fees payable under sub- section (3) of section 117A;

</section>

<section><tid>1506220</tid>
<number>xiic</number>the form in which, and the particulars to be included in, the 
application to the Appellate Board under sub- section (1) of section 
117D;";

</section>

<section><tid>1266200</tid>
<number>e</number>in clause (xiv), after the word" maintained", the words, brackets 
and figures" under sub- section (1) of section 125 and the safeguards 
to be observed in the maintenance of such register of patent agents on 
computer floppies, diskettes or any other el ctronic form under 
sub- section (2) of that section" shall be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1914177</tid>
<number>65</number>Omission of section 161.- Section 161 of the principal Act shall 
be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>796550</tid>
<number>66</number>Amendment of section 162.- In section 162 of the principal Act, 
sub- sections (2) and (3) shall be omitted.
----

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>