<act><tid>1453818</tid>
<title>THE OFFSHORE AREAS MINERAL (DEVELOPMENT AND REGULATION) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 17 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 30th January, <year>2003</year>.]

AN ACT to provide for development and regulation of mineral resources 
in the territorial waters, continental shelf, exclusive economic zone 
and other maritime zones of India and to provide for matters connected 
therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1422378</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1376133</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Offshore Areas Mineral (Development and Regulation) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>334905</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1714336</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to expediency of Union control.- It is hereby 
declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the Union 
should take under its control the regulation of mines and the 
development of minerals in offshore areas to the extent herei after 
provided.


</article>



<article><tid>41639</tid>
<number> 3</number> Application.-
<section><tid>1882673</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act shall apply to all minerals in the  
offshore areas including any mineral prescribed by notification under 
clause (g) of sub- section (1) of section 2 of the Atomic Energy Act, 
 <year>1962</year> (33 of <year>1962</year>) except mineral oils and hydrocarb ns related 
thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1735759</tid>
<number>2</number>Except as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of this 
Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other law 
for the time being in force in the offshore areas.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>49499</tid>
<number> 4</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1338990</tid>
<number>a</number>" administering authority" means an authority notified, in the 
Official Gazette, by the Central Government for the purposes of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1862237</tid>
<number>b</number>'' atomic minerals" means the minerals included in atomic minerals 
specified in Part B of the First Schedule to the Mines and Minerals 
 (Development and Regulation) Act, <year>1957</year> (67 of <year>1957</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>993477</tid>
<number>c</number>" Coast Guard" means the Coast Guard constituted under the Coast 
Guard Act, <year>1978</year> (30 of <year>1978</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>139828</tid>
<number>d</number>" exploration licence" means a licence granted under section 12;

</section>

<section><tid>1734271</tid>
<number>e</number>" exploration operation" means any operation undertaken for the 
purpose of exploring, locating or proving the mineral deposits;

</section>

<section><tid>1804783</tid>
<number>f</number>" holder", in relation to any operating right, means the lessee, 
licensee or permittee, as the case may be, in respect of such 
operating right;

</section>

<section><tid>708325</tid>
<number>g</number>" hydrocarbon" means very large group of chemical compounds 
composed of carbon and hydrogen;

</section>

<section><tid>1876782</tid>
<number>h</number>" Indian national" means a citizen of India and includes a firm or 
other association, if all the members of the firm or, as the case may 
be, the members of the association, are citizens of India;

</section>

<section><tid>122313</tid>
<number>i</number>" lessee" means the person in whose name the production lease is 
granted;

</section>

<section><tid>1135355</tid>
<number>j</number>" licensee" means the person in whose name the exploration licence 
is granted;

</section>

<section><tid>402578</tid>
<number>k</number>" mine" means any place in the offshore area wherein any 
exploration or production operation is carried on, together with any 
vessel, erection, appliance, artificial island or platform and 
premises in the offshore area used for the purposes of explor tion, 
winning, treating or preparing minerals, obtaining or extracting any 
mineral or metal by any mode or method, and includes any area covered 
by an exploration licence or production lease where exploration or 
production operation has been, or is bei g, or may be, carried on 
under the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>950858</tid>
<number>l</number>" mineral" includes all minerals except mineral oil and hydrocarbon 
resources relating thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1349432</tid>
<number>m</number>" mineral oil" includes natural gas and petroleum;

</section>

<section><tid>306992</tid>
<number>n</number>" offshore area" means the territorial waters, continental shelf, 
exclusive economic zone and other maritime zones of India under the 
Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Exclusive Economic Zone and 
Other Maritime Zones Act, <year>1976</year> (80 of <year>1976</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>742548</tid>
<number>o</number>" operating right" means the right of holder of a reconnaissance 
permit, or an exploration licence, or a production lease;

</section>

<section><tid>1612983</tid>
<number>p</number>" permittee" means the person in whose name the reconnaissance 
permit is granted;

</section>

<section><tid>1346194</tid>
<number>q</number>" pollution of offshore environment" means the introduction by any 
person, directly or indirectly, of substances or energy into the 
offshore environment which results, or is likely to result, in 
deleterious effect on living resources and marine life, azards to 
human health, hindrance to marine activities, including fishing and 
other legitimate uses of the offshore areas and impairment of quality 
of sea water for use and reduction of amenities;

</section>

<section><tid>791097</tid>
<number>r</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>289583</tid>
<number>s</number>" production operation" means any operation undertaken for the 
purpose of winning any mineral from the offshore area and includes any 
operation directly or indirectly necessary therefor or incidental 
thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1764149</tid>
<number>t</number>" production lease" means a lease granted under section 13 which 
confers an exclusive right for the purpose of undertaking production 
operation;

</section>

<section><tid>126875</tid>
<number>u</number>" reconnaissance operation" means any preliminary geo- scientific 
survey undertaken for the purpose of searching or locating mineral 
deposits;

</section>

<section><tid>1748740</tid>
<number>v</number>" reconnaissance permit" means a permit granted under section 11 
for the purpose of undertaking reconnaissance operation;

</section>

<section><tid>1109994</tid>
<number>w</number>" vessel" includes any ship, boat, sailing vessel or any other 
vessel of any description.
CHAP

GENERAL PROVISIONS FOR ACQUISITION OF OPERATING RIGHTS IN THE OFFSHOREAREAS.

CHAPTER II

GENERAL PROVISIONS FOR ACQUISITION OF OPERATING RIGHTS IN THE OFFSHORE 
AREAS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1815040</tid>
<number> 5</number> Reconnaisance, exploration or production to be under permit, 
licence or lease.-
<section><tid>1566173</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall undertake any reconnaissance  
operation, exploration operation or production operation in the 
offshore areas, except under and in accordance with the pr scribed 
terms and conditions of a reconnaissance permit, exploration licence 
or production lease granted under this Act and the rules made 
thereunder:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to any 
reconnaissance operation or exploration operation undertaken by the 
Geological Survey of India, Atomic Minerals Directorate of Exploration 
and Research, the Chief Hydrographer to the Government of India of 
Naval Hydrographic Office of the Indian Navy, the National Institute 
of Oceanography, the National Institute of Ocean Technology of 
Department of Ocean Development of the Government of India, or any 
other agency duly authorised in this behalf by the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>29263</tid>
<number>2</number>A permittee or licensee or lessee shall furnish-

<subsection><tid>1570216</tid>
<number>a</number>all data, as the case may be, relating to reconnaissance operation 
or mineral exploration or mining such as bathymetry, geomorphology, 
mineral distribution, anomaly maps, sections, core logs, location 
maps, plans, structures, contour maps, chemical a alysis, data on 
current tides, waves, wind, other geophysical and geotechnical data 
and any other data collected during exploration operation or mining 
operation, to the Director- General, Geological Survey of India, 
Kolkata and the Controller General, In ian Bureau of Mines, Nagpur;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>512704</tid>
<number>b</number>all information pertaining to atomic minerals collected, as the 
case may be, during reconnaissance operation or exploration operation 
or mining operation, to the Secretary to the Government of India 
dealing with the Atomic Energy, Director- General, eological Survey of 
India, Kolkata and the Controller General, Indian Bureau of Mines, 
Nagpur;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1364053</tid>
<number>c</number>a six monthly report on the work done by him stating the number of 
persons engaged and disclosing in full the geological, geophysical, 
geochemical, geo- environmental or other valuable data collected by him 
during the period under report, to the Direc or- General, Geological 
Survey of India, Kolkata and the Controller General, Indian Bureau of 
Mines, Nagpur and the report shall be submitted within three months of 
the closing of the period to which it relates: Provided that in the 
case of investigations pertaining to the atomic minerals, such report 
shall also be submitted to the Secretary to the Government of India 
dealing with the Atomic Energy;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>517879</tid>
<number>d</number>a full report of the work done by him and all information relevant 
to mineral resources collected by him during the course of exploration 
operation of the area covered by the licence within three months of 
the expiry of the licence, or abandonment of operation or termination 
of the licence, whichever is earlier, to the Director- General, 
Geological Survey of India, Kolkata and the Controller General, Indian 
Bureau of Mines, Nagpur and shall also give therein reasons and 
indicate whether the whole or ny part of the report or data submitted 
by him should be kept confidential.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>761914</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Central 
Government may-

<subsection><tid>388702</tid>
<number>a</number>authorise seaward artillery practice under the Seaward Artillery 
Practice Act, <year>1949</year> (8 of <year>1949</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>57371</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for, by notification in the Official Gazette, special 
measures to ensure public safety and interest, the defence of India 
and civil defence, conduct of the naval operations and exercises, 
national security and other strategic considerations a d the matters 
connected therewith during war like conditions or otherwise.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1598250</tid>
<number>4</number>No operating right shall be granted or renewed otherwise than in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
thereunder and any reconnaissance permit, exploration licence or 
production lease granted, renewed or acquired in contraven ion of the 
provisions of this Act or any rules made thereunder, shall be void.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1760264</tid>
<number> 6</number> Grant of operating right.- The Central Government shall not grant 
an operating right to any person unless such person-
<section><tid>857953</tid>
<number>a</number>is an Indian national, or a company as defined in section 3 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>); and

</section>

<section><tid>919545</tid>
<number>b</number>satisfies such conditions as may be prescribed:
Provided that no production lease for atomic minerals or prescribed 
substances may be granted without consultation with the Department of 
the Government of India dealing with the Atomic Energy.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1372062</tid>
<number> 7</number> Termination of operating right.-
<section><tid>214068</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Government,  
after consultation with the administering authority, is of the opinion 
that it is expedient in the interest of development and regulation of 
offshore mineral resources, preservation of natural environment and 
prevention of pollution, avoidance of danger to public health or 
communication, ensuring safety of any offshore structure or 
conservation of mineral resources, the Central Government may 
prematurely terminate any operating righ in respect of any mineral in 
any offshore area or part thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1107276</tid>
<number>2</number>No order for premature termination of operating right under 
sub- section (1) shall be made except after giving the holder of 
operating right a reasonable opportunity of being heard.

</section>

<section><tid>1733099</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the holder of any operating right fails to commence 
operation within the period specified in section 14 or discontinues 
the operation for a period of two years, the operating right shall 
lapse from the date of execution of the lease or, as the ase may be, 
discontinuance of the operation:
Provided that the administering authority, on an application made by 
the holder of operating right and after being satisfied that such 
non- commencement of operation or discontinuation thereof, is due to 
the reasons beyond the control of the holder of o erating right, may 
condone such non- commencement or discontinuation.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1217446</tid>
<number> 8</number> Reservation of areas.-
<section><tid>1473640</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, from time to  
time, by notification in the Official Gazette, reserve any offshore 
area not already held under any operating right, for the purposes of 
the Central Government and, where it proposes t do so, it shall, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify the boundaries of such 
area and the mineral or minerals in respect of which such area shall 
be reserved.

</section>

<section><tid>910726</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, from time to time, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, dereserve, any area reserved under sub- section 
 (1), in the interest of development and regulation of the offshore 
mineral.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>643346</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power to close areas.-
<section><tid>1619664</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, in the  
public interest, by order in writing and communicated to the 
permittee, licensee or lessee, as the case may be, close any area 
either in part or whole, covered under any operating right, fo the 
preservation of natural environment and prevention of pollution, or to 
avoid danger to public health, or communication, or to ensure safety 
of any offshore structure or platform, or for the conservation of 
offshore mineral, or for national security r for any other strategic 
consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1990964</tid>
<number>2</number>Any area, either in part or whole closed under sub- section (1) and 
included in any operating right, shall, from the date of such order, 
be deemed to be excluded for the purposes of the operating right and 
the holder of the operating right shall not u dertake any operation in 
the area covered under such order from the date specified therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1537687</tid>
<number> 10</number> Availability of areas for grant of permit, licence or lease.-
<section><tid>1046998</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Within six months from the date of commencement of this Act, and 
subsequently at such times as may be considered necessary in this 
behalf by the administering authority, it shall, by no ification in 
the Official Gazette, declare the parts of the offshore areas which 
shall be available for grant of reconnaissance permit, exploration 
licence or production lease.

</section>

<section><tid>1050460</tid>
<number>2</number>Any application for the grant of reconnaissance permit, 
exploration licence or production lease in respect of any area not 
covered by a notification issued under sub- section (1) shall be deemed 
to be premature and no application shall be entertained herefor.

</section>

<section><tid>786212</tid>
<number>3</number>Operating rights shall be granted in standard block of five 
minutes longitude by five minutes latitude and such grant may cover 
more than one standard block which shall be contiguous.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>857538</tid>
<number> 11</number> Grant of reconnaissance permit.-
<section><tid>1368309</tid>
<number>1</number>The administering authority  
may grant a non- exclusive reconnaissance permit to any person eligible 
under section 6 for grant of operating right.

</section>

<section><tid>1359756</tid>
<number>2</number>The period for which a reconnaissance permit may be granted under 
sub- section (1) shall be for a period specified in such permit which 
shall not exceed two years.

</section>

<section><tid>1885637</tid>
<number>3</number>A reconnaissance permit granted under sub- section (1) may be 
renewed for a period not exceeding two years if, after a review of the 
progress made during the period of such grant, the administering 
authority is satisfied that a further period is neces ary to complete 
the reconnaissance operation.

</section>

<section><tid>1227762</tid>
<number>4</number>The area that may be granted under one reconnaissance permit shall 
not exceed a block of two degree latitude by two degree longitude.

</section>

<section><tid>295835</tid>
<number>5</number>The administering authority may grant reconnaissance permits to 
more than one person in respect of the same area for the same mineral 
deposits in the interest of offshore mineral development.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1952440</tid>
<number> 12</number> Grant of exploration licence.-
<section><tid>775124</tid>
<number>1</number>The administering authority may  
grant an exploration licence to any person who-

<subsection><tid>942307</tid>
<number>a</number>is eligible under section 6 for grant of operating right;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>69740</tid>
<number>b</number>produces, to the satisfaction of the administering authority, 
evidence that such person possesses the requisite technical ability 
and financial resources to undertake exploration operation based on 
such scientific parameters, as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1428213</tid>
<number>c</number>submits a work programme for the area applied for, prepared in 
such manner and supported by such data as may be prescribed, setting 
forth the activities proposed to be carried out during the period of 
the exploration licence including the intended ex loration schedule 
and methods to be used, an estimated schedule of expenditure, measures 
to prevent pollution and protect the environment and to monitor the 
effectiveness of environmental safeguards subject to the modifications 
which the administering au hority may make in such work programme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>442040</tid>
<number>d</number>undertakes not to deviate from the work programme for exploration 
licence approved by the administering authority; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>82054</tid>
<number>e</number>has fulfilled, to the satisfaction of administering authority, all 
his statutory obligations under any operating right previously-

<subsubsection><tid>1086810</tid>
<number>i</number>granted; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>857432</tid>
<number>ii</number>transferred in the prescribed manner,
to him.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1133136</tid>
<number>2</number>The administering authority may, if there is any reasonable cause 
to believe that any person, to whom an exploration licence has been 
granted, has violated any undertaking given under clause (d) of 
sub- section (1), terminate the exploration licenc.

</section>

<section><tid>376342</tid>
<number>3</number>All applications for the grant of exploration licence received 
within the prescribed time and which satisfy the conditions specified 
in sub- section (1) shall be considered together and while making a 
selection for the grant of exploration licence, the administering 
authority shall follow the procedure given below, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1467241</tid>
<number>a</number>where only one application is received in respect of an area, the 
administering authority may grant the exploration licence to the 
applicant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>680413</tid>
<number>b</number>where two or more applications are received in respect of the same 
area or substantially the same area, the order of preference shall be 
as follows, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>1913465</tid>
<number>I</number>preference shall be given to an applicant who requires the mineral 
for use in an industry either already owned by the applicant or who 
has taken sufficient steps to set- up such industry:
Provided that where there are more than one application of such 
category, the administering authority may grant licence based on a 
comparative evaluation of the-


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>713242</tid>
<number>i</number>nature, quality and experience of the technical personnel employed 
by the applicant;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>85558</tid>
<number>ii</number>financial resources of the applicant;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1912658</tid>
<number>iii</number>nature and quantum of the exploration work proposed by the 
applicant; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>676350</tid>
<number>iv</number>nature, quality and quantum of data submitted along with the 
programme of exploration;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1963506</tid>
<number>II</number>in case of other applicants, not covered under sub- clause (I), 
the administering authority may grant licence based on a comparative 
evaluation of matters stated in items (i) to (iv) of the proviso to 
sub- clause (I).

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>982024</tid>
<number>4</number>The period for which an exploration licence may be granted shall 
not exceed three years.

</section>

<section><tid>818466</tid>
<number>5</number>An exploration licence granted under sub- section (1) may be 
renewed for a period not exceeding two years if, after a review, the 
administering authority is satisfied that the licensee has been 
conducting the exploration operation in accordance with the work 
programme approved by the administering authority regarding such 
licence and longer period of renewal of the licence is considered 
necessary to enable the licensee to complete exploration.

</section>

<section><tid>1801727</tid>
<number>6</number>The area that may be granted under exploration licence shall not 
exceed a block of thirty minutes latitude by thirty minutes longitude:
Provided that if the administering authority is of the opinion that in 
the interest of the development of any mineral, it is necessary so to 
do, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, permit any person 
to acquire an area in excess of the area sp cified in this 
sub- section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>75742</tid>
<number> 13</number> Grant of production lease.-
<section><tid>410454</tid>
<number>1</number>The administering authority shall  
grant a production lease to any person who-

<subsection><tid>1314349</tid>
<number>a</number>is eligible under section 6 for grant of operating right;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1892682</tid>
<number>b</number>produces, to the satisfaction of the administering authority, 
evidence that such person possesses the requisite technical ability 
and financial resources to undertake production operation based on 
such scientific parameters as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1944879</tid>
<number>c</number>submits a work programme for the systematic development of the 
mineral deposits of the area applied for, prepared in such manner and 
supported by such data as may be prescribed and obtained through 
exploration operation, setting forth the activiti s proposed to be 
carried out during the period of the lease including the resources 
assessment of the area, the intended schedule of commercial 
production, methods and technologies to be used for commercial 
production and processing, measures to be ta en to protect the 
environment and to monitor the effectiveness of environmental 
safeguards;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1449813</tid>
<number>d</number>undertakes not to deviate from work programme for production lease 
approved by the administering authority; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>382648</tid>
<number>e</number>has fulfilled, to the satisfaction of the administering authority, 
all the statutory obligations under any operating right previously-

<subsubsection><tid>26061</tid>
<number>I</number>granted; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>742978</tid>
<number>II</number>transferred in the prescribed manner,
to him:

Provided that a licensee shall have the exclusive right to a 
production lease over such part of the offshore area covered by his 
exploration licence as he may desire subject to the condition that the 
administering authority is satisfied that the licensee


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>318287</tid>
<number>i</number>has undertaken exploration operation to establish mineral 
resources in such offshore area;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1161602</tid>
<number>ii</number>has not committed any breach of the terms and conditions of the 
exploration licence; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>545149</tid>
<number>iii</number>has not become ineligible under the provisions of this Act.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1184107</tid>
<number>2</number>The administering authority may, if there is any reasonable cause 
to believe that any person, to whom a production lease has been 
granted, has violated any undertaking given under clause (d) of 
sub- section (1), terminate the production lease.

</section>

<section><tid>1703813</tid>
<number>3</number>The period for which a production lease may be granted shall not 
exceed thirty years.

</section>

<section><tid>341978</tid>
<number>4</number>A production lease granted under sub- section (1) may be renewed 
for a period not exceeding twenty years, if, after a review, the 
administering authority is satisfied that the lessee has been 
conducting the production operation in accordance with the ork 
programme approved by the administering authority regarding such 
lease.

</section>

<section><tid>320896</tid>
<number>5</number>The area under a production lease shall not exceed a block of 
fifteen minutes latitude by fifteen minutes longitude:
Provided that if the administering authority is of the opinion that in 
the interest of the development of any mineral, it is necessary so to 
do, it may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, permit any person 
to acquire an area in excess of the area sp cified in this 
sub- section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>169830</tid>
<number> 14</number> Period of commencement of operating rights.- A holder of operating 
right shall commence operation within the period specified below after 
the grant of the operating right and shall thereafter conduct such 
operation in proper, skilful and workman- li e manner, as follows:-
<section><tid>1902706</tid>
<number>a</number>reconnaissance permit- six months;

</section>

<section><tid>1103832</tid>
<number>b</number>exploration licence- one year; and

</section>

<section><tid>1733296</tid>
<number>c</number>production lease- two years.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>759245</tid>
<number>15</number>Power of Central Government to authorize survey, research and 
scientific investigations in areas covered under operating rights.- Any 
person or agency authorised by notification in the Official Gazette, 
by the Central Government in this behalf, may co duct survey, 
research, diving operations and scientific investigations in the 
offshore areas, including any area covered under operating rights and 
the permittee, licensee or lessee, as the case may be, shall permit 
such person or agency to undertake the said investigations in their 
respective areas and to render such assistance as may be necessary for 
conduct of the investigations.


</article>



<article><tid>1167921</tid>
<number> 16</number> Royalty.-
<section><tid>221168</tid>
<number>1</number>A lessee shall pay royalty to the Central Government  
in respect of any mineral removed or consumed by him from the area 
covered under the production lease, at the rate for the time being 
specified in the First Schedule in respect of that mineral.

</section>

<section><tid>1037748</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, amend the First Schedule so as to enhance or reduce the rate 
at which royalty shall be payable in respect of any mineral with 
effect from such date as may be specified in the notif cation:
Provided that the Central Government shall not enhance the rate of 
royalty in respect of any mineral more than once during any period of 
three years.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>406034</tid>
<number> 17</number> Fixed rent.-
<section><tid>513426</tid>
<number>1</number>A lessee shall pay to the Central Government,  
every year, fixed rent in respect of the area covered under the 
production lease, at the rate for the time being specified in the 
Second Schedule:
Provided that where the lessee becomes liable under section 16 to pay 
royalty for any mineral removed or consumed by him from the area 
covered under such lease, he shall be liable to pay either such 
royalty or the fixed rent in respect of that area, w ichever is 
greater.


</section>

<section><tid>1297163</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, amend the Second Schedule so as to enhance or reduce the rate 
at which fixed rent shall be payable in respect of any area covered 
under a production lease and such enhancement or re uction shall take 
effect from such date as may be specified in the notification:
Provided that the Central Government shall not enhance the rate of the 
fixed rent more than once during any period of three years.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1496945</tid>
<number>18</number>Contribution towards International Seabed Authority.- Every 
lessee, whose production operation extends beyond two hundred nautical 
miles from the baseline from which the breadth of the territorial sea 
is measured, shall pay in advance, in addition to ther payments 
required under this Act, to the Central Government, the amount to be 
paid to the International Seabed Authority towards fulfilment of 
obligation of the Central Government under Article 82 of the United 
Nations Convention on Law of the Sea, 982.


</article>



<article><tid>1031090</tid>
<number> 19</number> Safety of persons and property.-
<section><tid>804801</tid>
<number>1</number>The permittee, licensee,  
lessee or any other person undertaking the reconnaissance operation or 
exploration operation or production operation under sub- section (1) of 
section 5 or any agency undertaking the reconna ssance operation or 
exploration operation under the proviso to sub- section (1) of the said 
section shall be responsible to ensure that the concerned operation is 
conducted with due regard to the safety and health of persons 
including divers and safety an security of property engaged in the 
operation.

</section>

<section><tid>812292</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, declare safety zones in respect of offshore activities as may 
be necessary and prescribe the norms for regulating the safety and 
health of persons and safety of property engaged in perations 
authorised under this Act, the implementation thereof and matters 
connected therewith.

</section>

<section><tid>64620</tid>
<number>3</number>In the event of any contravention of provisions of sub- section (1) 
or the norms prescribed under sub- section (2) by the permittee, 
licensee, lessee or any other person undertaking the reconnaissance 
operation or exploration operation or production op ration under 
sub- section (1) of section 5, or any other agency undertaking the 
reconnaissance operation or exploration operation under the proviso to 
sub- section (1) of the said section, shall also be deemed to be 
responsible for such contravention unles he or it proves that he or 
it, as the case may be, had taken all reasonable precautions within 
his or its means for enforcing those provisions, to prevent such 
contravention.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>584941</tid>
<number> 20</number> Prevention and control of pollution and protection of marine 
environment.-
<section><tid>602495</tid>
<number>1</number>Every holder of the operating rights shall carry out  
the operations authorised under this Act subject to the provisions of 
this Act and the rules made thereunder and any o her law and the rules 
made thereunder, for the time being in force for the prevention and 
control of pollution and protection of marine environment.

</section>

<section><tid>1759434</tid>
<number>2</number>Every holder of an operating right shall be liable for any 
pollution of, or damage to, the marine environment resulting from his 
activities relating to his operating right in the offshore areas and 
shall pay such compensation, as may be determined by the administering 
authority keeping in view the extent of pollution or damage, as the 
case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>653241</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may prescribe measures to be taken for 
prevention and control of pollution and protection of marine 
environment due to activities in the offshore areas.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>985554</tid>
<number> 21</number> Power of Central Government and administering authority to issue 
directions.-
<section><tid>683839</tid>
<number>1</number>The permittee, licensee or lessee shall comply with  
such directions as the Central Government or the administering 
authority may issue, from time to time, for the conse vation and 
systematic development of offshore minerals, prevention of pollution, 
protection of marine environment, prevention of coastal erosion or 
prevention of danger to life or property including the marine life.

</section>

<section><tid>148784</tid>
<number>2</number>The permittee, licensee or lessee shall comply with such 
directions as may be issued from time to time by the competent 
authority or Coast Guard regarding national security, safety and 
national integrity. Explanation.-" competent authority" means the 
competent authority appointed for the purposes of sub- section (2) by 
the Central Government in the Ministry dealing with defence of India.
CHAP

POWER OF ENTRY, INSPECTION, SEARCH AND SEIZURE

CHAPTER III

POWER OF ENTRY, INSPECTION, SEARCH AND SEIZURE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1243003</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power of entry, inspection, search and seizure.-
<section><tid>1993552</tid>
<number>1</number>For the  
purpose of ascertaining the position of the working, actual or 
prospective, of any mine or abandoned mine, or for any other purpose 
connected with this Act or the rules made thereunder, any fficer 
authorised, by the Central Government in this behalf, by general or 
special order, may-

<subsection><tid>439696</tid>
<number>a</number>enter and inspect, at all reasonable times, any mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>553383</tid>
<number>b</number>weigh, draw samples or take measurements of the stocks of minerals 
recovered from any mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>368292</tid>
<number>c</number>survey and take samples and measurements in any such mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1453969</tid>
<number>d</number>examine any document, book, register or record in the possession 
or power of any person having the control of, or connected with, any 
mine and place marks of identification thereon and take extracts from, 
or make copies of, such document, book, regis er or record;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>455400</tid>
<number>e</number>order the production of any such document, book, register and 
record, by the person referred to in clause (d); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>508137</tid>
<number>f</number>examine any person having the control of, or connected with, any 
mine.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>22698</tid>
<number>2</number>Any authorised officer may, for the purpose of ascertaining 
whether or not the requirements of this Act or any rule made 
thereunder have been complied with, either with, or where it is not 
possible to obtain warrant conveniently, then, without, a war ant,-

<subsection><tid>1461984</tid>
<number>a</number>search any mine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1343870</tid>
<number>b</number>stop or board and search any vessel which is engaged or which is 
likely to be engaged in any activity regulated under this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>34872</tid>
<number>c</number>require the person for the time being having command or charge of 
mine or such vessel to produce any licence, permit, log book or other 
document relating, to the vessel or mine and examine or take copies of 
such licence, permit, log book or other doc ment, as the case may be, 
for ascertaining the requirements of sub- section (1).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>675454</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the authorised officer has reason to believe that any vessel 
or mine has been, or is being, or is about to be, used or employed, as 
the case may be, in violation of any provision of this Act or rule 
made thereunder, he may, with, or where it is not possible to obtain 
warrant conveniently, then, without, a warrant,-

<subsection><tid>106274</tid>
<number>a</number>seize and detain such vessel or mine, including any gear, 
equipment, stores or cargo found on board such vessel or belonging to 
the vessel and seize any mineral found on board the vessel;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>930416</tid>
<number>b</number>seize any evidence relating to violation of any provision of this 
Act or rule made thereunder;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1241520</tid>
<number>c</number>require the person for the time being having command or charge of 
the vessel, platform or erection of the mine so seized or detained to 
bring such vessel, platform or erection to any specified port;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1532743</tid>
<number>d</number>arrest any person whom such officer has reason to believe, has 
committed such violation:
Provided that the authorised officer, after arresting such person and 
before producing him before the competent court, shall inform the 
administering authority regarding the arrest and grounds of arrest 
communicated to the person so arrested.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>769837</tid>
<number>4</number>In taking any action under sub- section (3), the authorised officer 
may use such force as may be reasonably necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>341123</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any vessel or other things are seized or detained, under 
sub- section (3),-

<subsection><tid>835164</tid>
<number>a</number>the vessel or other things so seized or detained shall, as soon as 
possible, be produced before the court competent to try an offence 
under this Act and the court shall make such order as it may deem fit 
for the retention or custody of such vessel or things with the Central 
Government or any other authority pending the completion of any 
proceedings for the prosecution of any offence relating to such vessel 
or things, as the case may be, under this Act or rules made 
thereunder:
Provided that the court may, on an application made by the owner or 
the person for the time being having command or charge of the vessel 
or mine, order the release of the vessel or other things so seized or 
detained, to the owner or the person for the ti e being having command 
or charge of the vessel or mine, furnishing security in the form of 
cash or a bank guarantee for an amount which is not less than fifty 
per cent. of the value of the vessel or things so seized or detained;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1775400</tid>
<number>b</number>the administering authority shall be informed by the authorised 
officer of such seizure and the details thereof.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>800070</tid>
<number>6</number>Where, in pursuance of the commission of any offence under this 
Act, any vessel is pursued beyond the limits of the offshore area, the 
powers conferred on an authorised officer by this section may be 
exercised beyond such limits in the circumstances nd to the extent 
recognised by international law and State practice.

</section>

<section><tid>774185</tid>
<number>7</number>Every person to whom an order or warrant is issued or given by 
virtue of the powers conferred by this section shall be legally bound 
to comply with such order or warrant.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>1044965</tid>
<number>i</number>" authorised officer" means an officer of the Central Government 
notified as such in the Official Gazette, by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753888</tid>
<number>ii</number>" warrant" means a warrant issued by the Judicial Magistrate or 
the Metropolitan Magistrate, as the case may be, within whose 
jurisdiction the place, where the warrant is to be executed, is 
situated.
CHAP

OFFENCES

CHAPTER IV

OFFENCES




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>443313</tid>
<number> 23</number> Offences.-
<section><tid>1944185</tid>
<number>1</number> (a) Whoever undertakes any reconnaissance  
operation, exploration operation or production operation in offshore 
area without any permit, licence or lease, as the case may be, granted 
under this Act shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to five years, or with fine which may extend to fifty 
thousand rupees, or with both.

<subsection><tid>513795</tid>
<number>b</number>A permittee, licensee or lessee who does not furnish any data, 
information or document under sub- section (2) of section 5, in the 
manner provided therein, shall be punished with imprisonment which may 
extend to three years, or with fine which may ex end to twenty- five 
thousand rupees, or with both.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>415911</tid>
<number>c</number>Any vessel, together with its gear, boats, stores and cargo, used 
or employed in violation of section 5, along with any mineral 
recovered or processed in violation of that section, if any, shall be 
confiscated.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1797938</tid>
<number>d</number>Whoever ships, transports, offers for sale, sells, purchases, 
imports, exports, or has custody, control or possession of, any 
mineral recovered, processed or retained in violation of this Act or 
any rule made thereunder shall be punished with impriso ment which may 
extend to three years, or with fine which may extend to fifty lakh 
rupees, or with both.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1984783</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever-

<subsection><tid>1664795</tid>
<number>a</number>intentionally obstructs any authorised officer referred to in 
section 22 in the exercise of any powers conferred under this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1043449</tid>
<number>b</number>fails to afford reasonable facilities to the authorised officer 
referred to in section 22 or his assistant to board the vessel or 
enter the mine or to provide for adequate security to such officer or 
assistant at the time of entry into the vessel or ine or when they are 
on board such vessel or mine; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1406889</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to stop the vessel or mine or to produce the licence, 
permit, log book or any other document, as the case may be, on board 
such vessel, or mine, when required to do so by the authorised officer 
referred to in section 22; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>353421</tid>
<number>d</number>interferes with, delays, or prevents, by any means, the lawful 
apprehension of any person under this Act,
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
five years, or with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1186734</tid>
<number>3</number>Whoever contravenes any other provision of this Act or rules made 
thereunder, other than those specified in sub- sections (1) and (2) 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
five years, or with fine which may extend to one c ore rupees, or with 
both, and in the case of continuing contravention, with an additional 
fine which may extend to five lakh rupees for every day during which 
such contravention continues.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>929345</tid>
<number> 24</number> Offences by companies.-
<section><tid>453697</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act has  
been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence 
was committed, was directly in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render any 
such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge and that 
he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the c mmission of such 
offence.


</section>

<section><tid>695052</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where an 
offence under this Act, has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the art of, any 
director, manager, secretary, or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>86240</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1081683</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1086228</tid>
<number>25</number>Place of trial.- Notwithstanding anything contained in other law 
for the time being in force, any person committing an offence under 
this Act or any rule made thereunder or under any of the enactment 
extended under this Act or under the rules made the eunder shall be 
tried for the offence in such place as the Central Government may, by 
general or special order published in the Official Gazette, direct in 
this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>1921935</tid>
<number>26</number>Previous sanction of Central Government for prosecution.- No 
prosecution for an offence committed under this Act shall be 
instituted except with the previous sanction of the Central Government 
or such officer or authority as may be authorised by the C ntral 
Government, by order in writing in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>24824</tid>
<number>27</number>Offences triable by Court of Session.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), all 
offences under this Act shall be triable by the Court of Session.
CHAP

CIVIL LIABILITY AND ADJUDICATION

CHAPTER V

CIVIL LIABILITY AND ADJUDICATION



</article>



<article><tid>329956</tid>
<number> 28</number> Civil liability and adjudication.-
<section><tid>115591</tid>
<number>1</number>A person to whom a permit,  
licence or lease is granted under this Act,-

<subsection><tid>546290</tid>
<number>a</number>contravenes the general terms and conditions imposed by the rules 
made under this Act shall be liable to pay to the Central Government 
an amount which shall not be less than five lakh rupees and which may 
extend to one crore rupees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1080183</tid>
<number>b</number>contravenes any particular terms and conditions applicable only in 
case of such permittee, licensee or lessee as the case may be, shall 
also be liable, apart from the liability under clause (a), to pay 
additional amount to the Central Government whi h shall not be less 
than one lakh rupees and which may extend to ten lakh rupees.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>188609</tid>
<number>2</number>No court or other authority except the authorised officer 
designated by the Central Government for this purpose, shall have 
jurisdiction to hear and decide the cases relating to clauses (a) and 
 (b) of sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>307236</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer of the Central Government who has been authorised by 
that Government to file an application before the authorised officer 
designated under sub- section (2), shall file an application against 
licensee, lessee or permittee, as the case may be indicating the civil 
wrong committed by him under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub- section 
 (1) in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1927852</tid>
<number>4</number>When an application is filed under sub- section (3), before an 
authorised officer designated under sub- section (2), he shall serve 
notice along with the copy of such application to the person, against 
whom the application is made, to provide him an o portunity to file 
reply to the application in the prescribed manner and the authorised 
officer shall dispose of the case after considering the evidence 
produced either in support or in opposition to the application and 
after providing the opportunity of hearing.

</section>

<section><tid>276795</tid>
<number>5</number>For the purposes of this section, the authorised officer 
designated under sub- section (2), shall have the same powers as are 
vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>224762</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining 
him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1664034</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>104823</tid>
<number>c</number>receiving evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1852866</tid>
<number>d</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1094949</tid>
<number>e</number>reviewing its decisions; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>18979</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VI

MISCELLANEOUS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1385804</tid>
<number> 29</number> Extension of enactments to offshore areas.- The Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette,-
<section><tid>1235358</tid>
<number>a</number>extend with such restrictions and modifications as it thinks fit, 
any enactment for the time being in force in India or any part thereof 
to the offshore area or any part thereof; and

</section>

<section><tid>1258928</tid>
<number>b</number>make such provisions as it may consider necessary for facilitating 
the enforcement of such enactment,
and any enactment so extended shall have effect as if the offshore 
area or the part thereof, as the case may be, is a part of the 
territory of India.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1265845</tid>
<number> 30</number> Compounding of offences.-
<section><tid>612335</tid>
<number>1</number>Any offence punishable under this  
Act may, either before or after the institution of the prosecution, be 
compounded by the administering authority or any other officer 
authorised by the Central Government with respect to hat offence, on 
payment for credit to that Government of such sum as that 
administering authority or officer, as the case may be, may specify:
Provided that such sum shall not, in any case, exceed the maximum 
amount of the fine which may be imposed under this Act for the offence 
so compounded.


</section>

<section><tid>900174</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an offence is compounded under sub- section (1), no 
proceeding or further proceeding, as the case may be, shall be taken 
against the offender in respect of the offence so compounded and the 
offender, if in custody, shall be released forthwith.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>937375</tid>
<number>31</number>Recovery of certain sums as arrears of land revenue.- Any licence 
fee, royalty, fixed rent or other sum due to the Central Government 
under this Act or rules made thereunder or under the terms and 
conditions of a reconnaissance permit, exploration l cence or 
production lease may, on a certificate issued by the administering 
authority, be recovered in the same manner as if it were an arrear of 
land revenue and every such sum together with the interest due 
thereon, shall be the first charge on the ass ts of the permittee, 
licensee or lessee, as the case may be.


</article>



<article><tid>1922144</tid>
<number>32</number>Delegation of powers.- The Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, direct that any power exercisable by it under 
this Act or any rule made thereunder may, in relation to such matter 
and subject to such conditions, if any, as m y be specified in the 
notification, be exercisable also by such officer or authority 
subordinate to that Government as may be specified in the 
notification.


</article>



<article><tid>887681</tid>
<number>33</number>Protection of action taken in good faith.- No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceedings shall lie against any person for anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or 
any rule made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1246556</tid>
<number> 34</number> Appeals.-
<section><tid>1423094</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), any  
person aggrieved by an order made by the administering authority or 
any officer under this Act or the rules made thereunder may prefer an 
appeal against such order to the Central Governme t.

</section>

<section><tid>1142203</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such appeal shall be preferred within prescribed period from 
the date on which the impugned order was made:
Provided that the Central Government may, if it is satisfied that the 
appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring the appeal 
within such prescribed period, permit the appellant to prefer the 
appeal within a further period as may be prescr bed.


</section>

<section><tid>861110</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of any such appeal, the Central Government shall, after 
giving the parties to the appeal a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard and after making such inquiry as it deems proper, make such 
order, as it may think fit, confirming, modifying r reversing the 
order appealed against, or may send back the case with such direction 
as it may think fit for a fresh order after taking additional 
evidence, if necessary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1075981</tid>
<number> 35</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>1088790</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purposes of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>569073</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such 
rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>931364</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of a reconnaissance permit, exploration 
licence or production lease under sub- section (1) of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>473555</tid>
<number>b</number>conditions for grant of operating right under clause (b) of 
section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1491182</tid>
<number>c</number>substances to be prescribed under proviso to section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1912073</tid>
<number>d</number>the requisite technical ability and financial resources to 
undertake exploration operation on scientific parameters under clause 
 (b) of sub- section (1) of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>814906</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which a work programme shall be prepared and the 
data by which the work programme shall be supported under clause (c) 
of sub- section (1) of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>309931</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner of transfer referred to in sub- clause (ii) of clause 
 (e) of sub- section (1) of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452949</tid>
<number>g</number>the time within which the applications under sub- section (3) of 
section 12 are to be received;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1652752</tid>
<number>h</number>the requisite technical ability and financial resources to 
undertake production operation on scientific parameters under clause 
 (b) of sub- section (1) of section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>630818</tid>
<number>i</number>the manner in which a work programme shall be prepared and the 
data by which the work programme shall be supported under clause (c) 
of sub- section (1) of section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>850618</tid>
<number>j</number>the manner of transfer referred to in sub- clause (II) of clause 
 (e) of sub- section (1) of section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>964545</tid>
<number>k</number>norms for regulating the safety and health of persons and safety 
of property engaged in operations authorised under this Act, the 
implementation thereof and matters connected therewith under 
sub- section (2) of section 19;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1761677</tid>
<number>l</number>the measures to be taken for prevention and control of pollution 
and protection of marine environment due to activities in the offshore 
areas under sub- section (3) of section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1758153</tid>
<number>m</number>the manner of filing application under sub- section (3) of section 
28;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1400938</tid>
<number>n</number>the manner of filing reply under sub- section (4) of section 28;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>141238</tid>
<number>o</number>any other matter under clause (f) of sub- section (5) of section 
28;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1532038</tid>
<number>p</number>the period within which appeal shall be preferred under, and the 
further period which may be permitted under the proviso to, 
sub- section (2) of section 34;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1110478</tid>
<number>q</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed under this 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>853022</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be 
laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or ore successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the ule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1729324</tid>
<number>36</number>Relaxation in specific cases.- Notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in this Act or any rule made thereunder, the 
Central Government may, if it is of the opinion that in the interests 
of the offshore mineral development, it is necessary s to do, by order 
and for reasons to be recorded in writing, authorise in any specific 
case the grant, renewal or transfer of any operating right to any 
person on such terms and conditions as it may specify in this behalf 
in such order.


</article>



<article><tid>962880</tid>
<number>37</number>Persons to be public servants.- The administering authority or any 
other officer shall be deemed, while acting or purporting to act in 
pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, to be public servants 
within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (4 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>845446</tid>
<number> 38</number> Removal of difficulties.-
<section><tid>563239</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in giving  
effect to the provisions of this Act, or of any of the enactments 
extended under section 29, the Central Government may, by order 
published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions ot 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or, as the case may be, 
of such enactment, as may appear to it to be necessary or expedient 
for removing the difficulty:
Provided that no order shall be made under this section,-


<subsection><tid>27900</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of any difficulty arising in giving effect to any 
provision of this Act, after the expiry of three years from the 
commencement of such provision;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1162386</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any difficulty arising in giving effect to the 
provisions of any enactment extended under section 29, after the 
expiry of three years from the extension of such enactment.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>223973</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



 </act>