<act><title>


    The Dissolution of Muslim 
    Marriages Act, 1939</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Dissolution of Muslim Marriages Act, 1939. —(1) 
    This Act may be called the Dissolution of Muslim Marriages Act, 1939." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[except the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir]].
  
 

    State Amendment
 <subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—In 
    section 1, after sub-section (2), add the following:—
 
           “Provided that 
    nothing contained in this Act shall apply to Renoncants of the Union 
    territory of Pondicherry”, vide the Pondicherry (Extension of Laws) 
    Act, 1968, sec. 3 and Sch.
  






 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Grounds for decree for dissolution of marriage.—A 
    woman married under Muslim law shall be entitled to obtain a decree for the 
    dissolution of her marriage on any one or more of the following grounds, 
    namely:— —A 
    woman married under Muslim law shall be entitled to obtain a decree for the 
    dissolution of her marriage on any one or more of the following grounds, 
    namely\:—" 
 <section>
<number>i</number>  that the whereabouts 
    of the husband have not been known for a period of four years;  (i) that the whereabouts of the husband have not been known for a 
    period of four years;" 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>  that the husband has 
    neglected or has failed to provide for her maintenance for a period of two 
    years;  (ii) that the husband has neglected or has failed to provide for her 
    maintenance for a period of two years;" 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>  that the husband 
    has been sentenced to imprisonment for a period of seven years or upwards;  (iii) that the husband has been sentenced to imprisonment for a period 
    of seven years or upwards;" 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>  that the husband has 
    failed to perform, without reasonable cause, his marital obligations for a 
    period of three years;  (iv) that the husband has failed to perform, without reasonable cause, 
    his marital obligations for a period of three years;" 
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>  that the husband was 
    impotent at the time of the marriage and continues to be so;  (v) that the husband was impotent at the time of the marriage and 
    continues to be so;" 
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>  that the husband has 
    been insane for a period of two years or is suffering from leprosy or 
    virulent venereal disease;  (vi) that the husband has been insane for a period of two years or is 
    suffering from leprosy or virulent venereal disease;" 
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>  that she, having 
    been given in marriage by her father or other guardian before she attained 
    the age of fifteen years, repudiated the marriage before attaining the age 
    of eighteen years:  (vii) that she, having been given in marriage by her father or other 
    guardian before she attained the age of fifteen years, repudiated the 
    marriage before attaining the age of eighteen years\:" 
 
    Provided that the 
    marriage has not been consummated;  Provided that the marriage has not been consummated;" 
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>  that the husband 
    treats her with cruelty, that is to say,—  (viii) that the husband treats her with cruelty, that is to say,—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  habitually assaults 
    her or makes her life miserable by cruelty of conduct even if such conduct 
    does not amount to physical ill-treatment, or  (a) habitually assaults her or makes her life miserable by cruelty of 
    conduct even if such conduct does not amount to physical ill-treatment, or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  associates with women 
    of evil repute or leads an infamous life, or  (b) associates with women of evil repute or leads an infamous life, 
    or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  attempts to force her 
    to lead an immoral life, or  (c) attempts to force her to lead an immoral life, or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  disposes of her 
    property or prevents her exercising her legal rights over it, or  (d) disposes of her property or prevents her exercising her legal 
    rights over it, or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>  obstructs her in the 
    observance of her religious profession or practice, or  (e) obstructs her in the observance of her religious profession or 
    practice, or" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>  if he has more wives 
    than one, does not treat her equitably in accordance with the injunctions of 
    the Quran;  (f) if he has more wives than one, does not treat her equitably in 
    accordance with the injunctions of the Quran;" 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ix</number>  on any other ground 
    which is recognised as valid for the dissolution of marriages under Muslim 
    law:  (ix) on any other ground which is recognised as valid for the 
    dissolution of marriages under Muslim law\:" 
 

    Provided that—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  no decree shall be 
    passed on ground (iii) until the sentence has become final;  (a) no decree shall be passed on ground (iii) until the sentence has 
    become final;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  a decree passed on 
    ground (i) shall not take effect for a period of six months from the date of 
    such decree, and if the husband appears either in person or through an 
    authorised agent within that period and satisfies the Court that he is 
    prepared to perform his conjugal duties, the Court shall set aside the said 
    decree; and  (b) a decree passed on ground (i) shall not take effect for a period 
    of six months from the date of such decree, and if the husband appears 
    either in person or through an authorised agent within that period and 
    satisfies the Court that he is prepared to perform his conjugal duties, the 
    Court shall set aside the said decree; and" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  before passing a 
    decree on ground (v) the Court shall, on application by the husband, make an 
    order requiring the husband to satisfy the Court within a period of one year 
    from the date of such order that he has ceased to be impotent, and if the 
    husband so satisfies the Court within such period, no decree shall be passed 
    on the said ground.  (c) before passing a decree on ground (v) the Court shall, on 
    application by the husband, make an order requiring the husband to satisfy 
    the Court within a period of one year from the date of such order that he 
    has ceased to be impotent, and if the husband so satisfies the Court within 
    such period, no decree shall be passed on the said ground." 
  











 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Notice to be served on heirs of the husband, when the husband’s whereabouts 
    are not known.—In 
    a suit to which clause 
<section><number>i</number> of section 2 applies— —In 
    a suit to which clause (i) of section 2 applies—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  the names and 
    addresses of the persons who would have been the heirs of the husband under 
    Muslim law if he had died on the date of the filing of the plaint shall be 
    stated in the plaint,  (a) the names and addresses of the persons who would have been the 
    heirs of the husband under Muslim law if he had died on the date of the 
    filing of the plaint shall be stated in the plaint," 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  notice of the suit 
    shall be served on such persons, and  (b) notice of the suit shall be served on such persons, and" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  such persons shall 
    have the right to be heard in the suit:  (c) such persons shall have the right to be heard in the suit\:" 
 

    Provided that paternal uncle and brother of the husband, if any, shall be 
    cited as party even if he or they are not heirs.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Effect of conversion to another faith.—The 
    renunciation of Islam by a married Muslim woman or her conversion to faith 
    other than Islam shall not by itself operate to dissolve her marriage: —The 
    renunciation of Islam by a married Muslim woman or her conversion to faith 
    other than Islam shall not by itself operate to dissolve her marriage\:" 
 

    Provided that after such renunciation, or conversion, the woman shall be 
    entitled to obtain a decree for the dissolution of her marriage on any of 
    the grounds mentioned in section 2:
 

    Provided further that the provisions of this section shall not apply to a 
    woman converted to Islam from some other faith who re-embraces her former 
    faith.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article></article><article>
<number>5</number> 
    Rights to dower not to be affected.—Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall affect any right which a married woman may have 
    under Muslim law to her dower or any part thereof on the dissolution of her 
    marriage. —Nothing 
    contained in this Act shall affect any right which a married woman may have 
    under Muslim law to her dower or any part thereof on the dissolution of her 
    marriage." 
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
 Subs. by the Adaptation 
    of Laws (No. 3) Order, 1956, for "Part B States".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Subs. by Act 48 of 1959  
    sec. 3 and Sch. I, for certain words (w.e.f. 1-2-1960).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>