<act><title>

The
Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Slaughter House) Rules, 20011</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Slaughter House)
Rules, 2001. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
  


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 (59 of
1960);  
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
“slaughter” means the killing or destruction of any animal for the
purpose of food and includes all the processes and operations performed on all
such animals in order to prepare it for being slaughtered; 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“slaughter house” means a slaughter house wherein 10 or more than 10
animals are slaughtered per day and is duly licensed or recognised under a
Central, State or Provincial Act or any rules or regulations made thereunder;  
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
“veterinary doctor” means a person registered with the Veterinary
Council of India established under the Indian Veterinary Council Act, 1984 (52
of 1984).  
 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Animals not to be slaughtered except in recognised or licensed houses.—

<section><number>1</number> No person shall slaughter any animal within a municipal area except in a
slaughter house recognised or licensed by the concerned authority empowered
under the law for the time being in force to do so. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No animal which,—
 


 <subsection><number>i</number>
is pregnant, or  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
has an offspring less than three months old, or  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
is under the age of three months, or  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
has not been certified by a veterinary doctor that it is in a fit
condition to be slaughtered, 
 

 shall
be slaughtered.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
The municipal or other local authority specified by the Central Government for
this purpose shall, having regard to the capacity of the slaughter house and the
requirement of the local population of the area in which a slaughter house is
situated, determine the maximum number of animals that may be slaughtered in a
day. 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Reception area or resting grounds.—
<section><number>1</number>
The slaughter house shall have a reception area of adequate size sufficient for
livestock subject to veterinary inspection.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The veterinary doctor shall examine thoroughly not more than 12 animals in an
hour and not more than 96 animals in a day. 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The veterinary doctor after examining the animal shall issue a fitness
certificate in the form specified by the Central Government for this purpose. 
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The reception area of slaughter house shall have proper ramps for direct
unloading of animals from vehicles or railway wagons and the said reception area
shall have adequate facility sufficient for feeding and watering of animals. 
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Separate isolation pens shall be provided in slaughter house with watering and
feeding arrangements for animals suspected to be suffering from contagious and
infectious diseases, and fractious animals, in order to segregate them from the
remaining animals. 
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Adequate holding area shall be provided in slaughter house according to the
class of animals to be slaughtered and the said holding area shall have water
and feeding facilities. 
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
The resting grounds in slaughter house shall have overhead protective shelters. 
 


 </section><section><number>8</number>
Ante-mortem and pen area in slaughter house shall be paved with impervious
material such as concrete non-slippery herring-bone type suitable to stand wear
and tear by hooves, or brick, and pitched to suitable drainage facilities and
the curbs of said impervious material 150 to 300 mm high shall be provided
around the borders of livestock pen area, except at the entrances and such pen
shall preferably be covered. 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Lairages.—
<section><number>1</number> Every animal after it
has been subject to veterinary inspection shall be passed on to a lairage for
resting for 24 hours before slaughter. 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The lairage of the slaughter house shall be adequate in size sufficient for the
number of animals to be laired.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The space provided in the pens of such lairage shall be not less than 2.8 sq.mt.
per large animal and 1.6 sq.mt. per small animal.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The animals shall be kept in such lairage separately depending upon their type
and class and such lairage shall be so constructed as to protect the animals
from heat, cold and rain.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
The lairage shall have adequate facilities for watering and post-mortem
inspection. 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Slaughter.—
<section><number>1</number> No animal shall be
slaughtered in a slaughter house in sight of other animals 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
No animal shall be administered any chemical, drug or hormone before slaughter
except drug for its treatment from any specific disease or ailment. 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The slaughter halls in a slaughter house shall provide separate sections of
adequate dimensions sufficient for slaughter of individual animals to ensure
that the animal to be slaughtered is not within the sight of other animals. 
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every slaughter house as soon as possible shall provide a separate space for
stunning of animals prior to slaughter, bleeding and dressing of the carcasses.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
Knocking section in slaughter house may be so planned as to suit the animal and
particularly the ritual slaughter, if any and such knocking section and dry
landing area associated with it shall be so built that escape from this section
can be easily carried out by an operator without allowing the animal to pass the
escape barrier. 
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
A curbed-in bleeding area of adequate size as specified by the Central
Government shall be provided in a slaughter house and it shall be so located
that the blood could not be splashed on other animals being slaughtered or on
the carcass being skinned. 
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
The blood drain and collection in a slaughter house shall be immediate and
proper.
 


 </section><section><number>8</number>
A floor wash point shall be provided in a slaughter house for intermittent
cleaning and a hand-wash basin and knife sterilizer shall also be provided for
the sticker to sterilize knife and wash his hands periodically. 
 


 </section><section><number>9</number>
Dressing of carcasses in a slaughter house shall not be done on floor and
adequate means and tools for dehiding or belting of the animals shall be
provided in a slaughter house with means for immediate disposal of hides or
skins.
 


 </section><section><number>10</number>
Hides or skins shall be immediately transported from a slaughter house either in
a closed wheelbarrow or by a chute provided with self-closing door and in no
case such hides or skins shall be spread on slaughter floor for inspection. 
 


 </section><section><number>11</number>
Floor wash point and adequate number of hand wash-basins with sterilizer shall
be provided in a dressing area of a slaughter house with means for immediate
disposal of legs, horns, hooves and other parts of animals through spring load
floor chutes or sidewall doors or closed wheelbarrows and in case wheelbarrows
or trucks are used in a slaughter house, care shall be taken that no point
wheelbarrow or truck has to ply under the dressing rails and a clear passage is
provided for movement of the trucks. 
 


 </section><section><number>12</number>
Adequate space and suitable and properly located facilities shall be provided
sufficient for inspection of the viscera of the various types of animals
slaughtered in a slaughter house and it shall have adequate facilities for hand
washing, tool sterilisation and floor washing and contrivances for immediate
separation and disposal of condemned material. 
 


 </section><section><number>13</number>
Adequate arrangements shall be made in a slaughter house by its owner for
identification, inspection and correlation of carcass, viscera and head. 
 


 </section><section><number>14</number>
In a slaughter house, a curbed and separately drained area or an area of
sufficient size, sloped 33 mm per metre to a floor drain, where the carcasses
may be washed with a jet of water, shall be provided by the owner of such
slaughter house. 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Slaughter house building.—The
different construction of a slaughter house shall be built and maintained by its
owner in the manner as specified below, namely:—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
Plant Building.—(i) Materials used shall be impervious, easily
cleansable, and resistant to wear and corrosion. (ii) Materials such as wood,
plaster board, and porous acoustic-type boards, which are absorbent and
difficult to keep clean shall not be used;  
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
Floors.—The floors shall be non-absorbent and non-slippery with
rough finish and shall have suitable gradient for drainage;  
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
Coves.— Coves with radii sufficient to promote sanitation shall
be installed at the juncture of floors and walls, in all rooms and which shall
not be less than 100 mm; 
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
Interior Walls.—(i) Interior walls shall be smooth and flat and
constructed of impervious materials such a glazed brick, glazed tile, smooth
surface Portland cement plaster, or other non-toxic, non-absorber material
applied to a suitable base. (ii) Walls shall be provided with suitable sanitary
type bumpers to prevent damage by hand trucks, carcass shanks, and the like.
(iii) The interior walls shall have washable surface up to the height of 2
metres from the floor so that the splashes may be washed and disinfected;  
 

 </section><section><number>e</number>
Ceilings.—(i) Ceilings shall be of the height of 5 metres or
more in workrooms and so far as structure conditions permit, ceilings shall be
smooth and flat (ii) Ceilings shall be constructed of Portland cement plaster,
large size cement asbestos boards with joints sealed with a flexible sealing
compound, or other acceptable impervious material and finished so as to minimise
condensation, mould development, flaking and accumulation of dirt. (iii) The
walls above glazed type portion and ceiling shall be painted with
water-resistant paint to maintain them clean; 
 

 </section><section><number>f</number>
Window Ledges.—Window ledges shall be sloped at 45 degrees to
promote sanitation and to avoid damage to glass in windows from impact of hand
trucks and similar equipment, the windowsills shall be 1200 mm above the floor
level with proper ventilation through mechanical venting or through working
vents shall be provided in the roof structure;  
 

 </section><section><number>g</number>
Doorways and Doors.—(i) Doorways through which product is
transferred on rails or in hand trucks shall be at least 1500 mm high and shall
be at least 1500 mm wide. (ii) Doors shall either be of rust-resistant metal
construction throughout, or if made with rust-resistant metal having tight
softwood, they shall be clad on both sides with soldered or welded seams. (iii)
Doorjambs shall be clad with rust-resistant metal securely affixed so as to
provide no crevices for dirt or vermin and the juncture at which the door joins
the walls shall be effectively sealed with a flexible sealing compound;  
 

 </section><section><number>h</number>
Screens and Insect control.—All windows, doorways and other
openings that may admit flies shall be equipped with effective insect and rodent
screens and ‘Fly chaser’ fans and ducts or air curtains shall be provided
over doorways in outside wall of food handling areas that are used for dispatch
or receiving;  
 

 </section><section><number>i</number>
Rodent-Proofing.—Except in the case of solid masonry, walls
constructed of glazed tile, glazed brick, and the like, expanded metal or wire
mesh not exceeding 12.5 mm mesh, shall be embedded in walls and floor at their
junction and such mesh shall extend vertically and horizontally to a sufficient
distance to exclude the entrance of rats and other rodents;  
 

 </section><section><number>j</number>
Vehicular areas for Trucks.—(i) Concrete paved areas, properly
drained and extending at least 6 metres from building, loading docks or
livestock platforms shall be provided at places where vehicles are loaded or
unloaded. (ii) Pressure washing jets and disinfection facilities for trucks
carrying animals shall also be provided at such places; 
 

 </section><section><number>k</number>
Drainage.—(i) All parts of floors where wet operations are
conducted shall be well drained and as far as possible, one drainage inlet shall
be provided for each 37 metre square of floor space (ii) A slope of about 20 mm
per metre to drainage inlets shall be provided for usual conditions and it shall
be ensured that the floor slopes uniformly to drains with no low spots, which
collect liquid. (iii) Floor drains shall not be provided in freezer rooms or dry
storage areas and when floor drains are installed in rooms where the water seal
in traps is likely to evaporate without replenishment, they shall be provided
with suitable removable metal screw plugs;  
 

 </section><section><number>l</number>
Traps and vents on drainage lines.—(i) Each floor drain,
including blood drains, shall be equipped with a deep seal trap (P-, U-, or
S-shape) (ii) Drainage lines shall be properly vented to the outside air and be
equipped with effective rodent screens;  
 

 </section><section><number>m</number>
Sanitary drainage lines.—Drainage line from toilet pans and
urinals shall not be connected with other drainage lines within the plant and
shall not discharge into a grease catch basin and such lines shall be installed
so that if leakage develops, it shall not affect the product or the equipment;  
 

 </section><section><number>n</number>
Lighting and ventilation.—(i) Unrefrigerated work rooms shall be
provided with adequate direct natural light and ventilation or ample artificial
light and ventilation by mechanical means. (ii) Uncoloured glass having a high
transmissibility of light shall be used in skylights and windows. (iii) The
glass area shall be approximately one-fourth of the floor area of a workroom and
such ratio shall be increased where there are obstructions, such as adjacent
buildings, overhead catwalks, and hoists, which interfere with the admittance of
direct natural light. (iv) Distributed artificial lighting of much quality and
at such distances as may be specified by the Central Government shall be
provided at all places where adequate natural light is not available or is
insufficient;  
 

 </section><section><number>o</number>
Every abattoir shall be provided with distributed artificial light of an
overall intensity of not less than 200 lux at the distances as may be specified
by the Central Government throughout the slaughter hall and workrooms and at
places where meat inspection is carried out, the overall intensity of artificial
light shall be not less than 500 lux;  
 

 </section><section><number>p</number>
every abattoir shall be provided with suitable and sufficient means of
ventilation to the outside air and the construction of the slaughter hall shall
be so arranged that the dressed carcasses are not exposed to direct sunlight;  
 

 </section><section><number>q</number>
a sufficient, safe, potable and constant supply of fresh water shall be
available at adequate pressure through the premises;  
 

 </section><section><number>r</number>
the pressure for the general purpose of floor washing may preferably be
200 to 330 kPa for thorough floor cleaning;  
 

 </section><section><number>s</number>
for thorough and efficient washing of carcasses, a higher pressure
between 1000 kPa to 1700 kPa shall be maintained;  
 

 </section><section><number>t</number>
floor washing point shall be provided preferably for minimum 37 metre
square on slaughter floor and working departments; 
 

 </section><section><number>u</number>
a constant supply of clean hot water shall be available in the slaughter
hall and workrooms during working hours and the hot water required for frequent
sterilising of equipment shall not be less than 82 degree celsius;  
 

 </section><section><number>v</number>
where necessary for sanitary maintenance, equipment shall be constructed
and installed so as to be completely self-draining;  
 

 </section><section><number>w</number>
the following materials shall not be used in an abattoir, namely— 
 

 <subsection><number>i</number>
copper and its alloys in equipment used for edible products; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
cadmium in any form in equipment handling edible products;  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
equipment with painted surface in product zone; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
enamel containers or equipment is not desirable; and  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>
lead; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number>
all permanently mounted equipment shall either be installed sufficiently
away from walls (minimum 300 mm) to provide access for cleaning and inspection; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>y</number>
all permanently mounted equipment shall either be installed sufficiently
above the floor (minimum 300 mm) to provide access for cleaning and inspection
or be completely sealed (watertight) to the floor area.  
 
 



  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Engagement in slaughter house.—
<section><number>1</number>
No owner or occupier of a slaughter house shall engage a person for slaughtering
animals unless he possesses a valid license or authorisation issued by the
municipal or other local authority. 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
No person who has not attained the age of 18 years shall be employed in any
manner in a slaughter house. 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
No person who is suffering from any communicable or infectious disease shall be
permitted to slaughter an animal. 
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
Inspection of slaughter house.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Animal Welfare Board of India or any person or Animal Welfare Organisation
authorised by it may inspect any slaughter house without notice to its owner or
the person incharge of it at any time during the working hours to ensure that
the provisions of these rules are being complied with. 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The person or the Animal Welfare Organisation authorised under sub-rule (1)
shall after inspection send its report to Animal Welfare Board of India as well
as to the municipal or local authority for appropriate action including
initiation of legal proceedings if any, in the event of violation of any
provisions of these rules.
 


 


  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>