<act> 
 
The Armed Forces (Emergency  
Duties) Act, 1947
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and extent.—1[***] 
This Act may be called the Armed Forces (Emergency Duties) Act, 1947.
 

2[***]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Armed Forces (Emergency  
Duties) Act, 1947
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Emergency duties of Armed Forces.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare any 
specified service 

1[in a State] to be a service of vital 
importance to the community:
 
Provided that such notification shall remain 
in force for one month in the first instance, but may be extended, from time to 
time, by a like notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon a declaration being made under 
sub-section (1) and until it is rescinded, it shall be the duty of every person 
subject to 

2[the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force 
Act 1950], or 

3[***] 

4[the Navy Act, 1957] to obey any 
command given by any superior officer in relation to employment upon or in 
connection with the services specified in the declaration, and every such 
command shall be deemed to be a lawful command within the meaning and for the 
purposes of the said Acts.









</section></article> 
 
The Armed Forces (Emergency  
Duties) Act, 1947
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Validation of certain past commands.—Every 
command given, after the 30th day of September, 1946, and before the 
commencement of this Act, to any person referred to in sub-section (2) of 
section 2 by any superior officer in relation to employment upon or in 
connection with any such service as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, specify in his behalf, shall be deemed to have been a 
lawful command within the meaning and for the purposes of the Acts referred to 
in that sub-section, so, however, that no such person shall be punished by 
reason only of his not having obeyed any such command.
 
 
 
 
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>