<act><title>

the 
    Indian Tolls (Army ANd Air Force) Rules, 1942</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Indian Tolls (Army and Air Force) Rules, 
    1942.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    extend to the whole of India.  
 

  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Save as hereinafter otherwise provided in Rule 3, where exemption from the 
    payment of tolls is claimed under the Indian Tolls (Army and Air Force) Act, 
    1901 (II of 1901), in respect of any person or body of persons or any 
    property, a pass, in the Form annexed, shall be presented on the demand of 
    the person authorized to demand the tolls.  
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    
<section><number>1</number> No passes shall be required in the case of—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    Officers, soldiers and airmen of—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the Regular Forces,  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    any Irregular Corps, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    Armed Forces maintained by Part B 
    States, in uniform when on duty or on the march;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    members of the Territorial Army or of 
    the National Cadet Corps in uniform when on duty or when proceedings to or 
    returning from duty;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    officers, soldiers and airmen of the 
    Indian Reserve forces in uniform when proceeding from their place of 
    residence on being called out for service, training or muster or when 
    proceeding back to their place of residence after such service, training or 
    muster;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    authorized followers of—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the Regular Forces,  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the Territorial army or the National 
    Cadet Corps,  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    Any Irregular Corps, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    Armed Forces maintained by Part B 
    States, when they accompany and body of such Forces or Corps on the march.  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    members of the families of officers, 
    soldiers, airmen or authorized followers of—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the Regular Forces, or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    any Irregular Corps,  
 
when accompanying any body of troops on duty 
    or on the march;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    Prisoners under military or air force 
    escort in uniform;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the carriages, horses and baggage, and 
    the persons (if any) employed in driving the carriages or in carrying the 
    baggage, of any persons exempted under any of the foregoing clauses, when 
    such carriages, horses, baggage, or persons accompany the persons so 
    exempted under the circumstances mentioned in those clauses, respectively;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    carriages and horses belonging to the 
    Government or employed in the Indian military or air force service and all 
    persons in charge of or accompanying the same, when conveying any such 
    persons as herein before in this rule mentioned, or when conveying baggage 
    or stores;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    animals accompanying any body of troops 
    which are intended to be slaughtered for food or kept for any purpose 
    connected with the provisioning of such troops; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    persons in charge of any carriage, 
    horse or animal exempted under any of the foregoing clauses when 
    accompanying the same under the circumstances mentioned in those clauses 
    respectively.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No passes 
    shall be required in the case of officers of the Regular Forces, the 
    Territorial Army, the National Cadet Corps or of any Irregular Corps or of 
    any Armed Forces maintained by Part B States, when travelling on duty, 
    though not in uniform:  
 
Provided that 
    the officer so travelling shall furnish in writing to the person authorized 
    to demand toll his name, rank and a statement that he is travelling on duty.  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
Every pass shall be signed by the 
    Commanding Officer of the regiment, corps, unit, or detachment concerned, or 
    by a station staff officer.  
  

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



the 
    Indian Tolls (Army ANd Air Force) Rules, 1942
 

 
 


Form of Pass
 

 
 


[Issued under the Indian Tolls (Army and Air 
    Force), Act, 1901 II of 1901]
 


This pass issued subject to the rules on the 
    reverse in respect of the persons and property specified in the annexed 
    schedule, and exempt from the payment of tolls on the occasion of:—
 


Embarking or being shipped 
    at.............................
 


Disembarking or being landed 
    at.............................
 


proceeding from.......... to up to the 20
 


It will remain in force 
    from.............................
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



the 
    Indian Tolls (Army ANd Air Force) Rules, 1942
 

 
 



    Schedule
 
 
 Number
 Name of 
        Corps
 Remarks

 
  
  
  

 
 
 

Part 1
  
  

 
 
 

Person
  
  


 


Officers.. .. .. ..
 


Soldiers.. .. .. ..
 


Airman.. .. .. ..
 


Members of the Territorial Army
 


or the National Cadet Corps..
 


Authorised followers of Forces or
 


Corps.. .. .. ..
 


Members of families of officers,
 


soldiers, airman or authorised
 


followers.. .. .. ..
 


Persons in charge of carriages, 
 


horses, slaughter animals or
 


baggage.. .. .. ..
 


Part II
 


Property
 


Horses as defined in the Act.*
 


Carriages.. .. .. ..
 


Slaughter animals.. .. .. ..
 


Baggage.. ..            .. ..
 

 
 


* “Horse” includes a mule and any beast of 
    whatever description which is used for burden or draught for carrying 
    persons. Section 2, clause (e).
 


 
 


Place.............................
 


Date.............................
 
 
  
  
 
 


(Sd)
 


Commanding Officer or 

        Station Staff Officer or


 




 


 

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>