<act><title>THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 19711 </title> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 19711
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These Rules may be called the Insecticides Rules, 1971.
 

2[(2) They shall 
come into force on 
the 30th of October, 1971].
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires—
 
 

1[
<section><number>a</number>  “Act” means the Insecticides 
Act, 1968 (46 of 1968);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “Commercial Pest Control 
Operation” means any application or dispersion of Insecticide including 
fumigants in household or
 
              public or private premises or 
land and includes pest control operations in the fields including aerial 
applications for commercial purposes but excludes private use;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “dealer” means a person carrying 
on the business of selling insecticides, whether wholesale or retail, and 
includes an agent of a dealer;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “expiry date” means the date that 
is mentioned on the container, label or wrapper of an insecticide against the 
column ‘date of expiry’;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  “Form” means a form set out in 
the First Schedule;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  “Laboratory” means the Central 
Insecticides Laboratory;
 </section><section>
       <number>g</number>  “manufacturer” means any person 
who manufactures insecticides and includes a formulator of the insecticides;
 </section><section>
       <number>h</number>  “pests” means any insect, rodent, 
fungi, weed and other forms of plant or animal life not useful to human beings;
 </section><section>
        <number>i</number>  “Pest Control Operator” means 
any person who undertakes pest control operations and includes the person or the 
firm or the company or the organisation under whose control such a person is 
operating;
 </section><section>
        <number>j</number>  “primary package” means the 
immediate package containing the insecticides;
 </section><section>
       <number>k</number>  “principal” means the importer or 
manufacturer of insecticides, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
        <number>l</number>  “registration” includes 
provisional registration;
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  “rural area” means an area which 
falls outside the limits of any Municipal Corporation or Municipal Committee or 
a Notified Area Committee or a Cantonment;
 </section><section>
       <number>n</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule 
annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>o</number>  “secondary package” means a 
package which is neither a primary package nor a transportation package;
 </section><section>
       <number>p</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>q</number>  “testing facility” means an 
operational unit where the experimental studies are being carried out or have 
been carried out in relation to submission of data on product quality or on 
safety or on efficacy or on residues or on stability in storage of the 
insecticides for which an application for registration is made;
 </section><section>
        <number>r</number>  “transportation package” means 
the outer most package used for transportation of insecticides.]
 
 























</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 


 <article>
<number>3</number> Functions of the Board.—The 
Board shall, in addition to the functions assigned to it by the Act, carry out 
the following functions, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  advise the Central Government on 
the manufacture of insecticides under the Industries (Development and 
Regulation) Act, 1951 (65 of 1951);
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  specify the uses of 
classification of insecticides on the basis of their toxicity as well as their 
being suitable for aerial application;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  advise tolerance limits for 
insecticides, residues and on establishment of minimum intervals between the 
application of insecticides and harvest in respect of various commodities;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  specify the shelf-life of 
insecticides;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  suggest colourisation, including 
colouring matter which may be mixed with concentrates of insecticides, 
particularly those of highly toxic nature;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  carry out such other functions 
as are supplemental, incidental or consequential to any of the functions 
conferred by the Act or these rules.
 
 
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Functions of 
Registration Committee.—The 
Registration Committee shall, in addition to the functions assigned to it by the 
Act, perform the following functions, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  specify the precautions to be 
taken against poisoning through the use or handling of insecticides;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  carry out such other incidental 
or consequential matters necessary for carrying out the functions assigned to it 
under the Act or these rules.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Functions of 
Laboratory.—The 
functions of the laboratory shall be as follows:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  to analyse such samples of 
insecticides sent to it under the Act by any officer or authority authorised by 
the Central or State Governments and submission of certificates of analysis to 
the concerned authority;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  to analyse samples of materials 
for insecticide residues under the provisions of the Act;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  to carry out such investigations 
as may be necessary for the purpose of ensuring the conditions of Registration 
of Insecticides;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  to determine the efficacy and 
toxicity of insecticides;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  to carry out such other functions 
as may be entrusted to it by the Central Government or by a State Government 
with the permission of the Central Government and after consultation with the 
Board.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Manner of Registration.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> An application for registration of an insecticide under the Act shall be 
made in Form I and the said Form including the verification portion, shall be 
signed in case of an individual by the individual himself or a person duly 
authorised by him; in case of Hindu Undivided Family, by the Karta or any person 
duly authorised by him; in case of partnership firm by the managing partner; in 
case of a company, by any person duly authorised in that behalf by the Board of 
directors; and in any other case by the person in charge or responsible for the 
conduct of the business. Any change in members of Hindu Undivided Family or 
partners or the Board of Directors or the person in charge, as the case may be, 
shall be forthwith intimated to the Secretary, Central Insecticides Board and 
Registration Committee and the Licensing Officer.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> The Registration 
Committee may, if necessary direct the inspection of the ‘testing facility’ for 
establishing the authenticity of the data.]
 

2[(2) An 
application form duly filled together with a bank draft, drawn in favour of the 
Accounts Officer, Directorate of Plant Protection, Quarantine &amp; Storage, payable 
at Faridabad towards registration fee shall be sent to the Secretary, 
Registration on Committee, Directorate of Plant Protection, Quarantine &amp; 
Storage, NH-IV, Faridabad-121001, Haryana. The fee shall be payable as follows:—
 <subsubsection>
        <number>i</number>  rupees five thousand each in 
case of application for registration under section 9(3) and 9(3B) of the 
Insecticides Act, 1968;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number>  rupees two thousand five 
hundred in case of application for registration under section 9(4) of the 
Insecticides Act, 1968.]
 

1[(3) The 
registration fee payable shall be paid by a demand draft drawn on the State Bank 
of India, Faridabad, in favour of the Accounts Officer, Directorate of Plant 
Protection, Quarantine and Storage, Faridabad, Haryana.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The certificate of 
registration shall be in Form II or Form II A, as the case may be and shall be 
subject to such conditions as specified therein.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>6A</number> Issue of 
duplicate Certificate of Registration.—A fee of rupees one hundred shall be 
paid in the form of demand draft drawn on the State Bank of India, Faridabad in 
favour of the Accounts Officer, Directorate of Plant Protection, Quarantine &amp; 
Storage, Faridabad, Haryana for a duplicate copy of a Certificate of 
Registration if the original is defaced, damaged or lost.]
 
 



</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>6B</number> Addition, 
deletion or alteration on the Certificate of Registration including labels and 
leaflets.—A fee of rupees one hundred shall be paid in the form of demand 
draft drawn on the State Bank of India, Faridabad, in favour of the Accounts 
Officer, Directorate of Plant Protection, Quarantine and Storage, Faridabad, 
Haryana on each occasion for each Certificate of Registration for addition, 
deletion, alteration on the Certificate of Registration including labels and 
leaflets.]
 
 



</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal against any decision of the Registration Committee under section 9 
shall be preferred in writing 

1[in Form II B, in 
duplicate] to the Central Government in the Department of Agriculture.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The appeal shall be in 
writing and shall set out concisely and under distinct heads the grounds on 
which the appeal is preferred.
 

2[(3) Every appeal 
shall be accompanied by a demand draft of rupees one thousand towards fee and a 
copy of the decision appealed against.]
 

3[(4) The fee 
payable for preferring an appeal shall be paid by a demand draft drawn on the 
State Bank of India, New Delhi, in favour of the Pay and Accounts Officer, 
Department of Agriculture and Cooperation, New Delhi.]
 
‘Miscellaneous’—Fees, 
Fines, etc., realised under Insecticides Act, 1968”.
 
 





</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Manner of publication 
of refusal to register or cancellation of the certificate of registration.—A 
refusal to register an insecticide or a cancellation of the certificate of 
registration of an insecticide shall also be published in any two English and 
Hindi Newspapers which have circulation in a substantial part of India and in 
any of the journals published by the Department of Agriculture of the Government 
of India.
 
 
 
 
</article> 
 THE 
INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
  
 <article><number>9</number> Licences to manufacture 
insecticides.—1[
<section><number>1</number> Application for the grant 
or renewal of a licence to manufacture any insecticide shall be made in Form III 
or Form IV, as the case may be, to the licensing officer and shall be 
accompanied by a fee of rupees two thousand for every insecticide and a maximum 
of rupees twenty thousand for all insecticides for which the licence is 
applied.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> If an insecticide is 
proposed to be manufactured at more than one place, separate applications shall 
be made and separate licences shall be issued in respect of every such 
place.
 2[(3) A licence to manufacture 
insecticides shall be issued in Form V and shall be subject to the following 
conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  The licence and any certificate of renewal shall be kept on the 
approved premises and shall be produced for inspection at the request of an 
Insecticide Inspector appointed under the Act or any other officer or authority 
authorised by the licensing officer.
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  Any change in the expert staff named in the licence shall forthwith 
be reported to the licensing officer.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  If 
the licensee wants to undertake during the currency of the licence to 
manufacture for sale additional insecticides, he shall apply to the licensing 
officer for the necessary endorsement in the licence on payment of the 
prescribed fee for every category of insecticides.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  An 
application for the renewal of a licence shall be made as laid down in rule 
11.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number>  The 
licensee shall comply with the provisions of the Act and the rules made 
thereunder for the time being in force.]
        
3[(vi)  The Licensee shall obtain 
ISI Mark Certificate from Bureau of Indian Standard within three months of the 
commencement of the manufacture.
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>vii</number>  No 
Insecticides shall be sold or distributed without ISI Mark 
Certification.]
 4[(4) A licensing officer may, 
after giving reasonable opportunity of being heard, to the applicant, refuse to 
grant any licence.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4A</number> No licence to manufacture 
an insecticide shall be granted unless the licensing officer is satisfied that 
necessary plant and machinery, safety devices and first-aid facilities, 
etc., exist in the premises where the insecticide is proposed to be 
manufactured.]
 5[(5) A fee of rupees one hundred 
shall be paid for a duplicate copy of a licence issued under this rule, if the 
original is defaced, damaged or lost.]
  







</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Licences for sale, 
etc., of insecticides.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Applications for the grant or renewal of a licence to sell, stock or exhibit for 
sale or distribute insecticides shall be made in Form VI or Form VII, as the 
case may be, to the licensing officer and shall be accompanied by the fees 
specified in sub-rule (2).
 

1[(2) The fee 
payable under sub-rule (1) for grant or renewal of a licence shall be rupees 
five hundred for every insecticide for which the licence is applied. There shall 
be a separate fee for each place, if any insecticide is sold, stocked or 
exhibited for sale at more than one place:
 
Provided that the maximum 
fee payable in respect of insecticides commonly used for household purposes and 
registered as such shall be rupees seven thousand five-hundred for every place:
 
Provided further that, if 
the place of sale is established in the rural areas, the fee shall be one fifth 
of the fee specified in this rule].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any insecticide is 
proposed to be sold or stocked for sale at more than one place, separate 
applications shall be made and separate licences shall be issued in respect of 
every such place 

2[and for every 
insecticide].
 

3[(3A) Pest Control 
Operators—(i) Any person who desires to undertake pest control operations, with 
the use of Aluminium Phosphide, Methyl bromide, Ethylene dibromide or as 
notified shall apply for a licence in Form VI A with a fee of rupees one 
thousand for each place of operation. The licence granted for such operations 
shall be valid for a period of five years provided that the licence shall be 
renewed after verification or inspection at the expiry of this period on 
application in Form VI B for a further period of five years with an application 
fee of rupees one thousand.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> A licence to stock 
and use insecticides for pest control operators will be issued in Form VI C.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> Any person who 
applied for grant of licence for undertaking pest control operations should be 
at least a graduate in Agriculture or in Science with Chemistry as a subject 
with a certificate of minimum 15 days training from any of the following 
Institutions—Central Good Technological Research Institute, Mysore; Indian Grain 
Storage Institute, Hapur and National Plant Protection Training Institute, 
Hyderabad.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number> For undertaking 
fumigation, the pest control operators shall have to obtain special permission 
from the Plant Protection Adviser to the Government of India in addition to 
obtaining licence. The Plant Protection Adviser will grant such permission as 
per procedure or guidelines approved by the Registration Committee.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number> The commercial pest 
control operators, shall adhere to the prescribed guidelines or procedures as 
laid down by the Plant Protection Adviser to the Government of India in regard 
to the fumigation operations undertaken by them.]
 

4[(4) A licence to 
sell, stock or exhibit for sale or distribute insecticides shall be issued in 
Form VIII and shall be subject to the following conditions, namely:—
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  The licence shall be displayed 
in a prominent place in the part of the premises open to the public.
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  The licensee shall comply with 
the provisions of the Act, and the rules made thereunder for the time being in 
force.
 

       5[(iii)  Where the licensee 
wants to sell, stock or exhibit for sale or distribute any additional 
insecticides during the currency of the licence, he may apply to the licensing 
officer for necessary endorsement on the licence on payment of fee specified in 
sub-rule (2).]
 

       6[(iv)  if the licensing 
officer is satisfied that a particular insecticide is harmful to human beings, 
animals or environment, he may after recording reasons and referring the 
Insecticide to the Insecticide Analyst, prohibit temporarily its sale for a 
period of thirty days or till he obtains the report of the Analyst, whichever is 
earlier.]
 

7[(4A)8[(i)   
Every person shall along with his application for grant or renewal of a licence 
to undertake operation or sell, stock or exhibit for sale or distribute 
insecticides, file a certificate from the principal whom he represents or 
desires to represent in Form VI D.]
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  The certificate to be issued by 
the principal shall be addressed to the licensing officer of the concerned area 
and shall contain full particulars of the principal including their registration 
and manufacturing licence numbers, full name and address of the person proposed 
to be authorised and also the type of formulations to be used in commercial pest 
control operations, sold, stocked or exhibited for sale or distribution.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  In order to verify the 
genuineness or otherwise of the certificate, the principal shall send to the 
licensing officer of the State where he intends to sell his products an adequate 
number of copies of the specimen signature or the specimen signatures of the 
persons authorised in writing to issue the principal’s certificate.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  In case of suspension, 
revocation or cancellation of the certificate, the principal shall forthwith 
intimate the licensing officer having jurisdiction.]
 

9[(5) A licensing 
officer may, after giving a reasonable opportunity of being heard to the 
applicant, refuse to grant any licence.]
 

10[(6) A fee of 
rupees one hundred shall be payable for a duplicate copy of licence issued under 
this rule if the original is defaced, damaged or lost.]]
 
 












</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10A</number> 
Segregation and disposal of date-expired pesticides.—
<section><number>a</number> Immediately after 
the date of expiry all such stocks after being segregated and stamped ‘not for 
sale’ or ‘not for use’ or ‘not for manufacture’, as the case may be, shall be 
kept by the licensee in a separate place specially demarcated for the purpose 
with a declaration ‘date-expired insecticides’ to be exhibited on the 
conspicuous part of the place.
 

2[(b) All such 
stocks then shall be disposed of in an environment friendly manner as may be 
specified from time to time by the Central Government in consultation with the 
Central Insecticides Board and shall not be used for remanufacture.]]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10B</number> Special 
provision with regard to sulphur.—In regard to insecticide and its 
formulations, all licensees shall:
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  observe all precautions to 
prevent its theft;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  report any such theft to the 
nearest police authorities promptly; and
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  maintain a separate register 
showing names and addresses of all the persons to whom it has been sold or 
distributed and the quantities to be sold or distributed.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 


 <article>

1[<number>10C</number> 
Prohibition against sale or storage of insecticides in certain places.—No 
person shall manufacture, store or expose for sale or permit the sale or storage 
of any insecticide in the same building where any articles consumable by human 
beings or animals are manufactured, stored or exposed for sale.
 
Explanation.—Nothing 
contained in this rule will apply to the retail sales of household insecticides 
from the building wherefrom other article consumable by human beings or animals 
are usually sold provided such household insecticides have been registered as 
such and are packed and labelled in accordance with these rules.]
 
 



</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Duration of licences.—1[
<section><number>a</number> 
Any licence issued or renewed under this chapter shall, unless sooner suspended 
or cancelled, be in force for a period of two calendar years:
 
Provided that the licence 
to manufacture insecticides, if any, issued on the basis of provisional 
registration granted under sub-section (3B) of section 9, shall expire on the 
date of expiry of the provisional registration:
 
Provided further that the 
licence granted by endorsement on the main licence under clause (iii) of 
sub-rule (8) or rule 9 or under clause (iii) of sub-rule (4) of Rule 10 under 
sub-rule (3) of Rule 10A shall expire or be renewable along with the main 
licence.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> An application for the 
renewal of a licence shall be made before its expiry and if such an application 
is made after the date of expiry but within three months from such date, a late 
fee of—
 

         2[(i)  rupees five hundred 
for the first month or part thereof, rupees one thousand for the second month or 
part thereof and rupees one thousand and five-hundred for the third month or 
part thereof, in case of licence to manufacture insecticides or to carry pest 
control operations;
 <subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  rupees one hundred for the 
first month or part thereof, rupees two hundred for the second month or part 
thereof and rupees three hundred for the third-month or part thereof, in case of 
any other licence shall be paid alongwith the application for renewal:
 
Provided that where the 
main pest control operation unit or the place of sale is located in the rural 
areas, the late fee shall be one-fifth of the said late fee:
 
Provided further that in 
case of death or disability or the licensee, the Licensing Officer may after 
recording reasons in writing, exempt the applicant from payment of the late 
fee.]
 
Explanation.—(1) 
Where an application for renewal is made before the expiry of the licence and 
the order regarding refusal or renewal is passed after the expiry of the licence, 
the applicant shall be deemed to have been carrying on his business in 
accordance with the expired licence till the date of communication of the final 
order on that application.
 <subsubsection>
<number>2</number> Where an application 
for renewal is made after the expiry of the licence with late fee, the applicant 
shall be deemed to have been carrying on his business in accordance with the 
expired licence (from the date of expiry) till the date of communication of the 
final order on that application.]
 

3[(c) The licence 
shall continue to be in force until it is renewed or revoked. Where an appeal is 
preferred under section 15, the licence shall continue to be revoked until 
disposal of appeal or as ordered by the appellate authority pending disposal of 
the appeal.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number> A licence officer may, 
after giving an opportunity of being heard, refuse to renew the licence 

4[for reasons to be 
recorded in writing].
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Conditions of licence.—1[
<section><number>a</number>] 
Subject to conditions laid down in sub-rule (3) of rule 9 and sub-rule (4) of 
rule 10, a licence shall not be granted to any person under this Chapter unless 
the licensing officer is satisfied that the premises in respect of which licence 
is to be granted are adequate and equipped with proper storage accommodation for 
avoiding any hazards for preserving the properties of insecticides in respect of 
which the licence is granted.]
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> In granting a licence, 
the licensing officer shall have regard, among other things, to:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  The number of licences granted 
in the locality during any year; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  the occupation, trade or 
business carried on by the applicant.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Varying or amending a 
licence.—The 
licensing officer may either on an application made by the licensee or if he is 
satisfied that the conditions under which a licence has been granted under this 
Chapter have been changed that it is necessary so to do, vary or amend a licence,


1[after satisfying 
himself that the Registration Committee has amended the registration certificate 
and] after giving an opportunity of being heard to the person holding the 
licence.
 
 



</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Transfer of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The holder of a licence may, at any time, before the expiry of the licence, 
apply for permission to transfer the licence to any other person.
 

1[(2) The 
application under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a fee of rupees one 
hundred.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensing officer 
may, after such inquiry as he thinks fit, accord permission to transfer the 
licence and on such permission being given, an endorsement to that effect shall 
be made in the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the permission to 
transfer a licence is refused, the fee paid therefore shall be refunded to the 
applicant.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>15</number> Issuing 
cash or credit memo and maintenance of register, books of accounts and records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All sales of insecticides shall be made by a bill or cash memo or credit memo in 
the form prescribed under any law.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All sales of 
insecticides made to a licensed manufacturer (formulator or packer), stockist, 
distributor, dealer, retailer or to a bulk consumer shall be entered insecticide 
wise, in a register in Form XIII and a Statewise monthly return of all sales to 
actual consumers shall be sent to the licensing officer, in Form XIV within 15 
days from the close of the relevant month.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every importer or 
manufacturer of insecticide shall maintain a stock register in Form XV for 
technical grade insecticides and in Form XVI for formulated insecticides.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every manufacturer or 
importer shall maintain a book of accounts and register of such sale, 
manufacture or import of technical Grade Insecticide and formulated Insecticide 
and submit the monthly statement or return to the licensing officer, in Form XVA 
and XVIA respectively within 15 days from the closing of the month.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Without prejudice to 
the provisions of sub-rules (1) and (4), the Central Government or the State 
Government or any other person authorised by the Central Government or the State 
Government, as the case may be, may, by notice in writing require any importer 
or manufacturer or any other person dealing in insecticides to furnish within 
the time specified in the notice, such registers, books of accounts, records, 
documents or other such information with respect to any insecticides or any 
batch thereof, including the particulars of all persons to whom it has been sold 
or distributed, as it may consider necessary.]
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Prohibition of sale or 
distribution unless packed and labelled.—No 
person shall stock or exhibit for sale or distribute 

1[or cause to be 
transported] any insecticide unless it is packed and labelled in accordance with 
the provisions of these rules.
 
 



</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17</number> Packing of 
insecticides.—
<section><number>1</number> Every package containing the insecticides shall be of a 
type approved by the Registration Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before putting any 
insecticide into the primary package, every batch thereof shall be analysed as 
per the relevant specifications of the manufacture thereof, in accordance with 
the approved methods of analysis and the result of such an analysis shall be 
recorded in the register maintained for the purpose. If any insecticide is put 
in the package it shall be presumed that it is fit and ready for sale, 
distribution or use for which it is intended, notwithstanding the fact any 
further steps are still required to be taken to make it marketable.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Leaflet to be 
contained in a package.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
The packing of every insecticide shall include a leaflet containing the 
following details, namely;—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the plant disease, insects and 
noxious animals or weeds for which the insecticide is to be applied, the 
adequate direction concerning the manner in which the insecticide is to be used 
at the time of application;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  particulars regarding chemicals 
harmful to human being, animals and wild life, warning and cautionary statements 
including the symptoms of poisoning, suitable and adequate safety measures and 
emergency first-aid treatment where necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  cautions regarding storage and 
application of insecticides with suitable warning relating to inflammable, 
explosive or other substance harmful to the skin;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  instructions concerning the 
decontamination or safe disposal of used containers;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  a statement showing the antidote 
for the poison shall be included in the leaflet and the label;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  if the insecticide is irritating 
to the skin, nose, throat or eyes, a statement shall be included to the effect.
 

        2[(g)  common name of the 
insecticide as adopted by the International Standards Organisation and where 
such a name has not yet been adopted such other name as may be approved by the 
Registration Committee;]
 

2[(2) Two copies of 
the leaflets duly approved by the Registration Committee and signed by the 
Secretary, Registration Committee, shall be returned to the manufacturer and one 
copy thereof the State licensing officer.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Manner of labelling.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The following particulars shall be either printed or written in indelible 
ink on the label of the innermost container of any insecticide and on the 
outmost covering in which the container is packed:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  Name of the manufacturer (if the 
manufacturer is not the person in whose name the insecticide is registered under 
the Act, the relationship between the person in whose name the insecticide has 
been registered and the person who manufacturers, packs or distributes or sells 
shall be stated).
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  Name of the insecticide. (Brand 
name or trade mark under which the insecticide is sold).
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  Registration number of the 
insecticide.
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  Kind and name of active and 
other ingredients and percentage of each (common name accepted by the 
International Standards Organisation or the Indian Standards Institution of each 
of the ingredients shall be given and if no common name exists, the correct 
chemical name which conforms most closely with the generally accepted rules of 
chemical nomenclature shall be given.)
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>v</number>  Net content of volume. (The net 
content shall be exclusive of wrapper or other material. The correct statement 
of the net content to terms of weight, measure, number of units of activity, as 
the case may be, shall be given. The weight and volume shall be expressed in the 
metric system).
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vi</number>  Batch number.
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>vii</number>  Expiry date, i.e. upto 
the date insecticide shall retain its efficiency and safety.
 </subsection><subsection>
     <number>viii</number>  Antidote statement.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The label shall be so 
affixed to the container that it cannot be ordinarily removed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The label shall 
contain in a prominent place and occupying not less than one sixteenth of the 
total area of the face of the label, a square, set at an angle of 450 (diamond 
shape). The dimension of the said square shall depend on the size of the package 
on which the label is to be affixed. The said square shall be divided into two 
equal triangles, the upper portion shall contain the symbol and signal word 
specified in sub-rule (4) and the lower portion shall contain the colour 
specified in sub-rule (5).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The upper portion of 
the square, referred to in sub-rule (93) shall contain the following symbols and 
warning statements:—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  insecticides belonging to 
Category I (extremely toxic) shall contain the symbol of a skull and cross-bones 
and the word “POISON” printed in red;
 
              the following warning 
statements shall also appear on the label at appropriate place, outside the 
triangle:—
 <subsubsection>
            <number>a</number>  “KEEP OUT OF THE REACH OF 
CHILDREN”,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>b</number>  “IF SWALLOWED OR IF SYMPTOMS 
OF POISONING OCCUR, CALL PHYSICIAN IMMEDIATELY”;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  insecticides in Category II 
(highly toxic) shall bear the word “POISON” printed in red and the statement 
“KEEP OUT OF THE REACH OF CHILDREN”, shall also appear on the label at suitable 
place outside the triangle;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iii</number>  insecticides in Category III 
(Moderately toxic) shall bear the word “DANGER” and the statement “KEEP OUT OF 
REACH OF CHILDREN”; shall also appear on the label at suitable place outside the 
triangle;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  insecticides in Category IV 
(Slightly toxic) shall bear the word “CAUTION”.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The lower portion of 
the square referred to in sub-rule (94) shall contain the colour specified in 
column (4) of the Table below, depending on the classification of the 
insecticides specified in the corresponding entry in column (1) of the said 
Table.
 
TABLE
 
 
Classification 
  of            Medium lethal dose            Medium lethal dose         Colour 
  of identification 

 
the 
insecticides              by the oral route             by the dermal route 
           band on the label.
 

                                  acute toxicity LD 50          dermal toxicity 
LD 50
 

                                   mg/kg body weight           mg/kg. body 
weight 
 

                                     of test animals.                 of test 
animals.
 
 

   1                                            
  2                                     3                                     4
 </section><section>
<number>1</number> 
Extremely toxic                  1—50                              
1—200                           Bright red
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
Highly toxic                       51-500                           
201-2000                       Bright yellow
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
Moderately toxic             501—5000                      
2001—20000                      Bright blue
 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
  Slightly toxic               More than 5000                More than 
  20000                  Bright green
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In addition to the 
precautions to be undertaken under sub-rules (3), (4) and (5), the label to be 
affixed in the package containing insecticides which are highly inflammable 
shall indicate that it is inflammable or that the insecticides should be kept 
away from heat or open flame and the like.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The label and leaflets 
to be affixed or attached to the package containing insecticides shall be 
printed in Hindi, English and in one or two regional languages in use in the 
areas where the said packages are likely to be stocked, sold or distributed.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Labelling of 
insecticides must not bear any unwarranted claims for the safety of the product 
or its ingredients. This includes statements such as ‘SAFE’, ‘NON-POISONOUS’, 
‘NON-INJURIOUS’ or ‘HARMLESS’ with or without such qualified phrase as “when 
used as directed”.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Prohibition against 
altering inscription, etc. on containers, labels or wrappers of 
insecticides.—No 
person shall alter, obliterate or deface any inscription or make made or 
recorded by the manufacturer on the container, label or wrapper of any 
insecticide:
 
Provided that nothing in 
this rule shall apply to any alteration of any inscription or mark made on the 
container, label or wrapper of any insecticide at the instance, direction or 
permission of the Registration Committee.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Qualifications of 
Insecticide Analyst.—A 
person shall be eligible for appointment as an Insecticide Analyst under the Act 
only if he possesses the following qualification, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  a graduate in Agriculture or a 
graduate in Science with Chemistry as a special subject; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  adequate training in analysing 
insecticides in a recognised Laboratory.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Powers of Insecticide 
Analyst.—The 
Insecticide Analyst shall have the power to call for such information or 
particulars or do anything as may be necessary for the proper examination of the 
samples sent to him either from the Insecticide Inspector or the person from 
whom the sample was obtained.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Duties of Insecticide 
Analyst.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Insecticide Analyst shall analyse or cause to be analysed or test or cause 
to be tested such samples of Insecticides as may be sent to him by the 
Insecticide Inspector under the provisions of the Act and shall finish reports 
or results of such test or analysis.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An Insecticide Analyst 
shall, from time to time, forward to the State Government reports giving the 
result of analytical work and investigation with a view to their publication at 
the discretion of the Government.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Procedure on receipt 
of sample.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of a package from an Insecticide Inspector containing a sample for 
test or analysis, the Insecticide Analyst shall compare the seals of the packet 
with the specimen impression received separately and shall note the condition of 
the seals on the packet.
 

1[(2) In making the 
test or analysis of insecticides, it shall be sufficient if the Insecticides 
Analyst follows that specifications and the months of examination of samples as 
approved by the Registration Committee.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After the test or 
analysis has been carried out under sub-rule (2), the Insecticide Analyst shall 
forthwith supply to the Insecticide Inspector a report in triplicate in Form IX 
of the result of test or analysis.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Fees payable for 
testing or analysis.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
The fees payable for testing or analysing insecticides under sub-section (5) of 
section 24 of the Act shall be as specified in the Second Schedule.]
 

2[(2) The fee 
payable for testing or analysing samples received from the Insecticides 
Inspector shall also be as specified in the Second Schedule:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government may, after taking into consideration the genuine difficulties of any 
particular State Government, exempt the payment of the fee for such period as it 
may consider reasonable.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Qualifications of 
Insecticide Inspector.—A 
person shall be eligible for appointment as an Insecticide Inspector under the 
Act only if he possesses the following qualifications, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  graduate in Agriculture, or 
graduate in Science with Chemistry as one of the subjects;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  adequate field experience.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Duties of Insecticide 
Inspector.—The 
Insecticide Inspector shall have the following duties, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>1</number>  to inspect not less than three 
times in a year all establishments selling insecticides within the areas of his 
jurisdiction;
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  to satisfy himself that the 
conditions of licence are being complied with;
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  to procure and send for test and 
analysis, samples of insecticide which he has reason to suspect are being sold, 
stocked or accepted for sale in contravention of the provisions of the Act or 
rules made thereunder;
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  to investigate any complaint in 
writing which may be made to him;
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number>  to institute prosecutions in 
respect of breaches of the Act and the rules made thereunder;
 </section><section>
       <number>6</number>  to maintain a record of all 
inspections made and action taken by him in the performance of his duties 
including the taking of samples and the seizure of stocks and to submit copies 
of such record to the licensing officer;
 </section><section>
       <number>7</number>  to make such inquiries and 
inspections as may be necessary to detect the sale and use of insecticides in 
contravention of the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE 
INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
  
 <article><number>28</number> Duties of Inspectors 
specially authorised to inspect manufacture of insecticides.—It shall be the duty of an 
Inspector authorised to inspect the manufacture of insecticides—
 <section>       <number>1</number>  to 
inspect not less than twice a year all premises licensed for the manufacture of 
insecticides within the area of his jurisdiction and to satisfy himself that the 
conditions of the licence and the provisions of the Act or the rule made 
thereunder are being observed;
 </section><section>       <number>2</number>  to 
send forthwith to the licensing officer after each inspection, a detailed report 
indicating the conditions of the licence and the provisions of the Act or rules 
made thereunder which are being observed and the conditions and provisions, if 
any, which are not being observed;
 </section><section>       <number>3</number>  to 
draw samples of insecticides manufactured on the premises and send them for test 
or analysis in accordance with these rules;
 </section><section>       <number>4</number>  to 
report to the Government all occurrences of poisoning.
  </section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Prohibition of 
disclosure of information.—Except 
for the purpose of official business or when required by a court of law, an 
Insecticide Inspector shall not disclose to any person any information acquired 
by him in the performance of his official duties.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Form of order not to 
dispose of stock.—An 
order by the Insecticide Inspector requiring a person not to dispose of any 
stock in his possession shall be in Form X.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Prohibition of sale.—No 
person in possession of an insecticide in respect of which an Insecticide 
Inspector has made an order under rule 30 shall, in contravention of that order, 
sell or otherwise dispose of any stock of such insecticide.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Form of receipt for 
seized insecticide.—A 
receipt by an Insecticide Inspector for the stock of any insecticide seized 
shall be in Form XI.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Form of intimation for 
purpose of taking samples.—Where 
an Inspector takes a sample of an insecticide for the purpose of test or 
analysis, he shall intimate such purpose in writing in Form XII to the person 
from whom he takes it.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Despatch of samples 
for test or analysis.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Samples for test or analysis under the Act shall be sent by registered post or 
by hand in a sealed packet together with a memorandum in Form XII in an outer 
cover addressed to the Insecticide Analyst.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The packet as well as 
the outer cover shall be marked with a distinct mark.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A copy of the 
memorandum in Form XIII together with a specimen, impression of the seals of the 
Inspector and of the seals, if any, of the person from whom he takes such 
samples, shall be sent separately by registered post or by hand to the 
Insecticide Analyst.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> 

1[Manner of 
packing, storage while transporting].—
<section><number>1</number> 
Packages containing insecticides offered for transport by rail, shall be packed 
in accordance with the conditions specified in the Red Tariff, issued by the 
Ministry of Railways.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No insecticide shall 
be transported or stored in such a way as to come into direct contact with 
foodstuffs or animal feeds.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No foodstuffs or 
animal feeds which got mixed up with insecticide as a result of any damage to 
the packages containing insecticides during transport or storage shall be 
released to the consignees unless it has been examined for possible 
contamination by competent authorities, as may be notified by the State 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any insecticide is 
found to have leaked out in transport or storage, it shall be the responsibility 
of the transport agency or the storage owner to take such measures urgently to 
prevent poisoning and pollution of soil or water, if any.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Conditions to be 
specified for storage of insecticides.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The packages containing insecticides shall be stored in separate rooms or 
premises, away from the rooms or premises used for storing other articles or 
shall be kept in separate almirahs under lock and keys depending upon the 
quantity and nature of the insecticides.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The rooms or premises 
meant for storing insecticides shall be well-built, dry, well lit and ventilated 
and of sufficient dimension.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 


 <article>

1[<number>37</number> Medical 
Examination.—
<section><number>1</number> All persons, who are engaged in the work of handling, 
dealing or otherwise coming in contact with the insecticides during 
manufacture/formulation of insecticides or being engaged in spraying during 
operation shall be examined medically before their employment, and at least 
quarterly in the case of those engaged in manufacturing/formulation units, 
yearly in other cases including operators while in service by a qualified doctor 
who is aware of risks to which such persons are exposed. Particulars of all such 
persons, including the particulars of their medical examination, shall be 
entered in a register in Form XVII. Where the insecticide in question is an 
organo-phosphorous compound or a carbamate compound, the blood cholinesterage 
level shall be measured at least once a month of all persons working in the 
manufacturing units. The blood residue estimation shall be done once in a year 
in the case of persons working with organo chlorine group of insecticides in a 
manufacturing/formulation unit. In the case of spraying people working with the 
pest control operators, the estimation of cholinesterage level (if working with 
organo phosphorous or carbamate compounds) and blood residue (if working with 
organo chlorine group) shall be conducted as and when advised by the doctor as 
part of the general medical test.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person showing 
symptoms of poisoning shall be immediately examined and given proper treatment.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> First-aid measures.—In 
all cases of poisoning, first-aid treatment shall always be given before the 
physician is called. The Indian Standards Guide for handling cases of pesticide 
poisoning—Part I, First Aid Measures [I.S. 4015 (Part I)—1967] and Part- II 
symptoms, diagnosis and treatment [I.S. 4015 (Part II)—1967] shall be consulted 
for such first-aid treatment in addition to any other book on the subject. The 
workers also should be educated regarding the effects of poisoning and the 
first-aid treatment to be given.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Protective clothing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Persons handling insecticides during its manufacture, formulation, transport, 
distribution or application shall be adequately protected with appropriate 
clothing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The protective 
clothing shall be used wherever necessary, in conjunction with respiratory 
devices as laid down in rule 40.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The protective 
clothing shall be made of materials which prevent or resist the penetration of 
any form of insecticide formulations. The materials shall also be washable so 
that the toxic elements may be removed after each use.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A complete suit of 
protective clothing shall consist of the following dresses, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  protective outer 
garment/overalls/hood/hat;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  rubber gloves or such other 
protective gloves extending half-way upto the forearm, made of materials 
impermeable to liquids;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  dust-proof goggles;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  boots.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Respiratory devices.—For 
preventing inhalation of toxic dusts, vapours or gases, the workers shall use 
any of the following types of respirators or gas-masks suitable for the purpose, 
namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  Chemical-Cartridge respirator;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  Supplied-Air respirator;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  Demand flow type respirator;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  Full-face or half-face gas masks 
with canister.
 
In no case shall the 
concentrates of insecticides in the air where the insecticides are mixed exceed 
the maximum permissible values.
 
 
</section></article> 
 THE 
INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
  
 <article><number>41</number> Manufacturers, etc. 
to keep sufficient quantities of antidotes and first-aid 
medicines.—The 
manufacturers and distributors of insecticides and persons who undertake to 
spray insecticide on a commercial basis (hereafter in these rules referred to as 
operators) shall keep sufficient stocks of such first-aid tools, equipment, 
antidotes, injections and medicines as operators shall keep sufficient stocks of 
such first-aid tools, equipment, antidotes, injections and medicines as may be 
required to treat poisoning cases arising from inhalation, skin contamination, 
eye contamination and swallowing.
  </article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Training of workers.—The 
manufacturers and distributors of insecticides and operators shall arrange for 
suitable training in observing safety precautions and handling safety equipment 
provided to them.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Aerial spraying 
operations.—The 
aerial application of insecticides shall be subject to the following provisions, 
namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  marking of the area shall be 
responsibility of the operators;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the operators shall use only 
approved insecticides and their formulations at approved concentration and 
height;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  washing, decontamination and 
first-aid facilities shall be provided by the operators;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  all aerial operations shall be 
notified to the public not less than twenty four hours in advance through 
competent authorities;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  animals and persons not connected 
with the operations shall be prevented from entering such areas for a specified 
period; and
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  the pilots shall undergo 
specialised training including clinical effects of the insecticides.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Disposal of used 
packages, surplus materials and washings of insecticides.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the manufacturers, formulators of insecticides and 
operators to dispose packages or surplus material and washings in a safe manner 
so as to prevent environmental or water pollution.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The used packages 
shall not be left outside to prevent their re-use.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The packages shall be 
broken and hurried away from habitation.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>45</number>Places at which the insecticides may be imported. </title>—No 
insecticides shall be imported into India except through one of the following 
places, namely— 
 Ferozepore Cantonment and Amritsar railway stations in respect of 
insecticides imported by rail across the frontier with West Pakistan . 
 Ranaghat, Bongaon and Mahiassan railway stations in respect of insecticides 
imported by rail across the frontier with East Pakistan . 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Chennai, Kandla, Kochi , Kolkata, Mormugao, Mumbai and Tuticorin 
(Ennor)—in respect of insecticides imported by sea into India ]. 
 Madras , Calcutta , Bombay , Delhi and Ahmedabad—in respect of insecticides 
imported by air into India .



</article> 
 
THE INSECTICIDES RULES, 1971
 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Travelling and other 
allowances payable to the members of the Board, etc.—The 
members of the Board, Registration Committee and any other committee appointed 
by the Board shall be entitled to such travelling and other allowances for 
attending meetings of the Board, Registration Committee or other committee, as 
the case may be, as are for the time being admissible to Grade I officers of the 
Central Government.
  
</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 128(E), dated 26th February, 2009 , for 
“Chennai, Kandla, Kochi , Kolkata, Mumbai and Tulicorn (Ennor)—in respect of 
insecticides imported by sea into India ” (w.e.f. 26-2-2009 ). Earlier these 
words were substituted by G.S.R. 692(E), dated 7th November, 2006 (w.e.f. 
7-11-2006 ).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>