<act><title>


THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 19721</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Payment of Gratuity (Central) Rules, 1972.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules shall come 
into force on the 16th September, 1972.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>
<number>a</number> “Act” means the 
Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972 (39 of 1972);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> “Appellate authority” 
means the Central Government or the authority specified by the Central 
Government under sub-section (7) of section 7;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> “Form” means a form 
appended  to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> “nomination”  means 
nomination made under section 6;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> “Section” means a 
section of the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Notice of opening, 
change or closure of the establishment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Within thirty days of the rules becoming applicable to an establishment, a 
notice in Form ‘A’ shall be submitted by the employer to the controlling 
authority of the area.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A notice in Form ‘B’ 
shall be submitted by the employer to the controlling authority of the area 
within thirty days of any change in the name, address, employer or nature of 
business.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an employer 
intends to close down the business he shall submit a notice in Form ‘C’ to the 
controlling authority of the area at least sixty days before the intended 
closure.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Display of notice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer shall display conspicuously a notice at or near the main entrance 
of the establishment in bold letters in English and in a language understood by 
the majority of the employees specifying the name of officer with designation 
authorised by the employer to receive on his behalf notices under the Act or the 
rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A fresh notice shall 
be displayed immediately after the notice referred to in sub-rule (1) becomes 
illegible or requires a change.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
*<number>5</number> Form of notice 
under proviso to section (2) (h) (ii).—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notice under the proviso  to sub-clause (ii) of clause (h) of section 2 shall 
be in Form ‘D’ and sent in triplicate by the employee to the employer, who 
shall, after recording its receipt on one copy thereof, return the copy to the 
employee and send the second copy to the controlling authority of the area.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An employee may 
withdraw the notice referred to in sub-rule (1) by giving another notice in 
triplicate in Form ‘E’ to the employer, who shall follow the same procedure as 
in sub-rule (1).
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A nomination shall be in Form ‘F’ and submitted in duplicate by personal service 
by the employee, after taking proper receipt or by sending through registered 
post acknowledgement due to the employer,
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  in the case of an 
employee who is already in employment for a year or more on the date of 
commencement of these rules, ordinarily, within ninety days from such date, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> in the case of an 
employee who completes one year of service after the date of commencement of 
these rules, ordinarily within thirty days of the completion of one year of 
service:
 
Provided that nomination 
in Form ‘F’ shall be accepted by the employer after the specified period, if 
filed with reasonable grounds for delay, and no nomination so accepted shall be 
invalid merely because it was filed after the specified period.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Within thirty days of 
the receipt of nomination in Form ‘F’ under sub-rule (1), the employer shall get 
the service particulars of the employee, as mentioned in the form of nomination, 
verified with reference to the records of the establishment and return to the 
employee, after obtaining a receipt thereof, the duplicate copy of the 
nomination in Form ‘F’ duly attested  either by the employer or an officer 
authorised in this behalf by him, as a token of recording of the nomination by 
the employer and the other copy of the nomination shall be recorded.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An employee who has no 
family at the time of making a nomination shall, within ninety days of acquiring 
a family submit in the manner specified in sub-rule (1), a fresh nomination, as 
required under sub-section (4) of section 6, duplicate in Form ‘G’ to the 
employer and thereafter the provisions of sub-rule (2) shall apply mutatis 
mutandis as if it was made under sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A notice of 
modification of a nomination, including cases where a nominee predeceases an 
employee, shall be submitted in duplicate in Form ‘H’ to the employer in the 
manner specified in sub-rule (1), and thereafter the provisions of sub-rule (2) 
shall apply mutatis mutandis.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A nomination or a 
fresh nomination or a notice of modification of nomination shall be signed by 
the employee or, if illiterate, shall bear his thumb impression, in the presence 
of two witnesses, who shall also sign a declaration to that effect in the 
nomination, fresh nomination or notice of modification of nomination, as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A nomination, fresh 
nomination or notice of modification of nomination shall take effect from the 
date of receipt thereof by the employer.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Application for 
gratuity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An employee who is eligible for payment of gratuity under the Act, or any person 
authorised, in writing, to act on his behalf, shall apply, ordinarily within 
thirty days from the date the gratuity became payable, in Form ‘I’ to the 
employer:
 
Provided that where the 
date of superannuation or retirement of an employee is known, the employee may 
apply to the employer before thirty days of the date of superannuation or 
retirement.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A nominee  of an 
employee who is eligible for payment of gratuity under the second proviso to 
sub-section (1) of section 4 shall apply, ordinarily within thirty days from the 
date of gratuity became payable to him, in Form ‘J’ to the employer:
 
Provided that an 
application in plain paper with relevant particulars shall also be accepted. 
The  employer may obtain such other particulars as may be deemed necessary by 
him.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A legal heir of an 
employee who is eligible for payment of gratuity under the second proviso to 
sub-section (1) of section 4 shall apply, ordinarily within one year from the 
date of gratuity became payable to him, in Form ‘K’ to the employer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where gratuity becomes 
payable under the Act before the commencement of these rules, the periods of 
limitation specified in sub-rules (1), (2) and (3) shall be deemed to be 
operative from the date of such commencement.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An application for 
payment of gratuity filed after the expiry of the periods specified in this rule 
shall also be entertained by the employer, if  the applicant adduces sufficient 
cause for the delay in preferring his claim, and no claim for gratuity under the 
Act shall be invalid merely because the claimant failed to present his 
application within the specified period. Any dispute  in this regard shall be 
referred to the controlling authority for his decision.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> An application under 
this rule shall be presented to the employer either by personal service or by 
registered post acknowledgement due.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Notice for payment 
of gratuity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Within fifteen days of the receipt of an application under rule 7 for payment of 
gratuity, the employer shall—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  if the claim is found 
admissible on verification, issue a notice in Form ‘L’ to the applicant 
employee, nominee or legal heir, as the case may be, specifying the amount of 
gratuity payable and fixing a date, not being later than the thirtieth day after 
the date of receipt of the application, for payment thereof, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> if the claim for 
gratuity is not found admissible, issue a notice in Form ‘M’ to the applicant 
employee, nominee or legal heir, as the case may be, specifying the reasons why 
the claim for gratuity is not considered admissible.
 
In either case a copy of 
the notice shall be endorsed to the controlling authority.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In case payment of 
gratuity is due to be made in the employer’s office, the date fixed for the 
purpose in the notice in Form ‘L’ under clause (i) of sub-rule (1) shall be 
refixed by the employer, if a written application in this behalf is made by the 
payee explaining why it is not possible for him to be present in person on the 
date specified.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the claimant for 
gratuity is a nominee or a legal heir, the employer may ask for such witness or 
evidence as may be deemed relevant for establishing his identity or 
maintainability of his claim, as the case may be. In that case, the time limit 
specified for issuance of notices under sub-rule (1) shall be operative with 
effect from the date such witness or evidence, as the case may be, called for by 
the employer is furnished to the employer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A notice in Form ‘L’ 
or Form ‘M’ shall be served on the applicant either by personal service after 
taking receipt or by registered post with acknowledgement due.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A notice under 
sub-section (2) of section 7 shall be in Form ‘L’.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Mode of payment of 
gratuity.—The 
gratuity payable under the Act shall be paid in cash or, if so desired by the 
payee, in Demand Draft or bank cheque to the eligible employee, nominee or legal 
heir, as the case may be:
 
Provided that in case the 
eligible employee, nominee or legal heir, as the case may be, so desires and the 
amount of gratuity payable is less than one thousand rupees, payment may be made 
by postal money order after deducting the postal money order commission therefor 
from the amount payable:
 
Provided further that 
intimation about the details of payment shall also be given by the employer to 
the controlling authority of the area:
 

1[Provided further 
that in the case of nominee, or an heir, who is minor, the controlling authority 
shall invest the gratuity amount deposited with him for the benefit of such 
minor in term deposit with the State Bank of India or any of its subsidiaries or 
any Nationalised Bank.
 
Explanation.—”Nationalised 
Bank” means a corresponding new bank specified in the First Schedule to the 
Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 
1970) or a corresponding new bank specified in the First Schedule of the Banking 
Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980).]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Application to 
controlling authority for direction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If an employer—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  refuses to accept a 
nomination or to entertain an application sought to be filed under rule 7, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> issues a notice under 
sub-rule (1) of rule 8 either specifying an amount of gratuity which is 
considered by the applicant less than what is payable or rejecting eligibility 
to payment of gratuity, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> having received an 
application under rule 7 fails to issue any notice as required under rule 8 
within the time specified therein,
 
the claimant employee, 
nominee or legal heir, as the case may be, may, within ninety days of the 
occurrence of the cause for the application, apply in Form ‘N’ to the 
controlling authority for issuing a direction under sub-section (4) of section 7 
with as many extra copies as are the opposite party:
 
Provided that the 
controlling authority may accept any application under this sub-rule, on 
sufficient cause being shown by the applicant, after the expiry of the specified 
period.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Application under 
sub-rule (1) and other documents relevant to such an application shall be 
presented in person to the controlling authority or shall be sent by registered 
post acknowledgement due.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Procedure for 
dealing with application for direction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of an application under rule 10 the controlling authority shall, by 
issuing a notice in Form ‘O’, call upon the applicant as well as the employer to 
appear before him on a specified date, time and place, either by himself or 
through his authorised representative together with all relevant documents and 
witnesses, if any.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person desiring to 
act on behalf of an employer or employee, nominee or legal heir, as the cases 
may be, shall present to the controlling authority a letter of authority from 
the employer or the person concerned, as the case may be, on whose behalf he 
seeks to act together with a written statement explaining his interest in the 
matter and praying for permission so to act. The controlling authority shall 
record thereon an order either according his approval or specifying, in the case 
of refusal to grant the permission prayed for, the reasons for the refusal.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A party appearing by 
an authorised representative shall be bound by the acts of the representative.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> After completion of 
hearing on the date fixed under sub-rule (1), or after such further evidence, 
examination of documents, witnesses, hearing and enquiry, as may be deemed 
necessary, the controlling authority shall record his finding as to whether any 
amount is payable to the applicant under the Act. A copy of the finding shall be 
given to each of the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the employer 
concerned fails to appear on the specified date of hearing after due service of 
notice without sufficient cause, the controlling authority may proceed to hear 
and determine the application ex parte. If the applicant fails to appear 
on the specified date of hearing without sufficient cause, the controlling 
authority may dismiss the application:
 
Provided that an order 
under this sub-rule may, on good cause being shown within thirty days of the 
said order, be reviewed and the application re-heard after giving not less than 
fourteen days’ notice to the opposite party of the date fixed for rehearing of 
the application.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Place and time of 
hearing.—The 
sittings of the controlling authority shall be held at such times and at such 
places as he may fix and he shall inform the parties of the same in such manner 
as he thinks fit.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Administration of 
oath.—The 
controlling authority may authorise a clerk of his office to administer oaths 
for the purpose of making affidavits.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Summoning and 
attendance of witnesses.—The 
controlling authority may, at any stage of the proceedings before him, either 
upon or without an application by any of the parties involved in the proceedings 
before him, and on such terms as may appear to the controlling authority just, 
issue summons to any person in Form ‘P’ either to give evidence or to produce 
documents or for both purposes on a specified date, time and place.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Maintenance of 
records of cases by the controlling authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The controlling authority shall record the particulars of each case under 
section 7, in Form ‘Q’ and at the time of passing orders shall sign and date the 
particulars so recorded.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The controlling 
authority shall, while passing orders in each case, also record the findings on 
the merits of the case and file it together with the memoranda of evidence with 
the order sheet.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any record, other than 
a record of any order or direction, which is required by these rules to be 
signed by the controlling authority, may be signed on behalf of and under the 
direction of the controlling authority by any subordinate officer appointed in 
writing for this purpose by the controlling authority.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>16</number> Maintenance of records of 
cases by the controlling authority.—
<section><number>1</number> The controlling authority 
shall record the particulars of each case under section 7, in Form ‘Q’ and at 
the time of passing orders shall sign and date the particulars so 
recorded.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The controlling authority 
shall, while passing orders in each case, also record the findings on the merits 
of the case and file it together with the memoranda of evidence with the order 
sheet.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any record, other than a 
record of any order or direction, which is required by these rules to be signed 
by the controlling authority, may be signed on behalf of and under the direction 
of the controlling authority by any subordinate officer appointed in writing for 
this purpose by the controlling authority.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Direction for 
payment of gratuity.—If 
a finding is recorded under sub-rule (4) of rule 11 that the applicant is 
entitled to payment of gratuity under the Act, the controlling authority shall 
issue a notice to the employer concerned in Form ‘R’ specifying the amount 
payable and directing payment thereof to the applicant under intimation to the 
controlling authority within thirty days from the date of the receipt of the  
notice by the employer. A copy of the notice shall be endorsed to the applicant 
employee, nominee or legal heir, as the case may be.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Memorandum of appeal under sub-section (7) of section 7 of the Act shall be 
submitted to the appellate authority with a copy thereof to the opposite party 
and the controlling authority either through delivery in person or under 
registered post acknowledgement due.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Memorandum of 
appeal shall contain the facts of the case, the decision of the controlling 
authority, the grounds of appeal and the relief sought.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> There shall be 
appended to the Memorandum of appeal a certified copy of the finding of the 
controlling authority and direction for payment of gratuity.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the copy 
of Memorandum of appeal, the controlling authority shall forward records of the 
case to the appellate authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Within 14 days of the 
receipt of the copy of the Memorandum of appeal, the opposite party shall submit 
his comments of each paragraph of the Memorandum with additional pleas, if any, 
to the appellate authority with a copy to the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The appellate 
authority shall record its decision after giving the parties to the appeal a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard. A copy of the decision shall be given to 
the parties to the appeal and a copy thereof shall be sent to the controlling 
authority returning his records of the case.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The controlling 
authority shall, on receipt of the decision of the appellate authority, make 
necessary entry in the records of the case maintained in Form ‘Q’ under sub-rule 
(1) of rule 16.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> On receipt of the 
decision of the appellate authority, the controlling authority shall, if 
required under that decision, modify his direction for payment of gratuity and 
issue a notice to the employer concerned in Form ‘S’ specifying the modified 
amount payable and directing payment thereof to the applicant, under intimation 
to the controlling authority within fifteen days of the receipt of the notice by 
the employer. A copy of the notice be endorsed to the appellant employee, 
nominee or legal heir, as the case may be and to the appellate authority.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Application for 
recovery of gratuity.—Where 
an employer fails to pay the gratuity due under the Act in accordance with the 
notice by the controlling authority under rule 17 or rule 18, as the case may 
be, the employee concerned, his nominee or legal heir, as the case may be, to 
whom the gratuity is payable may apply to the controlling authority in duplicate 
in Form ‘T’ for recovery thereof under section 8 of the Act.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Display of abstract 
of the Act and Rules.—The 
employer shall display an abstract of the Act and the rules made thereunder


1[as given in Form 
‘U’] in English and in the language understood by the majority of the employees 
at conspicuous place at or near the main entrance of the establishment.
 
 




</article><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘A’
 


[See sub-rule (1) of 
rule 3]
 




Notice of Opening
 


1.   Name and 
address of the Establishment.
 


2.   Name and 
designation of the Employer.
 


3.   Number of 
persons employed.
 


4.   Maximum 
number of persons employed on any day during the preceding twelve months with 
date.
 


5.   Number of 
employees covered by the Act.
 


6.   Nature of 
industry.
 


7.   Whether 
seasonal.
 


8.   Date of 
opening.
 


9.   Details of 
Head Office/Branches.
 


(a)  Name and address 
of the head office.
 


      
Number of employees.
 


(b)  Names and 
addresses of other branches in India.
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


I verify that the 
information furnished above is true to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 



Place.............................                                                                                                     
Signature of the employer
 



Date.............................                                                                                                    
with name and designation
 


 
 


To
 


The Controlling 
Authority
 



........................................
 



.......................................
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘B’
 


[See sub-rule (2) of 
rule 3]
 




Notice of Change
 


Name and address of 

 


the Establishment,
 


Take notice that following 
changes have taken place with effect from ....................... in the 
particulars furnished by me in notice dated ........................... on Form 
‘A’.
 


Name.
 


Address.
 


Name of the employer.
 


Nature of business
 



Place.............................                                                                                                     
Signature of the employer
 



Date.............................                                                                                                    
with name and designation
 


 
 


To
 


The Controlling 
Authority
 



........................................
 



........................................
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘C’
 


[See sub-rule (3) of 
rule 3]
 




Notice of Closure
 


Take notice that it is 
intended to close down the establishment with effect from .................. The 
other details are furnished below:
 


1.   Name and 
address of the establishment.
 


2.   Name and 
address of the Head Office, if any.
 


3.   Name and 
designation of the employer.
 


4.   Number of 
persons in employment.
 


5.   Number of 
employees entitled to Gratuity.
 


6.   Amount of 
Gratuity involved.
 



Place.............................                                                                                                     
Signature of the employer
 



Date.............................                                                                                                    
with name and designation
 


 
 


To
 


The Controlling 
Authority
 



........................................
 



......................................
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘D’
 


[See sub-rule (1) of 
rule 5]
 




Notice for excluding husband from family
 


From 
.............................................................................
 


1.   Name of the 
female employee.
 


2.   Name or 
description of establishment where employed.
 


3.   Post held 
with Ticket or Serial No., if any.
 


4.   
Department/Branch/Section where employed.
 


5.   Permanent 
address.
 


Take notice that I, 
Shrimati ..................... desire to exclude my husband Shri 
.....................from my family for the purposes of the Payment of Gratuity 
Act, 1972.
 



Place.............................                                                                                                     
Signature/Thumb impression
 



Date.............................                                                                                                                        
of the employee.
 


 
 


Declaration by witnesses
 


The above notice was 
signed/thumb impressed before me.
 


Name in full and full                                                            
Signature of witnesses.
 


address of witnesses.
 


1.                                                                                        
1.
 


2.                                                                                        
2.
 



Place............................
 



Date.............................
 


To 
 


The Controlling 
Authority.
 


(Through the employer)
 


[Name and address of the 
employer here]
 


For use by the employer
 


Received and recorded in 
this establishment.
 



Date.............................                                                                                              
Signature of the employer or an 
 


                                                                                                                                    
officer authorised in this behalf 
 


                                                                                                                                                           
by the employer
 


Reference No.
 


To
 


1. 
............................... (Employee)
 


2.   The 
Controlling Authority.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




*FORM ‘E’
 


[See sub-rule (2) of 
rule 5]
 


Notice 
of withdrawal of notice for excluding husband from family
 


1.   Name of the 
female employee.
 


2.   Name or 
description of establishment where employed.
 


3.   Post held 
with Ticket or Serial No., if any.
 


4.   
Department/Branch/Section where employed.
 


5.   Permanent 
address.
 


Take notice that I, 
Shrimati .................... hereby withdraw the notice dated 
.................... whereby I exclude my husband Shri ................... from 
my family for the purposes of the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972. The earlier 
notice was recorded under your reference No. ............dated 
.........................
 



Place.............................                                                                                                    
Signature/Thumb impression
 



Date.............................                                                                                                                       
of the employee.
 


 
 




Declaration by 
witnesses
 


The above notice of 
withdrawal was signed/thumb impressed before me.
 


Name in full and full                                                            
Signature of witnesses.
 


address of witnesses.
 


1.                                                                                        
1.
 


2.                                                                                        
2.
 



Place............................
 



Date.............................
 


To 
 


The Controlling 
Authority.
 


(Through the employer)
 


[Name and address of the 
employer]
 


For use by the employer
 


Received and recorded in 
this establishment.
 


Reference No.                                                                                                                   
Signature of the employer or 
 



Date.............................                                                                                                                     
officer authorised. 
 


                                                                                                                                                   
or rubber stamp of the
 


                                                                                                                                                               
establishment.
 


To
 


1. 
........................... (Employee)
 


2. The Controlling 
Authority.
 


 
 


—————
 


    * 
Ed.—Form D and E have became redundant as rule 5 of these Rules have 
became redundant because of proviso to sub-clause (ii) of clause (h) of section 
2 of the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1872 has been omitted by the Payment of 
Gratuity Act, 1987 (22 of 1987), sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1987).
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘H’
 


[See sub-rule (4) of 
rule 6]
 




Modification of nomination
 


To 
..................................................................................................................................
 


            
[Give here name or description of the establishment with full address]
 


I, Shri/Shrimati/Kumari 
.................. [Name in full here] whose particulars are given in the 
statement below, hereby give notice that the nomination filed by me on [date] 
and recorded under your reference No. .......... dated .................. shall 
stand modified in the following manner:
 


[Here give details of the 
modifications intended]
 


Statement
 


1.   Name of the 
employee in full.
 


2.   Sex.
 


3.   Religion.
 


4.   Whether 
unmarried/married/widow/widower.
 


5.   
Department/Branch/Section where employed.
 


6.   Post held 
with Ticket No. or Serial No., if any.
 


7.   Date of 
appointment.
 


8.   Address in 
full.
 



Place.............................                                                                                                     
Signature/Thumb impression
 



Date.............................                                                                                                                        
of the employee.
 


 
 


Declaration by witnesses
 


Modification of nomination 
signed/thumb impressed before me.
 


Name in full and full                                                   
Signature of witnesses.
 


address of witnesses.
 


1.                                                                                        
1.
 


2.                                                                                        
2.
 



Place............................. 
 



Date.............................
 


Certificate by the 
employer
 


Certified that the  
above modification have been recorded.
 


Employer’s reference 
No., if any.                                                                               
Signature of the employer/
 


                                                                                                                                
officer authorised  
 


                                                                                                                                
Designation
 


                                                                                                                                
Name and address of the 
 


                                                                                                                                
establishment or rubber 
 


                                                                                                                                
stamp thereof.
 


Acknowledgement by the 
employee
 


Received the duplicate copy 
of the notice for modification in Form ‘H’ filed by me on ................. duly 
certified by the employer.
 



Date.............................                                                                                                         
Signature of the employee
 


Note: 
Strike out the words not applicable.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘I’
 


[See sub-rule (1) of 
rule 7]
 




Application of gratuity by an employee
 


To 
............................................................................................................................................
 


      
[Give here name or description of the establishment with full address]
 


Sir/Gentlemen,
 


I beg to apply for payment 
of gratuity to which I am entitled under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the 
Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972 on account of my 
superannuation/retirement/resignation after completion of not less than five 
years of continuous service/ total disablement due to accident/total disablement 
due to disease with effect from the .................. Necessary particulars 
relating to my appointment in the establishment are given in the statement 
below:
 


Statement
 


1.   Name in 
full.
 


2.   Address in 
full.
 


3.   
Department/Branch/Section where last employed.
 


4.   Post held 
with Ticket No. or Serial No., if any.
 


5.   Date of 
appointment.
 


6.   Date and 
cause of termination of service.
 


7.   Total period 
of service.
 


8.   Amount of 
wages last drawn.
 


9.   Amount of 
gratuity claimed.
 


I was rendered totally 
disabled as a result of 
 


[Here give the details of 
the nature of disease or accident]
 


The evidences/witnesses in 
support of my total disablement are as follows:
 


[Here give details]
 


Payment may please be made 
in cash/open or crossed bank cheque.
 


As the amount of gratuity 
payable is less than rupees one thousand, I shall request you to arrange for 
payment of the sum due to me by Postal Money Order at the address mentioned 
above after deducting postal money order commission therefrom.
 


                                                                                                                                       
Yours faithfully,
 



Place............................                                                                                                  
Signature/Thumb impression of
 



Date.............................                                                                                                  
the applicant employee.
 


Note.—1. 
Strike out the words not applicable.
 


            
2. Strike out paragraph or paragraphs not applicable.
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘J’
 


[See sub-rule (2) of 
rule 7]
 




Application for gratuity by a nominee
 


To 
.........................................................................................................................................
 


      
[Give here the name or description of the establishment with full address]
 


Sir/Gentlemen,
 


I beg to apply for payment 
of gratuity to which I am entitled under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the 
Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972 as a nominee of late.................. [name of 
the employee] who was an employee of your establishment and died on the 
.................. The gratuity is payable on account of the death of the 
aforesaid employee while in service/superannuation of the aforesaid employee on 
.................. retirement of/resignation of the aforesaid employee on 
.................. after completion of .................. years of service/total 
disablement of the aforesaid employee due to accident or disease while in 
service with effect from the .................. Necessary particulars relating 
to my claim given in the statement below:
 


Statement
 


1.   Name of 
applicant nominee.
 


2.   Address in 
full of the applicant nominee.
 


3.   Marital 
status of the applicant nominee         

(unmarried/married/widow/widower)
 


4.   Name in full 
of the employee.
 


5.   Marital 
status of employee.
 


6.   Relationship 
of the nominee with employee.
 


7.   Total period 
of service of the employee.
 


8.   Date of 
appointment of the employee.
 


9.   Date and 
cause of termination of service of the employee.
 


10. 
Department/Branch/Section where the employee last worked.
 


11. Post last held by the 
employee with Ticket or Serial No., if any.
 


12. Total wages last drawn 
by the employee.
 


13. Date of death and 
evidence/witness as proof of death of the employee.
 


14. Reference No. of 
recorded nomination, if available.
 


15. Total gratuity payable 
to the employee.
 


16. Share of gratuity 
claimed.
 


2. I declare that the 
particulars mentioned in the above statement are true and correct to the best of 
my knowledge and belief.
 


3. Payment may please be 
made in cash/crossed or open bank cheque.
 


4. As the amount payable is 
less than rupees one thousand, I shall request you to arrange for payment of the 
sum due to me by Postal Money Order at the address mentioned above after 
deducting Postal Money Order commission therefrom.
 


                                                                                                                                                               
Yours faithfully,
 



Place............................                                                                                                     
Signature/Thumb impression
 



Date.............................                                                                                                                
of applicant nominee.
 


Note.—1. 
Strike out the words not applicable.
 


            
2. Strike out the paragraph or paragraphs not applicable.
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘K’
 


[See sub-rule (3) of 
rule 7]
 




Application for gratuity by a legal heir
 


To 
..........................................................................................................................................
 


      
[Give here the name or description of the establishment with full address]
 


Sir/Gentlemen,
 


I beg to apply for payment 
of gratuity to which I am entitled under sub-section (1) of section 4 of the 
Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972 as a legal heir of late .................. [name 
of the employee] who was an employee of your establishment and died on the 
....... without making any nomination. The gratuity is payable on account of the 
death of the aforesaid employee while in service/ superannuation of the 
aforesaid employee on the .................. retirement or resignation of the 
aforesaid employee on the ..................  after completion of 
..................  years of service/total disablement of the aforesaid 
employee due to accident or disease while in service with effect from the 
.................. Necessary particulars relating to my claim are given in the 
statement below:
 


Statement
 


1.   Name of 
applicant legal heir.
 


2.   Address in 
full of applicant legal heir.
 


3.   Marital 
status of the applicant legal heir (unmarried/married/widow/widower)
 


4.   Name in full 
of the employee.
 


5.   Relationship 
of the applicant with the employee.
 


6.   Religion of 
both the applicant and the employee.
 


7.   Date of 
appointment and total period of service of the employee.
 


8.   
Department/Branch/Section where the employee worked last.
 


9.   Post last 
held by the employee with Ticket or Serial No., if any.
 


10. Total wages last drawn 
by the employee.
 


11. Date and cause of 
termination of service of the employee (death or otherwise).
 


12. Date of death of the 
employee and evidence/witness in support thereof.
 


13. Total gratuity payable 
to the employee.
 


14. Percentage of the 
gratuity claimed.
 


15. Basis of the claim and 
evidence/witness in support thereof.
 


2. I declare that the 
particulars mentioned in the above statement are true and correct to the best of 
my knowledge and belief.
 


3. Payment may please be 
made in cash/open or crossed  bank cheque.
 


4. As the amount payable is 
less than rupees one thousand, I shall request you to arrange for payment of the 
sum due to me by Postal Money Order at the address mentioned above, after 
deducting Postal Money Order commission therefrom.
 


                                                                                                                                           
Yours faithfully,
 



Place............................                                                                                                      
Signature/Thumb impression
 



Date.............................                                                                                                      
of applicant legal heir.
 


Note.—Strike 
out the words not applicable.
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘M’
 


[See clause (ii) of 
sub-rule (1) of rule 8]
 




Notice rejecting claim for payment of gratuity
 


To
 


[Name and address of the 
applicant employee/nominee/legal heir]
 


You are hereby informed as 
required under clause (ii) of sub-rule (i) of rule 8 of the Payment of Gratuity 
(Central) Rules, 1972 that your claim for payment of gratuity as indicated on 
your application in Form ........ under the said rules is not admissible for the 
reasons stated below:
 


Reasons
 


[Here specify the reasons]
 



Place............................                                                                                                   
Signature of the employer/
 



Date.............................                                                                                                   
Authorised Officer.
 


                                                                                                                                       
Name or description of  

                                                                                                                                             
establishment or rubber 
 


                                                                                                                                       
stamp thereof.
 


Copy to : The 
Controlling Authority.
 


Note: 
Strike out the words not 
applicable.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘O’
 


[See sub-rule (1) of 
rule 11]
 




Notice for appearance before the controlling authority
 


From:
 


The Controlling Authority 
under the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972.
 


To
 



......................................................................................................................................................
 


        
[Name and address of the employee/applicant]
 


Whereas Shri 
....................., an employee under you/a nominee(s) legal heir(s) of Shri 
.....................an employee under the above-mentioned employer, has/have 
filed an application under sub-rule (1) of rule 10 of the Payment of Gratuity 
(Central) Rules, 1972 alleging that ..................
 


[A copy of the said 
application is enclosed]
 


Now, therefore, you are 
hereby called upon to appear before me at  ..................... [place] 
either personally or through a person duly authorised in this behalf for the 
purpose of answering all material questions relating to the application on the 
................ day of ............... 20..... at .......... o’clock in the 
forenoon/afternoon in support of/to answer the allegation; and as the day fixed 
for your appearance is appointed for final disposal of the application, you must 
be prepared to produce on that day all the witnesses upon whose evidence, and 
the documents upon which you intend to rely in support of your allegation/defence.
 


Take notice that in default 
of your appearance on the day before mentioned the application will be 
dismissed/heard and determined in your absence.
 


Give under my hand and 
seal, this ............... day of ............... 20 .....
 


Controlling Authority
 


Note 
: Strike out the words and paragraphs not applicable.
 





</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘P’
 


(See  rule 14)
 




Summons
 


Before the Controlling 
Authority under the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972.
 


To
 



.......................................................................................................................................................
 


 [Name and address]
 


Whereas your attendance is 
required to give evidence/you are required to produce the documents mentioned in 
this list below, on behalf of .......... in the case arising out of the claim 
for gratuity by..................... from ..................... and referred to 
this Authority by an application under section 7 of the Payment of Gratuity Act, 
1972, you are hereby summoned to appear personally before this Authority on the 
.......... day of ............20 ..... at .......... o’clock in the 
forenoon/afternoon and to bring with you (or to send to this Authority) the said 
documents.
 


List of Documents
 


1.
 


2.
 


3. so on                                                                                                                                         
Controlling Authority
 


Dated this ............... 
day of .............. 20 .....
 


Notes.—1.  
The portion not applicable to be deleted.
 


 2.  The summons shall 
be issued in duplicate. The duplicate is to be signed and returned by the person 
served before the date fixed.
 


 3.  In case summons 
is issued only for producing a document and not to give evidence, it will be 
sufficient compliance to the summons if the documents are caused to be produced 
before the controlling authority on the day and hour fixed for the purpose.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




FORM ‘Q’
 


[See sub-rule (1) of 
rule 19]
 




Particulars of application under section 7
 


1.   Serial No.
 


2.   Date of the 
Application.
 


3.   Name and 
address of the applicant.
 


4.   Name and 
address of the employer.
 


5.   Amount of 
gratuity claimed.
 


6.   Dates of 
hearing.
 


7.   Findings 
with date.
 


8.   Amount 
awarded.
 


9.   Cost, if 
any, awarded.
 


10. Date of notice issued 
for payment of gratuity.
 


11. Date of appeal, if any.
 


12. Decision of the 
appellate authority.
 


13  Date of issue of 
Final Notice for payment of gratuity.
 


14. Date of payment of 
gratuity by Employer with mode of payment.
 


15. Date of Receipt of 
application for recovery of Gratuity.
 


16. Date of Issue of 
Recovery Certificate.
 


17. Date of Recovery.
 


18. Other remarks.
 


19. Signed.
 


20. Date.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




Form ‘R’
 


(See rule 17)
 




Notice for payment of gratuity
 


To 
........................................................................ [Name 
and address of employer]
 


Whereas Shri/Smt/Kumari 
..................... of .......................... (address) an [employee under 
you/a nominee(s) legal heir(s) of late ..................... and employee under 
you, filed an application under section 7 of the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972 
before me;
 


And whereas the application 
was heard in your presence on and after the  hearing I have come to the 
finding that the said Shri/Smt./ Kumari ..................... is entitled to  
a payment of Rs ............ as gratuity under the Payment of Gratuity Act, 
1972;
 


Now, therefore, I hereby 
direct to pay the said sum of Rs ............. to Shri/Smt./Kumari 
..................... within thirty days of the receipt of this notice with an 
intimation thereof to me.
 


Given under my hand and 
seal, this ............. day of ............ 20 ......
 


Controlling Authority
 


Copy to :
 


(Applicant)
 


He is advised to contact 
the employer for collecting payment.
 


Note.—The 
portion not applicable to be deleted.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




Form ‘S’
 


[See sub-rule (5) of 
rule 18]
 




Notice for Payment of Gratuity as determined  

by Appellate Authority
 


To
 


        
[Name and address of employer]
 


Whereas a notice was given 
to you on ...................... Form ‘R’ requiring you to make a payment of Rs 
.................  to Shri/Smt./Kumari .................... as gratuity 
under the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972;
 


Whereas you/the applicant 
went in appeal before the appellate authority, who has decided that an amount of 
Rs ................ is due to be paid to Shri/Smt./Kumari ..................... 
as gratuity due under the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972; 
 


Now, therefore, I hereby 
direct you to pay the said sum of Rs ............... to Shri/Smt./Kumari 
..................... within 30 days of the receipt of this notice with an 
intimation thereof to me.
 


Given under my hand and 
seal, this ........... day of ........... 20.....
 


Controlling Authority.
 


Copy to:
 


1. The Applicant.
 


      
He is advised to contact the employer for collecting payment.
 


2. The Appellate Authority.
 


Note.— 
The portion not applicable to be deleted.
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




Form ‘T’
 


(See rule 19)
 




Application for recovery of gratuity
 


Before the Controlling 
Authority under the Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972.
 


Application 
No...............                                                                                              
Date .......................
 


           
Between .........................................................
 


           
[Name in full of the applicant with address]
 


And 
 


           
[Name in full of the employer with full address]
 


The applicant is an 
employee of the above-mentioned employer/a nominee of late................. an 
employee of the above mentioned employer/a legal heir of late............., an 
employee of the above mentioned employer, and you were pleased to direct the 
said employer in your notice dated the ................. under rule 
................ of the Payment of Gratuity (Central) Rules, 1972 for payment of 
a sum of Rs ............. as gratuity payable under the Payment of Gratuity Act, 
1972.
 


2. The applicant submits 
that the said employer failed to pay the said amount of gratuity to me as 
directed by you although I approached him for payment.
 


3. The applicant therefore 
prays that a certificate may be issued under section ............. of the said 
Act for the recovery of the said sum of Rs.................. due to me as 
gratuity in terms of your direction.
 



Place............................                                                                                                    
Signature/Thumb impression  
 



Date.............................                                                                                                    
of the applicant
 




</form><form>
 




THE PAYMENT OF GRATUITY (CENTRAL) RULES, 1972
 


 
 




1[Form 
‘U’
 




Abstract of the Act and Rules
 


1. Extent of the Act.—The 
Act extends to the whole of India:
 


Provided that insofar as it 
relates to plantations or ports, it shall not extend to the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir. [Section 1(2)]
 


2. To whom the Act 
applies.—The Act 
applies to (a) every factory, mine, oilfield, plantation, port and railway 
company; (b) every shop or establishment within the meaning of any law for the 
time being in force in relation to shops and establishments in State, in which 
ten or more persons are employed, or were employed, on any day of the preceding 
twelve months; and (c) such other establishment, or class of establishments, in 
which ten or more employees are employed, or were employed, on any day of the 
preceding twelve months, as the Central Government may, by notification, specify 
in this behalf. [Section 1(3)].
 


3. Definitions.—(a) 
“Appropriate Government” means—
 


(i)   in relation 
to an establishment;
 


(a) belonging to, or under 
the control of, the Central Government,
 


(b) having branches in more 
than one State,
 


(c) of a factory belonging 
to, or under the control of, the Central Government,
 


(d) of a major port, mine, 
oilfield or railway company, the Central Government.
 


(ii) in any other case, the 
State Government. [Section 2(a)].
 


(b) “Completed year of 
service” means continuous service for one year; [Section 2(b)].
 


(c) “Continuous Service” 
means uninterrupted service and includes service which is interrupted by 
sickness, accident, leave, lay-off, strike or a lock-out or cessation of work 
not due to any fault of the employees concerned, whether such uninterrupted or 
interrupted service was rendered before or after the commencement of this Act.
 


Explanation I.—In 
the case of an employee who is not in uninterrupted service for one year, he 
shall be deemed to be in continuous service if he has been actually employed by 
an employer during the twelve months immediately preceding the year for not less 
than—
 


(i)   190 days, 
if employed below the ground in a mine, or
 


(ii)  240 days, in any 
other case, except when he is employed in seasonal establishment.
 


Explanation II.—An 
employee of a seasonal establishment shall be deemed to be in continuous service 
if he has actually worked for not less than seventy-five per cent of the number 
of days on which the establishment was in operation during the year. [Section 
2(d)].
 


(d) “Controlling authority” 
means an authority appointed by an appropriate Government under section 3. 
[Section 2(d)].
 


(e) “family”, in relation 
to an employee, shall be deemed to consist of—
 


(i)   in the case 
of a male employee, himself, his wife, his children, whether married or 
unmarried, his dependant parents and the widow and children, of his predeceased 
son, if any,
 


(ii) in the case of a 
female employee, herself, her husband, her children,
 


whether married or 
unmarried, her dependant parents and the dependant parents of her husband and 
the widow and children of her predeceased son, if any:
 


Provided that if a female 
employee, by a notice in writing to the controlling authority, express her 
desire to exclude her husband from her family, the husband and his dependant 
parents shall no longer be deemed for the purposes of this Act, to be included 
in the family of such female employee unless the said notice is subsequently 
withdrawn by such female employee.
 


Explanation.—Where 
the personal law of an employee permits the adoption by him of a child, any 
child lawfully adopted by him shall be deemed to be included in his family, and 
where a child of an employee has been adopted by another person and such 
adoption is, under the personal law of the person making such adoption, lawful, 
such child shall be deemed to be excluded from the family of the employee. 
[Section 2(h)].
 


4. Nomination.—(1) 
Each employee, who has completed one year of service, after the commencement of 
the Payment of Gratuity (Central) Rules, 1972, shall make within thirty days of 
completion of one year of service, a nomination [Section 6(1) read with Rule 8, 
6(1)].
 


(2) If an employee has a 
family at the time of making a nomination the nomination shall be made in favour 
of one or more members of his family and any nomination made by such employee in 
favour of a person who is not member of his family shall be void. [Section 
6(3)].
 


(3) If at the time of 
making a nomination, the employee has no family, the nomination can be made in 
favour of any person or persons, but if the employee subsequently acquires a 
family, such nomination shall forthwith become invalid and the employee shall 
make within  90 days a fresh nomination in favour of one or more members of 
this family. [Section 6(4) read with rule 6(3)].
 


(4) A nomination or a fresh 
nomination or a notice of modification of nomination shall be signed by the 
employee or, if illiterate, shall bear his thumb impression in the presence of 
two witnesses, who shall also sign declaration to that effect in that 
nomination, fresh nomination or notice of modification of nomination as the case 
may be. [Rule 6(5)].
 


(5) A nomination may, 
subject to the provisions of sub-sections (3) and (4) of section 6 be modified 
by an employee any time after giving to his employer a written notice of his 
intention to do so.[Section 6(5)].
 


(6) A nomination or fresh 
nomination or notice of modification of nomination shall take effect from the 
date of receipt of the same by the employer. [Rule 6(6)].
 


5. Application for 
gratuity.—(1) An 
employee who is eligible for payment of gratuity under the Act, or any person 
authorised, in writing, to act on his behalf, shall apply ordinarily within 
thirty days from the date of gratuity became payable:
 


Provided that where the 
date of superannuation or retirement of an employee is known, the employee may 
apply to the employer before thirty days of the date of superannuation or 
retirement. [Rule 7(1)].
 


(2) A nominee of an 
employee who is eligible for payment of gratuity shall apply, ordinarily within 
thirty days from the date the gratuity became payable to him, to the employer. 
[Rule 7(2)].
 


(3) A legal heir of an 
employee who is eligible for payment of gratuity shall apply, ordinarily within 
one year from the date the gratuity became payable to him, to the employer. 
[Rule 7(3)].
 


(4) An application for 
payment of gratuity filed after the expiry of the periods specified above shall 
also be entertained by the employer if the applicant adduces a sufficient cause 
for the delay. [Rule 7(5)].
 


6. Payment of gratuity.—(1) 
Gratuity shall be payable to an employee on the termination of his employment 
after he has rendered continuous service for not less than five years—
 


(a)  on his 
superannuation, or
 


(b) on his retirement or 
registration, or
 


(c) on his death or 
disablement due to accident or disease:
 


Provided that the 
completion of continuous service of five years shall not be necessary where the 
termination of the employment of any employee is due to death or disablement:
 


Provided further that in 
case of death of the employee, gratuity payable to him shall be paid to his 
nominee or, if no nomination has been made, to his heirs, and where any such 
nominees or heirs is a minor the shares of such minor, shall be deposited with 
the controlling authority who shall invest the same for the benefit of such 
minor in such bank or other financial institution, as may be prescribed, until 
such minor attains majority.
 


Disablement means such 
disablement which incapacitates an employee for the work which he was capable of 
performing before the accident or disease resulting in such disablement. 
[Section 4(1)].
 


(2) For every completed 
year of service or part thereof in excess of six months, the employer shall pay 
gratuity to an employee at the rate of fifteen days’ wages based on the rate of 
wages last drawn by the employee concerned:
 


Provided that in the case 
of a piece-rated  employee, daily wages shall be computed on the average of 
the total wages received by him for a period of three months immediately 
preceding the termination of his employment, and, for this purpose, the wages 
paid for any overtime work shall not be taken into account:
 


Provided further that in 
the case of an employee employed in seasonal establishment, the employer shall 
pay the gratuity at the rate of seven days’ wages for each season. [Section 
4(2)].
 


Explanation. 
—In case of a monthly rated 
employee, the fifteen days’ wages shall be calculated by dividing the monthly 
rate of wages last drawn by him by twenty-six and multiplying quotient by 
fifteen.
 


(3) The amount of gratuity 
payable to an employee shall not exceed twenty months wages. [Section 4(3)].
 


7. Forfeiture of 
gratuity.—(1) 
The gratuity of an employee, whose services have been terminated for any act, 
wilful omission or negligence causing any damage or loss to, or destruction of, 
property belonging to the employer, shall be forfeited to the extent of the 
damage or loss so caused;
 


(2) The gratuity payable to 
an employee shall be wholly forfeited—
 


(a)  If the services 
of such employee have been terminated for his riotous or disorderly conduct or 
any other act of violence on his part, or
 


(b)  If the services 
of such employee have been terminated for any act which constitutes an offence 
involving moral turpitude, provided that such offence is committed by him in the 
course of his employment.[Section 4(6)].
 


8. Notice of opening, 
change or closure of the establishment.— 
(1) A notice shall be submitted by the employer to the controlling authority of 
the area within thirty days of any change in the name, address, employer or 
nature of business.[Rule 3(2)].
 


(2) Where an employer 
intends to close down the business he shall submit a notice to the controlling 
authority of the area at least sixty days before the intended closure.[Rule 
3(3)].
 


9. Application to 
Controlling Authority for direction.—If 
an employer—
 


(i)   refuses to 
accept a nomination or to entertain an application for payment of gratuity, or
 


(ii)  issues a notice 
either specifying an amount of gratuity which is considered by the applicant 
less than what is payable or rejecting eligibility to payment of gratuity, or
 


(iii) having received an 
application for payment of gratuity, fails to issue notice within fifteen days; 
the claimant employee, nominee, or legal heir, as the case may be, may within 
ninety days of the occurrence of the cause for the application, apply to the 
controlling authority for issuing a direction under sub-section (4) of section 7 
with as many extra copies as are the opposite party:
 


Provided that Controlling 
Authority may accept any application on sufficient cause being shown by the 
applicant after the expiry of the period of ninety days. [Rule 10].
 


10. Appeal.—Any 
person aggrieved by an order of the controlling authority may, within sixty days 
from the date of the receipt of the order, prefer an appeal to the Regional 
Labour Commissioner (Central) of the area who has been appointed as the 
appellate authority by the Central Government:
 


Provided that the appellate 
authority may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient 
cause from preferring the appeal within the said period of sixty days, extend 
the said period by a further period of sixty days. [Section 7(7)].
 


11. Machinery for 
enforcement of the Act or Rules in Central spheres.—All 
Assistant Labour Commissioners (Central) have been appointed as Controlling 
Authorities and all the Regional Labour Commissioners (Central) Appellate 
Authorities.
 


12. Powers of the 
Controlling Authority.—The 
Controlling Authority for the purpose of conducting an inquiry as to the amount 
of gratuity payable to an employee or as to the admissibility of any claim of, 
or in relation to, an employee for payment of gratuity, or as to the person 
entitled to receive the gratuity, shall have the same powers as are vested in 
court, under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 in respect of the following 
matters, namely:—
 


(a) enforcing the 
attendance of any person or examining him on oath;
 


(b) requiring the discovery 
and production of documents;
 


(c) receiving evidence on 
affidavits; and
 


(d) issuing commissions for 
the examination of witnesses. [Section 7(5)].
 


13. Recovery of gratuity.—If 
the amount of gratuity payable is not paid by the employer, within the 
prescribed time, to the person entitled thereto the controlling authority shall, 
on an application made to it in this behalf by the aggrieved person, issue a 
certificate for that amount to the Collector, who shall recover the same 
together with compound interest thereon at the rate of nine per cent per annum, 
from the date of expiry of the prescribed time, as arrears of land revenue and 
pay the same to the person entitled thereto. [Section 8].
 


14. Protection of 
gratuity.—No 
gratuity payable under the Payment of Gratuity Act and rules made thereunder 
shall be liable to attachment in execution of any decree or order of any civil, 
revenue or criminal court. [Section 13].
 


15. Penalties for 
offences.—(1) 
Whoever, for the purpose of avoiding any payment to be made by himself or of 
enabling any other person to avoid such payment, knowingly makes or causes to be 
made any false statement or false representation shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees, or with both. [Section 9(1)].
 


(2) An employer who 
contravenes, or makes default in complying with, any of the provisions of the 
Act or any rule or order made thereunder shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees, or with both:
 


Provided that if the 
offence relates to non-payment of any gratuity payable under the Payment of 
Gratuity Act, the employer shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than three months unless the court trying the offence, 
for reasons to be recorded by it in writing, is of opinion that a lesser term of 
imprisonment or the imposition of a fine would meet the ends of justice. 
[Section 9(2)].
 


16. Display of notice.—The 
employer shall display conspicuously a notice at or near the main entrance of 
the establishment in bold letters in English and in the language understood by 
the majority of the employees specifying the name of the officer with 
designation authorised by the employer to receive on his behalf notices under 
the Payment of Gratuity Act or the rules made thereunder. [Rule 4].
 


17. Display of abstract 
of the Act and Rules.—The 
employer shall display an abstract of the Payment of Gratuity Act and the rules 
made thereunder in English and in the language understood by the majority of the 
employees at a conspicuous place at or near the main entrance of the 
establishment. [Rule 20].
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. 
by G.S.R. 2868, dated 22nd November, 1975.
 


 
 


 
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>