<act><tid>1470394</tid>
<title>THE MOTOR VEHICLES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 27 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 11th August, <year>2000</year>]

An Act further to amend the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1988</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1197911</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Motor Vehicles (Amendment) 
Act, <year>2000</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1830423</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new section for section 52.- For section 52 of the 
Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1988</year> (59 of <year>1988</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
' 52. Alteration in motor vehicle.- (1) No owner of a motor vehicle 
shall so alter the vehicle that the particulars contained in the 
certificate of registration are at variance with those originally 
specified by the manufacturer: Provided that where the owner of a 
motor vehicle makes modification of the engine, or any part thereof, 
of a vehicle for facilitating its operation by different type of fuel 
or source of energy including battery, compressed natural gas, solar 
power, liqu d petroleum gas or any other fuel or source of energy, by 
fitment of a conversion kit, such modification shall be carried out 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed:

Provided further that the Central Government may prescribe 
specifications, conditions for approval, retrofitment and other 
related matters for such conversion kits:

Provided also that the Central Government may grant exemption for 
alteration of vehicles in a manner other than specified above, for any 
specific purpose.

<section><tid>364918</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), a State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, authorise, 
subject to such conditions as may be specified in the notification, 
and permit any person owning not less than ten tran port vehicles to 
alter any vehicle owned by him so as to replace the engine thereof 
with engine of the same make and type, without the approval of 
registering authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1246890</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any alteration has been made in motor vehicle without the 
approval of registering authority or by reason of replacement of its 
engine without such approval under sub- section (2), the owner of the 
vehicle shall, within fourteen days of the maki g of the alteration, 
report the alteration to the registering authority within whose 
jurisdiction he resides and shall forward the certificate of 
registration to that authority together with the prescribed fee in 
order that particulars of registration ma be entered therein.

</section>

<section><tid>10079</tid>
<number>4</number>A registering authority other than the original registering 
authority making any such entry shall communicate the details of the 
entry to the original registering authority.

</section>

<section><tid>572409</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to the provisions made under sub- sections (1), (2), (3) 
and (4), no person holding a vehicle under a hire- purchase agreement 
shall make any alteration to the vehicle except with the written 
consent of the registered owner.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," alteration" means a 
change in the structure of a vehicle which results in a change in its 
basic feature.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>725744</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 58.- In section 58 of the principal Act, 
sub- section (4) shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>38261</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 66.- In section 66 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (3), clause (h) shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>174519</tid>
<number>5</number>Insertion of new section 217A.- After section 217 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 217A. Renewal of permits, driving licences and registration granted 
under the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1939</year>.- Notwithstanding the repeal by 
sub- section (1) of section 217 of the enactments referred to in that 
sub- section, any certificate of fitness or registr tion or licence or 
permit issued or granted under the said enactments may be renewed 
under this Act.".

SUBHASH C. JAIN 
Secretary to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>