<act><tid>1475538</tid>
<title>THE LEGAL PRACTITIONERS (FEES) ACT, <year>1926</year></title>

ACT No. 21 OF <year>1926</year>
[ 25th March, <year>1926</year>.]

An Act to define in certain cases the rights of legal practitioners to 
sue for their fees and their liabilities to be sued in respect of 
negligence in the discharge of their professional duties.

WHEREAS it is expedient to define in certain cases the rights of legal 
practitioners to sue for their fees and their liabilities to be sued 
in respect of negligence in the discharge of their professional 
duties; It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1438146</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>941184</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Legal Practitioners (Fees) Act, <year>1926</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1807206</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> except the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>1963534</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1642862</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation.- For the purposes of this Act, unless there is 
anything repugnant in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>133341</tid>
<number>a</number>" legal practitioner" means a legal practitioner as defined in 
section 3 of the Legal Practitioners Act, <year>1879</year> (18 of <year>1879</year>); and

</section>

<section><tid>1739012</tid>
<number>b</number>a legal practitioner shall not be deemed to" act" if he only 
pleads, or to" agree to act" if he agrees only to plead.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1974067</tid>
<number>3</number>Agreement for engagement of legal practitioner.- Any legal 
practitioner who acts or agrees to act for any person may be private 
agreement settle with such person the terms of his engagement and the 
fee to be paid for his professional services.


</article>



<article><tid>1802376</tid>
<number>4</number>Right of legal practitioner to sue for fees.- Any such legal 
practitioner shall be entitled to institute and maintain legal 
proceedings for the recovery of any fee due to him under the 
agreement, or, if no such fee has been settled, a fee computed in 
accordance with the law for the time being in force in regard to the 
computation of the costs to be awarded to a party in respect of the 
fee of his legal practitioner.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" except Part B 
States". 2. 1st June, <year>1926</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1926</year>, Pt. I, p. 
514.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1891037</tid>
<number>5</number>Liability of legal practitioner to be sued.- No legal practitioner 
who has acted or agreed to act shall, by reason only of being a legal 
practitioner, be exempt from liability to be sued in respect of any 
loss or injury due to any negligence in the conduct of his 
professional duties.


</article>



<article><tid>747236</tid>
<number>6</number>[ Repeals.]- Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1927</year> (12 of <year>1927</year>), s. 2 
and Sch.

</article>



 </act>