<act><tid>1482706</tid>
<title>THE HOTEL- RECEIPTS TAX ACT, <year>1980</year></title>

ACT NO. 54 OF <year>1980</year>
[ 9th December, <year>1980</year>.]

An Act to impose a special tax on gross receipts of certain hotels.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- first Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>688318</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>608899</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Hotel-  
Receipts Tax Act, <year>1980</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>612254</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1168354</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>154994</tid>
<number>1</number>" assessee" means a person by whom hotel- receipts tax or any 
other sum of money is payable under this Act and includes--

<subsection><tid>265979</tid>
<number>a</number>every person in respect of whom any proceeding under 
this Act has been taken for the assessment of his chargeable 
receipts or of the amount of refund due to him or of the 
chargeable receipts of any other person in respect of which he is 
assessable or of the amount of refund due to such other person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1865765</tid>
<number>b</number>every person who is deemed to be an assessee in default 
under any provision of this Act;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>329215</tid>
<number>2</number>" assessment" includes reassessment;

</section>

<section><tid>179136</tid>
<number>3</number>" assessment year" means the period of twelve months 
commencing on the 1st day of April every year;

</section>

<section><tid>149219</tid>
<number>4</number>" Board" means the Central Board of Direct Taxes constituted 
under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>348</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>610219</tid>
<number>5</number>" chargeable receipts" means the total amount of all charges 
referred to in section 6, computed in the manner laid down in section 
7;

</section>

<section><tid>1805599</tid>
<number>6</number>" hotel" includes a building or part of a building where 
residential accommodation is, by way of business, provided for a 
monetary consideration;

</section>

<section><tid>1967746</tid>
<number>7</number>" hotel- receipts tax" or" tax" means the tax chargeable under 
the provisions of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1167216</tid>
<number>8</number>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>778943</tid>
<number>9</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1955831</tid>
<number>10</number>" room charges" means the charges for a unit of residential 
accommodation in a hotel and includes the charges for--

<subsection><tid>1193708</tid>
<number>a</number>furniture, air- conditioner, refrigerator, radio, music, 
telephone, television, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1182831</tid>
<number>b</number>such other services as are normally included by a hotel 
in room rent,
but does not include charges for food, drink and any services other 
than those referred to in sub- clauses (a) and (b);


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1303434</tid>
<number>11</number>all other words and expression used herein but not defined 
and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1778765</tid>
<number> 3</number> Application of the Act.
<section><tid>1955398</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub-  
section (2) and sub- section (3), this Act shall apply in relation to 
every hotel wherein the room charges for residential accommodation 
provided to any person at any time during the previous year are 
seventy- five rupees or more per day per individual.
Explanation.-- Where the room charges are payable otherwise than 
on daily basis or per individual, then the room charges shall be 
computed as for a day and per individual based on the period of 
occupation of the residential accommodation for which the charges are 
payable and the number of individuals ordinarily permitted to occupy 
such accommodation according to the rules and custom of the hotel.


</section>

<section><tid>1330259</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a composite charge is payable in respect of residential 
accommodation and food, the room charges included therein shall be 
determined in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1749839</tid>
<number>3</number>Where--

<subsection><tid>1875087</tid>
<number>i</number>a composite charge is payable in respect of residential 
accommodation, food, drink and other services, or any of them, 
and the case is not covered by the provisions of sub- section (2), 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>976996</tid>
<number>ii</number>it appears to the Income- tax Officer that the charges 
for residential accommodation, food, drink or other services are 
so arranged that the room charges are understated and the other 
charges are overstated,
the Income- tax Officer shall, for the purposes of sub- section (1), 
determine the room charges on such reasonable basis as he may deem 
fit.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>349</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1659359</tid>
<number> 4</number> Tax authorities.
<section><tid>833973</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Director of Inspection,  
Commissioner of Income- Tax, Commissioner of Income- tax (Appeals), 
Inspecting Assistant Commissioner of Income- tax, Officer and Inspector 
of Income- tax shall have the like powers and perform the like 
functions under this Act as he has and performs under the Income- tax 
Act, and for the exercise of his powers and the performance of his 
functions, his jurisdiction under this Act shall be the same as he has 
under the Income- tax Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1249846</tid>
<number>2</number>All officers and persons employed in the execution of this 
Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions 
of the Board:
Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be 
issued--


<subsection><tid>124814</tid>
<number>a</number>so as to require any tax authority to make a particular 
assessment or to dispose of a particular case in a particular 
manner; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>548658</tid>
<number>b</number>so as to interfere with the discretion of the 
Commissioner (Appeals) in the exercise of his appellate 
functions.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1669725</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Income- tax Officer employed in the execution of this 
Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions 
issued for his guidance by the Director of Inspection or by the 
Commissioner or by the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner within whose 
jurisdiction he performs his functions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1057419</tid>
<number> 5</number> Charge of tax.
<section><tid>1480541</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act,  
there shall be charged on every person carrying on the business of a 
hotel in relation to which this Act applies, for every assessment year 
commencing on or after the 1st day of April, <year>1981</year>, a tax in respect of 
his chargeable receipts of the previous year at the rate of fifteen 
per cent. of such receipts:
Provided that where such chargeable receipts include any charges 
received in foreign exchange, then, the tax payable by the assessee 
shall be reduced by an amount equal to five per cent. of the charges 
 (exclusive of the amounts payable by way of sales tax, entertainment  
  tax, tax on luxuries or tax under this Act) so received in foreign 
exchange.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section,--


<subsection><tid>917192</tid>
<number>a</number>charges received in Indian currency obtained by 
conversion of foreign exchange into Indian currency shall, in 
such cases and in such circumstances as may be prescribed, be 
deemed to have been received in foreign exchange; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1592448</tid>
<number>b</number>" foreign exchange" and" Indian currency" shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in clauses (h) and (k) of 
section 2 of the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year> (46 of  
  <year>1973</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1285552</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, under an arrangement made between a person carrying on 
the business of a hotel to which this Act applies and any other person 
having close connection with him, any food, drink or other services is 
or are provided on the premises of such hotel by the second- mentioned 
person and the Income- tax Officer is of opinion that such arrangement 
has been made with a view to avoiding or reducing the liability under 
this Act by the first- mentioned person, then,

<subsection><tid>399234</tid>
<number>a</number>the second- mentioned person shall also be deemed to be a 
person carrying on the business of a hotel to which this Act 
applies; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>991618</tid>
<number>b</number>hotel- receipts tax shall be charged on the second- 
mentioned person in respect of charges for food, drink or other 
services so provided by him as if such charges were the 
chargeable receipts of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>350</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

business of a hotel deemed to be carried on by him under clause 
 (a), and all the provisions of this Act shall apply accordingly.

Explanation.-- For the purposes of this sub- section,--


<subsubsection><tid>180464</tid>
<number>i</number>a close connection shall be deemed to exist between a 
person carrying on the business of a hotel and another person if, 
in relation to the person carrying on the business of a hotel, 
such other person is a person referred to in clause (b) of sub- 
section (2) of section 40A of the Income- tax Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>812604</tid>
<number>ii</number>any food, drink or other service shall be deemed to 
have been provided on the premises of a hotel if the same is or 
are provided in the hotel or any place appurtenant thereto and 
where the hotel is situate in a part of building, in any other 
part of the building.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>193835</tid>
<number> 6</number> Scope of chargeable receipts.
<section><tid>45158</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act, the chargeable receipts of any previous year of an assessee 
shall be the total amount of all charges, by whatever name called, 
received by, or accruing or arising to, the assessee in connection 
with the provision of residential accommodation, food, drink and other 
services or any of them (including such charges from persons not  
provided with such accommodation <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> but excluding such charges from 
persons within] the purview of the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic 
Relations, <year>1961</year> or the Vienna Convention on Consular Relations, <year>1963</year> 
in the course of carrying on the business of a hotel to which this 
Act applies and shall also include every amount collected by the 
assessee by way of tax under this Act, sales tax, entertainment tax 
and tax on luxuries.

</section>

<section><tid>1035305</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that where 
any such charges have been included in the chargeable receipts of any 
previous year as charges accruing or arising to the assessee during 
that previous year, such charges shall not be included in the 
chargeable receipts of any subsequent previous year in which they are 
received by the assessee.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1589124</tid>
<number> 7</number> Computation of chargeable receipts.
<section><tid>751997</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2), the following deductions shall be 
allowed in computing the chargeable receipts of any previous year--

<subsection><tid>1213883</tid>
<number>i</number>the amount of charges accruing or arising in an earlier 
previous year which is established to have become a bad debt 
during the previous year:
Provided that such charges have been taken into account in 
computing the chargeable receipts of the assessee of any earlier 
previous year and the amount has been written off as 
irrecoverable in the accounts of the assessee for the previous 
year during which it is established to have become a bad debt;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>17921</tid>
<number>ii</number>any amount payable by way of sales tax, entertainment 
tax or tax on luxuries in respect of any charges included in the 
chargeable receipts of the previous year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>47263</tid>
<number>iii</number>the amount of tax chargeable under this Act.
Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that in computing the chargeable receipts of a previous year, no 
deduction, other than the deductions specified in this sub- section, 
shall be allowed from the total amount of charges received by, or 
accruing or arising to, the assessee.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1139411</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the chargeable receipts of a previous year, the 
amount of charges which is received by or which accrues or arises to 
the assessee before the expiry of one month from the end of the month 
in which this Act comes into force <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or after the 27th day of 
February, <year>1982</year>] shall not be taken into account.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>688318</tid>
<number>1</number>Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1982</year>, s. 41 (retrospectively). 
2. Ins. by s. 42, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1982</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>351</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1131726</tid>
<number> 8</number> Return of chargeable receipts.
<section><tid>548298</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person, who, during  
the previous year, carried on the business of a hotel in relation to 
which this Act applies or is assessable in respect of the chargeable 
receipts of any other person under this Act, shall furnish a return of 
his chargeable receipts or the chargeable receipts of such other 
person of the previous year in the prescribed form and verified in the 
prescribed manner and setting forth such other particulars as may be 
prescribed, before the expiry of four months from the end of the 
previous year in respect of the business of the hotel or where there 
is more than one previous year in respect of such business, from the 
end of the previous year which expired last before the commencement of 
the assessment year, or before the 30th day of June of the assessment 
year, whichever is later:
Provided that, on an application made in this behalf, the Income- 
tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for furnishing the 
return.


</section>

<section><tid>611227</tid>
<number>2</number>In the case of any person who, in the Income- tax Officer' s 
opinion is assessable under this Act, whether in respect of his own 
chargeable receipts or in respect of the chargeable receipts of any 
other person, the Income- tax Officer may, before the end of the 
relevant assessment year, issue a notice to him and serve the same 
upon him, requiring him to furnish within thirty days from the date of 
service of the notice a return of his chargeable receipts or the 
chargeable receipts of such other person of the previous year in the 
prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner and setting 
forth such other particulars as may be prescribed:
Provided that on an application made in this behalf, the Income- 
tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for furnishing the 
return.


</section>

<section><tid>1809548</tid>
<number>3</number>Any assessee who has not furnished a return within the time 
allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), or having furnished 
a return under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), discovers any 
omission or wrong statement therein, may furnish a return or a revised 
return, as the case may be, at any time before the assessment is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>162578</tid>
<number> 9</number> Self- assessment.
<section><tid>1353053</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any hotel- receipts tax is payable  
on the basis of any return required to be furnished under section 8 or 
section 13 after taking into account the amount of hotel- receipts tax, 
if any, already paid under any provision of this Act, the assessee 
shall be liable to pay such tax before furnishing the return and the 
return shall be accompanied by proof of payment of such tax.

</section>

<section><tid>734419</tid>
<number>2</number>After an assessment under section 10 or section 11 has been 
made, any amount paid under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have 
been paid towards such assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>587899</tid>
<number>3</number>If any assessee fails to pay the hotel- receipts tax or any 
part thereof in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Income- tax Officer may direct that a sum equal to two per cent. of 
such tax or part thereof, as the case may be, shall be recovered from 
him by way of penalty for every month during which the default 
continues:
Provided that before levying any such penalty, the assessee shall 
be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>16087</tid>
<number> 10</number> Assessment.
<section><tid>1328702</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of making an assessment under  
this Act, the Income- tax Officer may serve on any person who has 
furnished a return

<pagefootnote><pagenum>352</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

under section 8 or upon whom a notice has been served under sub- 
section (2) of section 8 (whether a return has been furnished or not) 
a notice requiring him on a date therein to be specified, to produce 
or cause to be produced such accounts or documents or other evidence 
as the Income- tax Officer may require for the purposes of this Act and 
may, from time to time, serve further notices requiring the production 
of such further accounts or documents or other evidence as he may 
require.


</section>

<section><tid>587938</tid>
<number>2</number>The Income- tax Officer, after considering such accounts, 
documents or other evidence, if any, as he has obtained under sub- 
section (1) and after taking into account any relevant material which 
he has gathered, shall, by an order in writing, assess the chargeable 
receipts and the amount of the hotel- receipts tax payable on the basis 
of such assessment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>824461</tid>
<number> 11</number> Best judgment assessment. If--
<section><tid>510918</tid>
<number>a</number>any person fails to make the return required by any 
notice given under sub- section (2) of section 8 and has not made 
a return or a revised return under sub- section (3) of that 
section, or

</section>

<section><tid>1287906</tid>
<number>b</number>any person having made a return, fails to comply with 
all the terms of a notice issued under sub- section (1) of section 
10, or

</section>

<section><tid>1548412</tid>
<number>c</number>the Income- tax Officer is not satisfied about the 
correctness or the completeness of the accounts of the assessee,
the Income- tax Officer, after taking into account all relevant 
material which he has gathered, shall make the assessment of the 
chargeable receipts to the best of his judgment and determine the sum 
payable by the assessee or refundable to the assessee on the basis of 
such assessment.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1189231</tid>
<number> 12</number> Re- opening of assessment at the instance of the assessee.
<section><tid>154440</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where an assessee assessed under section 11 makes an application to 
the Income- tax Officer, within one month from the date of service of a 
notice of demand issued in consequence of the assessment, for the 
cancellation of the assessment on the ground--

<subsection><tid>1176647</tid>
<number>i</number>that he was prevented by sufficient cause from making 
the return required under sub- section (2) of section 8, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>438898</tid>
<number>ii</number>that he did not receive the notice issued under sub- 
section (1) of section 10, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1411256</tid>
<number>iii</number>that he had not a reasonable opportunity to comply, or 
was prevented by sufficient cause from complying, with the terms 
of the notice referred to in clause (ii),
the Income- tax Officer shall, if satisfied about the existence of such 
ground, cancel the assessment and proceed to make a fresh assessment 
in accordance with the provisions of section 10 or section 11.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1151154</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application made under sub- section (1) shall be 
disposed of within ninety days from the date of receipt thereof by the 
Income- tax Officer:
Provided that in computing the period of ninety days aforesaid, 
any delay in disposing of the application which is attributable to the 
assessee shall be excluded.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>353</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>651565</tid>
<number> 13</number> Receipt' s escaping assessment. If--
<section><tid>1725292</tid>
<number>a</number>the Income- tax Officer has reason to believe that by 
reason of the omission or failure on the part of the assessee to 
make a return under section 8 for any assessment year or to 
disclose fully and truly all material facts necessary for his 
assessment for any assessment year, chargeable receipts for that 
year have escaped assessment or have been under- assessed or have 
been made the subject of excessive relief under this Act, or

</section>

<section><tid>162956</tid>
<number>b</number>notwithstanding that there has been no omission or 
failure as mentioned in clause (a) on the part of the assessee, 
the Income- tax Officer has, in consequence of information in his 
possession, reason to believe that chargeable receipts assessable 
for any assessment year have escaped assessment or have been 
under- assessed or have been the subject of excessive relief under 
this Act,
he may, in cases falling under clause (a), at any time, and in cases 
falling under clause (b), at any time within four years of the end of 
that assessment year, serve on the assessee a notice containing all or 
any of the requirements which may be included in a notice under 
section 8 and may proceed to assess or reassess the amount chargeable 
to hotel- receipts tax, and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as 
may be, apply, as if the notice were a notice issued under that 
section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1171770</tid>
<number> 14</number> Advance payment of hotel receipts tax.
<section><tid>1002241</tid>
<number>1</number>Hotel- receipts tax  
shall be payable in advance during the financial year in respect of 
the chargeable receipts of the period which would be the previous year 
for the immediately following assessment year in accordance with the 
provisions of this section.

</section>

<section><tid>354977</tid>
<number>2</number>Hotel- receipts tax shall be payable in advance in two 
instalments on the following dates during the financial year, namely:- 
-

<subsection><tid>126498</tid>
<number>i</number>the 15th day of September in respect of the chargeable 
receipts attributable to the first half of the previous year; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1925623</tid>
<number>ii</number>the 15th day of March in respect of the chargeable 
receipts attributable to the second half of the previous year:
Provided that the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance during 
the financial year commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1980</year> shall be 
payable in one sum on the 15th day of March, <year>1981</year>.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1322081</tid>
<number>3</number>Every assessee shall, in each financial year, on or before 
such of the dates on which an instalment of hotel- receipts tax is 
payable in advance, send to the Income- tax Officer, an estimate of the 
chargeable receipts attributable to the relevant part of the previous 
year and the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance on such chargeable 
receipts and shall pay such amount of hotel- receipts tax as accords 
with his estimate on or before the relevant date specified in sub- 
section (2):
Provided that in respect of the hotel- receipts tax payable in 
advance during the financial year commencing on the 1st day of April, 
<year>1980</year>, the assessee shall send to the Income- tax Officer an estimate of 
the chargeable receipts attributable to the period which would be the 
previous year for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1981</year> and the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance on such 
chargeable receipts and shall pay such amount of hotel- receipts tax as 
accords with his estimate on or before the 15th day of March, <year>1981</year>.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>354</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>289504</tid>
<number>4</number>Every estimate under this section shall be sent in the 
prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>28671</tid>
<number>5</number>If any assessee does not pay on or before the specified date 
any instalment of hotel- receipts tax payable in advance, he shall be 
deemed to be an assessee in default in respect of such instalment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1580804</tid>
<number> 15</number> Penalty for failure to furnish returns, comply with notices, 
concealment of receipts, etc.
<section><tid>949682</tid>
<number>1</number>If, in the course of any proceedings  
under this Act, the Income- tax Officer or the Commissioner (Appeals) 
is satisfied that any person--

<subsection><tid>926835</tid>
<number>a</number>has, without reasonable cause, failed to furnish the 
return of chargeable receipts which he was required to furnish 
under sub- section (1) of section 8 or by notice given under sub- 
section (2) of section 8 or section 13 or has, without reasonable 
cause, failed to furnish it within the time allowed and the 
manner required by sub- section (1) of section 8 or by such 
notice, as the case may be, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>690742</tid>
<number>b</number>has, without reasonable cause, failed to comply with the 
notice under sub- section (1) of section 10, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1269130</tid>
<number>c</number>has concealed the particulars of his chargeable receipts 
or furnished inaccurate particulars of such receipts,
he may direct that such person shall pay by way of penalty,--


<subsubsection><tid>699511</tid>
<number>i</number>in the cases referred to in clause (a), in addition to 
the hotel- receipts tax payable by him, a sum equal to two per 
cent. of the assessed tax for every month during which the 
default continued, but not exceeding in the aggregate fifty per 
cent. of the assessed tax.
Explanation.-- In this clause," assessed tax" means 
hotel- receipts tax chargeable under the provisions of this Act, 
as reduced by the sum, if any, paid in advance under section 14;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>829166</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the cases referred to in clause (b), in addition to 
the hotel- receipts tax payable by him, a sum which shall not be 
less than ten per cent. but which shall not exceed fifty per 
cent. of the amount of the hotel- receipts tax which would have 
been avoided if the return made by him had been accepted as 
correct;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>973165</tid>
<number>iii</number>in the cases referred to in clause (c), in addition to 
the hotel receipts tax payable by him, a sum which shall not be 
less than, but which shall not exceed twice, the amount of hotel- 
receipts tax which would have been avoided if the return made by 
him had been accepted as correct:
Provided that in a case falling under clause (c), the Income- tax 
Officer shall not impose any penalty without the previous approval of 
the Inspecting Assistant Commissioner.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>139322</tid>
<number>2</number>On making an order imposing a penalty under this section, the 
Commissioner (Appeals) shall forthwith send a copy of the same to the 
Income- tax Officer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>598261</tid>
<number> 16</number> Penality for false estimate of, or failure to pay, hotel- 
receipts tax payable in advance. If, in the course of any proceedings 
in connection with the assessment under section 10 or section 11, the 
Income- tax Officer is satisfied that any assessee--
<section><tid>1980509</tid>
<number>a</number>has furnished under section 14, an estimate of the 
hotel- receipts tax payable in advance by him which he knew or had 
reason to believe to be untrue, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>355</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1521960</tid>
<number>b</number>has, without reasonable cause, failed to furnish an 
estimate of the hotel- receipts tax payable in advance by him in 
accordance with the provisions of section 14,
he may direct that the assessee shall, in addition to the hotel- 
receipts tax payable by him, pay by way of penalty a sum--


<subsection><tid>61071</tid>
<number>i</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall not 
be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a half 
times the amount by which the hotel- receipts tax paid in advance 
during the financial year immediately preceding the assessment 
year, falls short of eighty- five per cent. of the hotel- receipts 
tax chargeable under the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>876170</tid>
<number>ii</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall not 
be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a half 
times of eighty- five per cent. of the hotel- receipts tax 
chargeable under the provisions of this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1903778</tid>
<number>17</number>Opportunity of being heard. No order imposing penalty under 
section 15 or section 16 shall be made unless the assessee has been 
heard, or has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</article>



<article><tid>1025023</tid>
<number> 18</number> Appeals to the Commissioner (Appeals).
<section><tid>1570149</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person  
objecting to the amount of hotel- receipts tax for which he is assessed 
by the Income- tax Officer, or denying his liablility to be assessed 
under this Act, or objecting to an order under section 12 refusing to 
re- open an assessment made under section 11 or objecting to any 
penalty or fine imposed by the Income- tax Officer, or to the amount 
allowed by the Income- tax Officer by way of any relief under any 
provision of this Act, or to any refusal by the Income- tax Officer to 
grant relief, or to an order of rectification having the effect of 
enhancing the assessment or reducing the refund, or to an order 
refusing to allow the claim made by the assessee for a rectification 
under section 20, may appeal to the Commissioner (Appeals).

</section>

<section><tid>640225</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be 
verified in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>811399</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal shall be presented within thirty days of the 
following date, that is to say,--

<subsection><tid>1871638</tid>
<number>a</number>where the appeal relates to assessment or penalty or 
fine, the date of service of the notice of demand relating to the 
assessment or penalty or fine, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>613861</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, the date on which the intimation of 
the order sought to be appealed against is served:
Provided that the Commissioner (Appeals) may admit an appeal 
after the expiration of the said period if he is satisfied that the 
appellant had sufficient cause for not presenting it within that 
period.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>204257</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner (Appeals) shall hear and determine the 
appeal and, subject to the provisions of this Act, pass such orders as 
he thinks fit and such orders may include an order enhancing the 
assessment or penalty:
Provided that an order enhancing the assessment or penalty shall 
not be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a 
reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>356</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>435035</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure to be adopted in the hearing and determination 
of the appeals shall, with any necessary modification, be in 
accordance with the procedure applicable in relation to income- tax.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>350333</tid>
<number> 19</number> Appeals to Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>349287</tid>
<number>1</number>Any assessee aggrieved by  
an order passed by a Commissioner under section 22, or an order passed 
by a Commissioner (Appeals) under any provision of this Act, may 
appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against such order.

</section>

<section><tid>355729</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner may, if he objects to any order passed by 
the Commissioner (Appeals) under any provision of this Act, direct the 
Income- tax Officer to appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against the 
order.

</section>

<section><tid>1168478</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall 
be filed within sixty days of the date on which the order sought to be 
appealed against is communicated to the assessee or to the 
Commissioner, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1258303</tid>
<number>4</number>The Income- tax Officer or the assessee, as the case may be, 
on receipt or a notice that an appeal against the order of the 
Commissioner (Appeals) has been preferred under sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) by the other party may, notwithstanding that he may 
not have appealed against such order or any part thereof, within 
thirty days of the receipt of the notice, file a memorandum of cross- 
objections, verified in the prescribed manner, against any part of the 
order of the Commissioner (Appeals), and such memorandum shall be 
disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it were an appeal 
presented within the time specified in sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>711893</tid>
<number>5</number>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the 
filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the 
relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if 
it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it 
within that period.

</section>

<section><tid>340397</tid>
<number>6</number>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the 
prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and 
shall, except in the case of an appeal referred to in sub- section (2) 
or a memorandum of cross- objections referred to in sub- section (4), be 
accompanied by a fee of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two hundred rupees].

</section>

<section><tid>320799</tid>
<number>7</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, in hearing and making 
an order on any appeal under this section, the Appellate Tribunal 
shall exercise the same powers and follow the same procedure as it 
exercises and follows in hearing and making an order on any appeal 
under the Income- tax Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1297400</tid>
<number> 20</number> Rectification of mistakes.
<section><tid>758868</tid>
<number>1</number>With a view to rectifying any  
mistake apparent from the record, the Income- tax Officer, the 
Commissioner (Appeals), the Commissioner and the Appellate Tribunal 
may, of his or its own motion or on an application by the assessee in 
this behalf, or where the authority concerned is the Commissioner 
 (Appeals), by the Income- tax Officer also, amend any order passed by 
him or it in any proceeding under this Act within four years of the 
date on which such order was passed.

</section>

<section><tid>978943</tid>
<number>2</number>An amendment which has the effect of enhancing the assessment 
or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability of the 
assessee shall not be made under this section unless the authority 
concerned has
<pagefootnote><pagenum>357</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 45 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


given notice to the assessee of its intention so to do and has allowed 
the assessee a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>935758</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an amendment is made under this section, the order 
shall be passed in writing by the authority concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>828199</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, where any such 
amendment has the effect of reducing the assessment, the Income- tax 
Officer shall make any refund which may be due to such assessee.

</section>

<section><tid>1066818</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the 
assessment or reducing the refund already made, the Income- tax Officer 
shall serve on the assessee a notice of demand in the prescribed form 
specifying the sum payable.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>201425</tid>
<number>21</number>Hotel- receipts tax deductible in computing total income under 
Income- tax Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax 
Act, in computing the income chargeable to income- tax under the head 
" Profits and gains of business or profession" in the case of an 
assessee carrying on the business of a hotel to which this Act 
applies, the hotel- receipts tax payable by the assessee for any 
assessment year shall be deductible from the profits and gains of the 
business of the hotel assessable for that assessment year.


</article>



<article><tid>1610547</tid>
<number> 22</number> Revision of order prejudicial to revenue.
<section><tid>639402</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Commissioner may call for and examine the record of any proceeding 
under this Act and if he considers that any order passed therein by 
the Income- tax Officer is erroneous in so far as it is prejudicial to 
the interests of the revenue, he may, after giving the assessee an 
opportunity of being heard and after making or causing to be made such 
enquiry as he deems necessary, pass such order thereon as the 
circumstances of the case justify, including an order enhancing or 
modifying the assessment, or cancelling the assessment and directing a 
fresh assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>1703392</tid>
<number>2</number>No order shall be made under sub- section (1)--

<subsection><tid>1593110</tid>
<number>a</number>to revise an order of reassessment made under section 
13, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1225474</tid>
<number>b</number>after the expiry of two years from the date of the order 
sought to be revised.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>289503</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), an 
order in revision under this section may be passed at any time in the 
case of an order which has been passed in consequence of, or to give 
effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order of the 
Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the Supreme Court.
Explanation.-- In computing the period of limitation for the 
purposes of sub- section (2), any period during which any proceeding 
under this section is stayed by an order or injunction of any court 
shall be excluded.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>864667</tid>
<number> 23</number> Revision of orders by Commissioner.
<section><tid>473450</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commissioner may,  
either of his own motion or on an application by the assessee for 
revision, call for the record of any proceeding under this Act which 
has been taken by an Income- tax Officer subordinate to him and may 
make such enquiry or cause such enquiry to be made and, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, may pass such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>358</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

order thereon, not being an order prejudicial to the assessee, as he 
thinks fit.


</section>

<section><tid>1392012</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner shall not of his own motion revise any order 
under this section if the order has been made more than one year 
previously.

</section>

<section><tid>356071</tid>
<number>3</number>In the case of an application for revision under this section 
by the assessee, the application shall be made within one year from 
the date on which the order in question was communicated to him or the 
date on which he otherwise came to know of it, whichever is earlier:
Provided that the Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the 
assessee was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application 
within that period, admit an application made after the expiry of that 
period.


</section>

<section><tid>951882</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall not revise any order under this 
section in the following cases:--

<subsection><tid>1839410</tid>
<number>a</number>where an appeal against the order lies to the 
Commissioner (Appeals) but has not been made and the time within 
which such appeal may be made has not expired, or the assessee 
has not waived his right of appeal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1145890</tid>
<number>b</number>where the order has been made the subject of an appeal 
to the Commissioner (Appeals).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1861243</tid>
<number>5</number>Every application by an assessee for revision under this 
section shall be accompanied by a fee of twenty- five rupees.
Explanation.-- An order by the Commissioner declining to interfere 
shall, for the purposes of this section, be deemed not to be an order 
prejudicial to the assessee.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1184574</tid>
<number> 24</number> Application of provisions of Income- tax Act. The provisions 
of the following sections and Schedules of the Income- tax Act and the 
Income- tax (Certificate Proceedings) Rules, <year>1962</year>, as in force from 
time to time, shall apply with necessary modifications as if the said 
provisions and the rules referred to hotel- receipts tax instead of to 
income- tax:--
<section><tid>562904</tid>
<number>43B</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and (44), 41 (4), 118, 125, 125A, 128 to 136 (both  
  inclusive), 138, 140, 144A, 156, 159 to 163 (both inclusive), 
166, 167, 170, 171, 173 to 179 (both inclusive), 187, 188, 189, 
 219 to 227 (both inclusive), 228A, 229, 231, 232, 237 to 242 
 (both inclusive), 244, 245, 254 to 262 (both inclusive), 265, 
266, 268, 269, 278B, 278C, 278D, 281, 281B, 282, 283, 284, 287, 
288, 288A, 288B, 289 to 293 (both inclusive), the Second Schedule 
and the Third Schedule:
Provided that references in the said provisions and the rules to 
the" assessee" shall be construed as references to an assessee as 
defined in this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1643602</tid>
<number> 25</number> Income- tax papers to be available for the purposes of this 
Act.
<section><tid>1216449</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, all  
information contained in any statement or return made or furnished 
under the provisions of that Act or obtained or collected for the 
purposes of that Act may be used for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1588982</tid>
<number>2</number>All information contained in any statement or return made on 
furnished under the provisions of this Act or obtained or collected 
for the purposes of this Act may be used for the purposes of the 
Income- tax Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>359</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1604209</tid>
<number> 26</number> Wilful attempt to evade tax, etc.
<section><tid>1780390</tid>
<number>1</number>If a person wilfully  
attempts in any manner whatsoever to evade any tax, penalty or 
interest chargeable or imposable under this Act, he shall, without 
prejudice to any penalty that may be imposable on him under any other 
provision of this Act, be punishable,--

<subsection><tid>1253562</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount sought to be evaded exceeds 
one hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than six months but which may extend 
to seven years and with fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1927282</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than three months but which may 
extend to three years and with fine.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1449835</tid>
<number>2</number>If a person wilfully attempts in any manner whatsoever to 
evade the payment of any tax, penalty or interest under this Act, he 
shall, without prejudice to any penalty that may be imposable on him 
under any other provision of this Act, be punishable with rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months but 
which may extend to three years and shall, in the discretion of the 
court, also be liable to fine.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, a wilful attempt 
to evade any tax, penalty or interest chargeable or imposable under 
this Act or the payment thereof shall include a case where any person- 
-


<subsection><tid>1460194</tid>
<number>i</number>has in his possession or control any books of account or 
other documents (being books of account or other documents  
  relevant to any proceeding under this Act) containing a false 
entry or statement; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1111237</tid>
<number>ii</number>makes or causes to be made any false entry or statement 
in such books of account or other documents; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>58381</tid>
<number>iii</number>wilfully omits or causes to be omitted any relevant 
entry or statement in such books of account or other documents; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901853</tid>
<number>iv</number>causes any other circumstance to exist which will have 
the effect of enabling such person to evade any tax, penalty or 
interest chargeable or imposable under this Act or the payment 
thereof.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1537178</tid>
<number> 27</number> Failure to furnish returns of chargeable receipts. If a 
person wilfully fails to furnish in due time the return of chargeable 
receipts which he is required to furnish under sub- section
<section><tid>318610</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 8 or by notice given under sub- section (2) of section 8 or 
section 13, he shall be punishable,--

<subsection><tid>1708585</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount of tax, which would have been 
evaded if the failure had not been discovered, exceeds one 
hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to 
seven years and with fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1297285</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than three months but which may extend to three 
years and with fine:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>360</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that a person shall not be proceeded against under this 
section for failure to furnish in due time the return of chargeable 
receipts under sub- section (1) of section 8, if--


<subsubsection><tid>35316</tid>
<number>a</number>the return is furnished by him before the expiry of the 
assessment year; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1927512</tid>
<number>b</number>the tax payable by him on the chargeable receipts 
determined on assessment as reduced by the tax paid in advance 
under section 14, if any, does not exceed three thousand rupees.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1081386</tid>
<number> 28</number> Failure to produce accounts and documents. If a person 
wilfully fails to produce, or cause to be produced, on or before the 
date specified in any notice served on him under sub- section
<section><tid>1995688</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 10, such accounts and documents as are referred to in the 
notice, he shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to one year, or with fine equal to a sum calculated 
at a rate which shall not be less than four rupees or more than ten 
rupees for every day during which the default continues, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1869015</tid>
<number> 29</number> False statement in verification, etc. If a person makes a 
statement in any verification under this Act or under any rule made 
thereunder, or delivers an account or statement which is false, and 
which he either knows or believes to be false, or does not believe to 
be true, he shall be punishable,--
<section><tid>108765</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount of tax, which would have been 
evaded if the statement or account had been accepted as true, 
exceeds one hundred thousand rupees, with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than six months but which may 
extend to seven years and with fine;

</section>

<section><tid>1225909</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than three months but which may 
extend to three years and with fine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1657230</tid>
<number> 30</number> Abetment of false return, etc. If a person abets or induces 
in any manner another person to make and deliver an account or a 
statement or declaration relating to any chargeable receipts which is 
false and which he either knows to be false or does not believe to be 
true or to commit an offence under sub- section
<section><tid>17231</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 26, he  
shall be punishable,--

<subsection><tid>1562845</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case where the amount of tax, penalty or interest 
which would have been evaded, if the declaration, account or 
statement had been accepted as true, or which is wilfully 
attempted to be evaded, exceeds one hundred thousand rupees, with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than six 
months but which may extend to seven years and with fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>50733</tid>
<number>ii</number>in any other case, with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which shall not be less than three months but which may 
extend to three years and with fine.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1965360</tid>
<number> 31</number> Punishment for second and subsequent offences. If any person 
convicted of an offence under sub- section
<section><tid>147508</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 26 or section  
 27 or section 29 or section 30 is again convicted for an offence under 
any of the aforesaid provisions, he shall be punishable for the second 
and for every subsequent offence with rigorous imprisonment for a term 
which shall not be less than six months but which may extend to seven 
years and with fine.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>361</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>496116</tid>
<number>32</number>Certain offences to be non- cognizable. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of  
  <year>1974</year>), an offence punishable under section 26 or section 27 or section 
 29 or section 30 shall be deemed to be non- cognizable within the 
meaning of that Code.


</article>



<article><tid>1429999</tid>
<number> 33</number> Institution of proceedings and composition of offences.
<section><tid>128635</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
person shall not be proceeded against for any offence under section 26 
or section 27 or section 28 or section 29 or section 30 for any 
offence under the Indian Penal Code relating to any matter connected 
with or arising out of this Act, (45 of <year>1860</year>) except at the instance 
of the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1887901</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner may, either before or after the institution 
of proceedings, compound any offence punishable under section 26 or 
section 27 or section 28 or section 29 or section 30.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>49994</tid>
<number> 34</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1041541</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, subject to the  
control of the Central Government, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>33037</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>233244</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the room charges may be determined 
under sub- section (2) of section 3 in cases where composite 
charges are payable in respect of residential accommodation and 
food;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1841480</tid>
<number>b</number>the cases and the circumstances in which payments made 
in Indian currency by conversion of foreign exchange into Indian 
currency shall be deemed to have been made in foreign exchange 
for the purposes of sub- section (1) of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>906255</tid>
<number>c</number>the form in which returns under section 8 may be 
furnished, the manner in which they may be verified and the other 
particulars which a form may contain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>145143</tid>
<number>d</number>the form in which an estimate under section 14 may be 
sent and the manner in which it may be verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>326445</tid>
<number>e</number>the form in which appeals under section 18 or section 19 
may be filed and the manner in which they may be verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>911546</tid>
<number>f</number>the form in which a memorandum of cross- objections under 
sub- section (4) of section 19 may be verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>523029</tid>
<number>g</number>the procedure to be followed on applications for 
rectification of mistakes under section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489504</tid>
<number>h</number>the form in which a notice of demand may be served on 
the assessee under sub- section (5) of section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>94442</tid>
<number>i</number>any other matter which by this Act is to be or may be 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1530672</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to make rules conferred by this section shall on 
the first occasion of the exercise thereof include the power to give 
retrospective effect to the rules or any of them from a date not 
earlier than the date of commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1465139</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall cause every rule made under this 
section to be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty

<pagefootnote><pagenum>362</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>591603</tid>
<number>35</number>Power to exempt. Where the Central Government is of the 
opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do either in the 
public interest or having regard to the peculiar circumstances of the 
case, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette and subject to 
such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the notification, 
exempt any hotel or any class of hotels from the levy of hotel- 
receipts tax.


</article>



<article><tid>1333549</tid>
<number>36</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the commencement of this Act.




</article>



 </act>