<act><title>THE  PLANT VARIETIES PROTECTION APPELLATE TRIBUNAL (APPLICATIONS 
AND APPEALS) RULES, 20101</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.</title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Plant Varieties Protection Appellate Tribunal (Applications and Appeals) Rules, 2010. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers' Rights  
    Act, 2001 (53 of 2001); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> rules means rules made under the Act. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> words and expressions used in these rules and not defined, but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Appeals to the Tribunal. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by an order or decision of the Authority or Registrar may prefer an appeal to the Tribunal within three months from the date on which the order or decision of the Authority or Registrar sought to be appealed against is communicated to such person preferring the appeal. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No appeal shall be admitted if it is preferred after the expiry of the period referred to in sub-rule (1): 
 Provided that an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the period referred to in sub-rule (1), if the appellant satisfies the Tribunal that he or she has sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within the specified period. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A copy of the order or decision of the Authority or Registrar appealed against shall accompany an appeal to the Tribunal. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Forms for making application for appeal. </title>The form of making applications for appeal to the Tribunal shall be as specified in the Schedule to these rules. 


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 21-9-2010.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>