<act><title>


the Highways Administration Rules, 2004*</title> 

 


 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules will be called the Highways Administration Rules, 2004.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date1 on 
which the Act shall come into force.
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Control of National Highways (Land and Traffic) Act, 
2002 (13 of 2003);
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>  
“section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Officer”, in respect of a Highway Administration, means the Officer 
referred to in clause (i) or clause (ii) of rule 3, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  “Senior Officer”, in respect of a Highway Administration, means the 
Officer designated as Senior Officer under clause (ii) of rule 3;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  “permit” means a permit issued under sub-section (2) of section 24 for 
granting permission under that sub-section;
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  “lease” means the lease granted under section 25;
 </section><section>

<number>g</number>  “licence”, 
for the purposes of rules 9 and 10, means the licence granted under section 25;
 </section><section>
       
<number>h</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule annexed to these rules; 
 </section><section>
        
<number>i</number>  words and expressions used in these rules which are not defined in 
these rules but are defined in the Act shall have the respective meanings 
assigned to them in the Act.
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>3</number> Exercise of powers 
and functions by Highway Administrations.—Subject 
to the provisions of the Act and the conditions or limitations imposed by the 
Central Government under the proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 3,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  where a Highway Administration consists of only one Officer, then, 
such Officer shall exercise the powers and discharge the functions of the 
Highway Administration under the Act and these rules by himself or such powers 
shall be exercised and functions shall be discharged by the subordinate officers 
under his supervision to the extent as is authorised by such Officer to the 
subordinate Officers from time to time;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  where a
Highway 
Administration consists of more than one Officer, then, the Central Government 
shall designate one of them as the Senior Officer who shall assign to each of 
such Officers (including himself), the length of Highway within the jurisdiction 
of such Highways and the Officer to whom such length of Highways is so assigned 
shall exercise the powers and discharge the functions of the Highway 
Administration under the Act and these rules in respect of such length of 
Highway in the manner as specified in clause (i) for exercising of powers and 
discharging of functions of Highway Administrations consisting of one Officer:
 
                 
Provided that the Senior Officer so designated shall have the general 
supervision over the exercising of powers and discharging of functions of the 
Highway Administration by the other Officers.
</subsection></section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>4</number> Maintenance of land 
records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be maintained at the head office of every Highway Administration a 
register to be called the Highway Land Register in the form specified in the 
Schedule I in which the particulars of the land situated within the jurisdiction 
of the Highway Administration of which the Central Government is the owner under 
section 23 shall be entered.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every page of the 
Highway Land Register shall be consecutively numbered and on the first page of 
the Register, the Officer or the Senior Officer, as the case may be, shall 
authenticate the number of pages which the Register contains and he shall, from 
time to time, inspect the Register and ensure that the entries made therein are 
correct.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>5</number> Claim for correction 
of records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person claiming against the ownership of the Central Government referred to 
in sub-section (1) of section 23 and desirous of getting a correction carried 
out in the Highway Land Register, shall make written complaint to the concerned 
Officer or the Senior Officer, as the case may be, and prove his claim before 
him and such Officer or Senior Officer, as the case may be, may after 
considering the evidence produced by such person order to correct the concerned 
entry in the Register or reject the claim.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Officer or 
the Senior Officer, as the case may be, orders to correct any entry in the 
Highway Land Register, such correction shall be made in that Register without 
delay by the concerned official of the Highway Administration and it shall also 
be signed by such official and counter-signed in red ink by the Officer or the 
Senior Officer, as the case may be.
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>6</number> Conditions subject 
to which permit may be issued.—A 
permit shall contain any one or more of the following conditions which the 
Highway Administration or any officer authorised under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 24, as the case may be, while granting a permission under sub-section 
(2) of the said section deems fit having regard to the safety and convenience of 
traffic and nature of the permission, namely:—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  that the person to whom the permission is granted shall not do or 
cause to be done any act in pursuance of the permission which may cause damage 
to highway and highway land or inconvenience to the traffic on the highway;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  that such person shall not do or cause to be done any act in 
pursuance of the permission which may cause any damage to the Highway land which 
cannot be restored immediately on the expiry of the permission granted;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  that such person shall not do or cause to be done any act on the 
Highway occupied in pursuance of the permission which may cause air pollution or 
water pollution or noise pollution on the Highway:
 
                 
Provided that such extent of reasonable pollution which the Central Government 
may, from time to time by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, shall 
be permissible under this clause;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  that such person shall not make or cause to be made any structure of 
such nature which cannot be removed easily on the expiry of the permission 
granted;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  that any breach of the conditions so imposed shall be a ground to 
cancel the permit.
</subsection></section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>8</number> Form of permit.—Every 
permit shall be issued in the Form specified in Schedule II.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>9</number> Condition subject to 
which a lease or licence may be granted.—A 
lease or licence of highway land granted to a person for temporary use shall 
contain the following conditions, namely:—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  such conditions which are agreed to by and between the Highway 
Administration or the officer authorised by such Administration in this behalf, 
and such person, having regard to the safety and convenience of traffic; and
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  any one or more of the following, which the Highway Administration or 
the officer authorised by such Administration deems fit, having regard to the 
safety and convenience of traffic, to impose—
 <subsection>
            
<number>a</number>  that such person shall not do or cause to be done any act on such 
Highway land which may cause damage or inconvenience to the traffic to the 
Highway;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>b</number>  that person shall not do or cause to be done any act on such Highway 
land which may cause any damage to the Highway land which cannot be restored on 
the termination of the lease or licence, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>c</number>  that such person shall not do or cause to be done any act on such 
Highway land which may cause air pollution or water pollution on the Highway;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>d</number>  that such person shall not make or cause to be made on such Highway 
land any structure of such nature which cannot be removed easily on the 
termination of the lease or licence, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>e</number>  that on any breach of the conditions imposed, the Highway 
Administration or the officer authorised by such Administration in this behalf 
may terminate the lease or licence, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>f</number>  that such lease or licence, as the case may be, shall be valid for a 
period determined by the Highway Administration at the time of lease or licence 
which shall not exceed five years on the expiry of lease.
</subsection></section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>11</number> Form of notice.—Every 
notice to be issued under sub-section (2) of section 26 shall be in the form as 
specified in Schedule III.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>12</number> The cost for making 
feasible construction, etc.—The 
cost for making construction including alteration of any construction feasible 
under sub-section (8) of section 26 shall be such as may be determined from time 
to time by the Highway Administration, having regard to the cost of material to 
be utilised for such construction or alteration of construction, the rate of 
labour charges in the concerned area and other relevant factors.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>13</number> Form of bill.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every bill to be served under sub-section (2) of section 27 shall be in the form 
as specified in Schedule IV.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The bill referred to 
in sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a certificate issued by the Highway 
Administration or the officer authorised by such Administration in this behalf 
and also with a brief description of unauthorised occupation, construction 
including alteration of construction in respect of any unauthorised construction 
or repairing of any damage, as the case may be, to which the bill belongs.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>14</number> Application for 
specific permission to access to a Highway.—The 
application for obtaining specific permission for access to a Highway under 
sub-section (2) of section 29 shall be in such Form as is specified in Schedule 
V and shall be accompanied by a fee of rupees five hundred drawn in favour of 
the concerned Highway Administration.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>15</number> Terms and 
conditions for specific permission to access to a Highway.—The 
Highway Administration may, while giving a permission under sub-section (2) of 
section 29, impose any one or more of the following terms and conditions, 
namely:—
 <section>
        
<number>i</number>  that the specific permission shall be for a limited period of time and 
for the purposes as specified by the Highway Administration in the licence 
issued under sub-section (3) of section 29;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  that the specific permission shall be limited for the access to such 
length of a Highway as may be specified in the said licence;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iii</number>  that the person to whom the specific permission is given shall not 
do or cause to be done in pursuance of the specific permission any act which may 
cause any damage to Highway;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  that such person shall not do or cause to be done, in pursuance of 
the specific permission, any act by which safety and convenience of traffic on 
the Highway shall be disturbed;
 </section><section>
       
<number>v</number>  that such person shall while utilising permission shall observe such 
guidelines relating to safety and convenience of traffic on the Highway, 
hygiene, prevention of nuisance and pollution on the Highway as may be specified 
by the Highway Administration in the said licence.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>16</number> Form of licence, 
period of validity and manner of renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The licence given under sub-section (3) of section 29 shall be in the Form as 
specified in the Schedule VI.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The specific 
permission under the licence referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be valid upto a 
period specified in the licence which shall not exceed six months at a time and 
the person in whose favour such permission is given may if he desires to obtain 
an extension of time, make an application within one month before the expiry of 
the permission so given to the Highway Administration and the Highway 
Administration may, having regard to the guidelines and instructions issued 
under sub-section (2) of section 28 and the notification under sub-section (3) 
of that section either renew the permission under the licence or reject the 
same.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the permission 
under licence is renewed under sub-rule (2), the Highway Administration shall 
make the entry for such renewal on the back of the licence and specify the time 
for which the renewal is made which shall not exceed six months at a time and 
endorse the same with signature and seal and where the renewal is rejected, the 
Highway Administration shall record the reason in writing for such rejection and 
communicate the same to the person concerned.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>17</number> Limit of laden 
weight.—The 
Highway Administration may, keeping in view the conditions of the surface of a 
Highway determine with the previous approval of the Central Government, the 
limit of laden weight in respect of the Highway or any part thereof, or any 
bridge, culvert or causeway built on or across the Highway, as the case may be, 
from time to time, which shall be the limit of laden weight for the purposes of 
section 32 and the Highway Administration shall publish such limits of laden 
weight in a local newspaper for the information of the concerned persons.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>18</number> Prohibition or 
restriction of the plying of vehicle under section 32.—Where 
the Highway Administration is satisfied that the surface of a Highway or any 
part thereof, or any bridge, culvert or causeway built on or across the Highway 
is not designed to carry vehicle of which the laden weight exceeds the limit of 
laden weight as determined under rule 17, it may, by public notice of such fact 
in the local newspapers and after placing signboards containing such fact at 
suitable distances nearby such Highway or any part thereof or any bridge, 
culvert or causeway built on or across the Highway, as the case may be, for the 
information of the traffic concerned, prohibit or restrict the plying of such 
vehicles on or over such Highway or any part thereof or such bridge, culvert or 
causeway built on or across the Highway, as the case may be, and in case of 
doubt, the Highway Administration may remove the additional laden weight in 
excess of the permissible limit of the laden weight of any vehicle to implement 
the provisions of this rule for directing such plying of the vehicle.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>19</number> Traffic signs to be 
placed or erected under section 35.—The 
Highway Administration shall, for the purposes of section 35 cause one or more 
of the traffic signs specified in the First Schedule to the Motor Vehicles Act, 
1988 (59 of 1988) suitable and sufficient to serve the purpose, to be placed or 
erected at suitable places for the convenience of the traffic:
 
Provided that in case the 
Highway Administration considers that any modification in any such sign is 
required to serve a particular purpose under section 35 in a more useful manner, 
it may place or erect such modified signs after the approval of the Central 
Government for the purpose.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>20</number> Safety control 
under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 37.—(1) 
No person in charge of, or in possession of, any vehicle shall allow such 
vehicle—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  to proceed on a Highway unless—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  such vehicle is driven within such limit of speed as is applicable for 
the driving of such vehicle in any public place under section 112 of the Motor 
Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  such vehicle is within the limits of weight within the meaning of 
sub-section (2) of section 113 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988) for 
its driving in any public place; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>c</number>  such vehicle complies with the rules made by the Central Government 
under section 110 of the Motor Vehicles Act, 1988 (59 of 1988) relating to 
brakes and steering gear, signalling appliances, lamps and reflectors, speed 
governors, emission of smokes, visible vapour, sparks, grid or oil, reduction of 
noise emitted by, or caused by, vehicles, auto dipper, provision for 
transportation of goods of dangerous or hazardous nature to human life and 
standards for emission or air pollutants; or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  to stand on a Highway unless—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  such vehicle stands in such circumstances which has not to cause or 
likely to cause danger, obstruction or undue inconvenience to other users of the 
Highway or to the passengers thereon;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  such vehicle is under the close supervision of its driver or any other 
person assigned its supervision and is not left unattended by such driver or 
person unattended for two hours or more;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>c</number>  such vehicle is parked in a place legally allowed or allowed by the 
Highway Administration for such parking;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>d</number>  such vehicle is wrecked, burnt or impartially dismantled condition 
creating a traffic hazard; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>e</number>  such vehicle is not creating any obstruction in a smooth and easy 
traffic movement on the Highway.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No person in charge 
of, or in possession of, any animal shall allow such animal—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  to proceed on a Highway unless—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  such animal is attended by a person so efficiently to avoid any danger 
or fear to the traffic on the Highway;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  such animal so attended by a person so as not to create any uneasiness 
to the traffic on the Highway; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>c</number>  such animal is so attended by a person so as not to allow such animal 
to damage the Highway;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  to stand on a Highway—
 <subsubsection>
            
<number>a</number>  at a place on the Highway other than a place which is specifically 
allocated by the Highway Administration for such purposes;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>b</number>  in a condition unattended by a person;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>c</number>  in a condition to allow the animal to cause any damage or fear to the 
traffic; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>d</number>  in a condition to allow the animal to pollute or damage the Highway.
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>21</number> The manner of handing over the 
vehicle or animal to the owner, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a vehicle or animal has 
been taken into possession by the Highway Administration under sub­-section 
(2) of section 37, a person claiming to be the owner of such vehicle or animal, 
as the case may be, may make an application to the Highway Administration 
stating therein that he is the owner of such vehicle or animal, as the case may 
be, and such vehicle or animal may be handed over to him by the Highway 
Administration on payment of expenses incurred by the Highway Administration in 
removal of the vehicle or animal under sub-section (2) of section 37.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The person making an 
application under sub-rule (1) shall also produce before the Highway 
Administration evidence to its satisfaction to prove that he is the owner of 
such vehicle or animal, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Highway 
Administration after considering the evidence under sub-rule (2), is satisfied 
that such person is the owner of such vehicle or animal, as the case may be, it 
shall assess the expenses incurred in the removal of such vehicle or animal 
under sub-section (2) of section 37 and after payment of the expenses so 
assessed to the Highway Administration by such person, the Highway 
Administration shall hand over such vehicle or animal, as the case may be, to 
such person.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If a vehicle remains unclaimed 
for seven days, a report in respect of such vehicle shall be made to the 
concerned police station.
 </section><section><number>5</number> If an animal remains 
unclaimed, the Highway Administration shall make suitable arrangement for the 
safe custody and maintenance of such animal till it is disposed 
of.</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>22</number> Form of application 
under sub-section (2) of section 38.—Every 
application under sub­-section (2) of section 38 shall be made in the Form 
specified in Schedule VII.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>24</number> Summary inquiry 
under section 43.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Highway Administration or the officer authorised in this behalf by such 
Administration, desires to make any inquiry for the purposes of the Act, he may 
make a summary inquiry in the following manner, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the Highway 
Authority or the Officer authorised by him, as the case may be, may visit the 
place of unauthorised occupation of the highway land, inspect such land and 
reduce his observations in writing to arrive at a conclusion for appropriate 
action under the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the Highway 
Administration or the Officer authorised by him, as the case may be, thinks 
necessary, he may record the statement of the concerned village headman, village 
accountant, village watchman or other village official referred to in section 42 
or any other person to arrive at the conclusion that any offence including 
unauthorised occupation, damage or destruction of a Highway land has been 
committed or not;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  where the 
Highway Administration or the Officer authorised by him, as the case may be, 
records the statement under clause (b), he shall record such statement in 
duplicate and obtain signature thereon of the concerned village headman, village 
accountant, village watchman, other village official or any other person, as the 
case may be, where statement has been so recorded.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where on the basis of 
the inquiry made under sub-rule (1), the Highway Administration or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by such Administration is satisfied that any action is 
required to be taken under the Act, the Highway Administration or the person 
authorised by him, as the case may be, shall take such action without any delay 
and where the Highway Administration or such officer is satisfied on the basis 
of such inquiry that any offence involving unauthorised occupation, damage or 
destruction of the Highway land has been committed, as the case may be, shall 
without delay inform the officer in charge of the police station concerned, 
along with the copy of relevant observation reduced in writing under clause (a) 
or statement recorded under clause (b) of sub-rule (1) of such commission of 
offence for taking necessary action.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every Highway 
Administration shall send a summary report once in every three months to the 
Central Government stating therein the brief description of inquiries made under 
sub-rule (1) within the jurisdiction of such Highway Administration within such 
period and the actions taken on the basis of such inquiries.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the 
summary reports under sub-rule (3), the Central Government may issue any general 
or special orders under the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 3, which such 
Government thinks fit for proper exercise of powers and discharge of functions 
by the Highway Administrations under the Act.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>25</number> Manner of service 
or presentation of notice or bill.— 
Save as otherwise provided in the Act, every notice or bill issued or prepared 
under section 47 may be served or presented in the following manner, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  such notice or 
bill may be served on the person concerned or presented to him by a messenger 
handing over a copy thereof or obtaining his signature on another copy thereof;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  in case the 
service or presentation of such notice or bill is not easily possible under 
clause (a), then, such notice or bill shall be sent to the person concerned by 
registered post or speed post at his known residence and the delivery of such 
registered post to such person shall be the service on or presentation to him on 
such notice or bill as the case may be and in case he refuses to receive such 
registered post or speed post, the remarks of such refusal by a post office 
official on the registered post shall be deemed to be the service on, or 
presentation to, such person of such notice or bill, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  in case the 
service or presentation of such notice or bill is not physically possible under 
clauses (a) and (b), then, the contents of such notice or bill shall be 
published in newspaper having circulation in the locality where the person 
concerned actually or voluntarily resides or carries on business or personally 
works for gain and such publication shall be deemed to be the service of such 
notice or bill, as the case may be, on such person or presentation thereof to 
him.
</section></article> 

 


 <article><number>26</number> 
Interpretation.—If 
any question arises relating to the implementation of these rules, the same 
shall be referred to the Central Government for its decision and the decision of 
the Central Government shall be implemented.
 
 
</article><form>
 




the Highways Administration Rules, 2004
 




 


SCHEDULE III 

 


(See rule 11)
 




NOTICE FOR REMOVAL OF UNAUTHORISED OCCUPATON
 


[Under sub-section (2) of 
section 26 of the Control of  

National Highways (Land and Traffic) Act, 2002]
 


Whereas I………….on periodical 
inspection of the Highway land on the information received by me, am satisfied 
that an unauthorised occupation has taken place on the Highway comprised of 
area………….(specify area) situated at K.M……..of N.H. No. ……….(indicate location 
sufficient to identify area) and such unauthorised occupation has been caused by 
you/you are responsible for such unauthorised occupation;
 


Therefore, you…….....(Name 
and address of person to whom notice is to be issued) take notice that you are 
hereby required to remove such unauthorised occupation within seven days from 
the date on which this notice is served on you. You may make representation 
within three days from the date on which this notice is served on you 
to……………………(indicate the designation and address of the officer to whom 
representation is to be made) and such representation, if made, shall be heard 
on........ (indicate the date and place of hearing) at…………and be aware of the 
notice that failure to comply with this notice shall render you liable to 
penalty and summary eviction from the aforementioned Highway land under 
sub-section (6) of section 26 of the Control of National Highways (Land and 
Traffic) Act, 2002 (13 of 2003).
 


Issued under my hand and 
seal at…………on………day of………20..….
 


Signature of Highway 
Administration or 
 


Officer authorised 

 


Seal
 


Place.................
 


State/Union Territory 
of.………….
 



</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>