<act><title>THE JUVENILE JUSTICE (CARE AND PROTECTION OF CHILDREN) ACT, 2000 </title> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent 


1[commencement and application].—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) 
Act, 2000.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on 
such date2 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 

3[(4) Notwithstanding anything contained 
in any other law for the time being in force, the provisions of this Act shall 
apply to all cases involving detention, prosecution, penalty or sentence of 
imprisonment of juveniles in conflict with law under any such law.]
  





</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “advisory board” means a Central or a State 
advisory board or a district and city level advisory board, as the case may be, 
constituted under section 62;
 
     1[(aa)  
“adoption” means the process through which the adopted child is permanently 
separated from his biological parents and become the legitimate child of his 
adoptive parents with all the rights, privileges and responsibilities that are 
attached to the relationship;]
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “begging” means—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  soliciting or receiving alms in a public 
place or entering into any private premises for the purpose of soliciting or 
receiving alms, whether under any pretence;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  exposing or exhibiting with the object of 
obtaining or extorting alms, any sore, wound, injury, deformity or disease, 
whether of himself or of any other person or of an animal;
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>c</number>  “Board” means a Juvenile Justice Board 
constituted under section 4;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  “child in need of care and protection” means a 
child—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  who is found without any home or settled 
place or abode and without any ostensible means of subsistence,
 
1[(ia)  
who is found begging, or who is either a street child or a working child,]
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  who resides with a person (whether a 
guardian of the child or not) and such person—
 <subsubsection>                 <number>a</number>  has threatened to kill or injure the 
child and there is a reasonable likelihood of the threat being carried out, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>                 <number>b</number>  has killed, abused or neglected some 
other child or children and there is a reasonable likelihood of the child in 
question being killed, abused or neglected by that person,
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  who is mentally or physically challenged 
or ill children or children suffering from terminal diseases or incurable 
diseases having no one to support or look after,
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number>  who has a parent or guardian and such 
parent or guardian is unfit or incapacitated to exercise control over the child,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>v</number>  who does not have parent and no one is 
willing to take care of or whose parents have abandoned
1[or 
surrendered] him or who is missing and run away child and whose parents cannot 
be found after reasonable injury,
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>vi</number>  who is being or is likely to be grossly 
abused, tortured or exploited for the purpose of sexual abuse or illegal acts,
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>vii</number>  who is found vulnerable and is likely to 
be inducted into drug abuse or trafficking,
 </subsection><subsection>          <number>viii</number>  who is being or is likely to be abused for 
unconscionable gains,
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ix</number>  who is victim of any armed conflict, civil 
commotion or natural calamity;
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>e</number>  “children’s home” means an institution 
established by a State Government or by voluntary organisation and certified by 
that Government under section 34;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  “Committee” means a Child Welfare Committee 
constituted under section 29;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  “competent authority” means in relation to 
children in need of care and protection a Committee and in relation to juveniles 
in conflict with law a Board;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  “fit institution” means a governmental or a 
registered non-governmental organisation or a voluntary organisation prepared to 
own the responsibility of a child and such organisation is found fit by the
2[State 
Government on the recommendation of the competent authority;]
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>  “fit person” means a person, being a social 
worker or any other person, who is prepared to own the responsibility of a child 
and is found fit by the competent authority to receive and take care of the 
child;
 </section><section>        <number>j</number>  “guardian”, in relation to a child, means his 
natural guardian or any other person having the actual charge or control over 
the child and recognised by the competent authority as a guardian in course of 
proceedings before that authority;
 </section><section>       <number>k</number>  “juvenile” or “child” means a person who has not 
completed eighteenth year of age;
 
3[(l)  
“juvenile in conflict with law” means a juvenile who is alleged to have 
committed an offence and has not completed eighteenth year of age as on the date 
of commission of such offence;]
 
4[***]
 </section><section>       <number>n</number>  “narcotic drug” and “psychotropic substance” 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Narcotic Drugs and 
Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 (61 of 1985);
 </section><section>       <number>o</number>  “observation home” means a home established by a 
State Government or by a voluntary organisation and certified by that State 
Government under section 8 as an observation home for the juvenile in conflict 
with law;
 </section><section>       <number>p</number>  “offence” means an offence punishable under any 
law for the time being in force;
 </section><section>       <number>q</number>  “place of safety” means any place or institution 
(not being a police lock-up or jail), the person incharge of which is willing 
temporarily to receive and take care of the juvenile and which, in the opinion 
of the competent authority, may be a place of safety for the juvenile;
 </section><section>        <number>r</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made 
under this Act;
 </section><section>       <number>s</number>  “probation officer” means an officer appointed 
by the State Government as a probation officer under the Probation of Offenders 
Act, 1958 (20 of 1958);
 </section><section>        <number>t</number>  “public place” shall have the meaning assigned 
to it in the Immoral Traffic (Prevention) Act, 1956 (104 of 1956);
 </section><section>       <number>u</number>  “shelter home” means a home or a drop-in-centre 
set up under section 37;
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  “special home” means an institution established 
by a State Government or by a voluntary organisation and certified by that 
Government under section 9;
 </section><section>       <number>w</number>  “special juvenile police unit” means a unit of 
the police force of a State designated for handling of juveniles or children 
under  
section 63;
 </section><section>       <number>x</number>  “State Government”, in relation to a Union 
territory, means the Administrator of that Union territory appointed by the 
President under article 239 of the Constitution;
 </section><section>       <number>y</number>  all words and expressions used but not defined 
in this Act and defined in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Code.
  






</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>3</number> Continuation of inquiry in 
respect of juvenile who has ceased to be a juvenile.—Where 
an inquiry has been initiated against a juvenile in conflict with law or a child 
in need of care and protection and during the course of such inquiry the 
juvenile or the child ceases to be such, then, notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act or in any other law for the time being in force, the 
inquiry may be continued and orders may be made in respect of such person as if 
such person had continued to be a juvenile or a child.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>4</number> Juvenile Justice Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in
the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), the State Government may,1[within a period of one year from the 
date of commencement of the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) 
Amendment Act, 2006, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for 
every district], one or more Juvenile Justice Boards for exercising the powers 
and discharging the duties conferred or imposed on such Boards in relation to 
juveniles in conflict with law under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A Board shall consist of a 
Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class, as the case 
may be, and two social workers of whom at least one shall be a woman, forming a 
Bench and every such Bench shall have the powers conferred by the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), on a Metropolitan Magistrate or, as the 
case may be, a Judicial Magistrate of the first class and the Magistrate on the 
Board shall be designated as the principal Magistrate.
 </section><section><number>3</number> No Magistrate shall be 
appointed as a member of the Board unless he has special knowledge or training 
in child psychology or child welfare and no social worker shall be appointed as 
a member of the Board unless he has been actively involved in health, education, 
or welfare activities pertaining to children for at least seven years.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The term of office of the 
members of the Board and the manner in which such member may resign shall be 
such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The appointment of any 
member of the Board may be terminated after holding inquiry, by the Sate 
Government, if—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  he has been found guilty of misuse of power 
vested under this Act,
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  he has been convicted of an offence involving 
moral turpitude, and such conviction has not been reversed or he has not been 
granted full pardon in respect of such offence,
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  he fails to attend the proceedings of the 
Board for consecutive three months without any valid reason or he fails to 
attend less than three-fourth of the sittings in a year.





</subsection></section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>5</number> Procedure, etc., in 
relation to Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board 
shall meet at such times and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to 
the transaction of business at its meetings, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A child in conflict with law 
may be produced before an individual member of the Board, when the Board is not 
sitting.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A Board may act 
notwithstanding the absence of any member of the Board, and no order made by the 
Board shall be invalid by reason only of the absence of any member during any 
stage of proceedings:
 Provided that there shall be at 
least two members including the principal Magistrate present at the time of 
final disposal of the case.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the event of any 
difference of opinion among the members of the Board in the interim or final 
disposition, the opinion of the majority shall prevail, but where there is no 
such majority, the opinion of the principal Magistrate shall prevail.


</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>6</number> Powers of Juvenile Justice 
Board.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a Board has been 
constituted for any district 

1[***], such Board shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law for the time being in force but save as 
otherwise expressly provided in this Act, have power to deal exclusively with 
all proceedings under this Act relating to juvenile in conflict with law.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The powers conferred on the 
Board by or under this Act may also be exercised by the High Court and the Court 
of Session, when the proceeding comes before them in appeal, revision or 
otherwise.
  



</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>7</number> Procedure to be followed 
by a Magistrate not empowered under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When any Magistrate not empowered to exercise the powers of a Board under this 
Act is of the opinion that a person brought before him under any of the 
provisions of this Act (other than for the purpose of giving evidence), is a 
juvenile or the child, he shall without any delay record such opinion and 
forward the juvenile or the child and the record of the proceeding to the 
competent authority having jurisdiction over the proceeding.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The competent authority to 
which the proceeding is forwarded under sub-section (1) shall hold the inquiry 
as if the juvenile or the child had originally been brought before it.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>7A</number> Procedure to be followed when 
claim of juvenility is raised before any court.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever a claim of 
juvenility is raised before any court or a court is of the opinion that an 
accused person was a juvenile on the date of commission of the offence, the 
court shall make an inquiry, take such evidence as may be necessary (but not an 
affidavit) so as to determine the age of such person, and shall record a finding 
whether the person is a juvenile or a child or not, stating his age as nearly as 
may be:
 Provided that a claim of 
juvenility may be raised before any court and it shall be recognised at any 
stage, even after final disposal of the case, and such claim shall be determined 
in terms of the provisions contained in this Act and the rules made thereunder, 
even if the juvenile has ceased to be so on or before the date of commencement 
of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the court finds a person 
to be a juvenile on the date of commission of the offence under sub-section (1), 
it shall forward the juvenile to the Board for passing appropriate orders and 
the sentence, if any, passed by a court shall be deemed to have no effect.]
  



</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>8</number> Observation homes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any State Government may establish and maintain either by itself or under an 
agreement with voluntary organisations, observation homes in every district or a 
group of districts, as may be required for the temporary reception of any 
juvenile in conflict with law during the pendency of any inquiry regarding them 
under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the State Government 
is of opinion that any institution other than a home established or maintained 
under sub-section (1), is fit for the temporary reception of juvenile in 
conflict with law during the pendency of any inquiry regarding them under this 
Act, it may certify such institution as an observation home for the purposes of 
this Act.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government may, by 
rules made under this Act, provide for the management of observation homes, 
including the standards and various types of services to be provided by them for 
rehabilitation and social integration of a juvenile, and the circumstances under 
which, and the manner in which, the certification of an observation home may be 
granted or withdrawn.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every juvenile who is not 
placed under the charge of parent or guardian and is sent to an observation home 
shall be initially kept in a reception unit of the observation home for 
preliminary inquiries, care and classification for juveniles according to his 
age group, such as seven to twelve years, twelve to sixteen years and sixteen to 
eighteen years, giving due considerations to physical and mental status and 
degree of the offence committed, for further induction into observation home.


</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>9</number> Special homes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any State Government may establish and maintain either by itself or under an 
agreement with voluntary organisations, special homes in every district or a 
group of districts, as may be required for reception and rehabilitation of 
juvenile in conflict with law under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the State Government 
is of opinion that any institution other than a home established or maintained 
under sub-section (1), is fit for the reception of juvenile in conflict with law 
to be sent there under this Act, it may certify such institution as a special 
home for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government may, by 
rules made under this Act, provide for the management of special homes, 
including the standards and various types of services to be provided by them 
which are necessary for re-socialisation of a juvenile, and the circumstances 
under which, and the manner in which, the certification of a special home may be 
granted or withdrawn.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The rules made under 
sub-section (3) may also provide for the classification and separation of 
juvenile in conflict with law on the basis of age and the nature of offences 
committed by them and his mental and physical status.


</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>10</number> Apprehension of juvenile 
in conflict with law.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
As soon as a juvenile in conflict with law is apprehended by police, he shall be 
placed under the charge of the special juvenile police unit or the designated 
police officer, who shall produce the juvenile before the Board without any loss 
of time but within a period of twenty-four hours of his apprehension excluding 
the time necessary for the journey, from the place where the juvenile was 
apprehended, to the Board:
 Provided that in no case, a 
juvenile in conflict with law shall be placed in a police lockup or lodged in a 
jail.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government may 
make rules consistent with this Act,—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  to provide for persons through whom (including 
registered voluntary organisations) any juvenile in conflict with law may be 
produced before the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  to provide the manner in which such juvenile 
may be sent to an observation home.






</subsection></section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>11</number> Control of custodian over 
juvenile.—Any person in whose charge 
a juvenile is placed in pursuance of this Act shall, while the order is in force 
have the control over the juvenile as he would have if he were his parents, and 
shall be responsible for his maintenance, and the juvenile shall continue in his 
charge for the period stated by competent authority, notwithstanding that he is 
claimed by his parents or any other person.


</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>12</number> Bail of juvenile.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When any person accused of a bailable or non-bailable offence, and apparently a 
juvenile, is arrested or detained or appears or is brought before a Board, such 
person shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) or in any other law for the time being in force, be 
released on bail with or without surety 

1[or placed under the supervision of a 
Probation Officer or under the care of any fit institution of fit person] but he 
shall not be so released if there appear reasonable grounds for believing that 
the release is likely to bring him into association with any known criminal or 
expose him to moral, physical or psychological danger or that his release would 
defeat the ends of justice.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When such person having been 
arrested is not released on bail under sub-section (1) by the officer incharge 
of the police station, such officer shall cause him to be kept only in an 
observation home in the prescribed manner until he can be brought before a 
Board.
 </section><section><number>3</number> When such person is not 
released on bail under sub-section (1) by the Board it shall, instead of 
committing him to prison, make an order sending him to an observation home or a 
place of safety for such period during the pendency of the inquiry regarding him 
as may be specified in the order.
  


</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>13</number> Information to parent, 
guardian or probation officer.—Where 
a juvenile is arrested, the officer incharge of the police station or the 
special juvenile police unit to which the juvenile is brought shall, as soon as 
may be after the arrest, inform—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  the parent or guardian of the juvenile, if he 
can be found of such arrest and direct him to be present at the Board before 
which the juvenile will appear; and
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  the probation officer of such arrest to enable 
him to obtain information regarding the antecedents and family background of the 
juvenile and other material circumstances likely to be of assistance to the 
Board for making the inquiry. 


</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>14</number> Inquiry by Board 
regarding juvenile.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
Where a juvenile having been charged with the offence is produced before a 
Board, the Board shall hold the inquiry in accordance with the provisions of 
this Act and may make such order in relation to the juvenile as it deems fit:
 Provided that an inquiry under 
this section shall be completed within a period of four months from the date of 
its commencement, unless the period is extended by the Board having regard to 
the circumstances of the case and in special cases after recording the reasons 
in writing for such extension.
 

2[(2) The Chief Judicial Magistrate or 
the Chief Metropolitan Magistrate shall review the pendency of cases of the 
Board at every six months, and shall direct the Board to increase the frequency 
of its sittings or may cause the constitution of additional Boards.]
  




</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>15</number> Order that may be passed 
regarding juvenile.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a Board 
is satisfied on inquiry that a juvenile has committed an offence, then, 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, the Board may, if it so thinks fit,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  allow the juvenile to go home after advice or 
admonition following appropriate inquiry against and counselling to the parent 
or the guardian and the juvenile;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  direct the juvenile to participate in group 
counselling and similar activities;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  order the juvenile to perform community service;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  order the parent of the juvenile or the juvenile 
himself to pay a fine, if he is over fourteen years of age and earns money;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  direct the juvenile to be released on probation 
of good conduct and placed under the care of any parent, guardian or other fit 
person, on such parent, guardian or other fit person executing a bond, with or 
without surety, as the Board may require, for the good behaviour and well-being 
of the juvenile for any period not exceeding three years;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  direct the juvenile to be released on probation 
of good conduct and placed under the care of any fit institution for the good 
behaviour and well-being of the juvenile for any period not exceeding three 
years;
 
1[(g)  
make an order directing the juvenile to be sent to a special home for a period 
of three years: 
 Provided that the Board may, if 
it is satisfied that having regard to the nature of the offence and the 
circumstances of the case, it is expedient so to do, for reasons to be recorded, 
reduce the period of stay to such period as it thinks fit.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Board shall obtain the 
social investigation report on juvenile either through a probation officer or a 
recognised voluntary organisation or otherwise, and shall take into 
consideration the findings of such report before passing an order.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an order under clause 
(d), clause (e) or clause (f) of sub-section (1) is made, the Board may, if it 
is of opinion that in the interests of the juvenile and of the public, it is 
expedient so to do, in addition make an order that the juvenile in conflict with 
law shall remain under the supervision of a probation officer named in the order 
during such period, not exceeding three years as may be specified therein, and 
may in such supervision order impose such conditions 
as it deems necessary for the due supervision of the juvenile in conflict with 
law:
 Provided that if at any time 
afterwards it appears to the Board on receiving a report from the probation 
officer or otherwise, that the juvenile in conflict with law has not been of 
good behaviour during the period of supervision or that the fit institution 
under whose care the juvenile was placed is no longer able or willing to ensure 
the good behaviour and well-being of the juvenile it may, after making such 
inquiry as it deems fit, order the juvenile in conflict with law to be sent to a 
special home.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Board shall while making 
a supervision order under sub-section (3), explain to the juvenile and the 
parent, guardian or other fit person or fit institution, as the case may be, 
under whose care the juvenile has been placed, the terms and conditions of the 
order and shall forthwith furnish one copy of the supervision order to the 
juvenile, the parent, guardian or other fit person or fit institution, as the 
case may be, the sureties, if any, and the probation officer.
  







</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>16</number> Order that may not be 
passed against juvenile.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, no juvenile in conflict with law shall be sentenced to death


1[or imprisonment for any term which may 
extend to imprisonment for life], or committed to prison in default of payment 
of fine or in default of furnishing security:
 Provided that where a juvenile 
who has attained the age of sixteen years has committed an offence and the Board 
is satisfied that the offence committed is so serious in nature or that his 
conduct and behaviour have been such that it would not be in his interest or in 
the interest of other juvenile in a special home to send him to such special 
home and that none of the other measures provided under this Act is suitable or 
sufficient, the Board may order the juvenile in conflict with law to be kept in 
such place of safety and in such manner as it thinks fit and shall report the 
case for the order of the State Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of a report from 
a Board under sub-section (1), the State Government may make such arrangement in 
respect of the juvenile as it deems proper and may order such juvenile to be 
kept under protective custody at such place and on such conditions as it thinks 
fit:
 

2[Provided that the period of detention 
so ordered shall not exceed in any case the maximum period provided under 
section 15 of this Act.]
  





</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>17</number> Proceeding under Chapter 
VIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure not competent against juvenile.—Notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974) no proceeding shall be instituted and no order shall be passed against the 
juvenile under Chapter VIII of the said Code.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>18</number> No joint proceeding of 
juvenile and person not a juvenile.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 223 of the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) or in any other law for the time being in force, no 
juvenile shall be charged with or tried for any offence together with a person 
who is not a juvenile.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If a juvenile is accused of 
an offence for which under section 223 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
(2 of 1974) or any other law for the time being in force, such juvenile and any 
person who is not a juvenile would, but for the prohibition contained in 
sub-section (1), have been charged and tried together, the Board taking 
cognizance of that offence shall direct separate trials of the juvenile and the 
other person.


</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>19</number> Removal of 
disqualification attaching to conviction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, a juvenile who has 
committed an offence and has been dealt with under the provisions of this Act 
shall not suffer disqualification, if any, attaching to a conviction of an 
offence under such law.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Board shall make an 
order directing that the relevant records of such conviction shall be removed 
after the expiry of the period of appeal or a reasonable period as prescribed 
under the rules, as the case may be.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>20</number> Special provision in 
respect of pending cases.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, all proceedings in respect of a juvenile pending 
in any court in any area on the date on which this Act comes into force in that 
area, shall be continued in that court as if this Act had not been passed and if 
the court finds that the juvenile has committed an offence, it shall record such 
finding and instead of passing any sentence in respect of the juvenile, forward 
the juvenile to the Board which shall pass orders in respect of that juvenile in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act as if it had been satisfied on 
inquiry under this Act that a juvenile has committed the offence.
 

1[Provided that the Board may, for any 
adequate and special reason to be mentioned in the order, review the case and 
pass appropriate order in the interest of such juvenile.
 Explanation.—In 
all pending cases including trial, revision, appeal or any other criminal 
proceedings in respect of a juvenile in conflict with law, in any court, the 
determination of juvenility of such a juvenile shall be in terms of clause (l) 
of section 2, even if the juvenile ceases to be so on or before the date of 
commencement of this Act and the provisions of this Act shall apply as if the 
said provisions had been in force, for all purposes and at all material times 
when the alleged offence was committed.]



</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article>

1[<number>21</number> Prohibition of publication of 
name, etc., of juvenile or child in need of care and protection involved in any 
proceeding under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> No report in any newspaper, magazine, 
news-sheet or visual media of any inquiry regarding a juvenile in conflict with 
law or a child in need of care and protection under this Act shall disclose the 
name, address or school or any other particulars calculated to lead to the 
identification of the juvenile or child nor shall any picture of any such 
juvenile or child be published:
 Provided that for reasons to be 
recorded in writing, the authority holding the inquiry may permit such 
disclosure, if in its opinion such disclosure is in the interest of the juvenile 
or the child.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person who contravenes 
the provisions of sub-section (1), shall be liable to a penalty which may extend 
to twenty five thousand rupees.]








</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>22</number> Provision in respect of 
escaped juvenile.—Notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in any other law for the time being in force, 
any police officer may take charge without warrant of a juvenile in conflict 
with law who has escaped from a special home or an observation home or from the 
care of a person under whom he was placed under this Act, and shall be sent back 
to the special home or the observation home or that person, as the case may be; 
and no proceeding shall be instituted in respect of the juvenile by reason of 
such escape, but the special home, or the observation home or the person may, 
after giving the information to the Board which passed the order in respect of 
the juvenile, take such steps in respect of the juvenile as may be deemed 
necessary under the provisions of this Act.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>23</number> Punishment for cruelty to 
juvenile or child.— Whoever, 
having the actual charge of, or control over, a juvenile or the child, assaults, 
abandons, exposes or wilfully neglects the juvenile or causes or procures him to 
be assaulted, abandoned, exposed or neglected in a manner likely to cause such 
juvenile or the child unnecessary mental or physical suffering shall be 
punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or fine, 
or with both.



</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>24</number> Employment of juvenile or 
child for begging.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever 
employs or uses any juvenile or the child for the purpose or causes any juvenile 
to beg shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years and shall also be liable to fine.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Whoever, having the actual 
charge of, or control over, a juvenile or the child abets the commission of the 
offence punishable under sub-section (1), shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to one year and shall also be liable to fine.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>25</number> Penalty for giving 
intoxicating liquor or narcotic drug or psychotropic substance to juvenile or 
child.—Whoever gives, or causes to be 
given, to any juvenile or the child any intoxicating liquor in a public place or 
any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance except upon the order of duly 
qualified medical practitioner or in case of sickness shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and shall also be liable 
to fine.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>26</number> Exploitation of juvenile 
or child employee.—Whoever ostensibly 
procures a juvenile or the child for the purpose of any hazardous employment 
keeps him in bondage and withholds his earnings or uses such earning for his own 
purposes shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years and shall also be liable to fine.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>27</number> Special offences.—The 
offences punishable under sections 23, 24, 25 and 26 shall be cognizable.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>28</number> Alternative punishment.—Where 
an act or omission constitute an offence punishable under this Act and also 
under any other Central or State Act, then, notwithstanding anything contained 
in any law for the time being in force, the offender found guilty of such 
offences shall be liable to punishment only under such Act as provides for 
punishment which is greater in degree.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>29</number> Child Welfare Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, 

1[within a period of one year from the 
date of commencement of the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of Children) 
Amendment Act, 2006, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute for 
every district], one or more Child Welfare Committees for exercising the powers 
and discharge the duties conferred on such Committees in relation to child in 
need of care and protection under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Committee shall consist 
of a Chairperson and four other members as the State Government may think fit to 
appoint, of whom at least one shall be a woman and another, an expert on matters 
concerning children.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The qualifications of the 
Chairperson and the members, and the tenure for which they may be appointed 
shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The appointment of any 
member of the Committee may be terminated, after holding inquiry, by the State 
Government, if—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  he has been found guilty of misuse of power 
vested under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  he has been convicted of an offence involving 
moral turpitude, and such conviction has not been reversed or he has not been 
granted full pardon in respect of such offence;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  he fails to attend the proceedings of the 
Committee for consecutive three months without any valid reason or he fails to 
attend less than three-fourth of the sittings in a year.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> The Committee shall function 
as a Bench of Magistrates and shall have the powers conferred by the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) on a Metropolitan Magistrate or, as the 
case may be, a Judicial Magistrate of the first class.





</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>30</number> Procedure, etc., in 
relation to Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Committee shall meet at such times and shall observe such rules of procedure in 
regard to the transaction of business at its meetings, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A child in need of care and 
protection may be produced before an individual member for being placed in safe 
custody or otherwise when the Committee is not in session.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the event of any 
difference of opinion among the members of the Committee at the time of any 
interim decision, the opinion of the majority shall prevail but where there is 
no such majority the opinion of the Chairperson shall prevail.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Subject to the provisions of 
sub-section (1), the Committee may act, notwithstanding the absence of any 
member of the Committee, and no order made by the Committee shall be invalid by 
reason only of the absence of any member during any stage of the proceeding.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>31</number> Powers of Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Committee shall have the final authority to dispose of cases for the care, 
protection, treatment, development and rehabilitation of the children as well as 
to provide for their basic needs and protection of human rights.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a Committee has been 
constituted for any area, such Committee shall, notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law for the time being in force but save as otherwise 
expressly provided in this Act, have the power to deal exclusively with all 
proceedings under this Act relating to children in need of care and protection.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>32</number> Production before 
Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> Any child in need of 
care and protection may be produced before the Committee by one of the following 
persons:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  any police officer or special juvenile police 
unit or a designated police officer;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  any public servant;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  childline, a registered voluntary organisation 
or by such other voluntary organisation or an agency as may be recognised by the 
State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  any social worker or a public spirited citizen
1[***]; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number>  by the child himself:
 

2[Provided that the child shall be 
produced before the Committee without any loss of time but within a period of 
twenty-four hours excluding the time necessary for the journey.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The State Government may 
make rules consistent with this Act to provide for the manner of making the 
report 

3[***] to the Committee and the manner of 
sending and entrusting the child to children’s home pending the inquiry.
  





</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>33</number> Inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of a report under section 32, the Committee 

1[***] shall hold an inquiry in the 
prescribed manner and the Committee, on its own or on the report from any person 
or agency as mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 32, may pass an order to 
send the child to the children’s home for speedy inquiry by a social worker or 
child welfare officer.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The inquiry under this 
section shall be completed within four months of the receipt of the order or 
within such shorter period as may be fixed by the Committee:
 Provided that the time for the 
submission of the inquiry report may be extended by such period as the Committee 
may, having regard to the circumstances and for the reasons recorded in writing, 
determine.
 

2[(3) The State Government shall review 
the pendency of cases of the Committee at every six months, and shall direct the 
Committee to increase the frequency of its sittings or may cause the 
constitution of additional Committees.
 </section><section><number>4</number> After the completion of the 
inquiry, if, the Committee is of the opinion that the said child has no family 
or ostensible support or is in continued need of care and protection, it may 
allow the child to remain in the children’s home or shelter home till suitable 
rehabilitation is found for him or till he attains the age of eighteen years.]
  





</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>34</number> Children’s homes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may establish and maintain either by itself or in 
association with the voluntary organisations, children’s homes, in every 
district or group of districts, as the case may be, for the reception of child 
in need of care and protection during the pendency of any inquiry and 
subsequently for their care, treatment, education, training, development and 
rehabilitation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government may, by 
rules made under this Act, provide for the management of children’s homes 
including the standards and the nature of services to be provided by them, and 
the circumstances under which, and the manner in which, the certification of a 
children’s home or recognition to a voluntary organisation may be granted or 
withdrawn.
 

1[(3) Without prejudice to anything 
contained in any other law for the time being in force, all institutions, 
whether State Government run or those run by voluntary organizations for 
children in need of care and protection shall, within a period of six months 
from the date of commencement of the Juvenile Justice (Care and Protection of 
Children) Amendment Act, 2006, be registered under this Act in such manner as 
may be prescribed.]





</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>35</number> Inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may appoint inspection committees for the children’s homes 
(hereinafter referred to as the inspection committees) for the State, a district 
and city, as the case may be, for such period and for such purposes as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The inspection committee of 
a State, district or of a city shall consist of such number of representatives 
from the State Government, 

1[***], Committee, voluntary 
organisations and such other medical experts and social workers as may be 
prescribed.
  



</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>36</number> Social auditing.—The 
Central Government or State Government may monitor and evaluate the functioning 
of the Children’s homes at such period and through such persons and institutions 
as may be specified by that Government.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>37</number> Shelter homes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may recognise, reputed and capable voluntary organisations 
and provide them assistance to set up and administer as many shelter homes for 
juveniles or children as may be required.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The shelter homes referred 
in sub-section (1) shall function as drop- 
in-centres for the children in the need of urgent support who have been brought 
to such homes through such persons as are referred to in sub-section (1) of 
section 32.
 </section><section><number>3</number> As far as possible, the 
shelter homes shall have such facilities as may be prescribed by the rules.


</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>38</number> Transfer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If during the inquiry it is found that the child hails from the place outside 
the jurisdiction of the Committee, the Committee shall order the transfer of the 
child to the competent authority having jurisdiction over the place of residence 
of the child.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such juvenile or the child 
shall be escorted by the staff of the home in which he is lodged originally.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government may 
make rules to provide for the travelling allowance to be paid to the child.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>39</number> Restoration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Restoration of and protection to a child shall be the prime objective of any 
children’s home or the shelter home.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The children’s home or a 
shelter home, as the case may be, shall take such steps as are considered 
necessary for the restoration of and protection to a child deprived of his 
family environment temporarily or permanently where such child is under the care 
and protection of a children’s home or a shelter home, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Committee shall have the 
powers to restore any child in need of care and protection to his parent, 
guardian, fit person or fit institution, as the case may be, and give them 
suitable directions.
 

1[Explanation.—For the purposes of 
this section “restoration of and protection of a child” means restoration to—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  parents;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  adopted parents;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  foster parents;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  guardian;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  fit person; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  fit institution.]
  






</subsection></section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>40</number> Process of rehabilitation 
and social reintegration.—The 
rehabilitation and social reintegration of a child shall begin during the stay 
of the child in a children’s home or special home and the rehabilitation and 
social reintegration of children shall be carried out alternatively by 
<section><number>i</number> 
adoption, (ii) foster care, (iii) sponsorship, and (iv) sending the child to an 
after-care organisation.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>41</number> Adoption.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The primary responsibility for providing care and protection to children shall 
be that of his family.
 

1[(2) Adoption shall be resorted to for 
the rehabilitation of the children who are orphan, abandoned or surrendered 
through such mechanism as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In keeping with the 
provisions of the various guidelines for adoption issued from time to time, by 
the State Government, or the Central Adoption Resource Agency and notified by 
the Central Government, children may be given in adoption by a court after 
satisfying itself regarding the investigations having been carried out as are 
required for giving such children in adoption.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The State Government shall 
recognise one or more of its institutions or voluntary organisations in each 
district as specialised adoption agencies in such manner as may be prescribed 
for the placement of orphan, abandoned or surrendered children for adoption in 
accordance with the guidelines notified under sub-section (3):
 Provided that the children’s 
homes and the institutions run by the State Government or a voluntary 
organisation for children in need of care and protection, who are orphan, 
abandoned or surrendered, shall ensure that these children are declared free for 
adoption by the Committee and all such cases shall be referred to the adoption 
agency in that district for placement of such children in adoption in accordance 
with the guidelines notified under sub-section (3).]
 </section><section><number>5</number> No child shall be offered 
for adoption—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  until two members of the Committee declare the 
child legally free for placement in the case of abandoned children,
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  till the two months period for reconsideration 
by the parent is over in the case of surrendered children, and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  without his consent in the case of a child who 
can understand and express his consent.
 

2[(6) The Court may allow a child to be 
given in adoption—
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>a</number>  to a person irrespective of Marital status or;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  to parents to adopt a child of same sex 
irrespective of the number of living biological sons or daughters; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  to childless couples.]
  









</subsection></section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>42</number> Foster care.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The foster care may be used for temporary placement of those infants who are 
ultimately to be given for adoption.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In foster care, the child 
may be placed in another family for a short or extended period of time, 
depending upon the circumstances where the child’s own parent usually visit 
regularly and eventually after the rehabilitation, where the children may return 
to their own homes.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government may 
make rules for the purposes of carrying out the scheme of foster care programme 
of children.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>43</number> Sponsorship.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The sponsorship programme may provide supplementary support to families, to 
children’s homes and to special homes to meet medical, nutritional, educational 
and other needs of the children with a view to improving their quality of life.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Government may 
make rules for the purposes of carrying out various schemes of sponsorship of 
children, such as individual to individual sponsorship, group sponsorship or 
community sponsorship.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>44</number> After-care organisation.—The 
Sate Government may, by rules made under this Act, provide—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  for the establishment or recognition of 
after-care organisations and the functions that may be performed by them under 
this Act;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  for a scheme of after-care programme to be 
followed by such after-care organisations for the purpose of taking care of 
juveniles or the children after they leave special homes, children homes and for 
the purpose of enabling them to lead an honest, industrious and useful life;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  for the preparation or submission of a report by 
the probation officer or any other officer appointed by that Government in 
respect of each juvenile or the child prior to his discharge from a special 
home, children’s home, regarding the necessity and nature of after-care of such 
juvenile or of a child, the period of such after-care, supervision thereof and 
for the submission of report by the probation officer or any other officer 
appointed for the purpose, on the progress of each juvenile or the child;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  for the standards and the nature of services to 
be maintained by such after care organisations;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  for such other matters as may be necessary for 
the purpose of carrying out the scheme of after-care programme for the juvenile 
or the child:
 Provided that any rule made 
under this section shall not provide for such juvenile or child to stay in the 
after-care organisation for more than three years:
 Provided further that a juvenile 
or child over seventeen years of age but less than eighteen years of age would 
stay in the after-care organisation till he attains the age of twenty years.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>45</number> Linkages and 
co-ordination.—The State Government 
may make rules to ensure effective linkages between various governmental, 
non-governmental, corporate and other community agencies for facilitating the 
rehabilitation and social reintegration of the child.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>46</number> Attendance of parent or 
guardian of juvenile or child.—Any 
competent authority before which a juvenile or the child is brought under any of 
the provisions of this Act, may, whenever it so thinks fit, require any parent 
or guardian having the actual charge of or control over the juvenile or the 
child to be present at any proceeding in respect of the juvenile or the child.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>47</number> Dispensing with 
attendance of juvenile or child.—If, 
at any stage during the course of an inquiry, a competent authority is satisfied 
that the attendance of the juvenile or the child is not essential for the 
purpose of inquiry, the competent authority may dispense with his attendance and 
proceed with the inquiry in the absence of the juvenile or the child.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>48</number> Committal to approved 
place of juvenile or child suffering from dangerous diseases and his future 
disposal.—
<section><number>1</number> When a juvenile or the 
child who has been brought before a competent authority under this Act, is found 
to be suffering from a disease requiring prolonged medical treatment or physical 
or mental complaint that will respond to treatment, the competent authority may 
send the juvenile or the child to any place recognised to be an approved place 
in accordance with the rules made under this Act for such period as it may think 
necessary for the required treatment.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a juvenile or the 
child is found to be suffering from leprosy, sexually transmitted disease, 
Hepatitis B, open cases of Tuberculosis and such other diseases or is of unsound 
mind, he shall be dealt with separately through various specialised referral 
services or under the relevant laws as such.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>49</number> Presumption and 
determination of age.—
<section><number>1</number> Where it 
appears to a competent authority that person brought before it under any of the 
provisions of this Act (otherwise than for the purpose of giving evidence) is a 
juvenile or the child, the competent authority shall make due inquiry so as to 
the age of that person and for that purpose shall take such evidence as may be 
necessary (but not an affidavit) and shall record a finding whether the person 
is a juvenile or the child or not, stating his age as nearly as may be.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No order of a competent 
authority shall be deemed to have become invalid merely by any subsequent proof 
that the person in respect of whom the order has been made is not a juvenile or 
the child, and the age recorded by the competent authority to be the age of 
person so brought before it, shall for the purpose of this Act, be deemed to be 
the true age of that person.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>50</number> Sending a juvenile or 
child outside jurisdiction.—In the 
case of a juvenile or the child, whose ordinary place of residence lies outside 
the jurisdiction of the competent authority before which he is brought, the 
competent authority may, if satisfied after due inquiry that it is expedient so 
to do, send the juvenile or the child back to a relative or other person who is 
fit and willing to receive him at his ordinary place of residence and exercise 
proper care and control over him, notwithstanding that such place of residence 
is outside the jurisdiction of the competent authority; and the competent 
authority exercising jurisdiction over the place to which the juvenile or the 
child is sent shall in respect of any matter arising subsequently have the same 
powers in relation to the juvenile or the child as if the original order had 
been passed by itself.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>51</number> Reports to be treated as 
confidential.—The report of the 
probation officer or social worker considered by the competent authority shall 
be treated as confidential:
 Provided that the competent 
authority may, if it so thinks fit, communicate the substance thereof to the 
juvenile or the child or his parent or guardian and may give such juvenile or 
the child, parent or guardian an opportunity of producing such evidence as may 
be relevant to the matter stated in the report.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>52</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this section, any person aggrieved by an order made 
by a competent authority under this Act may, within thirty days from the date of 
such order, prefer an appeal to the Court of Session:
 Provided that the Court of 
Session may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty 
days if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause 
from filing the appeal in time.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No appeal shall lie from—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  any order of acquittal made by the Board in 
respect of a juvenile alleged to have committed an offence; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  any order made by a Committee in respect of a 
finding that a person is not a neglected juvenile.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> No second appeal shall lie 
from any order of the Court of Session passed in appeal under this section.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>53</number> Revision.—The 
High Court may, at any time, either of its own motion or on an application 
received in this behalf, call for the record of any proceeding in which any 
competent authority or Court of Session has passed an order for the purpose of 
satisfying itself as to the legality or propriety of any such order and may pass 
such order in relation thereto as it thinks fit:
 Provided that the High Court 
shall not pass an order under this section prejudicial to any person without 
giving him a reasonable opportunity of being heard.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>54</number> Procedure in inquiries, 
appeals and revision proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise expressly provided by this Act, a competent authority while 
holding any inquiry under any of the provisions of this Act, shall follow such 
procedure as may be prescribed and subject thereto, shall follow, as far as may 
be, the procedure laid down in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) 
for trials in summons cases.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Save as otherwise expressly 
provided by or under this Act, the procedure to be followed in hearing appeals 
or revision proceedings under this Act shall be, as far as practicable, in 
accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974).
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>55</number> Power to amend orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to the provisions for appeal and revision under this Act, any 
competent authority may, on an application received in this behalf, amend any 
order as to the institution to which a juvenile or the child is to be sent or as 
to the person under whose care or supervision a juvenile or the child is to be 
placed under this Act:
 Provided that there shall be at 
least two members and the parties or its defence present during the course of 
hearing for passing an amendment in relation to any of its order.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Clerical mistakes in orders 
passed by a competent authority or errors arising therein from any accidental 
slip or omission may, at any time, be corrected by the competent authority 
either on its own motion or on an application received in this behalf.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>56</number> Power of competent 
authority to discharge and transfer juvenile or child.—The 
competent authority 

1[***] may, notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act, at any time, order a child in need of care and protection 
or a juvenile in conflict with law to be discharged or transferred from one 
children’s home or special home to another, as the case may be, keeping in view 
the best interest of the child or the juvenile, and his natural place of stay, 
either absolutely or on such conditions as it may think fit to impose:
 Provided that the total period 
of stay of the juvenile or the child in a childern’s home or a special home or a 
fit institution or under a fit person shall not be increased by such transfer.
  



</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article>

1[<number>57</number> Transfer between children’s 
homes, under the Act, and juvenile homes of like nature in different parts of 
India.—The State Government may direct any child or the juvenile to be 
transferred from any children’s home or special home within the State to any 
other children’s home, special home or institution of a like nature or to such 
institutions outside the state in consultation with the concerned State 
Government and with the prior intimation to the Committee or the Board, as the 
case may be, and such order shall be deemed to be operative for the competent 
authority of the area to which the child or the juvenile is sent.]
  



</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>58</number> Transfer of juvenile or 
child of unsound mind or suffering from leprosy or addicted to drugs.—Where 
it appears to the competent authority that any juvenile or the child kept in a 
special home or a children’s home or shelter home or in an institution in 
pursuance of this Act, is suffering from leprosy or is of unsound mind or is 
addicted to any narcotic drug or psychotropic substance, the competent authority 
may order his removal to a leper asylum or mental hospital or treatment centre 
for drug addicts or to a place of safety for being kept there for such period 
not exceeding the period for which he is required to be kept under the order of 
the competent authority or for such further period as may be certified by the 
medical officer necessary for the proper treatment of the juvenile or the child.


</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>59</number> Release and absence of 
juvenile or child on placement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
When a juvenile or the child is kept in a children’s home or special home and on 
a report of a probation officer or social worker or of Government or a voluntary 
organisation, as the case may be, the competent authority may consider, the 
release of such juvenile or the child permitting him to live with his parent or 
guardian or under the supervision of any authorised person named in the order, 
willing to receive and take charge of the juvenile or the child to educate and 
train him for some useful trade or calling or to look after him for 
rehabilitation.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The competent authority may 
also permit leave of absence to any juvenile or the child, to allow him, on 
special occasions like examination, marriage of relatives, death of kith and kin 
or the accident or serious illness of parent or any emergency of like nature, to 
go on leave under supervision, 

1[for a period generally not exceeding 
seven days], excluding the time taken in journey.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a permission has been 
revoked or forfeited and the juvenile or the child refuses or fails to return to 
the home concerned or juvenile to which he was directed so to return, the Board 
may, if necessary, cause him to be taken charge of and to be taken back to the 
concerned home.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The time during which a 
juvenile or the child is absent from a concerned home in pursuance of such 
permission granted under this section shall be deemed to be part of the time for 
which he is liable to be kept in the special home:
 Provided that when a juvenile 
has failed to return to the special home on the permission being revoked or 
forfeited, the time which elapses after his failure so to return shall be 
excluded in computing the time during which he is liable to be kept in the 
institution.
  



</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>60</number> Contribution by parents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The competent authority which makes an order for sending a juvenile or the child 
to a children’s home or to a special home or placing the juvenile under the care 
of a fit person or fit institution may make an order requiring the parent or 
other person liable to maintain the juvenile or the child to contribute to his 
maintenance, if able to do so, in the prescribed manner according to income.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The competent authority may 
direct, if necessary, the payment to be made to poor parent or guardian by the 
Superintendent or the Project Manager of the home to pay such expenses for the 
journey of the inmate or parent or guardian or both, from the home to his 
ordinary place of residence at the time of sending the juvenile as may be 
prescribed.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>61</number> Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government 

1[***] may create a Fund under such name 
as it thinks fit for the welfare and rehabilitation of the juvenile or the child 
dealt with under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be credited to 
the Fund such voluntary donations, contributions or subscriptions as may be made 
by any individual or organisation.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Fund created under 
sub-section (1) shall be administered by the State advisory board in such manner 
and for such purposes as may be prescribed.





</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>62</number> Central, State, district 
and city advisory boards.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government or a State Government may constitute a Central or a State 
advisory board, as the case may be, to advise that Government on matter relating 
to the establishment and maintenance of the homes, mobilisation of resources, 
provision of facilities for education, training and rehabilitation of child in 
need of care and protection and juvenile in conflict with law and co-ordination 
among the various official and non-official agencies concerned.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central or State 
advisory board shall consist of such persons as the Central Government or the 
State Government, as the case may be, may think fit and shall include eminent 
social workers, representatives of voluntary organisation in the field of child 
welfare corporate sector, academicians, medical professionals and the concerned 
Department of the State Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The district or city level 
inspection committee constituted under section 35 of this Act shall also 
function as the district or city advisory board.
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article>


1[<number>62A</number> Constitution of Child 
Protection Unit responsible for implementation of the Act.—Every State 
Government shall constitute a Child Protection Unit for the State and, such 
Unites for every District, consisting of such officers and other employees as 
may be appointed by that Government, to take up matters relating to children in 
need of care and protection and juveniles in conflict with law with a view to 
ensure the implementation of this Act including the establishment and 
maintenance of homes, notification of competent authorities in relation to these 
children and their rehabilitation and co-ordination with various official and 
non-official agencies concerned.]
  



</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>63</number> Special juvenile police 
unit.—
<section><number>1</number> In order to enable the 
police officers who frequently or exclusively deal with juveniles or are 
primarily engaged in the prevention of juvenile crime or handling of the 
juveniles or children under this Act to perform their functions more 
effectively, they shall be specially instructed and trained.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In every police station at 
least one officer with aptitude and appropriate training and orientation may be 
designated as the ‘juvenile or the child welfare officer’ who will handle the 
juvenile or the child in co-ordination with the police.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Special juvenile police 
unit, of which all police officers designated as above, to handle juveniles or 
children will be members, may be created in every district and city to 
co-ordinate and to upgrade the police treatment of the juveniles and the 
children.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>64</number> Juvenile in conflict with 
law undergoing sentence at commencement of this Act.—In 
any area in which this Act is brought into force, the State Government 

1[***] 

2[shall direct] that a juvenile in 
conflict with law who is undergoing any sentence of imprisonment at the 
commencement of this Act, shall, in lieu of undergoing such sentence, be sent to 
a special home or be kept in fit institution in such manner as the State 
Government 

1[***] thinks fit for the remainder of 
the period of the sentence; and the provisions of this Act shall apply to the 
juvenile as if he had been ordered by the Board to be sent to such special home 
or institution or, as the case may be, ordered to be kept under protective care 
under sub-section (2) of section 16 of this Act.
  




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>65</number> Procedure in respect of bonds. </title>—Provisions of Chapter XXXIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) shall, as far as may be, apply to bonds taken under this Act. 
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>66</number> Delegation of powers.—The 
State Government may, by the general order, direct that any power exercisable by 
it under this Act shall, in such circumstances and under such conditions, if 
any, as may be prescribed in the order, be exercisable also by an officer 
subordinate to that Government 

1[***].
  



</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>67</number> Protection of action 
taken in good faith.—No suit or legal 
proceedings shall lie against the State Government or voluntary organisation 
running the home or any officer and the staff appointed in pursuance of this Act 
in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or of any rules or order made thereunder.
  
</article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>68</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
carry out the purposes of this Act:
 

1[Provided that the Central Government 
may, frame model rules in respect of all or any of the matters with respect to 
which the State Government may make rules under this section, and where any such 
model rules have been framed in respect of any such matter, they shall apply to 
the State until the rules in respect of that matter is made by the State 
Government and while making any such rules, so far as is practicable, they 
conform to such model rules.]
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for 
all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  the term of office of the members of the Board 
and the manner in which such member may resign under sub-section (4) of section 
4;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  the time of the meetings of the Board and the 
rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meeting under 
sub-section (1) of section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  the management of observation homes including 
the standards and various types of services to be provided by them and the 
circumstances in which and the manner in which, the certification of the 
observation home may be granted or withdrawn and such other matters as are 
referred to in section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  the management of special homes including the 
standards and various types of services to be provided by them and the 
circumstances in which and the manner in which, the certification of the special 
home may be granted or withdrawn and such other matters as are referred to in 
section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number>  persons by whom any juvenile in conflict with 
law may be produced before the Board and the manner of sending such juvenile, to 
an observation home under sub-section (2) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number>  matters relating to removal of 
disqualifications attaching to conviction of a juvenile under section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>vii</number>  the qualifications of the Chairperson and 
members, and the tenure for which they may be appointed under sub-section (3) of 
section 29;
 </subsection><subsection>     <number>viii</number>  the time of the meetings of the Committee and 
the rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its meeting 
under sub-section (1) of section 30;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ix</number>  the manner of making the report to the police 
and to the Committee and the manner of sending and entrusting the child to 
children’s home pending the inquiry under sub-section (2) of section 32;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>x</number>  the management of children’s homes including the 
standards and nature of services to be provided by them, and the manner in which 
certification of a children’s home or recognition to a voluntary organisation 
may be granted or withdrawn under sub-section (2)
2[and the 
manner of registration of institutions under sub-section (3)] of section 34;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>xi</number>  appointment of inspection committees for 
children’s homes, their tenure and purposes for which inspection committees may 
be appointed and such other matters as are referred to in section 35;
 <subsubsection>      <number>xii</number>  facilities to be provided by the shelter homes 
under sub-section (3) of section 37;
 
2[(xiia)  
rehabilitation mechanism to be resorted to in adoption under sub-section (2), 
notification of guidelines under sub-section (3) and the manner of recognition 
of specialised adoption agencies under sub-section (4) of section 41;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>      <number>xiii</number>  for carrying out the scheme of foster care 
programme of children under sub-section (3) of section 42;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>     <number>xiv</number>  for carrying out various schemes of sponsorship 
of children under sub-section (2) of section 43;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>      <number>xv</number>  matters relating to after-care organisation 
under section 44;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>     <number>xvi</number>  for ensuring effective linkages between various 
agencies for facilitating rehabilitation and social integration of the child 
under section 45;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>     <number>xvii</number>  the purposes and the manner in which the Fund 
shall be administered under sub-section (3) of section 61;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>    <number>xviii</number>  any other matter which is required to be, or 
may be, prescribed.
 

3[(3) Every rule made by the Central 
Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, 
the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.]
 

4[(4)] Every rule made by a State 
Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before the Legislature of that State.





</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>69</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Juvenile Justice Act, 1986 (53 of 1986) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, 
anything done or any action taken under the said Act shall be deemed to have 
been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.
  
</section></article> 
 The Juvenile Justice (Care and 
Protection  
of Children) Act, 2000
  
 <article><number>70</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any difficulty 
arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove the 
difficulty:
 Provided that no such order 
shall be made after the expiry of the period of two years from the commencement 
of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> However, order made under 
the section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament.
 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Ins. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 9, for sub-section (1). 
Sub-section (1), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Ins. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Section 14 renumbered as sub-section thereof by Act 
33 of 2006, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 12, for clause (g). 
Clause (g), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 13, for “or life 
imprisonment” (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Ins. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 14.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 15, for section 21. 
Section 21, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 16, for “by 
notification in Official Gazette, constitute for every district or group of 
districts, specified in the notification” (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  The words “authorised by the State Government” 
omitted by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  The words “or any police officer or special juvenile 
police unit or the designated police officer” omitted by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 18 
(w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Ins. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 19 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  The words “local authority” omitted by Act 33 of 
2006, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 20, for  Explanation .
 Explanation , before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 21, for sub-sections 
(2), (3) and (4). Sub-section (2), (3)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  The words “or the local authority” omitted by Act 33 
of 2006, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 22, for section 57. 
Section 57, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Subs. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 23, for “for maximum 
seven days” (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  The words “or local authority” omitted by Act 33 of 
2006, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Ins. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 24 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>  The words “or the local authority” omitted by Act 33 
of 2006, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  The words “or the local authority” omitted by Act 33 
of 2006, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 22-8-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>  Ins. by Act 33 of 2006, sec. 26</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>