<act><tid>1490821</tid>
<title>THE UTTAR PRADESH APPROPRIATION ACT, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1996</year>
[ 27th March, <year>1996</year>]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-

An Act to authorise payment and appropriation of certain further 
sums 
from and out of the Consolidated Fund of the State of 
Uttar 
Pradesh for the services of the financial year <year>1995</year>- 96.





<article><tid>470025</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Uttar Pradesh 
Appropriation Act, <year>1996</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>34705</tid>
<number> 2</number> Issue of Rs. 2203, 52, 23, 000 out of the Consolidated Fund of 
the State of uttar Pradesh for the financial year <year>1995</year>- 96. From and 
out of the Consolidated Fund of the State of Uttar Pradesh there may 
be paid and applied sums not exceeding those specified in column 3 of 
the Schedule amounting in the aggregate[ inclusive of the sums 
specified in column 3 of the Schedule to the Order made by the 
President on the 12th January, <year>1996</year> under sub- clause (c) of clause
<section><tid>869743</tid>
<number>1</number> 
of article 357 of the Constitution and published with the notification 
of the Government of India in the Ministry of Finance (Department of  
  Economic Affairs) No. S. O. 40 (E), dated the 12th January, <year>1996</year>] to 
the sum of two thousand two hundred and three crores, fifty- two lakhs 
and twenty- three thousand rupees towards defraying the several charges 
which will come in course of payment during the financial year <year>1995</year>- 
96, in respect of the services specified in column 2 of the Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>799347</tid>
<number>3</number>Appropriation. The sums authorised to be paid and applied from 
and out of the Consolidated Fund of the State of Uttar Pradesh by this 
Act shall be appropriated for the services and purposes expressed in 
the Schedule in relation to the said year.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>