<act><tid>1490539</tid>
<title>THE STATE OF NAGALAND ACT, <year>1962</year></title>

ACT NO. 27 OF <year>1962</year>
[ 4th September, <year>1962</year>.]

An Act to provide for the formation of the State of Nagaland and for 
matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>479466</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the State of Nagaland Act, 
<year>1962</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>638335</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>177129</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> means the day which the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint;

</section>

<section><tid>826525</tid>
<number>b</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>876407</tid>
<number>c</number>" assembly constituency" and" parliamentary constituency" 
have the same meanings as in the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1074806</tid>
<number>d</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, 
order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other 
instrument or custom or usage having the force of law;

</section>

<section><tid>1050040</tid>
<number>e</number>" Naga Hills- Tuensang Area" means the Naga Hills- Tuensang 
Area specified in Part B of the Table appended to 
paragraph 20 of the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution, 
comprising the areas which at the commencement of the 
Constitution were known as the Naga- Hills District and 
the Naga Tribal Area;

</section>

<section><tid>972220</tid>
<number>f</number>" regional council" means the regional council referred 
to in article 371A.
PART

FORMATION OF THE STATE OF NAGALAND

PART II

FORMATION OF THE STATE OF NAGALAND




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>265768</tid>
<number> 3</number> Formation of State of Nagaland.
<section><tid>421149</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day,  
there shall be formed a new State to be known as the State of Nagaland 
comprising the territories which immediately before that day were 
comprised in the Naga
<pagefootnote><pagenum>674</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 12. <year>1963</year> vide Notification No. G. S. R. 1735 dt. 30. 10. 63, see 
Gaz. of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i). P. 2030.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Hills- Tuensang Area and thereupon the said territories shall cease to 
form part of the State of Assam.


</section>

<section><tid>1513446</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the power of the State Government to 
alter after the appointed day, the name, extent or boundaries of any 
district, the State of Nagaland shall consist of three districts to be 
called the Kohima district, Mokokchung district and Tuensang district, 
each comprising the areas respectively set out in the Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>622952</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under the 
heading" I. THE STATES"--
<section><tid>1366390</tid>
<number>a</number>in the paragraph relating to the territories of the 
State of Assam, the following shall be added at the 
end, namely:--
" and the territories specified in sub- section (1) 
of section 3 of the State of Nagaland Act, <year>1962</year>";


</section>

<section><tid>1243934</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 15, the following entry shall be inserted, 
namely:--
" 16. Nagaland... The territories specified in 
sub- section (1) of section 3 of the State of Nagaland 
Act, <year>1962</year>.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1072819</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of Sixth Schedule to the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in the Sixth Schedule to the Constitution--
<section><tid>1332283</tid>
<number>a</number>in paragraph 20--

<subsection><tid>1821479</tid>
<number>i</number>sub- paragraph (2B) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1662983</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- paragraph (3), the brackets and words 
" (other than the Naga Hills- Tuensang Area)" shall be 
omitted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>822255</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Table appended to paragraph 20, in Part B, the item 
" 2. The Naga Hills- Tuensang Area" shall be omitted.
PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

The Council of States




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1853812</tid>
<number> 6</number> Representation in Council of States. As from the appointed 
day--
<section><tid>681224</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be allotted one seat to the State of 
Nagaland in the Council of States;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>675</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1304875</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the 
Table--

<subsection><tid>840279</tid>
<number>i</number>entries 16 to 19 shall be re- numbered as 
entries 17 to 20,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1313281</tid>
<number>ii</number>after entry 15, the following entry shall be 
inserted, namely:--
" 16. Nagaland........... 1",


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>353004</tid>
<number>iii</number>at the end, for the figures" 224", the 
figures" 225" shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>883359</tid>
<number>7</number>Election to fill vacancy. As soon as may be after the 
appointed day, there shall be held an election to fill the seat 
allotted to the State of Nagaland in the Council of States.


</article>



<article><tid>1001829</tid>
<number>8</number>Term of office. The term of office of the member for the first 
time elected to fill the seat allotted to the State of Nagaland in the 
Council of States shall expire on the 2nd day of April, <year>1968</year>.
The House of the People



</article>



<article><tid>932359</tid>
<number> 9</number> Representation in House of the People.
<section><tid>1218837</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the  
appointed day--

<subsection><tid>160560</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be allotted one seat to the State of 
Nagaland in the House of the People;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>294289</tid>
<number>b</number>in the First Schedule to the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>).

<subsubsection><tid>1499099</tid>
<number>i</number>the entry" 25. Naga Hills- Tuensang 
Area...... 1" shall be omitted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1011971</tid>
<number>ii</number>entries 16 to 24 shall be re- numbered as 
entries 17 to 25;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>635492</tid>
<number>iii</number>after entry 15, the following entry shall be 
inserted, namely:--
" 16. Nagaland.......... 1".


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>673898</tid>
<number>2</number>The whole of the State of Nagaland shall from one 
parliamentary constituency to be called the parliamentary constituency 
of Nagaland for the purpose of filling the seat allotted to that State 
in the House of the People.

</section>

<section><tid>604908</tid>
<number>3</number>For the period referred to in clause (2) of article 371A, 
section 13D of the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>). shall apply in relation to the parliamentary constituency of 
Nagaland with the modification that it shall be necessary to prepare 
and revise separately the electoral roll for that part of the said 
parliamentary constituency which

<pagefootnote><pagenum>676</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

comprises the Tuensang district and the provisions of Part III of that 
Act shall apply in relation to the said part as they apply in relation 
to an assembly constituency.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>512498</tid>
<number>10</number>Provision as to sitting member. The sitting member of the 
House of the People representing, immediately before the appointed 
day, the Naga Hills- Tuensang Area shall, as from that day, represent 
the State of Nagaland in that House and shall continue to do so until 
a person is elected in accordance with law to fill the seat allotted 
to the parliamentary constituency of Nagaland.
The Legislative Assembly



</article>



<article><tid>1997167</tid>
<number> 11</number> Strength of Legislative Assembly.
<section><tid>79697</tid>
<number>1</number>The total number of  
seats to be filled by persons chosen by direct election in the 
Legislative Assembly of Nagaland shall be 60:
Provided that for the period referred to in clause (2) of article 
371A, the total number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of 
Nagaland shall be <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 52], of which--


<subsection><tid>1530998</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> twelve seats] shall be allocated to the Tuensang 
district and shall be filled by persons chosen by the 
members of the regional council from amongst themselves 
in such manner as the Governor, after consulting that 
council, may by notification in the Official Gazette 
specify, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>238678</tid>
<number>b</number>the remaining forty seats shall be filled by persons 
chosen by direct election from assembly constituencies 
in the rest of the State of Nagaland.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>421830</tid>
<number>2</number>In the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>).--

<subsection><tid>602975</tid>
<number>a</number>in section 7, the following proviso shall be inserted at 
the end, namely:--
" Provided that for the period referred to in 
clause (2) of article 371A, the total number of seats 
allotted to the Legislative Assembly of Nagaland shall 
be 46, of which--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>602975</tid>
<number>a</number>six seats shall be allocated to the 
Tuensang district and shall be filled by persons 
chosen by the members of the regional council 
referred to in that article from amongst 
themselves in such manner as the Governor, after 
consulting that council, may by notification in 
the Official Gazette specify, and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>677</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 61 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3, for" 46". 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" six seats".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>151454</tid>
<number>b</number>the remaining forty seats shall be filled by persons 
chosen by direct election from assembly constituencies 
in the rest of the State of Nagaland.";

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>151454</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Second Schedule, after entry 14, the following entry 
shall be inserted, namely:--
" 15. Nagaland... <footcitenum>60</footcitenum> for the period referred to in 
clause (2) of article 371A, 46].".


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>828869</tid>
<number>3</number>In the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>), 
in section 5, in clause (c), the following proviso shall be inserted 
at the end, namely:--
" Provided that for the period referred to in clause (2) 
of article 371A, a person shall not be qualified 
to be chosen to fill any seat allocated to the 
Tuensang district in the Legislative Assembly of 
Nagaland unless he is a member of the regional 
council referred to in that article.".


</section>

<section><tid>1911203</tid>
<number>4</number>The Election Commission shall delimit the assembly 
constituencies in accordance with the provisions of the Constitution 
on the basis of the latest census figures, and in doing so the 
Commission shall have regard to the following provisions, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1764807</tid>
<number>a</number>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, consist 
of geographically compact areas, and in delimiting 
them, regard shall be had to physical features, 
existing boundaries of administrative units, facilities 
of communication, public convenience and linguistic 
affinities of the people,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1719505</tid>
<number>b</number>all constituencies shall be single- member 
constituencies, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>334022</tid>
<number>c</number>the population of each constituency shall not, as far as 
practicable, be more than six thousand.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1072819</tid>
<number> 5</number> For the purpose of assisting the Election Commission in the 
performance of its functions under this section, the Commission shall 
associate with itself five persons of whom three shall be elected by 
the members of the Interim Body established under section 3 of the 
Nagaland (Transitional Provisions) Regulation, <year>1961</year> (Regulation 2 of  
  <year>1961</year>), from among themselves and two shall be nominated by the Central 
Government:
Provided that none of the said associate members shall have a 
right to vote or to sign any decision of the Election Commission.

<section><tid>91562</tid>
<number>6</number>The Election Commission shall--

<subsection><tid>690686</tid>
<number>a</number>formulate its proposals in regard to the matters 
mentioned in sub- section (4) and publish them in the 
Official Gazette

<pagefootnote><pagenum>678</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of the State of Assam and in such other manner as the 
Commission may consider fit, together with a notice 
inviting objections and suggestions in relation to the 
proposals and specifying a date on or after which the 
proposals will be further considered by it;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>965986</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified, and 
for the purpose of such consideration hold one or more 
public sittings at such place or places as it may think 
fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1617327</tid>
<number>c</number>after considering all objections and suggestions which 
may have been received by it before the date so 
specified, determine the matters mentioned in sub- 
section (4) by one or more final orders and cause such 
order or orders to be published in the Official Gazette 
of the State of Assam; and upon such publication the 
order or orders shall have the full force of law and 
shall not be called in question in any court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>374901</tid>
<number>d</number>amend the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly 
Constituencies Order, <year>1961</year>, so as to include therein 
the parliamentary constituency of Nagaland and the 
Assembly constituencies delimited under this section.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>470678</tid>
<number> 12</number> Rules of Procedure. The rules as to procedure and conduct of 
business in force immediately before the appointed day with respect to 
the Legislative Assembly of Assam shall, until rules are made under 
clause
<section><tid>1914073</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 208, have effect in relation to the Legislative  
Assembly of Nagaland, subject to such modifications and adaptations as 
may be made therein by the Speaker thereof.
PART

HIGH COURT

PART IV

HIGH COURT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>5875</tid>
<number> 13</number> Common High Court for Assam and Nagaland.
<section><tid>1017256</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the  
appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>424334</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be a common High Court for the State of 
Assam and the State of Nagaland to be called the High 
Court of Assam and Nagaland (hereinafter referred to as  
  the common High Court);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1541700</tid>
<number>b</number>the Judges of the High Court of Assam holding office 
immediately before that day shall, unless they have 
elected otherwise, become on that day the Judges of the 
common High Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>679</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1858919</tid>
<number>2</number>Expenditure in respect of the salaries and allowances of the 
Judges of the common High Court shall be allocated between the State 
of Assam and the State of Nagaland in such proportion as the 
President may by order determine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1774565</tid>
<number> 14</number> Provisions as to Advocates.
<section><tid>1192137</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day,-- 

<subsection><tid>1422149</tid>
<number>a</number>in the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (5 of <year>1961</year>), in section 3, 
in sub- section (1), for clause (b), the following 
clause shall be substituted, namely:--
" (b) for the States of Assam and Nagaland and the 
Union territory of Manipur, to be known as the Bar 
Council of Assam and Nagaland;";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1475280</tid>
<number>b</number>the Bar Council of Assam shall be deemed to be the Bar 
Council of Assam and Nagaland.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>721907</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who immediately before the appointed day is an 
advocate entitled to practise in the High Court of Assam shall be 
entitled to practise as an advocate in the common High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1587159</tid>
<number>3</number>All persons who immediately before the appointed day are 
advocates on the roll of the Bar Council of Assam shall as from that 
day become advocates on the roll of the Bar Council of Assam and 
Nagaland.

</section>

<section><tid>1223511</tid>
<number>4</number>The right of audience in the common High Court shall be 
regulated in accordance with the like principles as, immediately 
before the appointed day, are in force with respect to the right of 
audience in the High Court of Assam:
Provided that as between the Advocate- General of Assam and the 
Advocate- General of Nagaland the right of audience shall be determined 
with reference to their respective dates of enrolment as advocates.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1085216</tid>
<number>15</number>Practice and procedure in common High Court. Subject to the 
provisions of this Part, the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Assam shall, with necessary modifications, apply in relation to the 
common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>451167</tid>
<number>16</number>Custody of Seal of common High Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custody of 
the Seal of the High Court of Assam shall, with necessary 
modifications, apply with respect to the custody of the Seal of the 
common High Court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>680</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1294942</tid>
<number>17</number>Form of writs and other processes. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs 
and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court of Assam 
shall, with necessary modifications, apply with respect to the form of 
writs and other processes used, issued or awarded by the common High 
Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1524826</tid>
<number>18</number>Powers of Judges. The law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to the powers of the Chief Justice, single 
Judges and division courts of the High Court of Assam and with respect 
to all matters ancillary to the exercise of those powers shall, with 
necessary modifications, apply in relation to the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1295090</tid>
<number>19</number>Principal seat of common High Court. The principal seat of 
the common High Court shall, unless otherwise determined by the Chief 
Justice after consultation with the Governors of Assam and Nagaland, 
be at the same place as the principal seat of the High Court of Assam 
immediately before the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>751029</tid>
<number>20</number>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court. The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court from the High Court of Assam and the Judges and division 
courts thereof shall, with necessary modifications, apply in relation 
to the common High Court.


</article>



<article><tid>11101</tid>
<number>21</number>Pending suits, appeals and proceedings. All suits, appeals 
and proceedings, civil, criminal or otherwise, pending in the High 
Court of Assam immediately before the appointed day shall, on that 
day, stand removed to the common High Court and the common High Court 
shall have jurisdiction to hear and determine the same, and the 
judgments, decrees, sentences and orders of the High Court of Assam 
delivered, passed or made before the appointed day shall have the same 
force and effect as if they had been delivered, passed or made by the 
common High Court.
PART

FINANCIAL PROVISIONS

PART V

FINANCIAL PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1431519</tid>
<number>22</number>Authorisation of expenditure pending its sanction by 
Legislature. The President may, at any time before the appointed day, 
authorise such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the State of 
Nagaland as he deems necessary for a period of not more than six 
months beginning with the appointed day, pending the sanction of such 
expenditure by the Legislature of the State of Nagaland:
Provided that the Governor of Nagaland may, after the appointed 
day, authorise such further expenditure as he deems necessary


<pagefootnote><pagenum>681</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

from the Consolidated Fund of the State of Nagaland for any period not 
extending beyond the said period of six months.



</article>



<article><tid>147761</tid>
<number>22A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Allowances and privileges of Governor of Nagaland. The 
allowances and privileges of the Governor of Nagaland shall, until 
provision in that behalf is made by Parliament by law under clause (3) 
of article 158, be such as the President may, by order, determine.]


</article>



<article><tid>1320730</tid>
<number>23</number>Distribution of revenues. The President shall by order 
determine the grants- in- aid of the revenues of the State of Nagaland 
and the share of that State in the Union duties of excise, estate duty 
and taxes on income and for that purpose amend thereby the relevant 
provisions of the Union Duties of Excise (Distribution) Act, <year>1962</year> (3  
  of <year>1962</year>), the Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special  
  Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> (58 of <year>1957</year>), the Estate Duty (Distribution) 
Act, <year>1962</year> (9 of <year>1962</year>), and the Constitution (Distribution of  
  Revenues) Order, <year>1962</year> (C. O. 63), in such manner as he thinks fit.


</article>



<article><tid>545681</tid>
<number> 24</number> Property, assets, rights, liabilities and obligations.
<section><tid>862922</tid>
<number>1</number> 
All property and assets situated in, or used for, or in connection 
with the administration of, the Naga Hills- Tuensang Area and vested in 
the Union immediately before the appointed day (other than any  
  property or assets so vested for purposes of the Union) shall, as from 
that day, vest in the State of Nagaland:
Provided that the cash balances in the treasuries in the Naga 
Hills- Tuensang Area immediately before the appointed day shall, as 
from that day, vest in the State of Nagaland.


</section>

<section><tid>438571</tid>
<number>2</number>All rights, liabilities and obligations of the Central 
Government, whether arising out of any contract or otherwise, which 
are, immediately before the appointed day, the rights, liabilities and 
obligations of the Central Government arising out of the or in 
connection with the administration of the Naga Hills- Tuensang Area 
shall, as from that day, be the rights, liabilities and obligations of 
the Government of the State of Nagaland.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1969911</tid>
<number>25</number>Arrears of taxes. The right to recover arrears of any tax or 
duty (being a tax or duty enumerated in the State List in the Seventh  
  Schedule to the Constitution) which have fallen due in the Naga Hills- 
Tuensang Area shall pass to the State of Nagaland.
PART

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART VI

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1658036</tid>
<number> 26</number> Continuance of existing laws and their adaptation.
<section><tid>1542892</tid>
<number>1</number>All  
laws in force, immediately before the appointed day, in the Naga 
Hills- Tuensang Area shall continue to be in force in the State of 
Nagaland until altered, repealed or amended by a competent Legislature 
or other competent authority.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>682</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 35 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 26. 7. <year>1981</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>930142</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of facilitating the application in relation 
to the State of Nagaland of any law made before the appointed day, the 
appropriate Government may, within two years from that day, by order 
make such adaptations and modifications of the law, whether by way of 
repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient, and thereupon 
every such law shall have effect subject to the adaptations and 
modifications so made until altered, repealed or amended by a 
competent Legislature or other competent authority.
Explanation.-- In this section, the expression" appropriate 
Government" means, as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated 
in the Union List in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution, the 
Central Government; and as respects any other law, the Government of 
Nagaland.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1572281</tid>
<number>27</number>Power to construe laws. Notwithstanding that no provision or 
insufficient provision has been made under section 26 for the 
adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal 
or authority required or empowered to enforce such law may, for the 
purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the State of 
Nagaland, construe the law in such manner not affecting the substance 
as may be necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the 
court, tribunal or authority, as the case may be.


</article>



<article><tid>339882</tid>
<number> 28</number> Provisions as to continuance of courts and of officers, etc.

<section><tid>1844400</tid>
<number>1</number>All courts and tribunals and all authorities discharging lawful  
functions throughout the Naga Hills- Tuensang Area or any part thereof 
immediately before the appointed day shall, unless their continuance 
is inconsistent with the provisions of this Act or until other 
provision is made by a competent Legislature or other competent 
authority, continue to exercise their respective functions.

</section>

<section><tid>911145</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person who, immediately before the appointed day, is 
holding or discharging the duties of any post or office in connection 
with the administration of the Naga Hills- Tuensang Area or any part 
thereof shall, except where by virtue or in consequence of the 
provisions of this Act such post or office ceases to exist on that 
day, continue to hold the same post or office in the State of 
Nagaland, and shall be deemed, as from that day, to have been duly 
appointed to such post or office by the Government of, or other 
appropriate authority in, such State.

</section>

<section><tid>793443</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall be deemed to prevent a 
competent authority, after the appointed day, from passing in relation 
to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>683</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

any such person any order affecting his continuance in such post or 
office.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1557253</tid>
<number>29</number>Amendment of Act 37 of <year>1956</year>. As from the appointed day, in 
section 15 of the States Re- organisation Act, <year>1956</year>, in clause (c), for 
the words," and Assam", the words" Assam and Nagaland" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>598623</tid>
<number>30</number>Effect of provisions of Act inconsistent with other laws. The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.


</article>



<article><tid>1433372</tid>
<number> 31</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>368866</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by 
order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears 
to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpose of removing the 
difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1398224</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid before each 
House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>150446</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1675751</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>138892</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> immediately following the session] or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>579168</tid>
<number>33</number>[ Repealed.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1974</year> (56  
  of <year>1974</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>684</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1981</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 26- 7- <year>1981</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>