<act><tid>1501900</tid>
<title>THE MERCHANT SHIPPING (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 59 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 30th December, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>838783</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>814293</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Merchant Shipping (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1472282</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>773741</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new sections for sections 356A to 356H.- For sections 
 356A to 356H of the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44 of <year>1958</year>) 
 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), the following sections 
shall be substituted, namely:-
Application.

' 356A. Application.- (1) Save as otherwise provided, this Part shall 
apply to-

<section><tid>1272403</tid>
<number>a</number>oil tankers of one hundred and fifty tons gross or more, other 
ships of four hundred tons gross or more and off- shore installations; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>151124</tid>
<number>b</number>incidents of marine casualty or acts relating to such casualty 
occurring with grave and imminent danger to Indian coast line or 
related interests from pollution or threat of pollution in the sea by 
deliberate, negligent or accidental release of oil, ballast water, 
noxious liquid and other harmful substances into sea including such 
incidents occurring on the high seas.

<subsection><tid>705666</tid>
<number>2</number>This Part shall not apply to any war ships or other ships owned or 
operated by the Government and used for the time being on Government 
non- commercial service.
Definitions.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1941268</tid>
<number> 356B</number> Definitions.- In this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1866442</tid>
<number>a</number>" ballast" means any solid or liquid placed in a ship to increase 
the draft to change the trim, to regulate the stability, or to maintain 
stress load within such limits as may be prescribed;

</section>

<section><tid>1729777</tid>
<number>b</number>" cargo" includes ballast and ship' s stores and fuel;

</section>

<section><tid>459809</tid>
<number>c</number>" coasts" has the meaning assigned to it in section 357;

</section>

<section><tid>1104313</tid>
<number>d</number>" coastal waters" means any part of the territorial waters of India, 
or any marine areas adjacent thereto over which India has, or, may 
hereafter have, exclusive jurisdiction in regard to control of marine 
pollution under the Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Exclusive 
Economic Zone and other Maritime Zones Act, <year>1976</year> (80 of <year>1976</year>), or any 
other law for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>1095867</tid>
<number>e</number>" Convention" means the International Convention for the Prevention 
of Pollution from Ships, <year>1973</year>, including its Protocol of <year>1978</year>, as 
amended from time to time in the manner specified therein;

</section>

<section><tid>1713056</tid>
<number>f</number>" international pollution prevention certificate" means any 
certificate issued in accordance with the provisions of Pollution 
Prevention Conventions and Protocols thereto which are acceded to by 
India;

</section>

<section><tid>1169428</tid>
<number>g</number>" mile" means a nautical mile of 1, 852 metres;

</section>

<section><tid>1346204</tid>
<number>h</number>" noxious liquid substance" means any substance which has been 
designated as such by rules made under this Part;

</section>

<section><tid>474065</tid>
<number>i</number>" off- shore installation" means an installation, whether mobile or 
fixed, which is used or is intended to be used for under- water 
exploration or exploitation of crude oil, petroleum or other similar 
mineral oils, under lease, licence or any other form of contractual 
arrangement and includes-

</section>

<section><tid>1866442</tid>
<number>a</number>any installation which could be moved from place to place under its 
own motive power or otherwise; and

</section>

<section><tid>1729777</tid>
<number>b</number>a pipe- line; 
 (j)" oil" means petroleum in any form including crude oil, fuel oil, 
sludge, oil refuse and refined products;

</section>

<section><tid>330975</tid>
<number>k</number>" oily mixture" means a mixture with any oil content;

</section>

<section><tid>572953</tid>
<number>l</number>" oil tanker" means a ship constructed or adapted primarily to carry 
oil in bulk in its cargo spaces and includes any combination carrier or 
any chemical tanker when it is carrying a cargo or part cargo of oil in 
bulk;

</section>

<section><tid>1800205</tid>
<number>m</number>" reception facilities", in relation to a port, means facilities for 
enabling tankers or ships using the port to discharge or deposit 
residue or mixture of any substance subject to control by the 
Convention;

</section>

<section><tid>22480</tid>
<number>n</number>" ship" means a vessel of any type whatsoever operating in the 
marine environment and includes hydrofoil boats, air- cushion vehicles, 
submersibles, floating craft and fixed or floating platforms.
Issue of pollution prevention certificate.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>575002</tid>
<number> 356C</number> Issue of pollution prevention certificate.-
<section><tid>83504</tid>
<number>1</number>No Indian oil  
tanker or other Indian ship shall proceed to sea unless there is in 
force, in respect of that ship, a certificate issued by the Central 
Government, to be called an international oil pollution prevention 
certificate, in such form, for such duration and subject to such 
conditions as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1670497</tid>
<number>2</number>No Indian oil tanker or other Indian ship carrying noxious liquid 
substances in bulk shall proceed to sea except with a certificate 
issued by the Central Government, to be called an international 
pollution prevention certificate, in such form, for such duration and 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed for the carriage of 
noxious liquid substances in bulk.

</section>

<section><tid>875556</tid>
<number>3</number>No Indian oil tanker or other Indian ship to which Annexure IV of 
the Convention applies shall proceed to sea except with a certificate 
issued by the Central Government, to be called an international sewage 
pollution prevention certificate, in such form, for such duration and 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," sewage" means-


<subsection><tid>1273202</tid>
<number>i</number>drainage and other waste from any form of toilets, urinals and 
water closet scuppers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1471517</tid>
<number>ii</number>drainage from medical premises (dispensary, sick bay and other  
  like places) via wash basins, wash tubs and scuppers located in such 
premises;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>376816</tid>
<number>iii</number>drainage from spaces containing living animals; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>581699</tid>
<number>iv</number>other waste water when mixed with the drainages specified above.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>960890</tid>
<number>4</number>A valid international pollution prevention certificate issued in 
respect of an oil tanker or a ship, other than an Indian ship, by the 
Government of the country to which the ship belongs shall, subject to 
such rules as the Central Government may make in this behalf, have the 
same effect in India as the corresponding certificate issued in respect 
of an Indian ship has under this Part.
Issue of certificates for foreign ships in India and Indian ships in 
foreign countries.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1830089</tid>
<number> 356D</number> Issue of certificates for foreign ships in India and Indian ships 
in foreign countries.-
<section><tid>884765</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, at the request of  
the Government of a country to which the Convention applies, cause 
any international pollution prevention certificate to be issued in 
accordance with the Convention in respect of an oil tanker or other 
ship in that country, if it is satisfied that such certificate can 
properly be issued, and where a certificate is so issued, it shall 
contain a statement that it has been issued on request.

</section>

<section><tid>1015025</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may request the Government of a country to 
which the Convention applies, to issue any international pollution 
prevention certificate in accordance with the Convention in respect 
of a ship and the certificate issued in pursuance of such a request 
containing a statement that it has been so issued shall have the 
same effect as if it had been issued by the Central Government under 
this Act.
Requirement for construction and equipment in ships to prevent 
pollution.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>296898</tid>
<number>356E</number>Requirement for construction and equipment in ships to prevent 
pollution.- For the purpose of preventing or reducing discharges of 
harmful substances or mixtures containing such substances from the 
oil tankers or other ships, the Central Government may make rules 
requiring Indian oil tankers and other Indian ships to be fitted 
with such equipment and to comply with such requirements for 
construction, survey of equipment and structure of such oil tankers or 
other ships and specifying conditions for making of surveys of all oil 
tankers or other ships, as may be prescribed, prior to issuing an 
international pollution prevention certificate.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," harmful substance" 
means any substance which, if introduced into the sea, is liable to 
create hazards to human health, harm living resources and marine life, 
damage amenities or interfere with other legitimate uses of the sea, 
and includes any substance subject to control by the Convention.

Record books.

</article>



<article><tid>230234</tid>
<number> 356F</number> Record books.-
<section><tid>794412</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Indian oil tanker or other Indian ship  
which carries a substance subject to control by the Convention shall 
maintain, as may be required, record books in the prescribed forms, on 
board the oil tanker or other ship.

</section>

<section><tid>634824</tid>
<number>2</number>The manner in which record books shall be maintained, the nature 
of entries to be made therein, the custody and disposal thereof, and 
all other matters relating thereto shall be such as may be prescribed 
having regard to the provisions of the Convention.
Inspection and control of oil tankers and other ships to which the Part 
applies.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1873887</tid>
<number> 356G</number> Inspection and control of oil tankers and other ships to which 
the Part applies.-
<section><tid>1130317</tid>
<number>1</number>A surveyor or any person authorised in this  
behalf may go, at any reasonable time, on board an oil tanker or other 
ship to which any of the provisions of this Part applies, for the 
purposes of-

<subsection><tid>1939534</tid>
<number>a</number>ensuring that the prohibitions, restrictions and obligations 
imposed by or under this Part are complied with;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>847698</tid>
<number>b</number>satisfying himself about the adequacy of the measures taken to 
prevent pollution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1668108</tid>
<number>c</number>ascertaining the circumstances relating to an alleged discharge of 
a substance which is subject to control by the Convention from the oil 
tanker or other ship in contravention of the provisions of this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>517921</tid>
<number>d</number>inspecting any record required to be maintained on board; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>385764</tid>
<number>e</number>checking the validity of the international pollution prevention 
certificate.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1309671</tid>
<number>2</number>The surveyor or any such person may, if necessary, make, without 
unduly delaying the oil tanker or the other ship, a true copy of any 
record of the oil tanker or the other ship and may require the master 
of such tanker or ship to certify the copy to be a true copy and such 
copy shall be admissible as evidence of the facts stated therein.
Information regarding contravention of provisions of Convention.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>933581</tid>
<number> 356H</number> Information regarding contravention of provisions of Convention.-

<section><tid>126570</tid>
<number>1</number>If, on report from a surveyor or other person authorised to inspect  
an oil tanker or other ship under section 356G, the Director- General is 
satisfied that any provision of the Convention has been contravened by 
such oil tanker or other ship within the coastal waters, the Director- 
General or any officer authorised by him in this behalf, may-

<subsection><tid>1111327</tid>
<number>a</number>detain the oil tanker or other ship until the causes of such 
contravention are removed to the satisfaction of the Director- General 
or the officer authorised by him; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1708922</tid>
<number>b</number>proceed against such oil tanker or other ship for recovery of 
cost of pollution damage, if any, and the cost of prevention of 
pollution damage and cleaning of such pollution: 
Provided that where the Director- General deems it necessary, he may 
request the Indian Navy or the Coast Guard for preventing the oil 
tanker or other ship from proceeding to sea, and the Indian Navy or the 
Coast Guard, as the case may be, shall take action as requested by the 
Director- General.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>419843</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of information from the Government of any country to 
which the Convention applies that an Indian oil tanker or other 
ship has contravened any provision of the Convention, the Central 
Government may, if it deems it necessary so to do, request such 
Government to furnish further details of the alleged contravention and 
if satisfied that sufficient evidence is available to establish 
contravention of any of the provisions of this Part or the rules made 
thereunder, take appropriate action against the owner or master of the 
concerned oil tanker or other ship and intimate the reporting 
Government of the action so taken.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1288877</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 356-I.- In section 356-I of the principal Act, 
for the words" oil reception facilities", wherever they occur, the 
words" reception facilities" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>669896</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 356J.- In section 356J of the principal Act, 
for the word" oil", wherever it occurs, the words" oil or noxious 
liquid substance" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1030422</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 356K.- In section 356K of the principal Act, for 
the word" oil", wherever it occurs, the words" oil or noxious liquid 
substance" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>803528</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 356-O.- In section 356-O of the principal Act, 
in sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>693793</tid>
<number>i</number>for clauses (a) and (b), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (a) prescribe the limits of ballast, and designate noxious liquid 
substances, under clauses (a) and (h), respectively, of section 356B;


<subsection><tid>1482728</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribe the forms in which, the duration for which and the 
conditions subject to which, various international pollution prevention 
certificates shall be issued under section 356C;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>443419</tid>
<number>bb</number>prescribe the period within which, the manner in which and the 
conditions for making surveys of oil tankers or other ships prior to 
issuing 
an international pollution prevention certificate and the requirements 
as to equipment which are to be fitted for prevention of pollution by 
an oil tanker and other ship under section 356E;";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1040746</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (c), for the words" oil record books", the words" record 
books" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>17070</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (d), for the words" oil monitoring system, oily water 
separator, oil content metre, crude oil washing system, inert gas 
system or other equipments or contrivances carried out on board for 
preventing pollution of sea by oil", the words" various equipments 
required under the Convention" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>327751</tid>
<number>iv</number>after clause (e), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (ee) any other matter which, for the implementation of the 
Convention, has to be or may be prescribed.".

T. K. VISHWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>