<act><title>

The 
    Extradition Act, 1962</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Extradition Act, 1962.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1  as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint. 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 

1 [
<section><number>a</number> 
       “composite offence” means an act or conduct of a person occurred wholly 
    or in part, in a foreign State or in India but its effects or intended 
    effects, taken as a whole, would constitute an extradition offence in India 
    or in a foreign State, as the case may be;]3 [(a) 
    “composite offence” means an act or conduct of a person occurred wholly or 
    in part, in a foreign State or in India but its effects or intended effects, 
    taken as a whole, would constitute an extradition offence in India or in a 
    foreign State, as the case may be;]" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “conviction” and “convicted” do not 
    include or refer to a conviction which under foreign law is a conviction for 
    contumacy, but the term “person accused” includes a person so convicted for 
    contumacy; 
 

2 [(c) 
       “extradition offence” means— 
    4 [(c) “extradition offence” means—" 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    in relation to foreign State, being a 
    treaty State, an offence provided for in the extradition treaty with that 
    State; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in relation to a foreign State other 
    than a treaty State an offence punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
    shall not be less than one year under the laws of India or of foreign State 
    and includes a composite offence;] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>    “extradition treaty” means a 
    treaty 
3[, 
    agreement or arrangement] made by India with a foreign State relating to the 
    extradition of fugitive criminals, and includes an treaty 
3[, 
    agreement or arrangement] relating to the extradition of fugitive criminals 
    made before the 15th day of August, 1947, which extends to, and is binding 
    on, India;
5[, 
    agreement or arrangement] made by India with a foreign State relating to the 
    extradition of fugitive criminals, and includes an treaty 
5[, 
    agreement or arrangement] relating to the extradition of fugitive criminals 
    made before the 15th day of August, 1947, which extends to, and is binding 
    on, India;" 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “foreign State” means any State 
    outside India 
4[***] 
    and includes every constituent part, colony or dependency of such State;
6[***] 
    and includes every constituent part, colony or dependency of such State;" 
 

5[(f) 
       “fugitive criminal” means a person who is accused or convicted of an 
    extradition offence within the jurisdiction of a foreign State and includes 
    a person who, while in India, conspires, attempts to commit or incites or 
    participates as an accomplice in the commission of an extradition offence in 
    a foreign State;] 
    1[(f) “fugitive criminal” means a person who is 
    accused or convicted of an extradition offence within the jurisdiction of a 
    foreign State and includes a person who, while in India, conspires, attempts 
    to commit or incites or participates as an accomplice in the commission of 
    an extradition offence in a foreign State;]" 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “Magistrate” means a Magistrate of the 
    first class or a presidency Magistrate; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “notified order” means an order 
    notified in the Official Gazette; 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; and 
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>    “treaty State” means a foreign State 
    with which an extradition treaty is in operation. 
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Application of Act.—1[
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by 
      notified order, direct that the provisions of this Act other than Chapter 
      III shall apply to such foreign State or part thereof as may be specified 
      in the order.]—2[(1) 
    The Central Government may, by notified order, direct that the provisions of 
    this Act other than Chapter III shall apply to such foreign State or part 
    thereof as may be specified in the order.]" 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government may, by the same 
      notified order as is referred to in sub-section (1) or any subsequent 
      notified order, restrict such application to fugitive criminals found, or 
      suspected to be, in such part of India as may be specified in the 
      order. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the notified order relates to a treaty 
      State,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    it shall set out 
      in full the extradition treaty with that State; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    it shall not 
      remain in force for any period longer than that treaty; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    the Central 
      Government may, by the same or any subsequent notified order, render the 
      application of this Act subject to such modifications, exceptions, 
      conditions and qualifications as may be deemed expedient for implementing 
      the treaty with that State. 
 2[(4) Where there is no extradition 
      treaty made by India with any foreign State, the Central Government may, 
      by notified order, treat any Convention to which India and a foreign State 
      are parties, as an extradition treaty made by India with that foreign 
      State providing for extradition in respect of the offences specified in 
      that Convention.] 
  






 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Requisition for surrender.—A 
    requisition for the surrender of a fugitive criminal of a foreign State
    

    1[***] may be made to 
    the Central Government——A 
    requisition for the surrender of a fugitive criminal of a foreign State
    

    5[***] may be made to 
    the Central Government—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    by a diplomatic representative of 
    the foreign State 
1[***] 
    at Delhi; or
5[***] 
    at Delhi; or" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    by the Government of that foreign 
    State 
    2[***] communicating with the Central Government 
    through its diplomatic representative in that State 
3[***];
1[***] 
    communicating with the Central Government through its diplomatic 
    representative in that State 
2[***];" 
 
and if neither of these modes is 
    convenient, the requisition shall be made in such other mode as is settled 
    by arrangement made by the Government of the foreign State 
2[***] 
    with the Government of India.1[***] 
    with the Government of India." 
 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Order 
    for magisterial inquiry.—Where 
    such requisition is made, the Central Government may, if it thinks fit, 
    issue an order to any Magistrate who would have had jurisdiction to inquire 
    into the offence if it had been an offence committed within the local limits 
    of his jurisdiction, directing him to inquire into the case. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Issue of 
    warrant for arrest.—On receipt of 
    an order of the Central Government under section 5, the Magistrate shall 
    issue a warrant for the arrest of the fugitive criminal. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Procedure before Magistrate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When the fugitive criminal appears or is brought before the Magistrate, the 
    Magistrate shall inquire into the case in the same manner and shall have the 
    same jurisdiction and powers, as nearly as may be, as if the case were one 
    triable by a court of Session or High Court. 
 </section><section>
 <number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provisions, the 
    Magistrate shall, in particular, take such evidence as may be produced in 
    support of the requisition of the foreign State 

    1[***] and on behalf 
    of the fugitive criminal, including any evidence to show that the offence of 
    which the fugitive criminal is accused or has been convicted is an offence 
    of political character or is not an extradition offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    the Magistrate is of opinion that a prima facie case is not made out 
    in support of the requisition of the foreign State 

    1[***], he shall 
    discharge the fugitive criminal. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    the Magistrate is of opinion that a prima facie case is made out in support 
    of the requisition of the foreign State 

    1[***], he may commit 
    the fugitive criminal to prison to await the orders of the Central 
    Government, and shall report the result of his inquiry to the Central 
    Government; and shall forward together with such report, any written 
    statement which the fugitive criminal may desire to submit for the 
    consideration of the Central Government. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Surrender of fugitive criminal.—If, 
    upon receipt of the report and statement under sub-section (4) of section 7, 
    the Central Government is of opinion that the fugitive criminal ought to be 
    surrendered to the foreign State 

    1[***], it may issue a 
    warrant for the custody and removal of the fugitive criminal and for his 
    delivery at a place and to a person to be named in the warrant.—If, 
    upon receipt of the report and statement under sub-section (4) of section 7, 
    the Central Government is of opinion that the fugitive criminal ought to be 
    surrendered to the foreign State 

    1[***], it may issue a 
    warrant for the custody and removal of the fugitive criminal and for his 
    delivery at a place and to a person to be named in the warrant." 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Power of magistrate to issue warrant of arrest in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where it appears to any Magistrate that a person within the local limits of 
    his jurisdiction is a fugitive criminal of a foreign State 

    1[***], he may, if he 
    thinks fit, issue a warrant for the arrest of that person on such 
    information and on such evidence as would, in his opinion, justify the issue 
    of a warrant if the offence of which the person is accused or has been 
    convicted had been committed within the local limits of his jurisdiction.—(1) 
    Where it appears to any Magistrate that a person within the local limits of 
    his jurisdiction is a fugitive criminal of a foreign State 

    1[***], he may, if he 
    thinks fit, issue a warrant for the arrest of that person on such 
    information and on such evidence as would, in his opinion, justify the issue 
    of a warrant if the offence of which the person is accused or has been 
    convicted had been committed within the local limits of his jurisdiction." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Magistrate shall forthwith report the issue of a warrant under sub-section 
    (1) to the Central Government and shall forward the information, and the 
    evidence or certified copies thereof to that Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person 
    arrested on a warrant issued under sub-section (1) shall not be detained for 
    more than three months unless within that period the Magistrate receives 
    from the Central Government an order made with reference to such person 
    under section 5. 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Receipt in evidence of exhibits, depositions and other documents and 
    authentication thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any proceedings against a fugitive criminal of a foreign State 


    1[***] under this 
    Chapter, exhibits and depositions (whether received or taken in the presence 
    of the person against whom they are used or not) and copies thereof and 
    official certificates of facts and judicial documents stating facts may, if 
    duly authenticated, be received as evidence.—(1) 
    In any proceedings against a fugitive criminal of a foreign State 


    1[***] under this 
    Chapter, exhibits and depositions (whether received or taken in the presence 
    of the person against whom they are used or not) and copies thereof and 
    official certificates of facts and judicial documents stating facts may, if 
    duly authenticated, be received as evidence." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Warrants, 
    depositions or statements on oath, which purport to have been issued or 
    taken by any court of justice outside India or copies thereof, certificates 
    of, or judicial documents stating the facts of, conviction before any such 
    court shall be deemed to be duly authenticated if— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the warrant purports to be signed 
    by a Judge, magistrate or officer of the State 
2[***] 
    where the same was issued or acting in or for such State 
2[***];
2[***] 
    where the same was issued or acting in or for such State 
2[***];" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the depositions or statements or 
    copies thereof purport to be certified, under the hand of a Judge, 
    magistrate or officer of the State 
2[***], 
    where the same were taken, or acting in or for such State 
2[***], 
    to be the original depositions or statements or to be true copies thereof, 
    as the case may require;
2[***], 
    where the same were taken, or acting in or for such State 
2[***], 
    to be the original depositions or statements or to be true copies thereof, 
    as the case may require;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the certificate of, or judicial 
    document stating the fact of, a conviction purports to be certified by a 
    Judge, magistrate or officer of the State 
2[***] 
    where the conviction took place or acting in or for such State;
    2[***] where the conviction took place or acting in or 
    for such State;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the warrants, depositions, 
    statements, copies, certificates and judicial documents, as the case may be, 
    are authenticated by the oath of some witness or by the official seal of a 
    minister of the State 
2[***] 
    where the same were 
3[***] 
    issued, taken or given.
2[***] 
    where the same were 
3[***] 
    issued, taken or given." 
 
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Chapter not to apply to 

    1 [foreign 
    States] to which Chapter III applies.—Nothing 
    contained in this Chapter shall apply to fugitive criminals 

    2[***] to which 
    Chapter III applies. 
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Application of Chapter.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Chapter shall apply only to any such 

    1[Foreign State] to 
    which, by reason of an extradition arrangement entered into with that 


    2[State], it may seem 
    expedient to the Central Government to apply the same.—(1) 
    This Chapter shall apply only to any such 

    2[Foreign State] to 
    which, by reason of an extradition arrangement entered into with that 


    3[State], it may seem 
    expedient to the Central Government to apply the same." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every such application shall be by notified order, and the Central 
    Government may, by the same or any subsequent notified order, direct that 
    this Chapter and Chapters I, IV and V shall, in relation to any such 


    1[foreign State], 
    apply subject to such modifications, exceptions, conditions and 
    qualifications as it may think fit to specify in the order for the purpose 
    of implementing the arrangement. 
 
 
 

 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Liability of fugitive criminals from 

    1[foreign States] to 
    be apprehended and returned.—Where 
    a fugitive criminal of any 

    2[foreign State] to 
    which this Chapter applies is found in India, he shall be liable to be 
    apprehended and returned in the manner provided by this Chapter to that
    

    2[foreign State]. 
 
 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Endorsed and provisional warrants.—A 
    fugitive criminal may be apprehended in India under an endorsed warrant or a 
    provisional warrant. 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Endorsed warrant for apprehension of fugitive criminal.—Where 
    a warrant for the apprehension of a fugitive criminal has been issued in any
    

    1[foreign State] to 
    which this Chapter applies and such fugitive criminal is, or is suspected to 
    be, in India, the Central Government may, if satisfied that the warrant was 
    issued by a person having lawful authority to issue the same, endorse such 
    warrant in the manner prescribed, and the warrant so endorsed shall be 
    sufficient authority to apprehend the person named in the warrant and to 
    bring him before any magistrate in India.—Where 
    a warrant for the apprehension of a fugitive criminal has been issued in any
    

    2[foreign State] to 
    which this Chapter applies and such fugitive criminal is, or is suspected to 
    be, in India, the Central Government may, if satisfied that the warrant was 
    issued by a person having lawful authority to issue the same, endorse such 
    warrant in the manner prescribed, and the warrant so endorsed shall be 
    sufficient authority to apprehend the person named in the warrant and to 
    bring him before any magistrate in India." 
 
 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Provisional warrant for apprehension of fugitive criminal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any magistrate may issue a provisional warrant for the apprehension of a 
    fugitive criminal from any 

    1[foreign State] to 
    which this Chapter applies who is, or is suspected to be, in or on his way 
    to India, on such information and under such circumstances as would, in his 
    opinion, justify the issue of a warrant, if the offence of which the 
    fugitive criminal is accused or has been convicted had been committed within 
    his jurisdiction and such warrant may be executed accordingly.—(1) 
    Any magistrate may issue a provisional warrant for the apprehension of a 
    fugitive criminal from any 

    2[foreign State] to 
    which this Chapter applies who is, or is suspected to be, in or on his way 
    to India, on such information and under such circumstances as would, in his 
    opinion, justify the issue of a warrant, if the offence of which the 
    fugitive criminal is accused or has been convicted had been committed within 
    his jurisdiction and such warrant may be executed accordingly." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    magistrate issuing a provisional warrant shall forthwith send a report of 
    the issue of the warrant together with the information or a certified copy 
    thereof to the Central Government, and the Central Government may, if it 
    thinks fit, discharge the person apprehended under such warrant. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A fugitive 
    criminal apprehended on a provisional warrant may, from time to time, be 
    remanded for such reasonable time, not exceeding seven days at any one time, 
    as under the circumstances seems requisite for the production of an endorsed 
    warrant. 
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Dealing 
    with fugitive criminal when apprehended.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the magistrate, before whom a person apprehended under this Chapter is 
    brought, is satisfied on inquiry that the endorsed warrant for the 
    apprehension of the fugitive criminal is duly authenticated and that the 
    offence of which the person is accused or has been convicted is an 
    extradition offence, the magistrate shall commit the fugitive criminal to 
    prison to await his return and shall forthwith send to the Central 
    Government a certificate of the committal. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If on such 
    inquiry the Magistrate is of opinion that the endorsed warrant is not duly 
    authenticated or that the offence of which such person is accused or has 
    been convicted is not an extradition offence, the magistrate may, pending 
    the receipt of the orders of the Central Government, detain such person in 
    custody or release him on bail. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Magistrate shall report the result of his inquiry to the Central Government 
    and shall forward together with such report any written statement which the 
    fugitive criminal may desire to submit for the consideration of that 
    Government. 
 

 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Return of fugitive criminal by warrant.—The 
    Central Government may, at any time after a fugitive criminal has been 
    committed to prison under this Chapter, issue a warrant for the custody and 
    removal to the 

    1[foreign State] 
    concerned of the fugitive criminal and for his delivery at a place and to a 
    person to be named in the warrant.
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Mode of requisition or form of warrant for the surrender or return to India 
    of accused or convicted person who is in a foreign State 

    1[***]—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A requisition for the surrender of a person accused or convicted of an 
    extradition offence committed in India and who is or is suspected to be, in 
    any foreign State 

    2[***] to which 
    Chapter III does not apply, may be made by the Central Government— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to a diplomatic representative of that 
    State or country at Delhi; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to the Government of that State or 
    country the diplomatic representative of India in that State or country, 
 
and if neither of these modes is 
    convenient, the requisition shall be made in such other mode as is settled 
    by arrangement made by the Government of India with that State 
3[***].
5[***]." 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    warrant issued by a Magistrate in India for the apprehension of any person 
    who is, or is suspected to be, in any 

    4[foreign State] to 
    which Chapter III applies shall be in such form as may be prescribed. 
 
 
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Conveyance of accused or convicted person surrendered or returned.—Any 
    person accused or convicted of an extradition offence who is surrendered or 
    returned by a foreign State 

    1[***] may, under the 
    warrant of arrest for his surrender or return issued in such State 


    2[***] be brought into 
    India and delivered to the proper authority to be dealt with according to 
    law.
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 1[<number>21</number> 
    Accused or convicted person surrendered or returned by foreign State not to 
    be tried for certain offences.—Whenever 
    any person accused or convicted of an offence, which, if committed in India 
    would be an extradition offence, is surrendered or returned by a foreign 
    State, such person shall not, until he has been restored or has had an 
    opportunity of returning to that State, be tried in India for an offence 
    other than—


    3[21. Accused or 
    convicted person surrendered or returned by foreign State not to be tried 
    for certain offences.—Whenever 
    any person accused or convicted of an offence, which, if committed in India 
    would be an extradition offence, is surrendered or returned by a foreign 
    State, such person shall not, until he has been restored or has had an 
    opportunity of returning to that State, be tried in India for an offence 
    other than—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the extradition offence in relation to 
    which he has surrendered or returned; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any lesser offence disclosed by the 
    facts proved for the purposes of securing his surrender or return other than 
    an offence in relation to which an order for his surrender or return could 
    not be lawfully made; or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    the offence in respect of which the 
    foreign State has given its consent.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Liability of fugitive criminals to be arrested and surrendered or returned.—Every 
    fugitive criminal of a foreign State 

    1[***] shall, subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, be liable be arrested and surrendered or 
    returned, whether the offence in respect of which the surrender or return is 
    sought was committed before or after the commencement of this Act, and 
    whether or not a court in India has jurisdiction to try that offence.—Every 
    fugitive criminal of a foreign State 

    1[***] shall, subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, be liable be arrested and surrendered or 
    returned, whether the offence in respect of which the surrender or return is 
    sought was committed before or after the commencement of this Act, and 
    whether or not a court in India has jurisdiction to try that offence." 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Jurisdiction as to offences committed at sea or in air.—Where 
    the offence in respect of which the surrender or return of a fugitive 
    criminal is sought was committed on board any vessel on the high seas or any 
    aircraft while in the air outside India or the Indian territorial waters 
    which comes into any port or aerodrome of India, the Central Government and 
    any Magistrate having jurisdiction in such port or aerodrome may exercise 
    the powers conferred by this Act. 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Discharge of person apprehended if not surrendered or returned within two 
    months.—If 
    a fugitive criminal who, in pursuance of this Act, has been committed to 
    prison to await his surrender or return to any foreign State 

    1[***] is not conveyed 
    out of India within two months after such committal, the High Court, upon 
    application made to it by or on behalf of the fugitive criminal and upon 
    proof that reasonable notice of the intention to make such application has 
    been given to the Central Government, may order such prisoner to be 
    discharged unless sufficient cause is shown to the contrary.—If 
    a fugitive criminal who, in pursuance of this Act, has been committed to 
    prison to await his surrender or return to any foreign State 

    1[***] is not conveyed 
    out of India within two months after such committal, the High Court, upon 
    application made to it by or on behalf of the fugitive criminal and upon 
    proof that reasonable notice of the intention to make such application has 
    been given to the Central Government, may order such prisoner to be 
    discharged unless sufficient cause is shown to the contrary." 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Release of persons arrested on bail.—In 
    the case of a person who is a fugitive criminal arrested or detained under 
    this Act, the provisions of 

    1[the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], relating to bail shall apply in the same 
    manner as they would apply if such person were accused of committing in 
    India the offence of which he is accused or has been convicted, and in 
    relation to such bail, the magistrate before whom the fugitive criminal is 
    brought shall have, as far as may be, the same powers and jurisdiction as a 
    Court of Session under that Code.—In 
    the case of a person who is a fugitive criminal arrested or detained under 
    this Act, the provisions of 

    4[the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], relating to bail shall apply in the same 
    manner as they would apply if such person were accused of committing in 
    India the offence of which he is accused or has been convicted, and in 
    relation to such bail, the magistrate before whom the fugitive criminal is 
    brought shall have, as far as may be, the same powers and jurisdiction as a 
    Court of Session under that Code." 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Abetment of extradition offences.—A 
    fugitive criminal who is accused or convicted of abetting 

    1[, conspiring, 
    attempting to commit, inciting or participating as an accomplice in the 
    commission of] any extradition offence shall be deemed for the purposes of 
    this Act to be accused or convicted of having committed such offence and 
    shall be liable to be arrested and surrendered accordingly.—A 
    fugitive criminal who is accused or convicted of abetting 

    1[, conspiring, 
    attempting to commit, inciting or participating as an accomplice in the 
    commission of] any extradition offence shall be deemed for the purposes of 
    this Act to be accused or convicted of having committed such offence and 
    shall be liable to be arrested and surrendered accordingly." 
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Lawfulness of, and re-taking on escape from, custody under warrants.—It 
    shall be lawful for any person to whom a warrant is directed for the 
    apprehension of a fugitive criminal to hold in custody and convey the person 
    mentioned in the warrant to the place named in the warrant, and if such 
    person escapes out of any custody to which he may be delivered in pursuance 
    of such warrant, he may be re-taken as a person accused of an offence 
    against the law of India may be re-taken upon an escape. 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Property found on fugitive criminal.—Everything 
    found in the possession of a fugitive criminal at the time of his arrest 
    which may be material as evidence in proving the extradition offence may be 
    delivered up with the fugitive criminal on his surrender or return, subject 
    to the rights, if any, of third parties with respect thereto. 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Power 
    of Central Government to discharge any fugitive criminal.— 
    If it appears to the Central Government that by reason of the trivial nature 
    of the case or by reason of the application for the surrender or return of a 
    fugitive criminal not being made in good faith or in the interests of 
    justice or for political reasons or otherwise, it is unjust or inexpedient 
    to surrender or return the fugitive criminal, it may, by order, at any time, 
    stay any proceedings under this Act and direct any warrant issued or 
    endorsed under this Act to be cancelled and the person for whose arrest the 
    warrant has been issued or endorsed to be discharged. 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Simultaneous requisitions.—If 
    requisitions for the surrender of a fugitive criminal are received from more 
    than one foreign State 

    1[***] the Central 
    Government may, having regard to the circumstances of the case, surrender 
    the fugitive criminal to such State 

    2[***] as that 
    Government thinks fit. —If 
    requisitions for the surrender of a fugitive criminal are received from more 
    than one foreign State 

    2[***] the Central 
    Government may, having regard to the circumstances of the case, surrender 
    the fugitive criminal to such State 

    3[***] as that 
    Government thinks fit. " 
 
 
 

 










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Restrictions on surrender.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    A fugitive criminal shall not be surrendered or returned to a foreign State
    

    2[***]——4[(1)] 
    A fugitive criminal shall not be surrendered or returned to a foreign State
    

    5[***]—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if the offence in respect of which his 
    surrender is sought is of a political character or if he proves to the 
    satisfaction of the Magistrate or court before whom he may be produced or of 
    the Central Government that the requisition or warrant for his surrender 
    has, in fact, been made with a view to try or punish him for an offence of a 
    political character; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if prosecution for the offence in 
    respect of which his surrender is sought is according to the law of that 
    State 
    3[***] barred by time;
1[***] 
    barred by time;" 
 

4[(c) 
       unless provision is made by that law of the foreign State or in the 
    extradition treaty with the foreign State that the fugitive criminal shall 
    not be detained or tried in that State for an offence other than—2[(c) 
    unless provision is made by that law of the foreign State or in the 
    extradition treaty with the foreign State that the fugitive criminal shall 
    not be detained or tried in that State for an offence other than—" 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    the extradition offence in relation to 
    which he has surrendered or returned; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    any lesser offence disclosed by the 
    facts proved for the purpose of securing his surrender or return other than 
    an offence in relation to which an order for his surrender or return could 
    not be lawfully made; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    the offence in respect of which the 
    Central Government has given his consent.] 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    if he has been accused of some offence 
    in India, not being the offence for which his surrender or return is sought, 
    or is undergoing sentence under any conviction in India until after he has 
    been discharged, whether by acquittal or on expiration of his sentence or 
    otherwise; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    until after the expiration of fifteen 
    days from the date of his being committed to prison by the Magistrate. 
 


    5[(2) For the purpose 
    of sub-section (1), the offences specified in the Schedule shall not be 
    regarded as offences of a political character. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government having regard to the extradition treaty made by India 
    with any foreign State may, by notified order, add or omit any offence from 
    the list given in the Schedule.]  
 
 












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Sections 29 and 31 to apply without any modification thereof.—Notwithstanding 
    anything to the contrary contained in section 3 or section 12, the 
    provisions of sections 29 and 31 shall apply without any modifications to 
    every foreign State 

    1[***]—Notwithstanding 
    anything to the contrary contained in section 3 or section 12, the 
    provisions of sections 29 and 31 shall apply without any modifications to 
    every foreign State 

    4[***]" 
 
 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>33</number> Act not to affect the Foreigners Act, 
      1946.—Nothing in this Act shall 
      affect the provisions of the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946) or any 
      order made thereunder. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>34</number> 
    Extra-territorial jurisdiction.—An 
    extradition offence committed by any person in a foreign State shall be 
    deemed to have been committed in India and such person shall be liable to be 
    prosecuted in India for such offence.]5[34. 
    Extra-territorial jurisdiction.—An 
    extradition offence committed by any person in a foreign State shall be 
    deemed to have been committed in India and such person shall be liable to be 
    prosecuted in India for such offence.]" 
 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>34A</number> Prosecution on 
    refusal to extradition.—Where 
    the Central Government is of the opinion that a fugitive criminal cannot be 
    surrendered or returned pursuant to a request for extradition from a foreign 
    State, it may, as it thinks fit, take steps to prosecute such fugitive 
    criminal in India. ]
 

 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>34B</number> Provisional 
    arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of an urgent request from a foreign State for the immediate 
    arrest of a fugitive criminal, the Central Government may request the 
    Magistrate having competent jurisdiction to issue a provisional warrant for 
    the arrest of such fugitive criminal.1[34B. 
    Provisional arrest.—(1) 
    On receipt of an urgent request from a foreign State for the immediate 
    arrest of a fugitive criminal, the Central Government may request the 
    Magistrate having competent jurisdiction to issue a provisional warrant for 
    the arrest of such fugitive criminal." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A fugitive 
    criminal arrested under sub-section (1) shall be discharged upon the 
    expiration of sixty days from the date of his arrest if no request for his 
    surrender or return is received within the said period.]  
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>34C</number> Provision of 
    life imprisonment for death penalty.—Notwithstanding 
    contained in any other law for the time being in force, where a fugitive 
    criminal, who has committed an extradition offence punishable with death in 
    India is surrendered or returned by a foreign State on the request of the 
    Central Government and the laws of that foreign State do not provide for a 
    death penalty for such an offence, such fugitive criminal shall be liable 
    for punishment of imprisonment of life only for that offence.]1[34C. 
    Provision of life imprisonment for death penalty.—Notwithstanding 
    contained in any other law for the time being in force, where a fugitive 
    criminal, who has committed an extradition offence punishable with death in 
    India is surrendered or returned by a foreign State on the request of the 
    Central Government and the laws of that foreign State do not provide for a 
    death penalty for such an offence, such fugitive criminal shall be liable 
    for punishment of imprisonment of life only for that offence.]" 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Notified Orders and Notifications to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    notified order made or notification issued under this Act shall, as soon as 
    may be, after it is made or issued, be laid before each House of Parliament. 
 

 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry 
    out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the form in which a requisition for the 
    surrender of a fugitive criminal may be made; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the form in which a warrant for 
    the apprehension of any person in a 
1[foreign 
    State] to which Chapter III applies may be made;2[foreign 
    State] to which Chapter III applies may be made;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the manner in which any warrant may be 
    endorsed or authenticated under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the removal of fugitive criminals 
    accused or in custody under this Act and their control and maintenance until 
    such time as they are handed over to the persons named in the warrant as 
    entitled to receive them; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the seizure and disposition of any 
    property which is the subject of, or required for proof of, any alleged 
    offence to which this Act, applies; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the form and manner in which or the 
    channel through which a Magistrate may be required to make his report to the 
    Central Government under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    any other matter which has to be, or 
    may be, prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it 
    is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 


    2[in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule. 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Repeals 
    and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> The Indian 
    Extradition Act, 1903 (15 of 1903), and any law corresponding thereto in 
    force at the commencement of this Act in the territories which, immediately 
    before the 1st day of November, 1956, were comprised in Part B States and 
    the North East Frontier Agency and Tuensang District (Extradition) 
    Regulation, 1961 (3 of 1961), are hereby repealed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Extradition Acts, 1870 to 1932 and the Fugitive Offenders Act, 1881, 
    in-so-far as they apply to and operate as part of the law of India, are 
    hereby repealed. 
 

 
 

 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

1[THE 
    SCHEDULE
 
[See section 31(2)]
 

    Offences which are not to be regarded as offences of  
    a political character
  
 
The following list of offences is to be 
    construed according to the law in force in India on the date of the alleged 
    offence. Wherever the names of the relevant Acts are not given, the sections 
    referred to are the sections of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860):— 
 
 
 
Offences under the Anti-Hijacking Act, 1982 
      (65 of 1982). 
 
 
Offences under the Suppression of Unlawful 
      Acts against Safety of Civil Aviation Act, 1982 (66 of 1982). 
 
 
An offence within the scope of the 
      Convention on the punishment of crimes against Internationally protected 
      persons including diplomatic agents, opened for signature at New York on 
      14th December, 1973. 
 
 
An offence within the scope of the 
      International Convention against the taking of hostages opened for 
      signature at New York on 18th December, 1979. 
 
 
Culpable homicide, murder (Sections 299 to 
      304). 
 
 
Voluntarily causing hurt or grievous hurt by 
      a dangerous weapon or means (Sections 321 to 333). 
 
 
Offences under the Explosive Substances Act, 
      1908 (6 of 1908). 
 
 
Possession of a firearm or ammunition with 
      intention to endanger life [Section 27 of the Arms Act, 1959 (54 of 
      1959)]. 
 
 
The use of a firearm with intention to 
      resist or prevent the arrest or detention [Section 28 of the Arms Act, 
      1959 (54 of 1959)]. 
 
 
Causing of loss or damage to property used 
      for public utilities or otherwise with intention to endanger life (Section 
      425 read with Section 440). 
 
 
Wrongful restraint and wrongful confinement 
      (Sections 339 to 348). 
 
 
Kidnaping and abduction including taking of 
      hostages (Sections 359 to 369). 
 
 
Offences related to terrorism and terrorist 
      acts [Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act, 1987 (28 of 
      1987)]. 
 
 
Abetting, conspiring or attempting to 
      commit, inciting, participating as an accomplice in the commission of any 
      of the offences listed above.] 

 
 





 




<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>