<act><tid>1504607</tid>
<title>THE LIVE- STOCK IMPORTATION (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 28 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 29th August, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Live- stock Importation Act, <year>1898</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>166542</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1703421</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Live- stock Importation (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>915943</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 5th day of July, 
<year>2001</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>168224</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of preamble.- In the preamble of the Live- stock 
Importation Act, <year>1898</year> (9 of <year>1898</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act), after the word" live- stock", the words" and live- stock 
products" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>664869</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act, after 
clause (c), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (d)" live- stock products" include meat and meat products of all kinds 
including fresh, chilled and frozen meat, tissue, organs of poultry, 
pig, sheep, goat; egg and egg powder, milk and milk products; 
bovine, ovine and caprine, embryos, ova, semen; pet ood products of 
animal origin and any other animal product which may be specified by 
the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette.'.



</article>



<article><tid>442939</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (2) A notification issued under sub- section (1) or under section 3A 
shall operate as if it has been issued under section 11 of the Customs 
Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>) and the officers of the customs at every port, 
airport, Inland Container Depot and Land Cu toms Station shall have 
the same powers in respect of any live- stock or live- stock product or 
thing with regard to the importation of which such a notification has 
been issued and the vessel, aircraft, vehicle and other mode of 
conveyance containing the ame, as they have for the time being in 
respect of any article the importation of which is regulated, 
restricted or prohibited by the law relating to customs and the 
vessel, aircraft, vehicle and other mode of conveyance containing the 
same; and the enac ments for the time being in force relating to 
customs or any such article or vessel, aircraft, vehicle and other 
mode of conveyance shall apply accordingly.".



</article>



<article><tid>468925</tid>
<number>5</number>Insertion of new section 3A.- After section 3 of the principal Act, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 3A. Power to regulate Importation of live- stock products.- The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
regulate, restrict or prohibit in such manner and to such extent as it 
may think fit, the import into the territories to which this Act 
extends, of any live- stock product, which may be liable to affect 
human or animal health.".



</article>



<article><tid>950003</tid>
<number> 6</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1410977</tid>
<number>1</number>The Live- stock Importation (Amendment)  
Ordinance, <year>2001</year> (Ord. 5 of <year>2001</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>249084</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the principal Act, as amended by the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the principal Act, as amended 
by this Act.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>