<act><tid>1508480</tid>
<title>THE TAXATION LAWS (CONTINUATION AND VALIDATION OF  
  RECOVERYPROCEEDINGS) ACT, <year>1964</year></title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>1964</year>
[ 12th May, <year>1964</year>.]

An Act to provide for the continuation and Validation of pro- 
ceedings in relation to Government dues and for matters connected 
therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifteenth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1803063</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Taxation Laws 
 (Continuation. and Validation of Recovery Proceedings) Act, 
<year>1964</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1458106</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>728682</tid>
<number>a</number>assessee", in relation to-

<subsection><tid>1432295</tid>
<number>i</number>the Excess Profits Tax Act, <year>1940</year>, (15 of <year>1940</year>). or the 
Business Profits Tax Act, <year>1947</year>, (21 of <year>1947</year>). means a person 
by whom the tax or any other sum is payable under that Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>430389</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Estate Duty Act, <year>1953</year>, (34 of <year>1953</year>). means a person 
accountable or an accountable person as defined in that Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1922154</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other scheduled Act, means an assessee as defined in 
that Act;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1210390</tid>
<number>b</number>" Government dues", in relation to any scheduled Act, 
means any tax, duty, penalty, fine, interest, annuity deposit 
or any other sum payable to the Government by an assessee 
under that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1412218</tid>
<number>c</number>" scheduled, Act" means an Act specified in the 
Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>1113393</tid>
<number>d</number>" Taxing Authority in relation to any scheduled Act, 
means an officer (by whatever name called) empowered to serve 
' upon an assessee a notice of demand in respect of any 
Government dues under that Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1068989</tid>
<number>e</number>" Tax Recovery Officer", in relation to any scheduled 
Act, means a Tax Recovery- Officer as defined in that Act and 
where there is no such definition, means an officer (by  
  whatever name called) to whom a certificate for the recovery 
of arrears of Government dues may be issued under that Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1292</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>927608</tid>
<number> 3</number> Continuation and validation of certain proceedings.
<section><tid>1716991</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
any notice of demand in respect of any Government dues is served upon 
an assessee by a Taxing Authority under any scheduled Act, and any 
appeal or other proceeding is filed or taken in respect of such 
Government dues, then.-

<subsection><tid>12240</tid>
<number>a</number>where such Government dues are enhanced in such appeal 
or proceeding, the Taxing Authority shall serve upon the 
assessee another notice of demand only in respect of the 
amount by which such Government dues are enhanced and any 
proceedings in relation to such Government dues as are 
covered by the notice or notices of demand served upon him 
before the disposal of such appeal or proceeding may, without 
the service of any fresh notice of demand, be continued from 
the stage at which such proceedings stood immediately before 
such disposal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>544095</tid>
<number>b</number>where such Government dues are reduced in such appeal 
or proceeding,-

<subsubsection><tid>1161083</tid>
<number>i</number>it shall not be necessary for the Taxing Authority to 
serve upon the assessee a fresh notice of demand;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1909813</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Taxing Authority shall give intimation of the fact 
of such reduction to the assessee, and where a certificate 
has been issued to the Tax Recovery Officer for the recovery 
of such amount, also to that officer;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>36070</tid>
<number>iii</number>any proceedings initiated on the basis of the notice Or 
notices of demand served upon the assessee before the 
disposal of such appeal or proceeding may be continued in 
relation to the amount so reduced from the stage at which 
such proceedings stood immediately before such disposal;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1161121</tid>
<number>c</number>no proceedings in relation to such Government dues 
 (including the imposition of penalty or charging of interest) 
shall be invalid by reason only that no fresh notice of 
demand was served upon the assessee after the disposal of 
such appeal or proceeding or that such Government dues have 
been enhanced or reduced in such appeal or proceeding:
Provided that if as a result of any final order such 
Government dues (other than annuity deposit) have been 
reduced and the penalty imposed on the assessee for default 
in payment thereof exceeds the amount so reduced, the excess 
shall not be recovered and if it has already been recovered, 
it shall be refunded to the assessee on an application made 
by him to the Taxing Authority Within such time and in such 
manner as may be prescribed by rules made under this Act:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1293</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided further that if the amount of penalty imposed on 
the assessee for failure to make any annuity deposit exceeds 
one- half of the amount of the annuity deposit required to be 
made as a result of such order, the excess shall not be 
recovered, and if it has already been recovered, shall be 
refunded to the assessee on an application made by him to the 
Taxing Authority within such time and in such manner as may 
be prescribed by rules made under this Act;

Provided further that where any Government dues are reduced 
in such appeal or proceeding and the assessee is entitled to 
any refund thereof, such refund shall be made in accordance 
with the provisions of that Act,


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1615520</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that no 
fresh notice of demand shall be necessary in any case where the amount 
of Government dues is not varied as a result of any order passed in 
any appeal or other proceeding under any scheduled Act.

</section>

<section><tid>304474</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of this section shall have effect 
notwithstandIng any judgment, decree or order of any court, tribunal 
or other authority,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1846542</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to amend the Schedule. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, add the name of any Central Act 
providing for the imposition or levy of an tax or duty in the Schedule 
and on the issue of any such notification, the Act so added shall be 
deemed to be an Act specified in the Schedule within the meaning of 
clause (c) of section 2.


</article>



<article><tid>646721</tid>
<number>5</number>Act to have retrospective effect. The provisions of this 
Act shall apply and shall be deemed always to have applied, in 
relation. to every notice of demand served upon an assessee by any 
Taxing Authority under any scheduled Act whether such notice was or is 
served before or after the commencement of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>959701</tid>
<number>6</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions 
not inconsistent with the purposes of this Act, as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>1129977</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>243356</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by  
notification in the official Gazetted] make rules for carrying out 
the purposes of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1294</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>746178</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, that rule shall thereafter have effect, only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case. may be, so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>