<act><tid>1508011</tid>
<title>THE CASTE DISABILITIES REMOVAL ACT, <year>1850</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 21 OF <year>1850</year> 
[ 11th April, <year>1850</year>.]
An Act for extending the principle of section 9, Regulation VII, <year>1832</year>, 
of the Bengal Code throughout <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India].

Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is enacted by section 9, Regulation VII, 
 <year>1832</year> (Ben. Reg. VII of <year>1832</year>), of the Bengal Code, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> that" whenever 
in any civil suit the parties to such suit may be of different 
persuasions, when one party shall be of the Hindu and the other of the 
Muhammadan persuasion, or where one or more of the parties to the suit 
shall not be either of the Muhammadan or Hindu persuasions the laws of 
those religions shall not be permitted to operate to deprive such 
party or parties of any property to which,


<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>).

This Act has been extend to Berar by the Berar Laws Act, 
<year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>) and has been declared to be in force in all the 
Provinces of India, except the Scheduled Districts, by the Laws 
Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (5 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3.

It has been declared to be in force in the Sonthal Parganas 
by the Sonathal Pargnas Settlement Regulation, <year>1872</year> (3 of <year>1872</year>), 
s. 3.

The Act has been extended to and brought into force in Dadra 
and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 7-  
  <year>1965</year>) and to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of 
<year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14of 1874), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

West Jalpaiguri... See Gazette of India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 74.

The Districts of Hazaribagh, 
Lohardaga (now the Ranchi  
District, see Calcutta Gazette, 
  <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 44), and Man- 
bhum, and Pargana Dhalbhum 
and the Kolhan in the District 
of Singhbhum.... Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

The Scheduled portion of the 
Mirzapur District.... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 383.

Jaunsar Bawar.... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 382.

The District of Lahaul. Ditto <year>1886</year>, Pt. I, p. 301.

The Scheduled Districts 
the C. P..... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 771.

The Scheduled Districts in 
Ganjam and Vizagapatam... Ditto <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 870.

Coorg... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 747.

Assam (except the North  
  Lushai Hills)... Ditto <year>1897</year>, Pt. I, p. 299.

The Porahat Estate in the 
Singhbhum District... Ditto <year>1897</year>, Pt. I, p. 1059.

It has been extended by notification by s. 5 of the last- 
mentioned Act, to the following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

Kumaon and Garhwal. See Gazette of India, <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 606.

The Tarai of the Province of Agra Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 505.

It has also been extended to the New Provinces and Merged States, 
see Act 59 of <year>1949</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the territories 
subject to the Government of the East India Company".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Rep. by the Bengal Civil Courts Act, <year>1871</year> (6 of <year>1871</year>), which was 
rep. by the Bengal, North- Western Provinces and Assam Civil 
Courts Act, <year>1887</year> (12 of <year>1887</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

but for the operation of such laws, they would have been entitled"; 
and whereas it will be beneficial to extend the principle of that 
enactment throughout <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India]; It is enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>466892</tid>
<number>1</number>Law or usage which inflicts forfeiture of, or affects, rights 
on change of religion or loss of caste to cease to be enforced.-- So 
much of any law or usage now in force within <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] as inflicts 
on any person forfeiture of rights or property, or may be held in any 
way to impair or affect any right of inheritance, by reason of his or 
her renouncing, or having been excluded from the communion of, any 
religion, or being deprived of caste, shall cease to be enforced as 
law <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in any Court].


</article>



<article><tid>1510198</tid>
<number> 2</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Short title and extent.--
<section><tid>1639803</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act] may be called the  
Caste Disabilities Removal Act, <year>1850</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>240759</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the territories 
subject to the Government of the East India Company". 
2. Subs. by s. 3 and Sch., ibid., for" in the Courts of the East 
India Company, and in the Courts established by Royal Charter 
within the said territories". 
3. Added by s. 3 and Sch., ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>