<act><tid>1515277</tid>
<title>THE TECHNOLOGY DEVELOPMENT BOARD ACT, <year>1995</year></title>

ACT NO. 44 OF <year>1995</year>
[ 16th December, <year>1995</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of a Board for payment of 
equity capital or any other financial assistance to industrial 
concerns and other agencies attempting development and commercial 
application of indigenous technology or adapting imported technology 
to wider domestic applications and for matters connected therewith or 
incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>631992</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1512915</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Technology Development Board Act, <year>1955</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1033502</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1647575</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires-
<section><tid>179665</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Technology Development Board consti- 
tuted under subsection (1) of section 3;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>580730</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1675787</tid>
<number>c</number>" Fund" means the Fund for Technology Development and 
Application constituted under sub- section (1) of section 9;

</section>

<section><tid>439765</tid>
<number>d</number>" member" means a member of the Board and' includes the 
Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>824781</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1518292</tid>
<number>f</number>" Secretary" means the Secretary of the Board appointed 
under sub- section (1) of section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1949586</tid>
<number>g</number>words and expressions used herein and not defined but 
defined in the Research and Development Cess Art, <year>1986</year>, (32  
  of <year>1986</year>.) shall, have the meanings respectively assigned to 
them in that Act.
CHAP

TECHNOLOGY DEVELOPMENT BOARD

CHAPTER II

TECHNOLOGY DEVELOPMENT BOARD




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1225228</tid>
<number> 3</number> Constitution and incorporation of the Board.
<section><tid>1274391</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute, 
for the purposes of this Act, a Board to be called the Technology 
Development Board.

</section>

<section><tid>87324</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid 
having perpetual succession and a common seal with power. subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to contract and shall, by the said name, 
sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>780734</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>161235</tid>
<number>a</number>the Secretary to the Government of India incharge of, 
the Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
with Science and Technology
ex officio 
Chairperson;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>350932</tid>
<number>b</number>the Secretary to the Government of India incharge of 
the Ministry or Department the Central Government dealing 
with Scientific and Industrial Research
ex officio;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>699630</tid>
<number>c</number>the Secretary to the Government of India incharge of the 
Ministry or Department of the of the Central Government 
dealing with Finance (Expenditure)
ex- officio;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>944257</tid>
<number>d</number>the Secretary to the Government of India incharge of the 
Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing 
with Defence Research and Development.
ex- officio;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>464282</tid>
<number>e</number>the Secretary to the Government of India incharge of the 
Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing with 
industrial Development 
ex- officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>173694</tid>
<number>f</number>the Secretary to the Government of India incharge of the 
Ministry or Department of the Central Government dealing with 
Rural Development 
ex officio;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1106362</tid>
<number>g</number>such number of persons, not exceeding four as may be 
prescribed, to be appointed by the Central Government from 
amongst persons having experience in technology development 
and application, banking and finance, industry, agriculture 
and rural development; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1957570</tid>
<number>h</number>Secretary of the Board
ex offcio;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1413157</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office and other conditions of service of 
members specified in clause (g) of sub- section (3) shad be such as may 
be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1559803</tid>
<number>5</number>The Chairperson shall, in addition to pressing over, the 
meetings of the Board, exercise and discharge such powers and duties 
of the Board as may be delegated to him by the Board and such other 
powers and duties as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>84308</tid>
<number>6</number>No act or proceeding of the Board shall be invalidated 
merely by reason of-

<subsection><tid>1513327</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, 
the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>774637</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a 
member of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1104785</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Board not 
affecting the merits of the case.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>271495</tid>
<number> 4</number> Secretary and other officers and employees of the Board.

<section><tid>1572428</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may appoint the Secretary and such other officers and  
employees as it considers necessary for the efficient discharge of its 
functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1376138</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions of service of the Secretary and 
other officers and employees of the Board shall be such as may be 
determined by regulations.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1877623</tid>
<number> 5</number> Committees of the Board.
<section><tid>721113</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the rules made in  
this behalf, the Board may appoint, such committees as may be 
necessary for the efficient discharge of its duties and performance of 
its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>954173</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall have the power to co- opt as members of any 
committee appointed under sub- section (1), such number of persons who 
are hot members of the Board as it may think fit, and the person so 
co- opted shall have the right to attend the meetings of the committee, 
and take part in the proceedings of the committee, but shall not have 
the right to vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1062891</tid>
<number> 6</number> Functions of the Board. The Board may-
<section><tid>1165898</tid>
<number>a</number>provide equity capital, subject to such conditions as 
may be determind by regulations, or any other financial 
assistance to industrial concerns and other agencies 
attempting commercial application of indigenous technology 
or, adapting imported technology of wider domestic ap- 
plications;

</section>

<section><tid>958129</tid>
<number>b</number>provide financial assistance to such research and 
development institutions engaged in developing indigenous 
technology or adaptation of imported technology for 
commercial application, as may be recognised by the Central 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>162666</tid>
<number>c</number>perform such other functions as may be entrusted to it 
by the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

APPLICATION FOR GRANT OF FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE

CHAPTER III

APPLICATION FOR GRANT OF FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1512350</tid>
<number> 7</number> Application for grant of financial assistance etc.
<section><tid>69663</tid>
<number>1</number>An  
application for grant of financial assistance for the purposes men- 
tioned under section 6 shall be made to the Board in such form as may 
be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>134164</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may, after examining the application and after 
making such enquiries as it deems necessary by order, in writing, 
either grant the financial assistance or refuse to grant the same:
Provided that no refusal of grant shall be made unless an 
opportunity is given to the applicant of being heard.

CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1771133</tid>
<number>8</number>Grants and loans by the Central Government. The Central 
Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law, in 
this behalf, make to the Board grants and loans of such sums of money 
as that Government may consider necessary.


</article>



<article><tid>1302057</tid>
<number> 9</number> Fund for Technology Development and Application.
<section><tid>263160</tid>
<number>1</number>There  
shall be constituted a Fund to be called the Fund for Technology 
Development and Application and there shall be credited to the Fund-

<subsection><tid>1438887</tid>
<number>a</number>any grants and loans made to the Board by the Central 
Government under section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>641939</tid>
<number>b</number>all sums received by the Board from any other source;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>127766</tid>
<number>c</number>recoveries made of the amounts granted from the Fund; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1768937</tid>
<number>d</number>any income from investment of the amount of the Fund.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>470239</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall be applied for meeting-

<subsection><tid>731543</tid>
<number>a</number>expenses on the object and for the purposes authorised 
by this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>338210</tid>
<number>b</number>salaries, allowances and other expenses of officers and 
other employees of the Board; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>989898</tid>
<number>c</number>expenses of the Board in the discharge of its functions 
under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1509635</tid>
<number> 10</number> Transfer of money receipts and liabilities. On and from the 
commencement of this Act,-
<section><tid>920067</tid>
<number>a</number>the moneys standing at the credit of the Venture 
Capital Fund formed under section 5 of the Research and 
Development Cess Act, <year>1986</year> (32 of <year>1986</year>.) which is part of 
the Development Assistance Fund established by the 
Development Bank under section 14 of the Industrial 
Development Bank of India Act, <year>1964</year> (18 of <year>1964</year>.) shall 
stand transferred to and vest in the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1865954</tid>
<number>b</number>all sums of money due to the Development Bank 
immediately before such commencement shall be deemed to be 
due to the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1941781</tid>
<number>c</number>all debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all 
contracts or agreements entered into and all matters and 
things engaged to be done by, with or for the Development 
Bank immediately before such commencement for or in 
connection with the' purpose of the Venture Capital Fund

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into or 
engaged to be done by, with or for the Board; and


</section>

<section><tid>1164740</tid>
<number>d</number>all suits and other, legal proceedings instituted or 
which could have been instituted by or against the 
Development Bank immediately before such commencement may be 
continued or instituted by or against the Board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>848574</tid>
<number>11</number>Budget. The Board shall prepare, in such form and at such 
time in each financial year, as may be prescribed, its budget for the 
next financial year, showing the estimated. receipts and expenditure 
of We board and forward the same to the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1245728</tid>
<number>12</number>Annual Report. The Board shall prepare, in such form and at 
such time in each financial year, as may be prescribed, its annual 
report, giving a full account of its activities during the previous 
financial year, and submit a copy thereof to the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1773419</tid>
<number> 13</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>1823008</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts in such form as may, be prescribed by the Central Government 
in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1433826</tid>
<number>2</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any, other 
person appointed by him in connection with the auditing of the 
accounts of the Board under this Act shall have the same rights and 
privileges and the authority in connection with such audit as the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India has in connection with the 
auditing of the Government accounts and, in particular, shall have the 
right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers 
and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of 
the Board under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1109</tid>
<number>3</number>The accounts of the Board shall be audited by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India annually and any expenditure 
incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Board 
to the Comptroller and' Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>873675</tid>
<number>4</number>The Board shall furnish to the Central Government before 
such date as may be prescribed its audited copy of accounts together 
with auditor' s report.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>269638</tid>
<number>14</number>Annual report and auditors report to be laid before 
Parliament. The Central Government shall cause the annual report and 
auditor' s report to be laid, as soon as may be after they are 
received, before each House of Parliament.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1136577</tid>
<number> 15</number> Returns to be furnished to the Board.
<section><tid>246943</tid>
<number>1</number>An industrial  
concern or an institution receiving financial assistance from the 
Board shall furnish returns to the Board in such form and at such 
time as may be determined by regulations.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1582401</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may authorize an officer to visit any industrial 
concern or institution referred to in sub- section (1) at any time to 
verify the accuracy of any return made under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1934207</tid>
<number> 16</number> Power of the Central Government to issue direction.
<section><tid>1056082</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Board 
shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under this Act, be 
bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
Government may give in writing to it from time to time:
Provided that the Board shall, as far as practicable, be given an 
opportunity to express its views before any direction is given under 
this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>638729</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is 
one of policy or not shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1201506</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power of Central Government to supersede the Board.
<section><tid>1424366</tid>
<number>1</number>If  
at any time the Central Government is of opinion-

<subsection><tid>1592359</tid>
<number>a</number>that on account of grave emergency, the Board is unable 
to discharge the functions and the duties imposed on it by or 
under the provisions of this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1311570</tid>
<number>b</number>that the Board has persistently made default in 
complying with any direction issued by he Central Government 
under this Act or in the discharge of the functions and 
duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act 
and as a result of such default the financial position of the 
Board or the administration of the Board has deteriorated; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>356871</tid>
<number>c</number>that circumstances exist which render it necessary in 
the public interest so to do,
the Central Government may, be notification in the Official Gazette, 
supersede the Board for such period, not exceeding six months, as may 
be specified in the notification.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1898742</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon the publication of a notification under sub- section (1) 
superseding the Board,--

<subsection><tid>1033311</tid>
<number>a</number>all the members shall, as from the date of 
supersession, vacate their offices as such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1180011</tid>
<number>b</number>all the powers, functions and duties which may, by or 
under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or discharged 
by or on behalf of the Board shall, until the Board is 
reconstituted under sub- section (3), be exercised and 
discharged by such person or persons as the Central 
Government may direct; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>951247</tid>
<number>c</number>all property owned or controlled by the Board shall, 
until the Board is reconstituted under sub- section (3), vest 
in the Central Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1175607</tid>
<number>3</number>On the expiration of the period of supersession specified in 
the notification issued under sub- section (1), the Central Government 
may reconstitute the Board by a fresh appointment and in such case any 
person or persons who vacated their offices under clause (a) of sub- 
section (2), shall not be deemed to be disqualified for appointment:
Provided that the Central Government may, at any time, before the 
expiration of the period of supersession, take action under this sub- 
section.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>798161</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall cause a notification issued 
under sub- section (1) and a full report of any action, taken under 
this section and the circumstances leading to such action to be laid 
before each House of Parliament at the earliest.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1851203</tid>
<number>18</number>Delegation. The Board may, by general or special order in 
writing, delegate to the Chairperson or any other member or to any 
officer of the Board. subject to such conditions and limitations, if 
any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and 
functions under this Act (except) the power under section 22 as it 
may deem necessary.


</article>



<article><tid>853602</tid>
<number>19</number>Members, officers and employees of the Board to be public 
servants. All members, off- ices and another employees of the Board 
shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any 
of the provisions of this Act, to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)


</article>



<article><tid>269950</tid>
<number>20</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No prosecution or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government, or the Board 
or any committee appointed by it or any member of the Board or such 
committee, or any officer or employee of the Government or the Board 
or any other person authorised by the Government or the Board, for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act or the rules or regulations made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>169626</tid>
<number> 21</number> Power of Central Government to make Rules.
<section><tid>1474946</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1478899</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the Generality of the forgoing power, 
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>1227711</tid>
<number>a</number>the number of members of the Board under clause (g) of 
sub- section (3) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>189896</tid>
<number>b</number>the term of office and other conditions of service of 
the members of the Board, under sub- section (4) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>696334</tid>
<number>c</number>the powers and duties of the Chairperson under sub- 
section (5) of section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1841573</tid>
<number>d</number>the constitution of committees under sub- section (1) of 
section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>380123</tid>
<number>e</number>the form, of application under sub- section (1) of 
section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1525895</tid>
<number>f</number>the form in which, and the time at which the Board shall 
prepare its budget under section 11 and its annual report 
under section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>368476</tid>
<number>g</number>the form of annual statement of accounts under 
sub- section (1) of section 13 and the date before which 
the audited copy of the, accounts may be furnished to the 
Central Government under sub- section (4) of that section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>758542</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed 
or in respect of which provision is to be, or may be, made by 
rules.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>402284</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power of Board to make regulations.
<section><tid>774903</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, with  
the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with this Act and 
the rules generally to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>358314</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of 
the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>145879</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service of the Secretary 
and other officers and employees of the Board under sub- 
section (2) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1515340</tid>
<number>b</number>the conditions subject to which equity capital may be 
provided: by the Board under clause (a) of section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1171456</tid>
<number>c</number>the from, in which and the time at which the returns 
may be furnished to the Board under sub- section (1) of 
section 15.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>598</tid>
<number>23</number>Rules and regutions to be laid before Parliament. Every rule 
and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.
K. L. MOHANPURIA,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.

CORRIGENDA

In the Industrial Development Bank of India (Amendment) Ordinance, 
 <year>1995</year> (Ord. 2 of <year>1995</year>) as published in the Gazette of India, 
Extraordinary, Part II, Section 1, dated the 13th January, <year>1995</year> (Issue  
  No. 5),-

</article>



<article><tid>631992</tid>
<number> 1</number> At page 6,-
<section><tid>430966</tid>
<number>i</number>in line 4, after" director", insert" under";

</section>

<section><tid>75154</tid>
<number>ii</number>in line 25, for" cause", read" clause".

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1647575</tid>
<number>2</number>At page 7, in line 18, for" sub- section", read" sub- sections".
</article>



<article><tid>1225228</tid>
<number>3</number>At page 8, in line 42, for" India", read' Indian".

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

</article>



<article><tid>271495</tid>
<number> 4</number> At page 9,-
<section><tid>1551571</tid>
<number>i</number>in line 11, for" may extent", read" way extend";

</section>

<section><tid>891282</tid>
<number>ii</number>in line 18, for," holtdoy'", read" holiday";

</section>

<section><tid>1971129</tid>
<number>iii</number>in line 21, for, so Sunday", read" no Sunday".

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1877623</tid>
<number>5</number>At page 10, in line 15. for" 71" read" 17".
CORRIGENDA

In the Cable Television Networks (Regulation) Ordinance, <year>1995</year> 
 (Ord. 3 of <year>1995</year>) as published in the Gazette of India, Extraordinary, 
Part 11, Section 1, dated the 17th January, <year>1995</year> (Issue No. 6),-

</article>



<article><tid>631992</tid>
<number>1</number>At page 3. in line 39, for" gagets", read" gadgets".
</article>



<article><tid>1647575</tid>
<number>2</number>At page 4, in live 12, for" television", read" television".
CORRIGENDUM

In the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Under-  
  takings) Amendment Ordinance. <year>1995</year> (Ord. 4 of <year>1995</year>) as published in 
the Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Part II Section 1, dated the 21st 
January, <year>1995</year> (Issue No, 7), at page 3. in line 2. for" corespond", 
read" correspond-".

</article>



 </act>