<act><tid>1516931</tid>
<title>THE NATIONAL BANK FOR AGRICULTURE AND RURAL DEVELOPMENT 
 (AMENDMENT) ACT <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 55 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 30t December, <year>2000</year>.]

An Act further to amend the National Bank for Agriculture and Rural 
Development (Amendment) Act, <year>2000</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>962111</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>319394</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
National Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development (Amendment) Act, 
<year>2000</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1619722</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, it shall come into force 
on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1042362</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of long title.- In the National Bank for Agriculture and 
Rural Development Bank Act, <year>1981</year> (61 of <year>1981</year>)  (hereinafter referred to  
  as the principal Act), for the long title, the following shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" An Act to establish a development bank to be known as the National 
Bank for Agriculture and Rural Development for providing and 
regulating credit and other facilities for the promotion and 
development of agriculture, small- scale industries, cottage and 
village industries, handicrafts and other rural crafts and other 
allied economic activities in rural areas with a view to promoting 
integrated rural development and securing prosperity of rural areas 
and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.".



</article>



<article><tid>1633847</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act, in 
clause (e), the words" of the Board" shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1817170</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>756295</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), in the proviso, for the words" five hundred 
crores", the words" five thousand crores" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>372782</tid>
<number>ii</number>for sub- section (2), the following shall be substituted, namely:-
" (2) The capital of the National Bank shall be subscribed to by the 
Central Government and the Reserve Bank to such extent and in such 
proportion as may be notified by the Central Government in 
consultation with the Reserve Bank, from time to time:

Provided that the National Bank may issue capital to such institutions 
and persons in such manner as may be notified by the Central 
Government:

Provided further that the combined shareholding of the Central 
Government and the Reserve Bank shall not at any time be less than 
fifty- one per cent. of the total subscribed capital.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1603463</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 6.- In section 6 of the principal Act, for 
sub- sections
<section><tid>1248491</tid>
<number>1</number>and (2), the following sub- sections shall be  
substituted, namely:-
" (1) The Board of Directors of the National Bank shall consist of the 
following, namely:-


<subsection><tid>743139</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1880883</tid>
<number>b</number>three directors from amongst experts in rural economics, rural 
development, village and cottage industries, small- scale industries or 
persons having experience in the working of co- opeative banks, 
regional rural banks or commercial banks or any other matter the 
special knowledge or professional experience in which is considered by 
the Central Government as useful to the National Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>87058</tid>
<number>c</number>three directors from out of the directors of the Reserve Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1612744</tid>
<number>d</number>three directors from amongst the officials of the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>881003</tid>
<number>e</number>four directors from amongst the officials of the State 
Governments;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>578980</tid>
<number>f</number>such number of directors elected in the prescribed manner, by 
shareholders other than the Reserve Bank, the Central Government and 
other institutions owned or controlled by the Central Government whose 
names are entered on the register of shareholders of the National Bank 
ninety days before the date of the meeting in which such election 
takes place on the following basis, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>72471</tid>
<number>i</number>where the total amount of equity share capital issued to such 
shareholders is ten per cent. or less of the total issued equity 
capital........................ two directors;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>312987</tid>
<number>ii</number>where the total amount of equity share capital issued to such 
shareholders is more than ten per cent. but less than twenty- five per 
cent. of the total issued equity capital...... three directors; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>715784</tid>
<number>iii</number>where the total equity share capital issued to such shareholders 
is twenty- five per cent. or more of the total issued equity 
capital.................. four directors:
Provided that until the assumption of charge by the elected directors 
under this clause, the Central Government may at any time nominate 
such number of directors not exceeding four from amongst persons 
having special knowledge of, and professional experience in, 
agricultural science, technology, economics, banking, co- operatives, 
law, rural finance, investment, accountancy, marketing or any other 
matter, the special knowledge of, and professional experience in, 
which would, in the opinion of the Central Government, be useful to 
the National Bank for carrying out its functions; and


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>728754</tid>
<number>g</number>a Managing Director.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1854217</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman and other directors, excluding the directors referred 
to in clause (f), shall be appointed by the Central Government in 
consultation with the Reserve Bank:
Provided that no such consultation shall be necessary in the case of 
directors appointed under clause (d) of sub- section (1).".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1940239</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 7.- In section 7 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>120721</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (1), the words" and shall be eligible for 
re- appointment" shall be added at the end;

</section>

<section><tid>1454037</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- section (1A), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (1B) In the case of a vacancy in the office of the Chairman, the 
Managing Director shall perform the functions and duties of the 
Chairman during such vacancy.";


</section>

<section><tid>259214</tid>
<number>iii</number>in sub- section (2), the words" and thereafter until his 
successor enters upon his office" shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1110121</tid>
<number>iv</number>for sub- section (4), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (4) The Chairman and any other director, who is not an officer of the 
Central Government or a State Government or an officer of the Reserve 
Bank or any body or corporation established by or under any Central 
Act or any State Act and owned or controlled by such Government, shall 
be paid such fees and allowances as may be prescribed for attending 
the meetings of the Board or of any of its committees and for 
attending to any other work of the National Bank.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>770993</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 8.- In section 8 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, in clause (a), the words" and shall be eligible for 
re- appointment" shall be added at the end.


</article>



<article><tid>1544482</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 12.- In section 12 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), after the words" unable to attend any meeting,", the 
words" the Managing Director and in the absence of both, the Chairman 
and the Managing Director," shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>1169144</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of section 14.- In section 14 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the words" The Board shall", the words" The Board 
may" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>390563</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of section 19.- In section 19 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1083143</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (a), the following clause shall be substituted and 
shall be deemed to have been substituted with effect from the 26th day 
of September, <year>2000</year>, namely:-
" (a) issue and sell bonds, debentures and other financial instruments 
with or without guarantee of the Central Government on such terms and 
conditions as may be approved by the Board;";


</section>

<section><tid>349506</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clauses (b) to (e), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (b) borrow money from the Reserve Bank repayable on demand or 
otherwise on such terms and conditions including the terms relating to 
security and purposes as may be specified by the Reserve Bank;


<subsection><tid>98065</tid>
<number>c</number>borrow money from the Central Government and from any other 
authority or organisation or institution approved by the Board, on 
such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>124921</tid>
<number>d</number>accept from the Central Government, a State Government, a local 
authority, a State land development bank, a State co- operative bank or 
a scheduled bank or any person or body, whether incorporated or not, 
deposits repayable on such terms as the National Bank may, with the 
approval of the Reserve Bank, fix; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>142116</tid>
<number>e</number>receive gifts, grants, donations or benefactions from the Central 
Government or any State Government or any other source.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>731760</tid>
<number>11</number>Substitution of new section for section 20.- For section 20 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 20. Borrowings in foreign currency.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Foreign Exchange Management Act, <year>1999</year> (42 of <year>1999</year>), 
or in any other law for the time being in force, relating to foreign 
exchange, the National Bank may borrow, with the previous approval of 
the Central Government and in consultation with the Reserve Bank, 
foreign currency from any bank or financial institution in India or 
elsewhere, for granting loans and advances or for utilising such 
currency for any other purpose specified under the provisions of this 
Act.".



</article>



<article><tid>43737</tid>
<number>12</number>Amendment of section 25.- In section 25 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, in clause (d), after the words" by way of refinance", 
the words" or otherwise" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>2745</tid>
<number>13</number>Substitution of new section for section 26.- For section 26 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 26. Purchase and sale of shares.- The National Bank may subscribe to, 
or purchase or sell stocks, shares, bonds or debentures of, or invest 
in the securities of, any institution or class of institutions 
concerned with agriculture and rural development which the Board may 
approve subject to such terms and conditions as it may deem fit.".



</article>



<article><tid>625791</tid>
<number>14</number>Insertion of new section 27A.- After section 27 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 27A. Loans to State Government, undertakings, etc.- The National Bank 
may make loans and advances to any State Government or a corporation 
owned or controlled by the State Government or to any other person or 
class of persons, as may be approved by the Board, repayable on the 
expiry of a fixed period not exceeding twenty- five years from the date 
of making of such loans and advances and subject to such terms and 
conditions, as may be approved by the Board, for the purpose of 
development of infrastructure facilities for promotion of agriculture 
and rural development.".



</article>



<article><tid>1290564</tid>
<number>15</number>Amendment of section 28.- In section 28 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (3) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2), no guarantee or security referred to therein shall be 
required in cases in which the Board, for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, decides that no such security or guarantee is necessary in 
respect of a scheduled bank, a State co- operative bank or any person 
or class of persons, specifically approved by the Board or in respect 
of any scheme or class of schemes, having regard to the nature and 
scope of the scheme or schemes for which accommodation is proposed to 
be granted by the National Bank.".



</article>



<article><tid>1696557</tid>
<number>16</number>Amendment of section 29.- In section 29 of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (2), the following shall be inserted, namely:-
' (3) Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any law for 
the time being in force, where a liquidator is appointed for winding 
up a borrowing institution, it shall be the duty of the liquidator to 
forthwith pass on to the National Bank the sums recovered by the 
borrowing institution or the liquidator, as the case may be, in 
repayment or realisation of the loans and advances refinanced either 
wholly or partly by the National Bank to the extent the refinance is 
outstanding and the National Bank shall be entitled to enforce the 
securities held by the borrowing institution in trust for the National 
Bank as if every reference to the borrowing institution in any 
contract, security or other document obtained by borrowing institution 
is a reference to the National Bank and accordingly, the National Bank 
shall be entitled to recover the balance sums due under such loans and 
advances from the constituents of borrowing institution and any 
discharge given by the National Bank to such constituent shall be a 
valid discharge and the liquidator shall, on demand made by the 
National Bank, deliver to it all such contracts, securities and other 
documents, for due enforcement thereof by the National Bank.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, the word 
" liquidator" shall include liquidator or a provisional liquidator or 
any person or authority entrusted with the duty of liquidating the 
borrowing institution.'.



</article>



<article><tid>142952</tid>
<number>17</number>Substitution of new sections for section 30.- For section 30 of 
the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" 30. Direct loans.- The National Bank may, in exceptional 
circumstances to be recorded in writing by the Board, by itself or in 
association with other financial institutions or scheduled banks, make 
loans and advances, otherwise than by way of refinance to any person 
or class of persons or body corporate, on such terms and conditions, 
including security and repayable within such period not exceeding 
twenty- five years, as the National Bank may deem fit.

</article>



<article><tid>344614</tid>
<number>30A</number>The National Bank may rediscount bills of exchange and 
promissory notes made, drawn, accepted or endorsed by any company or 
body corporate concerned with agriculture and rural development 
presented by a scheduled bank, a State co- operative bank, State land 
development bank, regional rural bank or any other institution or 
class of institutions approved by the Board.".


</article>



<article><tid>1270913</tid>
<number>18</number>Substitution of new section for section 32.- For section 32 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 32. Issue of guarantees.- The National Bank may guarantee, subject to 
such directions as may be issued by the Board, from time to time, 
deferred payments in connection with the purchase of capital goods or 
for any other purpose for giving effect to the provisions of this Act, 
due from any person or class of persons, whether incorporated or 
not.".



</article>



<article><tid>597001</tid>
<number>19</number>Amendment of section 33.- In section 33 of the principal Act, for 
the words" under this Chapter with a borrowing institution", the words 
" under this Act with a borrower" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>731594</tid>
<number> 20</number> Substitution of new section for section 34.- For section 34 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 34. Power to call for repayment before agreed period.- 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any agreement or arrangement, 
the National Bank may, by notice in writing, require any borrower or 
assisted person to whom it has granted any loan or other financial 
assistance including grants, to discharge in full, the loan or other 
financial assistance, including grants, as the case may be,-

<section><tid>454704</tid>
<number>a</number>if it appears to the National Bank that false or misleading 
information in any material particulars was given in the application 
for the loan or other financial assistance; or

</section>

<section><tid>1973415</tid>
<number>b</number>if the borrower or the person has failed to comply with any of the 
terms of the contract or arrangement with the National Bank in the 
matter of loan or other financial assistance, including grants; or

</section>

<section><tid>327047</tid>
<number>c</number>if there is a reasonable apprehension that the borrower is unable 
to pay its debts or that proceedings for liquidation may be commenced 
in respect thereof; or

</section>

<section><tid>29808</tid>
<number>d</number>if for any reason it is necessary so to do, to protect the 
interests of the National Bank.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>812358</tid>
<number>21</number>Amendment of section 35.- In section 35 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) The National Bank shall have free access to all such records of a 
borrower seeking to avail of any credit or other facilities from the 
National Bank under this Act and also to all such records of any 
person seeking to avail of any credit or othher facilities from such 
borrower, perusal whereof may appear to the National Bank to be 
necessary in connection with the providing of finance or other 
assistance to such borrower or the refinancing of any loan or advance 
made to such person by the borrower.".



</article>



<article><tid>150909</tid>
<number> 22</number> Insertion of new section 37A.- After section 37 of the principal 
Act, the followin section shall be inserted, namely:-
' 37A. Prohibited business.- (1) The National Bank shall not make any 
loans or advances under section 30 or make any grants under this Act 
to any person or body of persons of which any of the directors of the 
National Bank is a proprietor, partner, director, manager, agent, 
employee or guarantor or in which one or more directors of the 
National Bank together hold substantial interest:

Provided that this sub- section shall not apply to any borrower if any 
director of the National Bank-

<section><tid>1182543</tid>
<number>a</number>is nominated as director of the Board of such borrower by the 
Government or a Government company as defined in section 617 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or by a corporation established by any 
other law;

</section>

<section><tid>1514717</tid>
<number>b</number>is elected on the Board of such borrower by virtue of shares held 
in the borrower organisation by the Government, or a Government 
company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>) or by a corporation establised by any other law,
by reason only of such nomination or election, as the case may be.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," substantial 
interest", in relation to a borrower, means the beneficial interest 
held by one or more of the directors of the National Bank or by any 
relative of such director as defined in clause (41) of section 2 of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), whether sinly or taken together, 
in the shares of the borrower, the aggregate amount paid- up on whichh 
either exceeds five lakhs of rupees or five per cent. of the paid- up 
share capital of the borrower, whichever is lesser.


<subsection><tid>921527</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sub- section (1)-

<subsubsection><tid>1502040</tid>
<number>a</number>shall not apply to any borrower, if the National Bank is satisfied 
that it is necessary in the public interest to enter into business 
with that borrower and entering into any kind of business with such 
borrower shall be in accordance with and subject to such conditions 
and limitations, as may be approved by the Board;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1452603</tid>
<number>b</number>shall not apply to any transaction relating to the business 
entered into prior to the commencement of the National Bank for 
Agriculture and Rural Development (Amendment) Act, <year>2000</year>, and all such 
business and any transaction in relation thereto may be implemented or 
continued as if that Act had not come into force;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>75051</tid>
<number>c</number>shall apply only so long as the conditions precedent to such 
disability as set out in the said sub- section continue.'.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>81060</tid>
<number> 23</number> Amendment of section 38.- In section 38 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1209851</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (iii), for the words" make grants", the words" make 
loans or advances or grants" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1399893</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (iii), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (iv) may provide technical, legal, financial, marketing and 
administrative assistance to any person engaged in agriculture and 
rural development activities;


<subsection><tid>1437055</tid>
<number>v</number>may provide consultancy services in the field of agriculture and 
rural development and other related matters in or outside India, on 
such terms and against such remuneration, as may be agreed upon;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1338668</tid>
<number>vi</number>may perform the functions entrusted to or required of the 
National Bank by any other law for the time being in force; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>907643</tid>
<number>vii</number>do any other kind of business or undertake any other kind of 
activity which the Central Government or the Reserve Bank may 
authorise.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1460595</tid>
<number>24</number>Insertion of new sections 38A to 38C.- After section 38 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 38A. Promotion of subsidiaries.- The National Bank may, in 
consultation with the Reserve Bank, promote, form or manage or 
associate itself in promotion, formation or management of companies, 
subsidiaries, affiliates, societies, trusts or such other association 
of persons, as it may deem fit, for the purpose of carrying out its 
functions under this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>1952328</tid>
<number> 38B</number> Securitisation of debt.- Notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, the National Bank may-
<section><tid>682121</tid>
<number>a</number>create one or more trusts and transfer loans and advances granted 
by it, with or without the securities, to such trusts, for 
consideration;

</section>

<section><tid>466061</tid>
<number>b</number>set aside loans or advances held by the National Bank and issue 
and sell securities based upon such loans or advances so set aside in 
the form of debt obligations, trust certificates of beneficial 
interest or other instruments, by whatever name called, and act as a 
trustee for the holders of such securities.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>424934</tid>
<number> 38C</number> Exemption from compulsory registration.- Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub- section
<section><tid>170541</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 17 of the Registration Act,  
 <year>1908</year> (16 of <year>1908</year>),-

<subsection><tid>545588</tid>
<number>a</number>any instrument in the form of debt obligations or trust 
certificate of beneficial interest or any other instrument, by 
whatsoever name called, issued by the National Bank or the trust 
created by it to securitise the loans granted by it and not creating, 
declaring, assigning, limiting or extinguishing any right, title or 
interest to or in immovable property; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1891974</tid>
<number>b</number>any transfer of such instruments referred to in clause (a), shall 
not require compulsory registration.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>826352</tid>
<number> 25</number> Substitution of new section for section 40.- For section 40 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 40. Deposits and investments.- (1) The National Bank may invest its 
funds in promissory notes, stocks or securities of the Central 
Government or keep the moneys deposited with the Reserve Bank or with 
any agency of the Reserve Bank or with a State co- operative bank or a 
scheduled bank.

<section><tid>1437453</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or section 
30A, the National Bank may, for beneficial investment of its surplus 
funds, rediscount bills of exchange or promissory notes arising out of 
bonafide trade and commercial transactions and also lend repayable at 
call or short notice to a scheduled bank or any financial institution 
approved by the Reserve Bank, or invest in certificates of deposit and 
other instruments or schemes as may be approved by the Board.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>11781</tid>
<number>26</number>Amendment of section 44.- In section 44 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for the words" makin of grants", the words" makin of 
loans or advances or grants" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1193466</tid>
<number>27</number>Amendment of section 45.- In section 45 of the principal Act, for 
the words" and such other funds", the words" and other Funds" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>49298</tid>
<number>28</number>Amendment of section 47.- In section 47 of the principal Act, for 
clause (ii), the following clause shall be substituted, namely:-
" (ii) after the expiry of the said period of fifteen years, the Board 
shall, after making provision for the Fund referred to in clause (i), 
disburse or spend te balance of the surplus in such manner as may be 
approved by the Board.".



</article>



<article><tid>1051960</tid>
<number> 29</number> Insertion of new section 52A.- After section 52 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 52A. Agreement with National Bank on appointment of directors to 
prevail.- (1) Where any agreement entered into by the National Bank wit 
a company or a body corporate while granting loans and advances, 
provides for the appointment by the National Bank of one or more 
directors of such company or body corporate, such provisions and any 
appointment of directors made in pursuance thereof shall be valid and 
effective, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or in any other law for the time being 
in force, or in the memorandum, articles of association or any other 
instrument relating to the company or body corporate, and any 
provision regarding share qualification, age- limit, number of 
directorships, removal from office of directors and such like 
conditions contained in any such law or instrument aforesaid, shall 
not apply to any director appointed by the National Bank in pursuance 
of the agreement as aforesaid.

<section><tid>1459640</tid>
<number>2</number>Any director appointed as aforesaid shall-

<subsection><tid>1787736</tid>
<number>a</number>hold office during the pleasure of the National Bank and may be 
removed or substituted by any person by order in writing of the 
National Bank;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>91575</tid>
<number>b</number>not incur any obligation or liability by reason only of his being 
a director or for anything done or omitted to be done in good faith in 
the discharge of his duties as a director or anything in relation 
thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1302714</tid>
<number>c</number>not be liable to retirement by rotation and shall not be taken 
into account for computing the number of directors liable to such 
retirement.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>85829</tid>
<number> 30</number> Amendment of section 60.- In section 60 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>1274676</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (e), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (e) the manner of election of directors under clause (f) of 
sub- section (1) of section 6;";


</section>

<section><tid>74519</tid>
<number>ii</number>clauses (f) and (h) shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>125948</tid>
<number> 31</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1156281</tid>
<number>1</number>The National Bank for Agriculture and  
Rural Development (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>2000</year> (Ord. 4 of <year>2000</year>) is 
hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1521363</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken 
under the principal Act as amended by the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the principal Act as amended 
by this Act.
SUBHASH C. JAIN 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>