<act> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Mines) Rules, 19561
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, 
application and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 1956.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules apply in 
respect of the payment of wages to persons employed, either by the owner or by a 
contractor engaged by the owner, in any mine to which the Mines Act, 1952 (XXXV 
of 1952), applies 

2[or in any oil 
field].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They extend to the 
whole of India 

3[***].
 
 





</section></article> 
 The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
  
 <article>1[<number>1A</number> The provisions of 
these rules shall apply in relation to oil fields as they apply in relation to 
mines.]
  


</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Payment of Wages 
Act, 1936 (IV of 1936);
 
 

1[(aa)  “agent” means an agent as 
defined in clause (c) of section 2 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);]
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “authority” means an authority 
appointed under sub-section (1) of section 15;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “contractor” means a person 
engaged under a contract, by the owner of the mine for work on the mine and 
includes a sub-contractor;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “Court” means the Court 
mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 17;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “deduction for breach of 
contract” means a deduction made in accordance with the provisions of the 
proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “deduction for damage or loss” 
means a deduction made in accordance with the provisions of clause (c) of 
sub-section (2) of section 7;
 
 

2[(ff)  “Deputy Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central)” means an officer appointed as such by the Central 
Government;]
 
 

3[(g)  “employer” means the owner of 
the mine and includes a contractor, an agent, or manager or any other person 
responsible under section 3 of the Act for payment of wages and includes in the 
case of a deceased employer, his legal representative;]
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  “Form” means a Form appended to 
these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  “Inspector” means an Inspector 
referred to in section 14;
 
 

4[(ii)  “manager” means the person 
appointed under section 17 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952), to discharge the 
functions of a manager;]
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  “mine” means a mine as defined 
in clause (j) of section 2 of the Mines Act, 1952 (XXXV of 1952);
 
 

4[(jj)  “oil field” means an oil field 
as defined in clause (e) of section 3 of the Oil Fields (Regulation and 
Development) Act, 1948 (53 of 1948);
 </section><section>
       <number>jjj</number>  “owner” means the owner as 
defined in clause (1) of section 2 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);]
 
 

3[(k)  “person employed” or “employed 
person” means a person employed in a mine or an oil field to whom the Act 
applies and includes, in the case of a deceased employed person, his legal 
representative;]
 
 

5[(kk)  “Regional Labour Commissioner


6[(Central)]” means an officer 
appointed as such by the Central Government;]
 </section><section>
         <number>l</number>  “section” means a section of 
the Act; and
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  words and expressions used in 
these rules and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the same meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 








</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>2A</number> Notice of 
opening, abandonment, discontinuance, reopening and change in the ownership and 
addresses, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> When a mine has been opened, the owner, agent or manager 
shall forthwith communicate the actual date of opening to the Regional Labour 
Commissioner 

2[(Central)] in 
Form A.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When it is intended to 
abandon a mine or seam or to discontinue working thereof for a period exceeding 
60 days, the owner, agent or manager shall not, less than 40 days before such 
abandonment or discontinuance, give to the Regional Labour Commissioner 

2[(Central)] a 
notice stating the reasons for the proposed abandonment or discontinuance and 
the number of persons likely to be affected thereby:
 
Provided that when on 
account of unforeseen circumstances a mine is abandoned or discontinued before 
the said notice has been given or when without previous intimation the 
discontinuance extends beyond a period of 60 days, the notice shall be given 
forthwith.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When a mine or seam 
has been abandoned or the working thereof has been discontinued over a period 
exceeding 60 days, the owner, agent or manager shall within seven days of the 
abandonment or the expiry of the said period, give to the Regional Labour 
Commissioner 

3[(Central)], 
notice in Form A.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When it is intended to 
re-open a mine or seam after abandonment or after discontinuance for a period 
exceeding 60 days, the owner, agent or manager shall, not less than 30 days 
before resumption of mining operations, give to the Regional Labour Commissioner


3[(Central)], 
notice in Form A.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> When a mine has been 
re-opened, the owner, agent or manager of the mine shall forthwith communicate 
the actual date of re-opening to the Regional Labour Commissioner 

3[(Central)].
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When a change occurs 
in the name or ownership of a mine or in the address of the owner, the owner, 
agent or manager shall, within seven days from the date of change, give to the 
Regional Labour Commissioner 

3[(Central)], a 
notice in Form A:
 
Provided that where the 
owner of a mine is a firm or other association of individuals, a change,—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  of any partner in the case of a 
firm;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  of any member, in the case of 
an association;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  of any director, in the case 
of a public company; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  of any shareholder, in the case 
of a private company;
 
shall be also intimated to the Regional 
Labour Commissioner 

3[Central)], within seven days from 
the date of the change.]
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Register of fines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every employer who has obtained approval under sub-section (1) of section 8 to a 
list of acts and omissions in respect of which fines may be imposed, shall 
maintain a Register of Fines in Form I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The list of acts and 
omissions in respect of which fine may be imposed, shall be entered in the 
Register of Fines, at the beginning.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At the beginning of 
the Register of Fines, there shall also be entered, serially numbered, the 
approved purpose or purposes on which the amount of the fines realised is to be 
expended.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> At the end of every 
month, the amounts realised as fines shall be totalled and carried forward, 
after deduction of disbursement, if any, as per Part II of Form I.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> When any disbursements 
are made from the amounts of the fines realised a deduct entry of the amount so 
expended shall be made in the Register of Fines, and a voucher or receipt in 
respect of the amount shall be affixed to the register. If more than one purpose 
has been approved, the entry of the disbursement shall also indicate the purpose 
for which it is made.
 

1[(6) The Register 
of Fines shall be kept at the work spot 

2[or where the 
employer experiences difficulty in keeping it at the work spot, at other 
suitable place approved by the 

3[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)] in this behalf] and maintained up-to-date. Where no fine 
has been imposed on any employee in a wage-period, a ‘nil’ entry shall be made 
across the body of the register at the end of the wage-period indicating also in 
precise terms the wage-period to which the ‘nil’ entry relates.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Register of deductions 
for damage or loss.—The 
register of deductions for damage or loss referred to in sub-section (2) of 
section 10 shall be in Form II 

1[and shall be kept 
at the work spot 

2[or, where the 
employer experiences difficulty in keeping it at the work spot, at other 
suitable place approved by the 

3[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)] in this behalf] and maintained up-to-date. Where no 
deduction has been made from the wages of any employee in a wage-period, a ‘nil’ 
entry shall be made across the body of the register at the end of the 
wage-period, indicating also in precise terms the wage-period to which the ‘nil’ 
entry relates.]
 
 





</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Register of Wages.—A 
Register of Wages in Form III shall be maintained 

1[up-to-date] and 
kept at the work-spot, 

2[or, where the 
employer experiences difficulty in keeping it at the work-spot, at other 
suitable place approved by the 

3[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central) in this behalf] by every employer in proof of payment of 
wages. The rates of wages for all classes of workers shall be entered at the 
beginning of the Register.
 
 





</article> 
 The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
  
 <article>1[<number>5A</number> The register 
required to be maintained under the Mines Rules, 1955 in Form B in the First 
Schedule to those rules shall be deemed to be required to be maintained under 
these rules also.]
  


</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>5B</number> Combined 
form of registers.—2[Notwithstanding 
anything contained in these rules, where mechanised pay rolls are introduced for 
better administration or a combined (alternative) form is sought to be used by 
the employer to avoid duplication of work for compliance with the provisions of 
any other Act or the rules framed thereunder, an alternative suitable form in 
lieu of any of the forms prescribed under these rules, may be used with the 
previous approval of the Central Government.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>6</number> 
Preservation and maintenance of registers.—
<section><number>1</number> Every register maintained 
under the Act or these rules shall be preserved for a period of three years 
after the date of the last entry made therein 

2[at the workspot 
or where the employer experiences difficulty in keeping them at the work spot, 
at other suitable place approved by the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central)] 
in this behalf].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The registers 
maintained under the Act or these rules shall be maintained in English and in 
Hindi, or in the language understood by the majority of the persons employed in 
the mine:
 
Provided that where a 
register is maintained in Hindi or any other language a true translation thereof 
in English shall also be maintained.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>6A</number> Production 
of registers and other records.—All registers and records required to be 
maintained by the employer under these rules shall on demand be produced before 
the Inspector:
 
Provided that where an 
establishment has been closed, the Inspector may demand the production of the 
registers and records in his office or such other public place as may be nearer 
to the employer.]
 
 



</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Places for displaying 
notices.—The 
Inspector shall specify such place of places in the mine as he thinks fit 
(hereinafter referred to as the “specified place or places”) for the display of 
notices, lists and rules under rules 8, 12 and 16.
 


</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Notices of dates of 
payment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer shall display in a conspicuous place outside the office of the mine 
and at the specified place or places, notices in English and Hindi or in the 
language, if that not be Hindi, of the majority of the persons employed at such 
place or places showing,—
 
 

1[(i)  the wages period for which the 
wages are payable;]
 
 

2[(ii)]  for not less than two weeks 
in advance, the days on which wages are to be paid; and
 
 

2[(iii)]  the rates of wages and 
scales of allowances payable to persons employed in the mines concerned in Form 
IV; 

1[and]
 
 

1[(iv)  the day or days on which 
unpaid wages are to be paid, indicating the relevant wage period.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Copies of all such 
notices and alterations therein shall be sent to the Inspector.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8A</number> 
Supervision of payment.—Whenever so directed by the Inspector, the employer 
or his representative at the workspot shall pay wages to the employed persons on 
the notified date of payment under the supervision of the Inspector.]
 
 



</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Prescribed authority.—The


1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner] 

2[(Central)] shall 
be the prescribed authority competent to approve, under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 8, acts and omissions in respect of which fines may be imposed and under 
sub-section (8) of section 8, the purposes to which the fines realised may be 
applied.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Application in respect 
of fines.—Every 
employer desiring to have the power to impose fines in respect of any acts and 
omissions on the part of employed persons shall send to the 

1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner] 

2[(Central)]—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  a list, in English in duplicate, 
clearly defining such acts and omissions;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  in cases where the employer 
himself does not intend to be the sole authority empowered to impose fines, a 
list, in duplicate, showing by virtue of office or otherwise, such members of 
his staff as may pass orders imposing fines and the class of establishment on 
which any such member may impose a fine.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Approval of list of 
acts and omissions.—The


1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner] 

2[(Central)] may, 
on receipt of the list referred to in clause 
<section><number>a</number> of rule 10, and after such 
inquiry as he considers necessary, pass orders in respect of the said list 
either—
 </section><section>
        <number>a</number>  disapproving the list, or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  approving the list in its 
original form or as amended by him, in which case such list shall be deemed to 
have been approved under sub-section (1) of section 8:
 
Provided that no order 
disapproving or amending the list shall be passed unless the employer shall have 
been given an opportunity of showing cause in writing against such order.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Posting of the list.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer shall also display outside the office of the mine and at the 
specified place or places, notice showing the name and complete address of the 
Inspector who exercises jurisdiction under the Act over that mine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The employer shall 
display outside the office of the mine and at the specified place or places, a 
copy in English, together with a literal translation thereof, in the language of 
the majority of the persons employed at such mine or place, of the list approved 
under rule 11.
 


</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Persons authorised to 
impose fines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fine may be imposed upon a person employed in a mine by any person other than 
the employer or by a person included in the list referred to in clause (b) of 
rule 10.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of persons 
employed by a contractor, no fine may be imposed by any person other than the 
contractor:
 
Provided that a contractor 
who runs more than one establishment in two or more localities, and who employs 
not less than fifty persons in one locality, may, with the approval of the


1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner] 

2[(Central)], 
delegate his power to fine to his representative in that locality.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Procedure in imposing 
fines and deductions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fines shall be imposed on and no deductions shall be made from the wages of 
any person employed in a mine except in accordance with the procedure laid down 
in the rules and regulations or certified Standing Orders in force in the mine, 
and no fine shall be imposed or deduction made from the wages until the employed 
person has been given an opportunity in writing of showing cause against such 
imposition or deduction.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No fine shall be 
imposed on and no deduction for damage or loss shall be made for, the wages of a 
person employed by a contractor until the person authorised to impose the fine 
or make the deduction has explained personally to the said person the act or 
omission, or damage or loss in respect of which the fine or deduction is 
proposed to be imposed or made and the amount of fine and deduction, which it is 
proposed to impose or make and has heard his explanation in the presence of at 
least one other employed person.
 


</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Information to the 
employer.—The 
person imposing a fine or directing the making of a deduction for damage or loss 
shall (unless such person is the employer) at once inform the employer of all 
particulars necessary for the completion of the register prescribed by rule 3 or 
rule 4, as the case may be.
 


</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Deductions under the 
proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No deduction under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9 shall be made 
from the wages of an employed person who is under the age of fifteen years or is 
a woman.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such deduction 
shall be made from the wages of any employed person unless—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  there is a provision in writing 
in the terms of the contract of employment or in the certified Standing Orders 
of the employer requiring him to give notice of the termination of his 
employment;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  this rule has been displayed in 
English and in the language of the majority of the employed persons outside the 
office of the mine, and at the specified place or places concerned, and has been 
so displayed for not less than one month before the commencement of the absence 
in respect of which the deduction is made; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  at least one week before such 
deduction is made, a notice has been displayed outside the office of the mine 
and at the specified place or places concerned, giving the names of the persons 
from whom deduction is proposed to be made, the number of days, wages to be 
deducted and the condition, if any, on which the deduction will be remitted:
 
Provided that where the 
deduction is proposed to be made from all the persons employed in any department 
or section of the mine, it shall be sufficient, in lieu of giving the names of 
such persons in the department or section of the mine, to specify the department 
or section affected.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No such deduction 
shall exceed the wages of the person employed for the period by which the notice 
of termination of service given falls short of the period of such notice 
required by the contract of employment or certified Standing Orders.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any conditions have 
been specified in the notice displayed under clause (c) of sub-rule (2), no such 
deduction shall be made from any person who has complied with such conditions.
 


</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Measurement of the 
amount of work done by piece workers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the case of piece rated work, the employer shall be responsible for 
arranging, at the end of each day or shift or such longer period not exceeding 
the wage-period as may be found convenient, for the weighment, measurement or 
assessment or work done by the workers concerned in their presence or in the 
presence of their gangman (mistry), if any, and for the recording immediately 
thereafter of the particulars in register maintained in Form IVA. At the close 
of the wage-period, the total weighment, measurement or assessment in respect of 
each worker shall be recorded in a slip and issued to the worker at least a day 
prior to the disbursement of wages. In case of any dispute regarding weighment, 
measurement or assessment, the employer shall, as far as possible, have the 
dispute settled, on the spot in consultation with the worker or his gangman, if 
any:
 

1[Provided that 
where the 

2[Deputy Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central)] is satisfied that the register or records 
maintained by an employer will serve the purpose, he may permit such employer to 
continue to maintain such register or records in lieu of the register required 
to be maintained in Form IVA.]
 

3[(1A) The Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central) may exempt, from the provisions of sub-rule (1), 
any mine which has provided weigh-bridge or any other mechanical device for the 
weighment of the work done by the workers subject to the condition that such 
weigh-bridge or mechanical device shall be tested and certified by the Inspector 
or by such other agency and at such intervals as may be specified by the Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central).]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All weights, measures 
and weighing machines which are used for checking or ascertaining the wages of 
employed persons shall be made available for examination to the Inspector, who 
may in the event of his not being satisfied with the correctness of the 
apparatus or the weights, seal and prohibit their future use and report the 
matter immediately for necessary action to the appropriate authority responsible 
for the administration of the Standards of Weights and Measures Act, 1956 (89 of 
1956).
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>18</number> Annual 
Return.—Every employer shall send a return in Form V so as to reach the 
Regional Labour Commissioner 

2[(Central)] not 
later than the 1st of February following the end of the year to which it relates 
endorsing simultaneously a copy thereof to the Inspector having jurisdiction 
under the Act over the mine.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Advances to person 
employed by an employer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An advance of wages not already earned shall not ordinarily exceed the amount 
equal to two calendar months’ wages of the employed person. In exceptional 
circumstances, the amount of such advance may, with the previous sanction of the


1[Regional Labour 
Commissioner] 

2[(Central)], be 
made to the extent of four calendar months’ wages.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The advance may be 
recovered in instalments by a deduction from the wages spread over not more than 
twelve months in the case of an ordinary advance and twenty-four months in the 
case of an advance granted in exceptional circumstances. In no case shall the 
amount of an instalment exceed one-fourth of the wages earned in a wage-period.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The amount of all 
advances sanctioned and repayments thereof shall be entered in a register in 
Form VI which shall be maintained in English and in the language spoken by the 
majority of workers.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Procedure, costs and 
court-fees.—The 
procedure to be followed by the authorities appointed under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 15 and the Courts mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 17, the scales 
of costs which may be allowed in, and the amount of court-fees payable in 
respect of proceedings under the Act to which these rules apply shall be such 
procedure, scales and amounts as are, from time to time, prescribed by the State 
Government in the exercise of its powers under the Act in that behalf for the 
authority or Court concerned.
 


</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Abstracts.—The 
abstracts of the Act and of the rules made thereunder to be displayed under 
section 25 shall be in Form VII.
 


</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22</number> Penalties.—Whoever, 
being required under these rules to maintain any register or records or to 
furnish an information or return fails to maintain such register or record or to 
furnish such information or return or fails to observe provisions of any of 
these rules shall, for each such offence, be punishable with fine which may 
extend to five hundred rupees:
 
Provided that an employer 
who maintains the required register or record or furnishes the required return 
without making up-to-date entries therein, or fails to display notices shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees:
 

2[Provided further 
that no penalty shall be imposed on any person under this rule without giving 
him a reasonable opportunity, of being heard.]
 
 




</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Rescission and 
savings.—The 
Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 1949, are hereby rescinded but all acts done and 
orders issued under the rules so rescinded shall so far as they are not 
inconsistent with these rules, be deemed to have been respectively done and 
issued under these rules.
 
 
  
</article><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Mines) 
Rules, 1956
 


 
 


Form VII
 


(See rule 21)
 


Abstract of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 
and the rules made thereunder
 


Whom the Act affects
 


1. The Act applies to the payment of wages to 
persons in mines receiving less than Rs. 1600 a month.
 


2. No employed person can give up by contract 
or agreement, his rights under the Act.
 


Definition of wages
 


3. ‘Wages’ means all remuneration (whether by 
way of salary, allowances or otherwise) expressed in terms of money or capable 
of being so expressed which, would, if the terms of employment, express or 
implied, were fulfilled, be payable to a person employed in respect of his 
employment or of work done in such employment, and includes—
 


      (a)  any remuneration payable under any 
award or settlement between the parties or order of a Court;
 


      (b)  any remuneration to which the 
person employed is entitled in respect of overtime work or holidays or any leave 
period;
 


      (c)  any additional remuneration 
payable under the terms of employment (whether called a bonus or by any other 
name);
 


      (d)  any sum which by reason of the 
termination of employment of the person employed is payable under any law, 
contract or instrument which provides for the payment of such sum, whether with 
or without deductions but does not provide for the time within which the payment 
is to be made;
 


      (e)  any sum to which the person 
employed is entitled under any scheme framed under any law for the time being in 
force.
 


but does not include—
 


      (1)  any bonus (whether under a scheme 
of profit sharing or otherwise) which does not form part of the remuneration 
payable under the terms of employment or which is not payable under any award or 
settlement between the parties or order of a Court;
 


      (2)  the value of any 
house-accommodation, or of the supply of light, water, medical attendance or 
other amenity or of any service excluded from the computation of wages by a 
special or general order of the State Government;
 


      (3)  any contribution paid by the 
employer to any pension or provident fund, and the interest which may have 
accrued thereon;
 


      (4)  any travelling allowance or the 
value of any travelling concessions;
 


      (5)  any sum paid to the employed 
person to defray special expenses entailed on him by the nature of his 
employment; or
 


      (6)  any gratuity payable on the 
termination of employment in cases other than those specified in sub-clause (d).
 


Responsibility for and method of payment
 


4. The employer is responsible for the 
payment under the Act of wages to persons employed under him, and any contractor 
employing persons is responsible for payment to the persons he employs.
 


5. Wage-periods shall be fixed for the 
payment of wages at intervals not exceeding one month.
 


6. Wages shall be paid on a working day 
within 7 days of the end of the wage-period (or within ten days if 1,000 or more 
persons are employed).
 


The wages of a person discharged shall be 
paid not later than the second working day after his discharge.
 


7. Payment in kind is prohibited.
 


Fines and Deductions
 


8. No deductions shall be made from wages 
except those authorised under the Act (See paragraphs 9-15 below).
 



1[9. (1) Fines can be imposed only for 
such acts and omissions as the employer may, with the previous approval of the 
Inspector, specify by a notice displayed at or near the main entrance of the 
work-place or places at the mine and after giving the employed person an 
opportunity for explanation.
 


(2) Fines,—
 


      (a)  shall not exceed three paise in 
the rupee;
 


      (b)  shall not be recovered by 
instalments, or later that sixty days of the date of imposition;
 


      (c)  shall be recorded in a register 
and applied to such purposes beneficial to the employed persons as are approved 
by the Inspector; and
 


      (d)  shall not be imposed on any 
employed person who is under the age of fifteen years.]
 


10. (a) Deductions for absence from duty can 
be made only or account of the absence of the employed person at times when he 
should be working and such deductions must not exceed an amount which is in the 
same proportion to his wages for the wage-period as the time he was absent in 
that period is to the total time he should have been at work.
 


(b) If ten or more employed persons, acting 
in concert, absent themselves without reasonable cause and without due notice, 
the deduction for absence can include wages for eight days in lieu of notice, 
but—
 


      (1)  No deduction for breaking contract 
can be made from a person under 15 or a woman;
 


      (2)  There must be a provision in 
writing which forms part of the contract of employment or the certified Standing 
Orders, requiring that a specific period of notice of intention to cease work 
not exceeding 15 days or the period of notice which the employer has to give to 
discharge a worker, must be given to the employer and that wages may be deducted 
in lieu of such notice;
 


      (3)  The above provision must be 
displayed at or near the main entrance of the work place or places at the mine 
or work place;
 


      (4)  No deduction of this nature can be 
made until a week’s notice that this deduction is to be made has been posted at 
or near the main entrance of the work place or places at the mine or work place;
 


      (5)  No deduction must exceed the wages 
of the employed person for the period by which the notice he gives of leaving 
employment, is less than the notice he should have given under his contract.
 


11. Deductions can be made for damage to or 
loss of goods expressly entrusted to an employed person or for loss of money for 
which he is required to account, where such damage or loss is due to his neglect 
or default.
 


Such deductions cannot exceed the amount of 
the damage or loss caused and can be made only after giving the employed persons 
an opportunity for explanation.
 


12. Deductions can be made, equivalent to the 
value thereof for house accommodation supplied by the employer or by the 
Government or any housing board set up under any law for the time being in force 
(whether the Government or the board is employer or not) or any other authority 
engaged in the business of subsidizing house accommodation which may be 
specified in this behalf by the Central Government, amenities and services 
(other than tools and raw materials) supplied by the employer: provided these 
are accepted by the employed person as a part of the terms of his employment and 
have in the case of amenities and services been authorised by order of the 
Central Government.
 


13. (a) Deductions can be made for the 
recovery of advances or for adjustment of over-payment of wages.
 


(b) Advances made before the employment began 
can only be recovered from the first payment of wages for a complete wage period 
but no recovery can be made of advances given for travelling expenses before 
employment began.
 


(c) Advances of unearned wages can be made at 
the employer’s discretion during the employment.
 


14. Deductions can be made for subscription 
to and for repayment of advances from any recognised provident fund.
 


15. Deductions can be made for payments to 
co-operative societies approved by the Central Government or to the postal 
insurance, subject to any conditions imposed by the Central Government.
 


Deductions can also be made with the written 
authorisation of the person employed for payment of any premium on his life 
insurance policy to the Life Insurance Corporation of India or for the purchase 
of securities of the Government of India or of any State Government or for being 
deposited in any Post Office Savings Bank in furtherance of any savings scheme 
of any such Government.
 


15A. Any loss of wages resulting from 
withholding of increment or promotion, reduction to a lower post or time scale 
or to a lower stage in the time scale or suspension does not constitute 
deduction from wages within the meaning of the Act. For this purpose the rules 
framed by an employer in relation to his employees in mines for the purpose of 
any of the aforesaid penalties shall provide that:—
 


       (i)  any such penalty as aforesaid, 
except the penalty of suspension, shall not be imposed unless the person 
concerned,—
 


           (a)  has been informed of the 
charges in respect of which it is proposed to impose the penalty;
 


           (b)  has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause why the proposed penalty should not be imposed.
 


      (ii)  the person concerned is given a 
right of appeal against any order imposing the penalty.
 


Inspections
 


16. An Inspector can enter on any premises 
and can exercise the powers of inspection (including examination of documents 
and taking of evidence) as he may deem necessary for carrying out the purposes 
of the Act.
 


Complaints of Deductions or Delays
 


17. (1) Where irregular deductions are made 
from wages, or delays in payment take place, an employed person can make an 
application in the prescribed form within 6 months to the Authority appointed by 
the State Government for the purpose. An application delayed beyond this period 
may be rejected unless sufficient cause for the delay is shown.
 


(2) Any legal practitioner, official of a 
registered trade union, Inspector under the Act or other person acting with the 
authority can make the complaint on behalf of an employed person.
 


(3) A single application may be presented by 
or on behalf of any number of persons belonging to the same mine the payment of 
whose wages has been delayed.
 


Action by the Authority
 


18. The Authority may award compensation to 
the employed person in addition to ordering the payment of delayed wages or the 
refund of illegal deductions.
 


If a malicious or vexatious complaint is 
made, the Authority may impose a penalty not exceeding Rs. 50 on the applicant 
and order that it be paid to the employer.
 


Appeal against the Authority
 


19. An appeal against an order dismissing 
either wholly or in part an application or against a direction may be preferred 
within thirty days in Calcutta to the Chief Judge, Court of Small Causes and 
elsewhere to the District Court,—
 


      (a)  by the employer if the total 
amount directed to be paid exceeds Rs. 300;
 


      (b)  by an employed person or any 
official of a registered trade union authorised in writing to act on his behalf, 
if the total amount of wages withheld from him or his co-workers, exceeds rupees 
fifty;
 


      (c)  by a person directed to pay a 
penalty for a malicious or vexatious application.
 


Punishments for breaches of the Act
 


20. Any one tried for delaying the payment of 
wages beyond the due date, or making any unauthorised deductions from wages is 
liable to a fine upto Rs. 500, but only if prosecuted with the sanction of the 
Authority of the Appellate Court.
 


21. The employer who,—
 


      (1)  does not fix a wage-period, or
 


      (2)  makes payment in kind, or
 


      (3)  fails to display at or near the 
main entrance of the work place or places at the mine or work place this 
abstract in English and in the language of the majority of the employed persons, 
or
 


      (4)  breaks certain rules made under 
this Act, 
 


is liable to fine not exceeding Rs. 200.
 


A complaint to this effect can be made only 
by the Inspector, or with his sanction.
 

 
</form><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Mines) Rules, 
1956
 


 
 



1[Form A
 


(See rule 2A)
 


Notice of opening, abandonment, 
discontinuance, re-opening and change in the ownership, address, etc.
 


From
 


...................................
 


...................................
 


To
 


The Regional Labour Commissioner (Central),
 



................................................................................
 


Sir,
 


I have to furnish the following particulars 
in respect of* ......................... at................... mine 
of...................... (owner).
 


       1. In the case of change of name of 
mine:
 


            Old name of mine
 


            Date of change            

 


       2.  (a) Situation of the 
mine:                     
 


            Village
 


            Police Station
 


            Sub-division (Taluk)
 


            
District                                                 
 


            State
 


            (b) In the case of new mine, 
particulars of situation of mine:
 


            Post 
Office                                           
 


            Telegraph Office
 


            Railway 
Station                                    
 


            Rest House
 


            (Give distance therefrom) Means 
of travelling
 


       3.  (a) Name and Postal address of 
Present/Previous**
 


             (i)  Owner
 


            (ii)  Managing Agent, if any
 


           (iii)  Agent, if any
 


           (iv)  Manager
 


            (v)  In case of change, date of 
change
 


       4. Date on which it is intended to 
open/reopen/abandon/ discontinue*** the mine.
 


       5. Actual date of 
opening/reopening/abandonment/discontinuance*** of the mine.
 


       6. 

2[No. of persons affected.]
 



                                                                                                            
Yours faithfully,
 



                                                                                                            
Signature
 



                                                                                                            
Designation: Owner/         Agent/Manager
 


Date.............................
 


Instructions
 


    *  Mention the matter to which the notice 
refers.
 


   **  To be filled in only when the notice 
refers to a change, and only against the item in respect of which notice is 
given.
 


***  Delete whatever is not applicable.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by S.O. 794, dated 24th February, 
1964.
 


   2.  Ins. by S.O. 3844, dated 18th 
November, 1970.
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>