<act><tid>1519306</tid>
<title>THE LOCAL AUTHORITIES PENSIONS AND GRATUITIES ACT, <year>1919</year></title>

ACT NO. 1 OF <year>1919</year>
[ 26th February, <year>1919</year>.]

An Act to extend the powers of local authorities in regard to the 
granting of pensions and gratuities.

WHEREAS it is expedient to extend the powers of local authorities 
in regard to the granting of pensions and gratuities;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>293439</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.-
<section><tid>1518359</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Local  
Authorities Pensions and Gratuities Act, <year>1919</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>486168</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1678700</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition.- In this Act," officer" means any person who has 
undertaken <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> service under the Government] and who immediately prior 
to undertaking such service, was paid and employed solely by a local 
authority and, but for undertaking such service, would in the ordinary 
course have continued in such employment; <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and, the" appropriate 
Government" means, in relation to cantonment authorities and port 
authorities in major ports, the Central Government, and in relation to 
other authorities, the State Government].


</article>



<article><tid>697053</tid>
<number>3</number>Power to grant extraordinary pensions and gratuities.- 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any enactment or in any rule 
made thereunder regulating the powers of local authorities, and 
without prejudice to any powers conferred by or under any such 
enactment, a local authority may grant a pension or gratuity to any 
officer thereof who may, since the 4th day of August, <year>1914</year>, have been 
wounded or otherwise incapacitated in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> service under the 
Government], and to the widow or child of any such officer who may 
have died in consequence of injuries received or illness contracted 
since the 4th day of August, <year>1914</year>, in the course of such service.


</article>



<article><tid>1919912</tid>
<number> 4</number> Provisions as to pensions and gratuities.-
<section><tid>728397</tid>
<number>1</number>Such pension or  
gratuity may be granted in addition to any pension or gratuity payable 
to the officer or his wife or child, as
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for sub- section (2). 
2. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
3. The words" the service of Government" successively amended by the 
A. O. <year>1937</year> and the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
4. Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the case may be, under any general or special orders of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> His Majesty 
in Council] or of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Central Government or any State Government], 
but shall not, save with the sanction of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appropriate 
Government], exceed the amount of the pension or gratuity to which the 
officer or his wife or child would have been entitled under any such 
orders if his employment by the local authority had been service for 
the same time and on the same pay <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> under the Government].


</section>

<section><tid>1046898</tid>
<number>2</number>Any pension granted under this Act may be made to take effect 
from such date subsequent to the 4th day of August, <year>1914</year>, and subject 
to such conditions as the local authority may think fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1740196</tid>
<number>5</number>Procedure.- Subject to the provisions of this Act, the decision 
of a local authority to grant a pension or gratuity thereunder shall 
be made in such manner and shall be subject to such sanction as may be 
prescribed by any enactment or rule regulating the grant by such local 
authority of pensions and gratuities:
Provided that in every case the sanction of the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> appropriate 
Government] shall be necessary.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>These words shall stand unmodified, vide A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C.". 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.". 
4. The words" under Government" successively amended by the A. O. 
<year>1937</year> and the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>