<act><title>The 
Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances (National Fund for Control of 
Drug Abuse) Rules, 20061</title> 

  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances 
(National Fund for Control of Drug Abuse) Rules, 2006.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on 
the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  

</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless the 
context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985 
(61 of 1985);
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  “Controlling Officer” means an officer who is entrusted, by the 
Central Government, with the responsibility of controlling the receipt of money 
in the Fund and incurring expenditure from the Fund.
 </section><section>       
<number>c</number>  “Governing Body” means the Governing Body constituted by the Central 
Government under sub-section (3) of section 7A of the Act;
 </section><section>       
<number>d</number>  “Form” means the Form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>       
<number>e</number>  “Fund” means the National Fund for Control of Drug Abuse constituted 
under section 7A of the Act;
 </section><section>        
<number>f</number>  all other words and expressions used in these rules and not defined, 
but defined in the Act, shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to 
them in the Act.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Procedure for remittance of 
grant to the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> Every grant made by any 
person or institution under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 7A of the 
Act shall be made by crossed cheque or demand draft in favour of the National 
Fund for Control of Drug Abuse and sent to the Joint Secretary (Revenue), 
Ministry of Finance, Department of Revenue, North Block, New Delhi–110001, who 
shall, on receipt of such cheque or demand draft issue a receipt to such person 
or institution making such grant.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All grants made under sub-rule 
(1) shall be unconditional and irrevocable.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Receipt of 
money.—All moneys 
received under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 7A of the Act shall be credited to the 
Fund without delay by the Controlling Officer.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Procedure for grant of money 
from the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> Any Department of the Central 
Government or of State Government(s) or any organisation(s) (hereinafter called 
as the ‘Applicant’) desirous of obtaining money from the Fund shall submit an 
application in Form ‘A’ appended to these rules, together with a project 
report.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every application made under 
sub-rule (1) shall be sent to the Joint Secretary (Revenue), Ministry of 
Finance, Department of Revenue, North Block, New Delhi – 
110001.</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Grant of money from the Fund. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
may require the Applicant to furnish further information or clarification 
regarding the activities and matters connected with the Applicant to enable it 
to consider payment out of the Fund. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the conditions specified in sub-rule (3), the Governing Body 
may sanction money out of the Fund to an Applicant within the limits notified by 
the Central Government and the Central Government may, on the recommendation of 
the Governing Body sanction such amount of money to an Applicant, as it 
considers appropriate. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every Applicant who has been sanctioned money out of the Fund under 
sub-rule (2) shall,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> apply the money to meet the expenditure incurred in connection with the 
  measures taken for combating illicit traffic in, or controlling abuse of, 
  narcotic drugs and psychotropic substances or controlled substances for all or 
  any of the purposes specified in sub-section (2) of section 7A of the Act; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> submit an annual return ending on the last day of March of every year, 
  within fifteen days of the end of the preceding year to the Central Government 
  in Form ‘B' appended to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> maintain regular books of accounts, showing receipt and expenditure, 
  which shall provide a true and fair view of the financial position of such 
  Applicant; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> be bound by the terms and conditions stipulated in the letter of 
  sanction of money issued by the Central Government. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> The money provided to the Applicant, and the assets acquired or created 
out of such money, shall be deemed to be entrusted to the Applicant for the 
purposes specified in sub-section (2) of section 7A of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Applicant shall retain, hold and use the money received by it from 
the Fund, and all assets acquired with such moneys, solely for the purposes 
specified in sub-section (2) of section 7A of the Act and for no other purpose. 

 </section><section><number>6</number> If the Central Government has reasons to believe that an Applicant,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> has failed to carry out the purposes specified in sub-section (2) of 
  section 7A of the Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> is likely to be wound up; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> is unable to maintain and preserve the assets acquired or created out 
  of the money received from the Fund; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> is unable to perform or is likely to commit breach of its obligations 
  under the grant of money, the Central Government may, at any time, revoke the 
  grant of money, and in such case the Applicant shall be disentitled to retain 
  the moneys paid out of the Fund or the assets acquired or created thereby: 
</subsection>
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Provided that no grant of money shall be revoked without giving 
the grantee a notice to show cause within thirty days from the date of the 
notice as to why the grant should not be revoked for the reasons indicated in 
the notice and if the grantee so requests, without giving him a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard in person: 
 Provided further that where the Central Government is of the opinion that the 
money that was granted is still with the grantee and that the grantee is likely 
to fritter away or squander the money, so that it is beyond the reach of the 
Central Government in case of revocation, it may revoke the grant and give 
notice to show cause to the grantee subsequent to the revocation and if the 
grantee so requests, give him a reasonable opportunity of being heard in 
person.] 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>7</number> Communication of 
sanctions.—All 
financial sanctions and orders issued by the Central Government under these 
rules shall be communicated to the Audit Officer or the Accounts Officer, as the 
case may be, in accordance with the procedure specified under the General 
Financial Rules, 2005.</article> 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Accounts and 
audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records as 
per the Accounting Procedure as at Annexure I, appended to these rules, and 
prepare a statement of accounts giving therein the details of the amount 
credited to the Fund and expenditure incurred therefrom, in consultation with 
the Comptroller and Auditor General of India.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The accounts of the Central 
Government under sub-rule (1) shall be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor 
General of India at such intervals as may be specified by him.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Comptroller and Auditor 
General of India shall have the same rights and privileges and authority, in 
connection with the audit of the Fund and accounts of the Central Government 
maintained under sub-rule (1) and also in connection with the audit of the 
accounts of the Applicant, as he has in connection with the audit of General 
Accounts and, in particular, shall have the rights to demand production of 
books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Central Government or the 
Applicant.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>9</number> Publication of annual report 
and statement of accounts.—The annual report giving an 
account of activities financed out of the Fund together with the statement of 
accounts referred to in section 7B of the Act shall be published in the Official 
Gazette as soon as possible after the end of each financial year and, in any 
case not later than 31st December of succeeding year.</article> 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Application of the provisions 
of General Financial Rules, 2005.—The provisions of the General 
Financial Rules, 2005 as amended from time to time shall, as far as may be, 
apply to the grant of money by the Central Government under these 
rules.</article><form>
 

THE NARCOTIC DRUGS AND PSYCHOTROPIC SUBSTANCES 
(NATIONAL FUND FOR CONTROL OF DRUG ABUSE) RULES, 20061 
 

 
 

FORM B 
 

[ See rule 6(3)(b)] 
 

FORMAT FOR ANNUAL RETURNS TO BE SUBMITTED BY THE 
 
APPLICANT RECEIVING PAYMENT OUT OF THE NATIONAL  
FUND FOR CONTROL OF DRUG 
ABUSE 
 

1. Year in respect of which returns filed 
 

2. Name of the Applicant 
 

3. Name of the Government/Non-Government Organisation who established the 
Applicant 
 

4. Address of the Applicant 
 

5. Amount spent by the Applicant during the year 
 

6. The amount out of item 5 spent from sources other than the Fund 
 

7. Results achieved and extent to which targets have been achieved 
 

8. Further action to be taken, giving specific recommendations for revision 
of the proposal in case the targets are not likely to be achieved. 
 

9. Name, designation and telephone number of the officer who is authorised to 
sign the return. 
 

 
 

Date........... 
 

Place........... 
 

Signature 
 

 
 

-------
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 177 (E), dated 24th March, 2006, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 24th March, 
2006. 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 232(E), dated 2nd April, 2009 (w.e.f. 2-4-2009 
).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>