<act> 
 OVERALL DIMENSIONS OF MOTOR VEHICLES 
(PRESCRIPTION OF CONDITIONS FOR EXEMPTION) RULES, 19911
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Overall Dimensions of Motor Vehicles (Prescription of Conditions for 
Exemption) Rules, 1991;
 </section><section><number>2</number> they shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 
 OVERALL DIMENSIONS OF MOTOR VEHICLES 
(PRESCRIPTION OF CONDITIONS FOR EXEMPTION) RULES, 1991
  
 <article><number>2</number> Conditions for the grant of 
exemption from Rule 93.—The State 
Government may exempt any motor vehicle or any class of descrip­tion of 
motor vehicles from the provisions of Rule 93 of the Central Motor Vehicles 
Rules, 1989, subject to the fulfilment of any or all of the conditions specified 
in these rules which that Government may deem fit to impose, namely:—
 <section><number>1</number> Such motor vehicle or class of 
description of motor vehicles shall —
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  observe such 
load restrictions as the State Government may by order specify in this 
behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  obtain the 
previous permission of such authority as may be specified by the State 
Government in this behalf before put­ting such vehicles on the load;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  not, if they 
are loaded, travel over such bridges and cross drainage structures on the road, 
which the State Government may, having regard to the safety of the road 
structures, speci­fy;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  where 
prohibited under clause (c) to travel over the structure referred  to in 
that clause, the owner or transporter shall at his cost make arrangements to 
cross the rivers in accor­dance with the directions given by the authority 
specified by the State Government in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  give advance 
intimation to such authority or officer specified in this behalf by the State 
Government regarding the movement of such vehicle;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  equip 
with necessary warning signals such as red flags in the day time, red light and 
reflectors in the night so as to indicate the extreme positions of the vehicle 
clearly;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  move without 
any hindrance to the normal flow of tra­ffic;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  not exceed the 
speed limit of 16 kms. per hour.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where any damage is caused to 
the roads or road structures directly or indirectly due to the movement of such 
vehicles, the operator of the vehicle or the transporter shall be liable to pay 
such amount to the State Government as may be assessed by the authorities in 
this behalf.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The State Government shall not 
be liable for any damage that may be caused to such vehicles or their contents 
through their transits.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any grant of exemption under 
these rules shall be without prejudice to the right of the authorities specified 
in this behalf by the State Government to regulate or stop the movement of such 
vehicles having regard to the safety of roads, bridges, structures and other 
road users.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The State Government may, in 
consultation with the operator of the vehicle or the owner, conduct route survey 
to assess the fitness of the roads for movement of such vehicles, feasibility of 
negotiating the curves more particularly in built-up areas, sufficiency of road 
width, adequacy of vertical clearance and deficiencies identified in the 
assessment shall be rectified by the operators or owners of the 
vehicles.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Exemption granted under these 
rules shall be applicable only for operating such vehicles on roads lying within 
the jurisdic­tion of the Public Works Department of the respective State 
Department and operators of the vehicles or their owners thereof shall make 
their own arrangements to obtain the approval of the other Departments of local 
body authorities for plying on the roads lying within their 
jurisdiction.</section></article> 
 OVERALL DIMENSIONS OF MOTOR VEHICLES 
(PRESCRIPTION OF CONDITIONS FOR EXEMPTION) RULES, 1991
  
 <article>

1[<number>3</number> Removal of doubts.—For 
removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that any exemption granted under these 
rules in any State shall be valid throughout India.]
 
 



</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>