<act><title>


The Prevention of Cruelty to Animals  
    (Registration of Cattle Premises) Rules, 19781</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and application.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Registration of 
    Cattle Premises) Rules, 1978.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules 
    shall apply only to cities or towns which have a population exceeding one 
    lakh. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    ‘cattle’ means oxen, buffaloes, cows, 
    bullocks and horses, including their young ones;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    ‘certificate’ means the certificate of 
    Registration;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    ‘registering authority’ means such 
    officers of the veterinary department of the State Government or of a local 
    authority as the State Government may, by general or special order, specify 
    in this behalf.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Registration of Premises.—Every 
    person owning or in charge of premises in which not less than five heads of 
    cattle are kept for the purpose of profit shall, in any case, where the 
    premises are already in existence, within three months from the commencement 
    of these rules and, in any case where, after the commencement of these rules 
    any such premises, apply to the registering authority for the registration 
    of such premises.  
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Application for registration.—Every 
    application for registration shall contain full information regarding the 
    number and types of animals kept or to be kept, the purpose for which they 
    are being kept or are to be kept, the provision made or to be made as 
    respects floor space, flooring ventilation, supply of food and water, 
    disinfection, drainage, disposal of dung or unwanted matter, boundary walls 
    and shall also contain such other information relevant to the matter as may 
    be specifically called for by the registering authority.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Certificate of registration.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    If the registering authority is satisfied that, having regard to the 
    information supplied, the welfare of the cattle is adequately secured and 
    that they are not likely to undergo any unnecessary suffering, he shall 
    register the premises and issue to the applicant a certificate in respect 
    thereof.  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Every 
    certificate shall be valid for a period of three years from the date of 
    issue thereof, but it may be renewed from time to time for a period of three 
    years at a time an application made by the person owning or in charge of the 
    premises, within three months from the date of expiry of the existing 
    certificate.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Inspection of premises.—Every 
    premises registered under these rules shall be open for inspection at all 
    reasonable times by any veterinary or public health officer of the local 
    authority or of the State Government who may be authorised by the State 
    Government in this behalf by general or special order.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Cancellation of registration.—If 
    any premises are not maintained in the manner required under these rules, 
    the registering authority may, by notice in writing stating the grounds on 
    which the notice proceeds and after giving an opportunity to the person 
    concerned to show cause, cancel the certificate.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Appeal.—An 
    appeal shall lie from any order refusing or cancelling the registration of 
    any premises under these rules to such officer or other authority as the 
    State Government may specify in this behalf.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number> Display of section 12 of the 
      Act.—If in any premises milch 
      cattle are kept, there shall be displayed by the owner of cattle 
      prominently in or near the premises, a copy of section 12 of the 
      Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 (59 of 1960) in a language 
      commonly understood in the locality.  
 If 
      any person performs upon any cow or other milch animal the operation 
      called phooka or doom dev or permits such operation being 
      performed upon any such animal in his possession or under his control, he 
      shall be punishable with fine which may be extended to one thousand 
      rupees, or with imprisonment for a fine which may extend to two years, or 
      with both, and the animal on which the operation was performed shall be 
      forfeited to the Government.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Saving.—If 
    in any area to which these rules apply, any rule, regulation or bye-law made 
    under any law for the time being in force, by any local authority which 
    contains the provisions for the registration or licensing of premises in 
    which cattle or any type thereof are kept then such rule, regulation or 
    bye-laws to the extent to which it contains provisions relating to cattle or 
    any type thereof, as the case may be, shall to that extent be of no avail.  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>