<act><title>

THE INDECENT REPRESENTATION OF WOMEN 
    (PROHIBITION) 
    RULES, 19871</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Indecent Representation of Women (Prohibition) 
    Rules, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the 2nd day 
    of October, 1987.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires:
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> “Act” 
    means the Indecent Representation of Women (Prohibition) Act, 1986 (60 of 
    1986);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> “article” 
    means any book, pamphlet, paper, slide, film, writing, drawing, painting, 
    photograph, representation of figure;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> 
    “authorized officer” means any Gazetted Officer authorized by the State 
    Government for the purpose of section 5 of the Act.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> “section” 
    means a section of the Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions used in these rules 
    and not defined, shall have the meanings respectively, assigned to them in 
    the Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Manner of seizure of articles.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every seizure made in pursuance of the provisions of sub-section (1) of 
    section 5 shall be made in the manner hereinafter provided in these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The authorized officer seizing any 
    advertisements or articles under sub-section (1) of section 5 shall prepare 
    a list of such advertisements or articles containing such details relating 
    to the description, quality, quantity, mark, number and other particulars 
    thereof as he may consider relevant to the identity of such advertisements 
    or articles in any proceeding under the Act, in the Form annexed to these 
    rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The authorized officer shall pack and seal 
    such advertisements or articles in the manner provided in rule 4 and shall 
    deliver a copy of the list so prepared to the person from whom such 
    advertisements or articles are seized.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The advertisements or articles so seized 
    shall be marked with a distinguishing number and shall also be signed by the 
    authorized officer, the person from whom such advertisements or articles 
    have been seized and two respectable inhabitants of the locality.  If it is 
    not possible to mark any such advertisement or article, the marking may be 
    done on the packaging or in any other manner which the authorized officer 
    thinks proper.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Manner of packing  and dealing with the 
    advertisements or articles seized.—
<section><number>1</number> The advertisements or articles 
    seized shall be packed in adequately strong paper, cloth or in any other 
    packing material in such a way that the advertisements or articles may not 
    be tampered with and the ends of the paper, cloth or other packing material 
    shall be neatly folded in and affixed by means of gum or other adhesive or 
    stitched in or tied.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The package shall be further secured by 
    means of strong twine or thread and the twine or thread shall be fastened on 
    the package by means of sealing wax on which there shall be at least four 
    distinct and clear impressions of the seal of the authorized officer of 
    which one shall be on the top of the package, one at the bottom and the 
    other two at the body of the package and knots of the twine or thread shall 
    be covered by means of sealing wax bearing the impression of the seal of the 
    authorized officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where  necessary,  the authorized  
    officer  shall  put the advertisements  or articles in a box, a container of 
    a suitable material and size and seal it in the manner provided in sub-rule 
    (2).

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Manner of seizing and sealing of 
    advertisements or articles in certain cases.—Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in rules 3 and 4, where the authorized officer is of the opinion 
    that it is not possible to seize and seal any advertisement or article in 
    the manner prescribed in rules 3 and 4 due to the size or the nature of such 
    advertisement or article, he may take such steps as he thinks fit for the 
    seizure and sealing of such advertisement or article without affecting the 
    integrity, utility or saleable value thereof.
 
 

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE INDECENT REPRESENTATION OF WOMEN 
    (PROHIBITION)  

    RULES, 1987
 

 
 

 
 




    Form
 


[See  rule 3(2)]
 



    List of Advertisements or Articles Seized
 


To
 


(Name and address of the person from whom the 
    advertisement(s) or article(s) are seized)
 



    ..................................................................................................................................................
 



    ...................................................................................................................................................
 


The  advertisement(s), article(s)  detailed  
    below  has/have this day been seized by me under sub-section (1) of section 
    5 of the  Indecent Representation of Women (Prohibition) Act, 1986 (60 of 
    1986), from the premises......... situated at..........
 


Details of the advertisement(s), article(s) 
    seized:
 


Place:.............
 


                                 
    ...................................
 


(Authorized Officer)
 


                                              
    Area................
 


SEAL 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>