<act><tid>1527072</tid>
<title>THE DIPLOMATIC AND CONSULAR OFFICERS (OATHS AND FEES) ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <footcitenum>1948</footcitenum>
An Act to provide for the administration of oaths by diplomatic and 
consular officers and to prescribe the fees leviable in respect of 
certain of their official duties.

[ 3rd September, <year>1948</year>.]

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the administration of 
oaths by diplomatic and consular officers and for the levy of fees in 
respect of certain official duties performed by them;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1397231</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Diplomatic and 
Consular Officers (Oaths and Fees) Act, <year>1948</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>561382</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act,-
<section><tid>1747810</tid>
<number>a</number>" consular officer" includes consul- general, consul, 
vice- consul, consular agent, pro- consul and any other 
person authorized to perform the duties of consul- 
general, consul, vice- consul or consular agent;

</section>

<section><tid>266088</tid>
<number>b</number>" diplomatic officer" means any ambassador, envoy, 
minister, charge d' affaires, or secretary of embassy or 
legation; and

</section>

<section><tid>1038904</tid>
<number>c</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1313435</tid>
<number> 3</number> Powers as to oaths and notarial acts abroad.-
<section><tid>1480147</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
diplomatic or consular officer may, in any foreign country or place 
where he is exercising his functions, administer any oath and take any 
affidavit and also do any notarial act which any notary public may do 
within <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a State]; and every oath, affidavit and notarial act 
administered, sworn or done by or before any such person shall be as 
effectual as if duly administered, sworn or done by or before any 
lawful authority in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a State].

</section>

<section><tid>790282</tid>
<number>2</number>Any document purporting to have affixed, impressed or 
subscribed thereon or thereto the seal and signature of any person 
authorized by this Act to administer an oath in testimony of any oath.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>564</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> This Act has been extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry 
by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (d) omitted by Act 2 of <year>1973</year>, s. 2. 
2 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>. 
3 Subs. ibid., for" any Part A State".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

affidavit or act, being administered, taken or done by or before him, 
shall be admitted in evidence without proof of the seal or signature 
being the seal or signature of that person, or of the official 
character of that person.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>478429</tid>
<number> 4</number> Punishment for offences under this Act.-
<section><tid>1431415</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever swears  
falsely in any oath or affidavit taken or made in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act shall be punished with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to three years and shall also be liable to fine.

</section>

<section><tid>1332057</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever forges or fraudulently alters the seal or signature 
of any person authorized by or under this Act to administer an oath or 
tenders in evidence, or otherwise uses, any affidavit having any seal 
or signature so forged or counterfeited or fraudulently altered 
knowing the same to be forged, counterfeited or fraudulently altered, 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years and shall also be liable to fine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1330158</tid>
<number>5</number>Trial of offences.- Any offence under this Act may be inquired 
into, dealt with, tried and punished in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> State]] in which the 
person charged with the offence was apprehended or is in custody, in 
the same manner and to the same extent as if the offence had been 
committed within the State where he was apprehended or is in custody.


</article>



<article><tid>1990486</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to prescribe fees.-
<section><tid>478176</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, from  
time to time, prescribe the fees to be levied in respect of any matter 
or thing done by a diplomatic or consular officer in the execution of 
his office.

</section>

<section><tid>1077816</tid>
<number>2</number>All such fees shall be levied, accounted for and applied and 
may be remitted in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>672455</tid>
<number>3</number>A diplomatic or consular officer shall not, save as may be 
provided by any rules made in this behalf, ask for or take any fee or 
reward for or on account of any act or thing, or service done, 
performed or rendered by him in the execution of his office.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1561912</tid>
<number> 7</number> Publication and issue of tables of fees.-
<section><tid>812438</tid>
<number>1</number>Tables of the  
fees which may, for the time being, be levied under the rules shall be 
published in such manner and copies thereof shall be issued 
gratuitously to such persons as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>72570</tid>
<number>2</number>Every consular officer, and every diplomatic officer in any 
foreign country or place where there is no consular officer, shall 
keep exhibited in a conspicuous place in his office a copy of the 
table of fees to be levied under this Act and shall permit the same to 
be inspected by any person interested therein.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>565</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" any Province of India". 
2 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part A 
or Part C State".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>860437</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power to make rules.-
<section><tid>232887</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, by  
notification in the official Gazette,] make rules <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1972010</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may prescribe-

<subsection><tid>1868347</tid>
<number>a</number>the scale of fees leviable under this Act and the manner 
in which such fees shall be levied and collected;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>174398</tid>
<number>b</number>the remuneration, if any, payable to a diplomatic or 
consular officer in the execution of any of the duties 
vested in him by this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1463184</tid>
<number>c</number>the registers to be kept and the returns to be made in 
pursuance of this Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>417836</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which copies of tables of fees may be 
published and distributed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1711043</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the 
expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>566</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
2 For the Diplomatic and Consular Officers (Fees) Rules, <year>1949</year>, see 
G. S. R. O. Vol. IV, p. 475. 
3 Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1973</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>