<act><title>THE TELECOMMUNICATION CONSUMERS EDUCATION AND PROTECTION FUND REGULATIONS, 20071</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> These regulations may be called the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund Regulations, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on their publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-In these regulations, unless the context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> "Act" means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 1997); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> "Authority" means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> "committee" means the committee constituted under regulation 7; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> "consumer" means a consumer of a service provider under the Act and includes a customer and subscriber thereof; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> "Corporation Bank" means the Corporation Bank specified under column 2 of the First Schedule to the Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980); 
 </section><section><number>f</number> "subscriber" means any person or legal entity, who or which subscribes to a service from the licensee; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> "Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund" means the fund established by the Authority under regulation 5; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> all other words and expressions used in these regulations but not defined, and defined in the Act and the rules and other regulations made thereunder, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act or the rules or other regulations, as the case may be. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Excess Amount collected by service providers from the subscribers to be transferred to the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund in certain cases. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Without prejudice to any order or direction of the Appellate Tribunal or any court or other tribunal or any other provision of the Act or any other law for the time being in force, every service provider, who has collected from its subscribers any amount in excess of,- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the rates of telecommunication service determined under any regulation or order or direction made under the Act, in a case where the rates have been determined and notified under sub­-section (2) of section 11 of the Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the rates announced by the service providers, in a case where the rates have been notified as rates under market forbearance under sub-section (2) of section 11 of the Act, 
 which has not been refunded to the concerned subscribers and lying as unclaimed with the service providers, shall,- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> in a case where a direction has been made by the Authority under section 13 or any other provisions of the Act, within a period of thirty days, after being so directed, transfer the excess amount so collected to the credit of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> in case where no direction has been made by the Authority under section 13 or any other provisions of the Act, within a period of thirty days, after expiry of twelve months from the date on which such amount became due for refund (including interest thereon, if any,) or after the expiry of the period of limitation specified under any law for the time being in force for refund of such amount, whichever is later, transfer the excess amount so collected to the credit of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund. 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any amount referred to in sub-clauses (i) and (ii) of sub-regulation (1) (including interest thereon, if any,) which had not been refunded to the concerned subscribers and lying as unclaimed, before the commencement of these regulations, with the service provider, for a period of twelve months, or more, from the date on which such amount became due for refund to the subscribers, or, after expiry of period of limitation specified under any law for the time being in force, whichever is later, shall, within thirty days after such commencement, be transferred to the credit of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund: 
 Provided that such service provider shall not transfer such amount to the credit of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund collected, whether before or after the commencement of these regulations, in excess of the rates referred to in sub-clause (i) or sub-clause (ii) of sub-regulation (1), in respect of which, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a claim has been filed, under the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 (68 of 1986) or before any court or tribunal, by a subscriber; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> an order has been made under the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 or an order has been made by any court or tribunal, and such amount shall be refunded to the subscribers in accordance with the order, made under that Act, or, of the court or tribunal, as the case may be. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The service provider shall, while making any transfer of the amount under sub-regulation (1) or sub-regulation (2), 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> keep records of all such particulars relevant and as may be considered necessary by it for transfer of such money in respect of all sums included in such transfer; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> furnish to the Authority, within fifteen days of transfer of such amount, a statement indicating therein the nature of all sums included in such transfer and such other details as may be relevant for transfer of such amount. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Procedure for depositing the excess amount collected by service providers from the subscribers in the Consumers Education and Protection Fund. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Any amount required to be transferred, under these regulations, by the service providers to the credit of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund shall be remitted into the branches of the Corporation Bank designated for the purpose by the said bank, within a period of thirty days of such amount becoming due to be credited to the Fund. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The amount, referred to in sub-regulation (1), shall be tendered by the service providers in the designated branches of the Corporation Bank along with challan in triplicate mentioning therein the head as "Telecommunication Consumer Education and Protection Fund", and the Corporation Bank shall return two copies duly stamped to the service providers as token of having received the amount referred to in sub-regulation (1). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The service provider shall,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> fill in the full description and the nature of the amount tendered and its Head of Account in the challan referred to in sub-regulation (2); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> file with the Authority one copy of the challan referred to in sub-regulation (2) evidencing deposit of the amount to the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund.
  
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> There shall be established by the Authority a fund, to be called the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be credited to the corpus of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the amount referred to in sub-regulations (1) and (2) of regulation 3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any income, by way of interest, on the amount referred to in clause (a), or, from investment of such amount. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The custody, control and management of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund shall be vested in the Authority. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> All the amounts referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of sub-regulation (2) credited to the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund shall be kept in separate accounts in the Corporation Bank. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Utilisation of the Telecommunication Consumers Education </title><title>and Protection Fund. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> All expenditure of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund shall be met out of the incomes referred to in clause (b) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 5. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The amount available by way of income referred to in clause (b) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 5, shall be utilised on the recommendation of the committee after obtaining the approval of the Authority, on the expenditure for the following purposes only, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> to undertake programmes to educate the consumers of the Telecommunication services about various measures taken by the Central Government or the Authority for protecting the interests of consumers of telecommunication services; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> to conduct studies and market research projects, either directly or through specialized agencies or institutions on matters relating to protection of the interests of consumers of telecommunication services; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> to organize seminars, symposia and workshops on the subject of consumer welfare and consumer education in the field of telecommunication: 
</subsection>
 Provided that the expenditure during the initial eighteen months beginning from the date of commencement of these regulations may be incurred out of the amount referred to in clause (a) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 5 for the purposes specified in this sub-regulation and in accordance with the provisions of these regulations: 
 Provided further that the expenditure referred to in the first proviso shall in no case exceed five per cent. of the amount referred to in clause (a) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 5 or rupees fifty lakh, whichever is less: 
 Provided also that no such expenditure shall be incurred out of the amount referred to in clause (a) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 5 after the expiry of the period of eighteen months referred to in the first proviso. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The accounts referred to in sub-regulation (4) of regulation 5 shall be operated, jointly by the presiding member and the member referred to in clause (e) of regulation 8. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Constitution of Committee. </title>-There shall be constituted a committee for,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> making recommendations to the Authority for utilisation of the amount for purposes referred to in clauses (a) to (c) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 6; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the utilisation of the amount referred to in sub-regulation (2) of regulation 6 with the approval of Authority; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> other purposes specified under these regulations. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Term of Office of the Committee. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The term of office of every member in the committee, other than those referred to in clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number>, (e), (f), (g) and (h) of regulation 8, shall be one year but such member shall be eligible for re-nomination by the Chairperson of the Authority, the Cellular Operators Association of India, the Association of the Unified Access Service Provider and other associations, as the case may be. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any vacancy arising on account of resignation, retirement, death of a member or for any other reason, shall be filled by the Authority or the respective association, as the case may be, for the remaining period of the term of such member. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Functions of the Committee. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The committee shall prepare annual budget estimates of the income referred to in clause (b) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 5 and the budget estimates of expenditure for utilisation of the amount referred to in regulation 6 along with the details of the programme, studies and market research projects, seminars, symposia and workshops and submit the same two months before beginning of each financial year for approval of the Authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The committee shall incur such expenditure on any of the purposes mentioned in clauses (a) to (c) of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 6 which has been included in the budget estimates referred to in sub-regulation (1) and sanctioned under sub-regulation (4) by the Authority. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every expenditure referred to in sub-regulation (2) shall be incurred after having passed a resolution for incurring such expenditure in the meeting of the committee. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every resolution referred to in sub-regulation (3) shall, mention the maximum amount of expenditure to be incurred and the purpose for such expenditure, and, such resolutions shall be submitted before the Authority for sanctioning of such expenditure. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> A copy of the summary of the programmes referred to in clause (a), studies and market research projects referred to in clause (b) and seminars, symposia and workshops referred to in clause (c), of sub-regulation (2) of regulation 6, shall be provided to the Authority within thirty days of the conclusion of the programmes, market research projects and seminars, symposia and workshops, as the case may be. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Meetings and Quorum. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The meetings of the Committee shall be held at Delhi . 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notice of not less than fifteen days in respect of a meeting of the committee shall be given to every member of the committee: 
 Provided that when the presiding member of the committee calls for a meeting for consideration of any matter which in his opinion is urgent, a notice shorter than fifteen days but not less than three days shall be deemed to be sufficient notice for purpose of this regulation. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The presiding member of the committee shall preside over the meeting of the committee and in his absence, the convener of the committee shall preside over the said meeting and shall have all the powers of the presiding member of the committee at such meeting. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> No business shall be transacted at a meeting unless majority of the members are present of which at least one member shall be a representative of a consumer organization referred to in clause (b) of regulation 8. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Every issue considered at a meeting of the committee shall be decided by a majority of votes of members present and voting and in the event of equality of votes on any issue or resolution, the presiding member of the committee shall, in addition, have a casting vote. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> No act or proceeding of the committee shall be invalid merely by reason of- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the committee; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any defect in the appointment of a person acting as member or convener of the committee; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any irregularity in the procedure of the committee not affecting the merits of the case.
  
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Minutes of the meeting. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The minutes of every meeting of the committee shall be kept by the convener member of the committee. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The minutes of all proceedings of every meeting of the committee shall be kept by making at the conclusion of every such meeting, the entries thereof in books kept for that purpose with their pages consecutively numbered and each page of every such book shall be initialled or signed and the last page of the record of proceedings of each meeting in such books shall be dated and signed. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The minutes of each meeting of the committee shall contain a fair and correct summary of the proceedings thereof. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> All the decisions of the committee shall be authenticated by the signature of the convener of the committee. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The minutes of each meeting of the committee constituted under regulation 7 shall be placed before the Authority within a period of fifteen days from the date of such meeting. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Expenses of the Committee. </title>-The expenses (including traveling allowance and all other allowances) of the members of the committee for attending the meetings of the committee shall be borne by- 
 
 <section><title></title><number>a</number> the Authority, in respect of the two representatives nominated by the chairperson of the Authority under clause (b) of regulation 8 from amongst such voluntary consumer organizations registered with the Authority; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the Cellular Operators Association of India, the Association of Unified Telecom Service Providers of India and such other association of the service providers in respect of members nominated by them under clauses (c) and (d) of regulation 8. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Maintenance of accounts. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The committee shall maintain proper and separate accounts and other relevant records in relation to the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund giving therein the details of all receipts in, and, expenditure from, such Fund and other relevant particulars. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The accounts referred to in sub-regulation (1) shall be prepared and got audited before the expiry of six months from the end of each financial year. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The committee shall submit to the Authority the accounts referred to in sub-regulation (1) duly audited under regulation 15 and signed by all the members of the committee. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Audit of Accounts and their publication. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The accounts of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund shall be audited by auditors who may be appointed by the Authority for the term of one year and such auditors shall be eligible for re-appointment. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall be eligible to be appointed as an auditor under sub-regulation (1) unless he is a chartered accountant as defined in clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The accounts of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund shall, after the completion of the audit under sub-regulation (1) and submission thereof to the Authority under sub-regulation (3) of regulation 14, be published on the website of the Authority for information of the general public. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Payment of money for making refund to subscribers. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Any person, becoming entitled to refund of any amount as referred to in regulation 3 in pursuance of an order made by a Consumer Forum under the Consumer Protection Act, 1986 (68 of 1986) or by any court or tribunal, subsequent to the transfer of such amount to the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund shall be paid such amount by the concerned service provider in accordance with the order made by the Consumer Forum or the court or tribunal, as the case may be, and such service provider may apply to the Authority for reimbursement of such amount. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The reimbursement of the amount referred to in sub-regulation (1) shall, on the recommendation of the committee, be made to the service provider after the approval of the Authority. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Power of Authority to issue directions for utilisation of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Without prejudice to any of the provisions of the Act, or any other regulations made under the Act or directions issued thereunder, the Authority may, from time to time, issue to the committee such directions as it may think necessary to protect the interests of consumers of the telecom sector. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions, the committee shall in the performance of its functions under regulation 10, be bound by such directions on questions of policy in respect of matters for utilisation of the Telecommunication Consumers Education and Protection Fund as the Authority may give to it from time to time and the committee shall comply with such directions. 


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>