<act><tid>1537352</tid>
<title>THE INDUSTRIAL FINANCE CORPORATION (TRANSFER OF UNDERTAKING  
  AND REPEAL) ACT <year>1993</year></title>

NO. 23 OF <year>1993</year> 
[ 2nd April, <year>1991</year>.]
An Act to provide for the transfer and vesting of the under- 
taking of the Industrial Finance Corporation of India to and in the 
Company to be formed and registered as a Company under the Companies 
Act, <year>1956</year>, and for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto 
and also to repeal the Industrial Finance Corporation Act, <year>1948</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the Re- 
public of India as follows:-




<article><tid>449905</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1522081</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Industrial Finance Corporation (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) 
Act, <year>1993</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1013052</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come inot force on the 1st day of 
October, <year>1992</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>669556</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>133288</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint under section 3:

</section>

<section><tid>982394</tid>
<number>b</number>" Company" means the Industrial Finance Corporation of 
India Limited to be formed and registered under the COmpanies 
Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1869662</tid>
<number>c</number>" Corporation" means the Industrial Finance Corporation of 
India established under sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Industrial 
Finance Corporation Act, <year>1948</year> (15 of <year>1984</year>).


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1755496</tid>
<number>3</number>Undertaking of the Corporation to vest in the company. On such 
date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint, there shall be transferred to, and vest in, the Com- 
pany, the undertaking of the Corporation.

</article>



<article><tid>1565096</tid>
<number> 4</number> General effect of vesting of undertaking in the Company.
<section><tid>1652191</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every shareholder of the Corporation immediately before the appointed 
day shall be deemed to be registered on and from the appointed day as 
a shareholder of the Company to the extent of the face value of the 
shares held by such shareholder.

</section>

<section><tid>81195</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertaking of the Corporation which is transferred to 
and which vests in the Company under section 3 shall be deemed to 
include all business, assets, rights, powers, authorities and 
privileges and all properties, movable and immovable, real and 
personal, corporeal and incorporeal, in possession or reservation, 
present or Contingent of whatever nature and wheresoever situate 
including lands, buildings, vehicles, cash balances, deposits, foreign 
currencies, disclosed and undisclosed reserves, reserve fund, special 
reserve fund, benevolent reserve fund, any other fund, stocks, invest- 
ments, shares, bonds, debentures, security, management of any 
industrial concern, loans, advances and guarantees given to industrial 
concerns, tenancies, leases and book debts and all other rights and 
interests arising out of such property as were immediately before the 
appointed day in the ownership, possession or power of the Corporation 
in relation to its undertaking, within or without India, all books of 
accounts, registers, records and documents relating thereto and shall 
also be deemed to include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations 
of whatever kind within or without India then subsisting of the 
Corporation in relation to its undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>901441</tid>
<number>3</number>All contracts, deeds. bonds. guarantees, powers of attorney, 
other instruments and working arrangements subsisting immediately 
before the appointed day and affecting the Corporation shall cease to 
have effect or to be enforceable against the Corporation and shall be 
of as full force and effect against or in favour of the Company in 
which the undertaking of the Corporation has vested by virtue of this 
Act and enforceable as fully and effectually as if instead of the 
Corporation. the Company had been named therein or had been a party 
thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>68369</tid>
<number>4</number>Any proceeding or cause of action pending or existing 
immediately before the appointed day by or against the Corporation in 
relation to its undertaking may, as from the appointed day, be 
continued and enforced by or against the Company in which the 
undertaking of the Corporation has vested by virtue of this Act as it 
might have been enforced by or against the Corporation if this Act bad 
not been enacted and shall cease to be enforceable by or against the 
Corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>952252</tid>
<number>5</number>Concession, etc., to be deemed to have been granted to the 
Company. With effect from the appointed day, all fiscal and other 
concessions, licences, benefits, privileges and exemptions granted to 
the Corporation in connection with the affairs and business of the 
Corporation under any law for the time being in force shall be deemed 
to have been granted to the Company.

</article>



<article><tid>1925068</tid>
<number> 6</number> Tax exemption or benefit to continue to have effect.
<section><tid>1353329</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
any exemption from, or any assessment with respect to, any tax has 
been granted or made or any benefit by way of set off or carry forward 
of any unabsorbed depreciation or investment allowance or other 
allowance or loss has been extended or is available to the Corporation 
under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), such exemption, assessment 
or benefit shall continue to have effect in relation to the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>687476</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any payment made by the Corporation is exempt from de- 
duction of tax at source under any provision of the Income- tax Act, 
 <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), such exemption will continue to be available as if 
the provisions of the said Act made applicable to the Corporation were 
operative in relation to the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1328196</tid>
<number>3</number>The transfer and vesting of the undertaking or any part 
thereof in terms of section 3 shall not be construed as a transfer 
within the meaning of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>) for the 
purposes of capital gains.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1063317</tid>
<number>7</number>Guarantee to be operative. Any guarantee given for or in favour 
of the Corporation with respect to any loan, lease finance or other 
assistance shall continue to be operative in relation to the Company.

</article>



<article><tid>1485249</tid>
<number> 8</number> Provisions in respect of officers and other employees of 
Corporation.
<section><tid>368386</tid>
<number>1</number>Every officer or other employee of the Corporation  
 (except a Director of the Board, Chairman or Managing Director) 
serving in the employment immediately before the appointed day shall, 
in so far as such officer or other employee is employed in connection 
with the undertaking which has vested in the Company by virtue of this 
Act, become, as from the appointed day, an officer or, as the case may 
be, other employee of the Company and shall hold his office or service 
therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration, upon the same 
terms and conditions, with the same obligations and with the same 
rights and privileges as to leave, leave fare concession, welfare 
scheme, medical benefit scheme, insurance, provident fund, other 
funds, retirement, voluntary retirement, gratuity and other benefits 
as he would have held under the Corporation if its undertaking had 
not, vested in the Company and shall continue to do so as an officer 
or, as the case may be, other employee of the Company or until the 
expiry of a period of six months from the appointed day if such 
officer or other employee opts not to continue to be the officer or 
other employee of the Company within such period.

</section>

<section><tid>1925525</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an officer or other employee of the Corporation opts 
under sub- section (1) not to be in employment or service of the 
Company, such officer or other employee shall be deemed to have 
resigned.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>603532</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time 
being in force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other 
employee of the Corporation to the Company shall not entitle such 
officer or other employee to any compensation under this Act or under 
any other law for the time being in force and no such claim shall be 
entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1851320</tid>
<number>4</number>The officers and other employees who have retired before the 
appointed day from the service of the Corporation and are entitled to 
any benefits, rights or privileges shall be entitled to receive the 
same benefits, rights or privileges from the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1346625</tid>
<number>5</number>The trusts of the provident fund or the gratuity fund of the 
Corporation and any other bodies created for the welfare of officers 
or employees would continue to discharge their functions in the 
Company as was being done hitherto in the Corporation and any tax 
exemption granted to the provident fund or the gratuity fund would 
continue to be applied to the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>1696754</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or in any other law for the time being 
in force or in the regulations of the Corporation, no Director of the 
Board, Chairman, Managing Director or any other person entitled to 
manage the whole or substantial part of the business and affairs of 
the Corporation shall be entitled to any compensation against the 
Corporation or the Company for the loss of office or for the premature 
termination of any contract of management entered into by him with the 
Corporation.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1654600</tid>
<number>9</number>Act 18 of <year>1891</year> to 
apply to the books of the Company. TheCompany shall be deemed to be a bank 
for the purposes of the Bankers' Books Ev

</article>



<article><tid>616322</tid>
<number>10</number>Shares, bonds and debentures to be deemed to be approved 
securities. Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for 
the time being in force. the shares, bonds and debentures of the 
Company shall be deemed to be approved securities for the purposes of 
the Indian Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2 of <year>1982</year>), the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4  
  of <year>1938</year>) and the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1803538</tid>
<number> 11</number> Repeal and saving of Act 15 of <year>1948</year>.
<section><tid>755295</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day,  
the Industrial Finance Corporation Act, <year>1948</year> shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1008129</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Industrial Finance 
Corporation Act, <year>1948</year> (15 of <year>1948</year>), the Company shall, so far as 
may be, comply with the provisions of sections 33, 34, 34A, 35 and 43 
of the Act so repealed for any of the purposes related to the annual 
accounts of the Corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1307751</tid>
<number> 12</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>787516</tid>
<number>1</number>The Industrial Finance Corporation  
 (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Ordinance, <year>1993</year> (Ord. 5 of <year>1993</year>) 
is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>121944</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Industrial Finance 
Corporation (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Ordinance, <year>1993</year>, 
 (Ord. 5 of <year>1993</year>), anything done or any action taken under the said 
Ordinance, shall' be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>