<act><tid>1542988</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN RAILWAY BOARD ACT, <year>1905</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1905</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 22nd March, <year>1905</year>.] W

An Act to provide for investing the Railway Board with certain powers 
or functions under the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year>.





<article><tid>556582</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and construction.
<section><tid>993849</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Indian Railway Board Act, <year>1905</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>296090</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be read with, and taken as part of, the Indian 
Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>.).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1261899</tid>
<number> 2</number> Investment of Railway Board with powers under Indian Railways 
Act, <year>1890</year>. The Central Government may, by notification <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in the 
Official Gazette, invest the Railway Board, either absolutely or 
subject to conditions,--
<section><tid>61210</tid>
<number>a</number>with all or any of the powers or functions of the 
Central Government under the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> 
 (9 of <year>1890</year>), with respect to all or any railways, and

</section>

<section><tid>399070</tid>
<number>b</number>with the power of the officer referred to in section 47 
of the said Act to make general rules for railways 
administered by the Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1411354</tid>
<number>3</number>Mode of signifying communications from the Railway Board. Any 
notice, determination, direction, requisition, appointment, expression 
of opinion, approval or sanction, to be given or signified on the part 
of the Railway Board, for any of the purposes of, or in relation to, 
any powers or functions with which it may be invested by notification 
under section 2, shall be sufficient and binding if in writing signed 
by the Secretary to the Railway Board, or by any other person 
authorized by the said Railway Board to act in its behalf in respect 
of the matters to which such authorization may relate; and the said 
Railway Board shall not in any case be bound in respect of any of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Berar by the Berar by the Berar 
Laws Act, <year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>) and has been declared to be in force in the 
Sonthal Parganas by notification under s. 3 (3)  (a) of the Sonthal 
Parganas Settlement Regulation (3 of <year>1872</year>), see Calcutta Gazette, 
<year>1906</year>, Pt. I, p. 334, and in the Angul District by the Angul Laws 
Regulation, <year>1936</year> (5 of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and Sch.

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch.

Extended to and brought into force in dara and nagar Haveli (w. e. f.  
  1- 7- 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>For notifications see Gazette of India, <year>1905</year>, Pt. I. p. 232; 
<year>1906</year>, Pt. I, p. 927, and <year>1908</year>, Pt. I, p. 169.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

matters aforesaid unless by some writing signed in manner aforesaid.



</article>



<article><tid>1146781</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[ Cessation of Railway Board on establishment of Federal 
Railway Authority.] Rep. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>123</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>