<act> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 20061
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Credit Information Companies Rules, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
 
<number>a</number>  “access” with its grammatical variations 
and cognate variations means gaining entry into, instructing or communicating 
with logical, arithmetical or memory function resources of a computer, computer 
system or computer network including approach or communication or making use of 
data, information or credit information through any means, physical or 
otherwise.
 </subsection><subsection>
 
<number>b</number>  “Act” means the Credit Information 
Companies (Regulation) Act, 2005 (30 of 2005);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  “agent” means a person duly 
authorised by a company or a credit information company, as the case may be, to 
present an appeal or a written reply on its behalf, before the appellate 
authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  “appeal” means an appeal filed 
under sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  “appellant” means an applicant 
company or a credit information company, as the case may be, making an appeal to 
the appellate authority under sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
 
<number>f</number>  “appellate authority” means the Central 
Government, or such other authority or tribunal as may be designated 
subsequently by the Central Government as per sub-section (1) of section 7 of 
the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  “data” in relation to a credit 
institution, or a credit information company, or a specified user means such 
facts which are collected by or furnished to them, in respect of a borrower or a 
client, as the case may be, and form part of the credit information relating to 
such borrower or client, which is maintained, disseminated and used by them in 
accordance with the provisions of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  “form” means the form appended to 
the Schedule to these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  “information” means, 
collectively all data, and credit information or any part thereof, collected by 
or furnished to, a credit institution, or a credit information company, or a 
specified user, as the case may be, in accordance with the provisions of the 
Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  “rules” means the rules made 
under the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions 
used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act or the Information 
Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000), shall have the same meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the said Acts.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Appellate Authority.—The 
Central Government, or such other Authority or Tribunal as may be designated 
subsequently by the Central Government as per sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 7 of 
the Act shall be the Appellate Authority for the purpose of sub-section (1) of 
section 7 of the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Form and procedure of 
appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
appeal as per the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Act, shall 
be presented in Form 1 in duplicate by an aggrieved credit information company, 
or its agent or by a duly authorised legal practitioner, before the appellate 
authority or shall be sent by registered post addressed to such authority with 
acknowledgement duly addressed to the appellate authority or any other officer 
authorised in writing by the appellate authority to receive the same.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An appeal sent by post 
under sub-rule (1) shall be deemed to have been presented to the appellate 
authority on the day on which it is received in the office of the appellate 
authority.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Sitting of appellate 
authority.—The 
appellate authority shall hold its sitting either at a place where its office is 
situated or at such other place as it may deem fit.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Language of appellate 
authority.—The 
proceedings of the appellate authority shall be conducted in English or Hindi 
and the appeal, application, or any other document submitted before the 
appellate authority, shall be in such language and in case any of such documents 
is in a different language, the transaction thereof in English or Hindi shall be 
required to be produced.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Appeal to be in 
writing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every appeal, application, reply, representation or any other document filed 
before the appellate authority shall be typewritten, cyclostyled or printed 
neatly and legibly on one side of the good quality paper in double space and 
separate sheets consecutively numbered shall be stitched together and filed in 
the manner as provided in sub-rule (2).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The appeal under 
sub-rule (1) shall be presented in duplicate duly signed by the agent of the 
aggrieved company or the credit information company, as the case may be.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Contents of memorandum 
of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every memorandum of appeal filed under rule 4 shall set forth concisely under 
distinct heads, the grounds of such appeal without any argument or narrative and 
such grounds shall be numbered consecutively.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For seeking an interim 
order or direction, appropriate submissions and relief prayed for in respect 
thereof may be included in the memorandum of appeal and it shall not be 
necessary to present separate application or memorandum in this behalf.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Credit Information Companies 
Rules, 2006
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Documents to accompany 
memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every memorandum of appeal shall be accompanied with copies of the order against 
which the appeal is filed and the documents relied upon by the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the appellant is 
represented by an agent, or any of its officers before the appellate authority, 
the document authorising him to act in such capacity shall also be appended to 
the memorandum of appeal.
 
 
</section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>10</number> Presentation and scrutiny of 
memorandum of appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> If, on scrutiny of the 
appeal received, it is found to be in order, the same shall be duly registered 
by the secretariat of the appellate authority and given a serial 
number.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If on scrutiny, an appeal is 
found to be defective and the defect is such that it could be allowed to be 
rectified, the appellate authority may grant time not exceeding thirty days for 
such rectification and direct its secretariat to communicate to the appellant 
the defect and the time granted for its rectification.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the appellant fails to 
rectify the defect within the time as allowed for the purpose as per sub-rule 
(2), the secretariat shall submit the report of such failure of the appellant 
for consideration of the appellate authority, who may by an order and for 
reasons to be recorded in writing, decline to register the appeal and direct the 
secretariat to communicate such order to the appellant within seven days from 
the date of the order.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the appellant submits any 
representation within a period of fifteen days from the date of receipt of 
communication as per sub-rule (3), with sufficient explanation in respect of its 
failure to rectify the defect within the time granted for the purpose as per 
sub-rule (2), the secretariat shall submit such representation for consideration 
of the appellate authority.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The appellate authority may, 
subject to its satisfaction about the sufficiency of the explanation furnished 
as per sub-rule (4), by an order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
review the order passed under sub-rule (3) and grant further time not exceeding 
fifteen days for rectification of the defect, or may reject the representation 
in case such explanation is not found to be satisfactory, and any such order 
passed by the appellate authority shall be final.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>11</number> Notice of appeal to the 
respondent.—A 
copy of the memorandum of appeal along with the copy of the documents submitted 
therewith, shall be served by the secretariat of the appellate authority on the 
respondent as soon as the appeal is registered as per sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 10, 
by hand delivery, or by registered post or speed post.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>12</number> Filing of reply to the 
appeal and other documents.—
<section><number>1</number> The respondent may file 
reply in duplicate to the appeal along with documents, in the secretariat of the 
appellate authority, within one month of the service of the notice on him of the 
filing of the memorandum of appeal.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The respondent shall also 
endorse one copy of the reply to the appeal along with documents filed as per 
sub-rule (1) to the appellant.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The appellate authority may, 
in its discretion on an application by the respondent, allow the filing of the 
reply after the expiry of period referred to in sub-rule (1).
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>13</number> Date of hearing to be 
communicated.—
<section><number>1</number> The appellate authority 
shall fix the date and place of hearing of the appeal and direct its secretariat 
to communicate the same to the appellant and the respondent in the manner as the 
appellate authority may by general or special order direct.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appellate authority may 
subject to its satisfaction adjourn the hearing of the appeal, if so requested 
by any of the parties to the appeal.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>14</number> Hearing of 
appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> On 
the date fixed for hearing or the next date in case of adjournment, the 
appellant and the respondent shall be given due opportunity for putting forth 
their submissions in support of their plea.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appellate authority may 
allow the parties to submit their written arguments in addition to their oral 
arguments.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In case of non-appearance of 
the appellant on the date fixed for hearing or the next date in case of 
adjournment, the appellate authority may, in its discretion adjourn the hearing 
or may dispose of the appeal on merits.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where an appeal has been 
disposed of as per sub-rule (3) and the appellant appears afterwards and 
furnishes satisfactory explanation for non-appearance on the date when the 
appeal was decided ex parte, the appellate authority may subject to its 
satisfaction about the explanation, set aside the ex parte order and 
restore the appeal and decide the same on merits after hearing the 
parties.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>15</number> Order to be signed and 
dated.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every order of the appellate authority shall be in writing and shall be signed 
and dated by the appellate authority passing the order.
 </section><section><number>2</number> During the pendency of the 
appeal, the appellate authority shall have powers to pass such interim order as 
it may deem fit including one of an injunction, subject to reasons to be 
recorded in writing, which it considers necessary in the interest of 
justice.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>16</number> Communication of 
order.—Every 
order passed on an appeal shall be communicated to the appellant and to the 
respondent concerned either in person or by registered post within a period of 
seven days from the date of the order.
  </article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>17</number> Orders and directions in 
certain cases.—The appellate authority may 
make such orders or give such directions, as may be necessary or expedient to 
give effect to its orders or to prevent abuse of its process.
  </article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>18</number> Steps for security and 
safeguards to be taken by credit institutions.—Every credit institution, in 
existence in India on the commencement of these rules, before the expiry of 
three months from such commencement, and every other credit institution before 
the expiry of three months of commencing their business in India, shall 
formulate appropriate policy and procedure, duly approved by its Board of 
Directors, specifying therein the steps and security safeguards, to be adopted 
in their operations relating to—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
collection, processing and collating of data, information and credit information 
by them relating to their borrower or client;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
steps to be taken for ensuring security and protection of data, information, and 
credit information maintained by them;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  
appropriate and necessary steps for maintaining an accurate, complete and 
updated data, information and credit information, in respect of their borrower 
or client, and to ensure the accuracy and completeness thereof while furnishing 
the same to a credit information company or making disclosure thereof to anyone 
else in accordance with the provisions of the Act; and
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  
transmitting data, information and credit information through secure 
medium.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>19</number> Collection of data and 
maintaining credit information.—
<section><number>1</number> A credit institution 
shall—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  
collect all such relevant data in respect of its borrower or client, as it may 
deem necessary and appropriate for maintaining an accurate and complete data, 
information and credit information in respect of such borrower or client; 
and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  use 
such data, information and credit information subject to the provisions of the 
Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
generality of the policy and procedure to be adopted as per rule 18 and sub-rule 
(1) with respect to collection and maintaining of data, information and credit 
information in relation to its borrower and client, a credit institution shall 
also collect all relevant and authentic available data and information as per 
Form II for preparing, maintaining credit information in relation to them and 
for establishing their identity.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>20</number> Accuracy of data provided by 
a credit institution.—
<section><number>1</number> Every credit institution 
before furnishing data or an information or credit information to a credit 
information company or making disclosure thereof to anyone else in accordance 
with the provisions of the Act shall ensure that the credit information is 
accurate and complete with reference to the date on which such information is 
furnished or disclosed and adopt appropriate procedure in this behalf with the 
approval of their Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If, for any reason beyond 
control, it is not possible for any credit institution to furnish credit 
information as per sub-rule (1), such credit institution while furnishing the 
credit information to a credit information company or making disclosure thereof 
to anyone else, shall make a remark with reference to the date up to which the 
accuracy and completeness of the credit information has been verified and found 
to be correct.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to the provisions of 
sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 21 of the Act, in respect of alteration and 
updating of credit information on request of a borrower in accordance with the 
said provisions, if a credit institution after furnishing the data or 
information or credit information, to a credit information company or making 
disclosure thereof to anyone else, in accordance with the Act, discovers of its 
own, or is informed about, any inaccuracy, error or discrepancy therein the 
credit institution shall—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  
latest by third day, send the intimation to the credit information company or 
the individual, as the case may be, of such inaccuracy, error or 
discrepancy;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  take 
immediate steps to correct such inaccuracy, error or discrepancy; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the 
credit institution shall forward the corrected particulars of the data or 
information or credit information, as the case may be, to the credit information 
company or the individual, as the case may be, within period of twenty-one days 
from the date when the credit institution had discovered such inaccuracy, error 
or discrepancy or information in respect thereof was given to it.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> If, for any reason beyond 
its control, it is not possible for a credit institution to take immediate steps 
as per sub-rule (3), such credit institution shall inform the credit information 
company or the individual, as the case may be, of the steps taken by it for 
correction of the inaccuracy, error or discrepancy and also the reasons for its 
inability to comply with the provisions of sub-rule (3) within the time 
stipulated therein.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any credit institution 
failing to take steps as per this rule, without any sufficient reason shall be 
liable for contravention of the provisions of the Act.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>21</number> Disclosure of disputed data 
by a credit institution.—If, in the opinion of a credit 
institution, correction of any inaccuracy, error or discrepancy as referred to 
in rule 20, is likely to take further time on account of any dispute raised by a 
borrower in respect thereof, with the credit institution or before a court of 
law, or any forum, or tribunal or any other authority, in such cases the credit 
institution shall adopt the following course of action, namely:—
 <section>
<number>a</number>  if the disputed data has 
not been furnished, in such event while furnishing such data to a credit 
information company or making disclosure thereof to anyone else, in accordance 
with the Act, the credit institution shall include an appropriate remark to 
reflect the nature of the inaccuracy, error or discrepancy found therein and the 
pendency of the dispute in respect thereof and in any subsequent disclosure of 
such disputed data the credit institution shall also disclose such remark; 
or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  in 
case such credit information has already been furnished to a credit information 
company or disclosed to anyone else, the credit institution shall inform the 
credit information company or the individual, as the case may be, to include the 
remark about such inaccuracy, error or discrepancy and the pending dispute in 
respect thereof, against such data, information or credit information received 
by them from the credit institution; and
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  the 
entries in books of the concerned credit institution shall be taken into account 
for the purposes of credit information relating to such borrower as provided 
under the provisions of second proviso to sub-section (3) of section 21 of the 
Act.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>22</number> Updating of the credit 
information by credit institution.—Without prejudice to the 
provisions of rule 21, if there is any change in the data, information or credit 
information, already furnished to a credit information company due to change in 
the liability of the borrower or his guarantor, on account of write off in full 
or in part of the amount of outstanding dues of the credit institution or the 
repayment thereof by the borrower or his guarantor, or release of the guarantor, 
or any scheme of arrangement entered into between the credit institution and the 
borrower, or the final settlement of the amount payable by the borrower pursuant 
to any scheme of arrangement with the credit institution, as the case may be, or 
on account of any such other reason, the credit institution shall,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
continue to update such data, information or credit information promptly or in 
any event, by the end of each reporting period not exceeding thirty days until 
the termination of the respective account relating to such credit information; 
and
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
furnish an updated credit information to the credit information company at the 
earliest in this behalf.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>23</number> Data security and system 
integrity safeguards.—Every credit institution shall 
adopt such procedure and measures in relation to their daily operations as may 
be necessary to safeguard and protect the data, information and the credit 
information maintained by them, against any unauthorised access to or misuse of 
the same including the following safeguards, namely:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
adopting the minimum standards for physical and operational security including 
site design, fire protection, environmental protection;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
keeping the round the clock physical security;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  issuance of instructions 
for removing, labelling and securing the removable electronic storage media at 
the end of the session or working day;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  
providing physical access to the critical systems to be on dual control 
basis;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  
making comprehensive succession plan for the key personnel so as to ensure that 
non-availability of a person does not disrupt the system;
 </section><section>        
<number>f</number>  keeping of paper based records, documentation and backup data 
containing all confidential information in secured and locked containers or 
filing system, separately from all other records;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>  adopting adequate 
procedure to ensure that the records could be accessed only by authorized 
persons on need to know basis;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>  providing details of 
creation of firewalls and stress testing of systems through ethical hacking to 
evaluate and ensure its robustness;
 </section><section>        
<number>i</number>  protecting systems against obsolescence;
 </section><section>        
<number>j</number>  adopting procedure for change of software and hardware;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>  providing for disaster 
recovery and management plan; and
 </section><section>        
<number>l</number>  taking necessary steps while handing over systems for maintenance to 
prevent unauthorised access or loss of data, information and credit information 
maintained by them.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>24</number> Formulation and adoption of 
the procedure by credit information companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Every credit information 
company, in existence on the commencement of these rules within three months of 
the commencement of these rules, and every credit information company to whom a 
certificate of registration has been granted, after the commencement of these 
rules within three months of such grant, shall take such requisite steps, as it 
may deem necessary, in relation to their operations and accordingly formulate 
policy and procedure duly approved by their Board of Directors and adopt the 
same with respect to the following operations, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  
collection, processing and collating of data, information and credit information 
relating to their borrower, or client, obtained and received by them from a 
member credit institution or credit information company, as the case may 
be;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  
steps to be taken for ensuring security and protection of such data, information 
and the credit information maintained by them;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  
appropriate and necessary steps for maintaining an accurate, complete and 
updated data, information and credit information, in respect of their borrower, 
or client, and to ensure the accuracy and completeness thereof while furnishing 
the same to a specified user or making disclosure thereof to anyone else, in 
accordance with the provisions of the Act; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> transmitting 
data, information and credit information through secured medium. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
generality of the policy as formulated and procedure as adopted under sub-rule 
(1), every credit information company shall include in its such policy and 
procedure, the following, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  it 
would have tested and documented internal system for evidencing robust matching 
levels which may in case of need be used also to provide requisite evidence and 
necessary examples to the Reserve Bank;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the 
procedure and parameters for verifying and providing certificate to the effect 
that the entire data, information and credit information, obtained and received 
by them, from a member credit institution, a credit information company, 
or from any other permissible source, as the case may be, in respect of their 
borrower, or client, has been collated without any distortion thereof and such 
data, information and credit information maintained by them is accurate, updated 
and complete with reference to the date of such certification by the credit 
institution, or the credit information company, by whom such data, information 
and credit information has been provided;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the 
procedure for making a notation in such data, information and credit information 
obtained and received by them from a member credit institution, or from any 
other permissible source, as the case may be and maintained by them in respect 
of their borrower or client which is not updated on the date of carrying out 
necessary verification and certification as per clause (b) with reference 
to the date up to which the same was certified by credit institution or the 
credit information company to be accurate, updated and complete.
  </subsection></section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>25</number> Accuracy of data provided by 
a credit information company.—
<section><number>1</number> Every credit information 
company shall adopt appropriate procedure with the approval of the Reserve 
Bank—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  for 
verifying the data, information or credit information maintained by them on the 
basis of the information obtained by them from credit institution or credit 
information company, as the case may be; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  to 
ensure, before furnishing data, information or credit information to a specified 
user or making disclosure thereof to anyone else in accordance with the Act, 
that such data, information or credit information maintained by them is 
accurate, complete and updated with reference to the date mentioned therein by 
the respective credit institution or credit information company, as the case may 
be.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If, for any reason beyond 
control, it is not possible for any credit information company to furnish 
complete and updated data, information or credit information, as per sub-rule 
(1), the credit information company shall make a remark with reference to the 
date up to which its accuracy and completeness has been verified and found to be 
correct.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subject to the provisions of 
sub-sections (2) and (3) of section 21 of the Act, in respect of alteration and 
updating of credit information on request of a borrower in accordance with said 
provisions, if a credit information company after furnishing the data, 
information or credit information to a specified user or making disclosure 
thereof to anyone else, in accordance with the Act, discovers of its own, or is 
informed about any inaccuracy, error or discrepancy in respect of the data, 
information or credit information, the credit information company 
shall,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  
latest by seventh day, send the intimation to the specified user or the 
individual, as the case may be, of such inaccuracy, error or 
discrepancy;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  take 
immediate steps to correct such inaccuracy, error or discrepancy; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  
forward the corrected particulars of the data, information or credit information 
to the specified user or the individual, as the case may be, within a period of 
thirty days from the date when the credit information company had discovered or 
was informed of such inaccuracy, error or discrepancy.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> If, for any reason beyond 
control, it is not possible for the credit information company to furnish 
corrected information as per sub-rule (3), the credit information company shall 
inform the specified user or the individual, as the case may be, of the steps 
taken by it at their end for correction of such inaccuracy, error or discrepancy 
and also the reasons for its inability to comply with the provisions of sub-rule 
(3).
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any credit information 
company failing to take steps as per sub-rule (3), without any sufficient 
reasons for its inability to comply with the said provisions, shall be liable 
for contravention of the provisions of the Act.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>26</number> Disclosure of disputed data 
by a credit information company.—If, in the opinion of a credit 
information company, correction of any inaccuracy, error or discrepancy referred 
to in rule 20, is likely to take further time on account of any dispute raised 
by a borrower in respect thereof with the credit institution or before a court 
of law, or any forum, or tribunal or any other authority, in such cases the 
credit information company shall adopt the following course of action, 
namely:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  if 
the disputed data, information or credit information has not been furnished, in 
such event while furnishing such data, information or credit information to a 
specified user or making disclosure thereof to anyone else, in accordance with 
the Act, the credit information company shall include an appropriate remark to 
reflect the nature of the inaccuracy, error or discrepancy found therein and 
pendency of the dispute in respect thereof and in any subsequent disclosure of 
such disputed data, information or credit information, the credit information 
company shall disclose such remark;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  in 
case such data, information or credit information has already been furnished to 
a specified user or disclosed to anyone else, the credit information company 
shall inform the specified user or the individual, as the case may be, to 
include remark of such inaccuracy, error or discrepancy therein and the pending 
dispute in respect thereof; and
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  the 
entries in books of the concerned credit institution shall be taken into account 
for the purposes of credit information relating to such borrower as provided 
under the provisions of second proviso to sub-section (3) of section 21 of the 
Act.
  </section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>27</number> Formulation and adoption of 
the procedure by specified user.—
<section><number>1</number> Every specified user, in 
existence on the commencement of these rules within three months of such 
commencement, and every specified user, coming into existence after the 
commencement of these rules within three months of its becoming member of a 
credit information company, shall take such requisite steps as it may deem 
necessary for ensuring and verifying the accuracy and completeness of data, 
information or credit information received from a credit information company 
before using the same in relation to a borrower, or a client, in relation to 
their operations and to ensure protection thereof from unauthorised access, or 
use and formulate and adopt an appropriate policy and procedure in this behalf 
with the approval of their Board of Directors.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
generality of the policy as formulated and procedure as adopted under sub-rule 
(1), every specified user shall include in such policy and procedure, the 
provisions relating to the following, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the 
level of officers to be authorised to access the data information and credit 
information received from a credit information company;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the 
parameters to be adopted for satisfying itself about the identity of the 
respective borrower, or the client whose credit report is to be taken into 
account by the specified user;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the 
appropriate measures so as to ensure that they do not fail to take note of any 
remark included by a credit information company in respect of any credit 
information; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  
procedure relating to receiving data, information and credit information through 
secured medium.
  </subsection></section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>28</number> Prohibition from 
unauthorised access or use or disclosure.—
<section><number>1</number> Every credit institution, 
credit information company, and specified user, existing before the commencement 
of these rules within three months of such commencement and every credit 
institution, credit information company or specified user coming into existence 
after the commencement of these rules within three months of commencement of 
their business, shall take such steps as they may deem necessary to ensure that 
the data, information and the credit information maintained by them is duly 
protected against any unauthorised access or use and formulate and adopt an 
appropriate policy and procedure in this behalf with the approval of their Board 
of Directors.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
generality of the policy and procedure, as formulated and adopted under sub-rule 
(1), every credit institution, credit information company, and specified user 
shall include such other aspects in such policy and procedure so as 
to,—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  secure the confidentiality of the data, information and credit 
information maintained by them;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>  ensure that access to 
the data, information and credit information maintained by them is permitted 
only to such of their managers or employees or designated officers, who are duly 
authorised for the purpose on a need to know basis;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>  ensure and control, 
access to the data, information and credit information, terminals and networks, 
maintained by them, by means of physical barriers including biometric access 
control and logical barriers by way of passwords and to ensure that the 
passwords used in this behalf are not shared by anyone else than who is 
authorised in this behalf and the passwords are changed frequently on irregular 
intervals;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  
ensure that the best practices in relation to the deletion and disposal of data, 
especially where records or discs are to be disposed of off-site or by external 
contractors are followed;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number>  
ensure that the system adopted for the purpose is sufficiently adequate to 
protect against any unauthorised modification or deletion of the data, 
information or credit information maintained by them;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>  ensure maintenance of 
log made for accessing to data, information or credit information maintained by 
them including—
 <subsubsection>            
<number>a</number>  the data relating to identify of all such persons whosoever had 
accessed or attempted to access the data information or credit information 
maintained by them and the date and time of such access, the identity of the 
borrower whose data or credit information were so accessed; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>b</number>  the provision relating to preservation of the records and entries 
pertaining to such log for minimum period of two years and to ensure that the 
same is available for examination by auditors, or the officials of the Reserve 
Bank authorised in this behalf, as the case may be.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>      <number>vii</number>  ensure 
the maintenance and review of records and entries of log, on a regular and 
frequent basis to detect and investigate any unusual or irregular patterns of 
use of or access to data including creation of the audit trails and verification 
thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>     <number>viii</number>  provide the 
guidelines for the use and access of information systems by external 
contractors; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ix</number>  
protection against pilferage of information while passing through the public and 
private networks.
  </subsection></section></article> 
 The Credit Information Companies Rules, 
2006
  
 <article><number>29</number> Obligation for fidelity and 
secrecy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every credit information company or credit institution or specified user, in 
possession or control of data, information and credit information shall adopt 
all reasonable procedure to ensure that their managers, officers employees are 
obliged to fidelity and secrecy in respect of credit information under their 
control or to which they have access.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every credit information 
company or credit institution or specified user, existing before the 
commencement of these rules shall within three months of such commencement of 
these rules and every credit institution or credit information company or 
specified user within three months of commencement of their business after 
coming into force of the rules shall, formulate the policy and procedure duly 
approved by its Board of Directors specifying therein the steps to be taken by 
them to ensure compliance of the fidelity and secrecy obligation by their 
managers, officers, employees with respect to data, information or credit 
information under their control.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Without prejudice to the 
generality of the policy and procedure as adopted under sub-rule (2), such 
policy and procedure shall also include therein the appropriate provisions 
relating to—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the 
requirement that their employees, authorised personnel, agents, contractors and 
other persons who deal with or have right to access data, information and credit 
information comply with confidentiality obligation and sign convenants with 
them; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the 
requirement that every chairperson, director, auditor, advisor, officer or other 
employee of a credit information company, before entering upon his duties makes 
a declaration in Form III for complying with such fidelity and secrecy 
obligation.
  </subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>