<act><tid>1545750</tid>
<title>DEKKHAN AGRICULTURISTS' RELIEF ACT, <year>1879</year></title>

ACT NO. 17 OF <year>1879</year>
[ 29th October, <year>1879</year>.] Prea

An Act for the relief of Indebted Agriculturists in certain parts of 
the Dekkhan.





<article><tid>1854653</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title, Commencement. This Act may be cited as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, <year>1879</year>: and it shall come into force 
on the first day of November, <year>1879</year>.
Local extent.

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> This section and] sections 11, 56, 60 and 62 extend to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
whole of India except <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the territories which, immediately before the 
 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in Part B States]]. The rest of 
this Act <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> extends only to the districts of Poona, Satara, Sholapur 
and Ahmednagar <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> but may, from time to time, be extended wholly or in 
part by the State Government <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> to any other district or districts 
in the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> territories which, immediately before the 1st November, 
<year>1956</year>, were comprised in the State of Bombay,]] <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> or to any part or 
parts of any other such district or districts].



<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Acts 17 of <year>1879</year>, 23 of <year>1881</year> and 22 of <year>1882</year> may be cited 
collectively as the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Acts, <year>1879</year> to <year>1882</year>- 
- see s. 1 (1) of the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, <year>1882</year> (22 of  
  <year>1882</year>). The Acts of <year>1879</year> to <year>1882</year> and Act 23 of <year>1886</year> may be cited 
collectively as the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Acts, <year>1879</year> to <year>1886</year>- 
- see s. 1 (1) of the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, <year>1886</year> (23 of  
  <year>1886</year>). The Acts of <year>1879</year> to <year>1886</year> and Act 6 of <year>1895</year> may be cited 
collectively as the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Acts, <year>1879</year> to <year>1895</year>- 
- see s. 1 (1) of the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, <year>1895</year> (6 of  
  <year>1895</year>). The Acts of <year>1879</year> to <year>1895</year> and Bom. Act 1 of <year>1902</year> may be cited 
collectively as the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Acts, <year>1876</year> to <year>1902</year>- 
- see s. 1 (1) of the Dekkhan Agriculturists' Relief Act, <year>1902</year> (Bom. 1  
  of <year>1902</year>). 
2 Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1881</year>, s. 3 (retrospectively). 
3 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" all the Provinces of India". 
4 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
5 The Act was repealed in the State of Bombay with effect from the 
27th May, <year>1950</year> by the Bombay Agricultural Debtor' s Relief Act, <year>1947</year> 
 (Bom. 28 of <year>1947</year>), s. 56 as amended, Hence the part applicable to that 
State only has not been reproduced.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1886</year>, s. 3. 
7 The words" with the previous sanction of the G. G. in C." rep. by 
Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. 
8 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" State 
of Bombay". 
9 Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1895</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>614200</tid>
<number>11</number>Agriculturists to be sued where they reside. Every suit of 
the description mentioned in section 3, clause (w) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> may, if the 
defendant, or, when there are several defendants, one only of such 
defendants, is an agriculturist, be instituted and tried in a Court 
within the local limits of whose jurisdiction such defendant resides, 
and not elsewhere.
Every such suit in which there are several defendants who are 
agriculturists may be instituted and tried in a Court within the local 
limits of whose jurisdiction any one of such defendants resides, and 
not elsewhere.

Nothing herein contained shall affect sections 22 to 25 (both  
  inclusive) of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Code of Civil Procedure.





</article>



<article><tid>422742</tid>
<number>56</number>Instruments executed by agriculturist not to be deemed valid 
unless executed before a Village registrar. No instrument which 
purports to create, modify, transfer, evidence or extinguish an 
obligation for the payment of money or a charge upon any property, or 
to be a conveyance or lease, and which is executed after this Act 
comes into force by an agriculturist residing in any local area for 
which a Village- registrar has been appointed, shall be admitted in 
evidence for any purpose by any person having by law or consent of 
parties authority to receive evidence, or shall be acted upon by any 
such person or by any public officer, unless such instrument is 
written by, or under the superintendence of, and is attested by, a 
Village- registrar:
Provided that nothing herein contained shall prevent the 
admission of any instrument in evidence in any criminal proceeding, 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or apply to any instrument which is executed by an agriculturist 
merely as a surety,] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or to any instrument required by section 17 of 
the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Indian Registration Act, <year>1877</year> (3 of <year>1877</year>.), to be registered 
under that Act.]





</article>



<article><tid>180454</tid>
<number>60</number>Registration under this Act to be deemed equivalent to 
registration under Indian Registration Act, <year>1877</year>. Every instrument 
executed and registered in accordance with the foregoing provisions 
shall be deemed to have been duly registered under the provisions of 
the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Indian Registration Act, <year>1877</year> (3 of <year>1877</year>.); and no instrument 
which ought to have been executed before a Village- registrar but has 
been otherwise executed shall be registered by any
<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Reproduced below:--

" (w) suits for the recovery of money alleged to be due to 
the plaintiff-- 
on account of money lent or advanced to, or paid for, 
the defendant, 
or as the price of goods sold, or 
on an account stated between the plaintiff and 
defendant, or 
on a written or unwritten engagement for the payment of 
money not hereinbefore provided for;".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>See now Act 5 of <year>1908</year>. 
3 Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1881</year>, s. 12. 
4 Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1886</year>, s. 9. 
5 See now the Indian Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16 of <year>1908</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


officer acting under the said Act, or in any public office, or shall 
be authenticated by any public officer.





</article>



<article><tid>1288679</tid>
<number>62</number>Exemption of instruments to which the Government or any 
officer of the Government is a party. Nothing in this Act shall be 
deemed to require any instrument, to which the Government or any 
officer of the Government in his official capacity is a party, to be 
executed before a Village- registrar <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" or any Society registered under the Co- operative 
Credit Societies Act, <year>1904</year>" ins. by Bom. Act 1 of <year>1910</year> were rep. by 
Bom. Act 1 of <year>1912</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>