<act><tid>154545</tid>
<title>THE BENGAL SUPPRESSION OF TERRORISTOUTRAGES (SUPPLEMENTARY) ACT, <year>1932</year></title>

ACT NO. 24 OF <year>1932</year>
[ 23rd December, <year>1932</year>.]

An Act to supplement the Bengal Suppression of Terrorist Outrages Act, 
<year>1932</year>.

WHEREAS it is expedient to supplement the Bengal Suppression of 
Terrorist Outrages Act, <year>1932</year> (Ben. Act 12 of <year>1932</year>); It is hereby 
enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1602067</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Bengal Suppression of 
Terrorist Outrages (Supplementary) Act, <year>1932</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1592016</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,-
<section><tid>1168193</tid>
<number>a</number>" Code" means the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5  
  of <year>1898</year>); and

</section>

<section><tid>132058</tid>
<number>b</number>" local Act" means the Bengal Suppression of Terrorist 
Outrages Act, <year>1932</year>. (Ben. Act 12 of <year>1932</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1963579</tid>
<number> 3</number> Appeals.
<section><tid>301620</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie to the High Court of  
Judicature at Fort William in Bengal, from-

<subsection><tid>1043125</tid>
<number>a</number>any sentence passed by a Special Magistrate in any 
trial held under the local Act in the presidency- town of 
Calcutta,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>477872</tid>
<number>b</number>any sentence of transportation for a term exceeding two 
years, or of imprisonment for a term exceeding four years 
passed by a Special Magistrate in any trial under the local 
Act held outside the presidency- town of Calcutta.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1732540</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal under sub- section (1) shall be presented within 
thirty days from the date of the sentence, and shall be disposed of by 
the High Court in the manner provided in Chapter XXXI of the Code for 
the hearing of appeals.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>57719</tid>
<number>4</number>Effect of section 19 of local act. Section 19 of the local 
Act shall have effect as if it had been enacted by the Indian 
legislature.


</article>



<article><tid>278329</tid>
<number>5</number>Exclusion of interference of courts with proceedings under 
local Act. Notwithstanding the provisions of the Code, or of any 
other law for the time being in force, or of anything having the force 
of law, there shall, save as provided in the local Act as supplemented

<pagefootnote><pagenum>660</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by this Act, be no appeal from any order or sentence passed by a 
Special Magistrate under the local Act and save as aforesaid no Court 
shall have authority to revise such order or sentence, or to transfer 
any case from any such Magistrate, or to make any order under section 
 491 of the Code, or have any jurisdiction of any kind in respect of 
any proceedings of any such Magistrate, or of any direction made under 
Chapter II of the local Act:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>661</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Proviso to s. 5 was rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>