<act><title>

THE CO-OPERATIVE BANKS 
    (NOMINATION) 
    RULES, 19851</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Co-operative Banks (Nomination) Rules, 1985.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
    Official Gazette. 


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    <number>2</number> Notification in respect of deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The nomination to be made by the depositor or, as the case may, all the 
    depositors together in respect of a deposit held by a Co-operative Bank to 
    the credit of one or more individuals shall be in Form DA 1.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The said nomination may be made only in respect of a deposit which is 
    held in the individual capacity of the depositor and not in any 
    representative capacity as the holder of an office or otherwise.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Where the nominee is a minor, the depositor or, as the case may be, all 
    the depositors together may, while making the nomination, appoint another 
    individual not being a minor, to receive the amount of the deposit on behalf 
    of the nominee in the event of the death of the depositor or, as the case 
    may be, all the depositors during the minority of the nominee.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> In the case of a deposit made in the name of a minor, the nomination 
    shall be made by a person lawfully entitled to act on behalf of the minor.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> The cancellation of the said nomination to be made by the depositor or, 
    as the case may be, all the depositors together, shall be in Form DA 2.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> A variation of the said nomination to be made by the depositor or, as 
    the case may be, all the depositors together, shall be in Form DA 3.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> The said nomination shall be made in favour of only one individual.  
 </section><section>


    <number>8</number>(a) A nomination, cancellation of nomination or variation of nomination 
    may be made as aforesaid at any time during which the deposit is held by a 
    Co-operative Bank to the credit of the depositor or depositors, as the case  
    may be.
 <subsection>


    <number>b</number> In the case of a deposit held to the credit of more  than one depositor, 
    the cancellation or variation of a nomination shall not be valid unless it 
    is made by all the depositors surviving at the time of the cancellation or 
    variation of the nomination.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>9</number> The Co-operative Bank shall acknowledge in writing to the concerned 
    depositor or depositors, the filing of the relevant duly completed Form of 
    nomination or cancellation of nomination or variation of nomination, as the 
    case may be, in respect of a deposit.  
 </section><section>


    <number>10</number> The relevant duly completed Form of nomination or cancellation of 
    nomination or variation of nomination filed with the Co-operative Bank shall 
    be registered in the books of the Co-operative Bank.  
 </section><section>


    <number>11</number> A nomination or cancellation of nomination or variation of nomination 
    shall not cease to be in force merely by reason of the renewal of the 
    deposit.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    <number>3</number> Nomination in respect of articles in safe custody.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The nomination to be made by an individual (hereinafter referred to as “the 
    depositor”), in respect of articles left in safe custody with a Co-operative 
    Bank shall be in Form SC 1.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Where the nominee is a minor, the depositor may, while making the 
    nomination, appoint another individual not being a minor, to receive the 
    said articles on behalf of the nominee in the event of the death of the 
    depositor during the minority of the nominee.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Where the articles are left in safe custody with a Co-operative Bank in 
    the name of a minor, the nomination shall be made by a person lawfully 
    entitled to act on behalf of the minor.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> The  cancellation of the said nomination to be made by the depositor 
    shall be in Form SC 2.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> A variation of the said nomination to be made by the depositor shall be 
    in Form SC 3.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> The said nomination shall be made in favour of only  one individual.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> A nomination, cancellation of nomination or variation of nomination may 
    be made by the depositor at any time during which the articles so deposited 
    are held in safe custody by the Co-operative Bank.  
 </section><section>


    <number>8</number> The Co-operative Bank shall acknowledge in writing, to the depositor, 
    the filing of the relevant duly completed Form of nomination or cancellation 
    of nomination or variation of nomination, as the case may be, in respect of 
    articles so deposited.  
 </section><section>


    <number>9</number> The relevant duly completed Form of nomination or cancellation of 
    nomination or variation of nomination filed with the Co-operative Bank, 
    shall be registered in the books of the Co-operative Bank.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    <number>4</number> Nomination in respect of safety locker.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The nomination to be made by an individual, who is a sole hirer of a locker 
    from a Co-operative Bank, shall be in Form SL 1.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Where the locker is hired from a Co-operative Bank by two or more 
    individuals jointly, the nomination to be made by such hirers shall be in 
    Form SL 1A.
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> In the case of a sole hirer of a locker, nomination shall be made in 
    favour of only one individual.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> Where the locker is hired in the name of a minor, the nomination shall 
    be made by a person lawfully entitled to act on behalf of the minor.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> The cancellation of the said nomination to be made by the sole hirer, or 
    as the case may be, joint hirers of a locker shall be in Form SL 2.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> A variation of the said nomination to be made by the sole hirer of a 
    locker shall be in Form SL 3.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> A variation of the said nomination to be made by the joint hirers of a 
    locker shall be in Form SL 3A.  
 </section><section>


    <number>8</number> A nomination, cancellation of nomination or variation of nomination may 
    be made as aforesaid at any time during which the locker is under hire.  
 </section><section>


    <number>9</number> A Co-operative Bank shall acknowledge in writing to the sole hirer or 
    joint hirers, the filing of the relevant duly completed Form of nomination 
    or cancellation of nomination or variation of nomination, as the case may 
    be, in respect of the locker so hired.  
 </section><section>


    <number>10</number> The relevant duly completed Form of nomination or cancellation of 
    nomination or variation of nomination filed with the Co-operative Bank shall 
    be registered in the books of the Co-operative Bank.  
  
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

THE CO-OPERATIVE 
      BANKS (NOMINATION)  
RULES, 1985
 

 
 

 
 

Form 
      DA 2
 

Cancellation 
      of nomination under section 45ZA read with section 56 of the Banking 
      Regulation Act, 1949, and rule 2(5) of the Co-operative Banks (Nomination) 
      Rules, 1985,  in respect of the bank deposits
 

 
 

 
 

I/We,........................,[Name(s) 
      and address(es)], hereby cancel the nomination made by me/us in favour 
      of................ (Name and address) in respect of 
      ...................(give details of deposit).
 

 
 

Place...........................
 

Date...........................
 

Name(s), 
      signature(s) 
      and                                                 
        
 

address(es) 
      of 
      witness(es)2

 

1Signature(s)/Thumb 
      impression(s)
 

of 
      depositor(s).
 

 
 

_______________
 

1.   
      Where deposit is made in the name of a minor, the cancellation of 
      nomination should be signed by a person lawfully entitled to act on behalf 
      of the minor.
 

2.   
      Thumb impression(s) shall be attested by two witnesses.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>