<act><title>

The 
    Industrial Reconstruction Bank 
    (Transfer of Undertakings and Repeal) 
    Act, 1997</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Industrial Reconstruction Bank (Transfer of 
    Undertakings and Repeal) Act, 1997.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>

<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    
    “appointed day” means such date as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint under section 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    
    “Company” means the Industrial Investment Bank of India Limited to be formed 
    and registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    
    “Reconstruction Bank” means the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India 
    established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Industrial 
    Reconstruction Bank of India Act, 1984 (62 of 1984). 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Undertakings of the Reconstruction Bank to vest in 
      Company.—On 
      such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be transferred to, and vest 
      in, the Company, the undertakings of Reconstruction 
      Bank.
  







 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number> General effect of vesting of undertaking in 
      Company.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
      Government, being the shareholder of the Reconstruction Bank immediately 
      before the appointed day, shall be deemed to be registered, on and from 
      the appointed day, as a shareholder of the Company. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The undertakings of the Reconstruction Bank 
      which are transferred to, and which vest in, Company under Section 3 shall 
      be deemed to include all business, assets, rights powers, authorities and 
      privileges and all properties, movable and immovable, real and personal, 
      corporeal and incorporeal, in possession or reservation, present or 
      contingent of whatever nature and wheresoever situate including lands, 
      buildings, vehicles, cash balances, deposits, foreign currencies, 
      disclosed and undisclosed reserves, reserve fund, special reserve fund, 
      benevolent reserve fund, any other fund, stocks, investments, shares, 
      bonds, debentures, security, management of any industrial concern, loans, 
      advances and guarantees given to the industrial concerns, tenancies, 
      leases and book debts and all other rights and interests arising out of 
      such property as were immediately before the appointed day in the 
      ownership, possession or power of the Reconstruction Bank in relation to 
      its undertakings, within or without India, all books of account, 
      registers, records and documents relating thereto and shall also be deemed 
      to include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind 
      within or without India then subsisting of the Reconstruction Bank in 
      relation to its undertakings. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> All contracts, deeds, bonds, guarantees, 
      powers of attorney, other instruments and working arrangements subsisting 
      immediately before the appointed day and affecting the Reconstruction Bank 
      shall cease to have effect or to be enforceable against the Reconstruction 
      Bank shall be of as full force and effect against or in favour of the 
      Company in which the undertakings of the Reconstruction Bank have vested 
      by virtue of this Act and enforceable as fully and effectually as if 
      instead of the Reconstruction Bank, the Company had been therein or had 
      been a party thereto. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any proceeding or cause of action pending or 
      existing immediately before the appointed day by or against the 
      Reconstruction Bank in relation to its undertakings may, as from the 
      appointed day, be continued and enforced by or against the Company in 
      which the undertakings of the Reconstruction Bank have vested by virtue of 
      this Act as it might have been enforced by or against the Reconstruction 
      Bank if this Act had not been enacted and shall cease to be enforceable by 
      or against the Reconstruction Bank. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Provisions in respect of officers and other 
      employees of Reconstruction Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> Every officer or other employee of the 
      Reconstruction Bank (except a Director of the Board or the Chairman and 
      Managing Director) serving in the employment immediately before the 
      appointed day shall, in so far as such officer or other employee is 
      employed in connection with the undertakings which have vested in the 
      Company by virtue of this Act, become, as from the appointed day, an 
      officer or, as the case may be, other employee of the Company and shall 
      hold his office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same 
      remuneration, upon the same terms and conditions, with the same 
      obligations and with the same rights and privileges as to leave, leave 
      fare concession, welfare scheme, medical benefit scheme, insurance, 
      provident fund, other funds, retirement, voluntary retirement, gratuity 
      and other benefits as he would have held under the Reconstruction Bank if 
      its undertakings had not vested in the Company and shall continue to do so 
      as an officer or, as the case may be, other employees of the Company or 
      until the expiry of a period of six months from the appointed day if such 
      officer or other employee opts not to continue to be the officer or other 
      employee of the Company within such period. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an officer or other employee of the 
      Reconstruction Bank opts under sub-section (1) not to be in employment or 
      service of the Company, such officer or other employee shall be deemed to 
      have resigned.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
      Industrial Dispute Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) or in any other law for the time 
      being in force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other 
      employee of the Reconstruction Bank to the Company shall not entitle such 
      officer or other employees to any compensation under this Act or under any 
      other law for the time being in force and no such claim shall be 
      entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The officer and other employees who have 
      retired before the appointed day from the service of the Reconstruction 
      Bank and are entitled to any benefits, rights or privileges shall be 
      entitled to receive the same benefits, rights or privileges from the 
      Company. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The trust of the provident fund or the 
      gratuity fund of the Reconstruction Bank and any other bodies created for 
      the welfare of officers or employees would continue to discharge their 
      functions in the Company as was being hitherto in the Reconstruction Bank 
      and tax exemption granted to the provident fund or the gratuity fund would 
      continue to be applied to the Company. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this 
      Act or in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or in any other law for the 
      time being in force or in the regulation of the Reconstruction Bank, no 
      Director of the Board, Chairman and Managing Director or any other person 
      entitled to manage the whole or substantial part of the business and 
      affairs of the Reconstruction Bank shall be entitled to any compensation 
      against the Reconstruction Bank or the Company for the loss of office or 
      for the premature termination of any contract of management entered into 
      by him with the Reconstruction Bank. 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Provisions in respect of officers and other 
      employees of Reconstruction Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> Every officer or other employee of the 
      Reconstruction Bank (except a Director of the Board or the Chairman and 
      Managing Director) serving in the employment immediately before the 
      appointed day shall, in so far as such officer or other employee is 
      employed in connection with the undertakings which have vested in the 
      Company by virtue of this Act, become, as from the appointed day, an 
      officer or, as the case may be, other employee of the Company and shall 
      hold his office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same 
      remuneration, upon the same terms and conditions, with the same 
      obligations and with the same rights and privileges as to leave, leave 
      fare concession, welfare scheme, medical benefit scheme, insurance, 
      provident fund, other funds, retirement, voluntary retirement, gratuity 
      and other benefits as he would have held under the Reconstruction Bank if 
      its undertakings had not vested in the Company and shall continue to do so 
      as an officer or, as the case may be, other employees of the Company or 
      until the expiry of a period of six months from the appointed day if such 
      officer or other employee opts not to continue to be the officer or other 
      employee of the Company within such period. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an officer or other employee of the 
      Reconstruction Bank opts under sub-section (1) not to be in employment or 
      service of the Company, such officer or other employee shall be deemed to 
      have resigned.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
      Industrial Dispute Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) or in any other law for the time 
      being in force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other 
      employee of the Reconstruction Bank to the Company shall not entitle such 
      officer or other employees to any compensation under this Act or under any 
      other law for the time being in force and no such claim shall be 
      entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The officer and other employees who have 
      retired before the appointed day from the service of the Reconstruction 
      Bank and are entitled to any benefits, rights or privileges shall be 
      entitled to receive the same benefits, rights or privileges from the 
      Company. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The trust of the provident fund or the 
      gratuity fund of the Reconstruction Bank and any other bodies created for 
      the welfare of officers or employees would continue to discharge their 
      functions in the Company as was being hitherto in the Reconstruction Bank 
      and tax exemption granted to the provident fund or the gratuity fund would 
      continue to be applied to the Company. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this 
      Act or in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or in any other law for the 
      time being in force or in the regulation of the Reconstruction Bank, no 
      Director of the Board, Chairman and Managing Director or any other person 
      entitled to manage the whole or substantial part of the business and 
      affairs of the Reconstruction Bank shall be entitled to any compensation 
      against the Reconstruction Bank or the Company for the loss of office or 
      for the premature termination of any contract of management entered into 
      by him with the Reconstruction Bank. 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Concession, etc., to 
    be deemed to have been granted to Company.—With 
    effect from the appointed day, all fiscal and other concessions, benefits, 
    privileges and exemptions granted to the Reconstruction Bank in connection 
    with the affairs and business of the Reconstruction Bank under any law for 
    the time being in force shall be deemed to have been granted to the Company. 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Tax exemption or 
    benefit to continue to have effect.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income Tax Act, 1961 (43 of 
    1961) or any other enactment for the time being in force relating to tax on 
    income, profits or gains, the Company shall not be liable to pay income tax 
    or any other tax for a period of five years computed from the appointed day 
    of any income, profits or gains derived, or any amount received by the 
    Company.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The transfer and vesting 
    of the undertakings or any part thereof in terms of section 3 shall not be 
    construed as a transfer within the meaning of the Income Tax Act, 1961 (43 
    of 1961) for the purpose of capital gains. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Guarantee to be 
    operative.—Any guarantee given 
    for or in favour of the Reconstruction Bank with respect of any loan, lease 
    finance or other assistance shall continue to be operative in relation to 
    the Company. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Arrangement with Company on appointment of director to prevail.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any arrangement entered into by the company with an industrial or 
    other concern provides for the appointment by the company of one or more 
    directors of such concern, such provision and any appointment of directors 
    made, in pursuance thereof shall be valid and effective notwithstanding 
    anything to the contrary contained in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or 
    in any other law for the time being in force or in the memorandum, articles 
    of association or any other instrument relating to such concern, and any 
    provision regarding share qualification, age limit, number of directorship, 
    removal from office of directors and such like conditions contained in any 
    such law or instrument aforesaid, shall not apply to any director appointed 
    by the company in pursuance of the arrangement as aforesaid.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    director appointed in pursuance of sub-section (1) shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    hold office during the 
    pleasure of the company and may be removed or substituted by any person by 
    order in writing by the company; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    not incur any obligation 
    or liability by reason only of his being a director or for anything done or 
    omitted to be done in good faith in the discharge of his duties as a 
    director or anything in relation thereto; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    not be liable to 
    retirement by rotation and shall not be taken into account for computing the 
    number of directors liable to such retirement. 
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Act 18 
    of 1891 to apply to the books of Company.—The 
    Company shall be deemed to be a bank for the purpose of the Banker’s Books 
    Evidence Act, 1891. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Shares, 
    bonds and debentures to be deemed to be approved securities.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the shares, 
    bonds and debentures of the Company shall be deemed to be approved 
    securities for the purposes of the Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882), the 
    Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938) and the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 
    1949). 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Substitution in Act, rules or regulations of company in place of the 
    Reconstruction Bank.—In every 
    Act, rule or regulation in force on the appointed day,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    for the words 
    “Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India”, wherever they occur the words 
    “Industrial Investment Bank of India Limited” shall be substituted; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    for the words 
    “Reconstruction Bank”, wherever they occur, the words “Industrial Investment 
    Bank” shall be substituted; 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Repeal 
    and saving of Act 62 of 1984.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On the appointed day, the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India Act, 1984 
    shall stand repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding the repeal of the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India 
    Act, 1984— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Company shall, so 
    far as may be, comply with the provisions of Chapter VII of the Act so 
    repealed for any of the purposes related to the annual accounts and audit of 
    the Reconstruction Bank; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the provisions of 
    Chapter VII of the Act so repealed will continue to be applicable in respect 
    of the arrangements entered into by the Reconstruction Bank with an 
    industrial concern under section 18 thereof up to the appointed day and the 
    Company will be entitled to act upon and enforce the same as fully and 
    effectually as if this Act had not been elected. 
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Insertion of new section 4A.—In 
    the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India Act, 1984 (62 of 1984), after 
    section 4, the following section shall be inserted, namely:—
 
“4A. Transitional provisions regarding 
    adjustment of capital of the Reconstruction Bank.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may reduce share capital of the Reconstruction Bank by,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    extinguishing or 
    reducing the liability of any of its equity shares;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    either with or without 
    extinguishing or reducing liability on any of its equity shares, concealing 
    any paid up share capital which is lost, or is unrepresented by available 
    assets; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    either with or without 
    extinguish or reducing liability on any of its equity shares, paying of any 
    paid up share capital which is in excess of the wants of the Reconstruction 
    Bank.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may at any time, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    convert such number of equity shares held by it, as it may decide into 
    redeemable preference shares. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    redeemable preference shares referred to in sub-section (2) shall carry such 
    fixed rates of dividend as the Central Government may specify at the time of 
    such conversion.”.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Repeal 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Industrial 
    Reconstruction Bank (Transfer of Undertakings and Repeal) Ordinance, 1997 (Ord 
    7 of 1997) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the 
    Ordinance so repealed, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
    corresponding provisions of this Act.
 


 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   27th day of March, 1997, vide 
      S.O. 242(E), dated 25th March, 1997, published in the Gazette of India, 
      Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3 (ii), dated 25th March, 1997.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>