<act><tid>1577226</tid>
<title>THE LIVE- STOCK IMPORTATION ACT, <year>1898</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>1898</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 12th August, <year>1898</year>.]

An Act to make better provision for the regulation of the importation 
of live- stock.

WHEREAS it is expedient to make better provision for the regula- 
tion of the importation of live- stock which is liable to be affected 
by infectious or contagious disorders; It is hereby enacted as 
follows:-





<article><tid>1413821</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and local extent.
<section><tid>1319173</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Live- stock Importation Act, <year>1898</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>269337</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>;] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>,
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1062992</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>318473</tid>
<number>a</number>the expression" infectious or contagious disorders" 
includes tick- pest, anthrax, glanders, farcy, scabies and any 
other disease or disorder which may be specified by the 
Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>1878594</tid>
<number>b</number>" live- stock" includes horses, kine, camels, sheep and 
any other animal which may be specified by the Central 
Government by notification in the Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1074433</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" import" means the bringing or taking, by sea, land 
or air, into <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> India].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>135473</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to regulate importation of live- stock.
<section><tid>24104</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
regulate, restrict or prohibit, in such manner and to such extent as 
it may think fit, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> the import], into <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> India] or any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to-

Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 
and Sch.

Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch, I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>). 
2 Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1953</year>, s. 2, for the former sub- section,

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by 
Act 62 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The word" and" and sub- section (3) rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch. II

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1950</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 62 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the territories to 
which this Act extends" (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1953</year>, s. 4, for" the bringing or taking, by 
sea or land".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

specified place therein, of any live- stock which may be liable to be 
affected by infectious or contagious disorders, and of any fodder, 
dung, stable- litter, clothing, harness or fittings appertaining to 
livestock or that may have been in contact therewith.


</section>

<section><tid>246109</tid>
<number>2</number>A notification under sub- section (1) shall operate as if it 
had been issued under section 19 of the Sea Customs Act, <year>1878</year>, (8 of  
  <year>1871</year>.) and the officers of customs at every port shall have the same 
power in respect of any live- stock or thing, with regard to the 
importation of which such a notification has been issued, and the 
vessel containing the same, as they have for the time being in respect 
of any article the importation of which is regulated, restricted or 
prohibited by the law relating to sea customs and the vessel 
containing the same; and the enactments for the time being in force 
relating to sea customs or any such article or vessel shall apply 
accordingly.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1100695</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power for State Government to make rules.
<section><tid>229008</tid>
<number>1</number>The State  
Government may <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> make rules for the detention, inspection, 
disinfection or destruction of imported live- stock, and of fodder, 
dung, stable- litter, clothing, harness or fittings appertaining to 
imported live- stock or that may have been in contact therewith, and 
for regulating the powers and duties of the officers whom it may 
appoint in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1981272</tid>
<number>2</number>In making any rule under this section the State Government 
may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which 
may extend to one thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>792135</tid>
<number>5</number>Protection to persons acting under Act. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person 
for anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" subject to the control of the Governor General in 
Council" omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>