<act><title>


    The Prevention of Cruelty (Capture of Animals) Rules, 19721</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Prevention of Cruelty (Capture of Animals) Rules, 
    1979.  


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Capture 
    of birds.—No bird shall be 
    captured for the purpose of sale, export or for any other purpose except by 
    net method.  
 

    Explanation.—A bird is said to be 
    captured by the net method if in its capture the following contrivance is 
    used, namely, a contrivance made of spun thread which is soft, pliable and 
    sufficiently strong, like cotton, jute or any synthetic fibre, woven in such 
    a way as to form a mesh of suitable size so that the bird is captured 
    without any injury being caused to it.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Capture 
    of other animals.—
<section><number>1</number> No animal 
    shall be captured for the purpose of sale, export or for any other purpose 
    except by sack and loop method:  
 
Provided that 
    an animal which cannot be captured by reason of its size, nature of other 
    condition or circumstance by the sack and loop method, may be captured with 
    the help of transquiliser guns or by any other method which renders the 
    animal insensible to pain before capture.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in 
    this rule shall apply to the capture of birds.  
 

    Explanation.—An animal is said to 
    be captured by the sack and loop method if in its capture the following 
    contrivance is used, namely, a strong canvass in the form of sack, not less 
    than 92 cms. in length and 138 cms in diameter, which has a smooth rope, not 
    less than 5.5 meter in length passing through ten or more rings of not less 
    than 4 cms. in diameter each attached at the open end, thus forming a loop, 
    the sack having small holes at convenient places to enable the animal to 
    breathe during captivity, and the animal is captured by the sack being 
    thrown on it and secured by having the loop pulled.  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>