<act><tid>1578520</tid>
<title>THE COCONUT DEVELOPMENT BOARD ACT, <year>1979</year></title>

ACT NO. 5 OF <year>1979</year>
[ 17th March, <year>1979</year>.]

An Act to provide for the development under the control of the Union 
of the coconut industry and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirtieth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>558781</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>799009</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Coconut Development Board Act, <year>1979</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1767958</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>819412</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1106030</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union. It is 
hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the 
Union should take under its control the coconut industry.


</article>



<article><tid>1286381</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1749357</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Coconut Development Board established 
under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1937856</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>410690</tid>
<number>c</number>" coconut" means the fruit of coconut palm and includes 
green coconut, ripe coconut and copra.
Explanation.--" Coconut palm" means the coconut tree, Cocos 
Nucifera Linn;


</section>

<section><tid>1631484</tid>
<number>d</number>" coconut industry" does not include--

<subsection><tid>1282839</tid>
<number>i</number>coir industry; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1294935</tid>
<number>ii</number>an industry from which products (including  
  by- products) out of coconut oil are manufactured;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>936757</tid>
<number>e</number>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the 
Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>434586</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>408</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 12. 1. <year>1981</year>: Vide Notifi. No. G. S. R. 13 (E), dated 12. 1. <year>1981</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

THE COCONUT DEVELOPMENT BOARD

CHAPTER II

THE COCONUT DEVELOPMENT BOARD




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>445040</tid>
<number> 4</number> Establishment and constitution of the Board.
<section><tid>1987843</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect  
from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette appoint in this behalf, there shall be established 
for the purposes of this Act, a Board to be called the Coconut 
Development Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1183050</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid, 
having perpetual succession and common seal, with power to acquire, 
hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable and to 
contract, and shall by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1983275</tid>
<number>3</number>The head office of the Board shall be at such place as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1090984</tid>
<number>4</number>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:--

<subsection><tid>14867</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman, to be appointed by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1225680</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Horticulture Commissioner] to the Government of 
India, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1243515</tid>
<number>c</number>the Director, Central Plantation Crops Research 
Institute (Indian Council of Agricultural Research), ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1729534</tid>
<number>d</number>the Chairman of the Coir Board constituted under section 
 4 of the Coir Industry Act, <year>1953</year> (45 of <year>1953</year>), ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>45548</tid>
<number>e</number>three members of Parliament of whom two shall be elected 
by the House of the People and one by the Council of 
States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>466845</tid>
<number>f</number>two members to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent respectively the Ministries of the Central 
Government dealing with--

<subsubsection><tid>560601</tid>
<number>i</number>Revenue: and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1904514</tid>
<number>ii</number>Civil Supplies and Co- operation;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1928458</tid>
<number>g</number>three members to be appointed by the Central Government 
one each to represent the Governments of the States of 
Kerala, Tamil Nadu and Karnataka, being States wherein 
coconut is grown on a large scale;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>334843</tid>
<number>h</number>five members to be appointed by the Central Government 
by rotation in the alphabetical order to represent the 
States of Andhra Pradesh, Assam, Maharashtra, Orissa 
and West Bengal and the Union territories of the 
Andaman and Nicobar Islands, Goa, Daman and Diu, 
Lakshadweep and Pondicherry;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>409</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 21 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2, for" the Agriculture Commission".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>641050</tid>
<number>i</number>four members to be appointed by the Central Government, 
two to represent the coconut growers of the State of 
Kerala and one each to represent the coconut growers of 
the States of Tamil Nadu and Karnataka;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1272695</tid>
<number>j</number>one member to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent the coconut processing industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>425437</tid>
<number>k</number>two members to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent such other interests connected with the 
coconut industry as, in the opinion of that Government, 
ought to be represented:
Provided that every appointment under clauses (g) and (h) shall 
be made on the recommendation of the State Government 
or, as the case may be, of the Union territory 
concerned.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>893389</tid>
<number>5</number>The Board shall elect, from amongst its members, a Vice- 
Chairman who shall exercise such of the powers and perform such of the 
functions of the Chairman as may be prescribed or as may be delegated 
to him by the Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>947433</tid>
<number>6</number>The term of office of the members and the manner of filling 
vacancies among, and the procedure to be followed in the discharge of 
their functions by, the members shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>647741</tid>
<number>7</number>Any officer of the Central Government, not being a member of 
the Board, when deputed by that Government in this behalf, shall have 
the right to attend the meetings of the Board and take part in the 
proceedings thereof but shall not be entitled to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>351442</tid>
<number>8</number>The Board may associate with itself in such manner, subject 
to such conditions and for such purposes as may be prescribed, any 
person whose assistance or advice it may desire in complying with any 
of the provisions of this Act and a person so associated shall have 
the right to take part in the discussions of the Board relevant to the 
purposes for which he has been associated but shall not have the right 
to vote and shall be entitled to receive such allowances or fees as 
may be fixed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1984934</tid>
<number>9</number>No act or proceeding of the Board or any committee appointed 
by it under section 9 shall be invalidated merely by reason of-

<subsection><tid>280392</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, 
the Board or such committee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>212775</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the appointment of a person acting as a 
member of the Board or such committee; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>315612</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in the procedure of the Board or such 
committee not affecting the merits of the case.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>410</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1155211</tid>
<number>10</number>The Board shall meet at such times and places and shall 
observe such rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of 
business at its meeting (including the quorum at meetings) as may be 
provided by regulations made, by the Board under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1764269</tid>
<number> 5</number> Salary and allowances and other conditions of service of 
Chairman and allowances of members.
<section><tid>920722</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman shall be entitled  
to such salary and allowances and shall be subject to such conditions 
of service in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and other 
matters as may, from time to time, be fixed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1612239</tid>
<number>2</number>The members of the Board shall receive such allowances as may 
be fixed by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>590966</tid>
<number>6</number>Registration of members. A member, other than an ex officio 
member, may resign his office by giving notice thereof in writing to 
the Central Government and on such resignation being accepted, he 
shall be deemed to have vacated his office.


</article>



<article><tid>1630196</tid>
<number> 7</number> Officers of the Board and other staff.
<section><tid>1491733</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chairman shall  
be the chief executive of the Board and shall exercise such powers and 
perform such duties as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1957093</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall appoint a Chief Coconut 
Development Officer to exercise such powers and perform such duties as 
may be prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1960115</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chief Coconut Development Officer appointed under 
sub- section (2) shall have the right to attend the meetings of the 
Board and its committees appointed under section 9 and take part in 
the proceedings thereof but shall not be entitled to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>743361</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall appoint a Secretary to the Board 
who shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be 
prescribed or as may be delegated to him by the Board or the Chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1221693</tid>
<number>5</number>The Chief Coconut Development Officer and the Secretary shall 
be entitled to such salary and allowances and shall be subject to such 
conditions of service in respect of leave, pension, provident fund and 
other matters as may, from time to time, be fixed by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1042618</tid>
<number>6</number>Subject to such control and restrictions as may be 
prescribed, the Board may appoint such other officers and employees as 
may be necessary for the efficient performance of its functions and 
the method of appointment, the conditions of service and the scales of 
pay and allowances of such other officers and employees of the Board 
shall be such as may be provided by the Board by regulations made 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1775184</tid>
<number>7</number>The Chairman, the Chief Coconut Development Officer, the 
Secretary and other officers and employees of the Board shall not 
undertake any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>411</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

work unconnected with their duties under this Act except with the 
permission of the Central Government.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1395931</tid>
<number> 8</number> Special provision for transfer of employees to the Board.
<section><tid>818145</tid>
<number>1</number> 
On the establishment of the Board, it shall be lawful for the Central 
Government to transfer to the Board, by order, and with effect from 
such date or dates as may be specified in the order, any officer or 
other employee holding office as such in the Directorate of Coconut 
Development immediately before the date on which the Board is 
established:
Provided that the scale of pay of the post to which such officer 
or other employee is transferred shall not be lower than the scale of 
pay of the post he was holding immediately before such transfer and 
the other terms and conditions of service (including pension, leave,  
  provident fund and medical benefits) of the post to which he is 
transferred shall not be less favourable than the terms and conditions 
of service in relation to the post held by him immediately before such 
transfer:

Provided further that if, immediately before the date of his 
transfer, any such officer or other employee is officiating in a 
higher post under the Central Government either in a leave vacancy or 
in any vacancy of specified duration, his pay and other allowances, if 
any, on transfer, shall be protected for the unexpired period of such 
vacancy and thereafter he shall be entitled to the scale of pay 
applicable to the post under the Central Government to which he would 
have reverted.


</section>

<section><tid>48881</tid>
<number>2</number>Before any order is issued under sub- section (1), all 
officers and other employees of the Directorate of Coconut Development 
shall be given an option in such form as may be prescribed, and within 
such time as may be specified in that behalf by the Central 
Government, to express their willingness or otherwise to become 
employees of the Board and such option once exercised shall be final:
Provided that no order under sub- section (1) shall be made in 
relation to any officer or other employee of the Directorate of 
Coconut Development who has intimated his intention of not becoming an 
employee of the Board within the time specified in that behalf:

Provided further that such of the persons employed by the Central 
Government in the said Directorate, who do not express, within the 
time specified in that behalf, their intention of becoming the 
employees of the Board, shall be dealt with in the same manner and in 
accordance with the same rules as would apply to the employees of the 
Central Government in the event of the reduction of the strength of 
the Department in which such persons have been employed.


</section>

<section><tid>429592</tid>
<number>3</number>An officer or other employee transferred by an order made 
under sub- section (1) shall, on and from the date of transfer, cease 
to be an

<pagefootnote><pagenum>412</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

employee of the Central Government and become an officer or other 
employee of the Board with such designation as the Board may determine 
and shall, subject to the provisions of the first and second provisos 
to sub- section (1), be governed by the regulations made by the Board 
under this Act in respect of remuneration and other conditions of 
service (including pension, leave, provident fund and medical  
  benefits) and shall continue to be an officer or other employee of the 
Board unless and until his employment is duly terminated by the Board:

Provided that till such time as the regulations referred to above 
governing the conditions of service of its officers or other employees 
are framed by the Board, the relevant rules and orders framed by the 
Central Government shall continue to be applicable to such officers or 
other employees.


</section>

<section><tid>1458923</tid>
<number>4</number>If a question arises whether the terms and conditions of 
service prescribed in the regulations framed by the Board in respect 
of any matter, including remuneration, pension, leave, provident fund 
and medical benefits, are less favourable than those attached to the 
post held by an officer or other employee immediately before his 
transfer to the Board, the decision of the Central Government in the 
matter shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>751121</tid>
<number> 9</number> Committees of the Board.
<section><tid>1938061</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may appoint such  
committees as may be necessary for the efficient discharge of its 
duties and performance of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>130499</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall have the power to co- opt as members of any 
committee appointed under sub- section (1) such number of persons who 
are not members of the Board as it may think fit and the persons so 
co- opted shall have the right to attend meetings of the committee and 
take part in its proceedings but shall not have the right to vote.

</section>

<section><tid>1467582</tid>
<number>3</number>The persons co- opted as members of a committee under 
sub- section (2) shall be entitled to receive such allowances or fees 
for attending meetings of the committee as may be fixed by the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1179338</tid>
<number> 10</number> Functions of the Board.
<section><tid>378715</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the duty of the Board  
to promote, by such measures as it thinks fit, the development under 
the control of the Central Government of the coconut industry.

</section>

<section><tid>1790299</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub- 
section (1), the measures referred to therein may provide for--

<subsection><tid>151031</tid>
<number>a</number>adopting measures for the development of coconut 
industry so that farmers, particularly small farmers, 
may become participants in, and beneficiaries of, the 
development and growth of coconut industry;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>413</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1833131</tid>
<number>b</number>recommending measures for improving the marketing of 
coconut and its products in India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>606094</tid>
<number>c</number>imparting technical advice to any person who is engaged 
in the cultivation of coconut or the processing or 
marketing of coconut and its products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>934692</tid>
<number>d</number>providing financial or other assistance for the 
development of high yielding coconut hybrids, adoption 
of improved methods of cultivation of coconut, modern 
technology for processing of coconut and extension of 
areas under coconut cultivation (including replanting) 
with a view to improving the growth of coconut 
industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>188144</tid>
<number>e</number>adopting such measures as may be practicable for 
assisting coconut growers to get incentive prices 
including recommending, as and when necessary, minimum 
and maximum prices for coconut and its products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>714886</tid>
<number>f</number>recommending measures for regulating import and export 
of coconut and its products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1905066</tid>
<number>g</number>collecting statistics from growers of coconut, dealers 
in coconut, manufacturers of coconut products and such 
other persons and institutions as may be prescribed, on 
any matter relating to coconut industry and publishing 
the statistics so collected or portions thereof or 
extracts therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1448439</tid>
<number>h</number>fixing grades, specifications and standards for coconut 
and its products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>971322</tid>
<number>i</number>financing suitable schemes in consultation with the 
Central Government and the Governments of the States 
where coconut is grown on a large scale, so as to 
increase the production of coconut and to improve its 
quality and yield; and for this purpose evolving 
schemes for award of prizes or grant of incentives to 
growers of coconut and the manufacturers of its 
products and for providing marketing facilities for 
coconut and its products;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>366175</tid>
<number>j</number>assisting, encouraging, promoting or financing 
agricultural, technological, industrial or economic 
research on coconut and its products in such manner as 
the Board may deem fit by making use of available 
institutions;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>414</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>396540</tid>
<number>k</number>undertaking such publicity and publishing such 
periodicals, books or bulletins, on the research and 
development of coconut and its products, as may be 
found necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>110854</tid>
<number>l</number>setting up of regional offices and other agencies for 
the promotion and development of production, grading 
and marketing of coconut and its products in coconut 
growing States and Union territories for the efficient 
discharge of the functions and objectives of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1814317</tid>
<number>m</number>such other measures as may, having regard to the 
purposes of this Act, be prescribed by the Central 
Government in consultation with the Governments of the 
States where coconut is grown on a large scale.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1670972</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall perform its functions under this section in 
accordance with, and subject to, such rules as may be made by the 
Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1654340</tid>
<number> 11</number> Dissolution of the Board.
<section><tid>620313</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette and for reasons to be specified 
therein, direct that the Board shall be dissolved from such date and 
for such period as may be specified in the notification:
Provided that before issuing any such notification, the Central 
Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to the Board to make 
representations against the proposed dissolution and shall consider 
the representations, if any, of the Board.


</section>

<section><tid>437536</tid>
<number>2</number>When the Board is dissolved under the provisions of sub- 
section (1),--

<subsection><tid>78461</tid>
<number>a</number>all members, notwithstanding that their term of office 
has not expired, shall, from the date of dissolution, 
vacate their offices as such members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1076939</tid>
<number>b</number>all powers and duties of the Board shall, during the 
period of dissolution, be exercised and performed by 
such person or persons as the Central Government may 
appoint in his behalf and their remuneration shall be 
such as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1377326</tid>
<number>c</number>all funds and other properties vested in the Board 
shall, during the period of dissolution, vest in the 
Central Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1854802</tid>
<number>d</number>as soon as the period of dissolution expires, the Board 
shall be reconstituted in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>415</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT

CHAPTER III

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS AND AUDIT




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>815993</tid>
<number>12</number>Grants and loans by the Central Government. The Central 
Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
this behalf, pay to the Board by way of grants or loans such sums of 
money as the Central Government may think fit for being utilised for 
the purposes of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>11608</tid>
<number> 13</number> Constitution of Coconut Development Fund.
<section><tid>1304168</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
formed a Fund to be called the Coconut Development Fund and there 
shall be credited thereto--
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


<subsection><tid>176822</tid>
<number>b</number>any grants or loans granted by the Central Government 
for the purposes of this Act:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>386309</tid>
<number>c</number>any grants or loans that may be made by any person for 
the purposes of this Act including loans under section 
14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>404949</tid>
<number>d</number>any grants or donations from State Governments, 
voluntary organisations or other institutions:
Provided that no such grant, loan or donation shall be credited 
to the Fund except with the prior approval of the Central Government.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1185745</tid>
<number>2</number>The Fund shall be applied--

<subsection><tid>171353</tid>
<number>a</number>for meeting the cost of the measures referred to in 
section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>957091</tid>
<number>b</number>for meeting the salaries, allowances and other 
remuneration of the members, officers and other 
employees, as the case may be, of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1325541</tid>
<number>c</number>for meeting the other administrative expenses of the 
Board and any other expenses authorised by or under 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1579439</tid>
<number>d</number>for repayment of any loans.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>608521</tid>
<number> 14</number> Borrowing powers of the Board.
<section><tid>1127415</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, for the  
purposes of carrying out its functions under this Act, and with the 
previous approval of, and subject to the directions of the Central 
Government, borrow money from--

<subsection><tid>763957</tid>
<number>a</number>the public by the issue or sale of bonds or debentures 
or both, carrying interest at such rates as may be 
specified therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373916</tid>
<number>b</number>any bank or other institution;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>416</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Cl. (a) Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 10.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1536210</tid>
<number>c</number>such other authority, organisation or institution as may 
be approved by the Central Government in this behalf.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>424693</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may guarantee the repayment of the 
monies borrowed by the Board under sub- section (1) and the payment of 
interest thereon and other incidental charges.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1375259</tid>
<number> 15</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>422012</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts, in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government 
in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1512132</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Board shall be audited by the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be specified by 
him and any expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall 
be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and Auditor- General.

</section>

<section><tid>997603</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Board shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General 
generally has in connection with the audit of the Government accounts 
and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of 
books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and 
to inspect any of the offices of the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>380260</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Board as certified by the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in this 
behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded 
annually to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the 
same to be laid before each House of Parliament.
CHAP

CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT

CHAPTER IV

CONTROL BY CENTRAL GOVERNMENT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1453859</tid>
<number>16</number>Directions by Central Government. The Board shall carry out 
such directions as may be issued to it from time to time by the 
Central Government for the efficient administration of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>131600</tid>
<number> 17</number> Returns and reports.
<section><tid>1511029</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall furnish to the  
Central Government at such time and in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed or as the Central Government may direct, such returns and 
statements and such particulars in regard to any proposed or existing 
programme for the promotion and development of the coconut industry, 
as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>417</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1192896</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall furnish a programme of its activities for 
each financial year to the Central Government for their information 
and directions, if any.

</section>

<section><tid>1697175</tid>
<number>3</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Board shall, as soon as possible, after the end of each financial 
year, submit to the Central Government a report in such form and 
before such date, as may be prescribed, giving a true and full account 
of its activities, policy and programmes during the previous financial 
year.

</section>

<section><tid>1661702</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the report received under sub- section (3) shall be 
laid, as soon as may be, after it is received, before each House of 
Parliament.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1306553</tid>
<number>18</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government, or the Board or any committee appointed by it, or any 
member of the Board or such committee, or any officer or other 
employee of the Central Government or of the Board or any other person 
authorised by the Central Government or the Board, for anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the 
rules made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1826614</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1958232</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>226696</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>922054</tid>
<number>a</number>the powers which may be exercised and functions which 
may be performed by the Vice- Chairman of the Board 
under sub- section (5) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1314952</tid>
<number>b</number>the term of office of the members, the manner of filling 
vacancies among, and the procedure to be followed in 
the discharge of their functions by, the members, under 
sub- section (6) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>971211</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which and the purposes for which any 
person may be associated by the Board under sub- section 
 (8) of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1285862</tid>
<number>d</number>the powers which may be exercised and the duties which 
may be performed by the Chairman as the chief executive 
of the Board under sub- section (1) of section 7;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>418</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1845080</tid>
<number>e</number>the powers which may be exercised and the duties which 
may be performed by the Chief Coconut Development 
Officer of the Board under sub- section (2) of section 
7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1466101</tid>
<number>f</number>the powers which may be exercised and the duties which 
may be performed by the Secretary of the Board under 
sub- section (4) of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1636811</tid>
<number>g</number>the control and restrictions subject to which officers 
and other employees may be appointed by the Board under 
sub- section (6) of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>473809</tid>
<number>h</number>the form in which option may be given by the officers 
and other employees of the Directorate of Coconut 
Development under sub- section (2) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1362023</tid>
<number>i</number>the collection of statistics in respect of any matter 
relating to coconut industry under clause (g) of sub- 
section (2) of section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>397739</tid>
<number>j</number>the matters in respect of which the Board may undertake 
measures in the discharge of its functions under clause 
 (m) of sub- section (2) of section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>760557</tid>
<number>k</number>the remuneration and other allowances payable to the 
person or persons referred to in clause (b) of sub- 
section (2) of section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1188899</tid>
<number>l</number>the form in which the accounts of the Board shall be 
maintained under sub- section (1) of section 15;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>203049</tid>
<number>m</number>the form and manner in which and the time at which the 
Board may furnish returns and reports to the Central 
Government under sub- section (1) of section 17;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1778497</tid>
<number>n</number>the form in which and the date before which the Board 
shall furnish to the Central Government the report of 
its activities and programmes under sub- section (3) of 
section 17;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225138</tid>
<number>o</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed 
by rules under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>944036</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>1850277</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, with the  
previous sanction of the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make regulations not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, to provide for 
all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the 
purposes of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>419</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1685517</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such regulations may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>950973</tid>
<number>a</number>the times and places at which meetings of the Board or 
any committee thereof, shall be held and the procedure 
to be followed thereat, and the number of members which 
shall form a quorum at a meeting under sub- section (10) 
of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1030527</tid>
<number>b</number>the method of appointment, the conditions of service and 
the scales of pay and allowances of any of the officers 
and other employees of the Board under sub- section (6) 
of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>287823</tid>
<number>c</number>generally, for the efficient conduct of the affairs of 
the Board.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>519377</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, modify or rescind any regulation sanctioned by it and the 
regulation so modified or rescinded shall have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that 
any such modification or rescission shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything done under the regulation before its modification 
or rescission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>568602</tid>
<number>21</number>Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation, as the case may be, or both 
Houses agree that the rule or regulation, as the case may be, should 
not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter have effect only 
in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule 
or regulation.

</article>



 </act>