<act><title>
The
public financial institutions (obligation as to fidelity and
secrecy) Act, 1983</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title.—This Act may be called
the Public Financial Institutions (Obligation as to Fidelity and Secrecy) Act,
1983.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act,
“public financial institution” means—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the Industrial Credit and Investment Corporation of India Limited, a
company formed and registered under the Indian Companies Act, 1913 (7 of 1913);
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the Industrial Reconstruction Corporation of India Limited, a company
formed and registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
any other institution, being a company as defined in section 617 of the
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or a company to which the provisions of section
619 of that Act apply, which the Central Government may, having regard to the
nature of the business carried on by such institution, by notification in the
Official Gazette, specify to be a public financial institution for the purposes
of this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Every notification issued under clause (c) of sub-section (1) shall, as soon as
may be, after it is issued, be laid before each House of Parliament.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Obligation as to fidelity and secrecy.—
<section><number>1</number>
A public financial institution shall not, except as otherwise provided in
sub-section (2) or in any other law for the time being in force, divulge any
information relating to, or to the affairs of, its constituents except in
circumstances in which it is, in accordance with the law or practice and usage,
customary among bankers, necessary or appropriate for the public financial
institution to divulge such information. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
A public financial institution may, for the purpose of efficient discharge of
its functions, collect from, or furnish to,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the Central Government; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the State Bank of India constituted under section 3 of the State Bank of
India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955), any subsidiary bank within the meaning of the
State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959 (38 of 1959), any corresponding
new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acquisition and
Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970) or under section 3 of the
Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of
1980), any other scheduled bank within the meaning of the Reserve Bank of India
Act, 1934 (2 of 1934); or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
any other public financial institution,
 such
credit information or other information as it may consider useful for the
purpose, in such manner and at such time as it may think fit.
 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this sub-section, the expression “credit information” shall
have the same meaning as in clause (c) of section 45A of the Reserve Bank of
India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934) subject to the modification that the banking company
referred to therein shall mean a bank referred to in clause (b) of this
sub-section or a public financial institution.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>3</number>
Nothing contained in this section shall apply to the credit information
disclosed under the Credit Information Companies (Regulation) Act, 2005.]
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Declaration of fidelity and secrecy.—Every
director, member of any committee, auditor or officer or any other employee of a
public financial institution to which this Act applies, shall,—
 <section><number>a</number>
before entering upon his duties; or 
 </section><section>
(b)
where he has entered upon his duties as such before the date on which
this Act became applicable to such institution, within thirty days from the date
on which this Act became applicable to such institution, 
 make
a declaration of fidelity and secrecy in the form set out in the Schedule to
this Act.
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Amendment of Act 15 of 1942.—[Rep.
by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f.
31-3-1988).]
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Amendment of Act 63 of 1951.—[Rep.
by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1988 (19 of 1988), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f.
31-3-1988).]
  
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  





 
Declaration
of Fidelity And Secrecy
 I,
........................., do hereby declare that I will faithfully, truly and
to the best of my skill and ability, execute and perform the duties required of
me as director, member of any committee, auditor, officer or other employee (as
the case may be) of the ........................................* and which
properly relate to the office or position held by me in, or in relation to,
the..................................................*
 I
further declare that I will not communicate or allow to be communicated to any
person not legally entitled thereto any information relating to the affairs of
the ................ ................................................* to the
affairs of any person having any dealing with
the............................................................* nor will I
allow any such person to inspect, or have access to, any books or documents
belonging to, or in the possession of,
the..................................................................* and
relating to the business of the
..................................................* or the business of any
person having any dealing with the
..................................................*
   


 Signed
before me Signature.
  
 
* Here insert the name
of the public financial Institution concerned. 
 


 
  



<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Ins. by Act 30 of 2005, sec. 34 and Sch.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>