<act><tid>1588084</tid>
<title>THE MERGED STATES (LAWS) ACT, <year>1949</year></title>

ACT NO. 59 OF <year>1949</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
[ 26th December, <year>1949</year>.]
An Act to extend certain laws to certain areas administered as 
parts of Governors' Provinces or as Chief Commissioners' Provinces.

WHEREAS by Orders under section 290A of the Government of India 
Act, <year>1935</year>, (25 and 26 Geo. 5, c. 2.) provision has been made for the 
administration of certain areas either as if they formed part of an 
adjoining Governor' s Province or as if they were a Chief 
Commissioner' s Province;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to provide that certain laws should 
be extended to, and by virtue of such extension, be in force in, the 
said areas;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--




<article><tid>973565</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1615460</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Merged States (Laws) Act, <year>1949</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>145424</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on the 1st day of January, <year>1950</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>63760</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,--
<section><tid>1813919</tid>
<number>a</number>the expressions" absorbing Province" and" merged State" 
have the same meanings as in the States' Merger 
 (Governors' Provinces) Order, <year>1949</year>, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as amended by 
the States' Merger (United Provinces) Order, <year>1949</year> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>883655</tid>
<number>b</number>the expression" new Provinces" means the Chief 
Commissioners' Provinces constituted by the States' 
Merger (Chief Commissioners' Provinces) Order, <year>1949</year>, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> 
as amended by the States' Merger (United Provinces) 
Order, <year>1949</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>149905</tid>
<number> 3</number> Extension of laws.
<section><tid>70489</tid>
<number>1</number>The Acts, Ordinances and Regulation  
specified in the Schedule are hereby extended to, and shall be in 
force in, all the new Provinces.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>116</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act was not adapted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
2. See S. O. 25, Gazette of India, <year>1949</year>, Extraodinary, p. 1317. 
3. See S. O. 27, ibid., p. 2611. 
4. See S. O. 26, ibid., p. 1343.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1410825</tid>
<number>2</number>So much of any of the Acts, Ordinances and Regulation 
specified in the Schedule as extends to any absorbing Province and 
relates to matters with respect to which the Dominion Legislature has 
power to make laws for a Governor' s Province is hereby extended to, 
and shall be in force in, all the merged States which are now 
administered as part of that Province.

</section>

<section><tid>769268</tid>
<number>3</number>If any of the said Acts, Ordinances and Regulation as in 
force in any absorbing Province immediately before the commencement of 
this Act is subject to any amendments made by the Legislature of that 
Province, that Act, Ordinance or Regulation shall be deemed to be 
extended to, and to be in force in, all the merged States which are 
now administered as part of that Province, subject to so much of the 
said amendments as relate to matters with respect to which the 
Dominion Legislature has power to make laws for a Governor' s Province.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1157446</tid>
<number> 4</number> Interpretation of laws as extended. In any Act, Ordinance or 
Regulation specified in the Schedule, notwithstanding anything 
contained in the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year>, (10 of <year>1897</year>.)--
<section><tid>1662074</tid>
<number>a</number>any reference, by whatever form of words, to the 
acceding States shall be construed as not including a 
reference to any of the merged States or to any of the 
States (other than the United State of Saurashtra) 
mentioned in the States' Merger (Chief Commissioners'  
  Provinces) Order, <year>1949</year> as amended by the States' Merger 
 (United Provinces) Order, <year>1949</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1109396</tid>
<number>b</number>any reference, by whatever form of words, to Indian 
British subjects shall be deemed to include a reference 
to persons who, immediately before the 1st day of 
August, <year>1949</year>, were subjects of any of the merged States 
or of any of the States (other than the United State of  
  Saurashtra) mentioned in the States' Merger (Chief  
  Commissioners' Provinces) Order, <year>1949</year>, as amended by 
the States' Merger (United Provinces) Order, <year>1949</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>843619</tid>
<number>c</number>any reference, by whatever form of words, to the 
Provinces generally or to the Chief Commissioners' 
Provinces generally shall be construed as including a 
reference to the new Provinces; and

</section>

<section><tid>1511832</tid>
<number>d</number>any reference, by whatever form of words, to an 
absorbing Province shall be construed as including a 
reference to the merged States which are now 
administered as part of that Province.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>117</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>991156</tid>
<number> 5</number> Repeal of corresponding laws. If immediately before the 
commencement of this Act there is in force in any of the new Provinces 
or merged States an Act, Ordinance, Regulation or other law 
corresponding to an Act, Ordinance or Regulation specified in the 
Schedule, whether such Act, Ordinance or Regulation is in force by 
virtue of an Order under the Extra- Provincial Jurisdiction Act, <year>1947</year>, 
 (47 of <year>1947</year>.) or by virtue of any other legislative power, such 
corresponding law shall upon the commencement of this Act,--
<section><tid>1749498</tid>
<number>a</number>in a new Province, stand repealed, and

</section>

<section><tid>1501774</tid>
<number>b</number>in a merged State, stand repealed to the extent to which 
the law relates to matters with respect to which the 
Dominion Legislature has power to make laws for a 
Governor' s Province.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>777532</tid>
<number> 6</number> Savings.
<section><tid>902323</tid>
<number>1</number>The repeal by section 5 of this Act of any  
corresponding law in force in the new Provinces or merged States 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall not affect--

<subsection><tid>1086458</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of any such law, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1434350</tid>
<number>b</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against any such law, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1925997</tid>
<number>c</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect 
of any such penalty, forfeiture or punishment,
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>89225</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), anything done 
or any action taken, including any appointment or delegation made, 
notification, order, instruction or direction issued, rule, 
regulation, form, bye- law or scheme framed, certificate, patent, 
permit or licence granted or registration effected, under such 
corresponding law shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provision of the Act, Ordinance or Regulation as now 
extended to, and in force in, the new Province or merged State and 
shall continue in force accordingly unless and until superseded by 
anything done or any action taken under the said Act, Ordinance or 
Regulation.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>664994</tid>
<number>7</number>Powers of Courts and other authorities for purposes of 
facilitating application of laws. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application in any of the new Provinces or merged States of any Act, 
Ordinance or Regulation specified in the Schedule, any Court or other 
authority may construe any such Act, Ordinance or Regulation with such 
alterations, not affecting the substance, as may be necessary or 
proper to adapt it to the matter before the Court or other authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>118</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>