<act><tid>1589017</tid>
<title>THE U. P. SUGARCANE CESS (VALIDATION) ACT, <year>1961</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 21st March, <year>1961</year>]

An Act to validate the imposition and collection of cesses on 
sugarcane under certain Acts of Uttar Pradesh.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1746422</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>59390</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
U. P. Sugarcane Cess (Validation) Act, <year>1961</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1204514</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 3rd day of 
February, <year>1961</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1687148</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,--
<section><tid>1426005</tid>
<number>a</number>" cess" means the cess payable under any State Act and 
includes any sum recoverable under any such Act by way of 
interest or penalty;

</section>

<section><tid>1481709</tid>
<number>b</number>" State Act" means any of the following Acts, namely:- 
 (i) The United Provinces Sugar Factories Control Act, 
 <year>1938</year> (U. P. Act 1 of <year>1938</year>).

<subsection><tid>1328273</tid>
<number>ii</number>The U. P. Sugarcane (Regulation of Supply and Pur-  
  chase) Act, <year>1953</year>; (U. P. Act XXIV of <year>1953</year>.) and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1591074</tid>
<number>iii</number>The U. P. Sugarcane Cess Act, <year>1956</year>. (U. P. Act XXII  
  of <year>1956</year>.)



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1232172</tid>
<number> 3</number> Validation of imposition and collection of cesses under State 
Acts during a period.
<section><tid>1186288</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding any judgment, decree or  
order of any court, all cesses imposed, assessed or collected or 
purporting to have been imposed, assessed or collected under any State 
Act <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> before the 3rd day of February, <year>1961</year>] shall be deemed to have 
been validly imposed, assessed or collected in accordance with law, as 
if the provisions of the State Acts and of all notifications, orders 
and rules issued or made thereunder, in so far as such provisions 
relate to the imposition, assessment and collection of such cess had 
been included in and formed part of this section and this section had 
been in force 
at all material times when such cess was imposed, assessed or collect- 
ed; and accordingly,-

<subsection><tid>143555</tid>
<number>a</number>no suit or other proceeding shall be maintained or con- 
tinued in any court for the refund of any cess paid under any 
State Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>904471</tid>
<number>b</number>no court shall enforce a decree or order r directing 
the refund of any cess paid under any State Act; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1242158</tid>
<number>c</number>any cess imposed or assessed under any State Act before 
the 3rd day of February, <year>1961</year> but not collected before that 
date, may be recovered (after assessment of the cess, where  
  necessary) in the manner provided under that Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>22170</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts it is hereby declared that nothing 
in sub- section (1) shall be construed as preventing any person,-

<subsection><tid>1105540</tid>
<number>a</number>from questioning in accordance with the provisions of 
any State Act and rules made thereunder the assessment of any 
cess for any period, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1577116</tid>
<number>b</number>from claiming refund of any cess paid by him in excess 
of the amount due from him under any State Act and the rules 
made thereunder.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1662643</tid>
<number>4</number>Repeal. The U. P. Sugarcane Cess (Validation) Ordinance, <year>1961</year>, 
 (1 of <year>1961</year>.) is here by repealed.

</article>



 </act>