<act><title>THE PRIVATE
SECURITY AGENCIES (REGULATION) ACT, 2005 tc "The Private Security Agencies
(Regulation) Act, 2005"



</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Private Security Agencies (Regulation) Act, 2005. 1. Short title, extent and
commencement.—(1) This Act may be
called the Private Security Agencies (Regulation) Act, 2005."

 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir. (2) It extends to the whole of
India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir."

 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may,
by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 


   




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the
context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
“armoured car service” means the service provided by deployment of
armed guards along with armoured car and such other related services which may
be notified by the Central Government or as the case may be, the State
Government from time to time;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Controlling Authority” means the Controlling Authority appointed
under sub‑section (1) of section 3;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“licence” means a licence granted under sub‑section (5) of
section 7;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“notification” means a notification published in the Official
Gazette;
 </section><section><number>e</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section><number>f</number>
“private security” means security provided by a person, other than a
public servant, to protect or guard any person or property or both and includes
provision of armoured car service;
 </section><section><number>g</number>
“private security agency” means a person or body of persons other
than a government agency, department or organisation engaged in the business of
providing private security services including training to private security
guards or their supervisor or providing private security guards to any
industrial or business undertaking or a company or any other person or property;
 </section><section><number>h</number>
“private security guard” means a person providing private security
with or without arms to another person or property or both and includes a
supervisor;
 </section><section><number>i</number>
“State Government”, in relation to a Union territory, includes the
Administrator of that Union territory appointed by the President under article
239 of the Constitution.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Appointment of Controlling Authority.—
<section><number>1</number>
The State Government shall by notification, designate an officer not below the
rank of a Joint Secretary in the Home Department of the State or an equivalent
officer to be the Controlling Authority, for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The State Government may, for efficient discharge of functions by the
Controlling Authority, provide it with such other officers and staff as that
Government considers necessary.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Persons or Private Security Agency not to engage or provide private security
guard without licence.—No person
shall carry on or commence the business of private security agency, unless he
holds a licence issued under this Act:
 Provided
that the person carrying on the business of private security agency, immediately
before the commencement of this Act, may continue to do so for a period of one
year from the date of such commencement and if he has made an application for
such licence within the said period of one year, till the disposal of such
application:
 Provided
further that no private security agency shall provide private security abroad
without obtaining permission of the Controlling Authority, which shall consult
the Central Government before according such permission.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Eligibility for licence.—An
application for issue of a licence under this Act shall only be considered from
a person after due verification of his antecedents.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Persons not eligible for licence.—
<section><number>1</number>
A person shall not be considered for issue of a licence under this Act, if he
has been­—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
convicted of an offence in connection with promotion, formation or
management of a company (any fraud or misfeasance committed by him in relation
to the company), including, an undischarged insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
convicted by a competent court for an offence, the prescribed punishment
for which is imprisonment of not less than two years; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
keeping links with any organisation or association which is banned under
any law on account of their activities which pose threat to national security or
public order or there is information about such a person indulging in activities
which are prejudicial to national security or public order; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
dismissed or removed from Government service on grounds of misconduct or
moral turpitude.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
A company, firm or an association of persons shall not be considered for issue
of a licence under this Act, if, it is not registered in India, or having a
proprietor or a majority shareholder, partner or director, who is not a citizen
of India.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Application for grant of licence.—
<section><number>1</number>
An application for grant of licence to a private security agency shall be made
to the Controlling Authority in such form as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The applicant shall submit an affidavit incorporating the details in relation to
the provisions contained in section 6, ensure the availability of the training
for its private security guards and supervisors required under sub‑section
(2) of section 9, fulfilment of conditions under section 11 and of cases
registered with police or pending in a court of law involving the applicant.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every application under sub‑section (1) shall be accompanied by a fee
of—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
rupees five thousand if the private security agency is operating in one
district of a State;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
rupees ten thousand if the agency is operating in more than one but up to
five districts of a State; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
rupees twenty‑five thousand if it is operating in the whole State.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number>
On receipt of an application under sub‑section (1), the Controlling
Authority may, after making such inquiries as it considers necessary and
obtaining no objection certificate from the concerned police authority, by order
in writing, either grant a licence or refuse to grant the same within a period
of sixty days from the date of receipt of application with complete particulars
and the prescribed fee:
 Provided
that no order of refusal shall be made unless—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the applicant has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the grounds on which licence is refused is mentioned in the order.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number>
A licence granted under this section—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
shall be valid for a period of five years unless the same is cancelled
under sub‑section (1) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
may be renewed from time to time after the expiry of five years, for a
further period of five years on payment of such fee as may be prescribed; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
shall be subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.
  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> An
application for renewal of licence shall be made to the Controlling Authority,
not less than forty‑five days before the date of expiry of the period of
validity thereof, in such form as may be prescribed and shall be accompanied by
the requisite fee and other documents required under sections 6, 7 and 11 of
this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Controlling Authority shall pass an order on application for renewal of
licence within thirty days from the date of receipt of application complete in
all respects.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
On receipt of an application under sub‑section (1), the Controlling
Authority may, after making such inquiries as he considers necessary and by
order in writing, renew the licence or refuse to renew the same:
 Provided
that no order of refusal shall be made except after giving the applicant a
reasonable opportunity of being heard.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Conditions for commencement of operation and engagement of supervisors.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every private security agency shall, within six months of obtaining the licence,
commence its activities.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every private security agency shall ensure imparting of such training and skills
to its private security guards and supervisors as may be prescribed:
 Provided
that the person carrying on the business of private security agency, before the
commencement of this Act, shall ensure the required training to its security
guards and supervisors within a period of one year from the date of such
commencement.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every private security agency shall, within sixty days from the date of issue of
the licence, employ such number of supervisors, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
A private security agency shall not employ or engage a person as a supervisor
unless he fulfils the conditions specified in sub‑section (1) of
section 10.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
While engaging a supervisor of private security guards, every private security
agency shall give preference to a person who has experience of serving in the
Army, Navy, Air Force, any other Armed forces of the Union or State Police
including armed constabular­ies and Home Guards for a period of not less than
three years.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Eligibility to be a private security guard.—
<section><number>1</number>
A private security agency shall not employ or engage any person as a private
security guard unless he—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
is a citizen of India or a citizen of such other country as the Central
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
has completed eighteen years of age but has not attained the age of
sixty‑five years;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
satisfies the agency about his character and antecedents in such manner
as may be prescribed;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
has completed the prescribed security training successfully;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
fulfils such physical standards as may be prescribed; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
satisfies such other conditions as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
No person who has been convicted by a competent court or who has been dismissed
or removed on grounds of misconduct or moral turpitude while serving in any of
the armed forces of the Union, State Police Organisations, Central or State
Governments or in any private security agency shall be employed or engaged as a
private security guard or a supervisor.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every private security agency may, while employing a person as a private
security guard, give preference to a person who has served as a member in one or
more of the following, namely:—
 <subsection><number>i</number>
Army;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
Navy;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
Air Force;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
any other armed forces of the Union;
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>
Police, including armed constabularies of States; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number>
Home Guards.
  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Conditions of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> The State
Government may frame rules to prescribe the conditions on which licence shall be
granted under this Act and such conditions shall include requirements as to the
training which the licensee is to undergo, details of the person or persons
forming the agency, obligation as to the information to be provided from time to
time to the Controlling Authority regarding any change in their address, change
of management and also about any criminal charge made against them in the course
of their performance of duties of the private security agency or as the case may
be, a private security guard employed or engaged by them.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The State Government may make provision in the rules to verify about imparting
of required training by the private security agency under sub‑section (2)
of section 9 and to review continuation or otherwise of licence of such private
security agency which may not have adhered to the condition of ensuring the
required training.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Licence to be exhibited.—Every
private security agency shall exhibit its licence or copy thereof in a
conspicuous place of its business.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Cancellation and suspension of licence.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Controlling Authority may cancel any licence on any one or more of the
following grounds, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
that the licence has been obtained on misrepresentation or suppression of
material facts;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
that the licence holder has used false documents or photographs;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
that the licence holder has violated the provisions of this Act or the
rules made thereunder or any of the conditions of the licence;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
that the licence holder has misused information obtained by him during
the discharge of his duties as the private security agency to any industrial or
business undertaking or a company or any other person;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
that the licence holder by using any letter‑head, advertisement or
any other printed matter or in any other manner represented that the private
security agency is an instrumentality of the Government or such agency is or has
been using a name different from that for which licence has been granted;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
that the licence holder is or has been impersonating or permitting or
aiding or abetting any body to impersonate as a public servant;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
that the private security agency had failed to commence its activities or
to engage a supervisor within the specified time period;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
that the licence holder is or has wilfully failed or refused to render
the services agreed to any person;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
that the licence holder has done any act which is in violation of a court
order or an order of a lawful authority or is or has been advising, encouraging
or assisting any person to violate any such order;
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
that the licence holder has violated the provisions of the Acts given in
the Schedule which may be modified by the Central Government, by notification in
the Official Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
that there have been repeated instances when the private security guard
or guards provided by the private security agency—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> failed
to provide private security or were guilty of gross negligence in not providing
such security;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> committed
a breach of trust or misappropriated the property or a part thereof which they
were supposed to protect;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> were
found habitually drunk or indisciplined;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> were
found to be involved in committing crimes; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> had
connived or abetted a crime against the person or property placed under their
charge; or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>l</number>
that the licence holder has done any act which poses a threat to national
security, or did not provide assistance to the police or other authority in the
discharge of its duties or acted in a manner prejudicial to national security or
public order or law and order.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where the Controlling Authority, for reasons to be recorded in writing, is
satisfied that pending the question of cancelling of licence on any of the
grounds mentioned in sub-­section (1) above, it is necessary to do so, that
Controlling Authority may, by order in writing, suspend the operation of the
licence for such period not exceeding thirty days as may be specified in the
order and require the licence holder to show cause, within fifteen days from the
date of issue of such order, as to why the suspension of the licence should not
be extended till the determination of the question of cancellation.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every order of suspending or cancelling of a licence shall be in writing and
shall specify the reasons for such suspension or cancellation and a copy thereof
shall be communicated to the person affected.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
No order of cancellation of licence under sub‑section (1) shall be made
unless the person concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of being
heard.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by
an order of the Controlling Authority refusing the licence under
sub‑section (4) of section 7 or renewal under sub‑section (3) of
section 8 or order of suspension of licence under sub‑section (2) of
section 13 or cancellation of licence under sub‑section (1) of that
section, may prefer an appeal against that order to the Home Secretary of the
State Government within a period of sixty days of the date of such order:
 Provided
that an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the said period of sixty days
if the appellant satisfies the State Government that he has sufficient cause for
not preferring the appeal within that period.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every appeal under sub‑section (1) shall be made in such form as may be
prescribed and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Before disposing of an appeal, the State Government shall give the appellant a
reasonable opportunity of being heard.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>15</number>
Register to be maintained by a private security agency.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every private security agency shall maintain a register containing—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the names and addresses of the persons managing the private security
agency;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the names, addresses, photographs and salaries of the private
security guards and supervisors under its control;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the names and addresses of the persons whom it had provided private
security guards or services; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
such other particulars as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The Controlling Authority may call for such information as it considers
necessary from any private security agency, supervisor or private security guard
to ensure due compliance of the Act.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>16</number>
Inspection of licence, etc.—The
Controlling Authority or any other officer authorised by it in this behalf may
at any reasonable time, enter the premises of the private security agency and
inspect and examine the place of business, the records, accounts and other
documents connected with the licence and may take copy of any document.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>17</number>
Issue of photo identity card.—
<section><number>1</number>
Every private security guard shall be issued a photo identity card, by the
private security agency employing or engaging the guard.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The photo identity card under sub‑section (1) shall be issued in such form
as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every private security guard or supervisor shall carry on his person the photo
identity card issued under sub‑section (1) and shall produce it on demand
for inspection by the Controlling Authority or any other officer authorised by
it in this behalf.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>18</number>
Disclosure of information to unauthorized person.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any person who may be or has been employed or engaged as a private security
guard by the private security agency shall not divulge to anyone other than the
employer, or in such manner and to such person as the employer directs, any
information acquired by him during such employment with respect to the work
which he has been assigned by such employer, except such disclosure as may be
required under this Act or in connection with any inquiry or investigation by
the police or as may be required by an authority or process of law.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
All private security guards of a private security agency shall render necessary
assistance to the police or to such authority in the process of any
investigation pertaining to the activities of that agency.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
If violation of any law is noticed by any private security guard during the
course of discharge of his duties, he shall bring it to the notice of his
superior, who in turn shall inform the police either through his employer or
agency or on his own.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>19</number>
Delegation.—The State Government
may, by notification, direct that any power or function (except the powers to
make rules under section 25)—
 <section><number>a</number>
which may be exercised or performed by it, or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
which may be exercised or performed by the Controlling Authority,
 under
this Act, may, in relation to such matter and subject to such conditions, if
any, as may be specified in the notification, be also exercised or performed by
such officer or authority subordinate to the Government or officer subordinate
to the Controlling Authority, as may be specified in such notification.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>20</number>
Punishment for contravention of certain provisions.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any person who contravenes the provisions of section 4 shall be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may
extend to twenty‑five thousand rupees, or with both.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Any person or private security agency who contravenes, the provisions of
sections 9, 10 and 12 of the Act, shall be punishable with a fine which may
extend to twenty‑five thousand rupees, in addition to suspension or
cancellation of the licence.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>21</number>
Penalty for unauthorized use of certain uniforms.—If
any private security guard or supervisor wears the uniform of the Army, Air
force, Navy or any other armed forces of the Union or Police or any dress having
the appearance or bearing any of the distinctive marks of that uniform, he and
the proprietor of the private security agency shall be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine which may
extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>22</number>
Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an
offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person who at the
time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the company,
shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded
against and punished accordingly:
 Provided
that nothing contained in this sub‑section shall render any such person
liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without
his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the
commission of such offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub‑section (1), where any offence
under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence
has been committed with the consent or connivance of or is attributable to, any
neglect on the part of any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the
company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and
punished accordingly.
 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this section—
 <subsection><number>a</number> "company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other
association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>23</number>
Indemnity.—No suit, prosecution or
other legal proceeding shall lie against the Controlling authority or any other
officer authorised by it in respect of anything in good faith done or intended
to be done under this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>24</number>
Framing of model rules for adoption by States.—The
Central Government may, frame model rules in respect of all or any of the
matters with respect to which the State Government may make rules under this
Act, and where any such model rules have been framed the State Government shall,
while making any rules in respect of that matter under section 25, so far as is
practicable, conform to such model rules.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>25</number>
Power of State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number>
The State Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power,
such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
the procedure for verification of character and antecedents under clause
(c) of sub‑section (1) of section 10; the type of training under clause
(d) of sub‑section (1) of section 10; the physical standard under clause
(e) of sub‑section (1) of section 10; and other conditions under clause
(f) of sub‑section (1) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the number of supervisors to be employed under sub‑section (3) of
section 9;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the form of an application for grant of licence under sub‑section
(1) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
the form in which the licence to be granted under sub‑section (4)
of section 7 and conditions subject to which such licence to be granted under
section 11;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
the form of an application for renewal of licence under sub‑section
(1) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
the form under sub‑section (2) of section 14 for preferring an
appeal;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
particulars to be maintained in a register under sub‑section (1) of
section 15;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
the form in which photo identity card under sub‑section (2) of 
section 17 be issued;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as
soon as may be after it is made, before each House of the State Legislature
where it consists of two Houses, or where such Legislature consists of one
House, before that House.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
In respect of Union territories, every rule made to carry out the provisions of
the Act shall be laid before each House of Parliament and where there exists a
Legislative Assembly, before that Assembly.
  
  

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The
Private Security Agencies (Regulation) Act, 2005
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


The
Schedule
 


[See
section 13(1)(j)]
 

(1)
The Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936).
 

(2)
The Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947).
 

(3)
The Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 1948).
 

(4)
The Employees’ Provident Funds and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1952
(19 of 1952).
 

(5)
The Payment of Bonus Act, 1965 (21 of 1965).
 

(6)
The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 (37 of 1970).
 

(7)
The Payment of Gratuity Act, 1972 (39 of 1972).
 

(8)
The Equal Remuneration Act, 1976 (25 of 1976).
 

(9)
The Inter‑State Migrant Workmen (Regulation of Employment and
Conditions of Service) Act, 1979 (30 of 1979).

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came
into force on 15-3-2006, vide S.O. 317(E), dated 14th March, 2006.    tc " 1.	Came into force on 15-3-2006,  vide
 S.O. 317(E), dated 14th March, 2006."
   
  tc
" (3) It shall come into force on
such date 1  as the Central Government may,
by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>