<act><tid>1603427</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN POWER ALCOHOL ACT, <year>1948</year></title>

ACT NO. 22 OF <year>1948</year>
[ 3rd April, <year>1948</year>.]

An Act to provide for the development of the power alcohol industry.

WHEREAS it is expedient in the public interest that the power 
alcohol industry should be developed under the control of the Central 
Government;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>544228</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and duration.
<section><tid>1896390</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Indian Power Alcohol Act, <year>1948</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>211868</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir].

</section>

<section><tid>1615487</tid>
<number>3</number>This Act or such portion thereof shall come into force in 
such area, and on such date as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1120667</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union. It is 
hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that the 
Union should take under its control the power alcohol industry.]


</article>



<article><tid>400475</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>807253</tid>
<number>a</number>" molasses" means the heavy, dark- coloured residual syrup 
drained away in the final stage of the manufacture of 
sugar by vacuum pans in sugar factories either from 
sugarcane or by refining gur, when such a syrup has 
fermentable sugars (expressed as reducing sugars), but 
does not include the final residual syrup left in the 
manufacture of sugar by the open pan process;

</section>

<section><tid>500489</tid>
<number>b</number>" petrol" means dangerous petroleum as defined in clause 
 (b) of section 2 of the Petroleum Act, <year>1934</year> (30 of  
  <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1491654</tid>
<number>c</number>" power alcohol" means ethyl alcohol containing not less 
than 99. 5 per cent. by volume of ethanol measured at 
sixty degrees Fahrenheit corresponding to 74. 4 over 
proof strength.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 73 of <year>1952</year>, s. 2, for" except Part B States". 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1276890</tid>
<number> 4</number> Production of power alcohol.
<section><tid>1525944</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall manufacture  
power alcohol from any substance other than molasses or such other 
substance as may be specified by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>319642</tid>
<number>2</number>If any dispute arises as to whether any substance is or is 
not molasses, the decision of an officer, authorized by the Central 
Government in this behalf, regarding such dispute shall be final and 
shall not be called in question in any Court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>409166</tid>
<number>5</number>Power to regulate production and disposal of power alcohol. 
The Central Government may regulate the production and disposal of 
power alcohol by any situated in any area in which this section is for 
the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>1132472</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to direct use of power alcohol as motive power.
<section><tid>1125566</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
direct that in such area as may be specified therein no petrol shall 
be sold or kept for sale except with an admixture of power alcohol.

</section>

<section><tid>643656</tid>
<number>2</number>The proportion of petrol and power alcohol in such mixture 
shall in any area and for any purpose be such as may from time to time 
be specified by the Central Government but such proportion of power 
alcohol in the case of mixture with petrol meant for use as motive 
power for any motor vehicle shall not be more than twenty- five per 
cent. or less than five per cent. by volume.

</section>

<section><tid>417780</tid>
<number>3</number>The power alcohol to be employed for such mixture shall be 
obtained from such distilleries as may, from time to time, be 
specified by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1971693</tid>
<number>7</number>Penalty. Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of sections 
 4 and 6 or any order of the Central Government issued thereunder shall 
be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six months or with 
fine not exceeding one thousand rupees or with both, and in the case 
of a continued contravention with a further fine which may extend to 
one hundred rupees for every day during which the contravention is 
continued after conviction therefor.


</article>



<article><tid>804205</tid>
<number> 8</number> Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power conferred 
by this Act shall, subject to such conditions, if any, as may be 
specified in the direction, be exercisable also by--
<section><tid>1306566</tid>
<number>a</number>such officer or authority subordinate to the Central 
Government, or

</section>

<section><tid>1261113</tid>
<number>b</number>Such State Government or such other officer or authority 
subordinate to a State Government
as may be specified in the direction.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>45726</tid>
<number>9</number>Offences to be bailable. All offences punishable under this 
Act or any rule made thereunder shall be bailable within the meaning 
of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1450057</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1093790</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> for the purpose of 
carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>517419</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such rules may--

<subsection><tid>29122</tid>
<number>a</number>provide for the licensing of the manufacture of power 
alcohol;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>964724</tid>
<number>b</number>prescribe the specifications and tests in respect of 
the purity of power alcohol intended for admixture with 
petrol in order to ensure its suitability for use in 
motor vehicles;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1077983</tid>
<number>c</number>fix the price at which power alcohol may be sold for the 
purpose of admixture with petrol;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>343411</tid>
<number>d</number>provide for imposing and collecting a duty of excise on 
power alcohol intended for admixture with petrol;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1122588</tid>
<number>e</number>prescribe conditions in respect of the transport and 
storage of power alcohol intended for admixture with 
petrol and for the manner in which the admixture is to 
be affected;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1516886</tid>
<number>f</number>prescribe the submission by a manufacturer of power 
alcohol or importer or distributor of petrol of 
returns regarding the power alcohol and petrol 
manufactured, purchased, stored or sold, as the case 
may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1483688</tid>
<number>g</number>provide for denaturing of power alcohol at the 
distilleries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>312753</tid>
<number>h</number>provide for any other matter which is to be or may be 
prescribed under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1436015</tid>
<number>3</number>Rules made under this Act may provide that any contravention 
of such rules shall render the offender liable on conviction to a fine 
not exceeding one thousand rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>213865</tid>
<number>11</number>Power of exemption. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
this Act, the Central Government may, by notification <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in the 
Official Gazette, declare that any of the provisions of this Act shall 
not apply to any case or class of cases.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For the Indian Power Alcohol Rules, <year>1950</year>, see Gazette of India, 
Extraordinary, <year>1952</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 909. 
2. For such notifications, see Gazette of India, <year>1953</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 
3, pp. 549 and 756 and ibid., <year>1955</year>, p. 240.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>