<act><tid>1604024</tid>
<title>THE LEVY SUGAR PRICE EQUALISATION FUND ACT, <year>1976</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 16th February, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment, in the interest of the 
general public,' of a fund to ensure that the price of levy sugar may 
be uniform throughout India and for matters connected therewith or 
incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>41630</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>237830</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Levy Sugar Price Equalisation Fund Act, <year>1976</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1645214</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>765616</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1013397</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1918391</tid>
<number>a</number>" controlled price" means the price of the relevant 
grade of levy sugar, determined from time to time under sub- 
section (3C) of section 3 of. the Essential Commodities Act, 
<year>1955</year>, (10 of <year>1955</year>.) or under the Defence and Internal 
Security of India Rules, <year>1971</year>, in relation to any year of 
production;

</section>

<section><tid>1750088</tid>
<number>b</number>" excess realisation", in relation to each grade of levy 
sugar,-

<subsection><tid>615652</tid>
<number>i</number>means the price realised by any producer, on the sale of 
levy sugar of such grade, in excess of-

<subsubsection><tid>329276</tid>
<number>a</number>the controlled price, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>182</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number>   1. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>: Vide Notifn. No. G. S. R. 251 (E), dt. 25- 3- <year>1976</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>107631</tid>
<number>b</number>where any fair price has been fixed by a court for levy 
sugar of such grade, such fair price, and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1734313</tid>
<number>ii</number>includes any realisation representing the difference 
between the controlled price and the price allowed by the 
court by an interim order, if such interim order is set 
aside, whether by the court which made the order or in appeal 
or revision;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby 
declared that where in relation to levy sugar of any grade 
sold by any producer, the producer has realised towards 
duties of excise with respect to such sugar any amount in 
excess of the amount payable by way of such duties, such 
excess shall also be deemed to be excess realisation within, 
meaning of this, clause;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>621261</tid>
<number>c</number>" fair price", in relation to levy sugar, means the 
price fixed by the court in excess of the controlled price, 
and, where an interim price, fixed by the court, is 
superseded by a price which is finally fixed by the court, 
the price so finally fixed;

</section>

<section><tid>321563</tid>
<number>d</number>" Fund" means the Levy Sugar Price Equalisation Fund, 
established under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1218246</tid>
<number>e</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" levy sugar" means the sugar requisitioned by the 
Central Government under clause (f) of sub- section (2) of 
section 3 of the Essential Commodities Act, <year>1955</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1552864</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1099663</tid>
<number>g</number>" producer" means a person carrying on the business of 
manufacturing sugar by the vacuum pan process.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>953897</tid>
<number> 3</number> Levy Sugar Price Equalisation Fund.
<section><tid>1473785</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
established a Fund, to be called the Levy Sugar Price Equalisation 
Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1303880</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> provided in sub- section (5)] there shall 
be credited to the Fund, in such manner as may be prescribed,-

<subsection><tid>1437337</tid>
<number>a</number>the amounts representing all excess realisations made 
by the producers, irrespective of whether such excess 
realisations were made before or after the commencement of 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1345461</tid>
<number>b</number>the amounts representing any loans which may be 
advanced, or grants which may be made, by the Central 
Government for carrying out the objects of the Fund.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>961213</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> provided in sub- section (5)] every 
producer shall,-

<subsection><tid>861731</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of an excess realisation made before the 
commencement of this Act, within thirty days from such 
commencement,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1255099</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of an excess realisation made after such 
commencement, within thirty days from the date on which such 
excess realisation was made,
credit to the Fund, the amount representing such excess realisations, 
together with interest due thereon at the rate of twelve and a half 
per cent. per annum, from the date on which such amount was realised 
by him;

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that--


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>861731</tid>
<number>a</number>the interest due on so much of any amount of any excess 
realisation made before the date of commencement of the Levy 
Sugar Price Equalisation Fund (Amendment) Act, <year>1984</year>, as is 
not credited to the Fund together with interest at the 
aforesaid rate of twelve and a half per cent. per annum 
before the expiry of, sixty days from the date of such 
commencement; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1255099</tid>
<number>b</number>the interest due on so much of the amount of any excess 
realisation made on or after the date of such commencement as 
is not credited to the Fund together with interest at the 
aforesaid rate of twelve and a half per cent. per annum 
within sixty days from the date on which such amount was 
realised,
shall be at the rate of fifteen per cent. per annum from the 
date on which such amount was realised by the producer];


<pagefootnote><pagenum>183</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. and subs. by Act 54 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2 (retrospectively.)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. and ins by s. 3, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>