<act><title>


the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals 
    (Transport of Animals on Foot) Rules, 20011</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Transport of 
    Animals on Foot) Rules, 2001.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette. 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “animal” means livestock and includes 
    the following animals, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>     cattle including cow, bulls and 
    bullocks, buffalo bulls and bullocks, cows, buffaloes, Mithuns, yaks and 
    calves;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>     equines including horse, ponies, 
    mules and donkeys;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>     horse including entires (stallions), 
    goldings, brood mares, colts and fillies;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>     goat including adult goat, male or 
    female of two years age and above;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>     ruck including male goat;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>     kid young goat below one year of age;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>     nanny female goat;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>     sheep including adult sheep, male 
    or female of two years age and above;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number>     ewe female sheep;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>     lamb young sheep below one year of 
    age;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>     ram male sheep;  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>xii</number>     whether includes male lamb that has 
    been castrated before reaching sexual maturity;  
 </section><section>
<number>xiii</number>     pig includes adult pig, male or 
    female of one year of age or above;   
 </section><section>
<number>xiv</number>     piglet includes young pig below one 
    year of age.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “veterinary doctor” means a person 
    registered with the Veterinary Council of India established under the Indian 
    Veterinary Council Act, 1984 (52 of 1984).   
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to 
    these rules.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Application of the 
      rules.—These rules shall apply to transport of animals on foot when 
      the distance from the boundary of village or town or city of the origin of 
      such transport to the last destination is 5 km or more than 5 km.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Condition of health of animals 
    transported on foot.—
<section><number>1</number> Every animal to be transported on foot shall be 
    healthy and in good condition for such transport.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A certificate of a veterinary doctor in 
    respect of each animal to be transported to the effect that such animal is 
    in a fit condition for such transportation and is not suffering from any 
    infectious, contagious or parasitic diseases and that it has been vaccinated 
    against any infectious, contagious or parasitic diseases shall accompany 
    such animal.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The certificate under sub-rule (1) shall 
    be in the form as specified in the First Schedule.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Certain animals not to transport on foot.—New 
    born animals of which the navel has not completely healed, diseased, blind, 
    emaciated, lame, fatigued, or having given birth during the preceding 
    seventy two hours or likely to give birth during transport shall not be 
    transported on foot.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Transport in on-farm social group.—Animals 
    shall be transported in their on-farm social groups (established at least 
    one week prior to journey).   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> First aid equipment to accompany the 
    animals transported on foot.—The owner of the animals shall provide 
    veterinary first aid equipment to be accompanied with such animals while 
    transported on foot. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Certificate to be carried during 
    transportation.—In case the person transporting the animals on foot is 
    not the owner of the animal then such person shall carry a certificate as 
    specified in the Second Schedule during such transportation.   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Watering arrangement during 
    transportation of animals.—The owner of the animals shall make watering 
    arrangement in route during transport of such animals on foot.   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Feed and fodder arrangements during 
    transportation of animals.—Sufficient feed and fodder with adequate 
    reserve of such feed and fodder for the animals shall be made available by 
    their owner during their transport on foot   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number>  Prohibition of the use of whip, etc. 
    during transportation of animals on foot.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall use a whip 
    or a stick in order to force the animal to walk or to hasten the pace of 
    their walk nor such person shall apply chillies or any other substance to 
    any part of the body of the animal for this purpose during their 
    transportation on foot.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any animal needs to be tied during 
    transport on foot, it shall be tied by a rope covered with suitable 
    cushioning such as cloth around its leg and such animal shall not be tied by 
    its nose, all legs or any other part of the body except by its neck.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If more than one animal is to be tied 
    adjacent to one another by a single rope during their transport on foot, the 
    space between any two of such animals shall be minimum two feet and animals 
    so tied shall be of similar physical condition and strength and no more than 
    two such animals shall be tied adjacent to each other by a single rope.   
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Certain prohibition on transport of 
    animals on foot.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall transport on foot an animal before 
    sunrise or after sunset.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No animal shall be transported on foot 
    beyond the distance, time, rest interval and temperature specified for such 
    animal in the Table below, namely,— 
 
Note.—After being provided with water 
    every animal shall be given a break of 20 minutes before the commencement of 
    the transport of the animal on foot and in case of feeding the break shall 
    be given for one hour before the commencement of the transport of the animal 
    on foot. 
 

 
TABLE
 
 
 
 
 
Species (Animal)
        
 
Maximum distance  covered/day/hour
 
Maximum no. of walking/day of hours (travelling)
 
Period of rest  
        (Interval) 
 
Temperature range Max.Min
        

 
 
Cattle (Cows)
 
 
30  Km/day
        
 
4 km/hr 
  
 
8 hours 
 
At every 2 hours for drinking and at 
        every 4 hrs. for feeding
 
12 deg. C. to 30 deg.C.
        

 
 
Buffaloes
 
 
25  Km/day
        
 
3 km/hr 
 
8 hours
 
At every 2 hours for drinking and at 
        every 4 hrs. for feeding
 
12 deg. C. to 30 deg.C.
        

 
 
Cows and  
        Buffaloes calves
 
 
16  Km/day
        
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>5 km/hr
 
 
6 hours 
 
At every 1½ hours for drinking and at 
        every 3 hrs. for feeding
 
15 deg. C. to 25 deg.C.
        

 
 
Horses, Ponies, Mules, Donkeys
        

 
 
45  Km/day
        
 
6 km/hr 
 
8 hours
 
At every 3 hours for drinking and at 
        every 6 hrs. for feeding
 
12 deg. C. to 30 deg.C.
        

 
 
 Young ones (foal)
        
 
 
25  Km/day
        
 
4 km/hr 
  
 
6 hours 
 
At every 2 hours for drinking and at 
        every 4 hrs. for feeding
 
15 deg. C. to 25 deg.C.
        

 
 
Goats and Sheep
 
 
30  Km/day
        
 
4 km/hr 
 
8 hours 
 
At every 2 hours for drinking and at 
        every 4 hrs. for feeding
 
12 deg. C. to 30 deg.C.
        

 
 
 
Kids and Lambs 
 
 
16  Km/day
        
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>5 km/hr
 
 
6 hours 
 
 
At every 1½ hours for drinking and at 
        every 3 hrs for feeding
 
 
15 deg. C. to 25 deg.C.
        

 
 
Pigs 
 
 
15  Km/day
        
 
2 km/hr 
 
8 hours
 
At every 1½ hours for drinking and at 
        every 3 hrs. for feeding
 
12 deg. C. to 25 deg.C.
        

 
 
 
 Piglets
 
 
 10 
        Km/day 
 </section><section>
<number>1</number>5 km/hr
 
 
 6 
        hours 
 
 
 At every 1½ hours for drinking and at every 
        3 hrs. for feeding
 
 
 15 
        deg. C. to 25 deg.C. 


 
 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No animal shall be made to walk under 
    conditions of heavy rain, thunderstorms or extremely dry or sultry 
    conditions during its transport on foot. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Transportation of animals in certain 
    cases not permitted without shoes.—Animals whose hooves are not provided 
    with shoes (as in the case of pack or draught animals) shall not be 
    transported on foot on hard cement, bitumen-coated or metalled roads, steep 
    gradients or hilly and rocky terrain, irrespective of weather conditions 
    (summer or winter).  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Power of police to require the owner to 
    take animal to nearest Magistrate.—
<section><number>1</number> If any police officer above the 
    rank of constable or any other person authorised in this behalf by the 
    Central or State Government or by the Animal Welfare Board of India by the 
    general or special order, has reason to believe that an offence has been or 
    is being committed in respect of an animal in contravention of these rules, 
    he may require the owner or other person in charge of such animal to take 
    the animal to the nearest magistrate.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the owner or the person in charge of 
    the animals referred to in sub-rule (1) refuses to comply with the demands 
    of the police officer under that sub-rule, it shall be lawful for such 
    police officer or such other persons to take the animal to the nearest 
    magistrate.   
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals 
    (Transport of Animals on Foot) Rules, 2001
 

 
 

 
 


FIRST SCHEDULE
 



Form for Certificate of 
    fitness for transport of animals
 


[See rule 4(3)] 
 


This Certificate should 
    be completed and signed by a qualified Veterinary Doctor
 


Date and time of 
    examination:
 


Species  
 


Number of Trucks/Railway 
    Wagons
 


Number of Cattle  
 


Sex Age
 


Identification 
 


Breed 
    (giving characteristics).—Area where it is found with status regarding 
    general resistance and heat tolerance.
 


Individual Features of 
    the animal— 

    Body Colour,
 


     Height,  

    Body weight (approx) 

    animal length,  

    breath (measured between pelvic bones),  

    colour of the eyes,  

    shape of the horns,  

    general conditions (like fleshy, bony projections)
 


Health Status
 


History of the animal, 
    feed status whether or not sign of anorexia/diarrohea
 


1.  Record Body 
    Temperature  
 


2.  Examine eyes for 
    bulging or protrusion of eyeball, blindness, Corneal opacity &amp; specify.
 


3.  Condition of skin, 
    (including signs of dehydration, injuries, anorexia (check for presence of 
    warts on the skin)
 


4.  Ears—
 


     Examine ears—(check 
    for animal body response to hearing, check for any infection, inflammation 
    or secretion (a) excess of wax, blood or any fluid)
 


5.  Examine sub maxillary 
    spell for swelling (for any abnormality or pain)
 


6.  Check for status of 
    pregnancy of female animal  

    If yes – which stage 1st, 2nd or 3rd stage.
 


7.  Examine udder &amp; teats 
    &amp; specify
 


     a. Relative size of 
    quarters.
 


     b. Check for signs 
    or swelling/atrophy/fibrous
 


     c. In duration on 
    palpation of individual quarter and specify.
 


     d. Check teat canal 
    for teat tumour or fibrosis of teat canal and specify.
 


8.   (a)   If female – 
    check 
 


     Check for sign of 
    vaginal discharge on examination of the vulva and specify
 


      (b)   In male – 
    check
 


Testicles—   Size, any 
    sign/abnormalities of monogastric 

    animals.
 


Penis—        injury, 
    abrasions or the sheath, discharges to be recorded
 


9.  Sign of abdominal 
    pain (check for gait or posture of the animal, check for signs of abdominal 
    distention, left flank to be checked for rumen examination (full, empty 
    tympani/blood
 


10.  Digestive System
 


       Examine mouth and 
    specify
 


         1.   Detail out 
    dentition
 


         2.   Specify – 
    evidences of
 


               – tooth 
    damage
 


               – broken 
    or worn incisors.
 


11.  Respiratory system—
 


       (a)   Record 
    Respiration rate.
 


       (b)   Auscultation 
    &amp; specify for signs of dyspnoea, respiratory distress &amp; specify.
 


12.  In cows possessing 
    horns check and specify—
 


       (a)   shape of 
    horns  
 


       (b)   number of 
    horn rings  
 


        (c)   any 
    difference in the direction  
 


       (d)   or 
    appearance of two horns.  
 


13.  Examine ribs for 
    fracture and specify.
 


14.  Examine abdominal 
    wall for presence of ventral or umbilical hernia and specify.
 


15.  Examine limbs and 
    joints for bony enlargements or synovial distentions &amp; specify check for 
    signs of lameness – specify
 


16.  Examine interdigital 
    space for any lesions check and specify.
 


17.  Any indications of 
    foot soreness, excessive wear of soles or laminitis.
 


18.  Examine circulatory 
    system—  
 


         1.   Specify 
    Pulse rate.  
 


         2.   Check for 
    presence of oedema dependent portion or ascitis and specify.
 


19.  Transported 
    from...................to.........................via
 

 
 


I hereby certify that I 
    have read the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Transport of Animals on 
    Foot) Rules, 2001.
 


1. That, at the request 
    of (consignor)............................I examined the above-mentioned 
    Cattle in the goods vehicle/railway wagons not more than 12 hours before 
    their departure.
 


2. That each cattle 
    appeared to be in a fit condition to travel by rail/road and is not showing 
    any signs of infectious or contagious or parasitic disease and that it has 
    been vaccinated against rinderpest and any other infections or contagious or 
    parasitic disease(s).
 


3. That the cattle were 
    adequately fed and watered for the purpose of the journey. 
 


4. That the cattle have 
    been vaccinated. 
 


 
     (a) Type of 
    vaccine                                (b)   Date of vaccination
 

 
 



    Signed..............................
 



    Date......................  
 



    Address..............................
 



    ........................................
 



    Qualification.........................
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals 
    (Transport of Animals on Foot) Rules, 2001
 

 
 

 
 


SECOND SCHEDULE
 



Authorisation Certificate
 


(See rule 8)
 


1.    Name and age of the 
    Owner:
 


2.    Father's Name: 
 


3.    Address of the 
    Owner: 
 


4.    No. of animals for 
    transport specifying species, age and sex of each animal:
 


5.    Name of the 
    person/persons transporting the animals.
 


6.    Specify the place 
    of origin and the place of last destination of such animals for transport:
 


7.    Attach a copy of 
    the veterinary certificate granted under Rule 8
 


8.    Details of feed, 
    fooder and watering arrangements provided during transoport of such animals.
 

 
 


I do hereby declare that 
    I am the owner of the aforementioned animals. I have authorized Shri 
    ...........................S/o...........................r/o..................................to 
    transport the said animals. I have read and understood the Transport of 
    Animals on Foot Rules, 2001 and undertake that the said Rules have been and 
    would be complied with during transport.
 


I do hereby state that 
    the above information is true and correct. 
 


Sd/-
 


(Owner)
 


To be filled-in by the 
    Transporter
 



    I............................S/o....................................r/o........................................do 
    hereby give my consent to transport the aforementioned animals from the 
    aforesaid place of origin to the place of destination.
 


I have read and 
    understood the Transport of Animals on Foot Rules, 2001 and undertake that 
    the said Rules would be complied with during transport.
 


I do hereby state that 
    the above information is true and correct.
 


Sd/-
 


(Transporter)
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>