<act><tid>1608688</tid>
<title>THE RIVER BOARDS ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 49 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 12th September, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of River Boards for the 
regulation and development of inter- State rivers and river valleys.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>430174</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>849969</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
River Boards Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1611407</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1725379</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to expediency of control by Central Government. It is hereby 
declared that it is expedient in the public interest th


</article>



<article><tid>46509</tid>
<number>3</number>Definitions. In this Act, unless the context 
otherwiserequires,- (a)" Board" means a River Board established 
under section 4; (b)" Gover
CHAP

ESTABLISHMENT OF RIVER BOARDS

CHAPTER II

ESTABLISHMENT OF RIVER BOARDS



</article>



<article><tid>1348184</tid>
<number> 4</number> Establishment of Boards.
<section><tid>1562522</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, on a  
request received in this behalf from a State Government or otherwise, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a River Board for 
advising the Governments interested in relation to such matters 
concerning the regulation or development of an inter- State river or 
river valley or any specified part thereof and for performing such 
other functions
<pagefootnote><pagenum>92</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli 
 (w. e. f. 1- 7- 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

Came into force on 15- 5- <year>1957</year>, vide notification EL- I- 452 (17) 57, 
dated 11- 5- 57, Gaz. of India, Section I, extraordinary, page- 165.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


as may be specified in the notification, and different Boards may be 
established for different inter- State rivers or river valleys:

Provided that no such notification shall be issued except after 
consultation with the Governments interested with respect to the 
proposal to establish the Board, the persons to be appointed as 
members thereof and the functions which the Board may be empowered to 
perform.


</section>

<section><tid>1642322</tid>
<number>2</number>A Board may be established under such name as may be 
specified in the notification under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>852566</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Board so established shall be a body corporate having 
perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name sue 
and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>344879</tid>
<number>4</number>Every Board shall exercise its jurisdiction within such 
limits of the river (including its tributaries, if any) or river 
valley as may be specified in the notification under sub- section (1) 
and the area so specified shall be called the area of operation of the 
Board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1658422</tid>
<number> 5</number> Composition of Board.
<section><tid>931078</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall consist of a  
Chairman and such other members as the Central Government thinks fit 
to appoint.

</section>

<section><tid>247116</tid>
<number>2</number>A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a member 
unless, in the opinion of the Central Government, he has special 
knowledge and experience in irrigation, electrical engineering, flood 
control, navigation, water conservation, soil conservation, 
administration or finance.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1706045</tid>
<number> 6</number> Terms and conditions of service of members.
<section><tid>792651</tid>
<number>1</number>A member  
shall, unless his appointment is terminated earlier by the Central 
Government, hold office for such period as may be notified in this 
behalf by the Central Government in the Official Gazette and shall, on 
the expiry of the term of his office, be eligible for re- appointment.

</section>

<section><tid>1927550</tid>
<number>2</number>A member may resign his office by writing under his hand 
addressed to the Central Government, but he shall continue in office 
until the appointment of his successor is notified in the Official 
Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1240800</tid>
<number>3</number>A casual vacancy created by the resignation of a member under 
sub- section (2) or for any other reason shall be filled by fresh 
appointment.

</section>

<section><tid>880254</tid>
<number>4</number>A member may be appointed either as a whole- time or part- time 
member as the Central Government thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1553019</tid>
<number>5</number>The terms and conditions of service of the Chairman and other 
members shall be such as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>93</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1250856</tid>
<number>7</number>Temporary absence of any member. If any member is by infirmity 
or otherwise rendered temporarily incapable of carrying out his duties 
or is absent on leave or otherwise in circumstances not involving the 
vacation of his appointment, the Central Government may appointment, 
the Central Government may appoint another person to act in his place.


</article>



<article><tid>1328555</tid>
<number>8</number>Meetings of Board. The Board shall meet at such times and 
places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings as may be provided by 
regulations made under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>60466</tid>
<number>9</number>Vacancy in Board, etc., not to invalidate acts or proceedings. 
No act or proceeding of the Board shall be deemed to be invalid by 
reason only of the existence of any vacancy in the Board or any defect 
in the appointment of a member thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>1712293</tid>
<number>10</number>Appointment of advisory committee. The Board may, from time 
to time, appoint one or more advisory committee or committees for the 
purpose of enabling it to carry out its functions under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1881707</tid>
<number> 11</number> Temporary association of persons with Board for particular 
purposes.
<section><tid>1267148</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may associate with itself in such manner and  
for such purposes as may be determined by regulations made under this 
Act any person whose assistance or advice it may desire in performing 
any of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>772587</tid>
<number>2</number>A person associated with the Board under sub- section (1) for 
any purpose shall have a right to take part in the discussions of the 
Board relevant to that purpose, but shall not have a right to vote at 
a meeting of the Board, and shall not be a member for any other 
purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1579945</tid>
<number>12</number>Staff of Board. Subject to such rules as may be made by the 
Central Government in this behalf, the Board may, for the purpose of 
enabling it to efficiently perform its functions or exercise its 
powers under this Act, appoint such officers as it may think fit and 
determine their functions and terms and conditions of service.
CHAP

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD

CHAPTER III

POWERS AND FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD



</article>



<article><tid>952346</tid>
<number> 13</number> Matters in respect of which a Board may be authorised to 
tender advice. A Board may be empowered under sub- section
<section><tid>1080831</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
section 14 to perform all or any of the following functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>590251</tid>
<number>a</number>advising the Governments interested on any matter 
concerning the regulation or development of any 
specified

<pagefootnote><pagenum>94</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

inter- State river or river valley within its area of 
operation and in particular, advising them in relation 
to the co- ordination of their activities with a view to 
resolve conflicts among them and to achieve maximum 
results in respect of the measures undertaken by them 
in the inter- State river or river valley for the 
purpose of-


<subsubsection><tid>733786</tid>
<number>i</number>conservation, control and optimum utilisation 
of water resources of the inter- State river;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>938492</tid>
<number>ii</number>promotion and operation of schemes for 
irrigation, water supply or drainage;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1932580</tid>
<number>iii</number>promotion and operation of schemes for the 
development of hydro- electric power;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1204555</tid>
<number>iv</number>promotion and operation of schemes for flood 
control;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1990500</tid>
<number>v</number>promotion and control of navigation;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>614475</tid>
<number>vi</number>promotion of afforestation and control of 
soil erosion;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1340611</tid>
<number>vii</number>prevention of pollution of the waters of the 
inter- State river;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>413552</tid>
<number>viii</number>such other matters as may be prescribed;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1142880</tid>
<number>b</number>preparing schemes, including multi- purpose schemes, for 
the purpose of regulating or developing the inter- State 
river or river valley and advising the Governments 
interested to undertake measures for executing the 
scheme prepared by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1333043</tid>
<number>c</number>allocating among the Governments interested the costs 
of executing any scheme prepared by the Board and of 
maintaining any works undertaken in the execution of 
the scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>341025</tid>
<number>d</number>watching the progress of the measures undertaken by the 
Governments interested;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>632098</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which is supplemental, incidental or 
consequential to any of the above functions.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>226626</tid>
<number> 14</number> Functions of Board.
<section><tid>1049521</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government, after  
consultation with the Governments interested, may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>95</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

empower the Board to perform all or such of the functions under 
section 13 as may be specified in the notification.


</section>

<section><tid>1685291</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall exercise its powers and perform all the 
functions which it is empowered to do by or under this Act within its 
area of operation.

</section>

<section><tid>234710</tid>
<number>3</number>In performing its functions under this Act, the Board shall 
consult the Governments interested at all stages and endeavour to 
secure, as far as may be practicable, agreement among such 
Governments.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>172198</tid>
<number> 15</number> Preparation of schemes by Board and their execution.
<section><tid>637402</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any Board has been empowered to perform functions under clause 
 (b) of section 13, the Board may, from time to time, prepare schemes, 
not inconsistent with its functions under this Act, for the purpose of 
regulating or developing any inter- State river or river valley within 
its area of operation.

</section>

<section><tid>141446</tid>
<number>2</number>After preparing any such scheme, the Board shall consult the 
Governments interested and the Central Government in respect of the 
scheme and after considering their suggestion, if any, the Board may 
confirm, modify or reject the scheme.

</section>

<section><tid>1592211</tid>
<number>3</number>The scheme as confirmed or modified under sub- section (2) 
shall thereupon become final and shall be called the approved scheme.

</section>

<section><tid>1852097</tid>
<number>4</number>Before any scheme is approved, the Board shall take into 
account the costs likely to be incurred in undertaking measures for 
executing the scheme and in maintaining any works to be undertaken in 
the execution of the scheme and the costs shall be allocated among the 
Governments interested in such proportion as may be agreed or, in 
default of agreement, as may be determined by the Board having regard 
to the benefits which will be received from the scheme by them.

</section>

<section><tid>1212649</tid>
<number>5</number>Every approved scheme shall be forwarded to the Governments 
interested and the Board may advise them to undertake measures for 
executing the scheme and a copy of the approved scheme shall also be 
forwarded to the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>599098</tid>
<number>6</number>The Central Government may, on a request received in this 
behalf from any Government interested or otherwise, assist the 
Governments interested in taking such steps as may be necessary for 
the execution of the scheme.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>96</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>238795</tid>
<number> 16</number> General Powers of Board. For the purpose of efficiently 
performing its functions under this Act, every Board may, within its 
area of operation,-
<section><tid>1232711</tid>
<number>a</number>acquire, hold and dispose of such property, both 
movable and immovable, as it deems necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>232604</tid>
<number>b</number>undertake such preliminary investigation or surveys or 
other measures as it deems necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>1721830</tid>
<number>c</number>inspect or cause to be inspected any works undertaken 
by any Government interested concerning the regulation 
or development of the inter- State river or river 
valley;

</section>

<section><tid>659200</tid>
<number>d</number>conduct and co- ordinate research on various aspects of 
the conservation, regulation or utilisation of water 
resources, such as water power generation, irrigation, 
navigation, flood control, soil conservation, land use 
and connected structural and design features:

</section>

<section><tid>1856928</tid>
<number>e</number>collect such topographical, meteorological, 
hydrological and sub- soil water data as it deems 
necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>1587671</tid>
<number>f</number>publish statistics or other information relating to the 
various aspects of the regulation or development of the 
inter- State river or river valley;

</section>

<section><tid>956285</tid>
<number>g</number>require any Government interested to furnish such 
information as the Board may require in relation to-

<subsection><tid>1793197</tid>
<number>i</number>the measures undertaken by that Government for 
the regulation or development of the inter- State river 
or river valley;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>179831</tid>
<number>ii</number>the topographical, meteorological, 
hydrological and sub- soil water data;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>524614</tid>
<number>iii</number>such other matters as may be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>713567</tid>
<number>17</number>Payment to Board. The Central Government may, after due 
appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the 
Board in each financial year such sums as the Central Government may 
consider necessary for the performance of the functions of the Board 
under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1211904</tid>
<number> 18</number> Fund of Board.
<section><tid>513449</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall have its own fund, and all  
sums which may, from time to time, be paid to it by the Central 
Government or a State Government and all other receipts of the Board 
shall be carried to the fund of the Board and all payments by the 
Board shall be made therefrom.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>97</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1072003</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for 
performing its functions under this Act, and such sums shall be 
treated as expenditure payable out of the fund of the Board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>812649</tid>
<number>19</number>Budget. The Board shall prepare, in such form and at such 
time each year as may be prescribed, a budget in respect of the 
financial year next ensuing showing the estimated receipts and 
expenditure, and copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central 
Government and the Governments interested.


</article>



<article><tid>720648</tid>
<number>20</number>Annual report. The Board shall prepare, in such form and at 
such time each year as may be prescribed, an annual report giving a 
true and full account of its activities during the previous year and 
copies thereof shall be forwarded to the Central Government and the 
Governments interested; and the Central Government shall cause every 
such report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament.


</article>



<article><tid>115010</tid>
<number> 21</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>1570728</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall cause to be  
maintained such books of account and other books in relation to its 
accounts in such form and in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1470044</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Board shall be audited at such time and 
in such manner as may be prescribed.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1693281</tid>
<number> 22</number> Arbitration.
<section><tid>1263601</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any dispute or difference arises  
between two or more Governments interested with respect to-

<subsection><tid>1022503</tid>
<number>a</number>any advice tendered by the Board under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>817566</tid>
<number>b</number>any measures undertaken by any Government interested in 
pursuance of any advice tendered by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1282763</tid>
<number>c</number>the refusal or neglect of any Government interested to 
undertake any measures in pursuance of any advice 
tendered by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>389250</tid>
<number>d</number>the sharing of benefits or financial liabilities 
arising out of any advice tendered by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1040726</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter covered by this Act or touching or 
arising out of it,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>98</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

any of the Governments interested may, in such form and in such manner 
as may be prescribed, refer the matter in dispute to arbitration.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1876878</tid>
<number>2</number>The arbitrator shall be a person to be appointed in this 
behalf by the Chief Justice of India from among persons who are, or 
have been, Judges of the Supreme Court or are Judges of a High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>64705</tid>
<number>3</number>The arbitrator may appoint two or more persons as assessors 
to assist him in the proceeding before him.

</section>

<section><tid>938191</tid>
<number>4</number>The decision of the arbitrator shall be final and binding on 
the parties to the dispute and shall be given effect to by them.

</section>

<section><tid>360337</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>), shall 
apply to arbitrations under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>860772</tid>
<number>23</number>Returns and reports. The Board shall furnish to the Central 
Government such returns, statistics, accounts and other information 
with respect to its fund or activities as the Central Government may 
from time to time require.


</article>



<article><tid>1475346</tid>
<number>24</number>Delegation of powers. The Board may, by general or special 
order in writing, delegate to the Chairman or any other member or any 
officer of the Board, subject to such conditions and limitations, if 
any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and 
functions under this Act as it may deem necessary for the efficient 
funning of the day- to- day administration of the Board.


</article>



<article><tid>111564</tid>
<number>25</number>Members and officers of Board to be public servants. All 
members and officers of a Board shall, when acting or purporting to 
act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, be deemed to be 
public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal 
Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>717027</tid>
<number>26</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against any member or officer of a Board in 
respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
in pursuance of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1431207</tid>
<number> 27</number> Dissolution of Board and transfer of assets and liabilities.

<section><tid>1686106</tid>
<number>1</number>When the Central Government is of opinion that a Board has  
performed its functions under this Act, the Central Government, after 
consultation with the Governments interested, may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, declare that the Board shall be dissolved from 
such date as may be specified in this behalf in such notification; and 
the Board shall be deemed to have been dissolved accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>99</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>434576</tid>
<number>2</number>On the dissolution of the Board by a notification under sub- 
section (1),-

<subsection><tid>507202</tid>
<number>a</number>all properties, funds and dues which are vested in, or 
realisable by, the Board shall vest in, and be 
realisable by, such Government or authority as may be 
specified in the said notification; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1413165</tid>
<number>b</number>all liabilities which are enforceable against the Board 
shall be enforceable only against the Government or 
authority specified in the said notification.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1970736</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>79081</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1824973</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely;-

<subsection><tid>1145780</tid>
<number>a</number>the salaries, allowances and conditions of service of 
members of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>407571</tid>
<number>b</number>the matters in respect of which the Board may tender 
advice to the Governments interested under sub- clause 
 (viii) of clause (a) of section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1104669</tid>
<number>c</number>the matters in respect of which the Board may require a 
Government interested to furnish information;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1066149</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which the Central Government may assist 
the Government interested to execute any scheme 
prepared by the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>155126</tid>
<number>e</number>the form in which, and the time within which, the 
budget and annual report of the Board may be prepared 
and forwarded to the Central Government and the 
Governments interested:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>988736</tid>
<number>f</number>the form and manner in which the accounts of the Board 
may be maintained, and the time at which, and the 
manner in which, such accounts may be audited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>56937</tid>
<number>g</number>the returns and information which the Board may be 
required to furnish to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>346859</tid>
<number>h</number>the form and manner in which a dispute may be referred 
to arbitration under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1868035</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure to be followed in arbitration proceedings 
under this Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>100</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1546837</tid>
<number>j</number>the manner of recruitment of the officers of a Board 
and the terms and conditions of service of such 
officers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1746861</tid>
<number>k</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>155769</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1456381</tid>
<number> 29</number> 
<section><tid>559464</tid>
<number>1</number>Power to make regulations. The Board may,  
with the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification 
in the Gazette of India, make regulations, not inconsistent with this 
Act or the rules made thereunder--

<subsection><tid>943454</tid>
<number>a</number>regulating the meetings of the Board and the procedure 
for conducting business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373219</tid>
<number>b</number>regulating the manner in which, and the purposes for 
which, advisory committees may be appointed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>761455</tid>
<number>c</number>regulating the manner in which and the purposes for 
which persons may be associated with the Board under 
section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>336057</tid>
<number>d</number>determining the terms and conditions of service of the 
members of advisory committees, of persons associated 
with the Board under section 11 and of all officers 
appointed by the Board.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>206538</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this section shall be laid, 
as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that regulation.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>101</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and sch. 
 (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>). 
2. Re- numbered by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 5- 186).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>