<act><tid>1617191</tid>
<title>THE RICE- MILLING INDUSTRY (REGULATION) ACT, <year>1958</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 21 OF <year>1958</year>
[ 18th May, <year>1958</year>.]

An Act to regulate the rice- milling industry in the interests of the 
general public.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Ninth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1133151</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1228098</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Rice- Milling Industry (Regulation) Act, <year>1958</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1662743</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.

</section>

<section><tid>372536</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>646112</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration as to expediency of control by the Union. It is 
hereby declared that it is expedient in the public interest that 
Union should take under its control the rice- milling industry.


</article>



<article><tid>1714113</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1169184</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" defunct rice mill" means--

<subsection><tid>1366052</tid>
<number>i</number>a rice mill in existence at the 
commencement of this Act but in which rice- milling 
operations have not been carried on for a 
continuous period of one year prior to such 
commencement; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1124424</tid>
<number>ii</number>a rice mill (whether established before  
  or after such commencement) in which rice- milling 
operations are not carried on for a continuous 
period of one year at any time after the 
cmmencement of the Rice- Milling Industry 
 (Regulation) Amendment Act, <year>1968</year>;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1605605</tid>
<number>b</number>" existing rice mill" means a rice mill carrying on rice- 
milling operations at the commencement of this Act, and 
includes a

<pagefootnote><pagenum>192</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch.; to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 
and Sch, I; and to Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch. The 
Act comes into force in the Union territory of Pondicherry on 
155- <year>1969</year>, vide State Gazette Exty., No. 54, dt, 7, 5, <year>1969</year>. Amended 
in west bengal by W. B. Act 24 of <year>1974</year>, Act 53 of <year>1974</year> and 25 of 
<year>1977</year>. 
2.  22nd April, <year>1959</year>, vide G. S. R. 511, dated the 22nd April, <year>1959</year>, 
See Gazette of India, Pt, II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 225. 
3. Sbs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 2, for clause (a)  (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

rice mill in existence at such commencement which is 
not carrying on rice- milling operations but in which 
rice- milling operations have been carried on at any 
time within a period of one year prior to such 
commencement:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that if in any such rice mill 
rice- milling operations are not carried on for a 
continuous period of one year at any time after 
the commencement of the Rice- Milling Industry 
 (Regulation) Amendment Act, <year>1968</year>, then, such mill 
shall, on the expiry of the said period of one 
year, cease to be an existing rice mill and be 
deemed to be a defunct rice mill;]


</section>

<section><tid>933373</tid>
<number>c</number>" licensing officer" means an officer appointed as such 
under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1267151</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" milling- rice", with its grammatical variations, 
means--

<subsection><tid>4228</tid>
<number>i</number>recovering rice or any product thereof 
from paddy;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>486733</tid>
<number>ii</number>polishing rice,
with the aid of power;]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1657185</tid>
<number>e</number>" new rice- mill" means a rice mill other than an existing 
rice mill or a defunct rice mill;

</section>

<section><tid>519288</tid>
<number>f</number>" notified order" means an order notified in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>214696</tid>
<number>g</number>" owner", in relation to a rice mill, means the person 
who, or the authority which, has the ultimate control 
over the affairs of the rice mill, and where the said 
affairs are entrusted to a manager, managing director 
or managing agent, such manager, managing director or 
managing agent shall be deemed to be the owner of the 
rice mill;

</section>

<section><tid>45696</tid>
<number>gg</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" polishing" in relation to rice means the removal of 
bran from the kernel of rice;]

</section>

<section><tid>1536685</tid>
<number>h</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>944755</tid>
<number>i</number>" rice mill" means the plant and machinery with which, 
and the premises, including the precincts thereof, in 
which or in any part of which, rice- milling operation 
is carried on.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>453294</tid>
<number>3A</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Application of the Act to rice- hullers. The provisions of 
this Act shall apply to rice- hullers attached to, or maintained with, 
any flour, oil, dal or other mill, or pumping set as
<pagefootnote><pagenum>193</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for clause (d)  (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>). 
3. Ins. by s. 2, ibid, (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>). 
4. Ins. by s. 3, ibid, (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


they apply to rice mills subject to the modification that any 
reference to the commencement of this Act in those provisions shall, 
in their application to such rice- hullers, be construed as a reference 
to the commencement of the Rice- Milling Industry (Regulation) 
Amendment Act, <year>1968</year>.]



</article>



<article><tid>1065999</tid>
<number> 4</number> Appointment of licensing officers. The Central Government may, 
by notified order,--
<section><tid>583174</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint such persons, being gazetted officers of 
Government, as it thinks fit to be licensing officers 
for the purposes of this Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>458174</tid>
<number>b</number>define the limits within which a licensing officer shall 
exercise the powers conferred on licensing officers by 
or under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1999099</tid>
<number> 5</number> Grant of permits in respect of new or defunct rice mills.
<section><tid>2549</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Any person or authority may make an application to the Central 
Government for the grant of a permit for the establishment of a new 
rice mill; and any owner of a defunct rice mill may make a like 
application for the grant of a permit for re- commencing rice- milling 
operation in such mill.

</section>

<section><tid>621322</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall be made in the 
prescribed form and shall contain the particulars regarding the 
location of the rice mill, the size and type thereof and such other 
particulars as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>498630</tid>
<number>3</number>If, on receipt of any such application for the grant of a 
permit, the Central Government is of opinion that it is necessary so 
to do for ensuring adequate supply of rice, it may, subject to the 
provisions of sub- section (4) and sub- section (5), grant the permit 
specifying therein the period within which the mill is to be 
established or, as the case may be, the mill is to re- commence is 
rice- milling operation and <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> such other conditions (including such  
conditions as to improvements to existing machinery, replacement of 
existing machinery and use of improved methods of rice- milling, as may 
be necessary to eliminate waste, obtain maximum production and improve 
  quality) as it may think fit] to impose, in accordance with the rules, 
if any, made in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1472752</tid>
<number>4</number>Before granting any permit under sub- section (3), the Central 
Government shall cause a full and complete investigation to be made in 
the prescribed manner in respect of the application and shall have due 
regard to--

<subsection><tid>1289731</tid>
<number>a</number>the number of rice mills operating in the locality;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1701312</tid>
<number>b</number>the availability of paddy in the locality;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>194</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 4, for" such other conditions as it 
may think fit" (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>631184</tid>
<number>c</number>the availability of power and water supply for the rice 
mill in respect of which a permit is applied for;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1859133</tid>
<number>d</number>whether the rice mill in respect of which a permit is 
applied for will be of the huller type, sheller type or 
combined sheller- huller type;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1549603</tid>
<number>e</number>whether the functioning of the rice mill in respect of 
which a permit is applied for would cause substantial 
unemployment in the locality;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1449166</tid>
<number>f</number>such other particulars as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1281780</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 

<subsection><tid>1168010</tid>
<number>a</number>In granting a permit under this section (whether for  
the establishment of a new rice mill or for re- commencing rice- milling 
  operation in a defunct rice mill), the Central Government shall give 
preference--

<subsubsection><tid>161426</tid>
<number>i</number>to a Government company or a corporation owned or 
controlled by the Government over every other 
applicant;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1249761</tid>
<number>ii</number>to a farmers' co- operative society over every other 
applicant not being a Government company or a 
corporation owned or controlled by the Government,
notwithstanding that such other applicant has applied for the grant of 
a permit for re- commencing rice- milling operation in a defunct rice 
mill.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1900740</tid>
<number>b</number>Subject to the provisions of clause (a), in granting a permit 
under this section, the Central Government shall give preference to a 
defunct rice mill over a new rice mill.
Explanation.-- In this sub- section,--


<subsubsection><tid>1596577</tid>
<number>i</number>" Co- operative society" means a society registered or 
deemed to be registered under the Co- operative 
Societies Act, <year>1912</year> (2 of <year>1912</year>) or any other law 
relating to co- operative societies for the time being 
in force in any State and" farmers" co- operative 
society" means a co- operative society the members 
whereof include farmers and the voting rights in which 
are, according to its rules and bye- laws, restricted to 
the following classes of its members, namely:--

<subsubsubsection><tid>567444</tid>
<number>a</number>farmers,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1556601</tid>
<number>b</number>State Governments,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1418174</tid>
<number>c</number>primary agricultural credit societies as 
defined in clause (cii) of section 2 of the 
Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>725715</tid>
<number>ii</number>" Government company" has the same meaning as in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>195</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 4, for sub- section (5)  (w. e. f. 1- 5-  
  <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1240891</tid>
<number>6</number>A permit granted under this section <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be valid] for 
the period specified therein or for such extended period as the 
Central Government may think fit to allow in any case:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that if in a mill in respect of which a permit has 
been granted under sub- section (3) rice- milling operation is not 
carried on for a continuous period of one year at any time after the 
commencement of the Rice- Milling Industry (Regulation) Amendment Act, 
<year>1968</year>, then, such permit shall cease to be valid upon the expiry of the 
said period of one year and a fresh permit shall be necessary for re- 
commencing rice- milling operation in that mill.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>192723</tid>
<number> 6</number> Grant of licences.
<section><tid>1340474</tid>
<number>1</number>Any owner of an existing rice mill or  
of a rice mill in respect of which <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> a permit granted under section 5 
is effective] may make an application to the licensing officer for the 
grant of a licence for carrying on rice- milling operation in that rice 
mill.

</section>

<section><tid>1415335</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall be made in the 
prescribed form and shall contain the particulars regarding the 
location of the rice mill, the size and type thereof and such other 
particulars as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>653593</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of any such application for the grant of a 
licence, the licensing officer shall grant the licence on such 
conditions <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> including such conditions as to improvements to existing 
machinery, replacement of existing machinery and use of improved 
methods of rice- milling, as may be necessary to eliminate waste, 
obtain maximum production and improve quality and conditions relating 
to the polishing of rice] on payment of such fees and on the deposit 
of such sum, if any, as security for the due performance of the 
conditions as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>795299</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> A licence granted under this section shall be valid for 
the period specified therein and may be renewed from time to time for 
such period and on payment of such fees and on such conditions 
 (including such conditions as to improvements to existing machinery,  
replacement of existing machinery and use of improved methods of rice- 
milling, as may be necessary to eliminate waste, obtain maximum 
  production and improve quality) as may be prescribed:
Provided that if in a mill in respect of which a licence has been 
granted under sub- section (3) rice- milling operations are not carried 
on for a continuous period of one year at any time after the 
commencement of the Rice- Milling Industry (Regulation) Amendment Act, 
<year>1968</year>, then, such licence

<pagefootnote><pagenum>196</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, for" shall be effective" (w. e. f. 1- 5-  
  <year>1970</year>). 
2. Added by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" a permit has been granted under 
section 5" (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 5, ibid, for sub- section (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall cease to be valid upon the expiry of the said period of one year 
and a fresh licence shall be necessary for carrying on rice- milling 
operations in that mill.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1569867</tid>
<number> 7</number> Revocation suspension and amendment of licences.
<section><tid>1209248</tid>
<number>1</number>If the  
licensing officer is satisfied, either on a reference made to him in 
this behalf or otherwise, that--

<subsection><tid>1780059</tid>
<number>a</number>a licence granted under section 6 has been obtained by 
misrepresentation as to an essential fact, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>76980</tid>
<number>b</number>the holder of a licence has, without reasonable cause, 
failed to comply with the conditions subject to which 
the licence has been granted or has contravened any of 
the provisions of this Act or the rules made 
thereunder.
then without prejudice to any other penalty to which the holder of the 
licence may be liable under this Act, the licensing officer may, after 
giving the holder of the licence an opportunity of showing cause, 
revoke or suspend the licence or forfeit the sum, if any, or any 
portion thereof deposited as security for the due performance of the 
conditions subject to which the licence has been granted.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>998811</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to any rules that may be made in this behalf, the 
licensing officer may also vary or amend a licence granted under 
section 6.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975816</tid>
<number> 8</number> Certain restrictions on rice mills.
<section><tid>1286076</tid>
<number>1</number>No person or authority  
shall, after the commencement of this Act, establish any new rice mill 
except under and in accordance with a permit granted under section 5.

</section>

<section><tid>1887126</tid>
<number>2</number>No owner of a rice mill shall, after the commencement of this 
Act, carry on rice- milling operation except under and in accordance 
with a licence granted under section 6:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to an 
existing rice mill for such period as may be specified in this behalf 
by the Central Government by notified order.


</section>

<section><tid>1668630</tid>
<number>3</number>No owner of a rice mill,--

<subsection><tid>1334997</tid>
<number>a</number>in respect of which a licence has been granted under 
section 6, shall carry on rice- milling operation in 
that mill <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> after the licence has ceased to be valid.]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>608338</tid>
<number>b</number>in respect of which the licence has been revoked or 
suspended under section 7, shall carry on rice- milling 
operation in that mill after the revocation or, as the 
case may be, during the period for which the licence 
has been suspended;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1022593</tid>
<number>c</number>shall, without the previous permission of the Central 
Government, change the location of the whole or any 
part of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>197</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 6 for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 5-  
  <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


rice mill in respect of which a licence has been 
granted under section 6;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>673109</tid>
<number>d</number>shall, after the commencement of this Act, effect any 
expansion of the rice mill except with the previous 
permission of the Central Government:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that no such permission shall be necessary,--


<subsubsection><tid>1553429</tid>
<number>i</number>where such expansion is in accordance with the terms and 
conditions of the permit or licence granted under this Act in respect 
of the rice mill; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1751302</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the replacement merely of any parts of the machinery of 
the rice mill if such replacement does not result in an increase in 
the productive capacity of the rice mill.]
Explanation.-- For the purposes of clause (a) of this sub- section, 
the period of the validity of a licence shall not be deemed to have 
expired, if an application for its renewal is pending before the 
licensing officer.




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>989407</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power of inspection. For the purpose of ascertaining the 
position or examining the working of any rice mill or for any other 
purpose mentioned in this Act or the rules made thereunder, the 
licensing officer or any person authorised by the Central Government 
in this behalf shall have the right--
<section><tid>104360</tid>
<number>a</number>to enter and inspect any rice mill;

</section>

<section><tid>1038575</tid>
<number>b</number>to order the production of any document, book, register 
or record in the possession or power of any person 
having the control of, or employed in connection with, 
any rice mill; and

</section>

<section><tid>518997</tid>
<number>c</number>to examine any person having the control of, or employed 
in connection with, any rice mill.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>85117</tid>
<number> 10</number> Decision of Central Government final respecting certain 
matters. If, for the purposes of this Act, any question arises as to 
whether,--
<section><tid>1102012</tid>
<number>a</number>there has been an expansion of a rice mill, or

</section>

<section><tid>833573</tid>
<number>b</number>the replacement of any parts of the machinery of a rice 
mill has resulted in an increase in the productive 
capacity of the rice mill,
the Central Government may, after giving the owner of the rice mill an 
opportunity of being heard, decide the question and the decision of 
the Central Government thereon shall be final.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>198</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 6, for the proviso (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1814217</tid>
<number>11</number>Returns. Every owner of a rice mill shall furnish to the 
Central Government such returns relating to the affairs of the rice 
mill and in such forms as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>902940</tid>
<number> 12</number> Appeals.
<section><tid>1224773</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by a decision of a  
licensing officer under section 6 or section 7 may, within thirty days 
from the date on which the decision is communicated to him, prefer an 
appeal to an appellate officer who shall be a person nominated in this 
behalf by the Central Government:
Provided that the appellate officer may entertain the appeal 
after the expiry of the said period of thirty days, if he is satisfied 
that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the 
appeal in time.


</section>

<section><tid>1300464</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of an appeal under sub- section (1), the appellate 
officer shall, after giving the appellant an opportunity of being 
heard, dispose of the appeal as expeditiously as possible.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1404574</tid>
<number> 13</number> Penalties. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>697934</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person contravenes or attempts to  
contravene or abets the contravention of any of the provisions of 
section 8 or sub- section (2) of section 18, he shall be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with 
fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or with both, and in the 
case of a continuing contravention, with an additional fine which may 
extend to five hundred rupees for every day during which such 
contravention continues after conviction for the first such 
contravention:
Provided that where such contravention, attempt or abetment 
relates to sub- section (1), or sub- section (2), or clause (a) or 
clause (b) of sub- section (3) of section 8, or sub- section (2) of 
section 18, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than one month.]


</section>

<section><tid>622324</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person.--

<subsection><tid>445524</tid>
<number>a</number>when required by this Act or by any order under this Act 
to make any statement or furnish any information makes 
any statement or furnishes any information which is 
false in any material particular and which he knows or 
has reason to believe to be false or does not believe 
to be true, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>779092</tid>
<number>b</number>makes any such statement as aforesaid in any book, 
account, record, declaration, return or other document 
which he is required to maintain or furnish under this 
Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1337600</tid>
<number>c</number>contravenes any rule the contravention of which is made 
punishable under this sub- section.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>199</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 7, sub- section (1)  (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a tern which may extend 
to three months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, 
or with both.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>217042</tid>
<number> 14</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1956598</tid>
<number>1</number>If the person committing an  
offence under this Act is a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment provided in this Act, if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>239343</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1335626</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate, and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>313023</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1914439</tid>
<number>14A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Burden of proof in certain cases. Where paddy, husk, rice 
or broken rice is recovered from the premises of a mill, it shall be 
presumed, unless the contrary is proved by the owner, that rice- 
milling operations are carried on in that mill.


</article>



<article><tid>1940228</tid>
<number>14B</number>Confiscation of plant and machinery. Where any person has 
been convicted for contravention of any of the provisions of section 8 
or of sub- section (2) of section 18, then the court convicting such 
person may order confiscation of the plant and machinery with which 
rice- milling operations in contravention of such provision were 
carried on:
Provided that where such person is convicted for a second or 
subsequent offence, the court shall order confiscation of such plant 
and machinery.]



</article>



<article><tid>743419</tid>
<number>15</number>Cognizance of offences. No court shall take cognizance of any 
offence punishable under this Act except on a report in writing of the 
facts constituting such offence
<pagefootnote><pagenum>199A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


made by the licensing officer or any person duly authorised by the 
Central Government or the licensing officer in this behalf.



</article>



<article><tid>1248920</tid>
<number>16</number>Jurisdiction of courts. No court inferior to that of a 
presidency magistrate or a magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence punishable under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>590584</tid>
<number>17</number>Special provision regarding fines. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in section 32 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of  
  <year>1898</year>), it shall be lawful for any magistrate of the first class or for 
any presidency magistrate to pass a sentence of fine exceeding two 
thousand rupees on any person convicted of any offence under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1563512</tid>
<number> 18</number> Power to exempt in special cases.
<section><tid>531777</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central  
Government is of opinion, having regard to the necessity for ensuring 
an adequate supply of rice in any area or to the conditions prevailing 
therein, that it would not be in the public interest to apply all or 
any of the provisions of this Act to the rice mills or to any class of 
rice mills in that area, it may, by notified order, exempt for such 
period and subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, 
all the rice mills or such class of rice mills in that area as it may 
specify in the order from the operation of all or any of the 
provisions of this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>54784</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any notified order under sub- section (1) granting an 
exemption is cancelled, no owner of a rice mill shall carry on rice- 
milling operation in that rice mill, after the expiry of such period 
as may be specified in the order cancelling the exemption, except 
under and in accordance with a licence granted to him under section 6.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1151710</tid>
<number> 19</number> Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by notified 
order, direct that any power exercisable by it under this Act shall, 
in relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, if any, as 
may be specified in the direction, be exercisable also by--
<section><tid>472615</tid>
<number>a</number>such officer or authority subordinate to the Central 
Government, or

</section>

<section><tid>794108</tid>
<number>b</number>such State Government or such officer or authority 
subordinate to a State Government,
As may be specified in the direction.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1989876</tid>
<number>20</number>Licensing officers, etc., to be public servants. The 
licensing officers and every person duly authorised to discharge any 
duties imposed on him by this Act shall be deemed to be public 
servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 
 (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>968761</tid>
<number> 21</number> Protection of action taken under the Act.
<section><tid>1895598</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any officer 
or authority] for anything which is in good faith done
<pagefootnote><pagenum>199B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 9, for" any person" (w. e. f. 1- 5-  
  <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order 
made thereunder.


</section>

<section><tid>212564</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of 
this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1631732</tid>
<number> 22</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>784432</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, subject  
to the condition of previous publication, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> for carrying 
out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1682241</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>910196</tid>
<number>a</number>the form of application for the grant of a permit under 
section 5 and the particulars it may contain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>135107</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which an investigation is to be made in 
respect of an application for a permit and the matters 
to be taken into account in granting or refusing a 
permit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>629193</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the form of a permit under section 5 and the 
conditions (including conditions relating to  
improvements to existing machinery, replacement of 
existing machinery and use of improved methods of rice- 
  milling) subject to which a permit may be granted and 
the time within which such conditions shall be complied 
with;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>347777</tid>
<number>c</number>the form of application for the grant or renewal of a 
licence in respect of a rice mill and the particulars 
it may contain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>141650</tid>
<number>d</number>the form of a licence which may be granted or renewed 
under section 6 and the conditions subject to which the 
licence may be granted or renewed, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> including 
conditions relating to improvements to existing 
machinery, replacement of existing machinery, use of 
improved methods of rice- milling and polishing of rice, 
the time within which such conditions shall be complied 
with], the fees to be levied for the grant or renewal 
of a licence and the deposit of any sum as security for 
the performance of such conditions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1897429</tid>
<number>e</number>the circumstances under which licences may be varied or 
amended under sub- section (2) of section 7;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1932944</tid>
<number>f</number>the submission of returns relating to a rice mill by the 
owner and the forms in which, and the authorities to 
which, such
<pagefootnote><pagenum>199C</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For such rules, see Gazette of India, <year>1959</year>, Extraordinary, Part 
II, Sec. 3 (1) pp. 219. 
2. Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 10, ibid., for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 5- <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


returns may be submitted; and the collection of any 
information or statistics in relation to rice mills;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>522293</tid>
<number>g</number>the form and manner in which appeals may be filed under 
section 12 and the procedure to be followed by 
appellate officers in disposing of the appeals;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1735988</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed 
under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>546151</tid>
<number>3</number>Any rule made under this section may provide that a 
contravention thereof shall be punishable under sub- section (2) of 
section 13.

</section>

<section><tid>1470456</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this 
section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so 
laid or the session immediately following, both Houses agree in making 
any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1032162</tid>
<number>23</number>Application of other laws not barred. The provisions of this 
Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any other 
Central Act for the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>970154</tid>
<number>24</number>Act not to apply to rice mills owned by Government. The 
provisions of this Act shall not apply to any rice mill owned by 
Government.


</article>



<article><tid>39763</tid>
<number> 25</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>61630</tid>
<number>1</number>If, immediately before the  
commencement of this Act, there is in force in any State to which this 
Act extends any law or order relating to the regulation or control of 
rice mills in that State, that law or order shall stand repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>168982</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, any certificate of registration, 
permit or licence granted in respect of any existing rice mill, under 
any such law or order hereby repealed and in force immediately before 
the commencement of this Act, shall continue to be in force for such 
period as may be allowed under the proviso to sub- section (2) of 
section 8 for the licensing of such rice mill under the provisions of 
this Act, and for the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that 
the provisions of section 6 of the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of  
  <year>1897</year>), shall apply in relation to such repeal, as they apply in 
relation to the repeal of an enactment by a Central Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1968</year>, s. 10, for sub- section (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 5-  
  <year>1970</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>