<act><tid>162393</tid>
<title>THE INTER- STATE CORPORATIONS ACT, <year>1957</year></title>

ACT NO. 38 OF <year>1957</year>
[ 20th September, <year>1957</year>.]

An Act to provide for the reorganisation of certain corporations 
functioning in two or more States by virtue of section 109 of the 
States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or of any other enactment 
relating to reorganisation of States], and for matters connected 
therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eighth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1116172</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Inter- State 
Corporations Act, <year>1957</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1702067</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," inter- State corporation" means any 
body corporate constituted under any of the Acts specified in the 
Schedule and functioning in two or more States by virtue of section 
 109 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>.) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or of any 
other enactment relating to reorganisation of States].


</article>



<article><tid>1437151</tid>
<number>3</number>Power of State Governments to frame schemes. If it appears to 
the Government of a State in any part of which an inter- State 
corporation is functioning that the inter- State corporation should be 
reconstituted and reorganised as one or more intra- State corporations 
or that it should be dissolved, the State Government may frame a 
scheme for such reconstitution and reorganisation or such dissolution, 
as the case may be, including proposals regarding the transfer of the 
assets, rights and liabilities of the inter- State corporation to any 
other corporations or State Governments and the transfer or re- 
employment of employees of the inter- State corporation and forward the 
scheme to the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1438414</tid>
<number> 4</number> Reorganisation of certain inter- State corporations.
<section><tid>577000</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
receipt of a scheme forwarded to it under section 3 the Central 
Government may, after consulting the State Governments concerned, 
approve the scheme with or without modifications and give effect to 
the scheme so approved by making such order as it thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1038066</tid>
<number>2</number>An order made under sub- section (1) may provide for all or 
any of the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>684429</tid>
<number>a</number>the dissolution of the inter- State corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1861097</tid>
<number>b</number>the reconstitution and reorganisation in any manner 
whatsoever of the inter- State corporation including the 
constitution, where necessary, of new corporations;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>510</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1960</year>, s. 75.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>973760</tid>
<number>c</number>the area in respect of which the reconstituted 
corporation or new corporation shall function and 
operate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1767110</tid>
<number>d</number>the transfer, in whole or in part, of the assets, rights 
and liabilities of the inter- State corporation 
 (including the rights and liabilities under any  
  contract made by it) to any other corporations or State 
Governments and the terms and conditions of such 
transfer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>646289</tid>
<number>e</number>the substitution of any such transferee for the inter- 
State corporation, or the addition of any such 
transferee, as a party to any legal proceeding to which 
the inter- State corporation is a party; and the 
transfer of any proceedings pending before the inter- 
State corporation to any such transferee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753504</tid>
<number>f</number>the transfer or re- employment of any employees of the 
inter- State corporation to, or by, any such transferee 
and subject to the provisions of section 111 of the 
States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of <year>1956</year>) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or of 
any other enactment relating to reorganisation of 
States], the terms and conditions of service applicable 
to such employees after such transfer or re- employment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370487</tid>
<number>g</number>the adaptations or modifications of the Act under which 
the inter- State corporation was constituted, whether by 
way of repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or 
expedient to give effect to the approved scheme;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>420746</tid>
<number>h</number>such incidental, consequential and supplementary matters 
as may be necessary to give effect to the approved 
scheme.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1388410</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an order is made under this section transferring the 
assets, rights and liabilities of any inter- State corporation, then, 
by virtue of that order, such assets, rights and liabilities of the 
inter- State corporation shall vest in, and be the assets, rights and 
liabilities of, the transferee.

</section>

<section><tid>497980</tid>
<number>4</number>Every order made under this section shall be published in the 
Official Gazette and the Act under which the inter- State corporation 
was constituted shall have effect subject to the provisions of the 
order and the adaptations and modifications made thereby until 
altered, repealed or amended by the competent Legislature of a State.

</section>

<section><tid>1104860</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the order or both Houses agree that the order should 
not be made, the order shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that order.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>846395</tid>
<number>5</number>Power of Central Government to add to the Schedule. The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in the Schedule any Act under which a body
<pagefootnote><pagenum>511</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1960</year>, s. 75. 
2. Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 and Sch (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


corporate constituted for a State is functioning in two or more States 
by virtue of section 109 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> (37 of  
  <year>1956</year>.) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or of any other enactment relating to reorganisation of 
States], and on the issue of such notification, the Schedule shall be 
deemed to be amended by the inclusion of the said Act therein.


</article>



 </act>