<act><tid>1626789</tid>
<title>THE SECURITIES LAWS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2004</year></title>

NO. 1 OF <year>2005</year>
[ 6th January, <year>2005</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, <year>1956</year> and the Depositories Act, <year>1996</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fifth Year of the Republic of India as follows:-

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1270928</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>162688</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Securities Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>2004</year>. 

</section>

<section><tid>1476917</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 12th day of October, <year>2004</year>.
CHAPTER II

AMENDMENTS TO THE SECURITIES CONTRACTS (REGULATION) ACT, <year>1956</year>

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENTS TO THE SECURITIES CONTRACTS (REGULATION) ACT, <year>1956</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1602079</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, <year>1956</year> (42 of <year>1956</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the principal Act),-
<section><tid>1065915</tid>
<number>i</number>clause (aa) shall be re- lettered as clause (ac) thereof and before the clause (ac) as so re- lettered, the following clauses shall be inserted, namely:-
' (aa)" corporatisation" means the succession of a recognised stock exchange, being a body of individuals or a society registered under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>), by another stock exchange, being a company incorporated for the purpose of assisting, regulating or controlling the business of buying, selling or dealing in securities carried on by such individuals or society;


<subsection><tid>994223</tid>
<number>ab</number>" demutualisation" means the segregation of ownership and management from the trading rights of the members of a recognised stock exchange in accordance with a scheme approved by the Securities and Exchange Board of India;';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>547780</tid>
<number>ii</number>clause (ga) shall be re- lettered as clause (gb) thereof and before the clause (gb) as so re- lettered, the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (ga)" scheme" means a scheme for corporatisation or demutualisation of a recognised stock exchange which may provide for-


</section>

<section><tid>1065915</tid>
<number>i</number>the issue of shares for a lawful consideration and provision of trading rights in lieu of membership cards of members of a recognised stock exchange;

</section>

<section><tid>547780</tid>
<number>ii</number>the restrictions on voting rights;

</section>

<section><tid>1665478</tid>
<number>iii</number>the transfer of property, business, assets, rights, liabilities, recognitions, contracts of the recognised stock exchange, legal proceedings by, or against, the recognised stock exchange, whether in the name of the recognised stock exchange or any trustee or otherwise and any permission given to, or by, the recognised stock exchange;

</section>

<section><tid>1207159</tid>
<number>iv</number>the transfer of employees of a recognised stock exchange to another recognised stock exchange;

</section>

<section><tid>1422266</tid>
<number>v</number>any other matter required for the purpose of, or in connection with, the corporatisation or demutualisation, as the case may be, of the recognised stock exchange;';

</section>

<section><tid>1665478</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (h), after sub- clause (ic), the following sub- clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (id) units or any other such instrument issued to the investors under any mutual fund scheme;";


</section>

<section><tid>1207159</tid>
<number>iv</number>for clause (j), the following clause shall be substituted, namely:-
' (j)" stock exchange" means-


<subsection><tid>1323155</tid>
<number>a</number>any body of individuals, whether incorporated or not, constituted before corporatisation and demutualisation under sections 4A and 4B, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>139723</tid>
<number>b</number>a body corporate incorporated under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> whether under a scheme of corporatisation and demutualisation or otherwise, 
for the purpose of assisting, regulating or controlling the business of buying, selling or dealing in securities;'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>571075</tid>
<number>3</number>Insertion of new sections 4A and 4B.- After section 4 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
' 4A. Corporatisation and demutualisation of stock exchanges.- On and from the appointed date, all recognised stock exchanges (if not corporatised and demutualised before the appointed date) shall be corporatised and demutualised in accordance with the provisions contained in section 4B: 
Provided that the Securities and Exchange Board of India may, if it is satisfied that any recognised stock exchange was prevented by sufficient cause from being corporatised and demutualised on or after the appointed date, specify another appointed date in respect of that recognised stock exchange and such recognised stock exchange may continue as such before such appointed date.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," appointed date" means the date which the Securities and Exchange Board of India may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint and different appointed dates may be appointed for different recognised stock exchanges.

</article>



<article><tid>1049430</tid>
<number> 4B</number> Procedure for corporatisation and demutualisation.-
<section><tid>631806</tid>
<number>1</number>All recognised stock exchanges referred to in section 4A shall, within such time as may be specified by the Securities and Exchange Board of India, submit a scheme for corporatisation and demutualisation for its approval: 
Provided that the Securities and Exchange Board of India, may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify name of the recognised stock exchange, which had already been corporatised and demutualised, and such stock exchange shall not be required to submit the scheme under this section.


</section>

<section><tid>1103844</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of the scheme referred to in sub- section (1), the Securities and Exchange Board of India may, after making such enquiry as may be necessary in this behalf and obtaining such further information, if any, as it may require and if it is satisfied that it would be in the interest of the trade and also in the public interest, approve the scheme with or without modification.

</section>

<section><tid>304051</tid>
<number>3</number>No scheme under sub- section (2) shall be approved by the Securities and Exchange Board of India if the issue of shares for a lawful consideration or provision of trading rights in lieu of membership card of the members of a recognised stock exchange or payment of dividends to members have been proposed out of any reserves or assets of that stock exchange.

</section>

<section><tid>279861</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the scheme is approved under sub- section (2), the scheme so approved shall be published immediately by-

<subsection><tid>703166</tid>
<number>a</number>the Securities and Exchange Board of India in the Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1198312</tid>
<number>b</number>the recognised stock exchange in such two daily newspapers circulating in India, as may be specified by the Securities and Exchange Board of India, 
and upon such publication, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in force or any agreement, award, judgment, decree or other instrument for the time being in force, the scheme shall have effect and be binding on all persons and authorities including all members, creditors, depositors and employees of the recognised stock exchange and on all persons having any contract, right, power, obligation or liability with, against, over, to, or in connection with, the recognised stock exchange or its members.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>59937</tid>
<number>5</number>Where the Securities and Exchange Board of India is satisfied that it would not be in the interest of the trade and also in the public interest to approve the scheme under sub- section (2), it may, by an order, reject the scheme and such order of rejection shall be published by it in the Official Gazette:
Provided that the Securities and Exchange Board of India shall give a reasonable opportunity of being heard to all the persons concerned and the recognised stock exchange concerned before passing an order rejecting the scheme.


</section>

<section><tid>1714202</tid>
<number>6</number>The Securities and Exchange Board of India may, while approving the scheme under sub- section (2), by an order in writing, restrict-

<subsection><tid>1620527</tid>
<number>a</number>the voting rights of the shareholders who are also stock brokers of the recognised stock exchange;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>343480</tid>
<number>b</number>the right of shareholders or a stock broker of the recognised stock exchange to appoint the representatives on the governing board of the stock exchange;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>98921</tid>
<number>c</number>the maximum number of representatives of the stock brokers of the recognised stock exchange to be appointed on the governing board of the recognised stock exchange, which shall not exceed one- fourth of the total strength of the governing board.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>623904</tid>
<number>7</number>The order made under sub- section (6) shall be published in the Official Gazette and on the publication thereof, the order shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or any other law for the time being in force, have full effect.

</section>

<section><tid>1257212</tid>
<number>8</number>Every recognised stock exchange, in respect of which the scheme for corporatisation or demutualisation has been approved under sub- section (2), shall, either by fresh issue of equity shares to the public or in any other manner as may be specified by the regulations made by the Securities and Exchange Board of India, ensure that at least fifty- one per cent. of its equity share capital is held, within twelve months from the date of publication of the order under sub- section (7), by the public other than shareholders having trading rights:
Provided that the Securities and Exchange Board of India may, on sufficient cause being shown to it and in the public interest, extend the said period by another twelve months.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>219509</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 5.- Section 5 of the principal Act shall be numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>1331167</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof and after sub- section (1) as so numbered, the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:- 
" (2) Where the recognised stock exchange has not been corporatised or demutualised or it fails to submit the scheme referred to in sub- section (1) of section 4B within the specified time therefor or the scheme has been rejected by the Securities and Exchange Board of India under sub- section (5) of section 4B, the recognition granted to such stock exchange under section 4, shall, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in this Act, stand withdrawn and the Central Government shall publish, by notification in the Official Gazette, such withdrawal of recognition:

Provided that no such withdrawal shall affect the validity of any contract entered into or made before the date of the notification, and the Securities and Exchange Board of India may, after consultation with the stock exchange, make such provisions as it deems fit in the order rejecting the scheme published in the Official Gazette under sub- section (5) of section 4B.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1589365</tid>
<number> 5</number> Insertion of new section 8A.- After section 8 of the principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 8A. Clearing corporation.- (1) A recognised stock exchange may, with the prior approval of the Securities and Exchange Board of India, transfer the duties and functions of a clearing house to a clearing corporation, being a company incorporated under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), for the purpose of-

<section><tid>4134</tid>
<number>a</number>the periodical settlement of contracts and differences thereunder;

</section>

<section><tid>526681</tid>
<number>b</number>the delivery of, and payment for, securities;

</section>

<section><tid>1375880</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter incidental to, or connected with, such transfer.

<subsection><tid>1875832</tid>
<number>2</number>Every clearing corporation shall, for the purpose of transfer of the duties and functions of a clearing house to a clearing corporation referred to in sub- section (1), make bye- laws and submit the same to the Securities and Exchange Board of India for its approval.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>302940</tid>
<number>3</number>The Securities and Exchange Board of India may, on being satisfied that it is in the interest of the trade and also in the public interest to transfer the duties and functions of a clearing house to a clearing corporation, grant approval to the bye- laws submitted to it under sub- section (2) and approve the transfer of the duties and functions of a clearing house to a clearing corporation referred to in sub- section (1).

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1035024</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of sections 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 and 12 shall, as far as may be, apply to a clearing corporation referred to in sub- section (1) as they apply in relation to a recognised stock exchange.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1503671</tid>
<number> 6</number> Insertion of new section 12A.- After section 12 of the principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
'' 12A. Poqwer to issue directions.- If, after making or causing to be made an inquiry, the Securities and Exchange Board of India is satisfied that it is necessary-

<section><tid>1280383</tid>
<number>a</number>in the interest of investors, or orderly development of securities market; or

</section>

<section><tid>1687337</tid>
<number>b</number>to prevent the affairs of any recognised stock exchange or clearing corporation, or such other agency or person, providing trading or clearing or settlement facility in respect of securities, being conducted in a manner detrimental to the interests of investors or securities market; or

</section>

<section><tid>1470027</tid>
<number>c</number>to secure the proper management of any such stock exchange or clearing corporation or agency or person, referred to in clause (b),
it may issue such directions,-


<subsection><tid>877548</tid>
<number>i</number>to any stock exchange or clearing corporation or agency or person referred to in clause (b) or any person or class of persons associated with the securities market; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1746727</tid>
<number>ii</number>to any company whose securities are listed or proposed to be listed in a recognised stock exchange,
as may be appropriate in the interests of investors in securities and the securities market.".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>137349</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1288496</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" between members of a recognised stock exchange", the words" between members of a recognised stock exchange or recognised stock exchanges" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1724287</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" State or area" wherever they occur, the words" State or States or area" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1609326</tid>
<number>c</number>the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that any contract entered into between members of two or more recognised stock exchanges in such State or States or area, shall-


<subsection><tid>285476</tid>
<number>i</number>be subject to such terms and conditions as may be stipulated by the respective stock exchanges with prior approval of Securities and Exchange Board of India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1111536</tid>
<number>ii</number>require prior permission from the respective stock exchanges if so stipulated by the stock exchanges with prior approval of Securities and Exchange Board of India.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>682227</tid>
<number> 8</number> Insertion of new section 21A.- After section 21 of the principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 21A. Delisting of securities.- (1) A recognised stock exchange may delist the securities, after recording the reasons therefor, from any recognised stock exchange on any of the ground or grounds as may be prescribed under this Act:

Provided that the securities of a company shall not be delisted unless the company concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.

<section><tid>1956772</tid>
<number>2</number>A listed company or an aggrieved investor may file an appeal before the Securities Appellate Tribunal against the decision of the recognised stock exchange delisting the securities within fifteen days from the date of the decision of the recognised stock exchange delisting the securities and the provisions of sections 22B to 22E of this Act, shall apply, as far as may be, to such appeals:
Provided that the Securities Appellate Tribunal may, if it is satisfied that the company was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding one month.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1837737</tid>
<number>9</number>Substitution of new section for section 22F.- For section 22F of the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 22F. Appeal to Supreme Court.- Any person aggrieved by any decision or order of the Securities Appellate Tribunal may file an appeal to the Supreme Court within sixty days from the date of communication of the decision or order of the Securities Appellate Tribunal to him on any question of law arising out of such order:

Provided that the Supreme Court may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days.".



</article>



<article><tid>1882598</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of section 23.- In section 23 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>663695</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), after clause (i), for the words" shall, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine or with both", the words" shall, without prejudice to any award of penalty by the Adjudicating Officer under this Act, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years or with fine, which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees or with both" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>368968</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>1748421</tid>
<number>i</number>for the word and figures" section 21," the words, figures and letter" section 21 or section 21A" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1036163</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" shall, on conviction, be punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees", the words" shall, without prejudice to any award of penalty by the Adjudicating Officer under this Act, on conviction, be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years or with fine, which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees, or with both" shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>67307</tid>
<number> 11</number> Insertion of new sections 23A to 23-O.- After section 23 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 23A. Penalty for failure to furnish information, return, etc.- Any person, who is required under this Act or any rules made thereunder,-

<section><tid>789714</tid>
<number>a</number>to furnish any information, document, books, returns or report to a recognised stock exchange, fails to furnish the same within the time specified therefor in the listing agreement or conditions or bye- laws of the recognised stock exchange, shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less for each such failure;

</section>

<section><tid>1848380</tid>
<number>b</number>to maintain books of account or records, as per the listing agreement or conditions, or bye- laws of a recognised stock exchange, fails to maintain the same, shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1066532</tid>
<number>23B</number>Penalty for failure by any person to enter into an agreement with clients.- If any person, who is required under this Act or any bye- laws of a recognised stock exchange made thereunder, to enter into an agreement with his client, fails to enter into such an agreement, he shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less for every such failure.
</article>



<article><tid>1229486</tid>
<number>23C</number>Penalty for failure to redress investors' grievances.- If any stock broker or sub- broker or a company whose securities are listed or proposed to be listed in a recognised stock exchange, after having been called upon by the Securities and Exchange Board of India or a recognised stock exchange in writing, to redress the grievances of the investors, fails to redress such grievances within the time stipulated by the Securities and Exchange Board of India or a recognised stock exchange, he or it shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.
</article>



<article><tid>89320</tid>
<number>23D</number>Penalty for failure to segregate securities or moneys of client or clients.- If any person, who is registered under section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, <year>1992</year> (15 of <year>1992</year>) as a stock broker or sub- broker, fails to segregate securities or moneys of the client or clients or uses the securities or moneys of a client or clients for self or for any other client, he shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding one crore rupees.
</article>



<article><tid>771701</tid>
<number>23E</number>Penalty for failure to comply with listing conditions or delisting conditions or grounds.- If a company or any person managing collective investment scheme or mutual fund, fails to comply with the listing conditions or delisting conditions or grounds or commits a breach thereof, it or he shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding twenty- five crore rupees.
</article>



<article><tid>1299275</tid>
<number>23F</number>Penalty for excess dematerialisation or delivery of unlisted securities.- If any issuer dematerialises securities more than the issued securities of a company or delivers in the stock exchanges the securities which are not listed in the recognised stock exchange or delivers securities where no trading permission has been given by the recognised stock exchange, he shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding twenty- five crore rupees.
</article>



<article><tid>308337</tid>
<number>23G</number>Penalty for failure to furnish periodical returns, etc.- If a recognised stock exchange fails or neglects to furnish periodical returns to the Securities and Exchange Board of India or fails or neglects to make or amend its rules or bye- laws as directed by the Securities and Exchange Board of India or fails to comply with directions issued by the Securities and Exchange Board of India, such recognised stock exchange shall be liable to a penalty which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees.
</article>



<article><tid>572346</tid>
<number>23H</number>Penalty for contravention where no separate penalty has been provided.- Whoever fails to comply with any provision of this Act, the rules or articles or bye- laws or the regulations of the recognised stock exchange or directions issued by the Securities and Exchange Board of India for which no separate penalty has been provided, shall be liable to a penalty which may extend to one crore rupees.
</article>



<article><tid>439129</tid>
<number> 23I</number> Power to adjudicate.-
<section><tid>378167</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of adjudging under sections 23A, 23B, 23C, 23D, 23E, 23F, 23G and 23H, the Securities and Exchange Board of India shall appoint any officer not below the rank of a Division Chief of the Securities and Exchange Board of India to be an adjudicating officer for holding an inquiry in the prescribed manner after giving any person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard for the purpose of imposing any penalty. 

</section>

<section><tid>984296</tid>
<number>2</number>While holding an inquiry, the adjudicating officer shall have power to summon and enforce the attendance of any person acquainted with the facts and circumstances of the case to give evidence or to produce any document, which in the opinion of the adjudicating officer, may be useful for or relevant to the subject- matter of the inquiry and if, on such inquiry, he is satisfied that the person has failed to comply with the provisions of any of the sections specified in sub- section (1), he may impose such penalty as he thinks fit in accordance with the provisions of any of those sections.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1137230</tid>
<number> 23J</number> Factors to be taken into account by adjudicating officer.- While adjudging the quantum of penalty under section 23-I, the adjudicating officer shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:-
<section><tid>549726</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount of disproportionate gain or unfair advantage, wherever quantifiable, made as a result of the default;

</section>

<section><tid>614488</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of loss caused to an investor or group of investors as a result of the default;

</section>

<section><tid>324288</tid>
<number>c</number>the repetitive nature of the default.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1970903</tid>
<number>23K</number>Crediting realized by way of penalties to Consolidated Fund of India.- All sums realised by way of penalties under this Act shall be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India.
</article>



<article><tid>301007</tid>
<number> 23L</number> Appeal to Securities Appellate Tribunal.-
<section><tid>1418647</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved, by the order or decision of the recognised stock exchange or the adjudicating officer or any order made by the Securities and Exchange Board of India under section 4B, may prefer an appeal before the Securities Appellate Tribunal and the provisions of sections 22B, 22C, 22D and 22E of this Act, shall apply, as far as may be, to such appeals. 

</section>

<section><tid>1900713</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal under sub- section (1) shall be filed within a period of forty- five days from the date on which a copy of the order or decision is received by the appellant and it shall be in such form and be accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed:
Provided that the Securities Appellate Tribunal may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period of forty- five days if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing it within that period.


</section>

<section><tid>623568</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of an appeal under sub- section (1), the Securities Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the appeal, an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, confirming, modifying or setting aside the order appealed against.

</section>

<section><tid>98343</tid>
<number>4</number>The Securities Appellate Tribunal shall send a copy of every order made by it to the parties to the appeal and to the concerned adjudicating officer.

</section>

<section><tid>1861598</tid>
<number>5</number>The appeal filed before the Securities Appellate Tribunal under sub- 
section (1) shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the appeal finally within six months from the date of receipt of the appeal.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1436575</tid>
<number> 23M</number> Offences.-
<section><tid>1297237</tid>
<number>1</number>Without prejudice to any award of penalty by the adjudicating officer under this Act, if any person contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of the provisions of this Act or of any rules or regulations or bye- laws made thereunder, for which no punishment is provided elsewhere in this Act, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years, or with fine, which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees or with both. 

</section>

<section><tid>1001099</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person fails to pay the penalty imposed by the adjudicating officer or fails to comply with any of his directions or orders, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one month but which may extend to ten years, or with fine, which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees, or with both.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>314172</tid>
<number>23N</number>Composition of certain offences.- Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), any offence punishable under this Act, not being an offence punishable with imprisonment only, or with imprisonment and also with fine, may either before or after the institution of any proceeding, be compounded by a Securities Appellate Tribunal or a court before which such proceedings are pending.
</article>



<article><tid>1963335</tid>
<number> 23O</number> Power to grant immunity.-
<section><tid>1913716</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, on recommendation by the Securities and Exchange Board of India, if the Central Government is satisfied, that any person, who is alleged to have violated any of the provisions of this Act or the rules or the regulations made thereunder, has made a full and true disclosure in respect of alleged violation, grant to such person, subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, immunity from prosecution for any offence under this Act, or the rules or the regulations made thereunder or also from the imposition of any penalty under this Act with respect to the alleged violation: 
Provided that no such immunity shall be granted by the Central Government in cases where the proceedings for the prosecution for any such offence have been instituted before the date of receipt of application for grant of such immunity:

Provided further that the recommendation of the Securities and Exchange Board of India under this sub- section shall not be binding upon the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1687740</tid>
<number>2</number>An immunity granted to a person under sub- section (1) may, at any time, be withdrawn by the Central Government, if it is satisfied that such person had, in the course of the proceedings, not complied with the condition on which the immunity was granted or had given false evidence, and thereupon such person may be tried for the offence with respect to which the immunity was granted or for any other offence of which he appears to have been guilty in connection with the contravention and shall also become liable to the imposition of any penalty under this Act to which such person would have been liable, had not such immunity been granted.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1913206</tid>
<number> 12</number> Amendment of section 25.- In section 25 of the principal Act, the words, brackets and figure" sub- section
<section><tid>1157959</tid>
<number>1</number>of" shall be omitted. 



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>291925</tid>
<number> 13</number> Substitution of new section for section 26.- For section 26 of the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 26. Cognizance of offences by courts.- (1) No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act or any rules or regulations or bye- laws made thereunder, save on a complaint made by the Central Government or State Government or the Securities and Exchange Board of India or a recognised stock exchange or by any person.

<section><tid>1730958</tid>
<number>2</number>No court inferior to that of a Court of Session shall try any offence punishable under this Act.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1900650</tid>
<number> 14</number> Insertion of new section 27B.- After section 27A of the principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 27B. Right to receive income from mutual fund.- (1) It shall be lawful for the holder of any securities, being units or other instruments issued by any mutual fund, whose name appears on the books of the mutual fund issuing the said security to receive and retain any income in respect of units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund declared by the mutual fund in respect thereof for any year, notwithstanding that the said security, being units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund, has already been transferred by him for consideration, unless the transferee who claims the income in respect of units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund from the transferor has lodged the security and all other documents relating to the transfer which may be required by the mutual fund with the mutual fund for being registered in his name within fifteen days of the date on which the income in respect of units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund became due.

Explanation.- The period specified in this section shall be extended-

<section><tid>150810</tid>
<number>i</number>in case of death of the transferee, by the actual period taken by his legal representative to establish his claim to the income in respect of units or other instrument issued by the mutual fund;

</section>

<section><tid>256234</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of loss of the transfer deed by theft or any other cause beyond the control of transferee, by the actual period taken for the replacement thereof; and

</section>

<section><tid>1249714</tid>
<number>iii</number>in case of delay in the lodging of any security, being units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund, and other documents relating to the transfer due to causes connected with the post, by the actual period of the delay.

<subsection><tid>1570806</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect-

<subsubsection><tid>903509</tid>
<number>a</number>the right of a mutual fund to pay any income from units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund which has become due to any person, whose name is for the time being registered in the books of the mutual fund as the holder of the security being units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund in respect of which the income in respect of units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund has become due; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1815120</tid>
<number>b</number>the right of a transferee of any security, being units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund, to enforce against the transferor or any other person, his rights, if any, in relation to the transfer in any case where the mutual fund has refused to register the transfer of the security being units or other instruments issued by the mutual fund in the name of the transferee.".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1315850</tid>
<number> 15</number> Amendment of section 30.- In section 30 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1997580</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2), for clause (ha), the following clauses shall be substituted, namely:-
" (ha) the grounds on which the securities of a company may be delisted from any recognised stock exchange under sub- section (1) of section 21A;


</section>

<section><tid>1965530</tid>
<number>hb</number>the form in which an appeal may be filed before the Securities Appellate Tribunal under sub- section (2) of section 21A and the fees payable in respect of such appeal;

</section>

<section><tid>1033888</tid>
<number>hc</number>the form in which an appeal may be filed before the Securities Appellate Tribunal under section 22A and the fees payable in respect of such appeal;

</section>

<section><tid>1934086</tid>
<number>hd</number>the manner of inquiry under sub- section (1) of section 23-I;

</section>

<section><tid>1547363</tid>
<number>he</number>the form in which an appeal may be filed before the Securities Appellate Tribunal under section 23L and the fees payable in respect of such appeal;";

</section>

<section><tid>1046904</tid>
<number>b</number>for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be substituted, namely:-
" (3) Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>980720</tid>
<number> 16</number> Insertion of new section 31.- After section 30 of the principal Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 31. Power of Securities and Exchange Board of India to make regulations.- (1) Without prejudice to the provisions contained in section 30 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, <year>1992</year> (15 of <year>1992</year>), the Securities and Exchange Board of India may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act.

<section><tid>905850</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for the manner in which at least fifty- one per cent. of equity share capital of a recognised stock exchange is held within twelve months from the date of publication of the order under sub- section (7) of section 4B by the public other than the shareholders having trading rights under sub- section (8) of that section.

</section>

<section><tid>881727</tid>
<number>3</number>Every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that regulation.".
CHAPTER III

AMENDMENTS TO THE DEPOSITORIES ACT, <year>1996</year>

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENTS TO THE DEPOSITORIES ACT, <year>1996</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>775055</tid>
<number> 17</number> Insertion of new sections 19A, 19B, 19C, 19D, 19E, 19F, 19E, 19F, 19G, 19H, 19-I, 19J.- After section 19 of the Depositories Act, <year>1996</year> (22 of <year>1996</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the principal Act), the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 19A. Penalty for failure to furnish information, return, etc.- Any person, who is required under this Act or any rules or regulations or bye- laws made thereunder,-

<section><tid>329653</tid>
<number>a</number>to furnish any information, document, books, returns or report to the Board, fails to furnish the same within the time specified therefor, he shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less for each such failure;

</section>

<section><tid>778121</tid>
<number>b</number>to file any return or furnish any information, books or other documents within the time specified therefor in the regulations or bye- laws, fails to file return or furnish the same within the time specified therefor, he shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less;

</section>

<section><tid>891150</tid>
<number>c</number>to maintain books of account or records, fails to maintain the same, he shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1422441</tid>
<number>19B</number>Penalty for failure to enter into an agreement.- If a depository or participant or any issuer or its agent or any person, who is registered as an intermediary under the provisions of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, <year>1992</year> (15 of <year>1992</year>), and is required under this Act or any rules or regulations made thereunder, to enter into an agreement, fails to enter into such agreement, such depository or participant or issuer or its agent or intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less for every such failure.
</article>



<article><tid>1221573</tid>
<number>19C</number>Penalty for failure to redress investors' grievances.- If any depository or participant or any issuer or its agent or any person, who is registered as an intermediary under the provisions of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, <year>1992</year>, after having been called upon by the Board in writing, to redress the grievances of the investors, fails to redress such grievances within the time specified by the Board, such depository or participant or issuer or its agents or intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.
</article>



<article><tid>1864940</tid>
<number>19D</number>Penalty for delay in dematerialisation or issue of certificate of securities.- If any issuer or its agent or any person, who is registered as an intermediary under the provisions of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, <year>1992</year> (15 of <year>1992</year>), fails to dematerialise or issue the certificate of securities on opting out of a depository by the investors, within the time specified under this Act or regulations or bye- laws made thereunder or abets in delaying the process of dematerialisation or issue the certificate of securities on opting out of a depository of securities, such issuer or its agent or intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.
</article>



<article><tid>1415747</tid>
<number>19E</number>Penalty for failure to reconcile records.- If a depository or participant or any issuer or its agent or any person, who is registered as an intermediary under the provisions of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, <year>1992</year> (15 of <year>1992</year>), fails to reconcile the records of dematerialised securities with all the securities issued by the issuer as specified in the regulations, such depository or participant or issuer or its agent or intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.
</article>



<article><tid>1003403</tid>
<number>19F</number>Penalty for failure to comply with directions issued by Board under section 19 of the Act.- If any person fails to comply with the directions issued by the Board under section 19, within the time specified by it, he shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.
</article>



<article><tid>95594</tid>
<number>19G</number>Penalty for contravention where no separate penalty has been provided.- Whoever fails to comply with any provision of this Act, the rules or the regulations or bye- laws made or directions issued by the Board thereunder for which no separate penalty has been provided, shall be liable to a penalty which may extend to one crore rupees.
</article>



<article><tid>1209594</tid>
<number> 19H</number> Power to adjudicate.-
<section><tid>1343003</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of adjudging under sections 19A, 19B, 19C, 19D, 19E, 19F and 19G, the Board shall appoint any officer not below the rank of a Division Chief of the Securities and Exchange Board of India to be an adjudicating officer for holding an inquiry in the prescribed manner after giving any person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard for the purpose of imposing any penalty. 

</section>

<section><tid>915043</tid>
<number>2</number>While holding an inquiry, the adjudicating officer shall have power to summon and enforce the attendance of any person acquainted with the facts and circumstances of the case to give evidence or to produce any document, which in the opinion of the adjudicating officer, may be useful for or relevant to the subject- matter of the inquiry and if, on such inquiry, he is satisfied that the person has failed to comply with the provisions of any of the sections specified in sub- section (1), he may impose such penalty as he thinks fit in accordance with the provisions of any of those sections.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>278668</tid>
<number> 19I</number> Factors to be taken into account by adjudicating officer.- While adjudging the quantum of penalty under section 19H, the adjudicating officer shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:-
<section><tid>760273</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount of disproportionate gain or unfair advantage, wherever quantifiable, made as a result of the default;

</section>

<section><tid>1041683</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of loss caused to an investor or group of investors as a result of the default;

</section>

<section><tid>343518</tid>
<number>c</number>the repetitive nature of the default.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1050876</tid>
<number>19J</number>Crediting sums realized by way of penalties to Consolidated Fund of India.- All sums realised by way of penalties under this Act shall be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India.".


</article>



<article><tid>205612</tid>
<number> 18</number> Substitution of new section for section 20.- For section 20 of the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 20. Offences.- (1) Without prejudice to any award of penalty by the adjudicating officer under this Act, if any person contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the contravention of the provisions of this Act or of any rules or regulations or bye- laws made thereunder, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years, or with fine, which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees, or with both.

<section><tid>1509775</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person fails to pay the penalty imposed by the adjudicating officer or fails to comply with any of his directions or orders, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than one month but which may extend to ten years, or with fine, which may extend to twenty- five crore rupees, or with both.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>770508</tid>
<number> 19</number> Substitution of new section for section 22.- For section 22 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be substituted, namely:-
" 22. Cognizance of offences by courts.- (1) No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act or any rules or regulations or bye- laws made thereunder, save on a complaint made by the Central Government or State Government or the Securities and Exchange Board of India or by any person.

<section><tid>412679</tid>
<number>2</number>No court inferior to that of a Court of Session shall try any offence punishable under this Act.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1050619</tid>
<number>22A</number>Composition of certain offences.- Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>), any offence punishable under this Act, not being an offence punishable with imprisonment only, or with imprisonment and also with fine, may either before or after the institution of any proceeding, be compounded by a Securities Appellate Tribunal or a court before which such proceedings are pending.
</article>



<article><tid>852408</tid>
<number> 22B</number> Power to grant immunity.-
<section><tid>807765</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, on recommendation by the Board, if the Central Government is satisfied, that any person, who is alleged to have violated any of the provisions of this Act or the rules or the regulations made thereunder, has made a full and true disclosure in respect of alleged violation, grant to such person, subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, immunity from prosecution for any offence under this Act, or the rules or the regulations made thereunder or also from the imposition of any penalty under this Act with respect to the alleged violation:  
Provided that no such immunity shall be granted by the Central Government in cases where the proceedings for the prosecution for any such offence have been instituted before the date of receipt of application for grant of such immunity:
Provided further that recommendation of the Board under this sub- section shall not be binding upon the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1245103</tid>
<number>2</number>An immunity granted to a person under sub- section (1) may, at any time, be withdrawn by the Central Government, if it is satisfied that such person had, in the course of the proceedings, not complied with the condition on which the immunity was granted or had given false evidence, and thereupon such person may be tried for the offence with respect to which the immunity was granted or for any other offence of which he appears to have been guilty in connection with the contravention and shall also become liable to the imposition of any penalty under this Act to which such person would have been liable, had not such immunity been granted.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>231999</tid>
<number>20</number>Amendment of section 23A.- In section 23A of the principal Act, in sub- section 1, after the words, brackets and figures" Save as provided in sub- section (2), any person aggrieved by an order of the Board made, on and after the commencement of the Securities Laws (Second Amendment) Act, <year>1999</year> (32 of <year>1999</year>), under this Act, or the regulations made thereunder," and before the words" may prefer an appeal to a Securities Appellate Tribunal having a jurisdiction in the matter," the words" or by an order made by an adjudicating officer under this Act" shall be inserted.


</article>



<article><tid>1755727</tid>
<number>21</number>Substitution of new section for section 23F.- For section 23F of the principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 23F. Appeal to Supreme Court.- Any person aggrieved by any decision or order of the Securities Appellate Tribunal may file an appeal to the Supreme Court within sixty days from the date of communication of the decision or order of the Securities Appellate Tribunal to him on any question of law arising out of such order:

Provided that the Supreme Court may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not exceeding sixty days.".



</article>



<article><tid>1157921</tid>
<number> 22</number> Amendment of section 24.- In section 24 of the principal Act, in sub- section (2), for clause (a), the following clauses shall be substituted, namely:-
" (a) the manner of inquiry under sub- section (1) of section 19H;

<section><tid>1714030</tid>
<number>aa</number>the time within which an appeal may be preferred under sub- section (1) of section 23;".
CHAPTER IV

REPEAL AND SAVING

CHAPTER IV

REPEAL AND SAVING




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1435069</tid>
<number> 23</number> Repeal and saving.-
<section><tid>1745698</tid>
<number>1</number>The Securities Laws (Amendment) Ordinance, <year>2004</year> (Ord. 4 of <year>2004</year>) is hereby repealed. 

</section>

<section><tid>510163</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken under the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, <year>1956</year> (42 of <year>1956</year>) and the Depositories Act, <year>1996</year> (22 of <year>1996</year>), as amended by the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of those Acts, as amended by this Act.
T. K. VISWANATHAN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.




</section>

</article>



 </act>