<act><tid>1630761</tid>
<title>The Explosive Substances (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 54 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 11th December, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Explosive Substances Act, <year>2001</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>611938</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>449608</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Explosive Substances (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1850900</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>984836</tid>
<number> 2</number> Substitution of new sections for sections 2 to 5.- In the 
Explosive Substances Act, <year>1908</year> (6 of <year>1908</year>.)  (hereinafter referred to  
  as the principal Act), for sections 2 to 5, the following sections 
shall be substituted, namely:-
' 2. Definitions.- In this Act,-

<section><tid>1397663</tid>
<number>a</number>the expression" explosive substance" shall be deemed to include 
any materials for making any explosive substance; also any apparatus, 
machine, implement or material used, or intended to be used, or 
adapted for causing, or aiding in causing, any explo ion in or with 
any explosive substance; also any part of any such apparatus, machine 
or implement;

</section>

<section><tid>481454</tid>
<number>b</number>the expression" special category explosive substance" shall be 
deemed to include research development explosive (RDX), penta 
erythritol tetra nitrate (PETN), high melting explosive (HMX), tri 
nitro toluene (TNT), low temperature plastic explosive (L PE), 
composition exploding (CE) 2, 4, 6 phenyl methyl nitramine or tetryl, 
OCTOL (mixture of high melting explosive and tri nitro toluene), 
plastic explosive kirkee- 1 (PEK- 1) and RDX TNT compounds and other 
similar type of explosive and a combination the eof and remote control 
devices causing explosion and any other substance and a combination 
thereof which the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, specify for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1464999</tid>
<number> 3</number> Punishment for causing explosion likely to endanger life or 
property.- Any person who unlawfully and maliciously causes by-
<section><tid>1812518</tid>
<number>a</number>any explosive substance an explosion of a nature likely to 
endanger life or to cause serious injury to property shall, whether 
any injury to person or property has been actually caused or not, be 
punished with imprisonment for life, or with rigorous mprisonment of 
either description which shall not be less than ten years, and shall 
also be liable to fine;

</section>

<section><tid>1838117</tid>
<number>b</number>any special category explosive substance an explosion of a nature 
likely to endanger life or to cause serious injury to property shall, 
whether any injury to person or property has been actually caused or 
not, be punished with death, or rigorous impr sonment for life, and 
shall also be liable to fine.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>506858</tid>
<number> 4</number> Punishment for attempt to cause explosion, or for making or 
keeping explosive with intent to endanger life or property.- Any 
person who unlawfully and maliciously-
<section><tid>1631487</tid>
<number>a</number>does any act with intent to cause by an explosive substance or 
special category explosive substance, or conspires to cause by an 
explosive substance or special category explosive substance, an 
explosion of a nature likely to endanger life or to cause serious 
injury to property; or

</section>

<section><tid>7151</tid>
<number>b</number>makes or has in his possession or under his control any explosive 
substance or special category explosive substance with intent by means 
thereof to endanger life, or cause serious injury to property, or to 
enable any other person by means thereof to ndanger life or cause 
serious injury to property in India,
shall, whether any explosion does or does not take place and whether 
any injury to person or property has been actually caused or not, be 
punished,-


<subsection><tid>962304</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of any explosive substance, with imprisonment for 
life, or with imprisonment of either description for a term which may 
extend to ten years, and shall also be liable to fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1788318</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of any special category explosive substance, with 
rigorous imprisonment for life, or with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to ten years, and shall also be liable to fine.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>279731</tid>
<number> 5</number> Punishment for making or possessing explosives under suspicious 
circumstances.- Any person who makes or knowingly has in his 
possession or under his control any explosive substance or special 
category explosive substance, under such circumstances as t give rise 
to a reasonable suspicion that he is not making it or does not have it 
in his possession or under his control for a lawful object, shall, 
unless he can show that he made it or had it in his possession or 
under his control for a lawful object, e punished,-
<section><tid>834853</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of any explosive substance, with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to ten years, and shall also be liable to fine;

</section>

<section><tid>1139685</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any special category explosive substance, with 
rigorous imprisonment for life, or with rigorous imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to ten years, and shall also be liable to 
fine.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1464999</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 7.- In section 7 of the principal Act, for 
the words" Central Government", the words" District Magistrate" shall 
be substituted.
SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>