<act><tid>1631854</tid>
<title>THE PUBLIC ACCOUNTANTS' DEFAULT ACT, 18501</title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1850</year> 
[ 22nd March, <year>1850</year>]
For avoiding loss by the default of Public Accountants.

Preamble.-- For better[ avoidance of loss through the default of 
public accountants: It is enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>938396</tid>
<number>1</number>Public Accountants to give security.-- Every public accountant 
shall give security for the due discharge of the trusts of his office, 
and for the due account of all moneys which shall come into his 
possession or control, by reason of his office.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been partially extended to Berar by the Berar Laws 
Act, <year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>) and has been declared to be in force in all 
the Provinces of India, except the Scheduled Districts, by the 
Laws Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3.

It has been declared to be in force in the Sonthal Parganas 
by the Sonthal Parganas Settlement Regulations <year>1872</year> (3 of <year>1872</year>), 
s. 3.

It has been declared by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following other Scheduled Districts, namely:-


West Jalpaiguri, the Western 
Hills of Darjiling, the Darjiling 
Tarai and the Damson Sub- 
Division of the Darjiling 
District... See Gazette of India <year>1881</year>, Pt. 1, p. 74.

The Districts of Hazaribagh, 
Lohardaga (now the Ranchi  
District, see Calcutta Gazette, 
  <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 44), and Man- 
bhum, and Pargana Dhalbhum 
and the Kolhan in the District 
of Singbhum.... Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

Kumaon and Garhwal.. Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 605.

The Scheduled portion of the 
Mirzapur District.. Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 383.

Jaunsar Bawar... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 382.

The Scheduled Districts of the 
C. P. (now Madhya Pradesh). Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 771.

The Scheduled Districts Gan- 
jam and Vizagapatam.. Ditto <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 870. 
and

Fort St. George Gazette. <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 666.

The Act has been extended to Union territory of Pondicherry by 
Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

The Act has been repealed in its application to Bellary District 
by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>.

The Act has been amended in Orissa by Orissa Act 3 of <year>1969</year>.

It has been extended, by notification[ under s.[ 5 of the last- 
mentioned[ Act, to the following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

The Tarai of the Province of 
Agra... See Gazette of India, <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 505.

Ajmer and Merwara. Ditto <year>1878</year>, Pt. I, p. 380.

Coorg. Ditto <year>1911</year>, Pt. I, p. 1477.

The Act has been partially repealed in the Bombay State, see the 
Bombay Land Revenue Code, <year>1879</year> (Bom. Act 5 of <year>1879</year>), 2 and Sch. A; and 
in Assam, in which it was declared to be in force by notifications 
under s. 3 (a) of the Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), 
Gazette of India, <year>1878</year> and <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, pp. 523 and 631, respectively, 
see the Assam Land and Revenue Regulation, <year>1886</year> (1 of <year>1886</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1302112</tid>
<number>2</number>Amount and kind of security, and with what sureties.-- In 
default of any Act having special reference to the office of any 
public accountant, the security given shall be of such amount and 
kind, real or personal, or both, and with such sureties (regard being  
  had to the nature of the office), as shall be required by any rules 
made or to be made from time to time by the authority by which each 
public accountant is appointed to his office, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</article>



<article><tid>993665</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" Public accountant" defined.-- For the purposes of 
sections 1 and 2 of this Act, the expression" public accountant" means 
any person who as Official Assignee or Trustee, or as sarbarahkar, is 
entrusted with the receipt, custody or control of any moneys or 
securities for money, or the management of any lands belonging to any 
other person or persons, and for the purposes of sections 4 and 5 of 
this Act the expression shall also include any person who, by reason 
of any office held by him in the service of the Central Government or 
the Government of a <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> State, is entrusted with the receipt, custody 
or control of any moneys or securities for money, or the management of 
any lands belonging to such Government.]


</article>



<article><tid>457559</tid>
<number>4</number>Prosecution of accountants and sureties.-- The person or 
persons at the head of the office to which any public accountant 
belongs may proceed against any such public accountant and his 
sureties for any loss or defalcation in his accounts, as if the amount 
thereof were an arrear of land- revenue due to Government.


</article>



<article><tid>914977</tid>
<number>5</number>Enactments applied to proceedings by and against accountants.- 
- All Regulations and Acts now or hereafter to be in force for the 
recovery of arrears of land- revenue due to Government, and for 
recovery of damages by any person wrongfully proceeded against for any 
such arrear shall apply, with such changes in the forms of procedure 
as are necessary to make them applicable to the case, to the 
proceedings against and by such public accountant.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" subject to the approval of the Governor or Governor in 
Council of the Presidency or place" rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
2. Subs., ibid., for the original s. 3. 
3. The word and letter" Part A" omitted by the Adaptation of Laws 
 (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>. 
4. For the law relating to the recovery of revenue- arrears, see the 
Revenue Recovery Act, <year>1890</year> (1 of <year>1890</year>).


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Public accountants to give security. Every public accountant 
shall give security for the due discharge of the trusts of his office, 
and for the due account of all 
1 Short title given by Act 14 of <year>1897</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
2 This Act has been partially extended to Berar by the Berar Laws 
Act, <year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>) and has been declared to be in force in all the 
Provinces of India (formerly the Part A States), except the Scheduled 
Districts, by the Laws Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3. 
It has been declared to be in force in the Santhal Parganas by 
the Santhal Parganas Settlement Regulation (3 of <year>1872</year>), s. 3. 
It has been extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 
26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Sch. It has been amended in Orissa by Orissa Act 
3 of <year>1969</year>. 
It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following other Scheduled Districts, namely:--

West Jalpaiguri, the Western Hills 
of Darjiling, the Darjiling Tarai 
and the Damson Sub- Division of the 
Darjiling District......... See Gazette of India, <year>1881</year>, 
Pt. I, p. 74.

The Districts of Hazaribagh, Loha- 
rdaga (now the Ranchi District See  
Calcutta Gazette, <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 
  44), and Manbhum, and Pargana Dha- 
lbhum and the Kolhan in the Distr- 
ict of Singbhum.......... Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

Kumaon and Garhwal.......... Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 605.

The Schedule portion of the Mirzapur 
District............... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 383.

Jaunsar Bawar............. Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 382.

The Scheduled Districts of the C. P. 
 (now Madhya Pradesh)......... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 771.

The Scheduled District in Ganjam and 
Vizagapatam............. Ditto <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 870.

and Fort St. George Gazette, 
<year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 666.

It has been extended, by notification under s. 5 of the 1ast- 
mentined Act, to the following Scheduled Districts, namely:--

The Tarai of the Province of Agra See Gazette of India, <year>1876</year>, 
Pt. I, p. 505.

Ajmer and Merwara.......... Ditto <year>1878</year>, Pt. I, p. 380.

Coorg................ Ditto <year>1911</year>, Pt. I, p. 1477.

The Act has been partially repealed in the Bombay State, see the 
Bombay Land- Revenue Code, <year>1879</year> (Bom. Act 5 of <year>1879</year>). s. 2 and Sch. A; 
and in Assam in which it was declared to be in force by notifications 
under s. 3 (a) of the Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), 
Gazette of India, <year>1878</year> and <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, pp. 523 and 631, respectively, 
see the Assam Land and Revenue Regulation, <year>1886</year> (1 of <year>1886</year>).

The Act has been repealed in its application to Bellary District 
by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>.

Extended to the Union Territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, 
s. 3 and Schedule.

Amended in Orissa by Orissa Act 3 of <year>1969</year>.


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Amount and kind of security, and with what sureties. In 
default of any Act having special reference to the office of any 
public accountant, the security given shall be of such amount and 
kind, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> real or personal, or both, and with such sureties (regard  
  being had to the nature of the office), as shall be required by any 
rules made or to be made from time to time, by the authority by which 
each public accountant is appointed to his office <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.[ 22nd March, 
<year>1850</year>.]


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" Public accountant" defined. For the purposes of sections 1 
and 2 of this Act, the expression" public accountant" means any person 
who, as Official Assignee or Trustee, or as sarbarahkar, is entrusted 
with the receipt, custody or control of any moneys or securities for 
money, or the management of any lands belonging to any other person or 
persons; and for the purposes of sections 4 and 5 of this Act the 
expression shall also include any person who, by reason of any office 
held by him in the service of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Central Government or the 
Government of a <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State], is entrusted with the receipt, custody or 
control of any moneys or securities for money, or the management of 
any lands belonging <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> to such Government].]


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Prosecution of accountants and sureties. The person or persons 
at the head of the office to which any public accountant belongs may 
proceed against any such public accountant and his sureties for any 
loss or defalcation in his accounts, as if the amount thereof were an 
arrear of land- revenue due to Government.


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Enactments applied to proceedings by and against accountants. 
All Regulations and Acts now or hereafter to be in force for the 
recovery of arrears of land- revenue due to Government, and for 
recovery of damages by any person wrongfully proceeded against for any 
such arrear shall apply, with such changes in the forms of procedure 
as are necessary to make them applicable to the case, to the 
proceedings against and by such public accountant. <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>


</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>[ Validation of former rules.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, <year>1870</year> 
 (14 of <year>1870</year>), s. 1 and Sch., Pt. II. 
1 The words" subject to the approval of the Governor or Governor in 
Council of the Presidency or place" rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
2 Subs., ibid., for the original s. 3. 
3 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Crown in India". 
4 The word and letter" Part A" omitted by the Adaptation of Laws 
 (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>. 
5 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" to the Crown". 
6 For the law relating to the recovery of revenue- arrears, see the 
Revenue Recovery Act, <year>1890</year> (1 of <year>1890</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>