<act><title>THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963 </title> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 19631
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Maternity Benefit
2[Mines 
and Circus] Rules, 1963.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 1st November, 1963.
  



</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>         <number>a</number> the “Act” means the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961 
(53 of 1961);
 
        1[(aa) 
“circus” means an establishment wherein persons are employed for the exhibition 
of equestrian, acrobatic and other performances;]
 
          2[(b) 
“Competent Authority” means the Chief Labour Commissioner (Central);]
 </section><section>         <number>c</number> “form” means a formAppended to these rules;
 </section><section>         <number>d</number> “muster-roll” means a muster-roll maintained 
under rule 3;
 </section><section>         <number>e</number> “Registered Medical Practitioner” means a 
medical practitioner whose name has been enrolled in a register maintained under 
any law for the time being in force regulating the registration of practitioners 
of medicine;
 </section><section>         <number>f</number> “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>g</number> All other words and expressions used 
hereinafter but not defined herein shall have the same meaning as respectively 
assigned to them in the Act.
  



</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>3</number> Muster-roll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer of 

1[every mine or circus] in which women 
are employed shall prepare and maintain a muster-roll in form ‘A’ and shall 
enter therein particulars of all women workers in 

2[the mine or circus].
 </section><section><number>2</number> All entries in the 
muster-roll shall be made in ink and maintained up-to-date and it shall always 
be available for inspection by the Inspector during working hours.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The employer may enter in 
the muster-roll such other particulars as may be required for any other purpose 
of the Act.
  



</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>4</number> Proof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fact that a woman is pregnant or has been delivered of a child 

1[or has undergone miscarriage or medical 
termination of pregnancy or tubectomy operation or is suffering from illness 
arising out of pregnancy, delivery, premature birth of a child or miscarriage or 
or medical termination of pregnancy or tubectomy operation] shall be proved by 
the production of a certificate to that effect,—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number> from a Medical Officer of a regional hospital 
or a dispensary set up under the Coal Mines Welfare Organisation; or
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number> where there is a Mines Board of Health within 
whose jurisdiction
2[the 
mine] is situated, from the Medical Officer of that Board; or 
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number> from a Registered Medical Practitioner.
 The certificate shall be in form 
‘B’.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The fact that a woman has 
been confined may also be proved by the production of a certified extract from a 
birth register maintained under the provisions of any law for the time being in 
force or a certificate signed by a registered midwife.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The fact that a woman has 
undergone miscarriage may also be proved by the production of a certificate 
signed by a registered midwife.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The fact of death of a woman 
or a child may be proved by the production of a certificate to that effect in 
form ‘C’ from any of the authorities referred to in sub-rule (1) or by the 
production of a certified extract from a death register maintained under the 
provisions of any law for the time being in force.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The certificate from a 
registered midwife shall be in form ‘D’.
  



</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Payment of maternity and other benefit. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A woman employed in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[a mine or circus] and entitled to maternity benefit shall give notice to her employer in form ‘E' and the employer shall make payment of the maternity benefit and any other amount due under the Act to the woman concerned, or, in case of her death before receiving such maternity benefit or amount, or where the employer is liable for maternity benefit under the second proviso to sub-section (3) of section 5, to the person nominated by the woman in her notice in form ‘E' and in case there is no such nominee to her legal representative. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of doubt, the maternity benefit or other amount due to a woman employed in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[a mine or circus] shall be deposited by the employer, within two months of the date of death of the woman concerned with the Competent Authority, who shall, after making necessary enquiries, pay it to the person who, in his opinion, is entitled to receive it. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Whenever the payment referred to in sub-rule (1) is made, a receipt shall be obtained by the employer in form ‘F' from the person to whom the payment is made. In cases falling under sub-rule (2), a receipt shall be given to the employer by the Competent Authority. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The medical bonus shall be paid along with the second instalment of the maternity benefit. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The maternity benefit or any other amount payable under section 7 shall be paid within two months of the date of death of the woman entitled to receive such benefit or amount. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The wages payable under section 9 shall be paid to the woman entitled to receive such wages within forty-eight hours of production by her of the certificate in form ‘B' or form ‘D'. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>6</number>(a) The wages payable under section 9A of the Act shall be paid to the woman entitled to receive such wages within forty-eight hours of production by her of the certificate in form B.] 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The wages payable under section 10 shall be paid to the woman entitled to receive such wages within forty-eight hours of the expiry of the period of leave referred to in that section. 



</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>6</number> Break for nursing child.—Each 
of the two breaks mentioned in section 11 shall be of 15 minutes’ duration. An 
extra sufficient period, depending upon the distance to be covered, shall be 
allowed for the purpose of journey to and from the creche or the place where the 
children are left by women while on duty, provided that such extra period shall 
not be of less than 5 minutes and more than 15 minutes’ duration. If any dispute 
arises regarding such extra period, the matter shall be referred to the 
Competent Authority for decision.
</article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>7</number> Duties and powers of the 
Competent Authority and Inspectors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Competent Authority shall be responsible for the administration of these 
rules throughout the territories to which they extend.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every Inspector shall 
discharge his duties within the area assigned to him by the Central Government 
and shall act under the supervision and control of the Competent Authority.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every Inspector shall at 
each inspection of 

1[a mine or circus] see.—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number> whether due action has been taken on every 
notice given under section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number> whether the Muster-roll prescribed under rule 3 
is correctly maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number> whether there have been any cases of discharge 
or dismissal or notices of discharge or dismissal in contravention of the 
provisions of section 12 since the last inspection;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>d</number> whether the provisions of sub-section (1) of 
section 4, sub-sections (5) and (6) of section 6, sections 8, 9,
2[9A], 
10, 11, 13 and 19 have been complied with and whether amounts due have been paid 
within the prescribed time;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>e</number> whether there have been any cases of deprival 
of maternity benefit or medical bonus in contravention of sub-section (2) of 
section 12; and 
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>f</number> how far the irregularities pointed out at 
previous inspections have been remedied and how far orders previously issued 
have been complied with.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Where an Inspector observes 
irregularities against the Act or these Rules, he shall issue orders in writing 
to the employer asking the latter to rectify the irregularities within a 
specified period and to report compliance to the Inspector.
  



</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>8</number> Acts which constitute 
gross misconduct.—The following acts 
shall constitute gross misconduct for purpose of section 12, namely:—
 <section>         <number>a</number> wilful destruction of employer’s goods or 
property;
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> assaulting any superior or co-employee at the 
place of work;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number> criminal offence involving moral turpitude 
resulting in conviction in a court of law;
 </section><section>         <number>d</number> theft, fraud, or dishonesty in connection with 
the employer’s business or property; and
 </section><section>         <number>e</number> wilful non-observance of safety measure or 
rules on the subject or wilful interference with safety devices or with fire 
fighting equipment.
</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>9</number> Appeal under section 12.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 12 shall be preferred 
to the Competent Authority in form ‘G’.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appeal may be made in 
writing and either handed over personally or sent under a registered cover to 
the Competent Authority.
 </section><section><number>3</number> When an appeal is received, 
the Competent Authority shall furnish a copy of the memorandum of appeal to the 
employer, call for his reply thereto and also ask him to produce documents 
connected with the issue of the appeal by a fixed date. The Competent Authority 
may ascertain further details, if necessary, from the employer as well as from 
the woman. On considering the facts presented to him and ascertained by him the 
Competent Authority shall give his decision. In case the employer fails to 
submit his reply or produce the required documents within the specified period, 
the Competent Authority may give his decision ex parte.
</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>10</number> Complaint under section 
17.—
<section><number>1</number> A complaint under sub-section 
(1) of section 17 shall be made in writing in form ‘H’, or ‘I’ as the case may 
be.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a complaint referred to 
in section 17 is received by an Inspector, he shall examine the relevant records 
maintained by the employer in this behalf, examine any person employed in 

1[the mine or circus] and take down 
necessary statement for the purpose of the enquiry and if he is satisfied that 
the maternity benefit or the amount has been improperly withheld, he shall 
direct the employer to make the payment to the woman or to the person claiming 
the payment under section 7, as the case may be, immediately or within a 
specified period.
  


</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>11</number> Appeal under section 17.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal against the decision of the Inspector under sub-section (2) of section 
17, shall lie to the Competent Authority.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The aggrieved person shall 
prefer an appeal in writing to the Competent Authority in form ‘J’ and file 
other supporting documents.
 </section><section><number>3</number> When an appeal is received, 
the Competent Authority shall call from the Inspector before a fixed date, the 
record of the case. The Competent Authority shall, if necessary, also record the 
statements of the aggrieved person, and of the Inspector and seek clarification 
if any is required.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Taking into account the 
documents, the evidence produced before him and the facts presented to him or 
ascertained by him, the Competent Authority shall give his decision.
</section></article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>12</number> Supply of forms.—The 
employer shall supply to every woman employed by him at her request free of cost 
copies of forms ‘B’, ‘C’, ‘D’, ‘E’, ‘F’, ‘G’, ‘H’ and ‘I’.
</article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>13</number> Non-submission of 
notices, appeals or complaints in the prescribed forms.—Nothing 
in rules 5,9 and 10 shall affect the right of a woman entitled to receive 
maternity benefit or any other amount due under the Act if she fails to submit a 
notice, appeal or complaint under the said rules, as the case may be, in a 
prescribed form:
 Provided that where a notice, 
appeal or complaint under the said rules has been submitted by a woman entitled 
to receive maternity benefit or any other amount due under the Act in a form 
other than the prescribed form, the authority concerned may, within 15 days of 
the receipt of such notice, appeal or complaint require the woman to submit the 
notice, appeal or complaint, as the case may be, in the prescribed form.
</article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>14</number> Records.—Records 
kept under the provisions of the Act and these Rules shall be preserved for a 
period of two years from the date of their preparation.
</article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>15</number> Abstract.—The 
abstract of the provisions of the Act and these rules required to be exhibited 
under section 19 shall be in form ‘K’ and shall be exhibited in such manner as 
the Competent Authority may require.
</article> 
 THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
  
 <article><number>16</number> Annual returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer of 

1[every mine or circus] shall on or 
before the 21st day of January in each year submit to the Competent Authority a 
return in each of the forms ‘L’, ‘M’, ‘N’ and ‘O’ giving information as to the 
particulars specified in respect of the preceding year.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the employer of 

1[a mine or circus] to which the Act 
applies sells, abandons or discontinues the working of 

1[the mine or circus] he shall, within 
one month of the date of sale or abandonment or four months of the date of 
discontinuance, as the case may be, submit to the Competent Authority a further 
return in each of the said forms in respect of the period between the end of the 
preceding year and the date of sale, abandonment or discontinuance.
  


</section></article><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

formA
 

(See rule 3)
 

MUSTER-ROLL
 

            Name of
1[mine or 
circus]
 

       1. Serial Number.
 

       2. Name of woman and her father’s (or, if married, 
husband’s) name.
 

       3. Date of appointment.
 

       4. Nature of work.
 

       5. Dates with month and year in which she is 
employed, laid off and not employed.
 


 


  Month            No. of                 No. of                 No. 
  of                   Remarks
 


                      days                   days                   days not
 


 


                        employed           laid off                employed
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


 

 
 

       6. Date on which the woman gives notice under 
section 6.
 

       7. Date of discharge/dismissal, if any.
 

       8. Date of production of proof of pregnancy under 
section 6.
 

       9. Date of birth of child.
 

     10. Date of production of proof of 
delivery/miscarriage/2[Medical 
Termination of pregnancy/tubectomy operation/death.]
 

     11. Date of production of proof of illness referred to 
in section 10.
 

     12. Date with the amount of maternity benefit paid in 
advance of expected delivery.
 

     13. Date with the amount of subsequent payment of 
maternity benefit.
 

     14. Date with the amount of bonus, if paid, under 
section 8.
 

     15. Date with the amount of wages paid on account of 
leave under section 9.
 


3[15A. 
Date with the amount of wages paid on account of leave under section 9A.]
 

     16. Date with the amount of wages paid on account of 
leave under section 10 and period of leave granted.
 

     17. Name of the person nominated by the woman under 
section 6.
 

     18. If the woman dies, the date of her death, the name 
of the person to whom maternity benefit and/or other amount was paid, the amount 
thereof, and the date of payment.
 

     19. If the woman dies and the child survives, the name 
of the person to whom the amount of maternity benefit was paid on behalf of the 
child and the period for which it was paid.
 

     20. Signature of the employer of
4[the 
mine or circus] authenticating the entries in the muster-roll.
 

     21. Remarks column for the use of the Inspector.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
 

   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 70 
(E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   3.  Ins. by G.S.R. 70 
(E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   4.  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form B
 

[See rule 4(1)]
 

This is to certify that I examined.....wife/daughter of.....a 
woman employee in.......(name of 1[mine or 
circus]) on.....(date) and found/cannot discover that she is pregnant and is 
expected to be delivered of a child within (month and/days) from the above 
mentioned date/has undergone miscarriage/1[Medical 
termination of pregnancy or tubectomy operation]/has been delivered of a child 
on.....(date) or is suffering from .....(date) from illness arising out of 
pregnancy/delivery/premature birth of a child or miscarriage/1[Medical 
termination of pregnancy or tubectomy operation].
 

Signature, qualifications 
and designation of  
Medical Officer/Medical Practitioner.
 

Date......................
 

Definitions of “child” and “miscarriage” as in the Maternity 
Benefit Act, 1961.—
 

       1. “Child” includes a 
still-born child.
 

       2. “Miscarriage” means 
expulsion of the contents of a pregnant uterus at any period prior to or during 
the twenty-sixth week of pregnancy but does not include any miscarriage, the 
causing of which is punishable under the Indian Penal Code.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Ins. by 
G.S.R. 70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 
31-1-1996).</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form C
 

[See rule 4(4)]
 

This is to certify that Smt..... wife/daughter of.....employed 
in..... (name of 1[mine or 
circus]) expired on .....before/ during/after confinement. The child died 
on...../survives her.
 

Signature, qualifications 
and designation of  
Medical Officer/Medical Practitioner
 

Date......................
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 59 (E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1975).</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form D
 

[See rule 4(5)]
 

This is to certify that I examined.....wife/daughter of.......a 
woman employed in .......(name of 1[mine or 
circus]) and found that she has been delivered of a child/has undergone 
miscarriage on.....(date).
 

Signature of registered 
midwife.
 

Date..................
 

Definitions of “child” and “miscarriage” as in the Maternity 
Benefit Act, 1961—
 

       1. “Child” includes a 
still-born child.
 

       2. “Miscarriage” means 
expulsion of the contents of a pregnant uterus at any period prior to or during 
the twenty-sixth week of pregnancy but does not include any miscarriage, the 
causing of which is punishable under the Indian Penal Code.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 59 (E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1975).</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form E
 

[See rule 5(1)]
 

NOTICE UNDER SECTION 6 OF THE MATERNITY BENEFIT ACT, 1961
 

To
 

.........(name of
1[mine or 
circus])
 

I........... (name of woman) wife/daughter of..... employed 
as........... at............ (name of
1[mine or 
circus]), hereby give notice that I expect to be confined within six weeks next 
following from the date of this notice/have given birth to a child on 
.............(date) and shall be absent from work from ...............(date). I 
shall not work in any establishment during the period for which I receive 
maternity benefit.
 

2. For the purpose of section 7, I hereby 
nominate................. (here enter name and address of the nominee) to 
receive maternity benefit and/or any other amount due to me under the Act in 
case of my death.
 

Signature of an Attestor in case 
 

the woman is not able to sign 
 

and affix thumb 
impression.                                                   Signature or thumb impression of woman
 

Date......................
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form F
 

[See rule 5(3)]
 

form OF RECEIPT OF MATERNITY BENEFIT
 

To
 

............... (name of
1[mine or 
circus]). I, .............., the undersigned, a woman employee/the nominee 
of.............woman employee/legal representative of........ woman employee 
deceased in..........(name of
1[mine or 
circus]) at........ in........ district received maternity benefit and/or other 
amount due under the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961, from the employer of
1[mine or 
circus] referred to above, as detailed below:—
 

            Rs............ 
being the first instalment of maternity benefit paid on.....
 

            Rs............ 
being the second instalment of maternity benefit after delivery paid 
on............
 

            Rs..............., 
being the medical bonus under section 8 of the Act paid on.........
 

            Rs............., being the wages for the leave 
period from ................. to............... mentioned under
2[section 
9, 9A or 10].
 

*My/Her confinement/miscarriage
3[Medical 
termination of pregnancy or tubectomy operation]took place on.....or I/she fell 
ill because of pregnancy, delivery, premature birth of a child or miscarriage
3[Medical 
termination of pregnancy or tubectomy operation] on..... In consequence I,..... 
her nominee/legal representative have received the aforesaid amounts prescribed 
in 2[sections 
5, 8, 9, 9A and 10] of the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961.
 

Signature or thumb 
impression of.........
 

*Woman employee or her nominee or 
legal representative
 

 
 


Signature of an Attestor in case the woman is 
 

not able to sign and 
affixes thumb impression
 

Date......................
 

*Strike out unnecessary portion.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
 

   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 70 
(E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   3. Ins. by G.S.R. 70 (E), 
dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form G
 

[See rule 9]
 

To
 

The Competent Authority
 

(Appointed under the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961).
 

......(Address)
 

Sir,
 

I,....., the undersigned, woman employee of..... (name and full 
address 1[mine or 
circus]) have been wrongly deprived by the employer of maternity benefit or 
medical bonus or both (strike out unnecessary portion) for the reasons attached 
hereto, prefer this appeal under sub-section (2) of section 12 and request that 
the said employer be ordered to pay the abovementioned amount to me. A copy of 
the order of the employer in this behalf is enclosed.
 

Date........................
 

     Signature or thumb impression of the 
woman
 

Signature of an Attestor in case the woman is 
 

not 
able to sign and affixes thumb impression.
 

Full address of the 
nominee/legal representative
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 59 (E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 
1-3-1975).</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form H
 

[See rule 10]
 

To
 

The Inspector,
 

(Under the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961)
 

Sir,
 

I............. (name of woman) employed in.......... (name and 
full address of 1[mine or 
circus]) having fulfilled the conditions laid down in the Maternity Benefit Act, 
1961 and the Rules thereunder, am entitled to Rs.............. being maternity 
benefit and/or Rs........... being the medical bonus and/or Rs............. 
being wages for leave due under 2[section 9 or 
9A] 10 but the same has been improperly withheld by the employer. He may, 
therefore, be directed to pay the amount to me.
 

Date.............                            
Signature or thumb impression of the woman.
 

Signature of an Attestor 
in case the woman 
 

is unable to sign and 
affixes thumb impression.
 

                          
Full address of the woman.
 

Date...............
 

 
 

—————
 

   1. Ins. by G.S.R. 
70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   2.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 
31-1-1996).</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form I
 

[See rule 10]
 

To
 

The Inspector
 

(Under the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961)
 

I,..........(name), a person nominated under section 6 by or a 
legal representative of............. (name of woman) employed in.......... (name 
and full address of 3[mine or 
circus]) have to complain that the said woman having fulfilled the conditions 
laid down in the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961 and the Rules thereunder is 
entitled to Rs........ being maternity benefit and/or Rs........ being the 
medical bonus and/or Rs........ being wages for leave due under 2[section 9 or 
9A] or 10 but the same has been improperly withheld by the employer. He may, 
therefore, be directed to pay the amount to me.
 

Date.................
 

            
Signature or thumb impression of the  
nominee/legal representative
 

Signature of an Attestor 
in case the nominee/legal 
 

representative is unable 
to sign and affixes thumb impression.
 

                                
Full address of the nominee/legal representative.
 

Date...................  
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 59 (E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
 

   2.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 
31-1-1996).</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form J
 

[See rule 11]
 

To
 

Sir,
 

Shri....., Inspector, having directed under sub-section (2) of 
section 17 to pay the maternity benefit or other amount being..... (nature of 
amount) to which..... (name of woman) is said to be entitled, I prefer this 
appeal under sub-section (3) of section 17. In view of the facts mentioned in 
the memorandum attached hereto and other documents filed herewith it is 
submitted that the woman is not entitled to the maternity benefit or the said 
amount and hence the decision of the Inspector in this behalf, copy of which is 
enclosed, may be set aside.
 

Signature of aggrieved 
person.
 

Full 
address.......................
 

Date....................</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form K
 

[See rule 15]
 

(Abstract of the Maternity Benefit Act, 1961, and the rules 
made thereunder).
 

1. No employer shall knowingly employ a woman during the six 
weeks immediately following the day of her delivery of miscarriage/1[Medical 
termination of pregnancy] and no woman shall work in any establishment during 
the said period.
 

2. No pregnant woman shall, on a request being made by her in 
this behalf, be required by her employer to do during the period of one month 
immediately preceding the period of six weeks before the date of her expected 
delivery and also for any period during this period of six weeks for which she 
does not avail of leave of absence, any work which is of an arduous nature or 
which involves long hours of standing, or which in way is likely to interfere 
with her pregnancy or the normal development of the foetus, or is likely to 
cause her miscarriage or otherwise to adversely affect her health.
 

3. 2[(1) Subject to 
the provisions of the Act, every woman who has actually worked in an 
establishment of the employer from whom she claims maternity benefit for a 
period of not less than eighty days, including the days during which she was 
laid off, shall be entitled to, and her employer shall be liable for, the 
payment of maternity benefit at the rate of her average daily wages, or the 
minimum rate of wage fixed or revised under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, or ten 
rupees a day, whichever is highest, for the period of her actual absence not 
exceeding six weeks immediately preceding the day of delivery and the remaining 
period immediately following that day:
 

Provided that the qualifying period of eighty days aforesaid 
shall not apply to a woman who has immigrated into the State of Assam and was 
pregnant at the time of the immigration:
 

Provided further that where a woman dies during the period for 
which maternity benefit is payable to her, the benefit shall be payable only for 
the days upto and including the day of her death. However, where the woman 
having been delivered of a child, dies during her delivery or during the 
remaining period of maternity benefit leaving behind in either case the child, 
the employer shall be liable for the payment of maternity benefit for the entire 
period of maternity benefit following the day of her delivery but if the child 
also dies during the said period, then, for the days upto and including the day 
of the death of the child.]
 

(2) The amount of maternity benefit for the period preceding the 
date of her expected delivery shall be paid in advance by the employer to the 
woman on production of a certificate in form ‘B’ stating that she is pregnant 
and is expected to be delivered of a child within six weeks of the date of 
production of the certificate, and the amount due for the subsequent period 
shall be paid by the employer to the woman within forty-eight hours of 
production of the certificate in form ‘B’ or form ‘D’ stating that she has been 
delivered of a child or production of a certified extract from a Birth Register 
maintained under the provisions of any law for the time being in force.
 

4. (1) Any woman employed in an establishment and entitled to 
maternity benefit under the provisions of this Act may give notice in writing in 
form ‘E’ to her employer, stating that her maternity benefit and any other 
amount to which she may be entitled under this Act may be paid to her or to such 
person as she may nominate in the notice and that she will not work in any 
establishment during the period for which she receives maternity benefit.
 

(2) In the case of a woman who is pregnant, such notice shall 
state the date from which she will be absent from work, not being a date earlier 
than six weeks from the date of her expected delivery.
 

(3) Any woman who has not given the notice when she was pregnant 
may give such notice as soon as possible after the delivery.
 

(4) On receipt of the notice, the employer shall permit such 
woman to absent herself from the establishment until the expiry 3[of the 
remaining period of maternity benefit] after the day of her delivery.
 

5. (1) Every woman entitled to maternity benefit under the Act 
shall also be entitled to receive from her employer a medical bonus of 3[two hundred and 
fifty rupees], if no pre-natal, confinement and post-natal care is provided for 
by the employer free of charge. The medical bonus shall be paid alongwith the 
second instalment of the maternity benefit.
 

(2) In case of miscarriage, a woman shall, on production of a 
certificate in form ‘B’ or form ‘D’ be entitled to leave with wages at the rate 
of maternity benefit, for a period of six weeks immediately following the day of 
her miscarriage. The wages shall be paid within 48 hours of production of the 
certificate in form ‘B’ or form ‘D’.
 

4[(2a) In case of 
medical termination of pregnancy, a woman shall, on production of a certificate 
in form ‘B’ be entitled to leave with wages of the rate of maternity benefit for 
a period of six weeks immediately following the day of her medical termination 
of pregnancy. The wages shall be paid within 48 hours of production of the 
certificate in form ‘B’.]
 

(3) A woman suffering from illness arising out of pregnancy, 
delivery, premature birth of child or miscarriage/3[medical 
termination of pregnancy or tubectomy operation] shall, on production of a 
certificate in form ‘B’, be entitled, in addition to the period of absence 
allowed to her on account of maternity or miscarriage/3[medical 
termination of pragnancy or tubectomy operation], as the case may be, to leave 
with wages at the rate of maternity benefit for a maximum period of one month. 
The wages for the leave period shall be paid within 48 hours of the expiry of 
that period.
 

6. Every woman delivered of a child who returns to duty after 
such delivery shall, in addition to the interval for rest allowed to her, be 
allowed in the course of her daily work two breaks of 15 minutes’ duration for 
nursing the child until the child attains the age of fifteen months. An extra 
sufficient period, depending upon the distance to be covered, shall be allowed 
for the purpose of the journey to and from the creche or the place where the 
children are left by women while on duty, provided that such extra period shall 
not be less than 5 minutes and more than 15 minutes’ duration.
 

7. (1) When a woman absents herself from work in accordance with 
the provisions of the Act, it shall be unlawful for her employer to discharge or 
dismiss her during or on account of such absence or to give notice of discharge 
or dismissal on such a day that the notice will expire during such absence, or 
to vary to her disadvantage any of the conditions of her service.
 

(2)(a) The discharge or dismissal of a woman at any time during 
her pregnancy, if the woman but for which discharge or dismissal would have been 
entitled to maternity benefit or medical bonus shall not have the effect of 
depriving her of the maternity benefit or medical bonus:
 

Provided that where the dismissal is for one or more of the 
following acts, the employer may, by order in writing communicate to the woman, 
deprive her of the maternity benefit or medical bonus or both—
 

       (i) wilful destruction 
of employer’s goods or property;
 

      (ii) assaulting any superior 
or co-employee at the place of work;
 

     (iii) criminal offence involving 
moral turpitude resulting in conviction in a court of law;
 

     (iv) theft, fraud, or dishonesty in 
connection with the employer’s business or property; and
 

      (v) wilful non-observance of 
safety measures or rules on the subject or wilful interference with safety 
devices or with fire-fighting equipment.
 

(b) Any woman deprived of maternity benefit or medical bonus or 
both, may within sixty days from the date on which the order of such deprivation 
is communicated to her, appeal in form ‘G’ to 5[the Competent 
Authority and his decision] on such appeal whether the woman should or should 
not be deprived of maternity benefit or medical bonus or both, shall be 
final.
 

8. If a woman works in any establishment after she has been 
permitted by her employer to absent herself under the provisions of the Act, she 
shall forfeit her claim to the maternity benefit for such period.
 

9. (1) Any woman claiming the maternity benefit or any other 
amount to which she is entitled under the Act and any person claiming that 
payment due has been improperly withheld may make a complaint to the Inspector 
in writing in form ‘H’ or ‘I’ as the case may be.
 

(2) The Inspector may, of his own motion or on receipt of a 
complaint in form ‘H’ or ‘I’ make an inquiry or cause an enquiry to be made and 
if satisfied that payment has been wrongfully withheld, may direct the payment 
to be made in accordance with his orders.
 

(3) Any person aggrieved by the decision of the Inspector may, 
within, thirty days from the date on which such decision is communicated to such 
person, appeal to 5[the Chief 
Inspector of Mines].
 

(4) The decision of 6[***] 5[the Competent 
Authority] where an appeal has been preferred to him or of the Inspector where 
no such appeal has been preferred, shall be final.
 

10. (a) The employer shall supply to every woman employed by him 
at her request free of cost copies of forms ‘B’, ‘C’, ‘D’, ‘E’, ‘F’, ‘G’, ‘H’ 
and ‘I’.
 

(b) The failure to submit a notice, appeal or complaint in the 
prescribed form will not affect the right of a woman entitled to receive 
maternity benefit or any other amount due under the Act. Where a notice, appeal 
or complaint has been received in a form other than the prescribed form, the 
authority concerned shall within fifteen days of the receipt of such notice, 
appeal or complaint, require the woman to submit the notice, appeal or 
complaint, as the case may be in the prescribed form.
 

11. (a) (1) The employer of 7[every mine or 
circus] in which women are employed shall prepare and maintain a muster roll in 
form ‘A’ and shall enter therein particulars of all women workers in 7[the mine or 
circus.]
 

(2) All entries in the muster-roll shall be made in ink and 
maintained up-to-date and it shall always be available for inspection by the 
Inspector during working hours.
 

(b) The employer of 8[every mine or 
circus] shall on or before the 21st day of January in each year submit 9[* * *] 10[the Competent 
Authority] a return in each of the forms ‘L’, ‘M’, ‘N’ and ‘O’, giving 
information as to the particulars specified in respect of the preceding 
year.
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Ins. by 
G.S.R. 70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   2.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   3.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   4.  Ins. by 
G.S.R. 70 (E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   5.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 64, dated 4th February, 1992 (w.e.f. 15-2-1992).
 

   6.  Omitted 
by G.S.R. 49, dated 4th January, 1988 (w.e.f. 16-1-1988).
 

   7.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 59 (E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
 

   8.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 59 (E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
 

   9.  Omitted 
by G.S.R. 49, dated 4th January, 1988 (w.e.f. 16-1-1988).
 

  10.  Subs. by 
G.S.R. 64, dated 4th February, 1992 (w.e.f. 15-2-1992).</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form L
 

[See rule 16]
 

ANNUAL RETURN FOR THE YEAR ENDING  

ON THE 31ST DECEMBER, 20....
 

       1.  Name of
1[the 
mine or circus]
 

       2.  Situation of
1[the 
mine or circus]
 

            Mauza
 

            District
 

            State
 

            Nearest Railway Station
 

       3.  Date of opening of
1[the 
mine or circus]
 

       4.  Date of closing, if closed.
 

       5.  Postal address of
1[the 
mine or circus]
 

       6. Name of employer.
 

            Postal address of employer.
 

       7.  Name of managing agent, if any.
 

            Postal address of managing agent.
 

       8. Name of Agent or representative of employer.
 

            Postal address of representative of employer.
 

       9. Name of Manager
 

            Postal address of manager
 

      10. (a)  Name of medical officer, attached to
1[the 
mine or circus]
 

            (b)  Qualification of medical officer attached 
to 1[the 
mine or circus]
 

            (c)  Is he resident at
1[the 
mine or circus]?
 

            (d)  If a part-time employee, how often does he 
pay visits to 1[the 
mine or circus]
 

      11. (a)  Is there any hospital at
1[the 
mine or circus]?
 

            (b)  If so, how many beds are provided for 
women employees?
 

            (c)  Is there a lady doctor?
 

            (d)  If so, what are her qualifications?
 

            (e)  Is there a qualified midwife?
 

             (f)  Has any creche been provided?
 

Signature of employer
 

Date...................
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form M
 

(See rule 16)
 

EMPLOYMENT, DISMISSAL, PAYMENT OF BONUS, ETC., OF WOMEN
 

FOR THE YEAR ENDING ON 31ST DECEMBER, 20.....
 

       1.
1[Mine or 
circus].
 

       2. Aggregate number of women permanently or 
temporarily employed during the year.
 

       3. Number of women who worked for a period of not 
less than 2[eighty 
days] in the twelve months immediately preceding the date of delivery.
 

       4. Number of women who gave notice under section 6.
 

       5. Number of women who were granted permission to 
remain absent on receipt of notice of confinement.
 

       6. Number of claims for maternity benefit paid.
 

       7. Number of claims for maternity benefit rejected.
 

       8. Number of cases where pre-natal, confinement and 
post-natal care was provided by the management free of charge (section 8).
 

       9. Number of claims for medical bonus paid (section 
8).
 

     10. Number of claims for medical bonus rejected.
 

     11. Number of cases in which leave for miscarriage/3[MTP] 
was granted.
 

     12. Number of cases in which leave for miscarriage/3[MTP] 
was applied for but was rejected.
 


3[12A.  
Number of cases in which leave for tubectomy operation under section 9A was 
granted.
 

   12B.  Number of cases in which leave for tubectomy 
operation was applied for but was rejected.]
 

     13. Number of cases in which additional leave for 
illness under section 10 was granted.
 

     14. Number of cases in which additional leave for 
illness under section 10 was applied for but was rejected.
 

     15. Number of women who died
 

            (a) before delivery.
 

            (b) after delivery.
 

     16. Number of cases in which payment was made to 
persons other than the woman concerned.
 

     17. Number of women discharged or dismissed while 
working.
 

     18. Number of women deprived of maternity benefit 
and/or medical bonus under proviso to sub-section (2) of section 12.
 

     19. Number of cases in which payment was made on the 
order of the Competent Authority or Inspector.
 

     20.  Remarks.
 

N.B.—Full particulars of each case and reasons for the 
action taken under serials 7, 10, 12, 14, 17 and 18 should be given in Appendix 
below:—
 

Signature of employer.
 

Date.................
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).
 

   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 70 
(E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
 

   3.  Ins. by G.S.R. 70 
(E), dated 31st january, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form N
 

(See rule 16)
 

DETAILS OF PAYMENT MADE DURING THE YEAR  

ENDING 31ST DECEMBER, 20.....
 

Name of person to whom 
paid       Amount paid
 

       1.  Date of payment.
 

       2.  Woman employee.
 

       3.  Nominee of the woman.
 

       4.  Legal representative of the woman.
 

       5.  Amount for the period preceding date of expected 
delivery.
 

       6.  Amount for the subsequent period.
 

       7.  Under section 8 of the Act.
 

       8.  Under section 9 of the Act.
 


   1[8a.  
Under section 9A of the Act.]
 

       9.  Under section 10 of the Act.
 

     10.  Number of women workers who absconded after 
receiving the first instalment of maternity benefit.
 

     11.  Cases where claims were contested in a court of 
law.
 

     12.  Results of such cases.
 

     13.  Remarks.
 

Signature of employer
 

Date....................
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 70 
(E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).
</form><form>
 

THE MATERNITY BENEFIT (MINES AND CIRCUS) RULES, 1963
 

 
 

form O
 

(See rule 16)
 

PROSECUTION DURING THE YEAR 
ENDING 31ST DECEMBER, 20.....
 


 


  Place of employment of     Number of cases      Number of cases    Remarks
 


the woman employee        instituted                 which resulted
 


 


                                                                            in 
  conviction
 

 
 

(For mines)
 

N.B.—Reasons for prosecution should be given in full in 
the Appendix below:
 

Signature of employer.
 

Date................
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 59(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 70(E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 70 
(E), dated 31st January, 1996 (w.e.f. 31-1-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 59 
(E), dated 27th February, 1975 (w.e.f. 1-3-1975).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>