<act><title>

    THE CONTEMPT OF COURTS (C.A.T.) RULES, 19921</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Contempt of Courts (C.A.T.) Rules, 1992.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless there is anything repugnant to the subject or context,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Contempt of Courts 
      Act, 1971 (70 of 1971);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Code” means the Code of Criminal 
      Procedure;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Form” means the form set out in the 
      appendix to these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Member” means a Member, whether 
      “Judicial” or “Administrative” and includes Vice-Chairman and Chairman;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “Registrar” means Registrar of the 
      Central Administrative Tribunal or its Benches where the contempt 
      proceedings are taken and shall include Joint Registrar and Deputy 
      Registrar, and the Section Officer authorised to discharge the functions 
      of the Registrar;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “Tribunal” means the Central 
      Administrative Tribunal constituted under the Administrative Tribunals 
      Act, 1985 or the Bench thereof, where the proceedings are taken cognizance 
      of;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “words and expression” not defined in 
      these rules shall have the same meaning as defined in the Act.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Form of motion.—Every 
    motion for initiating action for contempt of the Tribunal shall be in the 
    form of a petition described as “Contempt Petition (Civil)” in respect of 
    Civil Contempt and “Contempt Petition (Criminal)” in respect of Criminal 
    Contempt.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Parties to the proceedings.—The 
    party who presents the petition shall be described as the “Petitioner” and 
    the alleged contemner shall be described as the “Respondent”.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Contempt of the petition.—The 
    petition shall set out the following particulars:—
 
 <section>
<number>i</number>   (a)   Name (including as far as 
      possible the name of the father/mother/husband), age, occupation and 
      address of—
 
 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   the petitioner; and
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   the respondent.
 
If the alleged contemner is an officer, he 
        shall be described by name and designation.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>   provision of the Act invoked and the 
        nature of the contempt, “Civil” or “Criminal”;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the grounds and material facts 
        constituting the alleged contempt, including the date of alleged 
        contempt, divided into paragraphs, numbered consecutively, along with 
        supporting documents or certified/photostat (attested) copies of the 
        originals thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the nature of the order sought from 
        the Tribunal;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   if a petition has previously been 
        made by him on the same facts, the details, particulars and the result 
        thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the petition shall be supported by 
        an affidavit verifying the facts relied upon except when the motion is 
        by the Attorney General or the Solicitor General or the Additional 
        Solicitor General;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   every petition shall be signed by 
        the petitioner and his Advocate, if any, and shall show the place and 
        date;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   draft charges shall be enclosed in a 
        separate sheet;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   in the case of “Civil Contempt” 
        certified copy of the judgment, decree, order, writ or undertaking 
        alleged to have been disobeyed shall be filed along with the petition;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   where the petitioner relies upon any 
        other document(s) in his possession, or power, he shall file them along 
        with the petition;
</subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number>   in the case of “Criminal Contempt” of 
      the Tribunal other than a contempt referred to in section 14 of the Act, 
      the petitioner shall state whether he has obtained the consent of the 
      Attorney General or the Solicitor General or the Additional Solicitor 
      General and if so, produce the same, if not the reasons thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   the petitioner shall file three 
      complete sets of the petition including the annexures in paper book form, 
      duly indexed and paginated. Where the number of respondents is more than 
      one, equal number of extra paper books shall be filed;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   no fee shall be payable on a petition 
      or any document filed in the proceedings.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Taking cognizance.—Every 
    proceeding for contempt shall be dealt with by a Bench of not less than two 
    Members:
 
Provided where 
    the contempt is alleged to have been committed in view of, presence or 
    hearing of the Member(s), the same shall be dealt with by the Member(s) in 
    accordance with section 14 of the Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Initiation of proceedings.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    Every petition for “Civil Contempt” made in accordance with these rules 
    shall be scrutinised by the Registrar, registered and numbered in the 
    Registry and then placed before the Bench for preliminary hearing.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Every 
    petition for “Criminal Contempt” made in accordance with these rules and 
    every information other than a petition, for initiating action for criminal 
    contempt under the Act on being scrutinised by the Registrar shall first be 
    placed on the administrative side before the Chairman in the case of 
    Principal Bench and the concerned Vice-Chairman in the case of other Benches 
    or such other Member as may be designated by him for this purpose and he 
    considers it expedient and proper to take action under the Act, the said 
    petition or information shall be registered and numbered in the Registry and 
    placed before the Bench for preliminary hearing.
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> When 
    suo motu action is taken the statement of facts constituting the alleged 
    contempt and copy of the draft charges shall be prepared and signed by the 
    Registrar before placing them for preliminary hearing.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Preliminary hearing and notice.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    The Bench if satisfied that a prima facie case has been made out, may 
    direct issue of notice to the respondent, otherwise, it shall dismiss the 
    petition or drop the proceedings.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The 
    notice shall be in Form No. 1 and shall be accompanied by a copy of the 
    petition or information and annexures, if any, thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> Service 
    of notice shall be effected in the manner specified in the Central 
    Administrative Tribunal (Procedure) Rules, 1987 or in such other manner as 
    may be directed by the Bench.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Compelling attendance.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    The Tribunal may, if it has reason to believe, that the respondent is 
    absconding or is otherwise evading service of notice, or has failed to 
    appear in person in pursuance of the notice, direct a warrant, bailable or 
    non-bailable, for his arrest, addressed to one or more Police Officers or 
    may order attachment of property belonging to such person. The warrant and 
    the writ of attachment shall be issued under the signature of the Registrar. 
    The warrant shall be in Form No. II and shall be executed as far as may be, 
    in the manner provided for execution of warrants under the Code.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The 
    warrant shall be executed by the Officer or Officers to whom it is directed 
    and may also be executed by any other Police Officer whose name is endorsed 
    upon the warrant by the Officer to whom it is directed or endorsed.
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> Every 
    person who is arrested and detained shall, if he cannot be produced before 
    the Tribunal within twenty-four hours of arrest excluding the time necessary 
    for the journey from the place of arrest to the Tribunal, be produced before 
    the nearest Magistrate within the said period, who may authorise detention 
    till such person is produced before the Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> Every 
    person who is arrested and detained when produced before the Tribunal, may 
    be released on bail on a bond for such sum of money as the Tribunal thinks 
    sufficient with or without sureties, with the condition that the person so 
    released shall attend the Tribunal at the time and place mentioned in the 
    bond and shall continue to so attend until otherwise directed by the 
    Tribunal:
 
Provided that 
    the Tribunal may, if it thinks fit, instead of taking bail from such person, 
    release him on personal bond for his attendance. The provisions of the Code 
    shall, so far as may be, apply to all arrests made and bonds executed under 
    the Rules.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Appearance of the respondent.—Unless 
    ordered otherwise by the Tribunal, whenever a notice is issued under these 
    rules, the respondent shall appear in person in the case of “criminal 
    contempt” and in person or through an Advocate in the case of “civil 
    contempt” at the time and place specified in the notice and continue to 
    attend on subsequent dates to which the petition is posted.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Reply by the respondent.—The 
    respondent may file his reply duly supported by an affidavit on or before 
    the first date of hearing or within such extended time as may be granted by 
    the Tribunal.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Right to be defended by an Advocate.—Every 
    person against whom proceedings are initiated under the Act, may as of right 
    be defended by an Advocate of his choice.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Hearing of the case and trial.—Upon 
    consideration of the reply filed by the respondent and after hearing the 
    parties:
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   If the respondent has tendered an 
      unconditional apology after admitting that he has committed the contempt, 
      the Tribunal may proceed to pass such orders as it deems fit;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   If the respondent does not admit that 
      he has committed contempt, the Tribunal may,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   if it is satisfied that there is a
        prima facie case, proceed to frame the charge in Form No. III 
        (subject to modification or addition by the Tribunal at any time); or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   drop the proceedings and discharge 
        the respondent, if it is satisfied that there is no prima facie 
        case, or that it is not expedient to proceed;
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   The respondent shall be furnished with 
      a copy of the charge framed, which shall be read over and explained to the 
      respondent. The Tribunal shall then record his plea, if any;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   If the respondent pleads guilty, the 
      Tribunal may adjudge him guilty and proceed to pass such sentence as it 
      deems fit;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   If the respondent pleads not guilty, 
      the case may be taken up for trial on the same day or posted to any 
      subsequent date as may be directed by the Tribunal.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Assistance in the conduct of proceedings.—The 
    Attorney General/Solicitor General/Additional Solicitor General, or any 
    other Advocate as may be designated by the Tribunal shall appear and assist 
    the Tribunal in the conduct of the proceedings against the respondent.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Procedure for trial.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    Except as otherwise provided in the Act and these rules, the procedure 
    prescribed for summary trials under Chapter XXI of the Code shall as far as 
    practicable be followed in the trial of cases for contempt.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The 
    Tribunal may, at its discretion, direct that evidence be produced in the 
    form of affidavits.
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> The 
    Tribunal may, either suo motu or on motion made for that purpose, 
    order the attendance for cross-examination of a person whose affidavit has 
    been filed in the matter.
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> The 
    Tribunal may, at its discretion, direct any person to be examined as 
    Tribunal witness.
 </section><section>
<number>v</number> The 
    Tribunal may make such order as it deems fit for the purpose of securing the 
    attendance of any person to be examined as a witness and for discovery or 
    production of any document.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Expenses of witnesses.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    Where any person is summoned by the Tribunal to appear as a witness in any 
    proceedings under the Act, the expenses of such witness as may be determined 
    by the Tribunal shall be borne by the party who has cited him as a witness.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Where the 
    Tribunal summons any witness other than the witnesses cited by the parties, 
    his expenses as determined by the Tribunal shall be paid by the Registrar 
    from the funds for contingencies.
 
.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Execution of sentence.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    If the respondent is found guilty and is sentenced to imprisonment other 
    than imprisonment till rising of the Tribunal a warrant of commitment and 
    detention shall be made out in Form No. IV under the signature of the 
    Registrar. Every such warrant shall remain in force until it is executed or 
    cancelled by order of the Tribunal. The Superintendent of Jail specified in 
    the order shall, in pursuance of the warrant, detain the contemner in 
    custody for the period specified therein subject to such further direction 
    as the Tribunal may give.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> When the 
    Tribunal awards a sentence of fine and the fine amount is not paid at once 
    or within such time as may be granted by the Tribunal, the Registrar shall 
    take action in any one of the ways provided in section 421 of the Code.
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> Warrants 
    to be issued under sub-rule (ii) shall be in Form Nos. V and VI, as the case 
    may be.
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number> The 
    report of the action taken by the Superintendent of the Jail or the Police 
    Officer or District Collector to whom the warrant under sub-rule (iii) might 
    have been addressed shall be filed in the records of the case.
 
.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Execution of processes.—Processes 
    issued by the Tribunal shall, except as otherwise specifically provided, as 
    executed by the Superintendent of Police/Commissioner of Police, as the case 
    may be.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Procedure on forfeiture of the bond.—If 
    any bond given for appearance of the respondent is forfeited due to his 
    absence, the Tribunal may, after giving opportunity to the respondent or the 
    surety, as the case may be, levy the whole or any part of the amount 
    mentioned in the surety bond, as penalty and direct the same to be recovered 
    as if it were a fine imposed on the respondent/surety under the Code.
 
.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Apology at any stage of the proceedings.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    If at any time during the pendency of the proceedings, the contemner tenders 
    an apology, the same shall be placed expeditiously for orders of the Bench.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> If the 
    Tribunal accepts the apology, further proceedings shall be dropped.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Costs.—
<section><number>i</number> 
    The Tribunal may award costs as it deems fit in the circumstances of the 
    case.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The costs 
    so awarded shall be recovered in the same manner as a fine imposed under the 
    Code.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Application of other Rules of the Tribunal.—In 
    matters not specifically provided for in these rules, the procedure 
    prescribed in the relevant rules of the Tribunal as amended from time to 
    time shall mutatis mutandis apply to proceedings under these rules.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Application to pending proceedings.—These 
    rules shall as far as practicable to be applicable pending proceedings.
 


 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE CONTEMPT OF COURTS (C.A.T.) RULES, 1992
 

 
 

 
 

FORM NO. 1 

[See rule 8(ii)] 

Notice to Respondent 

In the Central 
    Administrative Tribunal
 
 



 
 
 
 

(Name of the Bench)
 
 

Place

 
 
 

Contempt 
            Petition Civil / Criminal 
            No..................................................

 
 
 


            Petitioner...................................................................................................................

 
 
 

v

 
 
 


            Respondent..............................................................................................................

 
 
 

(here 
            mention the name and address of the person to whom notice is being 
            sent).





 


Whereas information is laid/a petition is 
    filed/motion is made by .............................. that you (here 
    mention the gist of the accusation made in the information/petition/motion)
    
 


And whereas a petition has been registered for 
    action being taken against you under the Contempt of Courts Act, 1971;
 


You are hereby required to appear in person or 
    through a duly authorised advocate* on................day 
    of.................... at.................... and on subsequent dates to 
    which the proceedings are adjourned, unless otherwise ordered by the 
    Tribunal, and show cause why such action as is deemed fit under the Contempt 
    of Courts Act, 1971 should not be taken against you.
 


    Given under my hand and the seal of this Tribunal, on this 
    .................. day of ........................ 20..... 
 


    Seal.
 

 
 



 
 
 
 

 
 
 

 Registrar
 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

Central Administrative Tribunal
 
 

 




 

*Strike out whichever is not 
    applicable.
 

 
 

 
 



 



 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE CONTEMPT OF COURTS (C.A.T.) RULES, 1992
 

 
 

 
 



    Form No. II 

[See rule 9(i)] 

Warrant of Arrest 

In the Central 
    Administrative Tribunal
 


(Name of the Bench)   Place
 


Contempt Petition Civil/Criminal 
    No...........................................................................
 


Petitioner.........................................................................................................................
 



v.
 


Respondent......................................................................................................................
 


To
 


........................................................
 


.........................................................
 


(Name, designation and address of 
    the officer(s) authorised to execute the warrant).
 


Whereas Shri/Smt................of..................is 
    charged with committing contempt of the Tribunal, you are hereby directed to 
    arrest the said....................and to produce him/her before this 
    Tribunal.
 


Herein fail not.
 


(If the Tribunal 
    has issued a bailable warrant, the following endorsement shall be made on 
    the warrant).
 


If the 
    said...............shall give bail in the sum of Rs.............with one 
    surety in the sum of Rs................(or two sureties each in the sum of 
    Rs.............) to attend before this Tribunal on the .............day 
    of.................20..... and to continue so to attend until otherwise 
    directed by this Tribunal, he may be released.
 


Given under my 
    hand and the seal of the Tribunal this............ day 
    of..................20.....  
 


Seal.
 



 
 
 
 

 
 
 

 Registrar
 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

Central Administrative 
          Tribunal
 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 




 




 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE CONTEMPT OF COURTS (C.A.T.) RULES, 1992
 



 



 


Form No. III  

[See rule 13(b)(i)] 

Charge 

In the Central 
    Administrative Tribunal 
 


(Name of the Bench)   Place
 


    Contempt Petition Civil/Criminal 
    No................................................................................
 


    Petitioner....................................................................................................................................
 


v
 


    Respondents.................................................................................................................................
 


    Central Administrative Tribunal..............................Bench hereby 
    charges you.............. (name of the alleged contemner) as under:
 


That you, on or about....................day 
    of...............at...............(here give the gist of the 
    material..............................allegedly constituting contempt) and 
    thereby committed the contempt of this Tribunal punishable under 
    section......................(here give the relevant section of the Contempt 
    of Courts Act 1971), within our cognizance.
 


You are hereby directed to be tried by this 
    Tribunal for the aforesaid charge.
 


Signatures of the Hon’ble Member(s)
 


The charge was read over and explained to the 
    alleged contemner and his plea was recorded as under:
 


(1)   Do you plead guilty to the charge?
 


        Answer:
 


(2)   Do you have anything else to say?
 


        Answer:
 


    Signature of the alleged contemner
 


Signatures of the Hon’ble Member(s)  

    Presiding over the Bench.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE CONTEMPT OF COURTS (C.A.T.) RULES, 1992
 



 



 


Form No. IV 

[See rule 17(i)] 

Warrant of Commitment to Prison
 


(Name of the Bench)   Place.
 


Contempt Petition Civil/Criminal 
    No...............................................................................
 



    Petitioner................................................................................................................................
 


v
 



    Respondent/s........................................................................................................................
 


To
 


The Superintendent
 


(Name of the Jail)
 


Place
 


Whereas the Central Administrative 
    Tribunal..................................................................
 


Bench has on this.......................day 
    of...................adjudged.......................(name/description of the 
    contemner) guilty of wilful contempt of the Tribunal and sentenced to 
    undergo simple imprisonment for................... (here specify the term) 
    and/or pay a fine of Rs.........................and in default of payment of 
    fine to undergo simple imprisonment for......................(specify the 
    period).
 


This is to authorise and require you, the 
    Superintendent of the.................Jail, to receive the said (name of the 
    contemner) into your custody, together with this warrant and keep him safely 
    in the said jail for the said period or for such period as may hereinafter 
    be fixed by the order of this Tribunal and intimated to you. You are 
    directed to return this warrant with an endorsement certifying the manner of 
    its execution.
 


You are further directed that while the 
    said.............is in your custody, produce the said............... before 
    this Tribunal at all times when the Tribunal so directs.
 


Given under my hand and seal of the Tribunal 
    this.................day of................
 


Seal.
 


 
 


              
                             
                                                                                       Registrar 

                                      
              
                                                                   Central 
    Administrative Tribunal.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE CONTEMPT OF COURTS (C.A.T.) RULES, 1992
 



 



 

 
 

Form No. V 

[See rule 17(ii) and (iii)] 

Warrant for attachment of 
    Movables 

In the Central 
    Administrative Tribunal
 


(Name of the Bench)   Place
 


Contempt Petition Civil/Criminal 
    No................................................................................
 



    Petitioner.....................................................................................................
 


v
 



    Respondent..................................................................................................
 


To
 


.............................................
 


..............................................
 


(Name and designation of the Police Officer or 
    other officer authorised to execute the warrant).
 


Whereas the Central Administrative Tribunal on 
    (this day) had adjudged (name and description of the contemner) guilty of 
    wilful contempt of Tribunal and sentenced to pay a fine of Rs...................and 
    whereas the said..................(name) although required to pay the said 
    fine has not paid the same or any part thereof.
 


This is to authorise and require you to attach 
    any movable property belonging to the said...............(name) which may be 
    found within the district of....................and if 
    within.................(state the number of days or hours allowed) next 
    after such attachment, the said sum shall not be said to sell the moveable 
    property attached or so much thereof, as shall be sufficient to satisfy the 
    said fine, returning this warrant, with an endorsement certifying that you 
    have done under it, immediately upon its execution.
 


Given under my hand and the seal of the 
    Tribunal this..........day of.................20.....
 


Seal
 


 
 


                  
                                                                                                             
    Registrar 

                                             
                                                                    Central 
    Administrative Tribunal.
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE CONTEMPT OF COURTS (C.A.T.) RULES, 1992
 



 



 

 
 


Form No. VI 

[See rule 17(ii) &amp; (iii)] 

Warrant of Attachment by District 
    Collector/ 

    Deputy Commissioner 

In the Central 
    Administrative Tribunal
 


(Name of the Bench)   Place
 


Contempt Petition Civil/Criminal 
    No...............................................................................
 



    Petitioner....................................................................................................................................
 


v.
 



    Respondent.................................................................................................................................
 


To 
 


The District Collector/Deputy Commissioner
 



    .............................................................. District
 


Whereas the Central Administrative Tribunal on 
    (this day) has adjudged (name and description of the contemner) guilty of 
    wilful contempt of Tribunal and sentenced to pay a fine of Rs........and 
    whereas the said.................(name) although required to pay the said 
    fine has not paid the said fine/the sum of..............being the part 
    thereof.
 


This is to authorise and require you to 
    realise the amount by execution according to civil process against the 
    movable or immovable property or both of the respondent aforesaid in the 
    manner provided by section 421 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.
 


This order shall be deemed to be a decree and 
    you the decree holder, within the meaning of the Code of Civil Procedure, 
    1908 and the order shall be executable as such decree.
 


Given under my hand and the seal of this 
    court, this............day of..............20....
 


Seal.
 


 
 


                
                                                                                               
                    Registrar
 



                                                          
                                                           Central 
    Administrative Tribunal.
 

  




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>