<act><tid>1647317</tid>
<title>THE STATE AGRICULTURAL CREDIT CORPORATIONS ACT, <year>1968</year></title>

ACT NO. 60 OF <year>1968</year>
[ 29th December, <year>1968</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment in the States and Union 
territories of Agricultural Credit Corporation and for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by parliament in the Nineteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1519582</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>904466</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
State Agricultural Credit Corporations Act, <year>1968</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>12212</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, 
different dates may be appointed for different States or for different 
Union territories.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>281443</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1280324</tid>
<number>a</number>" agricultural marketing society" means a co- operative 
society the objects of which include the marketing of 
agricultural produce;

</section>

<section><tid>613834</tid>
<number>b</number>" agricultural operation" includes animal husbandry, 
dairy farming, pisciculture and poultry farming.
Explanation.-- The expression" pisciculture" includes the 
development of fisheries, both inland and marine, catching of 
fish and all activities connected therewith or incidental 
thereto;


</section>

<section><tid>1815927</tid>
<number>c</number>" agricultural processing society" means a co- operative 
society the objects of which include the processing of 
agricultural produce;

</section>

<section><tid>1338396</tid>
<number>d</number>" agricultural produce" includes the produce of an 
agricultural operation;

</section>

<section><tid>1994481</tid>
<number>e</number>" appropriate Government" means,-

<subsection><tid>1430091</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to any Corporation established in 
a Union territory, the Central Government, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>168</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>83604</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to any corporation established at 
any other place, the State Government;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1179014</tid>
<number>f</number>" banking company" has the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (c) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 
 <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1846960</tid>
<number>g</number>" Board" means the Board of directors of the 
Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>1462644</tid>
<number>h</number>" co- operative farming society" means a co- operative 
society the objects of which include the cultivation of 
land on a co- operative basis;

</section>

<section><tid>203160</tid>
<number>i</number>" Corporation", in relation to a State or Union 
territory, means the Agricultural Credit Corporation 
established under section 3 in that State or Union 
territory, as the case may be;

<subsection><tid>1592595</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" corresponding new bank" means a corresponding new 
bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking 
Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) 
Act, <year>1970</year> (5 of <year>1970</year>) <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or a corresponding new bank 
constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies 
 (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, <year>1980</year> 
 (40 of <year>1980</year>)];]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1000205</tid>
<number>j</number>" director" means a member of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>32989</tid>
<number>k</number>" Food Corporation" means the Food Corporation of India 
established under the Food Corporations Act, <year>1964</year> (27  
  of <year>1964</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1947448</tid>
<number>l</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>504875</tid>
<number>m</number>" Reserve Bank" means the Reserve Bank of India 
constituted under the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> 
 (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>489056</tid>
<number>n</number>" subsidiary banks" has the meaning assigned to it in 
the State Bank of India (subsidiary Banks) Act, <year>1959</year> 
 (38 of <year>1959</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>551608</tid>
<number>o</number>" Central Co- operative Bank"," co- operative Bank"," Co- 
operative Society", Primary Agricultural Credit 
Society"," Scheduled Bank"," State Bank" and" State Co- 
operative Bank", have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in section 2 of the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>).
CHAP

INCORPORATION OF STATE AGRICULTURAL CREDIT CORPORATIONS AND THEIRCAPITAL

CHAPTER II

INCORPORATION OF STATE AGRICULTURAL CREDIT CORPORATIONS AND THEIR 
CAPITAL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>672256</tid>
<number> 3</number> Establishment of State Agricultural Credit Corporations.
<section><tid>842193</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The appropriate Government may, by notification in the official 
Gazette, establish in any State or Union territory an Agri-
<pagefootnote><pagenum>169</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1970</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 19- 7- <year>1969</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1980</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 15- 4- <year>1980</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


cultural Credit Corporation under such name as may be specified in the 
notification:

Provided that no such Corporation shall be established in any 
State or Union territory other than the States of Assam, Bihar, 
Orissa, Rajasthan and West Bengal and the Union territories of Manipur 
and Tripura, except with the previous approval of the Central 
Government, and no such approval shall be given by the Central 
Government except after consultation with the Reserve Bank.


</section>

<section><tid>717480</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation established under this Act shall be a body 
corporate by the name specified in the notification referred to in 
sub- section (1), having perpetual succession and a common seal with 
power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and 
dispose of property, and to contract, and may by that name sue or be 
sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1076142</tid>
<number> 4</number> Head office and other offices.
<section><tid>1875971</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall  
establish its head office at such place in the State or Union 
territory as the appropriate Government may, after consultation with 
the Reserve Bank, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>1361026</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation may, after consultation with the appropriate 
Government, establish offices or agencies at other places in the State 
or Union territory, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>538080</tid>
<number> 5</number> Share capital and share- holders.
<section><tid>1441524</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorised capital of  
each Corporation shall be such sum as the appropriate Government may 
initially fix but it shall, in no case, be less than one crore of 
rupees or more than five crores of rupees:
Provided that where the authorised capital initially fixed is 
less than five crores of rupees, the appropriate Government may, from 
time to time, increase the authorised capital to such sum not 
exceeding five crores of rupees:

Provided further that where the appropriate Government is not the 
Central Government, the initial fixation of the authorised capital and 
any subsequent increase or reduction thereof, shall be made with the 
prior approval of the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>426541</tid>
<number>2</number>The authorised capital of each Corporation shall be divided 
into such number of shares as the appropriate Government may determine 
and shall be issued as fully paid- up shares to the parties mentioned 
in sub- section (3) at such times and in such manner and to such extent 
as the appropriate Government may determine and each of such shares 
shall have the same face value.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>170</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>792033</tid>
<number>3</number>Out of the capital issued under sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>1776864</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a Corporation established in a State, 
the Central Government shall subscribe for thirty per 
cent. of the share capital, and in the case of a 
Corporation established in a Union territory, the 
Central Government shall subscribe for fifty per cent. 
of the share capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>85850</tid>
<number>b</number>the Reserve Bank shall subscribe for twenty per cent. 
of the share capital;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1446408</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a Corporation established in a State, 
the State Government shall subscribe for twenty per 
cent. of the share capital:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1114530</tid>
<number>d</number>the Food Corporation, State Bank, subsidiary banks 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> corresponding new banks] and banking companies may 
subscribe for, in the aggregate, thirty per cent, of 
the share capital:
Provided that none of the said parties shall subscribe for more 
than fifteen per cent. of the share capital.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>266897</tid>
<number>4</number>The parties referred to in sub- section (3) shall subscribe 
for the shares before such date as may be specified in this behalf by 
the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1363246</tid>
<number>5</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), the Central 
Government shall determine the number of shares which are to be 
allotted to the parties referred to in clause (d) of that sub- section:
Provided that if any of the parties referred to in clause (d) of 
sub- section (3) fails to subscribe, by the date specified by the 
Central Government under sub- section (4), for any share allotted to 
it, such share shall be subscribed for by the Central Government, the 
Reserve Bank and the appropriate Government in such proportions as may 
be determined by the Central Government:

Provided further that the shares subscribed for by the Central 
Government, the Reserve Bank and the appropriate Government, in 
pursuance of the provisions of the foregoing proviso, may be 
transferred to any party who is eligible under clause (d) of sub- 
section (3) to subscribe for such shares in the first instance, so, 
however, that the total number of shares held by any of the parties 
referred to in that clause does not exceed fifteen per cent. of the 
share capital of the Corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>171</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1970</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 19- 7- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1812791</tid>
<number>6</number>Restrictions on transfer of shares. Save as otherwise provided 
in the second proviso to sub- section (5) of section 5, the shares of 
the Corporation shall not be transferable.
CHAP

MANAGEMENT OF THE CORPORATION

CHAPTER III

MANAGEMENT OF THE CORPORATION



</article>



<article><tid>1734172</tid>
<number> 7</number> Management.
<section><tid>403304</tid>
<number>1</number>The general superintendence, direction and  
management of the affairs and business of the Corporation shall vest 
in a Board of directors who may exercise all the powers and discharge 
all the functions which may be exercised or discharged by the 
Corporation other than those which are expressly directed or required 
by this Act to be done by the Corporation in general meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>208937</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board in discharging its functions shall act on business 
principles, regard being had to public interest.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1395944</tid>
<number>8</number>Corporation to be guided by directions of Central Government. 
In the discharge of its functions, the Corporation shall be guided by 
such directions in matters of policy involving public interest as the 
Central Government may, in consultation with the Reserve Bank, give to 
it in writing and, if any question arises whether a direction relates 
to a matter of policy involving public interest, the decision of the 
Central Government thereon shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>734642</tid>
<number> 9</number> Constitution of Board. The Board of directors of the 
Corporation shall consist of the following, namely:-
<section><tid>1114793</tid>
<number>a</number>one directors to be nominated by the Central Government 
who shall be the Chairman of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>419973</tid>
<number>b</number>two directors nominated by the appropriate Government, 
one of whom shall be a person who has special knowledge 
of co- operation and who is not an employee of the 
Central or State Government or of the Reserve Bank, 
State Bank, subsidiary bank, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> corresponding new 
bank,] banking company, or Food Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>154116</tid>
<number>c</number>one director to be nominated by the Reserve Bank;

</section>

<section><tid>1376293</tid>
<number>d</number>two directors to be elected in such manner as may be 
prescribed by the parties subscribing for shares in 
pursuance of the provisions of clause (d) of sub- 
section (3), and sub- section (5) of section 5;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>172</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1970</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 19- 7- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1587347</tid>
<number>e</number>a managing director, to be appointed by the Central 
Government and, except in the case of first 
appointment, after consultation with the Board:
Provided that, in appointing a managing director of a 
Corporation established in a State, the Central Government 
may also consult the Government of that State.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1738626</tid>
<number> 10</number> Managing director.
<section><tid>1792616</tid>
<number>1</number>The managing director shall- 

<subsection><tid>998957</tid>
<number>a</number>be a whole- time officer of the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>414804</tid>
<number>b</number>perform such duties as the Board may, by regulations or 
otherwise, assign to him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>140517</tid>
<number>c</number>hold office for such term, not exceeding three years, 
as the Central Government may specify at the time of 
the appointment and be eligible for re- appointment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1732475</tid>
<number>d</number>receive such salary and allowances and be governed by 
such terms and conditions of service as the Central 
Government may-

<subsubsection><tid>1606892</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of first appointment determine, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>774884</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of any subsequent appointment, 
determine after consultation with the Board.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>279616</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, after consultation with the Board 
and for sufficient cause, remove the managing director from office;
Provided that no managing director shall be so removed unless he 
has been given an opportunity of showing cause against his removal.


</section>

<section><tid>538015</tid>
<number>3</number>If the managing director is by infirmity or otherwise 
rendered incapable of carrying out his duties or is absent on leave or 
otherwise in circumstances not involving the vacation of his 
appointment, the Central Government may, after consultation with the 
Board, appoint another person to act in his place during his absence.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1368478</tid>
<number> 11</number> Term of office of directors other than managing director.
<section><tid>1750287</tid>
<number>1</number> 
A nominated director, other than the managing director, shall hold 
office during the pleasure of the authority nominating him and the 
period of such office, unless terminated earlier, shall be two years:
Provided that a nominated director shall be eligible for 
renomination.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>173</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1004208</tid>
<number>2</number>An elected director shall hold office for a period of two 
years from the date of his election:
Provided that an elected director shall continue in office until 
the election of his successor.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>248301</tid>
<number> 12</number> Disqualifications. No person shall be a director, who,-
<section><tid>1079331</tid>
<number>a</number>except in the case of the managing director, is a 
salaried official of the Corporation, or

</section>

<section><tid>589110</tid>
<number>b</number>is, or at any time has been, adjudged insolvent or has 
suspended payment of his debts or has compounded with 
his creditors, or

</section>

<section><tid>1286915</tid>
<number>c</number>is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a 
competent court, or

</section>

<section><tid>860497</tid>
<number>d</number>is or has been convicted of an offence which, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, involves moral 
turpitude.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1532207</tid>
<number> 13</number> Vacation of seats of directors.
<section><tid>855876</tid>
<number>1</number>If a director,- 

<subsection><tid>985444</tid>
<number>a</number>becomes subject to any disqualification specified in 
section 12, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>785639</tid>
<number>b</number>is absent without leave of the Board for more than 
three consecutive meetings thereof,
his seat shall thereupon become vacant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>343163</tid>
<number>2</number>The managing director or any other director may resign his 
office by giving notice thereof in writing to the authority by which 
he was appointed or nominated, or if he is a director elected under 
clause (d) of section 9, to the Board, and on such resignation being 
accepted, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>840250</tid>
<number> 14</number> Executive Committee and other committees of the Corporation.

<section><tid>1486806</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may constitute and Executive Committee consisting of the  
Chairman of the Board, who shall be the Chairman thereof, the managing 
director and two other directors, one of whom shall be a person 
nominated by the appropriate Government under clause (b) of section 9.

</section>

<section><tid>1382738</tid>
<number>2</number>The Executive Committee shall discharge such functions as may 
be prescribed, or may be delegated to it, by the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>725362</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board may constitute such other committees, whether 
consisting wholly of directors or wholly of other persons or partly of 
directors and partly of other persons, as it may think fit for such 
purposes as it may decide.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>174</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1578434</tid>
<number> 15</number> Meetings of Board and committees.
<section><tid>1829588</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board or the  
Executive Committee or any other committee shall meet at such times 
and places and shall observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1699385</tid>
<number>2</number>Three directors personally present at any meeting of the 
Board and two members personally present at a meeting of a committee 
shall be the quorum for such meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1039660</tid>
<number>3</number>If, for any reason, the Chairman of the Board or of any 
committee is unable to attend any meeting of the Board or the 
Committee, as the case may be, the members present at the meeting 
shall elect one of them to preside at the meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>1557582</tid>
<number>4</number>If for any reason a director nominated under clause (a), 
clause (b) or clause (c) of section 9 is unable to attend any meeting 
of the Board or of any committee if he is a member thereof, the 
Government or the Reserve Bank by which such director was nominated 
may depute any other person to attend such meeting and the person so 
deputed shall, for the purposes of the said meeting, be deemed to be a 
director nominated under clause (a), clause (b) or clause (c), as the 
case may be, of the said section 9 or a member of the committee 
concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>788474</tid>
<number>5</number>All questions which may come up before any meeting of the 
Board or a committee shall be decided by a majority of votes of the 
members present, and in the event of an equality of votes, the 
Chairman of the Board or of the Committee, as the case may be, or in 
his absence the person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1282055</tid>
<number>16</number>Directors of Board or members of a committee not to vote in 
certain cases. Every director or member of a committee who has any 
direct or indirect pecuniary or other interest in any matter coming up 
for consideration at a meeting of the Board or a committee shall, as 
soon as possible, after the relevant facts or circumstances have come 
to his knowledge, disclose the nature of his interest at such meeting 
and the disclosure so made shall be recorded in the minutes of the 
meeting of the Board or of the Committee, as the case may be, and no 
such director or member shall thereafter take any part in any 
deliberation or decision of the Board or committee with respect to 
that matter nor shall his presence at such meeting be taken into 
account for the purpose of determining the quorum for the meeting at 
the time of such deliberation or voting, and if he does vote, his vote 
shall be void:
Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to 
such director or member of a committee by reason only of his being a


<pagefootnote><pagenum>175</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shareholder holding not more than two per cent. of the paid- up capital 
in any public company as defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), or in any other Corporation established by any law for the time 
being in force in India or in any co- operative society, with which or 
to which the Corporation has entered into or made, or proposes to 
enter into or make, a contract, loan, arrangement or proposal.



</article>



<article><tid>730634</tid>
<number> 17</number> Defects in appointments not to invalidate acts, etc.
<section><tid>573715</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
act or proceeding of the Board or of any of its committees shall be 
questioned or be invalid on the ground merely of the existence of any 
vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Board or the 
committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1506357</tid>
<number>2</number>No act done by any person acting in good faith as a director 
or member of any committee shall be deemed to be invalid merely on the 
ground that he was disqualified to be a director or member or that 
there was any other defect in his nomination of appointment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1654101</tid>
<number>18</number>Fees and allowances of directors and members of committees. 
Every director and every member of a committee shall be paid such fees 
and allowances as the Board may, by regulations, determine, for 
attending the meetings of the Board or, as the case may be, any of its 
committees, or attending to any other work of the Corporation:
Provided that no fees be paid to the Chairman, managing director 
or any other director, if he is an officer of the Government, Reserve 
Bank, State Bank, subsidiary bank, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> corresponding new bank,] banking 
company or Food Corporation.

CHAP

BUSINESS AND FUNDS OF THE CORPORATION

CHAPTER IV

BUSINESS AND FUNDS OF THE CORPORATION



</article>



<article><tid>1940011</tid>
<number> 19</number> Business which the Corporation may transact. Subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Corporation may transact the following 
kinds of business, namely:-
<section><tid>740759</tid>
<number>a</number>the granting of loans and advances, repayable within a 
period, not exceeding five years, to agriculturists, 
agricultural marketing societies, agricultural 
processing societies, Central Co- operative Banks, co- 
operative farming societies or primary agricultural 
credit societies for agricultural operations or for 
such other operations connected there- with as the Board 
may by regulations determine;

</section>

<section><tid>196515</tid>
<number>b</number>the drawing, making, accepting, discounting, buying, 
selling, collecting and dealing in bills of exchange, 
hundies, promissory notes, coupons, drafts, bills of 
lading, railway
<pagefootnote><pagenum>176</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1970</year>, s. 20 (w. e. f. 19- 7- <year>1969</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


receipts, warrants, debentures, certificates, scrips 
and other instruments, and securities whether 
transferable or negotiable or not;


</section>

<section><tid>1218251</tid>
<number>c</number>the granting and issuing of letters of credit and 
acquiring, holding, issuing on commission, underwriting 
and dealing in stock, funds, shares, debentures, 
debenture stock, bonds, obligations, securities and 
investments of all kinds;

</section>

<section><tid>681607</tid>
<number>d</number>the purchasing and selling of bonds, scrips or other 
forms of securities on behalf of constituents or 
others, the negotiating of loans and advances, the 
receiving of all kinds of bonds, scrips of valuables on 
deposit or for safe custody or otherwise, providing of 
safe deposit vaults, and collecting and transmitting 
money and securities;

</section>

<section><tid>1174077</tid>
<number>e</number>the carrying on of agency business of any description 
including the clearing and forwarding of goods, giving 
of receipts and discharges;

</section>

<section><tid>530198</tid>
<number>f</number>the entering into contracts of indemnity, suretyship or 
guarantee with specific security or otherwise;

</section>

<section><tid>821498</tid>
<number>g</number>receiving in consideration of the services mentioned in 
clauses (b), (c), (d), (e) and (f) such commission as may 
be agreed upon;

</section>

<section><tid>761088</tid>
<number>h</number>managing or selling of any property which may come into 
the possession of the Corporation in satisfaction or 
part satisfaction of any of its claims;

</section>

<section><tid>677829</tid>
<number>i</number>acquiring or holding of any property or any right, 
title or interest in any property which may form the 
security or a part of the security for any loan or 
advance or which may be connected with any business of 
the Corporation;

</section>

<section><tid>1593997</tid>
<number>j</number>any other kind of business which the Central Government 
may, on the recommendation of the Reserve Bank, 
authorise;

</section>

<section><tid>541453</tid>
<number>k</number>generally the doing of such things and matters as may 
be incidental to or consequential upon the discharge of 
its functions under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>146581</tid>
<number> 20</number> Borrowing by the Corporation. Subject to the provisions of 
this Act, the Corporation may, for the purposes of carrying out its 
functions under this Act,-
<section><tid>386959</tid>
<number>a</number>re- discount with or sell to the Reserve Bank or borrow 
money from that Bank and for that purpose, the 
Corporation shall be deemed to be a State Co- operative 
Bank within the meaning of clause 2 (a), clause 2 (b), 
clause

<pagefootnote><pagenum>177</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>594893</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and clause (4) of section 17, sub- section (2) of 
section 46A and sub- section (2) of section 46B of the 
Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>378067</tid>
<number>b</number>borrow money from the Central Government or the State 
Government or such other authority or institution as 
approved in this behalf by the Central Government, on 
such terms and conditions as may be agreed upon.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1675079</tid>
<number>21</number>Deposits with the Corporation. The Corporation may, with the 
prior approval of the Reserve Bank, accept deposits from the 
appropriate Government, a local authority or any other person whether 
incorporated or not.


</article>



<article><tid>1087657</tid>
<number>22</number>Limits on borrowings and deposits. The aggregate of the 
amounts borrowed and deposits accepted by the Corporation and 
outstanding shall not at any time exceed ten times the amount of the 
paid- up share capital and the reserve fund of the Corporation or, with 
the prior approval of the Central Government, fifteen times the amount 
of such paid- up share capital and reserve fund.


</article>



<article><tid>44934</tid>
<number> 23</number> Corporation to maintain two funds. The Corporation shall 
establish two separate funds, namely:-
<section><tid>572084</tid>
<number>a</number>Agricultural Credit (Stabilization) Fund (hereinafter  
  referred to as the Stabilization Fund), and

</section>

<section><tid>1454801</tid>
<number>b</number>Reserve Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1401108</tid>
<number> 24</number> Stabilization Fund.
<section><tid>404379</tid>
<number>1</number>To the Stabilization Fund shall be  
credited such sum, not being less than ten and not more than fifteen 
per cent. as the Corporation may deem fit from out of its net annual 
profits before declaring a dividend.

</section>

<section><tid>300756</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to such conditions as may be specified by the Board 
by regulations, the amount lying to the credit of the Stabilization 
Fund shall be utilised solely for the purpose of making loans or 
advances with a view to enabling any co- operative society or other 
person to pay its or his dues in cases where, in the opinion of the 
Corporation, such society or other person is unable to pay such dues 
in time owing to drought, famine or other natural calamities.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>519323</tid>
<number> 25</number> Reserve Fund.
<section><tid>207965</tid>
<number>1</number>To the Reserve Fund shall be credited such  
sums not being more than fifteen per cent. as the Corporation may deem 
fit out of its net annual profits before declaring a dividend.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>178</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>215429</tid>
<number>2</number>The amounts lying to the credit of the Reserve Fund shall be 
utilised solely for such purposes as the Board may by regulations 
specify.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1466865</tid>
<number>26</number>Payment of dividend. After making provision for bad and 
doubtful debts, depreciation of assets and all other matters which are 
usually provided for by bankers, and after crediting to the 
Stabilization Fund under section 24 and to the Reserve Fund under 
section 25, the Corporation may, out of its annual net profits, 
declare a dividend.


</article>



<article><tid>854235</tid>
<number> 27</number> Investment of surplus funds. All moneys belonging to the 
Corporation which may not, for the time being be required by it shall 
be-
<section><tid>782189</tid>
<number>a</number>deposited with the Reserve Bank or with any agency of 
the Reserve Bank or in consultation with the Reserve 
Bank with a Scheduled Bank, State Co- operative Bank or 
Central Co- operative Bank; or

</section>

<section><tid>1185909</tid>
<number>b</number>invested in the securities of the Central Government or 
any State Government or in securities in which a 
trustee may invest money under clause (a), clause (b), 
clause (bb), clause (c) or clause (d) of section 20 of 
the Indian Trusts Act, <year>1882</year> (2 of <year>1882</year>); or

</section>

<section><tid>1454502</tid>
<number>c</number>utilised in such other manner as may be approved by 
the Reserve Bank.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1975124</tid>
<number>28</number>Recovery of moneys due to the Corporation. Where any amount 
is due to the Corporation in respect of loans or advances or other 
financial accommodation granted by it to any person, the Corporation 
or any person authorised by it in writing in this behalf, may, without 
prejudice to any other mode of recovery. make an application to the 
appropriate Government for the recovery of the amount due to it, and 
if the appropriate Government, or such authority, as that Government 
may specify in this behalf, is satisfied, after following such 
procedure as may be prescribed, that any amount is so due, it may 
issue a certificate for that amount to the Collector, and the 
Collector shall proceed to recover that amount in the same manner and 
under the same conditions as if it were an arrear of land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>439283</tid>
<number> 29</number> Acquisition or transfer by the Corporation of business, 
assets and liabilities from or to co- operative societies.
<section><tid>450367</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject  
to the provisions of any law relating to co- operative societies for 
the time being in force, the Corporation may-

<subsection><tid>705858</tid>
<number>a</number>acquire the whole or any part of the business including 
the assets and liabilities of a co- operative society;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>179</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>336146</tid>
<number>b</number>transfer the whole or any part of its business, 
including its assets or liabilities to a co- operative 
society.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>999207</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions relating to such acquisition or 
transfer, if agreed upon by the Board and the co- operative society 
concerned shall be submitted to the Reserve Bank for its approval and 
that Bank may by order in writing (hereafter in this section referred  
  to as the order of approval) accord its approval thereto:
Provided that where such acquisition or transfer involves the 
acquisition of the assets of the co- operative society or a transfer of 
the liabilities of the Corporation to the co- operative society, no 
such approval shall be accorded by the Reserve Bank, unless it is 
satisfied that-


<subsection><tid>1893501</tid>
<number>i</number>the co- operative society has given notice of the 
proposed acquisition or transfer, in such manner as may 
be provided under the law relating to co- operative 
societies applicable to it, to all its members and 
creditors, giving them the option, of demanding payment 
of their share or dues, as the case may be, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>348626</tid>
<number>ii</number>all the members and creditors have assented to the 
proposal or deemed to have assented thereto by virtue 
of any member or creditor failing to exercise his 
option within such period as may be specified in 
accordance with such law relating to co- operative 
societies for the time being in force.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>171817</tid>
<number>3</number>The terms and conditions as approved by the Reserve Bank 
shall come into effect from the date specified by the Bank in this 
behalf in the order of approval and be binding upon the Corporation 
and its shareholders and creditors and if such law relating to co- 
operative societies so provides be binding also upon the co- operative 
society and its shareholders and creditors.

</section>

<section><tid>1480278</tid>
<number>4</number>If for any reason the terms and conditions cannot come into 
effect on the date specified in the order of approval, the Reserve 
Bank may fix another suitable date for that purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>575752</tid>
<number>5</number>On the date on which the terms and conditions as aforesaid 
come into effect, the business, assets and liabilities of the 
Corporation, or as the case may be, the co- operative society 
concerned, shall, by virtue of and in accordance with the provisions 
of the aforesaid order of approval, and if such law relating to co- 
operative societies so provides, stand transferred to, and become the 
business, assets and liabilities of the co- operative society or the 
Corporation, as the case may be.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>180</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

GENERAL MEETINGS

CHAPTER V

GENERAL MEETINGS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>616949</tid>
<number> 30</number> General meetings.
<section><tid>1032614</tid>
<number>1</number>A general meeting (in this Act referred   
  to as an annual general meeting) of the Corporation shall be held at 
the Head Office of the Corporation within three months from the date 
on which the annual accounts of the Corporation are closed, and any 
other general meeting may be convened by the Board at any other time:
Provided that the Central Government may extend the time within 
which any annual general meeting shall be held, by a period not 
exceeding one month.


</section>

<section><tid>270096</tid>
<number>2</number>The shareholders present at an annual general meeting shall 
be entitled to discuss the balance- sheet and profit and loss account 
of the Corporation, the report of the Board on the working of the 
Corporation for the period covered by the accounts and the auditor' s 
report on the balance- sheet and accounts.
CHAP

ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND RETURNS

CHAPTER VI

ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND RETURNS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1949520</tid>
<number> 31</number> Accounts.
<section><tid>628505</tid>
<number>1</number>The balance- sheet and accounts including the  
profit and loss account of the Corporation shall be prepared and 
maintained in such form and manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1917742</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall cause the books and accounts of the 
Corporation to be balanced and closed on the thirtieth day of June 
each year.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1420667</tid>
<number> 32</number> Audit.
<section><tid>473330</tid>
<number>1</number>The accounts of the Corporation shall be audited  
by an auditor duly qualified to act as auditor under sub- section (1) 
of section 226 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) who shall be 
appointed by the Board with the previous approval of the Reserve Bank 
and shall receive such remuneration from the Corporation as the Board 
may with the approval of the Reserve Bank, fix:
Provided that the first auditor shall be appointed by the Central 
Government within one month from the establishment of Corporation on 
such terms and conditions as the Central Government may determine.


</section>

<section><tid>378375</tid>
<number>2</number>The auditor so appointed shall hold office from the 
conclusion of the annual general meeting of the Corporation until the 
conclusion of the next annual general meeting:
Provided that the first auditor shall hold office until the 
conclusion of the first annual general meeting.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>181</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1357585</tid>
<number>3</number>The Corporation shall supply its auditor with a copy of its 
annual balance- sheet and it shall be the duty of the auditor to 
examine such balance- sheet together with the accounts and vouchers 
relating thereto and he shall have a list delivered to him of all 
books kept by the Corporation and shall at all reasonable times have 
access to the books, accounts, vouchers and other documents of the 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1725527</tid>
<number>4</number>The auditor may, in relation to the accounts of the 
Corporation of which he is the auditor, examine any director or any 
officer or employee of the Corporation and shall be entitled to 
require from the officers of the Corporation such information and 
explanation as he may think necessary for the performance of his 
duties.

</section>

<section><tid>1981842</tid>
<number>5</number>The auditor shall make a report to the Corporation upon the 
annual balance- sheet and accounts examined by him and in every such 
report he shall state whether in his opinion the accounts exhibit a 
true and fair view,-

<subsection><tid>63376</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of the balance- sheet, of the state of 
affairs of the Corporation at the end of the year, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>453743</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of the profit and loss account, of the 
profit or loss for the year, and, in case he had called 
for any explanation or information from the Board, 
whether it has been given and whether it is 
satisfactory.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>499442</tid>
<number>6</number>Without prejudice to anything contained in the preceding 
sub- sections, the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India may, if so 
requested by the Central Government, examine and report upon the 
accounts of the Corporation and any expenditure incurred by him in 
connection with such examination and report shall be payable by such 
Corporation to the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1811377</tid>
<number> 33</number> Returns.
<section><tid>1049008</tid>
<number>1</number>The Corporation shall furnish, from time to  
time, to the appropriate Government and to the Reserve Bank such 
returns as the appropriate Government or the Reserve Bank may require.

</section>

<section><tid>866646</tid>
<number>2</number>The Corporation shall furnish to all its shareholders within 
three months from the date on which the annual accounts of the 
Corporation are closed, or within such further time not exceeding one 
month as the Central Government may specify, a copy of the balance- 
sheet as at the close of that year and profit and loss account for the 
year, the auditor' s report and a report of the Board on

<pagefootnote><pagenum>182</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the working of the Corporation during the year, and copies of the said 
balance- sheet, profit and loss account and reports shall be published 
in the Official Gazette.


</section>

<section><tid>685874</tid>
<number>3</number>The Corporation shall furnish a statement in such form as may 
be prescribed of its assets and liabilities as at the close of 
business on the last Friday of each month or if that day is a public 
holiday under the Negotiable Instruments Act, <year>1881</year> (26 of <year>1881</year>), as at 
the close of business at the preceding working day, to the Reserve 
Bank within ten days from the date to which the statement relates.
CHAP

APPLICATION OF CERTAIN ACTS TO THE CORPORATION

CHAPTER VII

APPLICATION OF CERTAIN ACTS TO THE CORPORATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>721429</tid>
<number> 34</number> Certain provisions of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year>, to 
apply to the Corporation. The provisions of sections 8, 9, 20, 20A, 
21, 23, 24, 26, 34A, <footcitenum>35</footcitenum> excluding sub- section (4)], 35A, clause (a) 
of sub- section
<section><tid>1091472</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 36, and sections 46, 47, 50, 53 and 54  
of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>), shall apply to or 
in relation to the Corporation as they apply to or in relation to co- 
operative banks.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1212296</tid>
<number>35</number>Certain provisions of the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> (2  
  of <year>1934</year>), to apply to the Corporation. The provisions of sections 18 
and 42 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year>, shall apply to or in 
relation to the Corporation as they apply to or in relation to a State 
Co- operative Bank.


</article>



<article><tid>501328</tid>
<number>36</number>Reserve Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year> and Banking Regulation Act, 
<year>1949</year>, not to apply except as otherwise provided. Save as otherwise 
provided in this Act, nothing contained in the Reserve Bank of India 
Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>), and the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of  
  <year>1949</year>), shall apply to or in relation to the Corporation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>183</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1274156</tid>
<number>37</number>The Bankers' Books Evidence Act, <year>1891</year> to apply. The Bankers' 
Books Evidence Act <year>1891</year> (18 of <year>1891</year>), shall apply to or in relation 
to the Corporation as it applies to or in relation to a bank as 
defined in section 2 of that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>11731</tid>
<number>38</number>Corporation to be deemed to be a co- operative society for the 
purposes of Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>. For the purposes of the Income- tax 
Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), or any other enactment for the time being in 
force relating to any tax on income, profits or gains the Corporation 
shall be deemed to be a co- operative society.


</article>



<article><tid>691531</tid>
<number>39</number>Court, Tribunal, etc., not to require production of report on 
inspection made by the Reserve Bank. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>), or any other 
law for the time being in force, no Court, Tribunal or other authority 
shall have power to require the Corporation, the Reserve Bank or any 
officer of the Corporation or the Reserve Bank to produce before such 
Court, Tribunal or other authority the report of any inspection, or 
any copy thereof, made by the Reserve Bank in pursuance of section 35 
of the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>), as applied to the 
Corporation under section 34.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VIII

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1153701</tid>
<number>40</number>Declaration of fidelity and secrecy. Every director, member 
of a committee, auditor, officer or other employee of the Corporation 
shall, before entering upon his duties, make a declaration of fidelity 
and secrecy in the form set out in the Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1408422</tid>
<number> 41</number> Indemnity of director.
<section><tid>1549726</tid>
<number>1</number>Every director shall be  
indemnified by the Corporation against all losses and expenses 
incurred by him in the discharge of his duties except such as are 
caused by his own wilful act or default.

</section>

<section><tid>1290748</tid>
<number>2</number>A director shall not be responsible for anything done or 
omitted to be done by any other director or officer or other employee 
of the Corporation or for any loss or expenses resulting to the 
Corporation by the insufficiency or deficiency of value of, or title 
to, any property or security acquired or taken on behalf of the 
Corporation

<pagefootnote><pagenum>184</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

in good faith, or by the wrongful act of any auditor or any person 
under obligation to the Corporation, or by anything done in good faith 
in the execution of the duties of his office or in relation thereto.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>791137</tid>
<number>42</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against the Corporation or the Central or 
State Government or the Reserve Bank or any director or officer of the 
Corporation or of the Central or State Government or of the Reserve 
Bank or any other person authorised by the Corporation to discharge 
any functions under this Act, for any loss or damage caused or likely 
to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done in pursuance of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>806632</tid>
<number> 43</number> Liquidation of the Corporation.
<section><tid>1784299</tid>
<number>1</number>No provision of law  
relating to the winding up of companies or corporations shall apply to 
the Corporation and the Corporation shall not be placed in liquidation 
save by order of the Central Government made in consultation with the 
State Government and in such manner as it may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>60548</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), any 
order made by the Central Government for the liquidation of a 
Corporation may provide for all matters for effectively winding up the 
affairs of the Corporation, including the repayment of capital, 
disposal of any fund established under this Act, the transfer of the 
business, property, assets and liabilities, rights, interests, 
privileges and obligations of whatever nature of the Corporation to 
such institution or institutions as the Central Government may direct 
and payment, receipt or disposal of compensation arising out of such 
transfer.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>87498</tid>
<number>44</number>Reserve Bank to submit report. The Reserve Bank shall, on the 
expiry of a period of three years, from the date of establishment of 
the Agricultural Credit Corporation in a State or Union territory and 
thereafter at an interval of three years and within such time as the 
Central Government may specify, submit a report to that Government as 
to the working of the Corporation and forward a copy thereof to the 
State Government concerned.


</article>



<article><tid>702863</tid>
<number> 45</number> Staff of the Corporation and delegation of powers.
<section><tid>121926</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Corporation may appoint such officers, advisers and employees as it 
considers necessary for the efficient performance of its function and 
determine, by regulations or otherwise, their conditions of 
appointment and service and the remuneration payable to them.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>185</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>958329</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may, by general or special order, delegate to the 
Managing Director or to any other officer of the Corporation, subject 
to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified, such 
of its powers and duties under this Act as it may deem necessary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>295436</tid>
<number> 46</number> Powers of the Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>830758</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1391569</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1370863</tid>
<number>a</number>functions which shall be discharged by the Executive 
Committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1822599</tid>
<number>b</number>rules of procedure with regard to the transaction of 
business at a meeting of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>617397</tid>
<number>c</number>rules of procedure with regard to the transaction of 
business at a meeting of any committee constituted by 
the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>637695</tid>
<number>d</number>the procedure to be followed by the appropriate 
Government or the authority specified by the 
appropriate Government for issuing the certificate 
under section 28;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1152460</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which the general meeting shall be 
convened, the quorum therefor, the procedure to be 
followed thereat and the manner in which voting rights 
may be exercised;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>945038</tid>
<number>f</number>form and manner in which accounts shall be maintained 
the balance- sheet and profit and loss account shall be 
prepared;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1901088</tid>
<number>g</number>form in which statement of assets and liabilities shall 
be furnished;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1504390</tid>
<number>h</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>626366</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised 
in one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or 
the successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect
<pagefootnote><pagenum>186</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1596098</tid>
<number> 47</number> Power of the Board to make regulations.
<section><tid>1586055</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board  
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> after consultation with the Reserve Bank, may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette"] make regulations not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder, to provide for 
all matters for which provision is necessary or expedient for the 
purposes of giving effect to the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1811473</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provisions, such regulations may provide for all or any of 
the following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>147347</tid>
<number>a</number>duties which the managing director shall perform;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>295041</tid>
<number>b</number>fees and allowances which may be paid to every director 
for attending any meeting of the Board or any committee 
thereof or for attending to any other work of the 
Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>381808</tid>
<number>c</number>duties, conduct, salaries and allowances and conditions 
of service of officers and other employees of the 
Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>826213</tid>
<number>d</number>establishment and maintenance of provident and other 
benefit funds for the employees of the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>918387</tid>
<number>e</number>the delegation of powers and functions to the officers 
and employees of the Corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>494677</tid>
<number>f</number>the purposes connected with agricultural purposes for 
which the Corporation may grant loans and advances;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>121599</tid>
<number>g</number>the conditions subject to which the amount in the 
Stabilisation Fund may be utilised;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1292906</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner in which the amount in the Reserve Fund may 
be utilised;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1476760</tid>
<number>i</number>conditions which the Corporation may impose on any loan 
or advance made by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1781317</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter which is, or may be, necessary for the 
efficient conduct of the affairs of the Corporation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1542145</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), the 
Reserve Bank may at any time within three months from the commencement 
of this Act make regulations with regard to any of the matters 
specified in sub- section (2) but the regulations so made may
<pagefootnote><pagenum>187</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


be rescinded or modified by the Board in exercise of the powers 
conferred on it by sub- section (1).


</section>

<section><tid>1330616</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as 
soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation, or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that regulation."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1234339</tid>
<number>48</number>Amendment of Act 10 of <year>1963</year>. In clause (f) of section 2 of 
the Agricultural Refinance Corporation Act, <year>1963</year>, after sub- clause 
 (ii), the following sub- clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (iii) an Agricultural Credit Corporation established under 
section 3 of the State Agricultural Credit Corporations 
Act, <year>1968</year> (60 of <year>1968</year>.)".


</article>



 </act>