<act> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 19681
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, 
application and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Payment of Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 
1968.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall apply in 
respect of payment of wages to persons employed in an air transport service 
either directly by the owner or through a contractor engaged by such owner.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They shall extend to 
the whole of India


2[***].
 
 




</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Payment of Wages 
Act, 1936 (4 of 1936);
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  “authority” means an authority 
appointed under sub-section (1) of section 15;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  “1[Deputy 
Chief Labour Commissioner (Central)]” means an officer appointed as such by the 
Central Government;
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  “contractor” means a person 
engaged under a contract, by the owner of an air transport service, to perform 
certain functions in relation to the air transport service, and includes a 
sub-contractor;
 </section><section>
        <number>e</number>  “court” means the court 
mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 17;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “deduction for breach of 
contract” means a deduction made in accordance with the proviso to sub-section 
(2) of section 9;
 </section><section>
        <number>g</number>  “deduction for damage or loss” 
means a deduction made in accordance with clause (c) of sub-section (2) of 
section 7;
 </section><section>
        <number>h</number>  “employed person” means a person 
employed in an air transport service to whom the Act applies;
 </section><section>
         <number>i</number>  “employer” means the owner of 
an air transport service and includes a contractor, agent, manager or any other 
person responsible under section 3 for payment of wages;
 </section><section>
         <number>j</number>  “Form” means a Form appended to 
these rules;
 </section><section>
        <number>k</number>  “Inspector” means an Inspector 
appointed under section 14;
 </section><section>
         <number>l</number>  “Regional Labour Commissioner


2[(Central)]” means an officer 
appointed as such by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
       <number>m</number>  “section” means a section of the 
Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>n</number>  words and expressions used in 
these rules and not defined herein shall have the same meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Act.
 
 




</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Notice of opening, 
abandonment, discontinuance, resumption and change in the ownership, addresses, 
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> When 
an air transport service has been opened, the employer shall forthwith 
communicate the actual date of opening to the Regional Labour Commissioner


1[(Central)] 
concerned notice in Form I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where it is intended 
to abandon an air transport service or to discontinue it for a period exceeding 
60 days, the employer shall, not less than 40 days before such abandonment or 
discontinuance, give to the Regional Labour Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned, a notice in Form I stating the reasons for the proposed abandonment 
or discontinuance and the number of persons likely to be affected thereby:
 
Provided that when an air 
transport service is abandoned or discontinued before the said notice was given, 
or when the discontinuance exceeds 60 days due to unforeseen circumstances, the 
notice be given forthwith.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When an air transport 
service has been abandoned or discontinued for a period exceeding 60 days, the 
employer shall forthwith communicate the actual date of abandonment or 
discontinuance, to the Regional Labour Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where it is intended 
to resume an air transport service after abandonment or after discontinuance for 
a period exceeding 60 days, the employer shall, not less than 30 days before the 
resumption of transport operations give to the Regional Labour Commissioner


1[(Central)] 
concerned notice in Form I.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where an air transport 
service has been resumed the employer of the air transport service shall 
forthwith communicate the actual date of resumption to the Regional Labour 
Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When a change occurs 
in the name or ownership of an air transport service or in the address of the 
owner, the employer shall, within seven days from the date of such change, give 
to the Regional Labour Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned, a notice in Form I:
 
Provided that where the 
owner of an air transport service is a firm or other association of individuals, 
a change:—
 <subsection>
         <number>i</number>  of any partner, in the case of 
a firm;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  of any member, in the case of 
an association;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iii</number>  of any director, in the case 
of a public company; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>iv</number>  of any shareholder, in the case 
of a private company,
 
shall also be intimated to the Regional 
Labour Commissioner 

2[(Central)] concerned within seven 
days from the date of such change.
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Register of fines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every employer who desires to impose fine on the employed persons shall obtain 
the approval of the Regional Labour Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned to a list of acts and omissions in respect of which fine may be 
imposed. The Regional Labour Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned shall be the authority competent to approve, under sub-section (8) of 
section 8, the purposes for which the amount of fines realised may be expended.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every employer who has 
obtained approval to the list of acts and omissions under sub-rule (1) shall 
maintain a register of fines in Form II.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The list of acts and 
omissions in respect of which fines may be imposed, shall be entered in the 
register of fines, at the beginning.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> At the beginning of 
the register of fines, there shall also be entered, serially numbered, the 
approved purpose or purposes on which the amount of the fines realised is to be 
expended.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> At the end of every 
month, the amounts realised as fines shall be totalled and carried forward after 
deduction of disbursement, if any, as per Part II or Form II.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When any disbursements 
are made from the amounts of the fines realised, a deduct entry of the amount so 
expended shall be made in the Register of Fines and a voucher or receipt in 
respect of the amount shall be affixed to the register. If more than one purpose 
has been approved, the entry of the disbursement shall also indicate the purpose 
for which it is made.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Register of Fines 
shall be 

2[***] maintained 
up-to-date. Where no fine has been imposed on any employee in a wage-period, a 
nil entry shall be made across the body of the register at the end of the 
wage-period indicating also in precise terms the wage-period to which the nil 
entry relates.
 
 




</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Register of deductions 
for damage or loss.—A 
register of deductions for damage or loss in Form III shall be 

1[***] maintained 
up-to-date. Where no deduction has been made from the wages of any employed 
person in a wage-period, a nil entry shall be made across the body of the 
register at the end of the wage-period indicating also in precise terms the 
wage-period to which the nil entry relates.
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Muster rolls and 
register of wages.—Every 
employer shall maintain a muster roll and register of wages in Forms IV and V 
respectively or a Muster Roll-cum-Register of Wages in Form VI. These records 
shall be maintained up-to-date 

1[***]. The 
attendance of an employed person shall be marked not later than one hour after 
the employed person commences work for the day.
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Combined form of 
registers.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in these rules, where mechanised pay rolls are introduced for 
better administration or a combined (alternative) form is sought to be used by 
an employer to avoid duplication of work for compliance with the provisions of 
any other Act or rules framed thereunder, an alternative suitable form may be 
used in lieu of any of the forms prescribed under these rules, with the prior 
approval of the 

1[Deputy] Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central).
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Preservation and 
maintenance of register.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Every register maintained under the Act or these rules shall be maintained 
up-to-date, kept and preserved for a period of three years after the date of 
last entry made therein in the establishment:
 
Provided that the employer 
may with prior approval of the Regional Labour Commissioner (Central) preserve 
and keep the register at a place other than the establishment specified by him.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The registers 
maintained under the Act or these rules shall be maintained in English or in 
Hindi, but where a register is maintained in Hindi, a true translation thereof 
in English shall also be maintained.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Production of registers 
and records.—All 
registers and records required to be maintained under these rules, shall be 
produced by the employer on demand before the Inspector:
 
Provided that where an 
establishment has been closed, the Inspector may demand the production of 
registers and records in his office or such other public place as may be nearer 
to the employer.
 


</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Places for displaying 
notices.—The 
Inspector shall specify such place or places in the establishment as he thinks 
fit (hereinafter referred to as the specified place or places) for the display 
of notices and lists under rules 11 and 12.
 


</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Notice of dates of 
payment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The employer shall display at a conspicuous place outside his office and at the 
specified place or places, notices in English or Hindi and in the language, if 
that be not Hindi, of the majority of the persons employed at such places 
showing,—
 
 

1[(i)  the wage-period for which wages 
are payable;]
 
 

2[(ii)]  for not less than two weeks 
in advance, the days on which wages are to be paid; 

3[***]
 
 

2[(iii)]  the rates of wages and 
scales of allowance payable to persons employed in Form VII.
 
 

2[(iv)]  the day or date on which 
unpaid wages are to be paid indicating the relevant wage-period to which the 
unpaid wages pertain. The employer may however disburse such unpaid wages on any 
day in addition to the prescribed day or date.]
 
Copies of all such notices and alterations 
therein shall be sent to the Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The employer shall 
display outside his office and at the specified place or places, a notice 
showing the name and complete address of the Inspector having jurisdiction over 
the establishment.
 
 





</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>11A</number> 
Supervision of payment.—Whenever an Inspector so desires, the employer or 
his representative of the establishment shall pay wages to the employed persons 
on the notified date of payment in his presence.]
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Lists of acts and 
omissions.—The 
employer shall display outside his office and at the specified place or places, 
a copy in English, or Hindi or in the language, if that be not Hindi, of the 
majority of persons employed, the list of acts and omissions approved under rule 
4.
 


</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Persons authorised to 
impose fines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fine shall be imposed by any person other than the employer or a member of 
his staff authorised by him in writing in this behalf. A copy of such 
authorisation shall be duly sent to the Inspector concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of persons 
employed by a contractor, no fine shall be imposed by any person other than the 
contractor:
 
Provided that a contractor 
who runs more than one establishment in two or more localities, and who employs 
not less than fifty persons in one locality, may, with the approval of the 
Regional Labour Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
delegate his powers to impose fine to his representative in that locality.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Procedure in imposing 
fines and deductions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No fines shall be imposed, except in accordance with the procedure laid down in 
any rules, regulations or certified standing orders in force in the 
establishment and until the employed person has been given an opportunity in 
written to show cause against such imposition and it has also been established 
that he was guilty of the act of omission or commission alleged against him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No deduction for 
damage or loss shall be made from the wages of an employed person except in 
accordance with the rules or regulations of the establishment or certified 
standing order in force in the establishment and until he has been given an 
opportunity to show cause against such deduction and it has also been 
established that the damage or loss sustained by the employer is directly 
attributable to the neglect or default of the employed person.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No fine shall be 
imposed on, and no deduction for damage or loss shall be made from the wages of 
a person employed by a contractor until the person competent to impose the fine 
or to make deduction has explained personally to the said person, the act or 
omission or damage or loss, in respect of which the fine or deduction is imposed 
or made and the amount of fine or deduction which it is proposed to impose or 
make and the employed person has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard in the presence of at least one more person.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Deduction under the 
proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No deduction under the proviso to sub-section (2) of section 9 shall be made 
from the wages of an employed person who is under the age of fifteen years or is 
a woman.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such deduction 
shall exceed the ages of the employed person for the period by which the notice 
of termination of service given falls short of the period of such notice 
required by the contract of employment or certified Standing Orders.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No such deduction 
shall be made from the wages of any employed person unless this rule has been 
displayed in English or Hindi and in the language, if that be not Hindi, of the 
majority of the employed persons, outside the office of the establishment and at 
the specified place or places concerned, and has been so displayed for not less 
than one month before the commencement of the absence in respect of which the 
deduction is made.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No such deduction 
shall be made from the wages of any employed person unless a notice has been 
displayed outside the office of the establishment and at the specified place or 
places, at least one week before such deduction is made giving the names of the 
persons from whom the deduction is proposed to be made, the number of day’s 
wages to be deducted and the conditions, if any, on which the deduction will be 
remitted:
 
Provided that where the 
deduction is proposed to be made from all the persons employed in any department 
or section of the establishment, it shall be sufficient, in lieu of giving the 
names of such persons in the department or section, to specify the department or 
section affected.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If any conditions have 
been specified in the notice displayed under sub-rule (4) no such deduction 
shall be made from any person who has complied with such conditions.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Annual Return.—Every 
employer shall send a return in Form VIII so as to reach the Regional Labour 
Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned not later than the 1st of February following the end of the year to 
which it relates endorsing simultaneously a copy thereof to the Inspector having 
jurisdiction over the establishment.
 
 



</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Advances to employed 
persons.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
advance of any nature (including advances for travelling allowance or conveyance 
allowance) shall not ordinarily exceed two calendar months’ wages of the 
employed person. In exceptional circumstances, the amount of such advance, may 
with the previous sanction of the Regional Labour Commissioner 

1[(Central)] 
concerned, be made to the extent of ten calendar months’ wages.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The advance may be 
recovered in instalments by deduction from wages of the employed person spread 
over not more than twelve months in the case of an ordinary advance and sixty 
months in the case of an advance granted in exceptional circumstances. In no 
case shall the amount of an instalment exceed one-fourth of the wages earned in 
a wage-period.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The amount of all 
advances sanctioned and repayments thereof shall be entered in a register in 
Form IX which shall be maintained up-to-date and kept at the establishment or as 
near to it as possible.
 
 



</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Loans for 
house-building and other purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A loan may be granted by the employer to an employed person for the purpose of,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  building a house or for 
effecting repairs in and extension of an existing house; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  purchase of a built house or of 
a plot for building a house; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the marriage of the employed 
person, his son or daughter; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  treatment of prolonged illness 
of the employed person or of a member of his family.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) A loan for the 
purposes specified in clause (a) of sub-rule (1), other than for the purposes of 
effecting repairs in an existing house and for the purposes of clauses (b) and 
(c) of the said sub-rule shall not exceed an amount equal to thirty-six calendar 
months’ wages of the employed person or ten thousand rupees whichever is less.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> For the purpose of 
effecting repairs to an existing house, the amount of loan shall not exceed 
three thousand rupees.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> The amount of loan 
for the purposes specified in clause (b) of sub-rule (1) shall not exceed a sum 
equivalent to four calendar months’ wages of the employed person or one thousand 
rupees whichever is less.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number> Interest on all such 
loans shall not exceed 6 per cent. per annum.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The amount of loans 
sanctioned under sub-rule (1) and repayments thereof together with interest 
thereon shall be entered in a register in Form X which shall be maintained 
up-to-date and kept at the establishment or as near to it as possible.
 


</section></article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Procedure, costs and 
court-fees.—The 
procedure to be followed by the authority and the court, the scales of costs 
which may be allowed in, and the amount of court-fees payable in respect of the 
proceedings before such authority or court, shall be such as may from time to 
time be determined by rules as made by the State Government under the Act in 
respect of the authority or the court concerned.
 
 
</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Abstracts.—The 
abstracts of the Act and the rules to be displayed under section 25 shall be as 
specified in Form XI and shall be in Hindi and in the language, if that be not 
Hindi, of the majority of the employed persons.
 
 
</article> 
 The Payment of 
Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Whoever being required under these rules to maintain any register or record or 
to furnish any information or return, fails to do so, or makes a false entry 
therein shall, for each such offence be punishable with fine which may extend to 
five hundred rupees; provided that an employer who maintains such registers and 
records, or furnishes the required return without making the necessary entries 
therein shall be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever contravenes 
the provisions of rules 11 and 12 shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
to two hundred rupees.
 
 
  
</section></article><form>
 

The Payment 
of Wages (Air Transport Services) Rules, 1968
 


 
 


Form XI
 


(See rule 20)
 


Abstract of the payment of wages Act, 1936 
and the Rules made thereunder
 


1. The Act applies to the payment of wages to 
persons employed in air transport services receiving less than Rs. 1600 a month.
 


2. No employed person can give up by 
contract, or agreement his rights under the Act.
 


Definition of wages
 


3. ‘Wages’ means all remuneration (whether by 
way of salary, allowances, or otherwise expressed in terms of money or capable 
of being so expressed which would, if the terms of employment, express or 
implied, were fulfilled, be payable to a person employed in respect of his 
employment or of work done in such employment and includes—
 


      (a)  any remuneration payable under any 
award or settlement between the parties or order of a Court;
 


      (b)  any remuneration to which the 
person employed is entitled in respect of overtime work or holidays or any leave 
period;
 


      (c)  any additional remuneration 
payable under the terms of employment (whether called a bonus or by any other 
name);
 


      (d)  any sum which by reason of the 
termination of employment of the person employed is payable under any law, 
contract or instrument which provides for the payment of such sum, whether with 
or without deductions, but does not provide for the time within which the 
payment is to be made;
 


      (e)  any sum to which the person 
employed is entitled under any scheme framed under any law for the time being in 
force, 
 


but does not includes,—
 


      (1)  any bonus (whether under a scheme 
of profit sharing or otherwise) which does not form part of the remuneration 
payable under the terms of employment or which is not payable under any award or 
settlement between the parties or order of a Court;
 


      (2)  the value of any 
house-accommodation, or of the supply of light, water, medical attendance or 
other amenity or of any service excluded from the computation of wages by a 
general or special order of the State Government;
 


      (3)  any contribution paid by the 
employer to any pension or provident fund, and the interest which may have 
accrued thereon;
 


      (4)  any travelling allowance or the 
value of any travelling concession;
 


      (5)  any sum paid to the employed 
person to defray special expenses entailed on him by the nature of his 
employment; or
 


      (6)  any gratuity payable on the 
termination of employment in cases other than those specified in sub-clause (d).
 


Responsibility for and method of payment
 


4. The employer is responsible for the 
payment under the Act of wages to persons employed under him, and any contractor 
employing persons is responsible for payment to the persons he employs.
 


5. Wage-periods shall be fixed for the 
payment of wages at intervals not exceeding one month.
 


6. Wages shall be paid on a working day 
within 7 days of the end of the wage-period (or within ten days if 1,000 or more 
persons are employed).
 


The wages of a person discharged shall be 
paid not later than the second working day after his discharge.
 


7. Payment in kind is prohibited.
 


Fines and Deductions
 


8. No deductions shall be made from wages 
except those authorised under the Act (See paragraphs 9-18 below).
 


9. (1) Fines can be imposed only for such 
acts and omissions as the employer may, with the previous approval of the 
Regional Labour Commissioner (Central), specify by a notice displayed at or near 
the entrance of the work-place or places at the establishment and after giving 
the employed person an opportunity for explanation.
 


(2) Fines,—
 


      (a)  shall not exceed three paise in 
the rupee;
 


      (b)  shall not be recovered by 
instalments, or later that sixty days of the date of imposition;
 


      (c)  shall be recorded in a register 
and applied to such purposes beneficial to the employed persons as are approved 
by the Inspector;
 


      (d)  shall not be imposed on employed 
persons who are under the age of fifteen years.
 


10. (a) Deductions for absence from duty can 
be made only on account of the absence of the employed person at times when he 
should be working and such deductions must not exceed an amount which is in the 
same proportion to his wages for the wage-period as the time he was absent in 
that period is to the total time he should have been at work.
 


(b) If ten or more employed persons, acting 
in concert, absent themselves without reasonable cause and without due notice, 
the deduction for absence can include wages for eight days in lieu of notice, 
but,—
 


       (i)  No deduction for breaking 
contract can be made from a person under 15 or a woman;
 


      (ii)  There must be a provision in 
writing which forms part of the contract of employment or the certified Standing 
Orders, requiring that a specific period of notice of intention to cease work 
not exceeding 15 days or the period of notice which the employer has to give to 
discharge a worker, must be given to the employer and that wages may be deducted 
in lieu of such notice;
 


     (iii)  The above provision must be 
displayed at or near the entrance of the work place or places at the 
establishment or work-place;
 


     (iv)  No deduction of this nature can be 
made until a week’s notice that this deduction is to be made has been posted at 
or near the main entrance of the work-place or places at the establishment or 
work-place;
 


      (v)  No deduction must exceed the wages 
of the employed person for the period by which the notice he gives of leaving 
employment, is less than the notice he should have given under his contract.
 


11. Deductions can be made for damage to or 
loss of goods expressly entrusted to an employed person or for loss of money for 
which he is required to account, where such damage or loss is due to his neglect 
or default.
 


Such deductions cannot exceed the amount of 
the damage or loss caused and can be made only after giving the employed persons 
an opportunity for explanation.
 


12. Deductions can be made, equivalent to the 
value thereof, for house accommodation supplied by the employer or by Government 
or any housing board set up under any law for time being in force (whether the 
Government or the board is the employer or not) or any other authority engaged 
in the business of subsidizing house accommodation which may be specified in 
this behalf by the Central Government, amenities and services (other than tools 
and raw materials) supplied by the employer: provided these are accepted by the 
employed person as a part of the terms of his employment and have in the case of 
amenities and services been authorised by order of the Central Government.
 


13. (a) Deductions can be made for the 
recovery of advance or for adjustment of over-payment of wages.
 


(b) Advances made before the employment began 
can only be recovered from the first payment of wages for a complete 
wage-period.
 


(c) Advances of whatever nature can be made 
at the employer’s discretion during the employment.
 


14. Deductions can be made for subscription 
to and for repayment of advances from any recognised provident fund.
 


15. Deductions can be made for payments to 
co-operative societies approved by the Central Government or to the Postal 
Insurance, subject to any conditions imposed by the State Government.
 


16. Deductions can be made for repayment of 
loans granted to the employed persons from funds constituted for welfare of 
labour.
 


17. Deductions can also be made for repayment 
of loans granted for house building and other purposes.
 


18. Deductions can also be made with the 
written authorisation of the person employed for payment of any premium on his 
life insurance policy to the Life Insurance Corporation of India or for the 
purchase of securities of the Government of India or of any State Government or 
for being deposited in any Post Office Savings Bank in furtherance of any 
savings scheme of any such Government.
 


19. Any loss of wages resulting from 
withholding of increment or promotion, reduction to a lower post or time-scale 
or to a lower stage in a time scale or suspension does not constitute deduction 
from wages within the meaning of the Act. For this purpose the rules framed by 
an employer in relation to his employees in the establishment for the purpose of 
any of the aforesaid penalties shall provide that—
 


       (i)  any such penalty as aforesaid, 
except the penalty of suspension, shall not be imposed unless the person 
concerned—
 


           (a)  has been informed of the 
charges in respect of which it is proposed to impose the penalty;
 


           (b)  has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of showing cause why the proposed penalty should not be imposed.
 


      (ii)  the person concerned is given a 
right of appeal against any order imposing the penalty.
 


Inspections
 


20. An Inspector can enter on any premises 
and can exercise the powers of inspection (including examination of documents 
and taking of evidence) as he may deem necessary for carrying out the purposes 
of the Act.
 


Complaints of Deductions or Delays
 


21. (a) Where irregular deductions are made 
from wages, or delays in payment take place, an employed person can make an 
application in the prescribed form within 12 months to the Authority appointed 
by the Central Government for the purpose. An application delayed beyond this 
period may be rejected unless sufficient cause for delay is shown.
 


(b) Any legal practitioner, official of a 
registered trade union, Inspector under the Act or other person acting with the 
authority can make the complaint on behalf of an employed person.
 


(c) A single application may be presented by 
or on behalf of any number of persons belonging to the same establishment the 
payment of whose wages has been delayed.
 


Action by the Authority
 


22. The Authority may award compensation to 
the employed person in addition to ordering the payment of delayed wages or the 
refund of illegal deductions.
 


If a malicious or vexatious complaint is 
made, the Authority may impose a penalty not exceeding Rs. 50 on the applicant 
and order that it be paid to the employer.
 


In a case in which compensation is directed 
to be paid under section 15 (3) the authority may direct that a penalty not 
exceeding fifty rupees be paid to the State Government by the employer or any 
other person responsible for the payment of wages.
 


Appeal against the Authority
 


23. An appeal against an order dismissing 
either wholly or in part an application or against a direction may be preferred 
within thirty days in Calcutta to the Chief Judge, Court of Small Causes and 
elsewhere to the District Court,—
 


      (a)  by the employer if the total 
amount directed to be paid exceeds Rs. 300;
 


      (b)  by an employed person or any legal 
practitioner or any official of a registered trade union authorised in writing 
to act on his behalf, or any Inspector under the Act or any other person 
permitted by the Authority to make an application, if the total amount of wages 
withheld from him exceeds Rs. 20 from unpaid group to which he belongs or 
belonged exceeds fifty rupees;
 


      (c)  by a person directed to pay a 
penalty for a malicious or vexatious application.
 


Punishments for breaches of the Act
 


24. Any one tried for delaying the payment of 
wages beyond the due date or making any unauthorised deduction from wages is 
liable to a fine upto Rs. 500 but only if prosecuted with the sanction of the 
Authority or the Appellate Court.
 


25. The employer who,—
 


      (1)  does not fix a wage-period, or
 


      (2)  makes payment in kind, or
 


      (3)  fails to display at or near the 
main entrance of the work-place or places at the establishment or work-place 
this abstract in English and in the language of the majority of the employed 
persons, or
 


      (4)  breaks certain rules made under 
the Act, 
 


is liable to fine not exceeding Rs. 200.
 


A complaint to this effect can be made only 
by the Inspector, or with his sanction.
 


 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>