<act><title>THE PROHIBITION OF SMOKING IN PUBLIC PLACES RULES, 
20081 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules 
may be called the Prohibition of Smoking in Public Places Rules, 2008. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the 2nd October, 2008.

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 <section><number>a</number> hotel shall mean a building or a part of a building where lodging, with 
or without board or other services, is provided by way of business for 
consideration monetary or otherwise and includes boarding house and guest house. 

 </section><section><number>b</number> restaurant shall mean any place to which the public has access and 
where any kind of food or drink is supplied for consumption on the premises by 
any person by way of business for consideration monetary or otherwise and shall 
include the open space surrounding such premises and includes: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> refreshment rooms, banquet halls, discotheques, canteen, coffee house, 
  pubs, bars, airport lounge, and the like. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>c</number> open space mentioned in section 3(1) of the Act shall not include any 
place visited by the public such as open auditorium, stadium, railway station, 
bus stop/stand and other such places. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> public place defined in section 3(1) of the Act shall also include work 
places, shopping malls, and cinema halls. 
 </section><section><number>e</number> smoking area or space mentioned in the proviso to section 4 of the Act 
shall mean a separately ventilated smoking room that: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> is physically separated and surrounded by full height walls on all four 
  sides; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> has an entrance with an automatically closing door normally kept in 
  close position; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> has an air flow system, as specified in Schedule I, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> has negative air pressure in comparison with the remainder of the 
  building. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>f</number> Words and expressions used herein and not defined in these rules but 
defined in the Act shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in 
the Act. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Prohibition of smoking in a public place. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The owner, 
proprietor, manager, supervisor or in charge of the affairs of a public place 
shall ensure that: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> No person smokes in the public place (under his jurisdiction/implied). 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The board as specified in Schedule II is displayed prominently at the 
  entrance of the public place, in case there are more than one entrance at each 
  such entrance and conspicuous place(s) inside. In case if there are more than 
  one floor, at each floor including the staircase and entrance to the lift/s at 
  each floor. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> No ashtrays, matches, lighters or other things designed to facilitate 
  smoking are provided in the public place. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The owner, proprietor, manager, supervisor or incharge of the affairs of 
a public place shall notify and cause to be displayed prominently the name of 
the person(s) to whom a complaint may be made by a person(s) who observes any 
person violating the provision of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the owner, proprietor, manager, supervisor or the authorized officer 
of a public place fails to act on report of such violation, the owner, 
proprietor, manager, supervisor or the authorized officer shall be liable to pay 
fine equivalent to the number of individual offences. 
 ( Explanation .For the purpose of these rules the word offence 
means a person found violating any provision of the rules). 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Hotels, Restaurants and Airports. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The owner, 
proprietor, manager, supervisor or in-charge of the affairs of a hotel having 
thirty or more rooms or restaurant having seating capacity of thirty persons or 
more and the manager of the airport may provide for a smoking area or space as 
defined in rule 2(e). 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Smoking area or space shall not be established at the entrance or exit of 
the hotel, restaurant and the airport and shall be distinctively marked as 
Smoking Area in English and one Indian language, as applicable. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A smoking area or space shall be used only for the purpose of smoking and 
no other service(s) shall be allowed. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The owner, proprietor, manager, supervisor or in-charge of the affairs of 
a hotel having thirty or more rooms may designate separate smoking rooms in the 
manner prescribed as under: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> all the rooms so designated shall form a separate section in the same 
  floor or wing, as the case may be. In case of more than one floors/wings the 
  room shall be in one floor/wing as the case may be. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> all such rooms shall be distinctively marked as Smoking rooms in 
  English and one Indian language, as applicable. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the smoke from such room shall be ventilated outside and does not 
  infiltrate/permeate into the non-smoking areas of the hotel including lobbies 
  and the corridors. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Recovery of fine by authorized officers. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
authorized officers mentioned in Schedule III shall be competent to act under 
and compound the offences committed in violation of section 4 of the Act. 

</section></article><form>
 

THE PROHIBITION OF SMOKING IN PUBLIC PLACES RULES, 
20081 
 

 
 

SCHEDULE 1 
 

[ See rule 2(e)(iii)] 
 

(i) That is exhausted directly to the outside and not mixed back into the 
supply air for the other parts of the building; and 
 

(ii) It is fitted with a non-re-circulating exhaust ventilation system or an 
air cleaning system, or by a combina­tion of the two, to ensure that the air 
discharges only in a manner that does not re-circulate or transfer it from a 
smoking area or space to non-smoking areas. 
 

--------------
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 417(E), dated 30th May, 2008, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 30th May, 
2008.</form><form>
 

THE PROHIBITION OF SMOKING IN PUBLIC PLACES RULES, 
20081
 

 
 

SCHEDULE II 
 

[ See rule 3(b)] 
 

1. The board shall be of a minimum size of 60 cm by 30 cm of white 
background. 
 

2. It shall contain a circle of no less than 15 cm outer diameter with a red 
perimeter of no less than 3 cm wide with a picture, in the centre, of a 
cigarette or beedi with black smoke and crossed by a red band. 
 

3. The width of the red band across the cigarette shall equal the width of 
the red perimeter. 
 

4. The board shall contain the warning No Smoking AreaSmoking Here is an 
Offence, in English or one Indian language, as applicable. 

 

------- 
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 417(E), dated 30th May, 2008, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 30th May, 2008. 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>