<act><tid>1663081</tid>
<title>FEDERAL COURT (ENLARGEMENT OF JURISDICTION) ACT, <year>1947</year></title>

ACT NO. 1 OF <year>1948</year> AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE ENLARGEMENT OF THE APPELLATE JU 
RISDIC- TION OF THE F
[ 5th January, <year>1948</year>.]

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the enlargement of the 
appellate jurisdiction of the Federal Court in civil cases It is 
hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>691246</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1492632</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Federal Court (Enlargement of Jurisdiction) Act, <year>1947</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1952735</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on the first day of February, <year>1948</year>, 
which day is hereinafter referred to as" the appointed day".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1799037</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,-
<section><tid>1846581</tid>
<number>a</number>" High Court" means any High Court to which the 
provisions of Chapter II of Part IX of the Government of 
India Act, <year>1935</year>, 1 apply; (25 and 26 Geo. 5, c. 2.)

</section>

<section><tid>1230423</tid>
<number>b</number>" judgment to which this Act applies" means any 
judgment, decree or final order of a High Court in a civil 
case from which a direct appeal could have been brought to 
His Majesty in Council, either with or without special leave, 
if this Act had not been passed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1141710</tid>
<number> 3</number> Enlargement of the Federal Court' s jurisdiction. As from the 
appointed day,-
<section><tid>604458</tid>
<number>a</number>an appeal shall lie to the Federal Court from any 
judgment to which this Act applies-

<subsection><tid>804890</tid>
<number>i</number>without the special leave of the Federal Court, if 
an appeal could have been brought to His Majesty in 
Council without special leave under the provisions of 
theCode (5 of <year>1908</year>) of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, or of 
any other law inforce immediately before the 
appointed day, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>790232</tid>
<number>ii</number>with the special leave of the Federal Court in any 
other case;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>682572</tid>
<number>b</number>in any such appeal as aforesaid it shall be competent for 
the Federal Court to consider any question of the nature 
mentioned in sub- section (1) of section 205 of the Government 
of India Act, <year>1935</year>; and (25 and 26 Geo. 5, c. 2.)

<pagefootnote><pagenum>92</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Now see Chapter V of Part VI of the Constitution of India.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1361271</tid>
<number>c</number>no direct appeal shall lie to His Majesty in Council, either 
with or without special leave, from any such judgment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>53498</tid>
<number>4</number>Continuance of certain proceedings in High Courts. All 
proceedings and steps taken in, and orders made and certificates 
granted by, a High Court in connection with an appeal to His Majesty 
in Council from a judgment to which this Act applies shall, unless the 
records pertaining to such appeal have before the appointed day been 
transmitted by the High Court concerned to His Majesty in Council, be 
deemed to be proceedings and steps taken, orders made, and 
certificates granted, in connection with an appeal from- that judgment 
to the Federal Court under this Act, and shall be concluded, or as the 
case may be, have effect, accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1447103</tid>
<number>5</number>Pending application for special leave to appeal. Every 
application to His Majesty in Council for special leave to appeal from 
a judgment to which this Act applies remaining undisposed of 
immediately before the appointed day shall on that day stand 
transferred to the Federal Court by virtue of this Act, and shall be 
disposed of by that Court as if it had been an application duly made 
to that Court for special leave to appeal from the said judgment.


</article>



<article><tid>113414</tid>
<number>6</number>Modification of existing laws. The provisions of the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>) and of any other law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to direct appeals in 
civil cases to His Majesty in Council shall, as from that day, have 
effect in relation to any appeal from a judgment to which this Act 
applies as if in the said provisions, for all references to His 
Majesty in Council, there had been substituted references to the 
Federal Court.


</article>



<article><tid>376730</tid>
<number> 7</number> Savings. The preceding provisions of this Act shall not 
apply to any appeal-
<section><tid>368277</tid>
<number>a</number>which immediately before the appointed day is pending 
before His Majesty in Council, if the records pertaining to 
such appeal have before that day been transmitted by the High 
Court concerned to His Majesty in Council; or

</section>

<section><tid>1665622</tid>
<number>b</number>to the bringing of which to His Majesty in Council 
special leave has- been granted before the appointed day;
and any such appeal may be disposed of by His Majesty in Council as if 
this Act had not been passed.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1812725</tid>
<number>8</number>Registrar' s certificate to be conclusive as to fact of 
transmisin of records. If any question arises under section 4 or 
section 7 whether the records pertaining to an appeal have before the 
appointed day been transmitted by the High Court concerned to His 
Majesty in Council a certificate of the Registrar of the High Court 
that they have been transmitted or not transmitted before the 
appointed day shall be conclusive evidence on the question.

</article>



 </act>