<act><title>


The Performing Animals (Registration) Rules, 20011</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Performing Animals (Registration) Rules, 2001.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
      
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals Act, 1960 (59 of 
1960); 
 </section><section>
      
<number>b</number>  “Board” means the Animal Welfare Board of India, established under 
section 4 and as reconstituted from time to time under section 5A of the Act;

 </section><section>
      
<number>c</number>  “film” means a cinematograph film as defined in the Cinematograph Act 
of 1952 (37 of 1952); 
 </section><section>
      
<number>d</number>  “fitness certificate” means a certificate granted by a veterinary 
doctor to be nominated by the prescribed authority certifying the health and 
fitness of the animal; 
 </section><section>
      
<number>e</number>  “owner' means the owner of an animal and includes any other person in 
possession or custody of such animal whether with or without the consent of the 
owner; 
 </section><section>
      
<number>f</number>  “ownership certificate” means a certificate granted under section 42 
of the Wildlife (Protection) Act, 1972 (53 of 1972); 
 



1[(g)  
“prescribed authority” means the Central Government, or such other authority 
including the Board or the State Government, as may be authorised by the Central 
Government;]
 </section><section>
      
<number>h</number>  “performing animal” means an animal which is used at or for the 
purpose of any entertainment including a film or an equine event to which the 
public are admitted; 
 </section><section>
       
<number>i</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to these rules; 
 </section><section>
      
<number>j</number>  “veterinary doctor” means a person registered with the Veterinary 
Council of India established under the Indian Veterinary Council Act, 1984 (52 
of 1984). 
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Application for 
registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person desirous of training or exhibiting a performing animal shall, within 
thirty days from the commencement of these rules, apply for registration to the 
prescribed authority and shall not exhibit or train any animal as a performing 
animal without being registered under these rules:
 

1[Provided that the 
race horses which have been registered by the owners with the Turf Authorities 
shall not, on intimation of such registration to the prescribed authority, 
require registration under this rule and the general conditions as specified in 
rule 8 shall apply to such registration subject to such other conditions as may 
be imposed by the prescribed authority.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person desirous of 
exhibiting or training any performing animal shall apply for registration in the 
form of application set out in the First Schedule. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every such application 
shall be made to the prescribed authority. 
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Fee and 
registration.—Every 
application for registration shall be accompanied by a fee of Rupees five 
hundred which may be paid either in cash or in such other manner as may be 
specified by the Board for this purpose. 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Power to call for 
additional information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The prescribed authority may call for such additional records and information as 
it may deem fit from the applicant in respect of the particulars furnished by 
it. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the prescribed 
authority is satisfied about the proposed performance and the method to be 
adopted for the training of such animals by the applicant it may grant 
registration.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The prescribed 
authority while granting registration may impose such other conditions, as it 
may deem appropriate for the training and upkeep of such performing animals.

</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Form of certificate 
of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The certificate of registration shall be issued by the prescribed authority in 
the form set out in the Second Schedule. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every registration 
shall be given a serial number in a order in which it is made, and it shall be 
indicated in the certificate of registration. 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Prior information 
for use of performing animals in films.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every owner desirous of hiringout or lending a performing animal in the making 
of a film shall give prior information in the format as specified by the 
prescribed authority for this purpose to specifying the kind of animal, age of 
animal, physical health of the animal, the nature of performance to be done by 
the animal, the duration for which the animal shall be used for such 
performance, the duration and method of training of the animal for such 
performance and justification for the use of such animals in the film and such 
other information as may be required by that authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such application 
shall be accompanied by a fitness certificate issued by a veterinary doctor 
certifying the health and fitness of the animal along with a ownership 
certificate in case of animals covered under the Wildlife (Protection) Act, 1972 
(53 of 1972). 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> General conditions 
for registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The prescribed authority while granting registration may impose such terms and 
conditions as it deems appropriate and 

1[may] impose the 
following conditions in granting registration, namely:—
 <subsection>
      
<number>i</number>  every owner who has ten or more such performing animals shall have a 
veterinarian as a regular employee for their care, treatment and transport;

 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>ii</number>  the owner shall not transport such animals by road continuously for 
more than 8 hours and except in cages admeasuring as specified in the Fifth 
Schedule; 
 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>iii</number>  the owner shall ensure proper watering and feeding halts during such 
transportation; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>iv</number>  
the owner after transportation shall provide feeding and retiring enclosures in 
respect of the animals specified in the Sixth Schedule; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>v</number>  
the owner shall ensure that any animal is not inflicted unnecessary pain or 
suffering before or during or after its training or exhibition; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>vi</number>  
the owner shall not deprive the animal of feed or water in order to compel the 
said animal to train or perform any trick; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>vii</number>  
the owner shall train an animal as a performing animal to perform an act in 
accordance with its basic natural instinct; 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>viii</number>  
the owner shall not make a performing animal perform if it is sick or injured or 
pregnant; 
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>ix</number>  
the owner shall ensure that no sudden loud noise is deliberately created within 
the vicinity of any performing animal or bring an animal close to fire which may 
frighten the animal; 
 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>x</number>  the owner in case the performing animal is to be exhibited under 
artificial light, the overall intensity of such light shall not be more than 500 
LUX; 
 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>xi</number>  the owner shall not subject the animals to any action which may 
either kill or injure or use the animal in scenes which may cause injury to the 
animals; 
 <subsubsection>
     
<number>xii</number>  the owner shall not use any tripping device or wires or pitfalls for 
such animals; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xiii</number>  
the owner shall not expose any animal to either burning fire or to fire 
accidents; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xiv</number>  
the owner shall not keep any animal including horses in close proximity while 
shooting scenes involving explosives or other loud noises; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xv</number>  
the owner shall ensure that props such as spears, nails, splinters, barbed wires 
or other such props shall not cause injury to the animals during performance;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>xvi</number>  
the owner shall ensure that the equines are not made to walk on hard surfaces 
without being shoed and shall further ensure that the animals are not used in 
downhill slides or rodeo slide stops without proper skid and hock boots; 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xvii</number>  
the owner of any equine shall not use any whip other than 

2[***] shock 
absorbing whip which has been scientifically tested to prove it will not cause 
weals, bruising or other damage to the horse and subject to the conditions that—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>a</number>   the whip shall not have raised binding, stitching, seam or flap;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>b</number>   the whip shall be used by licensed jockeys only;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>c</number>   the owner shall also ensure that the whip is not used other than 
either on the quarters in either the forehand or the backhand position or down 
the shoulder in the backhand position or use the whip with the arm above 
shoulder height;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>d</number>   the whip shall not be used more than 

3[eight times] in a 
race; 
 



4[(e)   
each horse immediately after the race and again after a period of six hours but 
within eight hours of the race shall be subject to the veterinary inspection to 
check for injuries;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>f</number>   the horses shall be housed in stables admeasuring 12ft X 12ft 
with adequate facility for the horses to see each other with adequate provision 
for proper ventilation and protection against heat, and an environmentally 
friendly atmosphere so far as possible:
 
                  
 Provided that if the whip is used more than eight times in a race, the 
prescribed authority in consultation with the Turf Authorities shall decide, if 
the use of such whip in excess of the number specified, was for any reason to 
save the horse or the jockey from any accident, for the purpose of initiating 
any action under the Act;]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
  <number>xviii</number>  the 
owner shall ensure that the animal is not used on floors that are very smooth 
without the use of non-skidding mats; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xix</number>  
the owner shall ensure that large gathering of animals is not allowed in such a 
way which may cause or result in stampede to the animals;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xx</number>  
the owner shall ensure that the animal is not made or incited to fight against 
other animals and shall further ensure that sedatives or tranquillisers or 
steroids or any other artificial enhancers are not administered to or inserted 
in any animal except the anaesthesia by a veterinary doctor for the purpose of 
treatment of an injured or sick animal 

4[and the use of 
steroids shall be avoided as far as possible provided the steroids may be used 
if no other option is available to be supported by a veterinary prescription and 
the purchase of such steroids shall be from a duly authorised sources]; 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
  <number>xxi</number>  the 
owner shall ensure that the animal shall not be transported or be kept or 
confined in cages and receptacles which do not measure in height, length or 
breadth as specified under the Transport of Animal Rules, 1978, the Recognition 
of Zoo Rules, 1992 or under any other Act, rule or order for this purpose;

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxii</number>  
the owner shall ensure that the animal is not continuously used for excessive 
number of takes in shooting a film without providing adequate rest to the animal 
and in the event of a snake being used it shall not be made to ingest any 
substances or made to crawl across tarred or any other heatened surface and 
shall not be contorted to wrestle; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>xxiii</number>  
the owner shall ensure that while using an animal in shooting a film, the fight 
sequence shall not be shot in any livestock holding area including poultry area 
and shall further ensure that no birds are shown in cages; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
  <number>xxiv</number>  the 
owner shall inform the prescribed authority at least four weeks in advance 
informing the place, date and time of the actual making of the film wherein the 
animal is to be used; 
 

5[(xxv)  
persons desirous of transporting horses from one place to another shall adhere 
to the following minimum norms to enhance conditions of travel as also safety of 
the horses, namely:—
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>a</number>   no horse shall be tied up in such a way that his head and neck 
movements are unnaturally restricted while travelling;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>b</number>   all horses must be watered at least every four hours and 
provided adequate ration of hay during the journey lasting more than eight 
hours;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>c</number>   adequate ventilation and free flow of fresh air in the vehicle 
shall be ensured during transport;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>d</number>   rubber mats shall preferably be used for flooring instead of 
straw bedding;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>e</number>   horses shall not be transported within twenty four hours of 
having raced;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>f</number>   no horse shall be raced, where the period of journey exceeds six 
hours, unless twenty four hours have elapsed since completion of the travel.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The prescribed 
authority may also impose such other conditions for the grant of registration as 
may be deemed appropriate to it for the welfare of animals. 
 
 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Register.—Every 
person to whom a certificate of registration is issued under these rules shall 
have his name entered in a register which shall be kept in the form set out in 
the Third Schedule.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Inspection of 
register.—The 
register kept for the purpose of these rules shall be open to inspection during 
office hours on any working day on payment of a fee of twenty rupees and any 
person may take extract therefrom or may require the prescribed authority to 
issue to him a certified copy of any entry made therein on payment of a fee of 
fifty rupees. 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Application for 
variation of entries in register.—Every 
application for the variation of any particular entered in the register 
maintained for the purpose of these rules shall be in the form set out in the 
Fourth Schedule and when any particular is varied the existing certificate of 
registration shall be cancelled and a new certificate be issued. 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Submission of 
report by veterinary doctor.—Every 
person who has been granted registration under these rules shall ensure that a 
monthly report of all the performing animals in the form to be specified by the 
prescribed authority in respect of their health, deaths and births duly 
certified by a veterinary doctor is submitted to the prescribed authority on or 
before the 7th of every succeeding month. 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Prohibition on 
exhibition and training of specified performing animals.—Performing 
animals whose performance has been prohibited under sub-section (2) of section 
22 of the Act shall not be trained or exhibited as a performing animal. 

</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Power to inspect.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The prescribed authority may depute an officer or authorise any other person, to 
inspect the mode of transport, care and upkeep of the animals, or to be present 
at the time of training or exhibition of the performing animals or during making 
of a film to ensure that the conditions of registration are being complied with.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The owner shall not 
obstruct the entry of such officer or authorised person and extend all possible 
assistance to enable him to discharge his duty. 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Report of 
inspection.—The 
officer deputed or person authorised under rule 14 shall after inspection submit 
a report to the prescribed authority about the compliance of the rules and the 
condition as specified by the prescribed authority. 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Cancellation of 
registration in respect of which registration has been granted.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every animal in respect of which registration has been granted under rule 5 
shall be exhibited and trained subject to the conditions of registration and 
these rules. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every animal in 
respect of which registration has been granted under rule 5 shall be exhibited 
for a film subject to the conditions of registration and these rules. 

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The prescribed 
authority in the event of breach of any of the conditions of registration under 
rule 5 or any provision of the Act or the rules made thereunder may suspend the 
registration pending enquiry and after granting an opportunity of hearing revoke 
the registration so granted or issue such orders or directions as it may 
consider proper for the welfare of the animals. 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Issue of duplicate 
copies of certificate.—Any 
person who has been granted registration under these rules may, on proof by him 
that the original certificate of registration has been lost or destroyed and on 
payment of a fee of one hundred rupees, be given a duplicate copy of the 
certificate of registration which for the purposes of these rules shall have the 
same effect as the original certificate of registration.
</article><form>
 




The Performing Animals (Registration) Rules, 2001
 


 
 




FOURTH SCHEDULE 
 




Form of Application for Variation of Particulars  

Entered In Register 
 


(See rule 11) 

 


 
 


Application to have the 
particulars entered in the register with respect to the applicant varied. 

 


To 
 


The prescribed authority,
 


Full Name of the applicant 
(in block letters) 
 


Number and date of 
Certificate of Registration 
 


I return herewith my 
certificate of registration under the Performing Animals (Registration) Rules, 
2000 and I hereby apply to have the particulars entered in the Register with 
respect to be varied as follows and the reasons given below: 
 


I also request that my 
existing certificate may be cancelled and a new certificate of registration may 
be issued to me. 
 


 
 



Signature............................ 
 



Address...............................
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Performing Animals (Registration) Rules, 2001
 


 
 




FIFTH SCHEDULE 
 




Suggestive Size of Cages for Transportation 
 


[See rule 8 (ii)]
 


 


Species                                                  
  Length (m)                       
  Breadth (m)                        
  Height (m)
 


 


Slender loris                                           
  0.40                                 
  0.25                                   
  0.35
 


Slow loris                                               
  0.60                                 
  0.25                                   
  0.45
 


Horse (domestic/wild)                            
  3.00                                 
  1.00                                   
  1.75
 


Ass (domestic/wild)                                
  2.25                                 
  .80                                     
  1.28
 


Zebra                                                     
  2.60                                 
  .95                                     
  1.80
 


Elephant (Adult)                                     
  4.80                                 
  2.40                                   
  2.84
 


Hippopotamus (Common)                      
  4.06                                 
  2.10                                   
  1.50
 


Pigmy Hippo                                           
  1.52                                 
  1.00                                   
  0.74
 


Civet                                                      
  0.79                                 
  .40                                     
  0.38
 


Mongoose                                              
  0.56                                 
  .25                                     
  0.13
 


Duck                                                       
  0.38 to 0.63                     
  22-0.35                              
  78
 


Dove                                                      
  0.46                                 
  0.20                                   
  0.21
</form><form>
 




The Performing Animals (Registration) Rules, 2001
 


 
 




SIXTH SCHEDULE 
 




Minimum prescribed size for feeding/retiring cubicle/enclosures for Important
 

mammalian species of captive animals 
 


[See rule 8(iv)]
 


 


Name of the Species                                                                                     
  Size of the cubicle/enclosures in meters
 


 


Family – Felidae                                                                                              
  Length              
  Breadth         Height
 


Leopard                                                                                                               
  2.00                  
  1.50               
  2.00
 


Small cats                                                                                                            
  1.80                  
  1.50               
  1.50
 


Family – Elephantidae
 


Elephant                                                                                                               
  8.0                    
  6.0                 
  5.5
 


Family – 
  Rhinocerotidae
 


One-horned Indian 
  Rhinoceros                                                                             
  5.0                    
  3.0                 
  2.5
 


Family – Carvidae
 


Brow antlered deer                                                                                               
  3.0                     
  2.0                 
  2.5
 


Hangul                                                                                                                  
  3.0                     
  2.0                 
  2.5
 


Swamp deer                                                                                                         
  3.0                     
  2.0                 
  2.5
 


Musk deer                                                                                                             
  2.5                     
  1.5                 
  2.0
 


Mouse deer                                                                                                           
  1.5                     
  1.0                 
  1.5
 


Family – Bovidae
 


Nilgiri tahr                                                                                                             
  2.5                     
  1.5                 
  2.0
 


Chinkara                                                                                                               
  2.5                     
  1.5                 
  2.0
 


Four horned antelope                                                                                           
  2.5                     
  1.5                 
  2.0
 


Wild Burrialo                                                                                                          
  3.0                    
  1.5                 
  2.0
 


Indian Bison                                                                                                          
  3.0                   
   2.0                 
  2.5
 


Yak                                                                                                                        
  4.0                    
  2.0                 
  2.5
 


Bharal, goral, wild sheep 
  and markhor                                                                 
  2.5                    
  1.5                 
  2.0
 


Family – Equidae
 


Horses                                                                                                                  
  6.0                    
  4.0                 
  3.0
 


Wild Ass                                                                                                                
  4.0                    
  2.0                 
  2.5
 


Family - Canidae
 


Jackal, wolf and wild dog                                                                                       
  2.0                    
  1.5                 
  1.5
 


Family – Vivirridae
 


Palm Civet                                                                                                             
  2.0                    
  1.0                 
  1.0
 


Large Indian civet &amp; 
  binturong                                                                              
  2.0                    
  1.5                 
  1.0
 


Family – Mustellidae
 


Otters all types                                                                                                     
  2.5                    
  1.5                 
  1.0
 


Rate/Hogbadger                                                                                                   
  2.5                    
  1.5                 
  1.0
 


Martens                                                                                                                 
  2.0                   1.5                 
  1.0
 


Family – Procyonidae
 


Red Panda                                                                                                            
  3.0                    
  1.5                 
  1.0
 


Family – Lorisidae
 


Slow loris and slender 
  loris                                                                                   
  1.0                    
  1.0                 
  1.5
 


 
 


 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>