<act><title>


THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF 
EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE) 
CENTRAL RULES, 19801</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Inter-State Migrant Workmen (Regulation of 
Employment and Conditions of Service) Central Rules, 1980.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force from the Second day of October, 1980.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules unless the subject or context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> “Act” means 
the Inter-State Migrant Workmen (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of 
Service) Act, 1979;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number> “Appellate 
Officer” means an appellate officer nominated by the Central Government under 
section 11;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number> “Deputy Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central)” means an officer as such appointed by the Central 
Government;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  “Form” means 
a form appended to these rules; 
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number> “Inspector” 
means an Inspector appointed by the Central Government under section 20;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number> “Licensing 
Officer” means the licensing officer appointed by the Central Government under 
section 7;
 </section><section>
         <number>g</number> “migrant 
workman” means an inter-State migrant workman as defined in section 2;
 </section><section>
         <number>h</number> “registering 
officer” means a registering officer appointed by the Central Government under 
section 3;
 </section><section>
          <number>i</number> “section” 
means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
          <number>j</number> “specified 
authority” means the authority specified by the Central Government for the 
purposes of sections 12 and 16; and 
 </section><section>
         <number>k</number> all other 
words and expressions used in these rules but not defined therein shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Manner of making application 
for registration of establishment.—
<section><number>1</number> The application for 
registration of an establishment shall be made in triplicate in Form I to the 
registering officer of the area in which the establishment sought to be 
registered is located.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application shall be 
accompanied by a crossed demand draft showing payment of the fees for the 
registration of the establishment.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The application shall be 
either personally delivered to the registering officer or sent to him by 
registered post.
 </section><section><number>4</number> On receipt of the application, 
the registering officer shall, after noting thereon the date of receipt by him 
of the application, give an acknowledgment to the 
applicant.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Manner of making 
application for registration of establishment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The application for registration of an establishment shall be made in triplicate 
in Form I to the registering officer of the area in which the establishment 
sought to be registered is located.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application shall 
be accompanied by a crossed demand draft showing payment of the fees for the 
registration of the establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application shall 
be either personally delivered to the registering officer or sent to him by 
registered post.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the 
application, the registering officer shall, after noting thereon the date of 
receipt by him of the application, give an acknowledgment to the applicant.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Issue of certificate 
of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the registering officer registers of establishment, he shall issue to the 
principal employer a certificate of registration in Form II.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The registering 
officer shall maintain a register in Form III showing the particulars of the 
establishment in relation to which certificates of registration are issued by 
him..
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, in relation to an 
establishment, there is any change in the particulars specified in the 
certificate of registration, the principal employer of the establishment shall 
intimate to the registration officer, within thirty days from the date when such 
change takes place the particulars of, and the reasons for, such change.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Circumstances in which 
applicants for registration may be rejected.—
<section><number>1</number> If any application for 
registration is not complete in all respects, the registering officer shall 
require the principal employer to amend the application so as to make it 
complete in all respects.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the principal employer, on 
being required by registering officer to amend his application for registration 
omits or fails to do so, the registering officer shall reject the application 
for registration.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Circumstances in 
which applicants for registration may be rejected.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any application for registration is not complete in all respects, the 
registering officer shall require the principal employer to amend the 
application so as to make it complete in all respects.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the principal 
employer, on being required by registering officer to amend his application for 
registration omits or fails to do so, the registering officer shall reject the 
application for registration.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Amendment of 
certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where on receipt of the intimation under sub-rule (3) of rule 4, the registering 
officer is satisfied that an amount higher than the amount, which has been paid 
by the principal employer as fees for the registration of the establishment is 
payable, he shall require such principal employer to deposit a sum which, 
together with the amount already paid by such principal employer , would be 
equal to such higher amount of fees payable for the registration of the 
establishment and to produce showing such deposit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where, on receipt of 
the intimation referred to in 

1[sub-rule (3)] 
rule 4, the registering officer is satisfied that there has occurred a change in 
the particulars of the establishment, as entered in the register in Form III, he 
shall amend the said register and record therein the change thus occurred:
 
Provided that no such 
amendment shall affect anything done or any action taken or any right, 
obligation or liability acquired or incurred before such amendment:
 
Provided further that the 
registering officer shall not carry out any amendment in the register in Form 
III unless the appropriate fees have been deposited by the principal employer.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Application for a 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application by a contractor for the grant of a licence for recruiting a 
person under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of section 8 shall be made in 
triplicate in Form IV to the licensing having jurisdiction in relation to the 
area wherein the recruitment is made.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application by a 
contractor for employing a migrant workman under clause (b) of sub-section (1) 
of section 8 shall be made in Form V to the licensing officer having 
jurisdiction in relation to the area wherein the establishment is situated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) Every application 
for the grant of a licenced under sub-rule (1), or sub-rule (2) shall be 
accompanied by a certificate of the principal employer in Form IV to the effect 
that he undertakes to be bound by all the provisions of the Act and the rules 
made thereunder so far as they are applicable to him in respect of the 
recruitment or employment of the migrant workmen, in respect of which the 
contractor is making the application.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Every such 
application shall be either personally delivered to the licensing officer 
concerned or sent to him by registered post.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the 
application referred to in sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2), the licensing officer 
concerned shall, after noting thereon the date of receipt of the application, 
grant an acknowledgment to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every application 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall also be accompanied by the receipt obtained as 
required by rule 20.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Matters to be taken into 
account in granting or refusing a licence.—In granting or refusing to grant 
a licence the licensing officer shall take the following matters into account, 
namely:—
 <section>         
<number>a</number> Whether the applicant—
 <subsection>               
<number>i</number> is a minor, or 
 </subsection><subsection>              
<number>ii</number> is a unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court, 
or
 </subsection><subsection>             
<number>iii</number> is an undischarged insolvent, or 
 </subsection><subsection>             
<number>iv</number> has been convicted at any time during the period of five years immediately 
preceding the date of application, of an offence which, in the opinion of the 
Central Government involves moral turpitude;
 </subsection></section><section>         
<number>b</number> whether any order had been made in respect of the applicant under 
sub-section (1) of section 10, and, if so, whether a period of three years has 
elapsed from the date of that order;
 </section><section>         
<number>c</number> whether the fees for the application has been deposited at the rates 
specified in rule 12; and
 </section><section>         
<number>d</number> whether security, wherever necessary, has been deposited by the applicant at 
the rates specified in sub-rule (1) of rule 10.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Matters to be taken 
into account in granting or refusing a licence.—In 
granting or refusing to grant a licence the licensing officer shall take the 
following matters into account, namely:—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> Whether the 
applicant—
 <subsection>
               <number>i</number> is a 
minor, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>ii</number> is a 
unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court, or
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number> is an 
undischarged insolvent, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iv</number> has been 
convicted at any time during the period of five years immediately preceding the 
date of application, of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
Government involves moral turpitude;
 </subsection></section><section>
         <number>b</number> whether any 
order had been made in respect of the applicant under sub-section (1) of section 
10, and, if so, whether a period of three years has elapsed from the date of 
that order;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number> whether the 
fees for the application has been deposited at the rates specified in rule 12; 
and
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number> whether 
security, wherever necessary, has been deposited by the applicant at the rates 
specified in sub-rule (1) of rule 10.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Refusal to the issue 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> On 
receipt of the application from the contractor, and as soon as possible 
thereafter, the licensing officer shall investigate or cause investigation to be 
made to satisfy himself about the correctness of the facts and particulars 
furnished in such application and the eligibility of the applicant for a licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) Where the 
licensing officer is of the opinion that the licence should not be issued, he 
shall, after affording reasonable opportunity to the applicant to be heard, make 
an order rejecting the application.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The order shall 
record the reason for the refusal and shall be communicated to the applicant.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Security.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the licensing officer is satisfied that any person who has applied for or 
who has been issued a licence should furnish security for the due performance of 
the conditions of the licence, he shall prepare an estimate of all the amounts 
needed to provide for recruitment or employment of migrant workmen on the basis 
of the following factors, namely:—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number> Wages 
equivalent to one wage period payable under clause (v) of sub-rule (2) of rule 
11, read with rule 25.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number> Provision of 
medical facilities under rule 37,
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number> Provision 
of protective clothing under rule 38, wherever applicable,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number> Provision of 
drinking water, latrines, urinals, and washing facilities under rule 39 read 
with rules 42 and 43,
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>v</number> Provision of 
rests rooms under rule 40, wherever applicable,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vi</number> Provision of 
canteens under rule 41, wherever applicable ,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vii</number> Provision of 
creche under rule 44, wherever applicable,
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>viii</number>  Provision 
of residential accommodation under rule 45,
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ix</number> Journey 
allowance under section 15,
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>x</number> Number of 
migrant workmen employed or recruited, and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>xi</number> Duration of 
work.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The licensing officer 
shall determine the amount of the security to be furnished by such person, after 
considering the solvency of such a person, not exceeding 40 percent of the 
amount estimated by him in accordance with sub-rule (1) above]
 

2[(3)] Where the 
applicant for licence was holding a licence in regard to another work and that 
licence had expired, the licensing officer, if he is of the view that any amount 
out of the security, if any deposited in respect of that licence is to be 
refunded to the applicant under rule 17, he may on an application made for the 
purpose in Form VII by the applicant adjust the amount so to be refunded towards 
the security, if any, required to be deposited in respect of the application for 
the new licence and the applicant need deposit, in such a case, only the balance 
amount if any, after making such adjustment.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Forms and terms and 
conditions of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every licence under sub-section (1) of section 8 shall be in Form VIII.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every licence granted 
under sub-rule (1) or renewed under rule 15 be subject to the following 
conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number> the licence 
shall be non-transferable;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number> the terms 
and conditions of the agreement or arrangement or the arrangement under which 
the migrant workman is recruited or employed;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number> the number 
of migrant workmen recruited or employed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number> the number of 
workmen recruited or employed as migrant workmen in the establishment shall not, 
on any day, exceed the maximum number specified in conditions (iii);
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>v</number> the rates of 
wages payable to the migrant workmen by the contractor shall not be less than 
the rates prescribed under the Minimum Wages Act, 1984, for such employment and 
where the rates have been fixed by the agreement, settlement or award, not less 
than the rates so fixed;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>vi</number> save as 
provided in these Rules the fees paid for the issue, or as the case may be, for 
renewal of licence shall be non-refundable;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>vii</number> (a) in cases 
where the migrant workmen recruited or employed by the contractor perform the 
same or similar kind of work as the workmen directly employed by the Principal 
Employer of the establishment, the wage rates, holidays, hours of work and other 
conditions of service of the migrant workmen of the contractor shall be the same 
as applicable to the workmen directly employed by the Principal Employer of the 
establishment on the same or similar kind of work:
 
                      
Provided that in the case of any disagreement with regard to the type of work, 
the same shall be decided by the Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central)


1[***];
 <subsubsection>
              <number>b</number> in other 
cases, the wage rates, holidays, hours of work and conditions of service of the 
migrant workmen recruited or employed by the contractor shall be such as 
prescribed in these Rules;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
       <number>viii</number>  every 
migrant workman shall be entitled to allowances, benefits, facilities, etc., 
as prescribed in the Act and the Rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ix</number> no female 
migrant workman shall be employed by any contractor before 6 A.M. or after 7 
P.M.:
 
                 Provided 
that this clauses shall not apply to the employment of female migrant workmen in 
Pit head Baths, Creches and canteens and Midwives and Nurses in hospitals and 
dispensaries;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>x</number> the 
contractor shall notify any change in the number of migrant workmen or the 
conditions of work to the licensing officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>xi</number> the 
contractor shall comply with all the provisions of the Act and the Rules;
 <subsubsection>
        <number>xii</number>  a copy of 
the licence shall be displayed prominently at the premises where the migrant 
workmen are employed;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>xiii</number>  the period 
for which the licence shall be valid;
 

       2[(xiv)  any 
change in the number of migrant workmen shall be notified to the licensing 
officer within seven days of this change.]
 
 




</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>12</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fees to be paid for the grant of certificate of registration of an 
establishment under section 7, shall be as specified below:—
 
If the number of migrant 
workmen proposed to be employed in the establishments on any day.
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> is 5 and not 
exceeding 20                           .         .           .           Rs.        60
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> exceeding 20 
and upto 50                           .         .           .           Rs.       150 

 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number> exceeding 50 
and upto 100                         .         .           .           Rs.       300
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number> exceeding 100 
and upto 200                       .         .           .           Rs.       600
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number> exceeding 200 
and upto 400                       .         .           .           Rs.    1,200
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number> exceeding 
400                                          .         .           .           Rs.    1,500
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The fees to be paid 
for grant of licence under section 7 shall be as specified below:—
 
If the number of workmen 
employed by the contractor on any day—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> is 5 and not 
exceeding 20                           .         .           .           Rs.     15
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> exceeding 20 
and upto 50                           .         .           .           Rs.     40
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number> exceeding 50 
and upto 100                         .         .           .           Rs.     80
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number> exceeding 100 
and upto 200                       .         .           .           Rs.    150
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number> exceeding 200 
and upto 400                       .         .           .           Rs.    300
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number> exceeding 
400                                          .         .           .           Rs.    400].
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Amendment of the 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
licence issued under rule 11 or renewed under rule 15 may, for good and 
sufficient reasons be amended by the licensing officer. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The contractor who 
desires to have to licence amended shall submit to the licensing officer an 
application stating the nature of amendment and reasons therefor.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) If the licensing 
officer allows the application he shall require the applicant to furnish a 
crossed demand draft for the amount if any, by which the fees that would have 
been payable if the licence had been originally issued in the amended form 
exceeds the fee originally paid for the licence;
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> on the applicant 
furnishing the requisite receipt, the licence shall be amended according to the 
orders of the licensing officer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the application 
for amendment is refused, the licensing officer shall record the reasons for 
such refusal and communicate the same to the applicant.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every contractor may apply to the licensing officer for renewal of the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application shall 
be in Form IX in triplicate and shall be made not less than thirty days before 
the date on which the licence expires, and if the application is so made the 
licence shall be deemed to have been renewed until such date when the renewed 
licence is issued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The fees chargeable 
for renewal of the licence shall be same as for the grant thereof:
 
Provided that if the 
application for renewal is not received within the time specified in sub-rule 
(2), a fee of twenty five per-cent. in excess of the fee ordinarily payable for 
the licence shall be payable for such renewal:
 
Provided further that in 
case where the licensing officer is satisfied that the delay in submission of 
the application is due to unavoidable circumstances beyond the control of the 
contractor, he may reduce or remit as he deems fit the payment of such excess 
fee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Period of renewal 
of the licence.—Every 
licence renewed under this rule 15 remain in force for a further period of 
twelve shall from the date of the order of renewal. 
</article> 

  
 <article><number>16</number> Issue of duplicate certificate 
of registration or licence.—Where a certificate of 
registration or licence granted or renewed under the preceding rules has been 
lost, defaced or accidentally destroyed, a duplicate thereof may be granted on 
payment of fees of 1[Rs. 20.00].
  


</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Issue of duplicate 
certificate of registration or licence.—Where 
a certificate of registration or licence granted or renewed under the preceding 
rules has been lost, defaced or accidentally destroyed, a duplicate thereof may 
be granted on payment of fees of 

1[Rs. 20.00].
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Refund of security.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) On expiry of the period of licence the contractor may, if he does not intent 
to have his licence renewed or get the security amount adjusted in respect of 
his fresh application for licence in terms of sub-rule (2) of rule 10, make an 
application to the licensing officer for the refund of the security, if any, 
deposited by him under rule 10.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> If the licensing 
officer is satisfied that there is no breach of the conditions of licence or 
there is no order under section 10 for the forfeiture of security or any portion 
thereof, he shall direct the refund of the security to the applicant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If there is any order 
directing the forfeiture of the whole or any part of the security, the amount to 
be forfeited shall be deducted from the security deposit, and balance, if any, 
shall be refunded to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application for 
refund shall as far as possible, be disposed of within sixty days of the receipt 
of the application.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Appeals and 
procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) Every appeal under section 11 shall be prepared in the form of a memorandum 
signed by the appellant or his authorised agent and presented to the appellate 
officer in person or sent to him by registered post.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The memorandum shall 
be accompanied by a certified copy of the order and a crossed demand draft for 
Rs. 25/.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The memorandum shall 
set forth precisely and under distinct heads the grounds of appeal to the order 
appealed from.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the memorandum 
of appeal does not comply with the provision of sub-rule (2) it may be rejected 
or returned to the appellant for the purpose of being amended within a time to 
be fixed by the appellate officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the appellate 
officer rejects the memorandum of appeal under sub-rule (3), he shall record the 
reasons, for such rejection and communicate the same to the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the memorandum 
of appeal is in order, the appellate officer shall admit the appeal, endorse 
thereon the date of presentation and shall register the appeal in the register 
of appeals kept for the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> (i) When the appeal 
has been admitted, the appellate officer shall send a notice to the registering 
officer or the licensing officer, as the case may be, from whose order the 
appeal has been preferred. The registering officer or as the case may be, the 
licensing officer shall thereupon send the record of the case to the appellate 
officer.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> On receipt of the 
record the appellate officer shall send a notice to the appellant to appear 
before him on such date and time as may be specified in the notice for the 
hearing of the appeal.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> If on the date fixed 
for the hearing, the appellant does not appear the appellate officer may dismiss 
the appeal for default of appearance of the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> (i) Where an appeal 
has been dismissed under sub- rule (7), the appellant may apply to the appellate 
officer for re-admission of the appeal, and where it is proved that he was 
prevented by any sufficient cause from appearing when appeal was called on for 
hearing, the appellate officer shall restore the appeal on its original number.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> An application under 
clause (i) shall, unless the appellate officer extend the time for sufficient 
reason, be made within thirty days of the date of dismissal.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>9</number> (i) If the appellant 
is present when the appeal is called on for hearing, the appellate officer shall 
proceed to hear the appellant or his authorised agent and nay other person 
summoned by him for the purpose, and pronounce judgment on the appeal either 
confirming reversing or modifying the order appealed from.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The judgement of the 
appellate officer shall state the points for determination, decisions thereon 
the reasons for the decisions.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> The order shall be 
communicated to the appellant and a copy thereof shall be sent to the 
registering officer or the licensing officer, as the case may be, from whose 
order the appeal has been preferred.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Obtaining of copies 
of orders.—A 
copy of the order of the registering officer, licensing officer or appellate 
officer may be obtained on payment of fees of 

1[Rs. 500] per copy 
of each order on application specifying the date and other particulars of the 
order, made to the officer concerned.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Payment of fees and 
security deposits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The payment of the various fees relating to registration, licensing and security 
deposits shall be made through a crossed Demand Draft drawn in favour of the 
concerned departmental officer and payable at the station at which he is 
stationed along with a Treasury Challan duly filled in dictating the relevant 
head of account creditable to the accounts of the concerned Pay and Accounts 
Office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The heads of accounts 
under which the receipt relating to the fees for registration, licensing and 
appeals, etc., shall be credited will be “B-Non-Tax Revenue-087 Labour 
and Employment—Receipts under the Inter-State Migrant Workmen (Regulations and 
Conditions of Service) Central Rules, 1980”. The Security Deposits are to be 
booked under the head “Deposits Advances—(b) Deposits not bearing 
interest—843—Civil-Deposits-Security Deposits.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Particulars of 
migrant workman.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every contractor shall furnish to the specified authorities the particulars 
regarding recruiting and employment of migrant workmen in Form X.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The particulars shall 
be either personally delivered by the contractor to the concerned specified 
authorities or sent to them by registered post.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Return fare.—The 
contractor shall pay to the migrant workman the return fare from the place of 
employment to the place of residence in the home-state of the migrant workman on 
the expiry of the period of employment and also on his—
 <section>
         <number>a</number> termination 
of service before the expiry of the period of employment for any reason 
whatsoever;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number> being 
incapacitated for further employments on accounts of injury or continued 
ill-health duly certified as such by a registered medical practitioner;]
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number> cessation of 
work in the establishments which is not due to any fault on the part of the 
migrant workman; and 
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number> resignation 
from service on account of non-fulfilment of terms and conditions of his 
employment by the contractor.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Pass Book.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the pass book referred to in clause (4) sub-section (1) of section 12, the 
following additional particulars shall be indicated namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> the date of 
recruitment;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> the date of 
employment;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number> total 
attendance/unit of work done (in respect of piece-rated migrant workman) total 
wages earned deductions if any 
made/net amount paid the signature of contractor or his duly authorised 
representative with date; and (These entries shall be made separately in respect 
of each wage period within three days from the date of payment.)
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number> name and 
address of the next of kinds of migrant workman.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In case of fatal 
accident of serious bodily injury to any migrant workman, the contractor shall 
immediately send telegrams to the specified authorities of both the States and 
also the next of the kins of the migrant workman intimating death or the nature 
of serious bodily injury sustained by the migrant workman, as the case may be, 
date, place and nature of accident. The contractor shall further send written 
report to the specified authorities concerned and the next of the kins of the 
migrant workman, undermentioned particulars by registered post within 24 hours 
of the occurrence of the accident:—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number> Name of the 
migrant workman;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number> Date, of 
place and nature of accident;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number> Condition 
of the migrant workman (if alive);
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number> Action taken 
by the contractor/ principal employer;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>v</number> Remarks.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> If the contractor 
fails to send the telegraphic intimation and/or written report as required under 
sub-rule (2), the principal employer shall comply with the requirements of sub-rule (2) as early as possible but in any case not later than 48 hours of the 
time of occurrence of the accident.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Return and Report.—Every 
contractor shall furnish a return regarding migrant workman who have ceased to 
be employed in Form X I to the specified authorities concerned either personally 
or by registered post so a to reach them to not later than 15 days from the date 
of migrant workman ceases to be employed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Rate of wages.—The 
rate of wages of a migrant workman in an establishments where he is a required 
to work which is neither same nor or similar kind as is being performed by any 
other workman in that establishment shall not be less than the rate of wages 
paid by the principal employer to a workman in the lowest category of workmen 
directly employed by him in that establishment or the minimum rates of wages 
notified by the Central Government under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 for the 
same or similar type of work performed by workmen in any scheduled employment in 
the area in which the establishment is located, or the rates of wages payable to 
the workmen for performing same or similar kind of work in that establishment in 
the State in which the establishment is located, whichever is higher.:
 
Provided that if there is 
any dispute is this regard or with regard to applicability of wage rate to a 
migrant workman under sub-clause (b) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 13, the same 
shall be decided by the Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) 

1[***].
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Wage-period.—The 
contractor shall fix wage periods in respect of which wages shall be payable.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
No wage period shall exceed one month.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Payment of wages.—The 
wages of every migrant workman in an establishment by a contractor where less 
than 1000 workmen are employed shall be paid before the expiry of the seventh 
day and in other cases before the expiry of tenth day every month.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Payment on 
termination.—Where 
the employment of any migrant workman is terminated by or on behalf of the 
contractor, the wages earned by the migrant workman shall be paid before the 
expiry of the second working day from the day on which his employment is 
terminated.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Mode of payment.—All 
payments of wages shall be made by the contractor on working day at the work 
premises and during the working time and on a date notified in advance and in 
case the work is completed before the expiry of final payments, shall be made 
within forty-eight hours of the last working day.
</article> 

  
 <article>31. Wages due to every migrant 
working, shall be paid to him direct or to other persons duly authorised by him 
in the behalf.</article> 

  
 <article><number>32</number> All wages shall be paid in 
current coin or in currency or in both. Wages shall be paid without any 
deduction of any kind except those specified by the Central Government by 
general or special order in this behalf or permissible under the Payment of 
Wages Act, 1936.</article> 

  
 <article><number>33</number> A notice showing the wages period 
and the place and time of disbursement of wages shall be displayed at the place 
of work and a copy sent by the Contractor to the Principal Employer under 
acknowledgment.</article> 

  
 <article><number>34</number> The principal employer shall 
ensure the presence of his authorised representative at the place and time of 
disbursement of wages by the contractor to the migrant workman; and it shall be 
the duty of the contractor to ensure the disbursement of wages in the presence 
of such authorised representative.</article> 

  
 <article>35. The authorised representative of 
the principal employer shall order under his signature a certificate at the end 
of all the entries in the register of wages or the wages-cum- muster roll, as 
the case may, be in the following form:—
               
“Certified that the amount shown in Column No. has been made to the migrant 
workman concerned to in my presence on..........."</article> 

  
 <article><number>36</number> Holidays hours of work and 
other conditions of service.—
<section><number>1</number> Holidays, hours of work 
including extra wages for overtime work done and other conditions of service of 
migrant workman shall not be less favourable than those obtaining in that 
establishment or in similar employment in the area in which the establishment is 
located, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where there is any dispute in 
this regard or with regard to applicability of holidays hours of work including 
extra wages for overtime work done and other conditions of service to a migrant 
workman under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 13, the same shall be 
decided by the Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) 1[***].
  


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> Holidays hours of 
work and other conditions of service.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Holidays, hours of work including extra wages for overtime work done and other 
conditions of service of migrant workman shall not be less favourable than those 
obtaining in that establishment or in similar employment in the area in which 
the establishment is located, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where there is any 
dispute in this regard or with regard to applicability of holidays hours of work 
including extra wages for overtime work done and other conditions of service to 
a migrant workman under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 13, the same 
shall be decided by the Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) 

1[***].
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Medical facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The contractor shall ensure provision of suitable and adequate medical 
facilities for outdoor treatment to the migrant workman free of cost for 
treatment of any ailment from which the migrant workman or any member of his 
family may suffer during his employment in the establishment or to meet any 
preventive measure against epidemic or any virus infection. Whenever any 
medicine is purchased by a migrant workman from market on the basis of the 
prescription issued by any Doctor provided by the contractor or the principal 
employer, as the case may be, or any registered medical practitioner, the cost 
of such medicine 

1[including the fee 
upto Rs. 10 per consultation], shall be reimbursed by the contractor to the 
migrant workman concerned within a period of seven days from the date of 
presentation of the bill by the migrant workman.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the event of 
migrant workman or any of his family members suffering from any ailment 
requiring hospitalisation during his employment in the establishment, the 
contractor shall promptly arrange for the hospitalisation of the migrant workman 
or the concerned member of his family. The contractor shall bear entire expenses 
on treatment, hospital charges (including diet), if any, and travel expenses for 
the patient from the place of his/her residence to the hospital and back.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every contractor shall 
provide and maintain so as to be readily accessible during all working hours 
first-aid boxes at the rate of not less than one box for one hundred and fifty 
workmen or part thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The first-aid box 
shall be distinctly marked with a Red Cross on a white ground and shall contain 
the following equipment, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> for the 
establishments in which number of migrant workmen employed does not exceed 
fifty, each first-aid box shall contain the following equipment:—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number> 6 small 
sterlized dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number> 3 
medium size sterlized dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number> 3 large 
size sterlized dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iv</number> 3 large 
sterlized burn dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>v</number> 1 (30 
ml.) bottle containing a two per cent alcoholic solution of iodine;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>vi</number> 1 (30 
ml.) bottle containing salvolatile having the dose and mode of administration 
indicated on the label;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>vii</number> 1 
snake-bite lancet;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>viii</number>  1 (30 
gms.) bottle of Potassium permanganate crystals;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ix</number> 1 pair 
scissors;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>x</number> 1 copy 
of the first-aid leaflet issued by the Director-General, Factory Advice Service 
and Labour Institute Government of India;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>xi</number> A bottle 
containing 100 tablets (each of 5 grains) of aspirin.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
             <number>xii</number> 
Ointment for burns; and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>xiii</number> A 
bottle of suitable surgical antiseptic solution.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> For 
establishment in which the number of migrant workmen exceed fifty, each 
first-aid box shall contain the following equipment:—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number> 12 
small sterilized dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number> 6 
medium size sterilized dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iii</number> 6 large 
size sterilized dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>iv</number> 6 large 
sterilized burn dressings;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>v</number> 6 (15 
gms.) packets sterilized cotton wool;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>vi</number> 1 (80 
ml.) bottle containing a two per cent alcoholic solution of iodine;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>vii</number> 1 (60 
ml.) bottle containing salvolatile having the dose and mode of administration 
indicated on the label;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>viii</number> 1 roll 
of adhesive plaster;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>ix</number> 1 
snake-bite lancet;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>x</number> 1 (30 
gms.) bottle of potassium permanganate crystals;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             <number>xi</number> 1 pair 
scissors;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
             <number>xii</number> 1 copy 
of the first-aid leaflet issued by the Director- General, Factory Advice Service 
and Labour Institute Government of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>xiii</number> A 
bottle containing 100 tablets (each of 5 grains) of aspirin.
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>xiv</number> Ointment 
for burns; and
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>xv</number> A bottle 
of suitable surgical antiseptic solution.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Adequate arrangements 
shall be made for immediate recoupment when necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Nothing except the 
contents mentioned in sub-rule (4) shall be kept in the first-aid box.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The first-aid box 
shall be in charge of a responsible person who shall always be readily available 
during the working hours of the establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The person in-charge 
of the first-aid box shall be a person trained in first-aid treatment, in 
establishments where the number of migrant workmen is one hundred and fifty or 
more.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Protective 
clothing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The contractor shall provide to every migrant workman where the temperature 
falls below 20 degree centigrade, protective clothing consisting of one woollen 
coat and one woollen trousers one in two years:
 
Provided that where the 
temperature falls below 5 degree centigrade an woollen overcoat shall also be 
provided to the migrant workmen once in three years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The protective 
clothing shall be provided by the contractor to every migrant workman before 
onset of winter season in the area where the establishment is located or on the 
30th day of September, whichever is earlier.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>39</number> Drinking water, latrines, 
urinals and washing facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> The contractor shall provide 
sufficient quantity of wholesome drinking water, sufficient number of sanitary 
latrines and urinals, washing facilities for the migrant workmen at the 
establishment in the case of existing establishments, within seven days of 
commencement of these rules, and in case of new establishment, within seven days 
of the commencement of employment of migrant workmen therein.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any of the facilities is 
not provided by the contractor within the specified period, the same shall be 
provided by the principal employer within seven days of the expiry of the period 
specified in sub-rule (1).</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Drinking water, 
latrines, urinals and washing facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The contractor shall provide sufficient quantity of wholesome drinking water, 
sufficient number of sanitary latrines and urinals, washing facilities for the 
migrant workmen at the establishment in the case of existing establishments, 
within seven days of commencement of these rules, and in case of new 
establishment, within seven days of the commencement of employment of migrant 
workmen therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any of the 
facilities is not provided by the contractor within the specified period, the 
same shall be provided by the principal employer within seven days of the expiry 
of the period specified in sub-rule (1).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Rest rooms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every place where migrant workmen are required to halt at night in connection 
with the working of the establishment and in which employment of migrant workmen 
is likely to continue for three months or more, the contractor shall provide and 
maintain rest rooms or other suitable alternatives accommodation within fifteen 
days of the coming into force of the rules in case of the existing 
establishments, and within fifteen days of the commencement of the employment of 
migrant workmen in the case of new establishments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the amenity is not 
provided by the contractor within the specified period, the principal employer 
shall provide the same within a period of fifteen days of the expiry of the 
period specified in sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Separate rooms shall 
be provided for female migrant workmen.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Effective and suitable 
provisions shall be made in every room for securing and maintaining adequate 
ventilation by circulation of fresh air, and there shall also be provided and 
maintained sufficient and suitable natural and artificial lighting.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The rest rooms, or 
other suitable alternative accommodation shall be of such dimensions so as to 
provide at least a floor area of 1.1 square meter for each person.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The rest room, rooms 
or other suitable alternative accommodation shall be so constructed as to afford 
adequate protection against heat, wind, rain and shall have smooth, hard and 
impervious floor surface.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The rest rooms or 
other suitable accommodation shall be at a convenient distance from the 
establishment and shall have adequate supply of wholesome drinking water.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Canteens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every establishment wherein work regarding the employment of migrant workmen 
is likely to continue for six months and wherein migrant workmen numbering one 
hundred or more are ordinarily employed an adequate canteen shall be provided by 
the contractor for the use of such migrant workmen within sixty days of the date 
of coming into force of the rules in the case of the existing establishments, 
and within sixty days of the commencement of the employment of migrant workmen 
in the case of new establishments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the contractor 
fails to provide canteen within the time laid down, the same shall be provided 
by the principal employer, within sixty days of the expiry of the time allowed 
to the contractor.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The canteen shall be 
maintained by the contractor or principal employer, as the case may be, in an 
efficient manner.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The canteen shall 
consist of at least a dinning hall, kitchen, store-room, pantry and washing 
places separately for migrant workmen and for utensils.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> (i) The canteen shall 
be sufficiently lighted at all times when any person has access to it.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The floor shall be 
made of smooth and impervious material and inside walls shall be lime-washed or 
colour-washed at least once in each year:
 
Provided that the inside 
walls of the kitchen shall be lime-washed every four months.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> (i) The precincts of 
the canteen shall be maintained in a clean and sanitary condition.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Waste water shall be 
carried away in suitable covered drains and shall not be allowed to accumulate 
so as to cause a nuisance.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> Suitable 
arrangements shall be made for the collection and disposal of garbage.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> The dinning hall shall 
accommodate at a time at least 30 per cent of the migrant workmen working at a 
time.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The floor area of the 
dinning hall, excluding the area occupied by the service counter and any 
furniture except tables and chairs shall not be less than one square metre per 
dinner to be accommodated as specified in sub-rule (7).
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> (i) A portion of the 
dinning hall and service counter shall be partitioned off and reserved for women 
migrant workmen in proportion to their number.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Washing places for 
women shall be separate and screened to secure privacy.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>10</number> Sufficient tables, 
stools, chairs or benches shall be available for the dinners to be accommodated 
as specified in sub-rule (7).
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> (i) There shall be 
provided and maintained sufficient utensils, crockery, cutlery, furniture and 
any other equipment necessary for the efficient running of the canteen.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The furniture, 
utensils and other equipment shall be maintained in a clean and hygienic 
condition.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>12</number> (i) Suitable clean 
clothes for the employees serving in the canteen shall be provided and 
maintained.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> A service counter, if 
provided, shall have top of smooth and impervious material.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> Suitable facilities 
including an adequate supply of hot water shall be provided for the cleaning of 
utensils and equipment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>13</number> The foodstuffs and 
other items to be served in the canteen shall be in conformity with the normal 
habits of the migrant workmen.
 </section><section>
<number>14</number> The charges for 
meals, other foodstuffs, beverages and other items served in the canteen shall 
be based on no-profit, no-loss basis and shall be conspicuously displayed in the 
canteen.
 </section><section>
<number>15</number> In arriving at the 
prices of foodstuffs and other articles served in the canteen the following 
items shall not be taken into consideration as expenditure, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> The rent for 
the land and buildings;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> The 
depreciation and maintenance charges for the building and equipment provided for 
in the canteen;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number> The cost of 
purchase, repairs and replacement of equipments including furniture, crockery, 
cutlery and utensils;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number> The water 
charges and other charges incurred for lighting and ventilation;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number> The interest 
on the amounts spent on the provision and maintenance of furniture and equipment 
provided for in the canteen.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>16</number> The books of accounts 
and registers and other documents used in connection with the running of the 
canteen shall be produced on demand to an Inspector.
 </section><section>
<number>17</number> The accounts 
pertaining to the canteen shall be audited once every twelve months by 
registered Accountants and Auditors:
 
Provided that the Deputy 
Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) may approve of any other person to audit the 
accounts, if he is satisfied that it is not feasible to appoint a registered 
Accountant and Auditor in view of the site or the location of the canteen.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Latrines and 
urinals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Latrines shall be provided in every establishment on the following scale, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> Where females 
are employed, there shall be at least one latrine for every 25 females;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> Where males 
are employed, there shall be at least one latrine for every 25 males:
 
Provided that where the 
number of males or females exceeds 190, it shall be sufficient if there is one 
latrine for 25 males or females, as the case may be, upto the first 100, and one 
for every 30 thereafter.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every latrine shall be 
under cover and so partitioned off as to secure privacy, and shall have a proper 
door and fastenings.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) Where workers of 
both sexes are employed there shall be displayed outside each block of latrine 
and urinal a notice in the language understood by the majority of the workers 
‘For Men only’, or ‘For Women only’, as the case may be.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The notice shall also 
bear the figure of a man or of a woman, as the case may be.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> There shall be at 
least one urinal for male workers upto fifty and one for female upto fifty 
employed at a time:
 
Provided that where the 
number of male or female workmen, as the case may be, exceeds 500 it shall be 
sufficient if there is one urinal for every fifty females upto the first 500 and 
one for every 100 or part thereof thereafter.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The latrines and 
urinals shall be conveniently situated and accessible to workers at all times at 
the establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> (i) The latrines and 
urinals shall be adequately lighted and shall be maintained in a clean and 
sanitary condition at all times.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Latrines and urinals 
other than those connected with a flush sewage system shall comply with the 
requirements of the public health authorities.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> Water shall be 
provided by the means of tap or otherwise so as to be conveniently accessible in 
or near the latrines and urinals.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> Washing facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every establishment adequate and suitable facilities for washing shall be 
provided and maintained for the use of migrant workmen employed therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Separate and adequate 
screening facilities shall be provided for the use of male and female migrant 
workmen.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Such facilities shall 
be conveniently accessible and shall be kept in clean and hygienic condition.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Creche.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every establishment where 20 or more workmen are ordinarily employed as 
migrant workmen and in which employment of migrant workmen is likely to continue 
for three months or more, the contractor shall provide and maintain two rooms of 
reasonable dimensions for the use of their children under the age of six years, 
within fifteen days of the coming into force of the rules, in case of existing 
establishment and within fifteen days of the commencement of the employment of 
not less than twenty women as migrant workmen in new establishments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> One of such rooms 
shall be used as playroom for the children and the other as bedroom for the 
children.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the contractor 
fails to provide the creche within the time laid down, the same shall be 
provided by the Principal Employer within fifteen days of the expiry of the time 
allowed to the Contractor.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The contractor or the 
principal employer as the case may be, shall supply adequate number of toys and 
games in the play rooms and sufficient number of cots and beddings in the 
sleeping room.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The creche shall be so 
constructed as to afford adequate protection against heat, damp, wind, rain and 
shall have smooth, hard and impervious floor surface.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The creche shall be at 
a convenient distance from the establishment and shall have adequate supply of 
wholesome drinking water.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Effective and suitable 
provisions shall be made in every room of the creche for securing and 
maintaining adequate ventilation by circulation of fresh air and there shall 
also be provided and maintained sufficient and suitable natural or artificial 
lighting.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Residential 
accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The contractor shall provide to every migrant workman:—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number> in case he 
is accompanied by any other member of his family a suitable barrack so as to 
accommodate one room having at least a floor area of 10 square metres, a 
verandah and adequate additional covered space for cooking food as well as one 
common sanitary latrine, one common bathroom for every three such quarters; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number> in case he 
is unaccompanied by any other member of his family a suitable barrack so as to 
accommodate not more than ten such migrant workmen, having at least a floor area 
of not less than 6.5 square metres for each such migrant workman making use of 
the barrack, a verandah and adequate additional covered space for cooking food 
as well as one common sanitary latrine and one common bathroom for every ten 
such migrant workmen;
 
within fifteen days of 
coming into force of the rules in the case of the existing establishments and 
within fifteen days of the commencement of the employment of migrant workmen in 
new establishment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every quarter and the 
barrack shall be so constructed as to afford adequate ventilation, protection 
against heat, wind, rain and shall have smooth, hard and impervious floor 
surface.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The quarters or the 
barracks, as the case may be, shall be at a convenient distance from the 
establishment and shall have adequate supply of wholesome drinking water.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The area in which the 
quarters and/or barracks are located as well as the latrines and bathrooms 
provided therein shall be kept in a clean and sanitary condition at all times.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the amenities 
referred to in sub-rule (1) are not provided by the contractor within the period 
prescribed, the principal employer shall provide the same within a period of 
fifteen days of the expiry of the period laid down in the said sub-rule.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If there is any 
dispute or disagreement regarding suitability or adequacy of provision of any of 
the amenities referred to in sub-rules (1) to (4) the same shall be decided by 
Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner Central 

1[***].
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>46</number> Liability of the principal 
employer in certain cases.—If any allowance required to be 
paid under section 14 or section 15 to a migrant workman employed in an 
establishment to which this Act applies is not paid by the contractor or if any 
facility specified in section 16 is not provided for the benefit of such migrant 
workman, such allowance shall be paid, or, as the case may be, the facility 
shall be provided, by the principal employer within fifteen days of the expiry 
of the time allowed to the contractor under the rules excepts where otherwise 
provided for in the relevant rules:
 Provided that in case of ailment 
requiring urgent medical attention or hospitalisation as the case may be, the 
principal employer shall provided the same immediately on the failure of the 
contractor to do so.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> Liability of the 
principal employer in certain cases.—If 
any allowance required to be paid under section 14 or section 15 to a migrant 
workman employed in an establishment to which this Act applies is not paid by 
the contractor or if any facility specified in section 16 is not provided for 
the benefit of such migrant workman, such allowance shall be paid, or, as the 
case may be, the facility shall be provided, by the principal employer within 
fifteen days of the expiry of the time allowed to the contractor under the rules 
excepts where otherwise provided for in the relevant rules:
 
Provided that in case of 
ailment requiring urgent medical attention or hospitalisation as the case may 
be, the principal employer shall provided the same immediately on the failure of 
the contractor to do so.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> Relaxation in 
certain cases.—If 
the contractor or principal employer, as the case may be, has already provided 
any facility relating to supply of wholesome drinking water or restrooms or 
latrines and urinals or washing, canteen or creche or first-aid as required 
under any Act applicable to the establishment and the same is adequate and also 
available for use for the migrant workmen, that facility shall be deemed to be 
provided for under these rules.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>48</number> Registers of 
Contractors.—Every principal employer shall 
maintain in respect of each registered establishment a register of contractors 
in Form XII.</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> Register of person 
employed.—Every 
principal employer and contractor shall maintain in respect of each 
establishment where he employes migrant workmen a register in Form XIII.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> Service 
certificate.—On 
termination of employment for any reason whatsoever, the contractor shall issue 
to the migrant workman whose services have been terminated a service certificate 
in Form XIV.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
Displacement-cum-outward journey allowances sheet and return journey allowances 
register.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
Every contractor shall maintain displacement-cum-outward journey allowance sheet 
in Form XV and return journey allowance register in Form XVI.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Entries in the sheet 
and the register required to be maintained under sub-rule (1) shall be 
authenticated by the contractor or his duly authorised representative.
 
 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>52</number> Muster roll, wages register, 
deductions register and overtime register.—
<section><number>1</number> In respect of establishments 
which are governed by the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 and the rules made 
thereunder or the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 and the rules made thereunder or 
Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 and the rules made 
thereunder, the following registers and records required to be maintained by the 
contractor as employer under those Acts and the Rules shall be deemed to be 
registers and records to be maintained by the contractor under these 
rules.
 <subsection>         
<number>a</number> Muster roll;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>b</number> register of wages;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>c</number> register of deductions;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>d</number> register of fines;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>e</number> register of overtime;
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>f</number> register of advances.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In respect of establishment 
not covered by any of the Acts or the Rules referred to in sub-rule (1), the 
following provisions shall apply, namely:—
 <subsection>         
<number>a</number> Every contractor shall maintain a Muster Roll Register and a Register of 
Wages in Forms XVII and XVIII respectively.
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>b</number> Signature of thumb-impression of every migrant workman on the register of 
wages shall be obtained and entries therein shall be authenticated by the 
signature of the contractor or his authorised representative, and duly certified 
by the authorised representative of the principal employer as requiring by rule 
35.
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>c</number> Register of deduction, register of fines and register of advances—Register 
of deductions for damage or loss, register of fines and register of advances 
shall be maintained by every contractor in Form XIX, XX and XXI 
respectively.
 </subsection><subsection>         
<number>d</number> Every contractor shall maintain register of overtime in Form 
XXII.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in these rules where a combined or alternative form is sought to be 
used for the contractor to avoid duplication of work for compliance with the 
provisions of any other Act or the rules framed thereunder or any other laws or 
regulations or in cases where mechanised pay rolls are introduced for better 
administration, alternative suitable form or forms in lieu of any of the forms 
prescribed under these rules, may be used with the previous approval of the 
Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central).</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> Muster roll, wages 
register, deductions register and overtime register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In respect of establishments which are governed by the Payment of Wages Act, 
1936 and the rules made thereunder or the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 and the rules 
made thereunder or Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 and the 
rules made thereunder, the following registers and records required to be 
maintained by the contractor as employer under those Acts and the Rules shall be 
deemed to be registers and records to be maintained by the contractor under 
these rules.
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> Muster roll;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> register of 
wages;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number> register of 
deductions;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number> register of 
fines;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number> register of 
overtime;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number> register of 
advances.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In respect of 
establishment not covered by any of the Acts or the Rules referred to in 
sub-rule (1), the following provisions shall apply, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> Every 
contractor shall maintain a Muster Roll Register and a Register of Wages in 
Forms XVII and XVIII respectively.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> Signature of 
thumb-impression of every migrant workman on the register of wages shall be 
obtained and entries therein shall be authenticated by the signature of the 
contractor or his authorised representative, and duly certified by the 
authorised representative of the principal employer as requiring by rule 35.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number> Register of 
deduction, register of fines and register of advances—Register of deductions for 
damage or loss, register of fines and register of advances shall be maintained 
by every contractor in Form XIX, XX and XXI respectively.
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number> Every 
contractor shall maintain register of overtime in Form XXII.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in these rules where a combined or alternative form is sought 
to be used for the contractor to avoid duplication of work for compliance with 
the provisions of any other Act or the rules framed thereunder or any other laws 
or regulations or in cases where mechanised pay rolls are introduced for better 
administration, alternative suitable form or forms in lieu of any of the forms 
prescribed under these rules, may be used with the previous approval of the 
Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> Maintenance and 
preservation of registers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All register and other records required to be maintained under the Act and 
Rules, shall be maintained complete and up-to-date, and, unless otherwise 
provided for, shall be kept at an office of the nearest convenient building 
within the precincts of the workplace or at a place, if any, specified by the 
Inspector on the specific request made by the contractor in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All the registers 
shall be maintained legibly in English or Hindi.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All the registers and 
other records shall be preserved in original for a period of 3 calendar years 
from the date of last entry made therein.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All, the registers, 
records and notices maintained under the Act or Rules shall be produced on 
demand before the Inspector or Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) or any 
other authority under the Act or any person authorised in that behalf by the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where no deduction or 
fine has been imposed or no overtime has been worked during any wage period, a 
‘Nil’ entry shall be made across the body of the register at the end of the 
every wage period indicating also in precise terms the wage period to which the 
‘Nil’ entry relates in the respective registers maintained in Form XIX and XX 
and XXI respectively.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>54</number> Display of an abstract of the 
Act and the Rules.—Every contractor shall display an 
abstract of the Act and the rules in English and Hindi and in language spoken by 
majority of migrant workmen in such form as may be approved by the Deputy Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central).</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> Notices.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) Notices showing the rates of wages, hours of work, wage periods, dates of 
payment of wages, names and addresses of the Inspectors having jurisdiction, and 
date of payment of unpaid wages, shall be displayed in English and in Hindi and 
in the local language understood by the majority of the workers in conspicuous 
places at the establishment and the work-site by the principal employer or the 
contractor, as the case may be.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> the notices shall be 
correctly maintained in a clean and legible condition.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the notice 
shall be sent to the Inspector and whenever any changes occur, the same shall be 
communicated to him forthwith.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> Periodical returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every contractor shall send half yearly return in Form XXIII (in duplicate) so 
as to reach the licensing officer concerned not later than thirty days from the 
close of the half-year.
 
Note.—Half 
year for the purpose of this rule means “a period of six months commencing from 
the 1st January and 1st July every year”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every principal 
employer of a registered establishment shall send annually a return in Form XXIV 
(in duplicate) so as to reach the registering officer concerned not later than 
the 15th February following the end of the year to which it relates.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>57</number> 
<section><number>1</number> The Deputy Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central) or the Inspector or any other authority under the Act 
shall have powers to call for any information or statistics in relation to 
migrant workmen from any contractor or principal employer at any time by an 
order in writing.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person called upon to 
furnish the information under sub-rule (1) shall be legally bound to do 
so.</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> Legal aid.—On 
receipt of a written application from migrant workmen or in the even of his 
death, from next of his kin for providing legal aid in relation to any 
proceedings before the Authority under section 15 of the Payment of Wages Act, 
1936 or Authority under section 20 of the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 or appropriate 
Labour Court under section 33C(2) of the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 or 
Commissioner for Workmen’s Compensation under the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 
1923, in which the migrant workman or his legal heir is a party, the specified 
authority concerned, if he is satisfied, may with the prior approval of the 
Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) engage an advocate to conduct the 
relevant proceedings on behalf of the migrant workman or his legal heir as the 
case may be and meet all legal expenses in this regard.
</article> 

  
 <article>*<number>59</number> 
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved by an 
order made under proviso to clause (vii) of sub-rule (2) of rule 11, rule 25, 
sub-rule (2) of rule 36, and sub-rule (6) of rule 45, within 30 days from the 
date of which order is communicated to him, may prefer an appeal to the Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central):
 Provided that the Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central) may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the period 
of 30 days, if he is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient 
cause from filing the appeal in time.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of an appeal under 
sub-rule (1), the Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) shall after giving the 
appellant an opportunity of being heard, dispose of the appeal as expeditiously 
as possible.
  


</section></article><form>
 




THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF  

EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE)  

CENTRAL RULES, 1980
 


 
 




FORM I
 


[See 
rule 3(1)]
 




Application for registration of establishments employing migrant workmen
 


1. Name and location of the 
establishment.
 


2. Postal Address of the 
establishment.
 


3. Full name and address of 
the principal employer (furnish father’s/husband’s name in the case of 
individuals).
 


4. Names and addresses of 
the directors/particular partners (in case of companies and firms).
 


5. Full names and address 
of the Manager or person responsible for the supervision and control of the 
establishment.
 


6. Nature of work carried 
on in the establishment.
 


7. Particulars of 
contractors and migrant workmen.
 


        (a) Names and 
addresses of contractors.
 


        (b) Nature of work 
for which migrant workmen are to be recruited or are employed.
 


        (c) Maximum number 
of migrant workmen to be employed on any day through each contractor.
 


        (d) Establishment 
date and commencement of work under each contractor.
 


        (e) Estimated date 
of termination of employment of migrant workmen under each contractor.
 


8. Particulars of crossed 
demand draft ________ (Name of the Bank, Amount, Number and Date)
 


I hereby declare that the 
particulars given above are true to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 


Principal Employer
 


Seal and Stamp
 


Office of the Registering 
Officer
 


 
 


Date of receipt of 
application:
</form><form>
 




THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF  

EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE)  

CENTRAL RULES, 1980
 


 
 




FORM II
 


[See 
rule 4(1)]
 




Certificate of registration
 


Date 
________________________
 



GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 



Office of the Registering Officer
 


A certificate of 
registration containing the following particulars is hereby granted under clause 
(a) of sub-section (2) of section 4 of the Inter-State Migrant Workmen 
(Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Act, 1979 and the rules 
made thereunder to......................
 


         1. Nature of work 
carried on in the establishment.
 


         2. Names and 
addresses of the contractors.
 


         3. Nature of work 
for which migrant workmen are to be employed or are employed.
 


         4. Maximum number 
of migrant workmen to be employed on any day through each contractor.
 


         5. Other 
particulars relevant to the employment of migrant workmen.
 


             (i)
 


            (ii)
 


 
 


Signature of Registering

 


Officer with Seal
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF  

EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE)  

CENTRAL RULES, 1980
 


 
 




FORM IV
 


[See 
rule 7(1)]
 




Application for Licence for recruitment
 


1. Name and address of the 
contractor (including his father’s/ husband’s name in case of individuals.)
 


2. Date of birth and age 
(in case of individuals).
 


3. Particulars of 
establishment where migrant workmen are to be employed.
 


        (a) Name and 
address of the establishment;
 


        (b) Type of 
business, trade, industry manufacture or occupation, which is carried on in the 
establishment;
 


        (c) Number and date 
of certificate of registration of the establishment under the Act;
 


        (d) Name and 
address of the principal employer.
 


4. Particulars of migrant 
workmen:
 


        (a) Nature of work 
in which migrant workmen are employed or are to be employed in the 
establishment.
 


        (b) Duration of the 
proposed contract work (give particulars of proposed date of commencing and 
ending).
 


        (c) Name and 
address of the agent or manager of the contractor at the work-site.
 


        (d) Maximum number 
of migrant workmen proposed to be employed in the establishment on any date.
 


        (e) Names and 
addresses of the directors/partners (in case of companies and firms).
 


         (f) Name(s) and 
address(es) of the person(s) in charge of and responsible to the company/firm, 
for the conduct of the business of the company/firm, as the case may be.
 


5. Whether the contractor 
was convicted of any offence within the preceding five years. If so, give 
details.
 


6. Whether there was any 
order against the contractor revoking or suspending licence or forfeiting 
security deposits in respect of an earlier contract. If so, the date of such 
order.
 


7. Whether the contractor 
has worked in any other establishment within the past five years. If so, give 
details of the principal employer, establishment, and nature of work.
 


8. Whether a certificate by 
the principal employer in Form VI is enclosed.
 


9. Amount of licence fee 
paid....................No. of crossed demand draft and date.
 


10. Amount of security 
deposit, if any.
 


 
 



Declaration
 


I hereby declare that the 
details given above are correct to the best of my knowledge and belief. 

 


 
 



Place............................
 



Date............................
 


Signature of the Applicant
 


(Contractor)
 


Note.— 
The application should be accompanied by a crossed demand draft showing the 
payment of the prescribed licence fee and security deposit, if any and a 
certificate in Form V from the Principal Employer.
 


 


 
 


(To 
be filled in the office of the Licensing Officer)
 


Date of receipt of the 
application with crossed demand draft for fees.
 


Signature of the Licensing 
Officer
</form><form>
 




THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF  

EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE)  

CENTRAL RULES, 1980
 


 
 




FORM V
 


[See 
rule 7(2)]
 




Application for Licence for Employment
 


1. Name and address of the 
contractor (including his father’s/ husband’s name in case of individuals.)
 


2. Date of birth and age 
(in case of individuals).
 


3. Particulars of 
establishment where migrant workmen are to be employed.
 


        (a) Name and 
address of the establishment;
 


        (b) Type of 
business, trade, industry manufacture or occupation, which is carried on in the 
establishment;
 


        (c) Number and date 
of certificate of registration of the establishment under the Act;
 


        (d) Name and 
address of the principal employer.
 


4. Particulars of migrant 
workmen:
 


        (a) Nature of work 
in which migrant workmen are employed or are to be employed in the 
establishment.
 


        (b) Duration of the 
proposed contract work (give particulars of proposed date of commencing and 
ending).
 


        (c) Name and 
address of the agent or manager of the contractor at the work-site.
 


        (d) Maximum number 
of migrant workmen proposed to be employed in the establishment on any date.
 


        (e) Names and 
addresses of the directors/partners (in case of companies and firms).
 


         (f) Name(s) and 
address(es) of the person(s) in charge of and responsible to the company/firm, 
for the conduct of the business of the company/firm, as the case may be.
 


5. Whether the contractor 
was convicted of any offence within the preceding five years. If so, give 
details.
 


6. Whether there was any 
order against the contractor revoking or suspending licence or forfeiting 
security deposits in respect of an earlier contract. If so, the date of such 
order.
 


7. Whether the contractor 
has worked in any other establishment within the past five years. If so, give 
details of the principal employer, establishment, and nature of work.
 


8. Whether a certificate by 
the principal employer in Form VI is enclosed.
 


9.Amount of licence fee 
paid......................No. of crossed demand draft  and date.
 


10. Amount of security 
deposit, if any.
 



Declaration
 


I hereby declare that the 
given are correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 



Place.........................
 



Date.........................
 


Signature of the Applicant
 


(Contractor)
 


Note.—The 
application should be accompanied by a crossed demand draft showing the payment 
of the prescribed fee and security deposit, if any certificate in Form VI from 
the principal employer.
 


(To 
be filled in the office of the Licensing Officer)
 


Date of receipt of the 
application with crossed demand draft for fees.
 


 
 


Signature of the Licensing 
Officer
</form><form>
 




THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF  

EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE)  

CENTRAL RULES, 1980
 


 
 




FORM VI
 


[See
rule 7(3)]
 




Form of certificate by principal employer 
 


Certified that I have 
engaged the applicant (Name of the contractor) as a contractor in my 
establishment. I undertake to be bound all the provisions of the Inter-State 
Migrant Workman (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Act, 1979 
and the Inter-State Migrant Workmen (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of 
Service) Central Rules, 1980 in so far as the provisions are applicable to me in 
respect of the employment of migrant workmen by the applicant in my 
establishment.
 


 
 



Place...........................                                                                                                        
 Signature of Principal Employer
 



Date.............................                                                                                                Name and address of establishment
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF  

EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE)  

CENTRAL RULES, 1980
 


 
 




FORM VIII
 


[See 
rule 11(1)]
 



GOVERNMENT OF INDIA
 



Office of Licensing Officer
 


Licence No. Dated Fee paid 
Rs.
 



LICENCE
 


Licence is hereby granted 
to ............. under section 8(1) of the Inter-State Migrant Workmen 
(Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Act, 1979 subject to the 
conditions specified in the annexure.
 


2. This licence is for 
doing the work of (nature of work to be indicated) in the establishment of (name 
of principal employer to be indicated) at (place of work to be indicated).
 


3. The licence shall remain 
in force till (date to be indicated).
 


 
 


Signature and Seal of 
Licensing Officer.
 


 
 



RENEWAL
 


[See 
rule 14)
 


Date of 
renewal                                     
Fee paid for renewal                                   
Date of expiry.
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 



Date..........................
 


Signature and Seal of 
Licensing Officer
 



 ANNEXURE
 


The licence is subject to 
the following conditions:—
 


1. The licence shall be 
non-transferable.
 


2. The number of workmen 
employed as migrant workmen in the establishment shall not, on any day, exceed 
the maximum number specified in the application for licence.
 


3. Save as provided in 
these rules the fees paid for the grant or as the case may be, for renewal of 
licence shall be non-refundable.
 


4. The rates of wages 
payable to the migrant workmen by the contractor shall not be less than the 
rates prescribed under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, for such employment where 
applicable, and where the rates have been fixed by agreement, settlement or 
award, not less than the rates so fixed.
 


5. (a) In case where the 
migrant workmen employed by the contractor perform the same or similar kind of 
work as the workmen directly employed by the principal employer of the 
establishment, the wage rates, holidays, hours of work and other conditions of 
service of the migrant workmen of the contractor shall be the same as applicable 
to the workmen directly employed by the principal employer of the establishment 
on the same or similar kind of work:
 


Provided that in the case 
of any disagreement with regard to the type of work, the same shall be decided 
by the Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) 

1[***];
 


(b) in other cases the wage 
rates, holidays, hours of work, and conditions of service of the migrant workmen 
of the contractor shall be such as prescribed in these rules.
 


6. Every migrant workmen 
shall be entitled to allowances benefits, facilities, etc., as prescribed in the 
Act and these rules.
 


7. No female migrant 
workmen shall be employed by any contractor before 6 am. or after 7 p.m.:
 


Provided that this clause 
shall not apply to the employment of female migrant workmen in pit head baths, 
creches and canteens and as midwives and nurses in hospitals and dispensaries.
 


8. The contractor shall 
notify any change in the number of migrant workmen or the conditions of work to 
the licensing officer.
 


9. The contractor shall 
comply with all the provisions of the Act and these Rules.
 


10. A copy of licence shall 
be displayed prominently at the premises where the migrant workmen are employed.
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Omitted by G.S.R. 
316(E), dated 25th February, 1986 (w.e.f. 25-2-1986).
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 




THE INTER-STATE MIGRANT WORKMEN (REGULATION OF  

EMPLOYMENT AND CONDITIONS OF SERVICE)  

CENTRAL RULES, 1980
 


 
 




FORM IX
 


[See 
rule 15(2)]
 




Application for Renewal of Licence
 


1. Name and address of the 
contractor.
 


2. Number and date of the 
licence.
 


3. Date of expiry of the 
previous licence.
 


4. Whether the licence of 
the Contractor was suspended or revoked.
 


5. Number and date of the 
crossed demand draft enclosed.
 



Place.........................                                                                                                                      
Signature of the Applicant
 


 



  Date........................
 


(To 
be filled in the Office of the Licensing Officer)
 


Date of receipt of the 
application with crossed demand draft No. and date.
 


Signature of the Licensing 
Officer
 



</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>