<act><title>THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956 </title> 
 THE NOTARIES RULES, 19561 
 
 
 <article> <number>1</number> Short title.—These 
rules may be called the Notaries Rules, 1956.
 
 



</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> “appropriate Government” means, in 
relation to a notary appointed by the Central Government , the Central 
Government and in relation to a notary appointed by the State Government, the 
State Government;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> “Form” means a Form appended to 
these Rules;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> “the Act” means the Notaries Act, 
1952 (53 of 1952);
 

        1[(d)  "Schedule" means the 
Schedule appended to these rules.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>3</number> 
Qualifications for appointment as a notary.—No person shall be eligible for 
appointment as a notary unless on the date of the application for such 
appointment—
 

        2[
<section><number>a</number> a person had been 
practising at least for ten years, or
 </section><section>
      <number>aa</number>  a person belonging to Scheduled 
Castes/Scheduled Tribes and other backward classes had been practising at least 
for seven years, or
 </section><section>
      <number>ab</number>  a woman who had been practising 
at least for seven years,
 
              as a legal practitioner, or]
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  he had been a member of the 
Indian Legal Service under the Central Government, or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  he had been at least for ten 
years,—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  a member of Judicial 
Service; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  held an office under the 
Central Government or a State Government requiring special knowledge of law 
after enrolment as an advocate; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  held an office in the 
department of Judge Advocate General or in the legal department of the armed 
forces.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Application for appointment as a notary. </title>— 
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> A person may make an application for appointment as a notary 
(hereinafter called “the applicant”), through the concerned District Judge or 
the Presiding Officer of the Court or Tribunal where he practices as an 
Advocate, in the Form of memorial addressed to such officer or authority 
(hereinafter referred to as the “competent authority”) of the appropriate 
Government as that Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
designate in this behalf.] <title></title>
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The memorial shall be drawn by a person referred to in 
clause (a) of rule 3 in accordance with Form I and by a person referred to in 
clauses (b) and (c) of the said rule in accordance with Form II. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> A person applying in Form II for appointment as a notary 
may submit the memorial direct to the Competent Authority of the Appropriate 
Government.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The memorial of a person referred to in clause (a) of rule 3 shall be 
signed by the applicant and shall be countersigned by the following persons:— 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a Magistrate; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a Manager of a nationalised bank; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a merchant; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> two prominent inhabitants of the local area within which the applicant 
  intends to practise as a notary.] </subsection>
  


 
 ‘(1) A person may make an application for appointment as a notary 
  (hereinafter called “the applicant”) in the Form of memorial addressed to such 
  officer or authority (hereinafter referred to as the “competent authority”) of 
  the appropriate Government as that Government may, by notification in the 
  Official Gazette, designate in this behalf.'. 

</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 

1[***]
 





 

  
 <article><title></title><title>[<number>6</number>Preliminary action on application. 
</title>— [
<section><number>1</number> The competent authority shall examine every 
application received by him and if he is satisfied that the application is not 
complete in all respects or the applicant does not possess the qualifications 
specified in rule 3, or that any previous application of the applicant for 
appointment as a notary was rejected within six months before the date of the 
application, shall reject it summarily and inform the applicant accordingly.] 
<title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the competent authority does not reject the application under sub- 
 rule (1),— 
 [***] 
 <subsection><number>b</number> he may, if he thinks fit, ascertain from any Bar Council, Bar 
Association, Incorporated Law Society or other authority in the area where the 
applicant proposes to practise, the objections, if any, to the appointment of 
the applicant as notary, to be submitted within the time fixed for the purpose.] 

 _____________
 <subsubsection><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 324, dated 14th February, 1956, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II,  Sec. 3, p. 191, dated 
15th February, 1956 and subsequently amended in the recent past by— 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>1</number> G.S.R. 296(E), dated 19th May, 2006 . 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>2</number> G.S.R. 501(E), dated 24th August, 2006 . 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>3</number> G.S.R. 73(E), dated 9th February, 2007 .
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>4</number> G.S.R. 86(E), dated 14th February, 2007 . 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>5</number> G.S.R. 319(E), dated 1st May, 2007 . 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section></article><article><number>6</number> G.S.R. 330(E), dated 8th May, 2007 . 
 </article><article><number>7</number> G.S.R. 686(E), dated 31st October, 2007 .
 </article><article><number>8</number> G.S.R. 51(E), dated 23rd February, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>9</number> G.S.R. 636(E), dated 3rd September, 2008 .
 </article><article><number>10</number> G.S.R. 764(E), dated 3rd November, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>11</number> G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 . 
 <section><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 151, dated 14th March, 1958 . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 , for 
sub-rule (1) (w.e.f. 1-3-2009 ). Sub-rule (1), before substitution, stood as 
under: 
 “ (1) The competent authority shall examine every application 
received by him and, if he is satisfied that the applicant does not possess the 
qualifications specified in rule 3, or that any previous application of the 
applicant for appointment as a notary was rejected within six months before the 
date of the application, shall reject it and inform the applicant accordingly.”. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> Clause (a) omitted by G.S.R. 370 (E), dated 8th July, 1997 
(w.e.f. 8-7-1997 ). </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Recommendation of the competent authority. </title>— 
[
<section><number>1</number> The competent authority shall, after holding such inquiry as he 
thinks fit and after giving the applicant an opportunity of making his 
representations against the objections, if any, received within the time fixed 
under sub-rule (2) of rule 6, make a report to the appropriate Government 
recommending that the applicant may be allowed to appear before the Interview 
Board.] <title></title>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The competent authority shall also make his recommendation in the report 
under sub-rule (1) regarding the persons by whom the whole or any part of the 
costs of the application including the cost of hearing, if any, shall be borne. 

 </section><section><number>3</number> In making his recommedation under sub-rule (1), the competent authority 
shall have due regard to the following matters, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> whether the applicant ordinarily resides in the area in which he 
  proposes to practise as a notary; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> whether, having regard to the commercial importance of the area in 
  which the applicant proposes to practise and the number of existing notaries 
  practising in the area, it is necessary to appoint any additional notaries for 
  the area; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> whether, having regard to his knowledge and experience of commercial 
  law and the nature of the objections, if any, raised in respect of his 
  appointment as a notary, and in the case of a legal practitioner also to the 
  extent of his practice, the applicant is fit to be appointed as a notary; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> where the applicant belongs to a firm of legal practitioners, whether, 
  having regard to the number of existing notaries in that firm, it is proper 
  and necessary to appoint any additional notary from that firm; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> where applications from other applicants in respect of the area are 
  pending, whether the applicant is more suitable than such other applicants. 
  </subsection>
 _____________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 324, dated 14th February, 1956, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II,  Sec. 3, p. 191, dated 
15th February, 1956 and subsequently amended in the recent past by— 
 </section><section><number>1</number> G.S.R. 296(E), dated 19th May, 2006 . 
 </section><section><number>2</number> G.S.R. 501(E), dated 24th August, 2006 . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> G.S.R. 73(E), dated 9th February, 2007 .
 </section><section><number>4</number> G.S.R. 86(E), dated 14th February, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>5</number> G.S.R. 319(E), dated 1st May, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>6</number> G.S.R. 330(E), dated 8th May, 2007 . 
 </section></article><article><number>7</number> G.S.R. 686(E), dated 31st October, 2007 .
 </article><article><number>8</number> G.S.R. 51(E), dated 23rd February, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>9</number> G.S.R. 636(E), dated 3rd September, 2008 .
 </article><article><number>10</number> G.S.R. 764(E), dated 3rd November, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>11</number> G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 . 
 <section><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009, for 
sub-rule (1) (w.e.f. 1-3-2009). Sub-rule (1), before substitution, stood as 
under: “(1) The competent authority shall, after holding such inquiry as he 
thinks fit and after giving the applicant an opportunity of making his 
representations against the objections, if any, received within the time fixed 
under sub-rule (2) of rule 6, make a report to the appropriate Government 
recommending either that the application may be allowed for the whole or any 
part of the area to which the application relates or that it may be 
rejected.”.</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum></title><title>[<number>7A</number> Constitution of the Interview 
Board. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> If the appropriate Government allows that the applicant may 
be asked to appear before the Interview Board, the competent authority shall 
inform the applicant to appear before the Interview Board, on the date, time and 
place fixed, to judge the competency of the applicant for being appointed as a 
Notary. The Interview Board shall submit its recommendations to the appropriate 
Government. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> For the said purpose, one or more Interview Boards shall be 
constituted by the appropriate Government from amongst its officers dealing with 
legal matters and the Chairperson of every Interview Board shall be an officer 
not below the rank of Joint Secretary or Law Officer of that Government.]] 
  



 
 “(2) For the said purpose, a three members Interview Board 
  shall be constituted by the appropriate Government from amongst its officers 
  dealing with legal matters. The Chairperson of the Interview Board shall not 
  be an officer below the rank of Joint Secretary of that Government.” 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>7B</number> Transitional provision. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> All the 
memorials received by the Competent Authority till 28th February, 2009 and which 
are pending shall be processed/examined in accordance with the provisions of the 
rules as amended by the Notaries (Amendment) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The fresh memorials shall only be submitted on or after 1st July, 2009 .] 



 
 
</section><section><number>1</number> G.S.R. 296(E), dated 19th May, 2006 . 
 </section><section><number>2</number> G.S.R. 501(E), dated 24th August, 2006 . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> G.S.R. 73(E), dated 9th February, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>4</number> G.S.R. 86(E), dated 14th February, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>5</number> G.S.R. 319(E), dated 1st May, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>6</number> G.S.R. 330(E), dated 8th May, 2007 . 
 </section></article><article><number>7</number> G.S.R. 686(E), dated 31st October, 2007 . 
 </article><article><number>8</number> G.S.R. 51(E), dated 23rd February, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>9</number> G.S.R. 636(E), dated 3rd September, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>10</number> G.S.R. 764(E), dated 3rd November, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>11</number> G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 . 
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number>Appointment of a notary. </title>— [
<section><number>1</number> 
[On receipt of the recommendations of the interview board, the 
appropriate Government shall consider the recommendation and shall—] 
<title></title>
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> allow the application in respect of the whole of the area to which it 
  relates; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> allow the application in respect of any part of the area to which it 
  relates; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> reject the application, </subsection>
 and shall also make such orders as the Government thinks fit regarding the 
persons by whom the whole or any part of the cost of the application including 
the cost of hearing, if any, shall be borne.] 
 </section><section>[<number>2</number> An applicant shall be informed of every order passed by the 
appropriate Government under sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any applicant whose application has been rejected [or allowed 
in respect of only a part of the area to which it relates] or against whom an 
order as to cost has been made under sub-rule (1) may, within sixty days of the 
date of the order apply to the appropriate Government for reviewing the order 
and that Government may, after making such further inquiry as it thinks fit pass 
such order as it considers necessary.] 
 </section><section>[<number>4</number>] Where the application is allowed, the appropriate 
Government shall appoint the applicant as a notary and direct his name to be 
entered in the Register of Notaries maintained by that Government under section 
4 of the Act and issue to him a certificate on payment of prescribed fees 
authorizing him to practise in the area to which the application relates or in 
such part thereof as the appropriate Government may specify in the certificate, 
as a notary for a period of [five years] from the date on which the 
certificate is issued to him. 
 </section><section>[<number>4A</number> The appropriate Government may on and after the ninth day 
of May, 2001, appoint notaries in a State or Union territory, as the case may 
be, not exceeding the number of notaries specified in the Schedule: 
 Provided that the number of notaries whose certificate of practice has been 
renewed under sub-section (2) of section 5 of the Act shall be included in the 
total number of notaries appointed for the purpose of counting the total number 
of notaries specified in the Schedule Provided further that if in a State or 
Union territory the number of notaries appointed before the ninth day of May, 
2001, exceeds the number of notaries specified in the Schedule, such notaries 
shall continue to be so appointed in that State or Union territory, as the case 
may be.] 
 [ [(5)] The Register of Notaries shall be in Form 
IIA and the certificate of practice shall be in Form IIB.] 
 _____________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 324, dated 14th February, 1956, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II,  Sec. 3, p. 191, dated 
15th February, 1956 and subsequently amended in the recent past by— 
 </section><section><number>1</number> G.S.R. 296(E), dated 19th May, 2006 . 
 </section><section><number>2</number> G.S.R. 501(E), dated 24th August, 2006 . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> G.S.R. 73(E), dated 9th February, 2007 .
 </section><section><number>4</number> G.S.R. 86(E), dated 14th February, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>5</number> G.S.R. 319(E), dated 1st May, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>6</number> G.S.R. 330(E), dated 8th May, 2007 . 
 </section><section><number>7</number> G.S.R. 686(E), dated 31st October, 2007 .
 </section></article><article><number>8</number> G.S.R. 51(E), dated 23rd February, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>9</number> G.S.R. 636(E), dated 3rd September, 2008 .
 </article><article><number>10</number> G.S.R. 764(E), dated 3rd November, 2008 . 
 </article><article><number>11</number> G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 . 
 <section><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 151, dated 14th March, 1958 . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 , for “On 
receipt of the report of the competent authority, the appropriate Government 
shall consider the report and shall—” (w.e.f. 1-3-2009 ). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 151, dated 14th March, 1958 . 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 1056, dated 30th October, 1958 . 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Re-numbered by G.S.R. 151, dated 14th March, 1958 . 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 262 (E), dated 28th March, 2000 (w.e.f. 
28-3-2000 ). 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 330 (E), dated 9th May, 2001 (w.e.f. 10-5-2001 
). 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Ins. by S.R.O. 1353, dated 6th June, 1956 . 
 </section><section><number>10</number> Re-numbered by G.S.R. 1056, dated 30th October, 1958 . 
  </section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>8A</number> Extension 
of area of practice.—A notary public who is already in possession of a 
certificate of practice in respect of a particular area, may for sufficient 
reasons, apply for extension of his area of practice. If the original 
certificate of practice had been issued by a State Government and the new area 
of practice applied for lies within the territory of that State, the application 
for extension of the area of practice shall be made to that State Government. In 
all cases where the original certificate of practice had been issued by the 
Central Government, the application for extension of the area of practice shall 
be made to the Central Government. Applications for the extension of the area of 
practice where the new area lies either wholly outside the State or partly 
inside and partly outside the State which granted the original certificate shall 
be made to the Central Government for the issue of a fresh certificate. The 
State Government or the Central Government, as the case may be, shall, after 
considering the reasons stated in the application and other factors, pass such 
orders thereon as it may deem fit. Any extension of the area of practice shall 
not have the effect of extending the period of validity of the original 
certificate beyond the period of 

2[five years] 
specified in rule 8(4)].
 
 




</article> 

 <title> </title>
 <article><title><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>8B</number> Renewal of 
Certificate of Practice. </title>—The certificate of practice issued under 
sub-rule (4) of rule 8 may be renewed for a further period of five years on 
payment of prescribed fee. An application for renewal of Certificate of Practice 
shall be submitted to the appropriate Government before three months from the 
date of expiry of its period of validity: 
 Provided that the appropriate Government may, after considering 
the reasons stated in the application, relax the condition of submission of 
application for renewal of certificate of practice before the above specified 
period.] 

</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>9</number> Fees for 
issue and renewal of certificate of practice and extension of area.—The fees 
for issue and renewal of certificate of practice and extension of area shall be 
as under,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  issue of certificate of 
practice—Rs. 1,000;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  extension of area of practice—Rs. 
750;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  renewal of certificate of 
practice—Rs. 500;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  issue of a duplicate certificate 
of practice—Rs. 300].
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Transaction of 
business by a notary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notary in transacting the business under the Act shall use the Forms set forth 
in the Appendix to these rules.
 

1[(2) Besides 
recording declaration of payment for honour a notary shall also register notings 
and protests made. Every notary shall maintain a Notarial Register in the 
prescribed Form XV.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any demand of 
acceptance or payment or better security has been made by a clerk, a notary 
shall, after examination of the entry in the Register relating to such demand, 
affix his signature thereto, and cause the clerk to affix his signature also to 
the entry.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Each notary shall, 
before bringing the Notarial Register into use, add a certificate on the title 
page specifying the number of pages it contains. Such certificate shall be 
signed and dated by the notary.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every notary shall 
permit the District Judge or such officer as the appropriate Government from 
time to time appoint in this behalf to inspect his register at such times, not 
often than twice a year, as the District Judge or officer may fix. District 
Judge or officer appointed by the State Government will have power to lodge a 
report to the appropriate Government for taking action against a notary.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When the original 
instrument is in a language other than, English, any noting or protest or entry 
in his register which has to be made in respect of the instrument by a notary 
may be made either in that language or in English.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In making presentment 
of bills or notes a notary shall observe the provisions of Chapter V of the 
Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (26 of 1881).
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The notary may—
 </section><section>
       <number>1</number>  draw, attest or certify documents 
under his official seal including conveyance of properties;
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>  note and certify the general 
transactions relating to negotiable instruments;
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>  prepare a Will or other 
testamentary documents; and
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>  prepare and take affidavits for 
various purposes for his notarial acts.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Every notary shall 
grant a receipt for the fees and charge realised by him and maintain a register 
showing all the fees and charges realised.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>13</number> Inquiry 
into the allegations of professional or other misconduct of a notary.—2[
<section><number>1</number> 
An inquiry into the misconduct of a notary may be initiated either suo motu
by the appropriate Government or on a complaint received in Form XIII.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such complaint 
shall contain the following particulars, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the acts and omissions which, if 
proved, would render the person complained against unfit to be a notary;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the oral or documentary evidence 
relied upon in support of the allegations made in the complaint.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The appropriate 
Government shall return a complaint which is not in the proper Form or which 
does not contain the aforesaid particulars to the complainant for representation 
after compliance with such objections and within such times as the appropriate 
Government may specify:
 
Provided that if the 
subject-matter in a complaint is, in the opinion of the said Government 
substantially the same as or covered by, any previous complaint and if there is 
no additional ground, the said Government shall file the said complaint without 
any further action and inform the complainant accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Within sixty days 
ordinarily of the receipt of complaint, the appropriate Government shall send a 
copy thereof to the notary at his address as entered in the Register of 
Notaries.
 

3[(4A) Where an 
inquiry is initiated, suo motu by the appropriate Government, the 
appropriate Government shall send to the notary a statement specifying the 
charge or charges against him, together with particulars of the oral or 
documentary evidence relied upon in support of such charge or charges.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 

2[A notary against 
whom an inquiry has been initiated may, within fourteen days of the service on 
him of a copy of the complaint under sub-rule (4) or of the statement of the 
charges under sub-rule (4A) as the case may be,] or within such time as may be 
extended by the appropriate Government , forward to that Government a written 
statement in his defence verified in the same manner as a pleading in a civil 
court.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If on a persual of


2[the written 
statement,] if any, of the notary concerned and other relevant documents and 
papers, the appropriate Government consider that there is a prima 
facie case against such notary, the appropriate Government shall cause an 
inquiry to be made in the matter by the competent authority. If the appropriate 
Government is of the opinion that there is no prima facie case against 
the notary concerned, 

4[the complaint or 
charge shall be filed] and the complainant and the notary concerned shall be 
informed accordingly.
 

5[(7) Every notice 
issued to a notary under this rule shall be sent to him by registered post. If 
any such notice is returned unserved with an endorsement indicating that the 
addressee has refused to accept the notice or the notice is not returned 
unserved within a period of thirty days from the date of its despatch, the 
notice shall be deemed to have been duly served upon the notary.]
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> It shall be the duty 
of the appropriate Government to place before the competent authority all facts 
brought to its knowledge which are relevant for the purpose of an inquiry by the 
competent authority.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> A notary who is 
proceeded against shall have right to defend himself before the competent 
authority either in person or through a legal practitioner or any other notary.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> Except as otherwise 
provided in these rules, the competent authority shall have the power to 
regulate his procedure relating to the inquiry in such manner as he considers 
necessary and during the course of inquiry, may examine witnesses and receive 
any other oral or documentary evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> The competent 
authority shall submit his report to the Government entrusting him with the 
inquiry.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> (a) The appropriate 
Government shall consider the report of the competent authority, and if in its 
opinion a further inquiry is necessary, may cause such further inquiry to be 
made and a further report submitted by the competent authority.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> If after considering 
the report of the competent authority, the appropriate Government is of the 
opinion that action should be taken against the notary the appropriate 
Government may make an order—
 <subsubsection>
        <number>i</number> cancelling the certificate of 
practice and perpetually debarring the notary from practice; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ii</number> suspending him from practice for 
a specified period; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>iii</number>  letting him off with a warning, 
according to the nature and gravity of the misconduct of the notary proved.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>13</number> Notification of 
removal—The removal of the name of any notary from the Register of Notaries 
from practice, as the case may be, shall be notified in Official Gazette and 
shall also be communicated in writing to the notary concerned.]
 
 







</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>14</number> Submission 
of returns.—Every notary shall, in the first week of January every year, 
submit to the appropriate Government, an annual return in Form XIV of the 
notarial acts done by him during the preceding year.]
 





</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 


 <article>
<number>15</number> 
Each notary shall have an office within the area mentioned in the certificate 
issued to him under rule 8 and he shall exhibit it in a conspicuous place 
thereat a board showing his name and his designation as a notary.
 


</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
If a notary has to deal with a case which does not in terms attract any of the 
Forms prescribed, the notary should adopt the form nearest to his case with such 
modifications thereto as he thinks the exceptional peculiarities of the case to 
justify.
 
 
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17</number> Annual 
publication of the list of notaries.—The list of notaries to be published by 
the Central Government and every State Government under section 6 of the Act, 
shall be in the following Form:—
 
 <section>
<number>Sl</number> No.     Name of notary      Residential 
  and    Qualifications       Area in which         Remarks
 

                                                professional 
                               he is authorised        
 
 

                                                   
  addresses                                      to practise
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



</section></article><form>
 

THE NOTARIES RULES, 1956 
 

 
 

1[FORM IIB 
 

[ See rule 8(5)] 
 

Government  
of........................................................... 
 

(Emblem) 
 

Certificate of Practice 
 

Certified that 
................................................................................... 
son/daughter/wife of 
................................................................resident of 
.................................................. has been appointed as a 
notary under the Notaries Act, 1952 (53 of 1952) and is authorised to practise 
as such in and throughout .............................. for a period of five 
years ......................... Given under my hand and seal of the Government 
of ............................ this..................................day of 
...................................... 
 

3 [Additional Secretary to the Government of India/  
Secretary 
to the Government of ..................................  
(Name of the 
State)]] 
 

-----------
 

1. Subs. by G.S.R. 370(E), dated 8th July, 1997 (w.e.f. 
8-7-1997). 
 

 
  </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009, for 
sub-rule (1) (w.e.f. 1-3-2009). Sub-rule (1), before substitution, stood as 
under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 370 (E), dated 8th July, 1997 (w.e.f. 
8-7-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 700(E), dated 24th September, 2009 (w.e.f. 
24-9-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Rule 5 omitted by G.S.R. 151, dated 
14th March, 1958.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 (w.e.f. 
1-3-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 700(E), dated 24th September, 2009, for 
sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 24-9-2009). Sub-rule (2), before substitution, stood as 
under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Vide  S.R.O. 324, dated 14th February, 1956, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 191, dated 15th 
February, 1956 and subsequently amended in the recent past by—</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 114(E), dated 24th February, 2009 (w.e.f. 
1-3-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 1056, dated 30th 
October,1958.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 262 (E), dated 28th 
March, 2000 (w.e.f. 28-3-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 686(E), dated 31st October, 2007 
(w.e.f. 31-10-2007 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 370 (E), dated 8th 
July, 1997 (w.e.f. 8-7-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by S.O. 83, dated 28th 
December,1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by S.O. 774, dated 9th March, 
1957.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 1056, dated 30th 
October, 1958.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Ins. by G.s.r. 
1056, dated 30th October, 1958.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 1056, dated 30th 
October, 1958.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 370 (E), dated 8th 
July, 1997 (w.e.f. 8-7-1997).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Subs. by S.O. 1285, dated 20th April, 
1957.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Ins. by S.O. 854, dated 11th March, 
1957.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>