<act><tid>1681403</tid>
<title>THE SECUNDERABAD AND AURANGABAD CNTONMENTS HOUSE RENT CONTROL 
LAW (REPEAL) ACT, <year>1972</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1972</year>
[]

Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1978</year> (38 of <year>1978</year>), s. 2 and 
Sch.





<article><tid>1025554</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Secunderabad and 
Aurangabad Cantonments House Rent Control Law (Repeal) Act, <year>1972</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1585676</tid>
<number>2</number>Repeal of Secunderabad and Aurangabad cantonments House Rent 
Control Law, <year>1949</year>, as in force in the Secunderbad Cantonment. On and 
from the date on which the Andhra Pradesh Buildings (Lease, Rent and  
  Eviction) Control Act, <year>1960</year> (Andhra Pradesh Act XV of <year>1960</year>.) is 
extended by notification under section 3 of the Cantonments (Extension  
  of Rent Control Laws) Act, <year>1957</year>, (1957) to the Secunderabad 
Cantonment, the Secunderabad and Aurangabad Cantonments House Rent 
Control Law, <year>1949</year>, as in force in that cantonment shall stand 
repealed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>146</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>165961</tid>
<number>3</number>Repeal of Secunderbad and Aurangabad Cantonment House Rent 
Control Law, <year>1949</year>, as in force in the Aurangabad Cantonment. On and 
from the date on which the Hyderabad Houses (Rent, Eviction and Lease) 
Control Act, <year>1954</year> (Hyderabad Act XX of <year>1954</year>.) is extended by 
notification under section 3 of the Cantonments (Extension of Rent  
  Control Laws) Act, <year>1957</year>, (46 of <year>1957</year>.) to the Aurangabad Cantonment, 
the Secunderabad and Aurangabad Cantonments House Rent Control Law, 
<year>1949</year>, as in force in that cantonment shall stand repealed.


</article>



<article><tid>374456</tid>
<number> 4</number> Savings.
<section><tid>1213810</tid>
<number>1</number>The repeal of the Secunderabad and Aurangabad  
Cantonments House Rent Control Law, <year>1949</year>, by section 2 or section 3, 
shall not affect---

<subsection><tid>1128504</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of the said Law or anything duly 
done or suffered thereunder; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518203</tid>
<number>b</number>any right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, 
accrued or incurred under the said Law; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>77389</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against the said Law; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1441108</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in 
respect of any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, 
penalty, forfeiture or punishment as aforesaid,
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
Instituted, continued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
Punishment may be imposed as if the said Law had not been repealed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>35842</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1), 
anything done or any action taken under the Law repealed by section 2 
' or section 3, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provisions of the Act, extended by notification as 
provided in that section to the cantonment of Secunderabad or the 
cantonment of Aurangabad, as the case may be, and shall continue to be 
in force accordingly unless and until superseded by anything done or 
any action taken under the Act so extended.


</section>

</article>



 </act>