<act><tid>1682231</tid>
<title>UNION TERRITORIES (STAMP AND COURT- FEES LAWS) ACT, <year>1961</year></title>

NO. 33 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 29th August, <year>1961</year>]

An Act to provide for the amendment and repeal of certain laws 
relating to stamp duties and court- fees as in force in certain Union 
territories.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>466407</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Union Territories 
 (Stamp and Court- fees Laws) Act, <year>1961</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1696066</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>, as in force in Himachal 
Pradesh. On such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, appoint, for Schedule I- A of the Indian Stamp 
Act, <year>1899</year>, (2of 1899.) as in force in the Union territory of Himachal 
Pradesh immediately before that date, there shall be substituted, with 
such modifications as may be specified in the notification, Schedule 
I- A to the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>, as in force in the State of Punjab 
on the 28th day of November, <year>1960</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>119442</tid>
<number>3</number>Repeal of Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year> (7 of <year>1870</year>.) as in force in 
Himachal Pradesh. On the date on which the Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year>, as 
in force in the State of Punjab, is extended to the Union territory of 
Himachal Pradesh by notification under section 2 of the Union 
Territories (Laws) Act, <year>1950</year>, (30 of <year>1950</year>.) the Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year>, 
as in force in that Union territory immediately before the date of 
such notification, shall stand repealed.


</article>



<article><tid>287703</tid>
<number> 4</number> Repeal of Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year>, (7 of <year>1870</year>.) as in force in 
Manipur and Tripura. (a) On the date on which the Court- fees Act, 
<year>1870</year>, as in force in the State of Assam, is extended to the Union 
territory of Manipur by notification under section 2 of the Union 
Territories (Laws) Act, <year>1950</year>, (30 of <year>1950</year>.) the Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year>, 
as in force in that Union territory immediately before the date of 
such notification, shall stand repealed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>194</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st April, <year>1964</year>, vide G. S. R. 517, and 18. 3. 64-------- p. 363

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 1st April, <year>1964</year>, vide G. S. R. 518, and 18. 3. <footcitenum>64</footcitenum> do p. 390].





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<section><tid>967514</tid>
<number>b</number>On the date on which the Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year>, as in force 
in the State of Assam, is extended to the Union territory of Tripura 
by notification under section 2 of the Union Territories (Laws) Act, 
<year>1950</year>, the Court- fees Act, <year>1870</year>, as in force in that Union territory 
immediately before the date of such notification, shall stand 
repealed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1171091</tid>
<number> 5</number> Repeal of Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>, as in force in Manipur and 
Tripura. (a) On the date on which the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>, (2 of  
  <year>1899</year>), as in force in the State of Assam, is extended to the Union 
territory of Manipur by notification under section 2 of the Union 
Territories (Laws) Act, <year>1950</year>, (30 of <year>1950</year>), the Indian Stamp Act, 
<year>1899</year>, as in force in that Union territory immediately before the date 
of such notification, shall stand repealed.
<section><tid>15745</tid>
<number>b</number>On the date on which the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>, as in force 
in the State of Assam, is extended to the Union territory of Tripura 
by notification under section 2 of the Union Territories (Laws) Act, 
<year>1950</year>, the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>, as in force in that Union territory 
immediately before the date of such notification, shall stand 
repealed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Validation of levy of stamp duties in certain cases.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>685166</tid>
<number>6</number>Validation of levy of stamp duties in Scertain cases. 
Any stamp duties levied and collected in the Union territory 
of Manipur during the period commencing on the 16th day of April, 
<year>1950</year>, and ending on the date on which the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year>, (2 of  
  <year>1899</year>), as in force in the State of Assam is extended to that Union 
territory under section 5, in the belief that the Indian Stamp Act, 
<year>1899</year>, as in force in the State of Assam immediately before the 16th 
day of April, <year>1950</year>, was applicable to that Union territory, shall be 
deemed always to have been levied and collected in accordance with 
law.

</article>



 </act>