<act><title>

The
Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial Institutions Act, 1993</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number>
Short title, extent, commencement and application.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial
Institutions Act, 1993.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>
It shall be deemed to come into force on the 24th day of June, 1993.
 


 </section><section>
<number>4</number>
The provisions of this Act shall not apply where the amount of debt due to any
bank or financial institution or to a consortium of banks or financial
institutions is less than ten lakh rupees or such other amount, being not less
than one lakh rupees, as the Central Government may, by notification, specify.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the
context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
“Appellate Tribunal” means an Appellate Tribunal established under
sub-section (1) of section 8;

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
“application” means an application made to a Tribunal under section
19;

 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
“appointed day”, in relation to a Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal,
means the date on which such Tribunal is established under sub-section (1) of
section 3 or, as the case may be, sub-section (1) of section 8;

 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
“bank” means—

 <subsection>
<number>i</number>
a banking company;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>
a corresponding new bank;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>
State Bank of India;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>
a subsidiary bank; or

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>
a Regional Rural Bank;

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>e</number>
“banking company” shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (c)
of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949);

 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>ea</number>
“Chairperson” means a Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal appointed
under section 9;]

 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
“corresponding new bank” shall have the meaning assigned to it in
clause (da) of section 5 of the Banking Regulation Act, 1949 (10 of 1949);

 </section><section>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>g</number>
“debt” means any liability (inclusive of interest) which is claimed
as due from any person by a bank or a financial institution or by a consortium
of banks or financial institutions during the course of any business activity
undertaken by the bank or the financial institution or the consortium under any
law for the time being in force, in cash or otherwise, whether secured or
unsecured, or assigned, or whether payable under a decree or order of any civil
court or any arbitration award or otherwise or under a mortgage and subsisting
on, and legally recoverable on, the date of the application;]

 </section><section>
<number>h</number>
“financial institution” means—

 </section><section>
<number>i</number>
a public financial institution within the meaning of section 4A of the
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);

 </section><section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ia</number>
the securitisation company or reconstruction company which has obtained a
certificate of registration under sub‑section (4) of section 3 of the
Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial Assets and Enforcement of
Security Interest Act, 2002 (54 of 2002);]
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>
such other institution as the Central Government may, having regard to
its business activity and the area of its operation in India by notification,
specify;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>
“notification” means a notification published in the Official
Gazette;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>ja</number>
“Presiding Officer” means the Presiding Officer of the Debts Recovery
Tribunal appointed under sub-section (1) of section 4;]

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>
“Recovery Officer” means a Recovery Officer appointed by the Central
Government for each Tribunal under sub-section (1) of section 7;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>
“Regional Rural Bank” means a Regional Rural Bank established under
section 3 of the Regional Rural Bank Act, 1976 (21 of 1976);

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>
“State Bank of India” means the State Bank of India constituted under
section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, 1955 (23 of 1955);

 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>n</number>
“subsidiary bank” shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (k)
of section 2 of the State Bank of India (Subsidiary Banks) Act, 1959
(38 of 1959);
 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>o</number>
“Tribunal” means the Tribunal established under sub-section (1) of
section 3.
  



























 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Establishment of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Central Government shall, by notification, establish one or more Tribunals, 
    to be known as the Debts Recovery Tribunal, to exercise the jurisdiction, 
    powers and authority conferred on such Tribunal by or under this Act.

 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government shall also specify, in the notification referred to in 
    sub-section (1), the areas within which the Tribunal may exercise 
    jurisdiction for entertaining and deciding the applications filed before it.

 

  


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number>
Composition of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> A
Tribunal shall consist of one person only (hereinafter referred to as the
Presiding Officer) to be appointed by notification, by the Central Government.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central Government
may authorise the Presiding Officer of one Tribunal to discharge also the
functions of the Presiding Officer of another Tribunal.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number>
Qualifications for appointment as Presiding Officer.—A
person shall not be qualified for appointment as the Presiding Officer of a
Tribunal unless he is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a District Judge.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number>
Term of Office.—The Presiding
Officer of a Tribunal shall hold office for a term of five years from the date
on which he enters upon his office or until he attains the age of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[sixty-two
years], whichever is earlier.
 


 
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number>
Staff of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government shall provide the Tribunal <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[with
one or more Recovery Officers] and such other officers and employees as that
Government may think fit.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[The
Recovery Officers] and other officers and employees of a Tribunal shall
discharge their functions under the general superintendence of the Presiding
Officer.
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number>
The salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of the 3[Recovery
Officers] and other officers and employees of a Tribunal shall be such as may be
prescribed.
 


 
  










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
Establishment of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall, by notification, establish one or more Appellate 
Tribunals, to be known as the Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal, to exercise the 
jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on such Tribunal by or under this 
Act.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central Government 
shall also specify in the notification, referred to in sub-section (1) the 
Tribunals in relation to which the Appellate Tribunal may exercise jurisdiction.
 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-sections (1) and (2), the Central Government may authorise the 
Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal to discharge also the functions of the 
Chairperson of other Appellate Tribunal.]
 


 
  


 
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Composition of Appellate Tribunal.—An 
    Appellate Tribunal shall consist of one person only (hereinafter referred to 
    as <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[the 
    Chairperson of the Appellate Tribunal]) to be appointed, by notification, by 
    the Central Government.
 
   






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Qualifications for appointment as <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[Chairperson 
    of the Appellate Tribunal].—A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[the 
    Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] unless he—
 <section>
<number>a</number>
is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
has been a member of the Indian Legal Service and has held a post in 
    Grade I of that service for at least three years; or

 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
has held office as the Presiding Officer of a Tribunal for at least 
    three years.
 
  


 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
  

    <number>11</number> Term of Office.—<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[The 
    Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] shall hold office for a term of five 
    years from the date on which he enters upon his office or until he attains 
    the age of <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[sixty-five 
    years], whichever is earlier.
 
   






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Staff 
of the Appellate Tribunal.—The 
provisions of section 7 (except those relating to Recovery Officer) shall, so 
far as may be, apply to an Appellate Tribunal as they apply to a Tribunal and 
accordingly references in that section to “Tribunal” shall be construed as 
references to “Appellate Tribunal” and references to “Recovery Officer” shall be 
deemed to have been omitted.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Salary and allowances and other terms and conditions of service of Presiding 
    Officers.—The salary and 
    allowances payable to and the other terms and conditions of service 
    (including pension, gratuity and other retirement benefits) of, <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[the 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] 
    shall be such as may be prescribed:
 
Provided 
    that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of 
    service of <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[the 
    Presiding officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal 
    shall be varied to his] disadvantage after appointment.
  
 
   







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Filling up of vacancies.—If, 
    for any reason other than temporary absence, any vacancy occurs in the 
    officer of <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[the 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate 
    Tribunal], then the Central Government shall appoint another person in 
    accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill the vacancy and the 
    proceedings may be continued before the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal 
    from the stage at which the vacancy is filled.

 

 
   

 
   





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Resignation and removal.—
<section><number>1</number>
    <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[The 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] 
    may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed to the Central 
    Government, resign his office:
 
Provided 
    that <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[the 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] 
    shall, unless he is permitted by the Central Government to relinquish his 
    office sooner, continue to hold office until the expiry of three months from 
    the date of receipt of such notice or until a person duly appointed as his 
    successor enters upon his office or until the expiry of his term of officer, 
    whichever is the earliest.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[The 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] 
    shall not be removed from his office except by an order made by the Central 
    Government on the ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity after 
    inquiry,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
in the case of the Presiding Officer of a Tribunal, made by a Judge 
    of a High Court;
 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>b</number>
in the case of <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[the 
    Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal], made by a Judge of the Supreme Court,
 
in which <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[the Presiding Officer of 
    a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] has been informed of 
    the charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in 
    respect of these charges.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for the 
    investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[the 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate 
    Tribunal].
 
   

 
  












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Orders constituting Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal to be final and not to 
    invalidate its proceedings.—No 
    order of the Central Government appointing any person as <footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[the 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] 
    shall be called in question in any manner, and no act or proceeding before a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal shall be called in question in any manner 
    on the ground merely of any defect in the constitution of a Tribunal or an 
    Appellate Tribunal.  

  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Jurisdiction, powers 
and authority of Tribunals.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
Tribunal shall exercise, on and from the appointed day, the jurisdiction, powers 
and authority to entertain and decide applications from the banks and financial 
institutions for recovery of debts due to such banks and financial institutions.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An Appellate Tribunal 
shall exercise, on and from the appointed day, the jurisdiction, powers and 
authority to entertain appeals against any order made, or deemed to have been 
made, by a Tribunal under this Act.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[<number>17A</number> 
    Power of Chairperson of Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson of an 
    Appellate Tribunal shall exercise general power of superintendence and 
    control over the Tribunals under his jurisdiction including the power of 
    appraising the work and recording the annual confidential reports of 
    Presiding Officers.

 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal having jurisdiction over the Tribunals 
    may, on the application of any of the parties or on his own motion after 
    notice to the parties and after hearing them, transfer any case from one 
    Tribunal for disposal to any other Tribunal.]

 

 
   





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Bar of 
Jurisdiction.—On 
and from the appointed day, no court or other authority shall have, or be 
entitled to exercise, any jurisdiction, powers or authority (except the Supreme 
Court, and a High Court exercising jurisdiction under articles 226 and 227 of 
the Constitution) in relation to the matters specified in section 17.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>19</number> 
    Application to the Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a bank or a financial institution 
    has to recover any debt from any person, it may make an application to the 
    Tribunal within the local limits of whose jurisdiction— 
 

 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the defendant, or each of the defendants where there are more than 
    one, at the time of making the application, actually and voluntarily resides 
    or carries on business or personally works for gain; or

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
any of the defendants, where there are more than one, at the time of 
    making the application, actually and voluntarily resides or carries on 
    business or personally works for gain; or

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the cause of action, wholly or in part, arises:

 
<footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[Provided 
    that the bank or financial institution may, with the permission of the Debts 
    Recovery Tribunal, on an application made by it, withdraw the application, 
    whether made before or after the Enforcement of Security Interest and 
    Recovery of Debts Laws (Amendment) Act, 2004 for the purpose of taking 
    action under the Securitisation and Reconstruction of Financial Assets and 
    Enforcement of Security Interest Act, 2002 (54 of 2002), if no such action 
    had been taken earlier under that Act:

 

 
Provided 
    further that any application made under the first proviso for seeking 
    permission from the Debts Recovery Tribunal to withdraw the application made 
    under sub‑section (1) shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible 
    and disposed of within thirty days from the date of such application:

 

 
Provided 
    also that in case the Debts Recovery Tribunal refuses to grant permission 
    for withdrawal of the application filed under this sub‑section, it shall 
    pass such orders after recording the reasons therefor.]

 

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 
    a bank or a financial institution, which has to recover its debt from any 
    person, has filed an application to the Tribunal under sub-section (1) and 
    against the same person another bank or financial institution also has claim 
    to recover its debt, then, the later bank or financial institution may join 
    the applicant bank or financial institution at any stage of the proceedings, 
    before the final order is passed, by making an application to that Tribunal. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    application under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be in such form 
    and accompanied by such documents or other evidence and by such fee as may 
    be prescribed:

 

 
Provided 
    that the fee may be prescribed having regard to the amount of debt to be 
    recovered:

 

 
Provided 
    further that nothing contained in this sub-section relating to fee shall 
    apply to cases transferred to the Tribunal under sub-section (1) of section 
    31.

 

 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On 
    receipt of the application under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the 
    Tribunal shall issue summons requiring the defendant to show cause within 
    thirty days of the service of summons as to why the relief prayed for should 
    not be granted.

 

 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    defendant shall, at or before the first hearing or within such time as the 
    Tribunal may permit, present a written statement of his defence.

 

 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where 
    the defendant claims to set-off against the applicant’s demand any 
    ascertained sum of money legally recoverable by him from such applicant, the 
    defendant may, at the first hearing of the application, but not afterwards 
    unless permitted by the Tribunal, present a written statement containing the 
    particulars of the debt sought to be set-off.

 

 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    written statement shall have the same effect as a plaint in a cross-suit so 
    as to enable the Tribunal to pass a final order in respect both of the 
    original claim and of the set-off.

 

 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A 
    defendant in an application may, in addition to his right of pleading a 
    set-off under sub-section (6), set up, by way of counter-claim against the 
    claim of the applicant, any right or claim in respect of a cause of action 
    accruing to the 
    defendant against the applicant either before or after the filing of the 
    application but before the defendant has delivered his defence or before the 
    time limited for delivering his defence has expired, whether such 
    counter-claim is in the nature of a claim for damages or not. 
 

 </section><section>
<number>9</number> A 
    counter-claim under sub-section (8) shall have the same effect as a 
    cross-suit so as to enable the Tribunal to pass a final order on the same 
    application, both on the original claim and on the counter-claim.

 

 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The 
    applicant shall be at liberty to file a written statement in answer to the 
    counter-claim of the defendant within such period as may be fixed by the 
    Tribunal.

 

 </section><section>
<number>11</number> 
    Where a defendant sets up a counter-claim and the applicant contends that 
    the claim thereby raised ought not to be disposed of by way of counter-claim 
    but in an independent action, the applicant may, at any time before issues 
    are settled in relation to the counter-claim, apply to the Tribunal for an 
    order that such counter-claim may be excluded, and the Tribunal may, on the 
    hearing of such application, make such order as it thinks fit. 

 

 </section><section>
<number>12</number> The 
    Tribunal may make an interim order (whether by way of injunction or stay or 
    attachment) against the defendant to debar him from transferring, alienating 
    or otherwise dealing with, or disposing of, any property and assets 
    belonging to him without the prior permission of the Tribunal.

 

 </section><section>
<number>13</number> (A) 
    Where, at any stage of the proceedings, the Tribunal is satisfied, by 
    affidavit or otherwise, that the defendant, with intent to obstruct or delay 
    or frustrate the execution of any order for the recovery of debt that may be 
    passed against him,—

 

 <subsection>
<number>i</number>
is about to dispose of the whole or any part of his property; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>
is about to remove the whole or any part of his property from the 
    local limits of the jurisdiction of the Tribunal; or

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>
is likely to cause any damage or mischief to the property or affect 
    its value by misuse or creating third party interest,

 
the Tribunal may direct the defendant, within 
    a time to be fixed by it, either to furnish security, in such sum as may be 
    specified in the order, to produce and place at the disposal of the 
    Tribunal, when required, the said property or the value of the same, or such 
    portion thereof as may be sufficient to satisfy the certificate for the 
    recovery of debt, or to appear and show cause why he should not furnish 
    security.
 <subsubsection>
<number>B</number> Where 
    the defendant fails to show cause why he should not furnish security, or 
    fails to furnish the security required, within the time fixed by the 
    Tribunal, the Tribunal may order the attachment of the whole or such portion 
    of the properties claimed by the applicant as the properties secured in his 
    favour or otherwise owned by the defendant as appears sufficient to satisfy 
    any certificate for the recovery of debt.

 

 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>14</number> The 
    applicant shall, unless the Tribunal otherwise directs, specify the property 
    required to be attached and the estimated value thereof.

 

 </section><section>
<number>15</number> The 
    Tribunal may also in the order direct the conditional attachment of the 
    whole or any portion of the property specified under sub-section (14).

 

 </section><section>
<number>16</number> If 
    an order of attachment is made without complying with the provisions of 
    sub-section (13), such attachment shall be void.

 

 </section><section>
<number>17</number> In 
    the case of disobedience of an order made by the Tribunal under sub-sections 
    (12), (13) and (18) or breach of any of the terms on which the order was 
    made, the Tribunal may order the properties of the person guilty of such 
    disobedience or breach to be attached and may also order such person to be 
    detained in the civil prison for a term not exceeding three months, unless 
    in the meantime the Tribunal directs his release.

 

 </section><section>
<number>18</number> 
    Where it appears to the Tribunal to be just and convenient, the Tribunal 
    may, by order—

 

 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
appoint a receiver of any property, whether before or after grant of 
    certificate for recovery of debt;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
remove any person from the possession or custody of the property; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
commit the same to the possession, custody or management of the 
    receiver;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
confer upon the receiver all such powers, as to bringing and 
    defending suits in the courts or filing and defending application before the 
    Tribunal and for the realization, management, protection, preservation and 
    improvement of the property, the collection of the rents and profits 
    thereof, the application and disposal of such rents and profits, and the 
    execution of documents as the owner himself has, or such of those powers as 
    the Tribunal thinks fit; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
appoint a Commissioner for preparation of an inventory of the 
    properties of the defendant or for the sale thereof.

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>19</number> 
    Where a certificate of recovery is issued against a company registered under 
    the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) the Tribunal may order the sale proceeds 
    of such company to be distributed among its secured creditors in accordance 
    with the provisions of section 529A of the Companies Act, 1956 and to pay 
    the surplus, if any, to the company.

 

 </section><section>
<number>20</number> The 
    Tribunal may, after giving the applicant and the defendant an opportunity of 
    being heard, pass such interim or final order, including the order for 
    payment of interest from the date on or before which payment of the amount 
    is found due upto the date of realisation or actual payment, on the 
    application as it thinks fit to meet the ends of justice.

 

 </section><section>
<number>21</number> The 
    Tribunal shall send a copy of every order passed by it to the applicant and 
    the defendant.

 

 </section><section>
<number>22</number> the 
    Presiding Officer shall issue a certificate under his signature on the basis 
    of the order of the Tribunal to the Recovery Officer for recovery of the 
    amount of debt specified in the certificate.

 

 </section><section>
<number>23</number> 
    Where the Tribunal, which has issued a certificate of recovery, is satisfied 
    that the property is situated within the local limits of the jurisdiction of 
    two or more Tribunals, it may send the copies of the certificate of recovery 
    for execution to such other Tribunals where the property is situated:

 

 
Provided 
    that in a case where the Tribunal to which the certificate of recovery is 
    sent for execution finds that it has no jurisdiction to comply with the 
    certificate of recovery, it shall return the same to the Tribunal which has 
    issued it.

 

 </section><section>
<number>24</number> The 
    application made to the Tribunal under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) 
    shall be dealt with by it as expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall 
    be made by it to dispose of the application finally within one hundred and 
    eighty days from the date of receipt of the application.

 

 </section><section>
<number>25</number> The 
    Tribunal may make such orders and give such directions as may be necessary 
    or expedient to give effect to its orders or to prevent abuse of its process 
    or to secure the ends of justice.]

  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Appeal 
to the Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as provided in sub-section (2), any person aggrieved by an order made, or 
deemed to have been made, by a Tribunal under this Act, may prefer an appeal to 
an Appellate Tribunal having jurisdiction in the matter.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal shall lie to 
the Appellate Tribunal from an order made by a Tribunal with the consent of the 
parties.
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every appeal under 
sub-section (1) shall be filed within a period of forty- 
five days from the date on which a copy of the order made, or deemed to have 
been made, by the Tribunal is received by him and it shall be in such form and 
be accompanied by such fee as may be prescribed:
 


 
Provided that the Appellate 
Tribunal may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period of 
forty-five days if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not 
filing it with in that period.
 


 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of an appeal 
under sub-section (1), the Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to 
the appeal, an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks 
fit, confirming, modifying or setting aside the order appealed against.
 


 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Appellate Tribunal 
shall send a copy of every order made by it to the parties to the appeal and to 
the concerned Tribunal.
 


 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The appeal filed before 
the Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (1) shall be dealt with by it as 
expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the 
appeal finally within six months from the date of receipt of the appeal.
 


  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Deposit of amount of 
debt due, on filing appeal.—Where an 
appeal is preferred by any person from whom the amount of debt is due to a bank 
or a financial institution or a consortium of banks or financial institutions, 
such appeal shall not be entertained by the Appellate Tribunal unless such 
person has deposited with the Appellate Tribunal seventy-five per cent. of the 
amount of debt so due from him as determined by the Tribunal under section 19:
 


 
Provided that the Appellate 
Tribunal may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, waive or reduce the amount 
to be deposited under this section.
 


  



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Procedure 
and Powers of the Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal.—

<section><number>1</number> The Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the 
procedure laid down by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), but shall 
be guided by the principles of natural justice and, subject to the other 
provisions of this Act and of any rules, the Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal 
shall have powers to regulate their own procedure including the places at which 
they shall have their sittings.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Tribunal and the 
Appellate Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging their functions 
under this Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the 
following matters, namely:—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on 
oath;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
requiring the discovery and production of documents;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
receiving evidence on affidavits;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
reviewing its decisions;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
dismissing an application for default or deciding it ex parte;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>
setting aside any order of dismissal of any application for default or 
any order passed by it ex parte;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>
any other matter which may be prescribed.

 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Any proceeding before 
the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial 
proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of 
section 196, of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Tribunal or the 
Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil court for all the purposes of 
section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974).
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Right to legal representation and Presenting Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A bank or a financial institution making an application to a Tribunal or an 
    appeal to an Appellate Tribunal may authorise one or more legal 
    practitioners or any of its officers to act as Presenting Officers and every 
    person so authorised by it may present its case before the Tribunal or the 
    Appellate Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    defendant may either appear in person or authorise one or more legal 
    practitioners or any of his or its officers to present his or its case 
    before the Tribunal or the Appellate Tribunal.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Limitation.—The 
provisions of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), shall, as far as may be, 
apply to an application made to a Tribunal.
 


  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Modes of recovery of 
debts.—The Recovery Officer shall, on 
receipt of the copy of the certificate under sub-section (7) of section 19, 
proceed to recover the amount of debt specified in the certificate by one or 
more of the following modes, namely:—
 


 <section>
 <number>a</number>
attachment and sale of the movable or immovable property of the 
defendant;

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
arrest of the defendant and his detention in prison;

 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
appointing a receiver for the management of the movable or immovable 
properties of the defendant.


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Validity of certificate and amendment thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall not be open to the defendant to dispute before the Recovery Officer 
    the correctness of the amount specified in the certificate, and no objection 
    to the certificate on any other ground shall also be entertained by the 
    Recovery Officer.

 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding the issue of a certificate to a Recovery Officer, the 
    Presiding Officer shall have power to withdraw the certificate or correct 
    any clerical or arithmetical mistake in the certificate by sending an 
    intimation to the Recovery Officer.

 

 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Presiding Officer shall intimate to the Recovery Officer any order 
    withdrawing or cancelling a certificate or any correction made by him under 
    sub-section (2).

 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Stay of proceedings 
under certificate and amendment or withdrawal thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding that a certificate has been issued to the Recovery Officer for 
the recovery of any amount, the Presiding Officer may grant time for the payment 
of the amount, and thereupon the Recovery Officer shall stay the proceedings 
until the expiry of the time so granted.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a certificate for 
the recovery of amount has been issued, the Presiding Officer shall keep the 
Recovery Officer informed of any amount paid or time granted for payment, 
subsequent to the issue of such certificate to the Recovery Officer.
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the order giving 
rise to a demand of amount for recovery of debt has been modified in appeal, 
and, as a consequence thereof the demand is reduced, the Presiding Officer shall 
stay the recovery of such part of the amount of the certificate as pertains to 
the said reduction for the period for which the appeal remains pending.
 


 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a certificate for 
the recovery of debt has been received by the Recovery Officer and subsequently 
the amount of the outstanding demands is reduced <footcitenum>28</footcitenum>[or enhanced] as a result of an 
appeal, the Presiding Officer shall, when the order which was the subject-matter 
of such appeal has become final and conclusive, amend the certificate or 
withdraw it, as the case may be.

  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
  
<number>28</number> Other modes of recovery.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a certificate has been issued to the Recovery Officer under sub-section 
(7) of section 19, the Recovery Officer may, without pre 

judice to the modes of recovery specified in section 25, recover the amount of 
debt by any one or more of the modes provided under this section.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any amount is due 
from any person to the defendant, the Recovery Officer may require such person 
to deduct from the said amount, the amount of debt due from the defendant under 
this Act and such person shall comply with any such requisition and shall pay 
the sum so deducted to the credit of the Recovery Officer:
 


 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub-section shall apply to any part of the amount exempt from attachment in 
execution of a decree of a civil court under section 60 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908).
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) The Recovery Officer 
may, at any time or from time to time, by notice in writing, require any person 
from whom money is due or may become due to the defendant or to any person who 
holds or may subsequently hold money for or on account of the defendant, to pay 
to the Recovery Officer either forthwith upon the money becoming due or being 
held or within the time specified in the notice (not being before the money 
becomes due or is held) so much of the money as is sufficient to pay the amount 
of debt due from the defendant or the whole of the money when it is equal to or 
less than that amount.
 


 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> A notice under this 
sub-section may be issued to any person who holds or may subsequently hold any 
money for or on account of the defendant jointly with any other person and for 
the purposes of this sub-section, the shares of the joint holders in such amount 
shall be presumed, until the contrary is proved, to be equal.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> A copy of the notice 
shall be forwarded to the defendant at his last address known to the Recovery 
Officer and in the case of a joint account to all the joint holders at their 
last addresses known to the Recovery Officer.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number> Save as otherwise 
provided in this sub-section, every person to whom a notice is issued under this 
sub-section shall be bound to comply with such notice, and, in particular, where 
any such notice is issued to a post office, bank, financial institution, or an 
insurer, it shall not be necessary for any pass book, deposit receipt, policy or 
any other document to be produced for the purpose of any entry, endorsement or 
the like to be made before the payment is made notwithstanding any rule, 
practice or requirement to the contrary.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number> Any claim respecting any 
property in relation to which a notice under this sub-section has been issued 
arising after the date of the notice shall be void as against any demand 
contained in the notice.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number> Where a person to whom 
a notice under this sub-section is sent objects to it by a statement on oath 
that the sum demanded or the part thereof is not due to the defendant or that he 
does not hold any money for or on account of the defendant, then, nothing 
contained in this sub-section shall be deemed to require such person to pay any 
such sum or part thereof, as the case may be, but if it is discovered that such 
statement was false in any material particular, such person shall be personally 
liable to the Recovery Officer to the extent of his own liability to the 
defendant on the date of the notice, or to the extent of the defendant’s 
liability for any sum due under this Act, whichever is less.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number> The Recovery Officer 
may, at any time or from time to time, amend or revoke any notice under this 
sub-section or extend the time for making any payment in pursuance of such 
notice.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number> The Recovery Officer 
shall grant a receipt for any amount paid in compliance with a notice issued 
under this sub-section, and the person so paying shall be fully discharged from 
his liability to the defendant to the extent of the amount so paid.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number> Any person discharging 
any liability to the defendant after the receipt of a notice under this 
sub-section shall be personally liable to the Recovery Officer to the extent of 
his own liability to the defendant so discharged or to the extent of the 
defendant’s liability for any debt due under this Act, whichever is less.
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number> If the person to whom a 
notice under this sub-section is sent fails to make payment in pursuance thereof 
to the Recovery Officer, he shall be deemed to be a defendant in default in 
respect of the amount specified in the notice and further proceedings may be 
taken against him for the realisation of the amount as if it were a debt due 
from him, in the manner provided in sections 25, 26 and 27 and the notice shall 
have the same effect as an attachment of a debt by the Recovery Officer in 
exercise of his powers under section 25.
 


 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Recovery Officer may 
apply to the court in whose custody there is money belonging to the defendant 
for payment to him of the entire amount of such money, or if it is more than the 
amount of debt due an amount sufficient to discharge the amount of debt so due.
 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> The Recovery Officer may, by 
order, at any stage of the execution of the certificate of recovery, require any 
person, and in case of a company, any of its officers against whom or which the 
certificate of recovery is issued, to declare on affidavit the particulars of 
his or its assets.]
 


 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Recovery Officer may 
recover any amount of debt due from the defendant by distraint and sale of his 
movable property in the manner laid down in the Third Schedule to the Income-Tax 
Act, 1961 (43 of 1961).
 


 
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number> Application of certain provisions of Income-tax 
      Act.—The provisions of the Second and Third 
      Schedules to the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) and the Income-tax 
      (Certificate Proceedings) Rules, 1962, as in force from time to time 
      shall, as far as possible, apply with necessary modifications as if the 
      said provisions and the rules referred to the amount of debt due under 
      this Act instead of to the Income-tax:  
 Provided that any reference under the said 
      provisions and the rules to the “assessee” shall be construed as a 
      reference to the defendant under this Act.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>30</footcitenum>[<number>30</number> Appeal against the order of 
Recovery Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in section 29, any 
person aggrieved by an order of the Recovery Officer made under this Act may, 
within thirty days from the date on which a copy of the order is issued to him, 
prefer an appeal to the Tribunal.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of an appeal under sub-section (1), 
the Tribunal may, after giving an opportunity to the appellant to be heard, and 
after making such inquiry as it deems fit, confirm, modify or set aside the 
order made by the Recovery Officer in exercise of his powers under sections 25 
to 28 (both inclusive).] 


  
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Transfer of pending 
cases.—
<section><number>1</number> Every suit or other 
proceeding pending before any court immediately before the date of establishment 
of a Tribunal under this Act, being a suit or proceeding the cause of action 
where on it is based is such that it would have been, if it had arisen after 
such establishment, within the jurisdiction of such Tribunal, shall stand 
transferred on that date to such Tribunal:
 


 
Provided that nothing in 
this sub-section shall apply to any appeal pending as aforesaid before any 
court.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any suit or other 
proceeding stands transferred from any court to a Tribunal under sub-section 
(1),—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the court shall, as soon as may be after such transfer, forward the 
records of such suit or other proceeding to the Tribunal; and

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the Tribunal may, on receipt of such records, proceed to deal with such 
suit or other proceeding, so far as may be, in the same manner as in the case of 
an application made under section 19 from the stage which was reached before 
such transfer or from any earlier stage 1[***] 
as the Tribunal may deem fit.

 
  







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>32</footcitenum>[<number>31A</number> Power of Tribunal to issue 
certificate of recovery in case of decree or order.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a decree or 
order was passed by any court before the commencement of the Recovery of Debts 
Due to Banks and Financial Institutions (Amendment) Act, 2000 and has not yet 
been executed, then, the decree-holder may apply to the Tribunal to pass an 
order for recovery of the amount.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of an 
application under sub-section (1), the Tribunal may issue a certificate for 
recovery to a Recovery Officer.
 


 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of a certificate under sub-section 
(2), the Recovery Officer shall proceed to recover the amount as if it was a 
certificate in respect of a debt recoverable under this Act.] 


  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[<number>32</number> Chairperson, Presiding 
Officer and staff of Appellate Tribunal and Tribunal to be public servants.—The 
Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal, the Presiding Officer of a Tribunal, the 
Recovery Officer and other officers and employees of an Appellate Tribunal and a 
Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 
of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).]
 


 
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
    Government or against <footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[the 
    Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or the Chairperson of an Appellate Tribunal] 
    or against the Recovery Officer for anything which is in good faith done or 
    intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made 
    thereunder. 


  
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>34</number> Act to have over-riding effect.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as 
      provided under sub-section (2), the provisions of this Act shall have 
      effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any 
      other law for the time being in force or in any instrument having effect 
      by virtue of any law other than this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The provisions of this Act or the rules made 
      thereunder shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the 
      Industrial Finance Corporation Act, 1948 (15 of 1948), the State Financial 
      Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951), the Unit Trust of India Act, 1963 (52 
      of 1963), the Industrial Reconstruction Bank of India Act, 1984 (62 of 
      1984) <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[, the Sick Industrial Companies (Special 
      Provisions) Act, 1985 (1 of 1986) and the Small Industries Development 
      Bank of India Act, 1989 (39 of 1989)].  
  
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Power 
to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette make such 
provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
 


 
Provided that no 
such order shall be made after the expiry of the period of three years from the 
date of commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid before each 
House of Parliament.
 


  
 
  



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may, provide for all or any of 
the following matters, namely:—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the salaries and allowances and other terms and conditions of service of <footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[the Chairpersons, the Presiding Officers], Recovery Officers and 
other officers and employees of the Tribunal and the Appellate Tribunal under 
sections 7, 12 and 13;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the procedure for the investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of <footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[the Chairpersons of Appellate Tribunals and the Presiding 
Officers of the Tribunals] under sub-section (3) of section 15;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the form in which an application may be made under section 19, the 
documents and other evidence by which such application shall be accompanied and 
the fees payable in respect of the filing of such application;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
the form in which an appeal may be filed before the Appellate Tribunal 
under section 20 and the fees payable in respect of such appeal;

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
any other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed.

 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Every notification issued 
under sub-section (4) of section 1, section 3 and section 8 and every rule made 
by the Central Government under this Act, shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the notification or rule or both Houses agree that 
the notification or rule should not be issued or made, the notification or rule 
shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as 
the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that 
notification or rule.]
 


 
  










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Repeal 
and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Recovery of Debts Due to Banks and Financial Institutions Ordinance, 1993 is 
hereby repealed.
 


 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal, anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance, shall be 
deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this 
Act.

  



 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins.
by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs.
by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 3, for clause (g) (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins.
by Act 30 of 2004, sec. 19 (w.r.e.f. 11-11-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins.
by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs.
by Act 28 of 1995, sec. 2, for “sixty years” (w.e.f. 9-8-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs.
by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 4, for “with a Recovery Officer” (w.r.e.f.
17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs.
by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 4, for “The Recovery Officer” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs.
by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 4, for "Recovery Officer" (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> 
Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 5 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of the 
    Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “Presiding Officer of the 
    Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for "The Presiding Officer of an 
    Appellate Tribunal" (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for "The Presiding Officer of an 
    Appellate Tribunal" (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>
Subs. by Act 28 of 1995, sec. 3, for "sixty-two years" (w.e.f. 
    9-8-1995).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate 
    Tribunal" (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 6, for “the said Presiding Officers 
    shall be varied to their” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate 
    Tribunal" (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate 
    Tribunal" (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc " 4. Subs. by Act 1 
    of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a Tribunal or an
Appellate Tribunal\" (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 7, for “the said Presiding Officer” (w.r.e.f. 
    17-1-2000). tc " 6. Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 7, 
    for “the said Presiding Officer” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of an 
    Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc " 2. 
    Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of an Appellate 
    Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 7, for “the Presiding Officer concerned” 
    (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc " 3. Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, 
    sec. 7, for “the Presiding Officer concerned” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 7, for “the aforesaid Presiding Officer” 
    (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc " 4. Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, 
    sec. 7, for “the aforesaid Presiding Officer” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>
Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 8 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc 
    " 5. Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 8 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 9, for section 19 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 9, for section 19 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>
Ins. by Act 30 of 2004, sec. 20 (w.r.e.f. 11-11-2004). tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 30 of 2004, sec. 20 (w.r.e.f. 11-11-2004)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> 
Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 10 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc " 
1. Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 10 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> 
Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 11 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000). tc " 
1. Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 11 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> 
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 12, for section 30 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> 
The words “or de novo” omitted by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 13 (w.r.e.f. 
17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> 
Ins. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 14 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number> 
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 15, for section 32 (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 2, for “the Presiding Officer of a 
    Tribunal or an Appellate Tribunal” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 
      16, for “and the Sick Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985 
      (1 of 1986)” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> 
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 17, for “the Presiding Officers” (w.r.e.f. 
17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number> 
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 17, for “the Presiding Officer of the Tribunal and 
Appellate Tribunals” (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> 
Subs. by Act 1 of 2000, sec. 17, for sub-section (3) (w.r.e.f. 17-1-2000).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>