<act><title>

THE AIRPORTS AUTHORITY OF 
    INDIA ACT, 1994</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, commencement and application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Airports Authority of India Act, 1994.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    applies to—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   all 
    airports whereat air transport services are operated or are intended to be 
    operated, other than airports and airfields belonging to, or subject to the 
    control of, any armed force of the Union;
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number>   all private airports 
    insofar as it relates to providing air traffic service, to issue directions 
    under section 37 to them and for the purposes of Chapter VA;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   all civil 
    enclaves;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   all 
    aeronautical communication stations; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   all 
    training stations, establishments and workshops relating to air transport 
    services.
</subsection>





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    “aeronautical communication station” means a station in the aeronautical 
    communication service which includes aeronautical practising service, 
    aeronautical fixed service, aeronautical mobile service and aeronautical 
    radio communication service;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “airport” 
    means a landing and taking off area for aircrafts, usually with runways and 
    aircraft maintenance and passenger facilities and includes aerodrome as 
    defined in Clause (2) of section 2 of the Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 1934);
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    “airstrip” means an area used or intended to be used for the landing and 
    take-off of aircrafts with short take-off and landing characteristics and 
    includes all buildings and structure thereon or appertaining thereto;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “air 
    traffic service” includes flight information service, alerting service, air 
    traffic advisory service, air traffic control service, area control service, 
    approach control service and airport control service;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “air 
    transport service” means any service, for any kind of remuneration, 
    whatsoever, for the transport by air of persons, mail or any other thing, 
    animate or inanimate, whether such service relates to a single flight or 
    series of flights;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   
    “appointed day” means such date as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint for the purposes of section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   
    “Authority” means the Airports Authority of India constituted under section 
    3;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   
    “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Authority appointed under clause 
    (a) of sub-section (3) of section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “civil 
    enclave” means the area, if any, allotted at an airport belonging to any 
    armed force of the Union, for use by persons availing of any air transport 
    services from such airport or for the handling of baggage or cargo by such 
    service, and includes land comprising of any building and structure on such 
    area;
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   
    “heliport” means an area, either at ground level or elevated on a structure, 
    used or intended to be used for the landing and take-off of helicopters and 
    includes any area for parking helicopters and all buildings and structures 
    thereon or appertaining thereto;
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   
    “International Airports Authority” means the International Airports 
    Authority of India constituted under section 3 of the International Airports 
    Authority Act, 1971 (43 of 971);
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   
    “member” means a member of the Authority and includes the Chairperson, but 
    does not include, for the purposes of sections 4, 5, 6 and 7, an ex 
    officio member referred to in clause (b) of sub-section (3) of section 
    3;
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>   “National 
    Airports Authority” means the National Airports Authority constituted under 
    section 3 of the National Airports Authority Act, 1985 (64 of 1985);
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>   
    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>

 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>nn</number>   “private airport” 
    means an airport owned, developed or managed by—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    any person or agency other than the Authority or any State Government; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any 
    person or agency jointly with the Authority or any State Govern­ment or both 
    where the share of such person or agency, as the case may be, in the assets 
    of the private airport is more than fifty per cent.;]
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>   
    “regulations” means regulations made under this Act.
</section>





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution and incorporation of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from the appointed day*, the Central Government shall, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an authority to be called 
    the Airports Authority of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Authority shall be a body corporate by the name aforesaid having perpetual 
    succession and a common seal, with power, subject to the provisions of this 
    Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property both movable and immovable, 
    and to contract and shall be the said name sue and be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Authority shall consist of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a 
    Chairperson to be appointed by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
    Director General of Civil Aviation, or an officer not below the rank of the 
    Deputy Director General of Civil Aviation, to be appointed by the Central 
    Government, ex officio;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   not 
    less than eight and not more than fourteen members to be appointed by the 
    Central Government.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Chairperson shall be a whole-time member and other members referred to in 
    clause (c) of sub-section (3) may be appointed as whole-time or part-time 
    members as the Central Government may think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Chairperson and the members referred to in clause (c) of sub-section (3) shall be chosen from among persons who have special knowledge 
    and experience in air transport or any other transport services, industry, 
    commercial or financial matters or administration and from among persons who 
    are capable of representing organisations of workers and consumers.





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Disqualification for office of member.—A 
    person shall be disqualified for being appointed as a member if he,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   has 
    been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence, which in the 
    opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   is an undischarged insolvent; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   is of 
    unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   has been 
    removed or dismissed from the service of the Government or a body corporate 
    owned or controlled by the Government; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   has in 
    the opinion of the Central Government such financial or other interest in 
    the Authority as is likely to affect prejudicially the discharge by him of 
    his function as a member.
</section>
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Term of office and conditions of service of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of section 6,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   every 
    whole-time member (other than the ex officio member) shall hold 
    office for a period of five years from the date on which he assumes office 
    or till he attains the age of sixty years, whichever is earlier, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   every 
    part-time member (other than the ex officio member) shall hold office 
    for a period of three years from the date on which he assumes office:
 
Provided that the Central 
    Government may,—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   terminate the appointment of any whole-time member, who is not a 
    servant of the Government, after giving him notice for a period of not less 
    than three months or, in lieu thereof, on payment of an amount equal to his 
    salary and allowances, if any, for a period of three months;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   terminate the appointment of any part-time member who is not a servant 
    of the Government after giving him notice for such period as may be 
    prescribed; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>   terminate at any time the appointment of any member who is a servant 
    of the Government.
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    other conditions of service of the members shall be such as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    member may resign his office by giving notice in writing for such period as 
    may be prescribed, to the Central Government and, on such resignation being 
    notified in the Official Gazette by that Government, such member shall be 
    deemed to have vacated his office.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Vacation of office of member.—The 
    Central Government shall remove a member if he—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   becomes 
    subject to any of the disqualifications mentioned in
    section 4:
 
Provided that no member shall be removed on the ground that he has become 
    subject to the disqualification mentioned in clause (e) of that section, 
    unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the 
    matter; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   refuses 
    to act or becomes incapable of acting; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   is, 
    without obtaining leave of absence from the Authority, absent from three 
    consecutive meetings of the Authority; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   in the 
    opinion of the Central Government, has so abused his position as to render 
    his continuance in office detrimental to the public interest:
 
Provided that no member shall be removed under this clause unless he has 
    been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.
</section>
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Eligibility of member for re-appointment.—Any 
    person ceasing to be a member shall, unless disqualified under section 4, be 
    eligible for re-appointment.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall meet at such times and places, and shall observe such 
    rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of the business at its 
    meetings (including the quorum at such meetings) as may be provided by 
    regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson, or, if for any reason he is unable to attend any meeting of the 
    Authority, any other member chosen by the members present at the meeting 
    shall preside at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    questions which come up before any meeting of the Authority shall be decided 
    by a majority of the votes of the members present and voting, and, in the 
    event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson, or in his absence, the 
    person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of the Authority.—No 
    act or proceeding of the Authority shall be invalid merely reason of—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   any 
    vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of the Authority; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   any 
    defect in the appointment of a person acting as a member of the Authority; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   any 
    irregularity in the procedure of the Authority not affecting the merits of 
    the case.
</section>
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Appointment of officers and other employees of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of enabling it efficiently to discharge its functions under 
    this Act, the Authority shall, subject to the provisions of section 18 to 
    and to such rules as may be made in this behalf, appoint (whether on 
    deputation or otherwise) such number of officers and other employees as it 
    may consider necessary:
 
Provided 
    that the appointment of such category of officers, as may be specified after 
    consultation with the Chairperson in such rules, shall be subject to the 
    approval of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of section 18, every officer or other employee 
    appointed by the Authority shall be subject to such conditions of service 
    and shall be entitled to such remuneration as may be determined by 
    regulations.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>11</number> 
      Authority to act on business principles.—In the discharge of its 
      functions under this Act, the Authority shall act, so far as may be, on 
      business principles.
  
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Functions of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the rules, if any, made by the Central Government in this behalf, 
    it shall be the function of the Authority to manage the airports, the civil 
    enclaves and the aeronautical communication stations efficiently.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall be the duty of the Authority to provide air traffic service and air 
    transport service at any airport and civil enclaves.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in 
    sub-sections (1) and (2), the Authority may—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   plan, 
    develop, construct and maintain runways, taxiways, aprons and terminals and 
    ancillary buildings at the airports and civil enclaves;
 </subsection><subsection>

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> 
      establish airports, or assist in the establishment of private airports, by 
    rendering such technical, financial or other assistance which the Central 
    Govern­ment may consider necessary for such purpose;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   plan, 
    procure, instal and maintain navigational aids, communication equipment, 
    beacons and ground aids at the airports and at such locations as may be 
    considered necessary for safe navigation and operation of aircrafts;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   provide 
    air safety services and search and rescue, facilities in co-ordination with 
    other agencies;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
    establish schools or institutions or centres for the training of its 
    officers and employees in regard to any matter connected with the purposes 
    of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   
    construct residential buildings for its employees;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   
    establish and maintain hotels, restaurants and restrooms at or near the airports;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   
    establish warehouses and cargo complexes at the airports for the storage or 
    processing of goods;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   arrange 
    for postal, money exchange, insurance and telephone facilities for the use 
    of passengers and other persons at the airports and civil enclaves;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   make 
    appropriate arrangements for watch and ward at the airports and civil 
    enclaves;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   
    regulate and control the plying of vehicles, and the entry and exit of 
    passengers and visitors, in the airports and civil enclaves with due regard 
    to the security and protocol functions of the Government of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   develop 
    and provide consultancy, construction or management services, and undertake 
    operations in India 
    and abroad in relation to airports, air-navigation services, ground aids and 
    safety services or any facilities thereat;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   
    establish and mange heliports and airstrips;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   provide 
    such transport facility as are, in the opinion of the Authority, necessary 
    to the passengers travelling by air;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   form one 
    or more companies under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or under any 
    other law relating to companies to further the efficient discharge of the 
    functions imposed on it by this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   take 
    all such steps as may be necessary or convenient for, or may be incidental 
    to, the exercise of any power or the discharge of any function conferred or 
    imposed on it by this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>   perform 
    any other function considered necessary or desirable by the Central 
    Government for ensuring the safe and efficient operation of aircraft to, 
    from and across the air space of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>   
    establish training institutes and workshops;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>   any 
    other activity at the airports and the civil enclaves in the best commercial 
    interests of the Authority including cargo handling, setting up of joint 
    ventures for the discharge of any function assigned to the Authority.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In 
    the discharge of its functions under this section, the Authority shall have 
    due regard to the development of air transport service and to the 
    efficiency, economy and safety of such service.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Nothing contained in this section shall be construed as—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   authorising the disregard by the Authority of any law for the time being in 
    force; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   authorising any person to institute any proceeding in respect of duty or 
    liability to which the Authority or its officers or other employees would 
    not otherwise be subject.
</subsection>

 
 
The Authority shall 
    manage the airports, the civil enclaves, and aeronantical communication 
    stations, subject to any rule made by the Central Government in this regard.






  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>12A</number> Lease by 
    the authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Authority may, in the 
    public interest or in the interest of  better management of airports, make a 
    lease of the premises of an airport (including buildings and structures 
    thereon and appertaining thereto) to carry out some of its functions under 
    section 12 as the Authority may deem fit:
 
Provided 
    that such lease shall not affect the functions of the Authority under 
    section 12 which relates to air traffic service or watch and ward at 
    airports and civil enclaves.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    lease under sub-section (1) shall be made without the previous approval of 
    the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    money, payable by the lessee in terms of the lease made under sub-­section 
    (1), shall form part of the fund of the Authority and shall be credited 
    thereto as if such money is the receipt of the Authority for all purposes of
    section 24.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    lessee, who has been assigned any function of the Authority under 
    sub-section (1), shall have all the powers of the Authority necessary for 
    the perfor­mance of such function in terms of the lease.]





  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Undertakings of the International Airports Authority and the National 
    Airports Authority to vest in the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On and from the appointed day, there shall be transferred to, and vest in, 
    the Authority constituted under section 3, the undertakings of the 
    International Airports Authority and the National Airports Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    undertaking of the International Airports Authority or the National Airports 
    Authority which is transferred to, and which vests in, the Authority under 
    sub-section (1) shall be deemed to include all assets, rights, powers, 
    authorities and privileges and all property movable and immovable, real or 
    personal, corporeal or incorporeal, present or contingent, or whatever 
    nature and wheresoever situate, including lands, buildings, machinery, 
    equipments, works, workshops, cash balances, capital, reserves, reserve 
    funds, investments, tenancies, leases and book debts and all other rights 
    and interests arising out of such property as were immediately before the 
    appointed day in the ownership, possession or power of the International 
    Airports Authority, or as the case may be, the National Airports Authority, 
    in relation to its undertaking, whether within or outside India, all books 
    of account and documents relating thereto and shall also be deemed to 
    include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind then 
    subsisting of the International Airports Authority, or as the case may be 
    the National Airports Authority in relation to its undertaking.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    General effect of vesting of undertaking in the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    All contracts, agreements and working arrangements subsisting immediately 
    before the appointed day and affecting the International Airports Authority, 
    or as the case may be, the National Airports Authority shall, in so far as 
    they relate to the International Airports Authority, or as the case may be, 
    the National Airports Authority, cease to have effect or be enforceable 
    against the International Airports Authority, or as the case may be, the 
    National Airports Authority and shall be of as full force and effect against 
    or in favour of the Authority in which the undertakings have vested by 
    virtue of this Act and enforceable as fully and effectually as if, instead 
    of the International Airports Authority, or as the case may be, the National 
    Airports Authority, the Authority had been named therein or had been a party 
    thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    proceeding, suit or cause of action pending or existing immediately before 
    the appointed day by or against the International Airports Authority or the 
    National Airports Authority in relation to its undertakings may, as from 
    that day, be continued and enforced by or against the Authority in which it 
    has vested by virtue of this Act, as it might have been enforced by or 
    against the International Airports Authority or the National Airports 
    Authority if this Act had not been passed, and shall cease to be enforceable 
    by or against the International Airports Authority, or as the case may be, 
    the National Airports Authority.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Licences, etc., to be deemed to have been granted to the Authority.—With 
    effect from appointed day, all licences, permits, quotas and exemptions, 
    granted to the International Airports Authority or the National Airports 
    Authority in connection with the affairs and business of the International 
    Airports Authority, or as the case may be, the National Airports Authority, 
    under any law for the time being in force, shall be deemed to have been 
    granted to the Authority in which the undertakings of the International 
    Airports Authority and the National Airports Authority have vested by virtue 
    of this Act.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Tax exemption or benefit to continue to have effect.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any exemption from, or any assessment with respect to, any tax has 
    been granted or made or any benefit by way of set off or carry forward, as 
    the case may be, of any unabsorbed depreciation or investment allowance or 
    other allowance or loss has been extended or is available to the 
    International Airports Authority or the National Airports Authority, under 
    the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), such exemption, assessment or benefit 
    shall continue to have effect in relation to the Authority in which the 
    undertakings of the International Airports Authority and the National 
    Airports Authority have vested by virtue of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 
    any payment made by the International Airports Authority or the National 
    Airports Authority is exempt from deduction of the tax at source under any 
    provision of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), the exemption from tax 
    will continue to be available as if the provisions of the said Act made 
    applicable to the International Airports Authority or the National Airports 
    Authority were operative in relation to the Authority in which the 
    undertakings of the International Airports Authority and the National 
    Airports have vested by virtue of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    transfer and vesting of the undertakings or any part thereof in terms of 
    section 13 shall not be construed as a transfer within the meaning of the 
    Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) for the purposes of capital gains.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Guarantee to be operative.—Any 
    guarantee given for or in favour of the International Airports Authority or 
    the National Airports Authority with respect to any loan or lease finance 
    shall continue to be operative in relation to the Authority in which the 
    undertakings of the International Airports Authority and the National 
    Airports Authority have vested by virtue of this Act.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Provisions in respect of officers and other employees of the International 
    Airports Authority and the National Airports Authority.—
    
<section><number>1</number>
<subsection><number>a</number> Every officer or other employee of the International Airports 
    Authority serving in its employment immediately before the appointed day 
    shall, in so far as such officer or other employee is employed in connection 
    with the undertaking which has vested in the Authority by virtue of this 
    Act, becomes, as from the appointed day, an officer or, as the case may be, 
    other employee of the International Airports Division of the Authority.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Every 
    officer or other employee of the National Airports Authority serving in its 
    employment immediately before the appointed day shall, in so far as such 
    officer or other employee is employed in connection with the undertaking 
    which has vested in the Authority by virtue of this Act, becomes, as from 
    the appointed day, an officer or, as the case may be, other employee of the 
    National Airports Division of the Authority.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    officer or other employee of the International Airports Authority or the 
    National Airports Authority who becomes an officer or, as the case may be, 
    other employee of the Authority, as referred to in sub-section (1), shall 
    hold his office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same 
    remuneration, upon the same terms and conditions, with the same obligation 
    and with the same rights and privileges as to leave, passage, insurance, 
    superannuation scheme, provident fund, other funds, retirement, pension, 
    gratuity and other benefits as he would have held under the International 
    Airport Authority or, as the case may be, the National Airports Authority if 
    its undertaking had not vested in the Authority and shall continue to do as 
    an officer or other employee, as the case may be, of the Authority or until 
    the expiry of a period of one year from the appointed day if such officer or 
    other employee opts not to be the officer or other employee of the Authority 
    within such period:
 
Provided 
    that if the Authority thinks it expedient to extend the period so fixed, it 
    may extend the same up to a maximum period of one year.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where 
    an officer or other employee of the International Authority or the National 
    Airports Authority opts under sub-section (2) not to be in the employment or 
    service of the Authority in which the undertakings of the International 
    Airports Authority and the national Airports Authority have vested, such 
    officer or other employee shall be deemed to have resigned from the 
    respective cadre.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 
    of 1947) or in any other law for the time being in force, the transfer of 
    the services of any officer or other employee of the International Airports 
    Authority or the National Airports Authority to the Authority shall not 
    entitle such officer or other employee to any compensation under this Act or 
    under any other law for the time being in force and no such claim shall be 
    entertained by any Court, Tribunal or other authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    officers and other employees who have retired before the appointed day from 
    the service of the International Airports Authority or the National Airports 
    Authority and are entitled to any benefits, rights or privileges shall be 
    entitled to receive the same benefits, rights or privileges from the 
    Authority in which the undertaking of the International Airports Authority 
    and the National Airports Authority have vested. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    trusts of the Provident Fund and Group Insurance and Superannuation Scheme 
    of the International Airports Authority or the National Airports Authority 
    and any other bodies created for the welfare of officers or employees would 
    continue to discharge their functions in the Authority as was being done 
    hitherto in the International Airports Authority or the National Airports 
    Authority and tax exemption granted to Provident Fund or Group Insurance and 
    Superannuation Scheme would continue to be applied to the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> After 
    the expiry of the period of one year, or the extended period, as referred to 
    in sub-section (2), all the officers and other employees transferred and 
    appointed to the Authority, other than those opting not to be the officers 
    or employees of the Authority within such period, shall be governed by the 
    rules and regulations made by the Authority in respect of the service 
    conditions of the officers and other employees of the said Authority. 
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Compulsory acquisition of land for the Authority.—Any 
    land required by the Authority for the discharge of its functions under this 
    Act shall be deemed to be needed for a public purpose and such land may be 
    acquired for the Authority under the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, 
    1894 (1 of 1894) or of any other corresponding law for the time being in 
    force.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>20</number> 
      Contracts by the Authority.—Subject to the provisions of 
      section 21, the Authority shall be competent to enter into and perform and 
      contract necessary for the discharge of its functions under this 
      Act.
  
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>21</number> Mode 
      of executing contracts on behalf of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> Every contract shall, on 
      behalf of the Authority, be made by the Chairperson or such other member 
      of such officer of the Authority as may be generally or specially 
      empowered in this behalf by the Authority and such contracts or class of 
      contracts as may be specified in the regulations shall be sealed with the 
      common seal of the Authority:
 Provided 
      that no contract exceeding such value or amount as the Central Government 
      may, from time to time, by order, fix in this behalf shall be made unless 
      it has been previously approved by the Authority:
 Provided 
      further that no contract for the acquisition or sale of immovable property 
      or for the lease of any such property for a term exceeding thirty years 
      and no other contract exceeding such value or amount as the Central 
      Government may, from time to time, by order fix in this behalf shall be 
      made unless it has been previously approved by the Central 
      Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject 
      to the provisions of sub-section (1), the form and manner in which any 
      contract shall be made under this Act shall be such as may be specified by 
      regulations. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No 
      contract which is not in accordance with the provisions of this Act and 
      the regulations shall be binding on the Authority.
  
  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Power of the Authority to charge fees, rent, etc.—The 
    Authority may,— 
 
 <section>
<number>i</number>   with 
    the previous approval of the Central Government, charges fees or rent—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    for the landing, housing or parking of aircraft or for any other service or 
    facility offered in connection with aircraft operations at any airport, 
    heliport or airstrip;
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this sub-clause “aircraft” does not include an aircraft belonging to any 
    armed force of the Union and “aircraft operations” does not include 
    operations of any aircraft belonging to the said force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    for providing air traffic services, ground safety services, aeronautical 
    communications and navigational aids and meteorogical services at any 
    airports and at any aeronautical communication station;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   for the 
    amenities given to the passengers and visitors at any airport, civil 
    enclave, heliport or airstrip;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
    for the use and employment by persons of facilities and other services 
    provided by the Authority at any airport, civil enclave, heliport or airstrip;
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   with 
    due regard to the instructions that the Central Government may give to the 
    Authority, from time to time, charge fees or rent from persons who are given 
    by the Authority any facility for carrying on any trade or business at any 
    airport, heliport or airstrip.
</section>
  

  


</article> 

  
 <title></title>
 <article><footcitenum>6</footcitenum><title>[<number>22A</number> Power of Authority to levy development fees at 
airports. </title>— <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[The authority may,— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> after the previous approval of the Central Government in this behalf, 
  levy on, and collect from, the embarking passengers at an airport other than 
  the major airports referred to in clause (h) of section 2 of the Airports 
  Economic Regulatory Authority of India Act, 2008 the development fees at the 
  rate as may be prescribed; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> levy on, and collect from, the embarking passengers at major airport 
  referred to in clause (h) of section 2 of the Airports Economic Regulatory 
  Authority of India Act, 2008 the development fees at the rate as may be 
  determined under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 13 of the Airports 
  Economic Regulatory Authority of India Act, 2008, </section>
 and such fees shall be credited to the Authority and shall be regulated and 
utilised in the prescribed manner, for the purposes of—] 
 
 <section><number>a</number> funding or financing the costs of upgradation, expansion or 
  develop­ment of the airport at which the fee is collected; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> establishment or development of a new airport in lieu of the airport 
  referred to in clause (a); or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> investment in the equity in respect of shares to be subscribed by the 
  Authority in companies engaged in establishing, owning, developing, 
  operat­ing or maintaining a private airport in lieu of the airport 
  referred to in clause (a) or advancement of loans to such companies or other 
  persons engaged in such activities.] </section>


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Additional capital and grant to the Authority by the Central Government.—The 
    Central Government may, after due appropriation made by Parliament by law in 
    this behalf,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   provide 
    any capital that may be required by the Authority for the discharge of its 
    functions under this Act or for any purpose connected therewith on such 
    terms and conditions at that Government may determine;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   pay to 
    the Authority, on such terms and conditions as the Central Government may 
    determine, by way of loans or grants such sums of money as that Government 
    may consider necessary for the efficient discharge by the Authority of its 
    functions under this Act.
</section>

 
 
The Central Government 
    may provide loan or grant to the Authority for its proper functioning, 
    subject to approval of such loan or grant by Parliament.



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Fund of the Authority and its investment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall have its own fund and all receipts of the Authority 
    shall be credited thereto and all payments of the Authority shall be made 
    therefrom.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Authority shall have power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to spend 
    such sums as it thinks fit to cover all administrative expenses of the 
    Authority and on objects or for purposes authorised by this Act and such 
    sums shall be treated as expenditure out of the fund of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    moneys standing at the credit of the Authority which cannot immediately be 
    applied as provided in sub-section (2), shall be—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    deposited in the State Bank of India or any such Scheduled bank or banks or 
    other public financial institutions subject to such conditions as may, from 
    time to time, be specified by the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   invested 
    in the securities of the Central Government or in such manner as may be 
    prescribed.
</subsection>
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this sub-section, “Scheduled bank” has the same meaning as in clause (e) of 
    section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Allocation of surplus funds.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority may, from time to time, set apart such amounts as it thinks 
    fit as a reserve fund or funds for the purpose of expanding existing 
    facilities or services or creating new facilities or services at any 
    airport, civil enclave, heliport or airstrip or for the purpose of providing 
    against any temporary decrease of revenue or increase of expenditure from 
    transient causes or for purposes of replacement or for meeting expenditure 
    arising from loss or damage from fire, cyclone, air-crash or other accident 
    or for meeting any liability arising out of any act or commission in the 
    discharge of its functions under this Act:
 
Provided 
    that without prejudice to the right of the Authority to establish specific 
    reserves for one or more specific purposes, the Authority shall also have 
    the power to establish a general reserve:
 
Provided 
    further that the sums set apart annually in respect of each or any of the 
    specific and general reserves and the aggregate at any time of such sums 
    shall not exceed such limits as may, from time to time, be fixed in that 
    behalf by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> After 
    making provision for such reserve fund or funds and for bad and doubtful 
    debts, depreciation in assets and all other matters which are usually 
    provided for by companies registered and incorporated under the Companies 
    Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the Authority shall pay the balance of its annual net 
    profits to the Central Government.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>26</number> 
      Submission of programme of activities and financial 
      estimates.— 
<section><number>1</number> The Authority shall, 
      before the commencement of each financial year, prepare a statement of the 
      programme of its activities during the forthcoming financial year as well 
      as financial estimate in respect thereof. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The 
      statement prepared under sub-section (1) shall, not less than three months 
      before the commencement of each financial year, be submitted for approval 
      to the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The 
      statement and the financial estimates of the Authority may, with the 
      approval of the Central Government, be revised by the 
      Authority.
  
  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Borrowing powers of the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority may, with the consent of the Central Government or in 
    accordance with the terms of any general or special authority given to it by 
    the Central Government, borrow money from any source by the issue of bonds, 
    debentures or such other instruments as it may deem fit for discharging all 
    or any of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government may guarantee in such manner as it thinks fit, the 
    repayment of the principal and the payment of interest thereon with respect 
    to the loans borrowed by the Authority under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Subject to such limits as the Central Government may, from time to time, lay 
    down, the Authority may borrow temporarily by way of overdraft or otherwise 
    such amounts as it may require for discharging its functions under this Act.

 
 
The Authority may 
    borrow money from any source by way of issuing bond, debenture or any such 
    instrument subject to prior consent of the Central Government. The Central 
    Government may guarantee for repayment of such loans.



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts including the profit and loss 
    account and the balance-sheet in such form as may be prescribed by the 
    Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General 
    of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Authority shall be audited annually by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India and any expenditure incurred by him in connection 
    with such audit shall be payable by the Authority to the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any person appointed by him in 
    connection with the audit of the accounts of the Authority shall have the 
    same rights and privileges and authority in connection with such audit as 
    the Comptroller and Auditor-General has in connection with the audit of 
    Government accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the 
    production of books, accounts, connected vouchers, documents and papers and 
    inspect any of the offices of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the Authority as certified by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India or any other person appointed by him in this behalf 
    together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the 
    Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to be laid 
    before both Houses of Parliament.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

[<number>28A</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Chapter, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “airport 
    premises” means any premises,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    belonging to airport; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    taken on lease for the purposes of airport;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   
    acquired for the Authority under the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, 
    1894 (1 of 1894) or any other corresponding law for the time being in force.
</subsection>
 
Explanation.—For the removal of 
    doubts, it is hereby declared that for the purposes of this clause, airport 
    includes private airport;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “eviction 
    officer” means an officer of the Authority appointed as such by it under 
    section 28B;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   
    “premises” means any land or building or part of a building, and includes—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    the garden, grounds and outhouses, if any, appertaining to such building or 
    part of a building; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    any fittings affixed to such building or part of a building for more 
    beneficial enjoyment thereof;
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “rent”, 
    in relation to any airport premises, means the consideration payable 
    periodically for the authorised occupation of the premises, and includes—
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    any charge for electricity, water or any other service in connec­tion with 
    the occupation of the premises; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    any tax, by whatever name called, payable in respect of the premises;
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   
    “Tribunal” means the Airport Appellate Tribunal established under 
    sub-section (1) of section 28-I;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   
    “unauthorised occupation”, in relation to any airport premises, means the 
    occupation by any person of the airport premises without authority for such 
    occupation and includes the continuance in occupation by any person of the 
    airport premises after the authority (whether by way of grant or any other 
    mode of transfer) under which he was allowed to occupy the premises has 
    expired or has been determined for any reason whatsoever.]
 

 
-------------
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>  Sections 28A ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).
 
-------------
</subsection></section>
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>28B</number> 
    Appointment of eviction officers.—The 
    Authority may, by general or special order in writing, appoint such number 
    of its officers, as it thinks fit, to be eviction officers for the purposes 
    of this Chapter, and define the local limits within which, or the categories 
    of airport premises in respect of which, the eviction officers shall 
    exercise the powers conferred and perform the duties imposed, on eviction 
    officers by or under this Chapter.]





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>28C</number> 
    Issue of notice to show cause against order of eviction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the eviction officer is of the opinion that any persons are in 
    unauthorised occupation of any airport premises and that they should be 
    evicted, the eviction officer shall, in the manner hereinafter provided, 
    issue a notice in writing calling upon all persons concerned to show cause 
    why an order of eviction should not be made.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    notice shall—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   specify 
    the grounds on which the order of eviction is proposed to be made; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   require 
    all persons concerned, that is to say, all persons who are or may be, in 
    occupation of, or claim interest in, the airport premises—
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   
    to show cause, if any, against the proposed order on or before such date as 
    is specified in the notice, being a date not earlier than seven days from 
    the date of issue thereof, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    to appear before the eviction officer on the date specified in the notice 
    along with the evidence which they intend to produce in support of the cause 
    shown and also for personal hearing, if such hearing is desired.
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    eviction officer shall cause the notice to be served by having it affixed on 
    the outer door or some other conspicuous part of the airport premises and in 
    such other manner as may be prescribed, whereupon the notice shall be deemed 
    to have been duly given to the persons concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where 
    the eviction officer knows or has reasons to believe that any person is in 
    occupation of the airport premises, then, without prejudice to the 
    provisions of sub-section (3), he shall cause a copy of the notice to be 
    served on every such person by post or by delivering or tendering it to that 
    person or in such other manner as may be prescribed.]






  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>28D</number> 
    Eviction of unauthorised occupants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, after considering the cause, if any, shown by any person in pursuance of 
    a notice under section 28C and any evidence produced by him in support of 
    the same and after personal hearing, if any, given under sub-clause (ii) of 
    clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 28C, the eviction officer is 
    satisfied that the airport premises are in unauthorised occupation, the 
    eviction officer may make an order of eviction, for reasons to be recorded 
    therein, directing that the airport premises shall be vacated, on such date 
    as may be specified in the order, by the persons who may be in occupation 
    thereof, and cause a copy of the order to be affixed on the outer door or 
    some other conspicuous part of the airport premises.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    any person refuses or fails to comply with the order of eviction on or 
    before the date specified in the order or within fifteen days of the date of 
    publication under sub-section (1), whichever is earlier, the eviction 
    officer or any other officer duly authorised by the eviction officer in this 
    behalf may, after the date so specified or after the expiry of the period 
    aforesaid, whichever is earlier, evict that person from, and take possession 
    of, the airport premises and may, for that purpose, use such force as may be 
    necessary.]
 








  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>28E</number> Disposal of 
      property left on airport premises by unauthorised 
      occupants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Where any persons have been evicted from any airport premises under 
      section 28D, the eviction officer may, after giving ten days’ notice to 
      the persons from whom possession of the airport premises has been taken 
      and after publishing the notice in at least one newspaper having 
      circulation in the locality, remove or cause to be removed or dispose of 
      by public auction any property remaining on such 
      premises.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where 
      any property is sold under sub-section (1), the sale proceeds thereof 
      shall, after deducting the expenses of the sale and the amount, if any, 
      due to the Central Government or the corporate authority on account of 
      arrears of rent or damages or costs, be paid to such person or persons as 
      may appear to the eviction officer to be entitled to the 
      same:
 Provided 
      that where the eviction officer is unable to decide as to the person or 
      persons to whom the balance of the amount is payable or as to the 
      apportionment of the same, he may refer such dispute to the Tribunal and 
      the decision of the Tribunal thereon shall be final.]
  





  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>28F</number> Power to remove unauthorised constructions, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   erect or place or 
      raise any building or any movable or immovable structure or fixture;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   display or spread 
      any goods;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   bring or keep any 
      cattle or other animal,
 
on or against or in 
      front of, any airport premises except in accordance with the authority 
      (whether by way of grant or any other mode of transfer) under which he was 
      allowed to occupy such airport premises.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where any building or other immovable structure or fixture has been erected, 
    placed or raised in any airport premises in contravention of the provisions 
    of sub­-section (1), the eviction officer may serve on the person erecting 
    such building or other structure or fixture, a notice requiring him either 
    to remove or show cause why he shall not remove such building or other 
    structure or fixture to or from the airport premises within such period, not 
    being less than seven days but not exceeding thirty days as may be specified 
    in the notice, and on the omission or refusal of such person to show cause, 
    or to remove such building or other structure or fixture from the airport 
    premises, or where the cause shown is not, in the opinion of the eviction 
    officer, sufficient, the eviction officer may, by order, remove or cause to 
    be removed the building or other structure or fixture from the airport 
    premises and the cost of such removal shall be recoverable from such person 
    as an arrear of land revenue.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where any movable structure or fixture has been erected, placed or raised, 
    or any goods have been displayed or spread or any cattle or other animal has 
    been brought or kept on any airport premises in contravention of the 
    provisions of sub­-section (1) by any person, the eviction officer may, by 
    order, remove or cause to be removed without notice, such structure, 
    fixture, goods, cattle or other animal, as the case may be, from the airport 
    premises and the cost of such removal shall be recover­able from such person 
    as an arrear of land revenue.]
 







  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>28G</number> Power to 
      require payment of rent or damages in respect of airport 
      premises.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Where any person is in arrears of rent payable in respect of airport 
      premises, the eviction officer may, by order, require that person to pay 
      the same within such time and in such instalments as may be specified in 
      the order.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where 
      any person is, or has at any time been, in unauthorised occupation of any 
      airport premises, the eviction officer may, having regard to such 
      principles of assessment of damages as may be prescribed, assess the 
      damages on account of the use and occupation of such premises and may, by 
      order, require that person to pay the damages within such time and in such 
      instalments as may be specified in the order.
 </section><section><number>3</number> While 
      making an order under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the eviction 
      officer may direct that the arrears of rent or, as the case may be, 
      damages shall be payable together with simple interest at such rate as may 
      be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> No order 
      under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall be made against any person 
      until after the issue of a notice in writing to the person calling upon 
      him to show cause within such period not being less than seven days but 
      not exceeding thirty days as may be specified in the notice as to why such 
      order should not be made, and until his objections, if any, and any 
      evidence he may produce in support of the same have been considered by the 
      eviction officer.]
  




  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

[<number>28H</number> 
    Powers of eviction officers.—An 
    eviction officer shall, for the purpose of holding any inquiry into this 
    Chapter, have the same powers, as are vested in a civil court under the Code 
    of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit in respect of the 
    following matters, namely:—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examin­ing him on oath;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    requiring the discovery and production of documents;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   any 
    other matter which may be prescribed.]
 

 
-------------
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>  Sections 28H ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).
 
-------------
</subsection></section>
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>28-I</number> 
    Establishment of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    establish a Tribunal, to be known as the Airport Appellate Tribunal, to 
    exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on it by or under 
    this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Tribunal shall consist of a Chairperson (hereinafter referred to in this 
    Act, as the Chairperson of the Tribunal).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    head office of the Tribunal shall be at New Delhi:
 
Provided 
    that the Tribunal may hold its sittings at other places as the Chairperson 
    of the Tribunal may decide, from time to time, having taken into 
    consideration the convenience to decide the appeals before the Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Chairperson of the Tribunal shall be appointed by the Central Govern­ment 
    after consultation with the Chief Justice of India.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as Chairperson of the Tribunal 
    unless he is, or has been, or is qualified to be, a Judge of a High Court.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Chairperson of the Tribunal shall hold office as such for a term of three 
    years from the date on which he enters upon his office or until he attains 
    the age of sixty-two years, whichever is earlier.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The 
    salaries and allowances payable to, and other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Chairperson of the Tribunal shall be such as may be 
    prescribed:
 
Provided 
    that neither the salary and allowances nor other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Chairperson of the Tribunal shall be varied to his 
    disadvantage after his appointment.]
 






  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>28J</number> 
    Resignation and removal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson of the Tribunal may, by notice in writing under his hand 
    addressed to the Central Government, resign his office:
 
Provided 
    that the Chairperson of the Tribunal shall, unless he is permitted by the 
    Central Government to relinquish his office sooner, continue to hold office 
    until the expiry of three months from the date of receipt of such notice or 
    until a person duly appointed as his successor enters upon his office or 
    until the expiry of his term of office, whichever is the earliest.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson of the Tribunal shall not be removed from his office except by 
    an order made by the Central Government on the ground of proved misbehaviour 
    or incapacity after an inquiry made by a Judge of the Supreme Court in which 
    such Chairperson had been informed of the charges against him and given 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, by rules, regulate the procedure for the 
    investigation of misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson of the 
    Tribunal.]
 






  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>28K</number> 
    Appeals to Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person aggrieved by an order of the eviction officer under this Chapter 
    may, within fifteen days from the date of such order, prefer an appeal to 
    the Tribunal in such form as may be prescribed:
 
Provided 
    that the Tribunal may entertain any appeal after the expiry of the said 
    period of fifteen days, but not after the period of thirty days from the 
    date aforesaid, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by 
    sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of an appeal under sub-section (1), the Tribunal shall, after giving 
    the appellant and the eviction officer an opportunity of being heard, pass 
    such order as it thinks fit.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Tribunal shall dispose of the appeal within thirty days from the date of 
    filing the appeal:
 
Provided 
    that the Tribunal may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, dispose of the 
    appeal within a further period of fifteen days.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An 
    order of the Tribunal passed under sub-section (2) shall be executable as a 
    decree of a civil court and for executing the same the Tribunal shall send a 
    copy thereof to the civil court having jurisdiction which shall execute the 
    same, as expeditiously as may be possible, as if such order is a decree 
    passed by that court.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On 
    and from the date from which any jurisdiction, powers and authority becomes 
    exercisable under this Chapter by the Tribunal in relation to any matter, no 
    court (except the Supreme Court under Article 136 and the High Court under 
    Articles 226 and 227 of the Constitution) shall have, or be entitled to 
    exercise any jurisdiction, powers or authority in relation to such matter.]
 






  



</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>28L</number> 
    Procedure and powers of Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down in the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) but shall be guided by the principles of 
    natural justice, and, subject to the other provisions of this Act and of any 
    rules made by the Central Government, the Tribunal shall have power to lay 
    down and regulate its own proce­dure including the fixing of places and 
    times of its inquiry and deciding whether to sit in public or in private.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Tribunal shall have, for the purpose of discharging its functions under this 
    Chapter, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit in respect of the 
    following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examin­ing him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    requiring the discovery and production of documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   any 
    other matter which may be prescribed.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    proceeding before the Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceed­ing 
    within the meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of section 
    196, of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Tribunal shall be deemed 
    to be a civil court for all the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of 
    the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).]
 






  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>28M</number> 
    Finality of orders.—Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, every order made by an eviction officer or 
    the Tribunal under this Chapter shall be final and shall not be called in 
    question in any suit, application, execution or other proceeding and no 
    injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in respect of 
    any action taken or intended to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred 
    by or under this Chapter.]
 






  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>28N</number> 
    Offences under this Chapter.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever, unlawfully occupies any airport premises, shall be punish­able with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to six years and with fine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Whoever fails to comply with any order of the eviction officer or the 
    Tribunal under this Chapter shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to seven years and with fine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    any person who has been evicted from any airport premises under this Chapter 
    again occupies the premises without authority for such occupation, he shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years and 
    with fine.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    court may, while convicting a person under sub-section (3), make an order 
    for evicting that person summarily and he shall be liable to such eviction 
    without prejudice to any other action that may be taken under this Chapter.]
 






  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

[<number>28-O</number> 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any offence under this Chapter has been committed by a company, every 
    person who, at the time the offence was committed, was directly in charge 
    of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of 
    the company, as well as the company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
    offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly:
 
Provided 
    that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
    liable to any punishment provided in this Chapter, if he proves that the 
    offence was committed without his knowledge or he has exercised all due 
    diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence 
    under this Chapter has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is 
    attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, 
    secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary 
    or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall 
    be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    “company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association 
    of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    “director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.]
 

 
-------------
 <subsubsection>
<number>1</number>  Sections 28-O ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).
 
-------------
</subsubsection></subsection>
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>28P</number> 
    Cognizance of offences.—No 
    court shall take cognizance of any offence under this Chapter except on a 
    complaint made by the Authority, eviction officer or any other officer 
    authorised by it and no court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate 
    or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence punishable 
    under this Chapter.]
 





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>28Q</number> 
    Power to obtain information.—If 
    the eviction officer has reason to believe that any persons are in an 
    unauthorised occupation of any airport premises, he or any other officer 
    authorised by him in this behalf may require those persons or any other 
    person to furnish information in relation to the names and other particulars 
    of the persons in occupation of the airport premises and every person so 
    required shall be bound to furnish the informa­tion in his possession.]
 





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[<number>28R</number> Officers, etc., to 
    aid and assist.—It 
    shall be the duty of all the officers of the Government including police 
    officers and any local authority to aid and assist the eviction officer or 
    other officers of the Authority in the discharge of their functions under 
    this Chapter.]
 





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>29</number> Submission of annual 
    report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall, as soon as may be after the end of each financial year, 
    prepare and submit to the Central Government in such form as may be 
    prescribed report giving an account of its activities during that financial 
    year and the report shall also give an account of the activities which are 
    likely to be undertaken by the Authority during the next financial year.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The Central Government 
    shall cause such report to be laid before both Houses of Parliament as soon 
    as may be after it is submitted.
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>30</number> Delegation.—The 
    Authority may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to the 
    Chairperson or any other member or to any officer of the Authority, subject 
    to such conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the 
    order, such of its powers and functions under this Act, (except the powers 
    under section 42) as it may deem necessary.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>31</number> Authentication of 
    orders and other instruments of the Authority.—All 
    orders and decisions of the Authority shall be authenticated by the 
    signature of the Chairperson or any other member authorised by the Authority 
    in this behalf and all other instruments executed by the Authority shall be 
    authenticated by the signature of an officer of the Authority authorised by 
    it in this behalf. 
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>32</number> Officers and 
    employees of the Authority to be public servants.—All 
    officers and employees of the Authority shall, while acting or purporting to 
    act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or regulation 
    made thereunder, be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
    section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
  

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>33</number> Protection of action taken 
      in good faith.—No suit, prosecution or other 
      legal proceeding shall lie against the Authority or any member or any 
      officer or other employee of the Authority <footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[or the Chairperson of the 
      Tribunal] for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
      in pursuance of this Act of any rule or regulation made thereunder or for 
      any damage sustained by any aircraft or vehicle in consequences of any 
      defect in any of the airports, civil enclaves, heliports, airstrips, 
      aeronautical communication stations or other things belonging to or under 
      the control of the Authority.
  




  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Custody and disposal of lost property.—Subject 
    to such regulations as the Authority may make in this behalf, the Authority 
    shall provide for securing the safe custody and restoration of any property 
    which, while not in proper custody, is found on any premises belonging to 
    the Authority or under its overall control or in any aircraft on any such 
    premises.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Provisions relating to income-tax.—For 
    the purposes of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961) or any other enactment 
    for the time being in force relating to income-tax or any other tax on 
    income, profits or gains, the Authority shall be deemed to be a company 
    within the meaning of the Income-tax Act, 1961 and shall be liable to tax 
    accordingly on its income, profits and gains.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Power of the Authority to undertake certain works.—The 
    Authority may undertake to carry out on behalf of any person any works or 
    services or any class of works or services on such terms and conditions as 
    may be agreed upon between the Authority and the person concerned.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Power to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority or any officer specially authorised by it in this behalf may, 
    from time to time, by order, issue directions, consistent with the 
    provisions of the Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 1934), and the rules made 
    thereunder, with respect to any of the matters specified in clauses (f), 
    (h), (i), (j), (k), (m), (p), (qq) and (r) of sub-section (2) of section 5 
    of that Act, to any person or persons engaged in aircraft operations or 
    using any airport, heliport, airstrip or civil enclave, in any case where 
    the Authority or the officer is satisfied that in the interests of the 
    security of India or for securing the security of the aircraft it is 
    necessary to do so. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    direction issued under sub-section (1) shall be complied with by the person 
    or persons to whom such direction is issued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    any person wilfully fails to comply with any direction issued under this 
    section, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to six months or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, 
    or with both.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Power of the Central Government to temporarily divest the Authority of the 
    management of any airport.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, at any time, the Central Government is of opinion that in the public 
    interest it is necessary or expedient so to do, it may, by order, direct the 
    Authority to entrust the administration, management or similar other 
    functions of any airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave, aeronautical 
    communication station, or any other agency or department of any airport, 
    heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or aeronautical communications station 
    with effect from such date and to such person as may be specified in the 
    order and the Authority shall be bound to comply with such direction:
 
Provided 
    that before an order is made under this sub-section the Authority shall be 
    given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where 
    the management of any airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or 
    aeronautical communication station or any other agency or department thereof 
    is entrusted to any person specified under sub-section (1) (hereafter 
    referred to in this section as the authorised person), the Authority shall 
    cease to exercise and discharge all its powers and functions under this Act 
    in relation to such airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or 
    aeronautical communication station or any other agency or department thereof 
    and such powers and functions shall be exercised and discharged by the 
    authorised person in accordance with the instructions, if any, which the 
    Central Government may give to the authorised person from time to time:
 
Provided 
    that no such power or function as may be specified by the Central Government 
    by a general or special order shall be exercised or discharged by the 
    authorised person except with the previous sanction of the Central 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    order made under sub-section (1) shall, unless rescinded, be in operation 
    for a period of six months from the date on which the management of the 
    airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or aeronautical communication 
    station or any other agency or department thereof is entrusted to the 
    authorised person: 
 
Provided 
    that the Central Government may extend such period for a period or periods 
    not exceeding eighteen months.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    During the operation of an order made under sub-section (1), it shall be 
    competent for the Cental Government to issue, from time to time, such 
    directions to the Authority as are necessary to enable the authorised person 
    to exercise the powers and discharge the functions of the Authority under 
    this Act in relation to the airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or 
    aeronautical communication station, or any other agency or department 
    thereof the management of which has been entrusted to him and in particular 
    to transfer any sum of money from the fund of the Authority to the 
    authorised person for the management of the airport, heliport, airstrip 
    civil enclave or aeronautical communication station or any other agency or 
    department thereof and every such direction shall be complied with by the 
    Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On 
    the cesser of operation of any order made under sub-section (1) in relation 
    to any airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or aeronautical 
    communication station, or any other agency or department thereof the 
    authorised person shall cease to exercise and perform the powers and 
    functions of the Authority under this Act in relation to such airport, 
    heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or aeronautical communication station or 
    any other agency or department thereof and the Authority shall continue to 
    exercise and perform such powers and functions in accordance with the 
    provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> On 
    the cesser of operation of any order made under sub-section (1) in relation 
    to any airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or aeronautical 
    communication station, or any other agency or department thereof the 
    authorised person shall hand over to the Authority any property (including 
    any sum of money or other asset) remaining with him in connection with the 
    management of such airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or 
    aeronautical communication station.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> 
    Anything done or any action taken lawfully by the authorised person in 
    relation to any airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or aeronautical 
    communication station or any other agency or department thereof during the 
    period of operation of an order made under sub-section (1) shall be deemed 
    to have been done or taken by the Authority and shall be binding on the 
    Authority.
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Power of the Central Government to supersede the Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, at any time, the Central Government is of opinion—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that on 
    account of a grave emergency, the Authority is unable to discharge the 
    functions and duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>   that the Authority has 
    persistently made default in complying with any direction issued by the 
    Central Government under this Act or in the discharge of the functions and 
    duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act and as a result 
    of which default the financial position of the Authority or the 
    administration of any airport, heliport, airstrip, civil enclave or 
    aeronautical communication station has deteriorated; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>   that circumstances exist which 
    render it necessary in the public interest so to do, 
 

    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    supersede the Authority for such period, not exceeding six months, as may be 
    specified in the notification: 
 

Provided that before 
    issuing a notification under this sub-section for the reasons mentioned in 
    clause (b), the Central Government shall give a reasonable opportunity to 
    the Authority to show cause why it should not be superseded and shall 
    consider the explanations and objections, if any, of the Authority.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Upon the publication 
    of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the Authority,—
 
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>   all the members shall, as 
    from the date of supersession, vacate their offices as such;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>   all the powers, functions 
    and duties which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, be exercised 
    or discharged by or on behalf of the Authority, shall until the Authority is 
    re-constituted under sub-section (3), be exercised and discharged by such 
    person or persons as the Central Government may direct;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>   all property owned or 
    controlled by the Authority shall, until the Authority is reconstituted 
    under sub-section (3), vest in the Central Government.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> On the expiration of 
    the period of supersession specified in the notification issued under 
    sub-section (1), the Central Government may,—
 
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>   extend the period of supersession for such further term not exceeding six months, as it may 
    consider necessary; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>   re-constitute the Authority 
    by fresh appointment and in such case the members who vacated their offices 
    under clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall not be deemed disqualified for appointment:
 

Provided that the Central 
    Government may, at any time before the expiration of the period of 
    supersession, whether as originally specified under sub-section (1) or as extended under this sub-section, take action under clause 
    (b) of this sub-section.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> The Central 
    Government shall cause a notification issued under sub-section (1) and a 
    full report of any action taken under this section and the circumstances 
    leading to such action to be laid before both Houses of Parliament at the 
    earliest opportunity.

 
 
The Central Government 
    under certain condition, may supersede the Authority. A report regarding 
    such supersession has to be laid before the Parliament at the earliest 
    opportunity.



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Power of the Central Government to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Authority 
    shall, in the discharge of its functions and duties under this Act, be found 
    by such directions on questions of policy as the Central Government may give 
    in writing to it from time to time:
 
Provided 
    that the Authority shall, as far as practicable, be given opportunity to 
    express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    decision of the Central Government whether a question is one of policy or 
    not shall be final. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government may, from time to time, issue directions to the Authority 
    regarding the discharge of any functions to it under clause (e) of 
    sub-section (3) of section 12 and the Authority shall be bound to comply 
    with such directions.
  

  


</section></article> 

  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>41</number> Power to make rules. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the provisions 
of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the period of notice as may be given by the Central Government to 
  terminate the appointment of any part-time member of the Authority under 
  clause (b) of proviso to sub-section (1) of section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the conditions of service of the members of the Authority under 
  sub-section (2) of section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the period of notice as may be given by any member to resign his office 
  under sub-section (3) of section 5; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the provisions subject to which officers and other employees may be 
  appointed by the Authority and the category of officers to be appointed after 
  approval of the Central Government under the proviso to sub-section (1) of 
  section 10; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the provisions subject to which the Authority may manage the airports, 
  civil enclaves and aeronautical communication stations under sub-section (1) 
  of section 12; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>ee</number> <footcitenum>25</footcitenum><title></title>[the rate 
  of development fees in respect of airports other than major airports and] the 
  manner of regulating and utilising the fees under section 22A;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the manner in which the Authority may invest its funds under clause (b) 
  of sub-section (3) of section 24; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> the form in which the annual statement of accounts shall be prepared by 
  the Authority under sub-section (1) of section 28; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>gi</number> the other manner of serving notice under 
  sub-section (3) of  section 28C;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>gii</number> the other manner of serving notice 
  under sub-section (4) of  section 28C;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>giii</number> the principles of assessment of 
  damages under sub-section (2) of section 28G;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>giv</number> the rate of simple interest under 
  sub-section (3) of section 28G;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>gv</number> any other matter under clause (c) of 
  section 28H;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>gvi</number> the salaries and allowances payable to, 
  and other terms and condi­tions of service of, the Chairperson of the 
  Tribunal under sub-section (7) of section 28-I;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>gvii</number> the procedure for the investigation of 
  misbehaviour or incapacity of the Chairperson of the Tribunal under 
  sub-section (3) of section 28J;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>gviii</number> the form of appeal under sub-section 
  (1) of section 28K;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>24</footcitenum><title></title>[<number>gix</number> any other matter under clause (c) of 
  sub-section (2) of section 28L;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> the form in which a report giving an account of its activities shall be 
  prepared and submitted by the Authority to the Central Government under 
  sub-section (1) of section 29; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> any other mater which is to be, or may be, prescribed. </subsection>


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Power to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority may make regulations not inconsistent with this Act and the 
    rules made thereunder to provide for all matters for which provisions is 
    necessary or expedient for the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of 
    this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations 
    may provide for—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the time 
    and places of the meetings of the Authority and the procedure to be followed 
    for the transaction of business including the quorum at such meetings under 
    sub-section (1) section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
    conditions of service and the remuneration of officers and other employees 
    to be appointed by the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the 
    construction of residential accommodation for the officers and other 
    employees appointed by the Authority under clause (e) of sub-section (3) of 
    section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the 
    storage or processing of goods in any warehouse established by the Authority 
    under clause (g) of sub-section (3) of section 12 and the charging of fees 
    for such storage or processing;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the 
    contracts or class of contracts which are to be sealed with the common seal 
    of the Authority and the form and manner in which a contract may be made by 
    the Authority under sub-section (1) of section 21;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the 
    custody and restoration of lost property and the terms and conditions under 
    which lost property may be restored to the persons entitled thereto under 
    section 34;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the 
    disposal of any lost property in cases where such property is not restored;
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   securing 
    the safety of aircraft, vehicles and persons using the airport or civil 
    enclave and preventing danger to the public arising from the use and 
    operation of aircraft in the airport or civil enclave;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    preventing obstruction within the airport or civil enclave for its normal 
    functioning;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   
    prohibiting the parking or waiting of any vehicle of carriage within the 
    airport or civil enclave except at places specified by the Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   
    prohibiting or restricting access to any part of the airport or civil enclave;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   
    preserving order within the airport or civil enclave and preventing damage 
    to property therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   
    regulating or restricting advertising within the airport or civil enclave;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   
    requiring any person, if so directed by an officer appointed by Authority in 
    this behalf, to leave the airport or civil enclave or any particular part of 
    the airport or civil enclave; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   
    generally for the efficient and proper management of the airport or civil enclave.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    regulation made under any of the clause (h) to (o) (both inclusive) of 
    sub-section (2) may provide that a contravention thereof shall be punishable 
    with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and in the case of a 
    continuing contravention with an additional fine which may extend of twenty 
    rupees for every day during which such contravention continues after 
    conviction for the first such contravention.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    regulation made by the Authority under this section shall have effect until 
    it has been approved by the Central Government and published in the Official 
    Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, the first regulations 
    under this Act shall be made by the Central Government and shall have effect 
    on being published in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    first regulations framed under sub-section (5) shall remain in force until 
    such time the Authority has made regulations and they are published in the 
    Official Gazette. 
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
    regulation, as the case may be, or both Houses agree that the rule or 
    regulation, as the case may be, should not be made, the rule or regulation 
    shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
    as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
    shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
    that rule or regulation.
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Power to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by general or special order published in the 
    Official Gazette, make such provisions not inconsistent with the provisions 
    of this Act as appear to it to be necessary or expedient for the removal of 
    the difficulty:
 
Provided 
    that no such order shall be made after the expiration of one year from the 
    commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    order made under sub-section (1) shall be laid, as soon as may be after it 
    is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
    total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two 
    or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the order or both Houses agree 
    that the order should not be made, the order shall thereafter have effect 
    only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
    however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
    to the validity of anything previously done under that order. 
  

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Amendment of Act 22 of 1934.—[Rep. 
    by Repealing and Amending Act, 2001 (30 of 2001), sec. 2 and Sch. I].
  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Repeal and saving.—On 
    and from the appointed date,— 
 
 <section>
<number>i</number>   the 
    International Airports Authority Act, 1971 (43 of 1971) and the national 
    Airports Authority Act, 1985 (64 of 1985) shall stand repealed;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   the 
    International Airports Authority and the National Airports Authority 
    constituted under the aforesaid Acts shall cease to exist.
</section>
 <section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken or purported 
    to have been done or taken under the aforesaid Acts so repealed shall, in so 
    far as it is not inconsistent with the provisions of his Act, be deemed to 
    have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.  

  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>     Came into force on 1-4-1995 vide 
    S.O. 285(E), dated 30th March, 1995, published in the Gazette of India, 
    Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 30th March, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Ins. by Act 43 of 2003, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 Ins. by Act 43 of 2003, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
 Ins. by Act 43 of 2003, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> 
 Ins. by Act 43 of 2003, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 2003, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 27 of 2008, sec. 54 and Sch., for “The Authority 
may, after the previous approval of the Central Govern­ment in this behalf, 
levy on, and collect from the embarking passengers at an airport, the 
development fees at the rate as may be prescribed and such fees shall be 
credited to the Authority and shall be regulated and utilised in the prescribed 
manner, for the purposes of,—”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Sections 28B ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Sections 28C ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Sections 28D ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Sections 28E ins. by 
      Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Sections 28F ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Sections 28G ins. by 
      Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Sections 28-I ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Sections 28J ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Sections 28K ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Sections 28L ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Sections 28M ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Sections 28N ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Sections 28P ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>  Sections 28Q ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Sections 28R ins. by 
    Act 43 of 2003, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> 
 Ins. by Act 43 of 2003, 
      sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Ins. by Act 43 of 2003, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-7-2004 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Subs. by Act 27 of 2008, sec. 54 and Sch., for “the rate of 
development fees and”.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>