<act><title>the 
Transport of Animals Rules, 19781</title> 

  
 
 <article><number>1</number> Short title.—These rules may be called the 
Transport of Animals Rules, 1978.
  


</article> 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless the 
context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  qualified veterinary surgeon means one who holds a diploma or a degree 
of a recognised veterinary college;
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to these rules.
  


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article><number>3</number> Rules 4 to 14 shall apply to the 
transport of dogs and cats of all breeds whether by rail, road, inland waterway, 
sea or air.
  


  



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> </title> 
<section><number>a</number> A valid health certificate by a qualified veterinary surgeon to the effect that the dogs and cats are in a fit condition to travel by a rail, road, inland waterway, sea or air and are not showing any sign of infectious or contagious disease including rabies, shall accompany each consignment and the certificate shall be in the form specified in Schedule A. 
 
 






</section><section><number>b</number> In the absence of such a certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the consignment for transport. 
</section></article> 

  
 
 <article><title><number>5</number> </title> No dog or cat in an advanced stage of pregnancy shall be transported. 
 ----------
 <section><number>1</number> Vide Government of India, Ministry of Agriculture and Irrigation (Department of Agriculture), Notification No. 18-6/70 LDI, dated 23rd March, 1978. 
</section></article>
  
  
  
  
 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> </title> 
<section><number>a</number> Dogs or cats to be transported in the same container shall be of the same species and breed. 
 
 






</section><section><number>b</number> Unweaned puppies or kittens shall not be transported with adult dogs or cats other than their dams. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> No female dog or cat in season (cestrus) shall be transported with any male. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> </title>
<section><number>a</number> Any dog or  cat reported to be vicious or exhibiting a vicious disposition shall be transported individually in a cage, muzzeled and labelled to give warning to handlers. 
 
 






</section><section><number>b</number> In extreme cases, the dogs or cats shall be administered with sedative drugs by a qualified veterinary surgeon.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> </title> 
<section><number>1</number> When dogs or cats are to be transported for long distances— 
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  they shall be fed and given water atleast two hours prior to their transport and shall not be packed for transport if they are hungry or thirsty; 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  they should be exercised as late as possible before despatch; 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  they shall be given adequate water for drinking every four hours in summer or every six hours during winter; 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  they shall be fed once in twelve hours in the case of adult dogs or cats and they shall be fed once in four hours in the case of puppies and kittens in accordance with the instructions of the consignors, if any; 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  adequate arrangements shall be made for their care and management during the journey. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> When the dogs or cats are to be transported by rail involving a journey of more than six hours, an attendant shall accompany the dogs or cats to supply them with food and water on the way and the attendant shall have access to the dogs or cats for this purpose at all stations and no dog or cat shall be exposed to the direct blast of air during such journey. 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> </title>Where dogs or cats are to be transported for short distance by road in a public vehicle, the following precautions are to be taken, namely:— 
 <section>       <number>a</number>  They shall be put in a cage and the cage containing the dogs or cats shall not be put on the roof of the vehicle but shall be put inside the vehicle preferably near the end of the vehicle; 
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  the vehicle transporting the dogs or cats shall as far as possible maintain constant speed, avoiding sudden stops and reducing effects of shocks and jolts to the minimum; 
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  atleast one attendant shall be present at all times during transit who shall ensure that proper transit conditions are observed and shall also replenish food and water whenever necessary. 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> </title>Where dogs or cats are to be transported by air:— 
 <section>       <number>a</number>  The cages shall be properly cleaned and disinfected before the dogs or cats are put in the cages; 
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  sufficient paddy straw or saw dust or paper cuttings shall be provided for cats in the cages as resting materials; 
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  for international transport, the dogs or cats shall be kept in a pressurized compartment with regulated temperature. 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> </title>The size and type of crates for transport of dogs and cats shall conform as clearly as may be to the size and  type specified in Schedule B and Schedule C respectively. 






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> </title>All containers of dogs or cats shall be clearly labelled showing the names, address and telephone number (if any) of the consignor. 






</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>13</number> </title>The consignee shall be informed about the train or transport arrival or flight number and its time of arrival in advance. 






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> </title> Consignment of dogs or cats to be transported by rail or road shall be booked by the next passenger or mail train or bus and should not be detained after accepting the consignment for booking. 






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number></title> Rules 16 to 23 shall apply to the transport of all types of monkeys from
the trapping area to the nearest rail-head.






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> A valid health certificate by a qualified veterinary surgeon to the effect
      that the monkeys are in a fit condition to travel from the trapping area to the
      nearest unit-head and are not showing any sign of infections or contagious 
  disease shall accompany each consignment.
 
 






</section><section>	 <number>b</number> In the absence of such a certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the
    consignment for transport.
 </section><section> 
    <number>c</number> The certificate shall be in a form specified in Schedule D.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> Monkeys from one trapping area shall not be allowed to mix with
  monkeys from any other trapping area for preventing the dangers of
crossinfection.
 </section><section> 
  <number>2</number> The time in transit from trapping area to the nearest rail-head shall be as
  short as possible and factors causing stress to monkeys shall be reduced to the
  minimum.
 </section><section> 
  <number>3</number> If the travel time is longer than six hours provision shall be made to feed
  and to give water to the monkeys enroute.
 </section><section> 
  <number>4</number> During transit, precautions shall be taken to protect the monkeys from
  extreme weather conditions and monkeys that die en route shall be removed at
  the earliest available opportunity.






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number></title> Monkeys that are not completely weaned, that is, under 1.8 kilogram in
  weight, shall not be transported except when specifically permitted by the
Central Government.






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> Pregnant and nursing monkeys shall not be transported except when
specifically permitted by the Central Government.
 </section><section> <number>b</number> Pregnant and nursing monkeys as well as monkeys weighing more than
    5 kilograms shall be transported in compartmented cages.






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number></title> All monkeys in the same cage shall be of the same species and of
approximately the same weight and size.






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number></title> Monkeys captured within their natural habitat shall be placed in new,
  sterilized or thoroughly cleaned cages and subsequent transfer, if any, shall also
be new, disinfected or thoroughly cleaned cages.






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number></title> Monkeys shall be transported from trapping area to the nearest rail-head
  by the fastest means of transport available and the monkeys should not be left
un-attended at any time during the journey.






</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> Monkeys shall be transported in suitable wooden or bamboo cages
  so constructed as not to allow the escape of the monkeys but permit sufficient
passage of air ventilation.
 
 
 </subsection><subsection> 
    <number>b</number> No nails, metallic projections or sharp edges shall be exposed on the
    exterior or in the interior of the cages.
 </subsection><subsection> 
    <number>c</number> Each cage shall be equipped with appropriate water and feed receptacles
    which are leak proof and capable of being cleaned and refilled during transit.
</subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The floor of the cages shall be made of bamboo reapers and the space
between each reaper shall range between 20 mm and 30 mm.
 </section><section> 
  <number>3</number> To facilitate carriage of these cages, provision may be made for rope loops
  at the four top ends.
 </section><section> 
  <number>4</number> The weight of any one loaded cage shall not exceed 45 kilograms.
 </section><section> 
  <number>5</number> The following two sizes of cages shall be used.—
 
 <subsection> 
    <number>a</number> 910 × 760 × 510 mm—to contain not more than twelve monkeys,
    weighing between 1.8 and 3.00 kilograms each or ten monkeys
    weighing between 3.1 and 5.0 kilograms each.
 </subsection><subsection> 
    <number>b</number> 710 × 710 × 510 mm—to contain not more than ten monkeys weighing
    between 1.8 and 3.00 kilograms each or eight monkeys weighing
    between 3.1 and 5.00 kilograms each :
</subsection>
  
  Provided that wooden cages as specified in Schedule F to these rules may
  also be used for carrying monkeys from the trapping area to the nearest rail-head.
 </section><section> 
  <number>6</number> The construction details of two types of cages shall be given in
  Schedule E.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> </title>Rules 25 to 32 shall apply to transport of monkeys from a rail-head to
another rail-head or from a rail-head to nearest airport.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> Loading and unloading shall be carried out quickly and efficiently.
 
 


</section><section> 
    <number>b</number> Cages shall be stored in such a manner that ventilation is adequate and
    the monkeys are not exposed to draught and direct heat or cold.
 </section><section> 
    <number>c</number> Monkeys found dead shall be removed as quickly as possible for suitable 
    disposal.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number></title> The transport cages shall be in accordance with specifications given in
rule 28.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> Due provision shall be made by the sender for a sufficient supply or
food and water for the journey.
 </section><section> 
  <number>2</number> In case the journey is over six hours an attendant shall accompany the
  monkeys to supply them food, water, and such other things, on route and he
  shall have access to the monkeys for feeding, giving water and attention at all 
  stations en route.
 </section><section> 
  <number>3</number> The food and water containers shall be checked atleast every six hours
  and refilled, if necessary.
 </section><section> 
  <number>4</number> Monkeys shall not be disturbed during the night hours.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number></title> Not more than one cage shall be placed over the other and gunny packing
shall be placed between two cages, when one is placed over the other.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> </title>Monkeys shall be brought to the airport sufficiently early.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number></title> Monkeys shall be provided with food and water immediately before
loading on the aircraft.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> The cages shall be clearly labelled showing the name, address and
telephone number (if any) of the consignor and the consignee in bold red letters.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> The consignee shall be informed about the train in which the consignment
  of monkeys is being sent and its arrival time in advance.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> The consignment of monkeys to be transported shall be booked by the
  next passenger or mail train and should not be detained after the consignment is
  accepted for booking.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> A valid health certificate by a qualified veterinary surgeon to the effect
  that the monkeys are in a fit condition to travel from the nearest rail-head to
  another rail-head or from a rail-head to the nearest airport and are not showing
any signs of infectious or contagious disease shall accompany each consignment.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> In the absence of such a certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the 
  consignment for transport.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> The certificate shall be in a form specified in Schedule D.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number></title> Rules 34 to 45 shall apply in relation to the transport of monkeys by air.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number></title> The time in transit shall be as short as possible and factors causing stress
to monkeys shall be reduced to the minimum.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>35</number></title> Monkeys that are not completely weaned, that is, under 1.8 kilograms in
  weight, shall not be transported except when specifically permitted by the
Central Government.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>36</number></title> Pregnant and nursing monkeys shall not be transported except when
  specifically permitted by the Central Government. Pregnant and nursing
  monkeys and monkeys weighing over 5 kilograms shall be transported in
specially designed individual cages.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>37</number></title> All monkeys in the same cage shall be of the same species and of
approximately the same weight and size.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>38</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> In view of the danger of infection, only monkeys of the same species
shall be transported in the same cabin or compartment of the aircraft.
 </section><section> 
  <number>2</number> Apparently sick or disabled monkeys exhibiting external injuries or
  infested with parasites shall not be transported.
 </section><section> 
  <number>3</number> Transport of other species of animals, birds, fish, food stuff or poisonous
  materials, such as pesticides and insecticides, in the same cabin or compartment
  shall not be permitted.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>39</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> At no time during transit shall the monkeys be left unattended when
carried in a freighter aircraft.
 </section><section> 
  <number>2</number> At least one attendant shall be present at all times when the aircraft is on
  the ground


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>40</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> Monkeys shall be transported in suitable wooden cages, so constructed
  as not to allow the escape of the monkeys and shall allow sufficient passage of
  air for ventilation; no nails, metallic projections or sharp edges shall be exposed
  in the interior or on the exterior of such cages. Each cage shall be equipped with
  water and food receptacles which shall be leak-proof and be capable of being
  cleaned and refilled during transit. A suitable absorbent material such as saw
dust shall be kept in the dropping trays.
 </section><section> 
  <number>2</number> The weight of any one loaded cage shall not exceed 45 kilograms in any
  case.
 </section><section> 
  <number>3</number> The following two sizes of cages shall be used:—
 
 <subsection> 
    <number>a</number> 460 × 460 × 460 mm — to contain not more than ten monkeys weighing
    from 1.8 to 3,0 kilograms each or four monkeys weighing from 3.1 to
    5.0 kilograms each; and
 </subsection><subsection> 
    <number>b</number> 760 × 530 × 460 mm to contain not more than ten monkeys weighing
    from 1.8 to 3.0 kilograms each or eight monkeys weighing from 3.1 to
    5.0 kilograms each.
</subsection>
 </section><section> 
  <number>4</number> The construction details of the two types of cages shall be as given in
  Schedule F.
 </section><section> 
  <number>5</number> The construction details of the two types of cages used for the transport
  of pregnant and nursing monkeys shall be as given in Schedule G.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>41</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> The cages shall be clearly labelled showing the name, address and
telephone number (if any) of the consignor and the consignee in bold red letters.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> The consignee shall be informed in advance about the flight number of
  the freighter aircraft in which the consignment of monkeys is being sent and its
  arrival time.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> The consignment of monkeys to be transported shall be booked by the
  next flight of the freighter aircraft and should not be detained after the
  consignment is accepted for booking.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>42</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> A valid health certificate by a qualified veterinary surgeon to the effect
  that the monkeys are fit to travel by air and are not showing any signs of
infectious or contagious disease shall accompany each consignment of monkeys.
 </section><section> 
  <number>2</number> In the absence of such a certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the 
  consignment for shipment.
 </section><section> <number>3</number> The form of a certificate under sub-rule (1) be as given in Schedule D.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>43</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> The air shall be changed not less than twelve times per hour and
draughts shall be avoided and there shall be no dead pockets of air.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Except when the monkeys are being fed and given water, they shall travel
  in semi-darkness to make them quieter and less inclined to fight and thus given
them better opportunities of resting.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>44</number> </title>The food and water containers shall be checked at every stop and refilled;
  if necessary, and a sufficient stock of food shall be available on the aircraft and
at likely stopping places.
  
<title>Note.</title>—About 85 grams of food per monkey is required daily. Suitable foods
  are dry cereal grains or gram. It is recommended that whole gram made into
  biscuits or wheat meal bread should be fed. A minimum of 140 ml. of water shall
  be allowed for each monkey per day.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>45</number></title> An empty cage of the usual dimensions with its sides covered except 50
  mm at the top to allow for ventilation shall be provided in the freighter aircraft
for housing the monkeys which fall sick or are injured during the journey.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>46</number></title> Rules 47 to 56 shall apply to the transport by rail or of cows, bulls, bullocks
buffaloes, yaks and calves (hereinafter in these rules referred to as ‘cattle’.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>47</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> A valid certificate by a qualified veterinary surgeon to the effect that the
  cattle are in a fit condition to travel by rail or road and are not suffering from any
  infectious or contagious or parasitic diseases and that they have been vaccinated
  against rinderpest and any other infectious or contagious or parasitic diseases
shall accompany each consignment.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> In the absence of such a certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the
  consignment for transport.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> The certificate shall be in the form specified in Schedule E.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>48</number></title> Veterinary first-aid equipment shall accompany all batches of cattle.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>49</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> Each consignment shall bear a label showing in bold red letters the
  name, address and telephone number (if any) of the consignor and consignee, the
  number and types of cattle being transported and quantity of rations and food
provided.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> The consignee shall be informed about the train or vehicle in which the
  consignment of cattle is being sent and its arrival time in advance.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> The consignment of cattle shall be booked by the next train or vehicle and
  shall not be detained after the consignment is accepted for booking.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>51</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> Suitable rope and platforms should be used for loading cattle from
vehicles.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> In case of railway wagon the dropped door of the wagon may be used as
  a ramp when loading or unloading is done to the platform.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>52</number></title> Cattle shall be loaded after they are properly fed and given water.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>53</number></title> Cattle in advanced stage of pregnancy shall not be mixed with young cattle
in order to avoid stampede during transportation.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>54</number></title> 
<section><number>1</number> Watering arrangements on route shall be made and sufficient quantities
of water shall be carried for emergency.
 </section><section> 
  <number>2</number> Sufficient feed and fodder with adequate reserve shall be carried to last
  during the journey.
 </section><section> 
  <number>3</number> Adequate ventilation shall be ensured.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>55</number></title> When cattle is to be transported by rail.—
 
 <section> 
    <number>a</number> an ordinary goods wagon shall carry not more than ten adult cattle or
    fifteen calves on broad gauge, not more than six adult cattle or ten
    calves on metre gauge, or not more than four adult cattle or six calves
  on narrow gauge;
 </section><section> <number>b</number> every wagon carrying cattle shall have atleast one attendant;
 </section><section> 
    <number>c</number> cattle shall be loaded parallel to the rails, facing each other;
 </section><section> 
    <number>d</number> rations for padding, such as straw, shall be placed on the floor to avoid
    injury if a cattle lies down and this shall not be less than 6 cms thick;
 </section><section> 
    <number>e</number> rations for the journey shall be carried in the middle of the wagon;
 </section><section> 
    <number>f</number> to provide adequate ventilation, upper door of one side of the wagon
    shall be kept open properly fixed and the upper door of the wagon
    shall have wire gauge closely welded mesh arrangements to prevent
    burning cinders from the engines entering the wagon and leading to
    fire outbreak;  
</section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>56</number> </title>When cattle are to be transported by goods vehicle the following precautions are to be taken, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> specially fitted goods vehicles with a special type of tail board on padding around the sides should be used; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> ordinary goods vehicles shall be provided with anti-slipping material, such as coir matting or wooden board on the floor and the superstructure, if low, should be raised; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> no goods vehicle shall carry more than six cattle; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> each goods vehicle shall be provided with one attendant; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> while transporting the cattle, the goods vehicle shall not be loaded with any other merchandise; and 
 </section><section><number>f</number> to prevent cattle being frightened or injured, they should preferably face the engine. 
  
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>57</number></title> Rules 57 to 63 shall apply to the transport by rail, road or sea of horses,
mules and donkeys (hereinafter in these rules referred to as ‘equines’).


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>58</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> A valid certificate by a qualified veterinary surgeon to the effect that the
  equines are in a fit condition to travel by rail; road or sea and are not suffering
  from any infectious contagious disease or diseases shall accompany each 
consignment.
 
 


</section><section> 
    <number>b</number> In the absence of such a certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the
    consignment for transport.
 </section><section> 
    <number>c</number> The certificate shall be in a form specified in Schedule 1.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>59</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> Each consignment shall bear a lable showing in bold red letters the
  name, address and telephone number (if any) of the consignor and consignee, the
  number and type of equines being transported and quantity of rations and food
provided.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> The consignee shall be informed in advance about the train or vehicle or
  ship in which the consignment of equines is being sent and its arrival time.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> The consignment of equines shall be booked by the next train or vehicle or
  ship and shall be accepted for booking.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>60</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> Pregnant and young equines shall not be mixed with other animals.
 
 


</section><section> 
    <number>b</number> Different species of equines shall be kept separately.
 </section><section> 
    <number>c</number> Equines shall be loaded after being fed and given water adequately,
    watering arrangements shall be made en route and sufficient food carried to last
    during the journey.
 </section><section> 
    <number>d</number> Veterinary first-aid equipment shall accompany all batches of equines.
 </section><section> 
    <number>e</number> Adequate ventilation shall be ensured.
 </section><section> 
    <number>f</number> Suitable ramps and platforms, improvised where not available, shall be
    used for loading and unloading equines.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>61</number></title> For the transport of equines by rail, the following precautions shall be
taken:—
 
 <section> 
    <number>a</number> equines shall be transported by passenger or mixed trains only;
 </section><section> 
    <number>b</number> ordinary goods wagon when used for transportation shall carry not
    more then eight to ten horses or ten mules or ten donkeys on broad
    gauge and not more than six horses or eight donkeys on metre-gauge;
 </section><section> 
    <number>c</number> in extreme hot water shall be sprinkled over the wagons containing
    equines by the railway authorities to bring down temperature. Ice slabs
    in specially made containers may be placed inside the wagon, if
    recommended by a qualified veterinary surgeon;
 </section><section> 
    <number>d</number> every wagon shall have two attendants if the equines are more than
    two in number;
 </section><section> 
    <number>e</number> equines shall be loaded parallel to the rails, facing each other;
 </section><section> 
    <number>f</number> material for padding, such as paddy straw, shall be placed on the floor
    to avoid injury if an animal lies down and this shall not be less than
    6 cm thick;
 </section><section> 
    <number>g</number> to provide adequate ventilation, upper door of the side of the wagon
    shall be kept upon and properly fixed and the upper door of the wagon
    shall have wire gauge closely welded mesh arrangements to prevent
    burning cinders from the engines entering the wagon and leading to
    fire break out;
 </section><section> 
    <number>h</number> two breast bars shall be provided on each side of the wagon, one at a
    height of 50 to 80 cm and the other at 110 cm.
</section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title>62</title>. For the transport of equines by goods-vehicles, the following precautions shall be taken, namely:—
 
 <section><number>a</number> specially fitted vehicles with a special type of tail-board and padding around the sides shall be used; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> ordinary goods vehicles shall be provided with anti slipping material on the floor and the superstructure, if low, should be raised; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> bamboo poles of at least 8 cm diameter between each animal and two stout batons at the back shall be provided to prevent the animal from falling; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> to prevent horses from being frightened or injured their heads should face left away from the passing traffic; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> each vehicle shall not carry more than four to six equines; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> each vehicle shall be provided with one attendant; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> these vehicles shall be driven at a speed not more than 35 kilometers per hour. 
  
</section>


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>63</number> </title>For the transport of equines by sea the following precautions shall be taken, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> horses may normally be accommodated in single stalls and mules in pens, each pen holding four to five mules; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> ample ventilation shall be ensured by keeping portholes and providing permanent air trunks or electric blowers on all decks, and exhaust fans shall be installed to blow out foul air; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> all standings shall be artwart the ship with heads facing inwards; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> to avoid distress specially during hot weather, the ship may go under way immediately after embarking and disembarking shall be done as early as possible after enchoring; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> colts and fillies shall be kept on the exposed decks; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> a pharmacy and spare stalls for five per cent of equines shall be available; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> passage between two rows of pens shall not be less than 1.5 metres. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>64</number></title> Rules 65 to 75 shall apply to the transport of sheep and goats by rail or
road involving journeys of more than six hours.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>65</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> A valid health certificate by a qualified veterinary surgeon to the effect
  that the sheep and goats are in a fit condition to travel by rail or road and are
  not suffering from infectious or contagious or parasitic disease shall accompany
each consignment.
 
 


</section><section> 
    <number>b</number> In the absence of such a certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the
    consignment for transport.
 </section><section> 
    <number>c</number> The certificate shall be in a form specified in Schedule J.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>66</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> Each consignment shall bear a label showing in bold red letter the
  name, address and telephone number (if any) of the consignor and consignee, the
  number and type of sheep or goats being transported and quantity of rations and
food provided.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> The consignee shall be informed in advance about the train or vehicle in
  which the consignment of sheep or goats are being sent and its arrival time.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> The consignment of sheep or goats shall be booked by the next train or
  vehicle and shall not be detained after the consignment is accepted for booking.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>67</number></title> 
<section><number>a</number> First-aid equipment shall accompany the sheep or goats in transit.
 </section><section> 
  <number>b</number> Suitable ramps shall be provided for loading and unloading the sheep or
  goats.
 </section><section> 
  <number>c</number> In the case of a railway wagon, when the loading or unloading is done on
  the platform the dropped door of the wagon shall be used as a ramp.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>68</number> </title>Sheep and goats shall be transported separately; but if the lots are small
special partition shall be provided to separate them.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>69</number></title> Rams and male young stock shall not be mixed with female stock in the
same compartment.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>70</number></title> Sufficient food and fodder shall be carried to last during the journey and
watering facility shall be provided at regular intervals.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>71</number></title> Material for padding, such as straw, shall be placed on the floor to avoid
injury if an animal lies down, and this shall be not less than 5 cm thick.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>72</number></title> The animals shall not be fettered unless there is a risk of their jumping out
and their legs shall not be tied down.


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>75</number> </title> 
<section><number>1</number> Goods vehicles of capacity of 5 or 4.5 tons, which are generally used for transporting animals, shall carry not more than forty sheep or goats. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the case of large goods vehicles and wagons, partition shall be provided at every two or three metres across the width to prevent the crowding and trapping of sheep and goats. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the case of ewes, goats or lambs or kids under six weeks of age, separate panels shall be provided. 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>76</number> Definitions. </title>—In this Chapter, unless the context otherwise requires, “Poultry” includes day old chicks and turkey poults, chickens, quails, guinea fowls, ducks, geese and turkeys. ] 





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>77</number> General requirement. </title>—In transport of poultry by rail, road or air— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> the containers shall be properly cleaned and sterilised before the poultry is placed in them; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> poultry shall not be exposed to the sunlight, rain and direct blast of air during transport; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> poultry shall not be transported when the temperature exceeds 25 degree Celsius or when the temperature falls below 15 degree Celsius.] 
</section>





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>78</number> Day-old chicks and turkey poults. </title>—In transport of day old chicks and poultry by rail, road and air— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Chicks and poults shall be packed and dispatched immediately after hatching and shall not be stored in boxes for any length of time before dispatch. <title></title>
 <title>Note: </title>In the said transport endeavour shall be made by the consignor or his agent so that consignments shall arrive at destination within the shortest possible time after being taken out of the incubator. Seventy-two hours shall normally be regarded as the maximum period to be taken from incubator to brooder in winter and 48 hours in summer; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> chicks or poults shall not be fed or watered before and during transportation; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> every effort shall be made to ensure that chicks and poults arrive as quickly as possible at the dispatching site; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> personal attention shall be given by the consignor or the forwarding agent to ensure that all consignments are kept out of direct sunlight, rain and heat; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> care shall be taken to carry the boxes in a level position so that chicks are not in danger of falling over on to their backs and the putting up of other merchandise over and around chick boxes shall be avoided.] 
</section>





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>79</number> Poultry other than day-old chicks and turkey poults. </title>—In transport of poultry other than day old chicks and turkey poult by rail, road or air— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> the poultry to be transported shall be healthy and in good condition and shall be examined and certified by a veterinary doctor for freedom from infectious diseases and fitness to undertake the journey; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> poultry transported in the same container shall be of the same species and of the same age group; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> poultry shall be properly fed and watered before it is placed in containers for transportation and extra feed and water shall be provided in suitable troughs fixed in the containers; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> arrangements shall be made for watering and feeding during transportation and during hot weather, watering shall be ensured every six hours; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> male stock shall not be transported with female stock in the same container. <title></title>] 
</section>





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>80</number> Road Travel. </title>—In transport of poultry by road the container shall not be placed one on the top of the other and shall be covered properly in order to provide light, ventilation and to protect from rain, heat and cold air. <title></title><title></title>] 
  





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>81</number> Rail Travel. </title>—In transport of poultry by rail,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> in case the journey is for more than twelve hours, an attendant shall accompany the consignment; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> poultry shall not be exposed to rain or direct blast of air; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> as far as possible poultry shall be transported in wagons having adequate facilities for ventilation and no other merchandise which may result in mortality of birds shall be loaded in the same wagon. <title></title>] 
</section>





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>82</number> Air travel. </title>—In transport of poultry by air or for international transport the containers carrying poultry shall be kept near the door and shall be unloaded immediately on arrival.
] 






</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>84</number> Special requirement of containers for chicks and poults. </title>—In transport of poultry by road, rail or air,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> wire mesh or a net of any material shall not be used as a bottom for the containers; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the container shall be properly secured to avoid pilferage; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> the following instruction shall be printed on a label and fixed to the lid or printed directly on sides, namely “Care in Transit”; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> the consignee shall be informed about the train, transport or flight number and its time of arrival well in advance; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> poultry shall not be transported continuously for more than 6 hours and whole batch shall be inspected at every 6 hours interval; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> the transportation shall not remain stationary for more than 30 min and during this period, it shall be parked in shade and arrangements shall be made for feeding and watering; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> all precautions against fire shall be taken and provision of fire extinguishers in transport shall be provided.] 
</section>





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>85</number> Definition. </title>—In this chapter, unless context otherwise requires, “pigs” includes piglets, hogs, hoglets and animals of pigs family.] <title></title>
  





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>86</number> Duration of travel. </title>—Rules 87 to 95 shall apply to the transport of pigs by rail or road involving journeys of more than six hours.] <title></title><title></title>
  





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>87</number> Health Certificate. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A valid health certificate by a veterinary doctor to the effect that the pigs are in a fit condition to travel by rail or road and are not suffering from infectious or contagious or parasitic disease shall accompany each consignment in the transport of pigs by rail or road. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the absence of a certificate under sub-rule (1), the carrier shall refuse to accept the consignment for transport. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The certificate under sub-rule (1) shall be in a form specified in 
  Schedule K.] 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>88</number> Identification of consignor and consignee. </title>—For the purpose of this Chapter— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> each consignment shall bear a label showing in bold red letters the name, address and telephone number (if any) of the consignor and consignee, the number and type of pigs being transported and quantity of rations and food provided to them; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the consignee shall be informed in advance about the train or vehicle in which the consignment of pigs is being sent and its arrival time; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> the consignment of pigs shall be booked by the next train or vehicle and shall not be detained after the consignment is accepted for booking. <title></title>] 
</section>





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>89</number> First aid. </title>—In transport of pigs by rail or road— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> first-aid equipment shall accompany the pigs; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> suitable ramps shall be provided for loading and unloading the pigs; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> in the case of a railway wagon, when the loading or unloading is done on the platform the dropped door of the wagon shall be used as a ramp. <title></title>] 
</section>





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title><title><number>90</number> Group of pigs. </title>—In transport of pigs by rail or road, male young stock shall not be mixed with female stock in the same compartment. <title></title>] 





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[</title><title> </title> <title><number>91</number> Facility of food and water. </title>—In transport of pigs by rail or road, sufficient food and fodder shall be carried to last during the journey and watering facility shall be provided at regular intervals. ] 





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>92</number> Padding of floor during travel. </title>—In transport of pigs by rail or road, material for padding, such as straw, shall be placed on the floor to avoid injury if an animal lies down, and this shall be not less than 5 cm thick. <title></title>] 





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>93</number> Ban on fettering. </title>—In transport of pigs by rail or road, the animals shall not be fettered unless there is a risk of their jumping out and their legs shall not be tied down. ] 





</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>96</number> Issue of certificate before transportation. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A valid certificate issued by an officer or any person or Animal Welfare Organisation duly recognised and authorised for this purpose by the Animal Welfare Board of India or the Central Government shall be procured by any person making transport of any animal before transportation of such animal verifying that all the relevant Central and State Acts, rules and orders pertaining to the said animals including the rules relating to transport of such animals have been duly complied with and that the animal is not being transported for any purpose contrary to the provision of any law. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the absence of such certificate, the carrier shall refuse to accept the consignment for transport. ] 
 Explanation.— For the purpose of this rule the certificate shall be issued in such form as may be specified for this purpose by the Central Government. ] 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>97</number> Cancellation of permit or authorisation for transport. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In the event of contravention or non-compliance of any of the rules contained in these rule for transport of animals, if it is pointed out in writing by any officer or persons or Animal Welfare Organisation authorised for this purpose by the Animal Welfare Board of India or the Central Government, then, any permit or authorisation issued for such transport shall be immediately cancelled by the concerned authority and it shall be the duty of the police to stop the further transport even from the intermediary station and proceed against the said offenders and deal with the animal in accordance with law. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The custody of the animals immediately after unloading from the rail wagons, truck or any other vehicle shall be given to the authorised Animal Welfare Organisation if available, till the competent authority or the Magistrate having jurisdiction decides about their care and upkeep.] <title></title>





</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>98</number> General conditions of transport. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Animals to be transported shall be healthy and in good condition and such animals shall be examined by a veterinary doctor for freedom from infectious diseases and their fitness to undertake the journey; provided that the nature and duration of the proposed journey shall be taken into account while deciding upon the degree of fitness. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An animal which is unfit for transport shall not be transported and the animals who are new born, diseased, blind emaciated, lame, fatigued or having given birth during the preceding seventy-two hours or likely to give birth during transport shall not be transported. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Pregnant and very young animals shall not be mixed with other animals during transport. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Different classes of animals shall be kept separately during transport. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Diseased animal, whenever transported for treatment, shall not be mixed with other animals. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Troublesome animals shall be given tranquilisers before loading during transport. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Animals shall be transported in their on-farm social groups (established atleast one week prior to journey).] 





</section></article><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE A
 


(See rule 4)
 




Proforma for certificate of fitness to Travel Dogs/Cats
 


This Certificate should be 
completed and signed by a qualified Veterinary Surgeon.
 


Date and time of 
examination................................................................................
 


Species of dogs/cats........................................................................................................
 


Number of 
cages.......................................Number of 
dogs/cats..............................
 


Sex 
..............................................................Age............................................................
 


Breed and identification 
marks, if any 
......................................................................
 


Transported from 
.........................................to..............................via 
......................
 


I hereby certify that I 
have read rules 8 to 14 in Chapter II of the Transport of Animals Rules, 1978.
 


1. That, at the request of 
(consignor)............................................................... I 
have examined the above mentioned dogs/cats in their travelling cages not more 
than 12 hours before their departure.
 


2. That each of the 
dogs/cats appeared to be in good health, free from signs of injury, contagious 
and infectious disease including rabies and in a fit condition to travel by 
rail/road/inland waterway/sea/air.
 


3. That the dogs/cats were 
adequately fed and watered for the purpose of the journey.
 


4. That the dogs/cats have 
been vaccinated.
 


        
(a)  Type of vaccine/s:
 


        
(b)  Date of vaccination/s:
 




 



Signed.........................................
 



Address........................................
 



Date.........................                                                                                                
Qualifications........................................
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE B
 


(See rule 11)
 




Size and Type of Crate for Transport of Dogs
 


The design of the cage 
mentioned in rule 11 in Chapter II of Transport of Animal Rules, 1978 shall be 
as per the design as printed on page 7 of IS : 4746-1968 published by the Indian 
Standards Institution.
 


All dimensions in 
Centimetres
 


By rail/road/inland 
waterway/sea, by air
 


Length (L)                     
A × 1½                    
A + C + 10
 


Width (W)                     
A                             
D + 2 + 10
 


Height (H)                     
B + 15                     
B +  10
 


Length—Tip of nose to root 
of tail (A)
 


Width—Width across the 
shoulders (D)
 


Height—Tip of ears to toe 
while standing (B)
 


Elbow Size—Toe to tip of 
elbow (C)
 


Note.—Cages, 
cartons or crates, used to transport dogs, shall be of such material which will 
not tear or crumble. They shall be well constructed, well ventilated and 
designed to protect the health of the dogs by giving them adequate space and 
safety. It is essential that wire mesh should be nose and paw proof; suitable 
material is a welded wire mesh of not less than 3 mm, with a spacing 12×12 mm. 
Expended metal and wire netting are unsuitable for this purpose. There should be 
no protruding nails or unprotected edges of wire. Dogs Kennels in rail coaches 
shall be so placed as to give protection to dogs from extreme of temperature and 
disturbance from birds and by giving them adequate space for health and safety.
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE C
 


(See rule 11)
 


SIZE AND TYPE OF CRATE 
FOR TRANSPORT OF CATS
 


The design of the cage 
mentioned in rule 11 in Chapter II of Transport of Animals Rules, 1978 shall be 
as per the design as printed on page 8 of IS : 4746-1968 published by the Indian 
Standards Institution.
 


All dimensions in 
Centimetres
 


By rail/road/inland 
water way/sea by air
 


Length (L)                     
A × 2                       
A × 2
 


Width (W)                     
A                             
A
 


Height (H)                     
B + 15                     
B + 10
 


Length—Tip of nose to root 
of tail (A)
 


Width—Width across the 
shoulders (D)
 


Height—Tip of ears to toe 
while standing (B)
 


Elbow Size—Toe to tip of 
elbow (C)
 


Note.—Cages, 
cartons or crates, used to transport cats, shall be of such material which will 
not tear or crumble. They shall be well constructed, well ventilated and 
designed to protect the health of the cats by giving them adequate space and 
safety. It is essential that wire mesh should be nose and paw proof; suitable 
material is a welded wire mesh of not less than 3 mm, with a spacing 12x12 mm. 
Expended metal and wire netting are unsuitable for this purpose. There should be 
no protruding nails or unprotected edges of wire. Cats Kennels in rail coaches 
shall be so placed as to give protection to cats from extremes of temperature 
and disturbance from birds and by giving them adequate space for health and 
safety.
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE D
 


(See rules 16 and 
32)
 


PROFORMA FOR CERTIFICATE 
OF FITNESS TO TRAVEL MONKEYS
 


This Certificate should be 
completed and signed by a qualified Veterinary Surgeon.
 


Date and time of 
examination.................................................................................
 


Species of Monkeys 
......................................................................................................
 


Number of Cages 
..........................................................................................................
 


Number of Monkeys 
......................................................................................................
 



Sex....................................................................Age 
......................................................
 


Breed and identification 
marks, if any 
..........................................................................
 


Transported from 
............................to 
..................................via.................................
 


I hereby certify that I 
have read rules 15 to 45 in Chapter III of the Transport of Animals Rules, 1978.
 


1. That, at the request of 
(consignor) ......................................................I examined the 
above  mentioned monkeys in their travelling cages not more than 12 hours 
before their departure.
 


2. That each monkey 
appeared to be in a fit condition to travel from the trapping area to the 
nearest rail-head/from the nearest rail-head to another rail-head/from the 
rail-head to the nearest airport/by air and is not showing any signs of 
infectious or contagious diseases.
 


3. That no monkeys appeared 
to be under 6 months of age and that no animal appeared to be pregnant.
 


4. That the monkeys were 
adequately fed and watered for the purpose of the journey.
 


5. That the monkeys have 
been vaccinated.
 


        
(a)  Type of vaccine/s :
 


        
(b)  Date of vaccination/s :
 




 



Signed.........................................
 



Address........................................
 



Date.........................                                                                                               
Qualifications........................................
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE E
 


[See rule 23(5)(a) 
and rule 23(6)]
 


SIZE AND TYPE OF CRATE 
FOR TRANSPORT OF MONKEYS FROM TRAPPING AREA TO NEAREST RAIL-HEAD
 


The construction detail of 
two types of cages mentioned in rule 22(5)(a) in Chapter III of the Transport of 
Animals Rules, 1978 shall be as per the dimensions and design as printed on page 
5 of IS : 3699 (Part-I)—1966 published by Indian Standard Institution.
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE F
 


[See rule 40(4)]
 


SIZE AND TYPE OF CRATE 
FOR TRANSPORT OF MONKEYS BY AIR
 


The construction details of 
the two types of cages mentioned in rule 40(3)(a) and (b) in Chapter III of 
Transport of Animal Rules, 1978 shall be as per the dimensions and design as 
printed on page 6 of IS : 3059—1965 published by Indian Standards Institution.
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE G
 


[See rule 40(5)]
 




Size and types of crate for transport by air of pregnant and nursing  

monkeys and monkeys weighing over 5 kg
 


The construction details of 
the two type of cages mentioned in rule 40(5) in Chapter III of Transport of 
Animal Rules, 1978 shall be as per the dimensions and design as printed on page 
7 of IS : 3059—1965 published by Indian Standards Institution.
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE H
 


(See rule 47)
 




proforma for certificate of fitness to travel cattle
 


This Certificate should be 
completed and signed by a qualified Veterinary Surgeon.
 


Date and time of 
examination 
....................................................................................
 


Species of Cattle  
.........................................................................................................
 


Number of Trucks/Railway 
Wagons 
..............................................................................
 


Number of Cattle 
.........................................................................................................
 


Sex 
...................................................................... Age 
.........................................
 


Breed and identification 
marks, if any 
.........................................................................
 


Transported from 
.....................................to ................................via 
.........................
 


I hereby certify that I 
have read rules 46 to 56 in Chapter IV of the Transport of Animals Rules, 1978,
 


1. That, at the request of 
(consignor) ........................................................ I examined 
the above mentioned cattle in the goods vehicle/railway wagons not more than 12 
hours before their departure.
 


2. That each cattle 
appeared to be in a fit condition to travel by rail/road and is not showing any 
signs of infectious or contagious or parasitic disease and that it has been 
vaccinated against rinderpest and any other infectious or contagious or 
parasitic disease(s).
 


3. That the cattle were 
adequately fed and watered for the purpose of the journey.
 


4. That the cattle have 
been vaccinated.
 


        
(a)  Type of vaccine:
 


        
(b)  Date of vaccination:
 


                                                                 
Signed..........................................
 


                                                                 
Address..........................................
 



Date..........................                                                                                              
Qualifications.........................................
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE I
 




proforma for certificate of fitness to travel equines
 


(See rule 58)
 


This Certificate should be 
completed and signed by a qualified Veterinary Surgeon.
 


Date and time of 
examination 
..............................................................................
 


Species of Equines  
......................................................................................................
 


Number of Equines 
.......................................................................................................
 


Sex 
...................................................................... Age 
................................................
 


Breed and identification 
marks, if any 
..........................................................................
 


Transported from 
.....................................to ................................via 
..........................
 


I hereby certify that I 
have read rules 57 to 63 in Chapter V of the Transport of Animals Rules, 1978,
 


1. That, at the request of 
(consignor) ........................................................ I examined 
the above mentioned equines not more than 12 hours before their departure.
 


2. That each equine 
appeared to be in a fit condition to travel by rail/road/sea and is not showing 
any signs of infectious or contagious disease(s) and that it has been vaccinated 
against any  infectious or contagious disease(s).
 


3. That the equines were 
adequately fed and watered for the purpose of the journey.
 


4. That the equines have 
been vaccinated.
 


        
(a)  Type of vaccine(s):     
 


        
(b)  Date of vaccination:
 



Signed.........................................
 



Address........................................
 



Date.........................                                                                                                
Qualifications........................................
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978
 





 


SCHEDULE J
 




proforma for certificate of fitness to travel sheep and goats
 


(See rule 65)
 


This Certificate should be 
completed and signed by a qualified Veterinary Surgeon.
 


Date and time of 
examination 
......................................................................................
 


Species of Animals  
......................................................................................................
 


Number of Animals 
......................................................................................................
 


Sex 
...................................................................... Age 
................................................
 


I hereby certify that I 
have read rules 64 to 75 in Chapter V of the Transport of Animals Rules, 1978.
 


1. That, at the request of 
(consignor) ........................................................ I examined 
the above mentioned animals not more than 12 hours before their departure.
 


2. That each appeared to be 
in a fit condition to travel by rail/road/sea and is not showing any signs of 
infectious or contagious or parasitic disease(s) and that it has been vaccinated 
against any  infectious or contagious disease (s).
 


3. That the animals were 
adequately fed and watered for the purpose of the journey.
 


4. That the animals have 
been vaccinated.
 


        
(a)  Type of vaccine(s):     
 


        
(b)  Date of vaccination:
 




 



Signed.........................................
 



Address........................................
 



Date.........................                                                                                                
Qualifications........................................
</form><form>
 




The Transport of Animals Rules, 1978 
 

 
 

1[ SCHEDULE K 
 

[ See  rule 87(3)] 
 

PROFORMA FOR CERTIFICATE OF FITNESS TO 
  TRAVEL PIGS 
 

(This certificate should be completed and signed by a Veterinary doctor.) 
 

Date and time of examination............................................................................................. 
 

Species of Animals................................................................................................................ 
 

Sex............................................................................................................................................ 
 

Age........................................................................................................................................... 
 

I hereby certify that I have read Rules 86 to 95 in Chapter VIII of the Transport of Animals Rules, 1978. 
 

1. That, at the request of (consignor)....................... I examined the above mentioned animals not more than 12 hours before their departure. 
 

2. That each appeared to be in a fit condition to travel by rail/road/sea and is not showing any signs of any infectious or contagious or parasitic disease(s) and that it has been vaccinated against any infectious or contagious disease(s). 
 

3. That the animals were adequately fed and watered for the purpose of the journey. 
 

4. That the animals have been vaccinated. 
 

(a) Type of vaccine(s): 
 

(b) Date of vaccination: 
 



 



Signed.........................................
 



Address........................................
 



Date.........................                                                                                                
Qualifications........................................
 

---------
 

1. Ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  rules 76  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  rules 77  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  rules 78  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  rules 79  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  rules 80  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  rules 81  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  rules 82  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  rules 84  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Rules 85  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Rules 86  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Rules 87  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Rules 88  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Rules 89  ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Rules 90 ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Rules 91 ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Rules 92 ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Rules 93 ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>Rules 96 ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>Rules 97 ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>Rules 98 ins. by G.S.R. 269(E), dated 26th March, 2001.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>