<act><tid>1685633</tid>
<title>THE SALAR JUNG MUSEUM ACT, <year>1961</year></title>

ACT NO. 26 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 19th May, <year>1961</year>.]

An Act to declare the Salar Jung Museum together with the Salar Jung 
Library at Hyderabad to be an institution of national importance and 
to provide for its administration and certain other connected matters.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1968746</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>167967</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Salar Jung Museum Act, <year>1961</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>149619</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>71503</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of Salar Jung Museum together with Salar Jung 
Library as an institution of national importance. It is hereby 
declared that the Salar Jung Museum together with the Salar Jung 
Library at Hyderabad in the State of Andhra Pradesh is an institution 
of national importance.


</article>



<article><tid>1717231</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1104472</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Board established under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1513775</tid>
<number>b</number>" Chairman" means the Chairman of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>486355</tid>
<number>c</number>" Fund" means the fund referred to in section 19;

</section>

<section><tid>1458306</tid>
<number>d</number>" member" means a member of the Board and includes the 
Chairman;

</section>

<section><tid>875602</tid>
<number>e</number>" museum" means the Salar Jung Museum together with the 
Salar Jung Library, declared to be an institution of 
national importance under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1998591</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>199120</tid>
<number>g</number>" State Government" means the Government of Andhra 
Pradesh.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>136</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1st July, <year>1961</year>; see Notification No. G. S. R. 817, dated the 15th 
June, <year>1961</year>, Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), p. 897.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

SALAR JUNG MUSEUM BOARD

CHAPTER II

SALAR JUNG MUSEUM BOARD




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>632077</tid>
<number> 4</number> Establishment and incorporation of the Board.
<section><tid>1822613</tid>
<number>1</number>With effect  
from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint, there shall be established for the purposes 
of this Act a Board to be known as the Salar Jung Museum Board.

</section>

<section><tid>941059</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall be a body corporate with the name aforesaid, 
having perpetual succession and a common seal with power, subject to 
the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and dispose of property 
and to contract, and may by that name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>1992837</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the 
Board shall not, except with the previous approval of the Central 
Government sell or otherwise dispose of any article or thing specified 
in Part I or II of the Schedule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1646824</tid>
<number> 5</number> Composition of the Board.
<section><tid>1028963</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall consist of the  
following persons, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1630082</tid>
<number>a</number>the Governor of Andhra Pradesh, ex officio Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1724922</tid>
<number>b</number>the Secretary to the Government of India in the 
Ministry concerned with matters relating to the museum, 
ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1088820</tid>
<number>c</number>the Mayor of the Corporation of Hyderabad, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>915136</tid>
<number>d</number>the Vice- Chancellor of the Osmania University, ex 
officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>831382</tid>
<number>e</number>the Accountant- General, Andhra Pradesh, ex officio;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1309480</tid>
<number>f</number>a person to be nominated by the Central Government, who 
shall be a member of the family of the late Nawab Salar 
Jung Bahadur who died on the 2nd day of March, <year>1949</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>831742</tid>
<number>g</number>three persons to be nominated by the Central Government 
who shall as far as possible be persons having 
knowledge of, and experience in, matters relating to 
the administration of museums and libraries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1805363</tid>
<number>h</number>two persons to be nominated by the State Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>72814</tid>
<number>2</number>Every nomination under this section shall take effect as soon 
as it is notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>831887</tid>
<number> 6</number> Term of office.
<section><tid>1431913</tid>
<number>1</number>The term of office of nominated members  
shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>388276</tid>
<number>2</number>Any nominated member may resign his office by giving notice 
in writing to the Central Government, and on such resignation being 
notified by the Central Government in the Official Gazette, shall be 
deemed to have vacated his office.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>137</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1777154</tid>
<number>3</number>A casual vacancy created by the resignation of a nominated 
member under sub- section (2) or for any other reason may be filled by 
fresh nomination.

</section>

<section><tid>1777038</tid>
<number>4</number>An outgoing member shall be eligible for renomination.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1942395</tid>
<number> 7</number> Temporary absence of member.
<section><tid>1621191</tid>
<number>1</number>If any nominated member is by  
infirmity or otherwise rendered temporarily incapable of carrying out 
his duties or is absent on leave or otherwise in circumstances not 
involving the vacation of his office, the Central Government or the 
State Government, as the case may be, may nominate another person to 
act in his place during his absence.

</section>

<section><tid>365697</tid>
<number>2</number>No act of the Board shall be invalid merely by reason of--

<subsection><tid>617106</tid>
<number>a</number>any vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of, the 
Board, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1446423</tid>
<number>b</number>any defect in the nomination of a person acting as a 
member thereof, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1531621</tid>
<number>c</number>any irregularity in its procedure not affecting the 
merits of the case.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1567832</tid>
<number> 8</number> Duty of Government nominating persons, etc.
<section><tid>1811066</tid>
<number>1</number>Before  
nominating a person to be a member of the Board, the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be, shall satisfy 
itself that the person will have no such financial or other interest 
as is likely to affect prejudicially the exercise or performance by 
him of his functions as a member of the Board, and the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be, shall also 
satisfy itself from time to time with respect to every member of the 
Board nominated by it that he has no such interest; and any person who 
is or whom the Central Government or the State Government, as the case 
may be, proposes to nominate, and who has consented to be, a member of 
the Board shall, whenever requested by the Central or State Government 
so to do, furnish to it such information as that Government considers 
necessary for the performance by it of its duties under this sub- 
section.

</section>

<section><tid>1780419</tid>
<number>2</number>A nominated member who is in any way, directly or indirectly, 
interested in a contract made, or proposed to be made, by the Board 
shall, as soon as possible, after relevant circumstances have come to 
his knowledge, disclose the nature of his interest at a meeting of the 
Board and the disclosure shall be recorded in the minutes of the Board 
and the member shall not take any part after the disclosure in any 
deliberation or decision of the Board with respect to that contract.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>138</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1993533</tid>
<number> 9</number> Meeting of the Board.
<section><tid>1959259</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall meet at such times  
and places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub- sections (2), 
 (3) and (4), observe such rules of procedure in regard to the 
transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum at  
  meetings) as may be provided by regulations made under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>183325</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chairman or, in his absence, any member chosen by the 
members present from among themselves, shall preside at a meeting of 
the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>407491</tid>
<number>3</number>If any of the members referred to in clauses (b), (c), (d) 
and (e) of section 5 is unable to attend any meeting of the Board, he 
may, with the previous approval of the Chairman, authorise any person 
in writing to do so.

</section>

<section><tid>761613</tid>
<number>4</number>All questions at a meeting of the Board shall be decided by a 
majority of the votes of the members present and voting and in the 
case of an equality of votes, the Chairman or, in his absence, the 
member presiding shall have a second or casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1503003</tid>
<number> 10</number> Temporary association of persons with the Board for 
particular purposes.
<section><tid>1119084</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may associate with itself in such  
manner and for such purposes as may be provided by regulations made 
under this Act any person whose assistance or advice it may desire in 
performing any of its functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1959116</tid>
<number>2</number>A person associated with it by the Board under sub- section 
 (1) for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the 
discussions of the Board relating to that purpose, but shall not by 
virtue of this section be entitled to vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>178711</tid>
<number>11</number>Authentication of orders and other instruments of the Board. 
All orders and decisions of the Board shall be authenticated by the 
signature of the Chairman or any other member authorised by the Board 
in this behalf, and all other Instruments issued by the Board shall be 
authenticated by the signature of an officer of the Board authorised 
in like manner in this behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>850153</tid>
<number> 12</number> Staff of the Board.
<section><tid>194047</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub-  
section (2), the Board may, for the purpose of enabling it efficiently 
to perform its functions under this Act, appoint such number of 
officers and other employees as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>200766</tid>
<number>2</number>The recruitment and conditions of service of such officers 
and employees shall be such as may be provided by regulations made 
under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>151573</tid>
<number>13</number>Transfer of service of existing employees to the Board. 
Subject to the provisions of this Act, every person employed in the 
museum immediately before the date of establishment of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>139</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Board shall, on and from such date, become an employee of the Board 
with such designation as the Board may determine and shall hold his 
office or service therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration 
and upon the same terms and conditions as he would have held the same 
on such date if the Board had not been established and shall continue 
to do so unless and until his employment in the Board is terminated or 
until such tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions are duly 
altered by the Board:

Provided that the tenure, remuneration and terms and conditions 
of service of any such person shall not be altered to his disadvantage 
without the previous approval of the Central Government.



</article>



<article><tid>1952410</tid>
<number>14</number>Location of museum. The museum shall be located at Hyderabad.
CHAP

FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD

CHAPTER III

FUNCTIONS OF THE BOARD



</article>



<article><tid>1969666</tid>
<number> 15</number> Duties of the Board.
<section><tid>1310607</tid>
<number>1</number>It shall be the general duty of the  
Board to manage the museum efficiently and to plan, promote, organise 
and implement programmes for the development of the museum and to 
perform such other functions as the Central Government may, from time 
to time, assign to the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>446253</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing provision, the Board may take such steps as it thinks fit--

<subsection><tid>1025451</tid>
<number>a</number>for providing for instruction and research in matters 
relating to museums and libraries and for the 
advancement of learning and dissemination of knowledge 
in such matters; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1757561</tid>
<number>b</number>to do all such other things as may be necessary for the 
discharge of its functions under this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>627351</tid>
<number> 16</number> Powers of the Board.
<section><tid>358936</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such conditions and  
restrictions as the Central Government may think fit to impose, the 
Board may exercise all such powers as may be necessary or expedient 
for the purpose of carrying out its duties under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>695977</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to such regulations as may be made by the Board in 
this behalf, the Board may, from time to time,-

<subsection><tid>1823065</tid>
<number>a</number>purchase or otherwise acquire such articles or things 
as may, in the opinion of the Board, be worthy of 
preservation in the museum; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1918921</tid>
<number>b</number>exchange, sell, or destroy any such article or thing as 
is purchased or acquired under clause (a); or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>140</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>840295</tid>
<number>c</number>lend within India any article or thing specified in 
Part I or Part II of the Schedule, or lend, whether 
within or without India, any such article or thing as 
is purchased or acquired under clause (a).
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1295629</tid>
<number>17</number>Vesting of property. The properties specified in Parts I, II 
and III of the Schedule, being properties which by virtue of the 
decree passed in C. S. No. 13 of <year>1958</year> on the file of the High Court of 
Andhra Pradesh vested absolutely in the Central Government, shall, on 
and from the date of the establishment of the Board, vest in the 
Board.


</article>



<article><tid>578007</tid>
<number>18</number>Grants by Central Government to the Board. For the purpose of 
enabling the Board to discharge its functions efficiently under this 
Act, the Central Government may, after due appropriation made by 
Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the Board in each financial 
year such sums of money as that Government considers necessary by way 
of grant, loan or otherwise.


</article>



<article><tid>1749726</tid>
<number> 19</number> Fund of the Board.
<section><tid>1524215</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall maintain a Fund to  
which shall be credited--

<subsection><tid>156369</tid>
<number>a</number>all moneys paid by the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1363244</tid>
<number>b</number>all fees and other charges levied under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>610175</tid>
<number>c</number>all moneys received by the Board by way of grant, gift, 
donation, benefaction, bequest, subscription, 
contribution or transfer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>486109</tid>
<number>d</number>all other moneys received by the Board in any other 
manner or from any other source.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>570842</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may expend such sums as it thinks fit for 
performing its functions under this Act and such sums shall be treated 
as expenditure payable out of the Fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1589481</tid>
<number>3</number>A sum of money not exceeding such amount as may be provided 
by regulations made under this Act may be kept in current account with 
any scheduled bank as defined in section 2 of the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>), or any other bank approved by the Central 
Government in this behalf, but any moneys in excess of that sum shall 
be deposited in the Reserve Bank of India or with the agents of the 
Reserve Bank of India or invested in such manner as may be approved by 
the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>141</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1646109</tid>
<number> 20</number> Budget.
<section><tid>112734</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall, by such date in each year as may  
be specified by the Central Government, submit to it for approval a 
budget for the next financial year in the form specified by it, 
showing the estimated receipts and expenditure, and the sums which 
would be required from the Central Government during the next 
financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>1221768</tid>
<number>2</number>If any sum granted by the Central Government remains wholly 
or partly unspent in any financial year, the unspent sum may be 
carried forward to the next financial year and taken into account in 
determining the sum to be provided by the Central Government for that 
year.

</section>

<section><tid>1167527</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (4), no sum shall be 
expended by or on behalf of the Board, unless the expenditure is 
covered by provision in the budget approved by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>102737</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to such conditions and restrictions as the Central 
Government may think fit to impose, the Board may sanction any re- 
appropriation from one head of expenditure to another or from a 
provision made for one purpose to that for another purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1294917</tid>
<number> 21</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>552340</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts including the balance sheet in such form as may be specified, 
and in accordance with such general directions as may be issued by the 
Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor 
General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>451849</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Board shall be audited annually by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any expenditure incurred 
by him in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Board to 
the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.

</section>

<section><tid>176254</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Board shall have the same rights, privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General of 
India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts, and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect the office of the Board, and the museum.

</section>

<section><tid>1579331</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Board as certified by the Comptroller and 
Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed by him in this 
behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall be forwarded 
annually to the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>142</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>416442</tid>
<number> 22</number> Returns and reports.
<section><tid>1663913</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall furnish to the  
Central Government at such time and in such form and in such manner as 
the Central Government may direct, such returns, statements and 
particulars as the Central Government may from time to time require.

</section>

<section><tid>338753</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Board shall, as soon as possible after the commencement of each 
financial year, submit to the Central Government within such time as 
may be specified by the Central Government a report giving a true and 
full account of the activities of the Board during the previous 
financial year and an account of the activities likely to be 
undertaken during the current financial year.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1502744</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power of Central Government to issue directions to the Board.

<section><tid>802215</tid>
<number>1</number>In the discharge of its functions under this Act, the Board shall  
be bound by such directions on questions of policy as the Central 
Government may give to it from time to time:
Provided that the Board shall be given an opportunity to express 
its views before any direction is given under this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>1118331</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the Central Government whether a question is 
one of policy or not shall be final.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1007878</tid>
<number>24</number>Delegation of powers and duties. The Board may, by general or 
special order in writing, direct that all or any of the powers or 
duties which may be exercised or discharged by it shall, in such 
circumstances and under such conditions, if any, as may be specified 
in the order, be exercised or discharged also by any member, officer 
or employee of the Board specified in this behalf in the order.


</article>



<article><tid>953620</tid>
<number>25</number>Officers and employee of the Board to be public servants. All 
officers and employees of the Board shall, when acting or purporting 
to act in pursuance of the provisions of this Act or of any rule or 
regulation made thereunder, be deemed to be public servants within the 
meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1866</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1851592</tid>
<number>26</number>Protection of action taken under Act. No suit, prosecution or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against the Board or any member, 
officer or employee of the Board for anything which is in good faith 
done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of any rule or 
regulation made there- under.


</article>



<article><tid>194204</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>1767446</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, after consultation with the Board, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the provisions of 
this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>143</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>185811</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>499528</tid>
<number>a</number>the term of office of, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, the members nominated under clauses 
 (f), (g) and (h) of sub- section (1) of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>549912</tid>
<number>b</number>the travelling and other allowances payable to a member 
other than the Chairman;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>743088</tid>
<number>c</number>the disqualifications for membership of the Board and 
the procedure to be followed in removing a member who 
is or becomes subject to any disqualification;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1412817</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which, 
contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the 
Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614837</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be levied for admission to the museum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>193801</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>608161</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1751157</tid>
<number> 28</number> Power of Board to make regulations.
<section><tid>702352</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, with  
the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, make regulations, not inconsistent with this Act 
and the rules made thereunder, for enabling it to discharge its 
functions under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1685040</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any or the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1218414</tid>
<number>a</number>the conditions and restrictions subject to which 
articles and things vested in the Board may be given on 
loan;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1442978</tid>
<number>b</number>the recruitment and conditions of service of officers 
and employees of the Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1116387</tid>
<number>c</number>the time and place of meetings of the Board, the 
procedure to be followed in regard to the transaction 
of business
<pagefootnote><pagenum>144</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


at such meetings and the quorum necessary for the 
transaction of business at a meeting;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1345058</tid>
<number>d</number>the maintenance of minutes of meetings of the Board and 
the transmission of copies thereof to the Central 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>463073</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of sub- committees, or the association 
of person by the Board, for the purpose of assisting or 
advising it in performing its functions under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1192357</tid>
<number>f</number>the persons by whom, and the manner in which, payments, 
deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the 
Board;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1835104</tid>
<number>g</number>the maximum amount that may be kept in the current 
account;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1588922</tid>
<number>h</number>the maintenance of registers and accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>799397</tid>
<number>i</number>the compilation of catalogues and inventories of the 
books, manuscripts and other articles and things in the 
museum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1798931</tid>
<number>j</number>the steps to be taken for the preservation of the 
books, manuscripts and other articles and things in the 
museum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1103002</tid>
<number>k</number>the general management of the museum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1095086</tid>
<number>l</number>the fees to be levied for purposes other than admission 
to the museum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>241642</tid>
<number>m</number>any other matter in respect of which provision is, in 
the opinion of the Board, necessary for the performance 
of its functions under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1373292</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, after consultation with the 
Board, by notification in the Official Gazette, amend, vary or rescind 
any regulation which it has approved; and thereupon the regulation 
shall have effect accordingly, but without prejudice to the exercise 
of the powers of the Board under sub- section (1) and (2).

</section>

<section><tid>659573</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every regulation made under this Act and every 
notification issued under sub- section (3) shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made or issued, before each House of Parliament, 
while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the regulation or notification or both House agree 
that the regulation or notification should not be made, the regulation 
or notification shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that regulation or notification."]


</section>

</article>



 </act>