<act><title>THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (BORROWING OR LENDING IN FOREIGN EXCHANGE) REGULATIONS, 20001</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>i</number> These regulations may be called the Foreign Exchange Management (Borrowing or Lending in Foreign Exchange) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> They shall come into force on the 1st day of June, 2000. 








</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-In these regulations, unless the context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> 'Act' means, the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 1999 (42 of 1999); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> 'authorised dealer' means a person authorised as an authorised dealer under sub-section (1) of section 10 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> 'EEFC account', 'RFC account' mean the accounts referred to in the Foreign Exchange Management (Foreign Currency Accounts by a Person Resident in India ) Regulations, 2000; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> 'FCNR (B) account', 'NRE account' means the accounts referred to in the Foreign Exchange Management (Deposit) Regulations, 2000; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> 'Indian entity' means a company or a body corporate or a firm in India ; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> 'joint venture abroad' means a foreign concern formed, registered or incorporated in a foreign country in accordance with the laws and regulations of that country and in which investment has been made by an Indian entity; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> 'Schedule' means the Schedule to these Regulations; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> 'wholly owned subsidiary abroad' means a foreign concern formed, registered or incorporated in a foreign country in accordance with the laws and regulations of that country and whose entire capital is owned by an Indian entity; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> the words and expressions used but not defined in these regulations shall have the same meaning respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>








</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Prohibition to borrow or lend in foreign exchange. </title>-Save as otherwise provided in the Act, rules or regulations made thereunder, no person resident in India shall borrow or lend in foreign exchange from or to person resident in or outside India: 
 Provided that the Reserve Bank may, for sufficient reasons, permit a person to borrow or lend in foreign exchange from or to a person resident outside India . 








</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Borrowing and lending in foreign exchange by an authorised dealer. </title>- 

<section><number>1</number> An authorised dealer in India or his branch outside India may lend in foreign currency in the circumstances and subject to the conditions mentioned below, namely:- 
 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> A branch outside India of an authorised dealer being a bank incorporated or constituted in India , may extend foreign currency loans in the normal course of its banking business outside India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> An authorised dealer may grant loans to his constituents in India for meeting their foreign exchange requirements or for their rupee working capital requirements or capital expenditure subject to compliance with prudential norms, interest rate directives and guidelines, if any, issued by Reserve Bank in this regard; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> An authorised dealer may extend credit facilities to a wholly owned subsidiary abroad or a joint venture abroad of an India entity: 
 Provided that not less than 51 per cent of equity in such subsidiary or joint venture is held by the Indian entity subject to compliance with the Foreign Exchange Management (Transfer and Issue of Foreign Security) Regulations, 2000; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> An authorised dealer may, in this commercial judgment and in compliance with the prudential norms, grant loans in foreign exchange to his constituent maintaining <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***] RFC Account, against the security of funds held in such account; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> A branch outside India of an authorised dealer may extend foreign currency loans against the security of funds held in NRE/FCNR deposit accounts maintained in accordance with the Foreign Exchange Management (Deposit) Regulations, 2000; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> Subject to the directions or guidelines issued by the Reserve Bank from time to time, an authorised dealer in India may extend foreign currency loans to another authorised dealer in India ; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>vii</number> An authorised dealer may grant foreign currency loans in India against the security of funds held in FCNR (B) account to the account holder only, subject to the guidelines issued by the Reserve Bank in this regard.] 
</subsection>
 
 Explanation .-For the purpose of clause (i), the aggregate loans availed of by all branches in India of the authorised dealer from his Head Office, all branches and correspondents outside India , shall be reckoned. 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***] 
 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>ii</number>] A branch outside India of an authorised dealer being a bank incorporated or constituted in India, may borrow in foreign currency in the normal course of its banking business outside India, subject to the directions or guidelines issued by the Reserve Bank from time to time, and the Regulatory Authority of the country where the branch is located. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>iii</number>] An authorised dealer may borrow in foreign currency from a bank or a financial institution outside India, for the purpose of granting pre-shipment or post-shipment credit in foreign currency to his exporter constituent, subject to compliance with the guidelines issued by the Reserve Bank in this regard. 
</subsection>














</section><section><number>2</number> An authorised dealer in India may borrow in foreign currency in the circumstances and subject to the conditions mentioned below, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> An authorised dealer may borrow from his Head Office or branch or correspondent outside India upto <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[fifty per cent] of this unimpaired Tier I capital or US$ 10 million, whichever is more, subject to such conditions as the Reserve Bank may direct. 
</subsection>
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Borrowing and lending in foreign exchange by persons other than authorised dealer. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> An Indian entity may lend in foreign exchange to its wholly owned subsidiary or joint venture abroad constituted in accordance with the provisions of Foreign Exchange Management (Transfer or Issue of Foreign Security) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person resident in India may borrow, whether by way of loan or overdraft or any other credit facility, from a bank situated outside India, for execution outside India of a turnkey project of civil construction contract or in connection with exports on deferred payment terms, provided the terms and conditions stipulated by the authority which has granted the approval to the project or contract or export in accordance with the Foreign Exchange Management (Export of Goods and Services) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An importer in India may, for import of goods into India, avail of foreign currency credit for a period not exceeding six months extended by the overseas supplier of goods, provided the import is in compliance with the Export Import Policy of the Government of India in force. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A person resident in India may lend in foreign currency out of funds held in his EEFC account, for trade related purposes to his overseas importer customer: 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[Provided that where the amount of loan exceeds US $ 100,000, a guarantee of a bank of international repute situated outside India is provided by the overseas borrower in favour of the lender.] 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Foreign currency loans may be extended by Export Import Bank of India, Industrial Development Bank of India, Industrial Finance Corporation of India, Industrial Credit and Investment Corporation of India Limited, Small Industries Development Bank of India Limited or any other institution in India to their constituents in India out of foreign currency borrowings raised by them with the approval of the Central Government for the purpose of onward lending. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> An individual resident in India may borrow a sum not exceeding US $ 250,000 or its equivalent from his close relatives outside India , subject to the conditions that- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the minimum maturity period of the loan is one year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the loan is free of interest; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the amount of loan is received by inward remittance in free foreign exchange through normal banking channels or by debit to the NRE/FCNR account of the non-resident lender. 
</subsection>
 Explanation .-'Close relative' means relative as defined in section 6 of the Companies Act, 1956.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> Indian companies in India may grant loans in foreign currency to the employees of their branches outside India for personal purposes provided that the loan shall be granted for personal purposes in accordance with the lender's Staff Welfare Scheme/Loan Rules and other terms and conditions as applicable to its staff resident in India and abroad.] 











</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>9</footcitenum><title>[<number>6</number> Other borrowings in foreign exchange under automatic route or with prior approval of the Reserve Bank of India under the approval route or as trade credit. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> A person resident in India, other than a branch or office in India owned or controlled by a person resident outside India, may raise in accordance with the provisions of the automatic route scheme specified in Schedule I, foreign currency loans of the nature and for the purposes as specified in that Schedule; provided that this shall be deemed to have come into force with effect from February 1, 2004, except in relation to item 1(iv) (A) (c) of 
Schedule I which shall be deemed to have come into force with effect from  
February 23, 2004. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person resident in India who desires to raise foreign currency loans of the nature or for the purpose as specified in Schedule II and who satisfies the eligibility and other conditions specified in that Schedule, may apply to the Reserve Bank for prior approval to raise such loans; provided that this shall be deemed to have come into force with effect from February 1, 2004, except in relation to item 3(iii)(A)(C) of Schedule II which shall be deemed to have come into force with effect from February 23, 2004. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Trade credit no exceeding US D 20 Million per import transaction shall be raised by borrowings subject to the terms specified in Schedule III hereto; provided that this shall be deemed to have come into force with effect from April 17, 2004.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>4</number>] <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[Where prior approval is required] the Reserve Bank may grant its approval subject to such terms and conditions as it may consider necessary: 
 Provided that while considering the grant of approval, the Reserve Bank shall take into account the overall limit stipulated by it, in consultation with the Central Government, for availment of such loans by the persons resident in India . 
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>5</number>] <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[Reserve Bank may grant its approval to any other foreign currency loan proposed to be raised by a person resident in India, which falls outside the scope of Schedules I, II and III, subject to such terms and conditions as it may consider necessary.] 













</section></article><form>
 

THE FOREIGN EXCHANGE MANAGEMENT (BORROWING OR LENDING IN FOREIGN EXCHANGE) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

2[Schedule I 
 

[ See regulation 6(1)] 
 

Borrowings in foreign exchange under the automatic route 
 

(1) Borrowing in foreign exchange up to US $ 500 million or its equivalent. The borrowing in foreign exchange by a person resident in India under the automatic route is subject to the terms and conditions set out in this Schedule. 
 

3[(i) Eligibility  
 
 

(a) Any company registered under the Companies Act, 1956, other than a financial intermediary (such as a bank, financial institution, housing finance company and a non-banking finance company) is eligible to borrow under this Schedule. 
 

(b) Non-Government organisations engaged in micro-finance activities may borrow in foreign exchange under this Schedule under such terms and conditions as specified by the Reserve Bank from time-to-time. 
 

(c) Any other entity as specified by the Reserve Bank.] 

 

3[(ii) Amount.  
 
 

(a) The borrowing in foreign exchange by an entity as specified in paragraph (i)(a) of section I of Schedule I, under the Automatic Route whether raised in tranches or otherwise, shall not exceed US $ 500 million or equivalent in any one financial year (April-March). 
 

(b) The borrowings in foreign currency under as specified in paragraph (i)(b) of section I of Schedule I, by a non-Government organisation engaged in micro-finance activities shall not exceed US $ 5 million or equivalent during a financial year (April-March).] 

 

(iii) Lenders. The borrowings in foreign currency by way of issue of bonds, floating rate notes or other debt instruments by whatever name called may be made from 
 
 

(a) International bank or export credit agency or international capital market, or 
 

(b) Multilateral financial institutions, namely, IFC, ADB, CDC, etc., or 
 

(c) Foreign collaborator or foreign equity holder as specified by the Reserve Bank, or 
 

(d) Supplier of equipment provided the amount of loan raised does not exceed the total cost of the equipment being supplied by the lender, or 
 

(e) Any other eligible entity as prescribed by the Reserve Bank in consultation with Government of India. 

 

(iv) Purpose (End-use). (A) Borrowing in foreign exchange in terms of this Schedule may be for any of the following purposes, namely: 
 
 

(a) for investment (such as import of capital goods, new projects, modernisation/expansion of existing production units) in real sectorindustrial sector including small and medium enterprises (SME) and infrastructure sector in India . 

 

4[ Explanation .The following sectors will qualify as infrastructure sectors, namely: (i) Power, (ii) Telecommunication, (iii) Railways, (iv) Road including Bridges, (v) Sea Port and Airport, (vi) Industrial Parks, (vii) Urban Infrastructure (water supply, sanitation and sewage projects) and (viii) Mining, Exploration and Refining.] 
 
 

(b) for first stage acquisition of shares in the disinvestment process and also in the mandatory second stage offer to the public under the Government's disinvestment programme of PSU shares, 
 

(c) for direct investment in overseas joint ventures (JV)/wholly  

    owned subsidiaries (WOS) subject to the existing guidelines on Indian direct investment in JV/WOS abroad. 
 

5[(d) any other eligible purpose as specified by the Reserve Bank.] 

 

6[(AA) Borrowings in foreign exchange per borrower company per financial year up to such amounts not exceeding US Dollars 500 million or its equivalent as directed by the Reserve Bank from time to time shall be permitted for such permissible end-uses as indicated by Reserve Bank from time to time.] 
 

(B) Other than the purposes specified hereinabove, the borrowings shall not be utilised for any other purpose including the following purposes, namely: 
 

On-lending, investment in capital (stock-market, investment in real estate business, working capital requirements, general corporate purpose, and repayment of rupee loans. 
 

7[***] 
 
 

(v) Maturity. The maturity of the borrowings in foreign exchange shall be as under : 

 

Amount Minimum average maturity 
 
 

(i) Up to US $ 20 million or equivalent Not less than 3 years; 
 

(ii) Exceeding US $ 20 million and up to US $ 500 Not less than 5 years, 
 

million or equivalen t 

 

Note. Borrowing up to US $ 20 million can have call/put option provided the minimum average maturity of three years as prescribed above is complied with before exercising call/put option. 
 
 

(vi) All-in-cost ceilings. The all-in-cost ceilings for the borrowing in foreign exchange shall be specified by the Reserve Bank from time to time. 
 

(vii) Security. The borrower shall be at liberty to provide security to the lender/suppliers, provided that 
 

(a) Where the security is in the form of immovable property in India or shares of a company in India , it shall be subject to regulation 8 of Notification No. FEMA. 21/2000-RB, dated 3rd May, 2000 and regulation 3 of Notification No. FEMA.20/2000-RB, dated 3rd May, 2000, respectively. 
 

(b) Guarantee. Banks, financial institutions and non-banking finance companies shall not provide (issue) guarantee or letter of comfort or standby letter of credit in favour of overseas lender on behalf of their constituents for their borrowings in foreign exchange. 

 

(viii) Prepayment. Notwithstanding the provisions of clause (v) above, prepayment of outstanding foreign currency loan may be made as per the directives issued by the Reserve Bank from time to time. 
 

8[(ix) Parking of loan amount .The proceeds of borrowings in foreign exchange availed under the schedule may, pending utilisation for permissible end-uses, be parked abroad or in India as directed by the Reserve Bank from time to time.] 
 

(x) Loan agreement. The loan agreement entered into by the borrower with the overseas lender shall strictly conform with these Regulations. The procedure for obtaining loan registration number would be prescribed by the Reserve Bank. 
 

(xi) Drawal of loan. Draw-downs of borrowing in foreign exchange shall be made strictly in accordance with the terms of the loan agreement only after obtaining the loan registration number from the Reserve Bank. 
 

(xii) Reporting. The borrower shall adhere to the reporting procedure as specified by the Reserve Bank from time to time. 
 

(xiii) Debt servicing. The designated authorised dealer (AD) shall have the general permission to make remittances of principal, interest and other charges in conformity with the guidelines on borrowing in foreign exchange from overseas, issued by the Central Government/the Reserve Bank from time to time. 
 

2. Refinancing of existing borrowing in foreign exchange. (i) Refinancing of outstanding amounts of loans raised in foreign exchange in accordance with the Act or the Rules and Regulations made there under, may be made by making fresh borrowing in foreign exchange in accordance with this Schedule provided that there is reduction in cost of borrowing and the outstanding maturity of the original borrowing is not reduced. 
 

(ii) Provisions of sub-paragraphs (ii), and (v) of paragraph 1 shall not apply to the borrowings made under clause 2(i). 
 

-----------
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 386(E), dated 3rd May, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
      Sec. 3 (i), dated 5th May, 2000 and subsequently amended vide : 
 

G.S.R. 674(E), dated 25-8-2000. G.S.R. 825(E), dated 22-12-2004. 
 

G.S.R. 476(E), dated 8-7-2002. G.S.R. 60(E), dated 9-2-2005. 
 

G.S.R. 854(E), dated 31-12-2002. G.S.R. 739(E), dated 22-12-2005. 
 

G.S.R. 531(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 663(E), dated 16-10-2007. 
 

G.S.R. 533(E), dated 9-7-2003. G.S.R. 61(E), dated 30-1-2009. 
 

G.S.R. 208(E), dated 23-3-2004. G.S.R. 547(E), dated 17-6-2009. 
 

2. Subs. by G.S.R. 825 (E), dated 13th December, 2004, for Schedule. 
 

3. Subs. by G.S.R. 739 (E), dated 6th December, 2005, for sub-paragraphs (i) and (ii) (w.r.e.f. 
  25-4-2005). 
 

4. Subs. by G.S.R. 547(E), dated 17th June, 2009, for Explanation (w.r.e.f. 8-10-2008). 
 

5. Ins. by G.S.R. 750(E), dated 19th December, 2005 (w.r.e.f. 25-4-2005). 
 

6. Subs by G.S.R. 547(E), dated 17th June, 2009 for Clause (AA) (w.r.e.f. 29-5-2008). Earlier Clause (AA) was inserted by G.R.S. 663(E), dated 30th August, 2007 (w.r.e.f. 7-8-2007). 
 

7. Note omitted by G.S.R. 663(E), dated 30th August, 2007 (w.r.e.f. 21-5-2007). 
 

8. Subs. by G.S.R. 547(E), dated 17th June, 2009, for sub-paragraph (ix) (w.r.e.f. 22-10-2008). 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 674 (E), dated 14th August, 2000 (w.e.f. 14-8-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Added by G.S.R. 533 (E), dated 10th January, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-7-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 61(E), dated 13th January, 2009 (w.r.e.f. 15-10-2008). Earlier it was substituted by G.S.R. 476(E), dated 29th April, 2002 (w.e.f. 8-7-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Clause (ii) omitted by G.S.R. 60 (E), dated 9th February, 2005 (w.r.e.f. 24-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Clauses (iii) and (iv) renumbered as clauses (ii) and (iii) respectively by G.S.R. 60 (E), dated 9th February, 2005 (w.r.e.f. 24-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 208 (E), dated 6th March, 2004, for the proviso (w.e.f. 23-3-2004).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 854 (E), dated 1st November, 2002 (w.e.f. 31-12-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 531 (E), dated 8th January, 2003 (w.e.f. 9-7-2003).  Ed  . sub-regulation (6) has already been inserted by G.S.R. 854 (E), dated 1st November, 2002 (w.e.f. 31-12-2002), hence sub-regulation (6) as inserted by G.S.R. 531 (E) has been numbered as sub-regulation (7).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 825 (E), dated 13th December, 2004, for regulation 6.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Sub-regulation (2) renumbered as sub-regulation (4) by G.S.R. 825 (E), dated 13th December, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 825 (E), dated 13th December, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Sub-regulation (3) renumbered as sub-regulation (5) by G.S.R. 825 (E), dated 13th December, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs by G.S.R. 825 (E), dated 13th December, 2004, for sub-regulation (3).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>