<act><title>THE TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF INDIA (ANNUAL 
REPORT AND RETURNS) RULES, 19991 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Annual Report and Returns) 
Rules, 1999. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 
  1997). 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Appendix means an Appendix annexed to these rules. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Words and expressions used in these rules but not defined in the Act 
  shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Furnishing of returns. </title>
<section><number>i</number> The Authority shall furnish 
quarterly, to the Central Government, returns and statements on the matters 
specified in Appendix-I, including matters as may be specified by the Central 
Government from time to time. 
 
 

</section><section><number>ii</number> The Authority shall also furnish such returns, statements or 
  particulars in regard to any proposed or existing programme for the promotion 
  and development of the Telecommunications services, as the Central Government 
  may direct from time to time. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Preparation and submission of annual report. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
Authority shall prepare as soon as may be, after the commencement of each 
financial year the annual report referred to in sub-section (2) of section 24 of 
the Act in the form specified in Appendix II. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The annual report shall give an account of the activities during the 
previous financial year containing inter alia  
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a statement of corporate and operational goals and objectives of the 
  Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> annual targets in physical and financial terms set for various 
  activities in the background of clause (a) together with a brief review of 
  actual performance with reference to those targets; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> An administrative report on the activities of the Authority during the 
  year just past and the current year and an account of the activities which are 
  likely to be taken up during the next financial year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> important changes in the organisational set up of the Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> report on employer-employees relations and welfare activities of the 
  Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> report on such other miscellaneous matters as deemed fit by the 
  Authority for reporting to the Central Government. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The annual report shall after adoption at a meeting of the Authority and 
be signed by the members and authenticated by affixing the common seal of the 
Authority and the requisite number of copies thereof shall be submitted to the 
Central Government by the 30th day of September. 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>