<act><tid>1691997</tid>
<title>THE BABASAHEB BHIMRAO AMBEDKAR UNIVERSITY ACT, <year>1994</year></title>

ACT NO. 58 OF <year>1994</year>
[ 30th September, <year>1994</year>.]

An Act to establish and incorporate a teaching and residential 
University in the State of Uttar Pradesh and to provide for matters 
connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1032015</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>726098</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Babasaheb Bhimrao Ambedkar University Act, <year>1994</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>560748</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1901960</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder, 
unless the context otherwise requires,--
<section><tid>1420425</tid>
<number>a</number>" Academic Council" means the Academic Council of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>330685</tid>
<number>b</number>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are 
designated as academic staff by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>1662535</tid>
<number>c</number>" Board of Management" means the Board of Management of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>361610</tid>
<number>d</number>" Board of Studies" means the Board of Studies of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>628862</tid>
<number>e</number>" Chancellor"," Vice- Chancellor" and" Pro- Vice- 
Chancellor" mean, respectively, the Chancellor, vice- Chancellor 
and Pro- vice- Chancellor of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1539109</tid>
<number>f</number>" College" means a College maintained by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1462711</tid>
<number>g</number>" Department" means a Department of Studies; and includes 
a Centre of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>503254</tid>
<number>h</number>" distance education system" means the system of 
imparting education through any means of communication, such as 
broadcasting, telecasting, correspondence courses, seminars, 
contract programmes or the combination of any two or more such 
means;

</section>

<section><tid>1908474</tid>
<number>i</number>" employee" means any person appointed by the University; 
and includes teachers and other staff of the University;
 1 10. 1. <year>1996</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 18 (E), dt. 5. 1. <year>1996</year>.


</section>

<section><tid>293631</tid>
<number>j</number>" Finance Committee" means the Finance Committee of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1323079</tid>
<number>k</number>" Hall" means a unit of residence or of corporate life 
for the students of the University, or of a College or of an 
Institution, maintained by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>880297</tid>
<number>l</number>" Institution" means an academic institution, not being a 
College, maintained by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>708194</tid>
<number>m</number>" Planning Board" means the Planning Board of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>881326</tid>
<number>n</number>" Principal" means the Head of a College or an 
Institution maintained by the University, and includes, where 
there is no Principal, the person for the time being duly 
appointed to act as Principal, and, in the absence of the 
Principal or the acting Principal, a Vice- Principal duly 
appointed as such;

</section>

<section><tid>941729</tid>
<number>o</number>" recognised institution" means an institution of higher 
learning recognised by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1781039</tid>
<number>p</number>" recognised teachers" means such persons as may be 
recognised by the University for the purpose of imparting 
instructions in a College or an Institution maintained by the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1439</tid>
<number>q</number>" Regulations" means the Regulations made by any 
authority of the University under this Act for the time being in 
force;

</section>

<section><tid>1280954</tid>
<number>r</number>" School" means a School of Studies of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>639628</tid>
<number>s</number>" Statutes" and" Ordinances" means, respectively, the 
Statutes and Ordinances of the University for the time being in 
force;

</section>

<section><tid>109708</tid>
<number>t</number>" teachers of the University" means Professors Readers, 
Lecturers and such other persons as may be appointed for 
imparting instruction or conducting research in the University or 
in any College or Institution maintained by the University and 
are designated as teachers by the Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>1459967</tid>
<number>u</number>" University" means the Babasaheb Bhimrao Ambedkar 
University established under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1381028</tid>
<number> 3</number> The University.
<section><tid>1158634</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established a University by  
the name of" Babasaheb Bhimrao Ambedkar University."

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>589202</tid>
<number>2</number>The headquarters of the University shall be at Lucknow and it 
may also establish campuses at such other places within its 
jurisdiction as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>227775</tid>
<number>3</number>The first Vice- Chancellor and the first members of the Board 
of Management or the Academic Council or the Planning Board and all 
persons who may hereafter become such officers or members, so long as 
they continue to hold such office or membership, are hereby 
constituted a body corporate by the name of Babasaheb Bhimrao Ambedkar 
University".

</section>

<section><tid>1091350</tid>
<number>4</number>The University shall have perpetual succession and a common 
seal and shall sue and be sued by the said name.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>459622</tid>
<number>4</number>Objects of the University. The objects of the University shall 
be to promote advanced knowledge by providing instructional and 
research facilities in such branches of learning as it may deem fit; 
to make provisions for integrated courses in Science and key and 
frontier areas of Technology and other allied disciplines in the 
educational programmes of the University; to offer appropriate courses 
relevant for the development of socially and economically depressed 
sections of the people, including agricultural technology and rural 
crafts; to promote the study of the principles for which Babasaheb 
Bhimrao Ambedkar worked during his life time, namely, national 
integration. social justice and democratic way of life, and also study 
of the Constitutions of the world to take appropriate measures for 
promoting innovations in teaching learning processes in inter- 
disciplinary studies and research and pay special attention to the 
promotion of educational and economic interests and welfare of the 
people in General and of members belonging to the Scheduled Castes and 
Scheduled Tribes in particular by providing adequate percentage of 
seats for the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes and the 
University shall, in organising its activities, have due regard to the 
objects specified in the First Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1082970</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of the University. The University shall have the 
following powers, namely:--
<section><tid>1000113</tid>
<number>i</number>to provide for instruction in such branches of learning 
as the University may, from time to time, determine and to make 
provision for research and for the advancement and dissemination 
of knowledge;

</section>

<section><tid>1829409</tid>
<number>ii</number>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University 
may determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or 
other academic distinctions on the basis of examinations, 
evaluation or any other method of testing on, persons, and to 
withdraw any such diplomas, certificates, degrees or other 
academic distinctions for good and sufficient cause;

</section>

<section><tid>698918</tid>
<number>iii</number>to organise and to undertake extra- mural studies, 
training and extension services;

</section>

<section><tid>710219</tid>
<number>iv</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the 
manner prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>1298862</tid>
<number>v</number>to provide facilities through the distance education 
system to such persons as it may determine;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>372355</tid>
<number>vi</number>to institute Principalships, Professorships, 
Readerships, Lecturerships and other teaching or academic 
positions, required by the University and to appoint persons to 
such Principalships, Professorships, Readerships, Lecturerships 
or other teaching on academic positions;

</section>

<section><tid>1835723</tid>
<number>vii</number>to recognise an institution of higher learning for 
such purposes as the University may determine and to withdraw 
such recognition;

</section>

<section><tid>227736</tid>
<number>viii</number>to recognise persons for imparting instructions in 
any College or Institution maintained by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1060019</tid>
<number>ix</number>to appoint persons working in any other University or 
organisation as teacher of the University for a specified period;

</section>

<section><tid>368359</tid>
<number>x</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts 
and to make appointments thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1881649</tid>
<number>xi</number>to co- operate or collaborate or associate with any 
other University or authority or institution of higher learning 
in such manner and for such purposes as the University may 
determine;

<subsection><tid>1676911</tid>
<number>xii</number>to establish such campuses, special centres, 
specialised laboratories or other units for research and 
instruction as are, in the opinion of the University, necessary 
for the furtherance of its objects;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>655901</tid>
<number>xiii</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1703492</tid>
<number>xiv</number>to establish and maintain Colleges, Institutions and 
Halls;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>105905</tid>
<number>xv</number>to make provision for research and advisory services 
and for that purpose to enter into such arrangements with other 
institutions, industrial or other organisations, as the 
University may deem necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>662591</tid>
<number>xvi</number>to organise and conduct refresher courses, orientation 
courses, workshops, seminars and other programmes for teachers, 
evaluators and other academic staff;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550617</tid>
<number>xvii</number>to make special arrangements in respect of the 
residence discipline and teaching of women students as the 
University may consider desirable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>309990</tid>
<number>xviii</number>to appoint on contract or otherwise visiting 
Professors Emeritus Professors, Consultants, Scholars and such 
other persons who may contribute to the advancement of the 
objects of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1162448</tid>
<number>xix</number>to confer autonomous status on a College or an 
Institution or a Department, as the case may be, in accordance 
with the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>760920</tid>
<number>xx</number>to determine standards of admission to the University 
which may include examination, evaluation or any other method of 
testing;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1586914</tid>
<number>xxi</number>to fix quota for students belonging to the Scheduled 
Castes and the Scheduled Tribes for admission purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>612414</tid>
<number>xxii</number>to demand and receive payment of fees and other 
charges;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>662802</tid>
<number>xxiii</number>to supervise the residences of the students of the 
University and to make arrangements for promoting their health 
and general welfare;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>310835</tid>
<number>xxiv</number>to lay down conditions of service of all categories 
of employees, including their code of conduct;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1298115</tid>
<number>xxv</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among the students 
and the employees, and to take such disciplinary measures in this 
regard as may be deemed by the University to be necessary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1090772</tid>
<number>xxvi</number>to make arrangements for promoting the health and 
general welfare of the employees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>31650</tid>
<number>xxvii</number>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts and to 
acquire, hold, mange and dispose of any property, movable or 
immovable including trust and endowment properties for the 
purposes of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>147932</tid>
<number>xxviii</number>to borrow, with the prior approval of the Central 
Government, on the security of the property of the University, 
money for the purposes of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>548206</tid>
<number>xxix</number>to do all such other acts and things as may be 
necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of all or 
any of its objects.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>984571</tid>
<number>6</number>Jurisdiction. The jurisdiction of the University shall extend 
to the whole of the State of Uttar Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>773008</tid>
<number>7</number>University open to all classes, castes and creed. The 
University shall be open to all persons of either sex and of whatever 
caste, creed, race, class, place of domicile and it shall not be 
lawful for the University to adopt or impose on any person, any test 
whatsoever of religious belief or profession in order to entitle him 
to be appointed as a teacher of the University or to hold any other 
office therein or be admitted as a student in the University or to 
graduate thereat or to enjoy or exercise any privilege thereof:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
the University from making special provisions for the employment or 
promotion of educational interests of women, physically handicapped or 
of persons belonging to the weaker sections of the society and, in 
particular, of the Scheduled Castes and the Scheduled Tribes.



</article>



<article><tid>256050</tid>
<number>8</number>Residence of students. Every student of the University (other  
than a student who pursues a course of study by distance education 
  system) shall normally reside in a Hall or hostel or under such 
conditions as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>1588624</tid>
<number> 9</number> The Visitor.
<section><tid>1373185</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India shall be the Visitor  
of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>81530</tid>
<number>2</number>The Visitor may, from time to time, appoint one or more 
persons to review the work and progress of the University, including 
Colleges and Institutions managed by it, and to submit a report 
thereon; and upon receipt of that report, the Visitor may, after 
obtaining the views of the Board of Management thereon through the 
Vice- Chancellor, take such action and issue such directions as he 
considers necessary in respect of any of the matters dealt with in the 
report and the University shall be bound to comply with such 
directions.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1932510</tid>
<number>3</number>The Visitor shall have the right to cause an inspection to be 
made by such person or persons as he may direct of the University, its 
buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any College or 
Institution maintained by the University and also of the examinations, 
teaching and other work conducted or done by the University and to 
cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in respect of any matter 
connected with the administration or finances of the University, 
Colleges or Institutions.

</section>

<section><tid>1806509</tid>
<number>4</number>The Visitor shall, in every matter referred to in sub- section 
 (2), give notice of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to 
be made to the University and the University shall have the right to 
make such representations to the Visitor, as it may consider 
necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>302873</tid>
<number>5</number>After considering the representations, if any, made by the 
University, the Visitor may cause to be made such inspection or 
inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>340713</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by 
the Visitor, the University shall be entitled to appoint a 
representative, who shall have the right to be present and be heard at 
such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>106653</tid>
<number>7</number>The Visitor may, if the inspection or inquiry is made in 
respect of the University or any College or Institution maintained by 
it, address the Vice- Chancellor with reference to the result of such 
inspection or inquiry together with such views and advice with regard 
to the action to be taken thereon, as the Visitor may be pleased to 
offer, and on receipt of address made by the Visitor, the Vice- 
Chancellor shall communicate to the Board of Management the views of 
the Visitor with such advice as the Visitor may offer upon the action 
to be taken thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>233943</tid>
<number>8</number>The Board of Management shall communicate, through the Vice- 
Chancellor, to the Visitor such action, if any, as it proposes to take 
or has been taken upon the result of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>1306812</tid>
<number>9</number>Where, the Board of Management does not, within a reasonable 
time, take action to the satisfaction of the Visitor, the Visitor may, 
after considering any explanation furnished or representation made by 
the Board of Management, issue such directions as he may think fit and 
the Board of Management shall comply with such directions.

</section>

<section><tid>52252</tid>
<number>10</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this 
section, the Visitor may, by order in writing, annul any proceeding of 
the University which is not in conformity with the Act, the Statutes 
or the Ordinances:
Provided that before making any such order, he shall call upon 
the Registrar to show cause why such an order should not be made, and, 
if any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the 
same.


</section>

<section><tid>11180</tid>
<number>11</number>The Visitor shall have such other powers as may be 
prescribed by the Statues.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1270044</tid>
<number> 10</number> Officers of the University. The following shall be the 
officers of the University:--
<section><tid>371718</tid>
<number>1</number>the Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>1245320</tid>
<number>2</number>the Vice- Chancellor;

</section>

<section><tid>1497666</tid>
<number>3</number>the Pro- Chancellors;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1726618</tid>
<number>4</number>the Deans of Schools;

</section>

<section><tid>194295</tid>
<number>5</number>the Registrar;

</section>

<section><tid>1250638</tid>
<number>6</number>the Finance Officer; and

</section>

<section><tid>216669</tid>
<number>7</number>such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes 
to be officers of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1016214</tid>
<number> 11</number> The Chancellor.
<section><tid>1196425</tid>
<number>1</number>The Chancellor shall be appointed by the  
Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>647216</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chancellor shall, by virtue of his office, be the head of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>24267</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chancellor shall, if present, preside at the convocation 
of the University held for conferring degrees, and may be delegated 
such powers as may be necessary.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>182514</tid>
<number> 12</number> The Vice- Chancellor.
<section><tid>1998093</tid>
<number>1</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be  
appointed by the Visitor in such manner as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1353892</tid>
<number>2</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall be the principal executive and 
academic officer of the University and shall exercise general 
supervision and control over the affairs of the University and give 
effect to the decisions of all the authorities of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1109805</tid>
<number>3</number>The Vice- Chancellor may, if he is of opinion that immediate 
action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power conferred on any 
authority of the University by or under this Act and shall report to 
such authority the action taken by him on such matter:
Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such 
action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the 
Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that any person in the service of the University 
who is aggrieved by the action taken by the Vice- Chancellor under this 
sub- section shall have the right to appeal against such action to the 
Board of Management within three months from the date on which 
decision on such action is communicated to him and thereupon the Board 
of Management may confirm, modify or reverse the action taken by the 
Vice- Chancellor.


</section>

<section><tid>1650712</tid>
<number>4</number>The Vice- Chancellor, if he is of the opinion that any 
decision of any authority of the University is beyond the powers of 
the authority conferred by the provisions of this Act, the Statutes or 
the Ordinances or that any decision taken is not in the interest of 
the University, may ask the authority concerned to review its decision 
within sixty days of such decision and if the authority refuses to 
review the decision either in whole or in part or no decision is taken 
by it within the said period of sixty days, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>146346</tid>
<number>5</number>The Vice- Chancellor shall exercise such other powers and 
perform such other duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes or the 
Ordinances.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1142853</tid>
<number>13</number>The Pro- Vice- Chancellor. One or more Pro- Vice- Chancellors 
shall be appointed in such manner and shall exercise such powers and 
perform such duties as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>86362</tid>
<number>14</number>Deans of Schools. Every Dean of a School shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>1165627</tid>
<number> 15</number> The Registrar.
<section><tid>835618</tid>
<number>1</number>The Registrar shall be appointed in such  
manner as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1465971</tid>
<number>2</number>The Registrar shall have the power to enter into agreement, 
sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of the University 
and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1597484</tid>
<number>16</number>The Finance Officer. The Finance Officer shall be appointed 
in such manner and shall exercise such powers and perform such duties 
as may be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>145685</tid>
<number>17</number>Other officers. The manner of appointment and powers and 
duties of the other officers of the University shall be prescribed by 
the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>576226</tid>
<number> 18</number> Authorities of the University. The following shall be the 
authorities of the University, namely:--
<section><tid>1392934</tid>
<number>1</number>the Board of Management;

</section>

<section><tid>1944694</tid>
<number>2</number>the Academic Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1626449</tid>
<number>3</number>the Planning Board;

</section>

<section><tid>654945</tid>
<number>4</number>the Boards of Studies;

</section>

<section><tid>396434</tid>
<number>5</number>the Finance Committee; and

</section>

<section><tid>320072</tid>
<number>6</number>such other authorities as may be declared by the 
Statutes to be the authorities of the University.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>821381</tid>
<number> 19</number> The Board of Management.
<section><tid>1774696</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board of Management shall be  
the principal executive body of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1780039</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Board of Management, the term of 
office of its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed 
by the Statutes:
Provided that the Board of Management shall also have 
representatives of the House of the People and the Council of States, 
the Government of India, the University Grants Commission and the 
teaching community.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1632647</tid>
<number> 20</number> The Academic Council.
<section><tid>807382</tid>
<number>1</number>The Academic Council shall be the  
principal academic body of the University and shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances, co- ordinate 
and exercise general supervision over the academic policies of the 
University.

</section>

<section><tid>1158674</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Academic Council, the term of office 
of its members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that representation shall be given to students also.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1746407</tid>
<number> 21</number> The planning Board.
<section><tid>776344</tid>
<number>1</number>The Planning Board shall be the  
principal planning Body of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1340066</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Planning Board, term of office of its 
members and its powers and functions shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes:
Provided that representation shall be given to non- teaching 
staff.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1284444</tid>
<number>22</number>The Board of Schools. The constitution, powers and functions 
of the Boards of Schools shall be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>94000</tid>
<number>23</number>The Finance Committee. The constitution, powers and functions 
of the Finance Committee shall be prescribed by the Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>162203</tid>
<number>24</number>Other authorities of the University. The constitution, powers 
and functions of other authorities, as may be declared by the Statutes 
to be the authorities of the University, shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.


</article>



<article><tid>932787</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power to make Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this 
Act, the Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:--
<section><tid>1637198</tid>
<number>a</number>the constitution, powers and functions of the 
authorities and other bodies of the University, as may be 
constituted from time to time;

</section>

<section><tid>979430</tid>
<number>b</number>the election and continuance in office of the members of 
the said authorities and bodies, the filling up of vacancies of 
members, and all other matters relating to those authorities and 
other bodies for which it may be necessary or desirable to 
provide;

</section>

<section><tid>542113</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment, powers and duties of the officers of 
the University and their emoluments;

</section>

<section><tid>1191218</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of teachers, academic staff and other 
employees of the University, their emoluments and other 
conditions of service;

</section>

<section><tid>572215</tid>
<number>e</number>the appointment of teachers, academic staff working in 
any other University or organisation for a specific period for 
undertaking a joint project;

</section>

<section><tid>1464207</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of service of employees including 
provision for pension, insurance and provident fund, the manner 
of termination of service and disciplinary action;

</section>

<section><tid>1527263</tid>
<number>g</number>the principles governing the seniority of service of the 
employees or students and the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1507131</tid>
<number>h</number>the procedure for arbitration in cases of dispute 
between employees or students and the University;

</section>

<section><tid>135538</tid>
<number>i</number>the procedure for appeal to the Board of Management by 
any employee or student against the action of any officer or 
authority of the University;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1057731</tid>
<number>j</number>the conferment of autonomous status on a College or an 
Institution or a Department;

</section>

<section><tid>1045793</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment and abolition of Schools, Departments, 
Centres, Halls, Colleges and Institutions;

</section>

<section><tid>1562067</tid>
<number>l</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>885601</tid>
<number>m</number>the withdrawal of degrees, diplomas, certificates and 
other academic distinctions;

</section>

<section><tid>1544172</tid>
<number>n</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1775130</tid>
<number>o</number>the delegation of powers vested in the authorities or 
officers of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1375112</tid>
<number>p</number>the maintenance of the discipline among the employees 
and students;

</section>

<section><tid>977195</tid>
<number>q</number>all other matters which by this Act are to be or may be 
provided for by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1047641</tid>
<number> 26</number> Statutes how to be made.
<section><tid>729120</tid>
<number>1</number>The first Statutes are those set  
out in the Second Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>453867</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board of Management may, from time to time, make new or 
additional Statutes or may amend or repeal the Statutes referred to in 
sub- section (1):
Provided that the Board of Management shall not make, amend or 
repeal any Statutes affecting the status, powers or constitution of 
any authority of the University until such authority has been given an 
opportunity of expressing an opinion in writing on the proposed 
changes, and any opinion so expressed shall be considered by the Board 
of Management.


</section>

<section><tid>51287</tid>
<number>3</number>Every new Statutes or addition to the Statutes or any 
amendment or repeal of a Statute shall require the assent of the 
Visitor who may assent thereto or withhold assent or remit to the 
Board of Management for reconsideration.

</section>

<section><tid>1731500</tid>
<number>4</number>A new Statute or a Statute amending or repealing an existing 
Statute shall have no validity unless it has been assented to by the 
Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>267815</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- 
sections, the Visitor, in exceptional circumstances, may direct the 
University to make provisions in the Statutes in respect of any matter 
specified by him and if the Board of Management is unable to implement 
such direction within sixty days of its receipt, the Visitor may, 
after considering the reasons, if any communicated by the Board of 
Management for its in ability to comply with such direction, make or 
amend the Statutes suitably.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>356406</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power to make Ordinances.
<section><tid>205291</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may provide for all or any 
of the following matters namely:-

<subsection><tid>1086913</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their 
enrolment as such;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>493863</tid>
<number>b</number>the courses of study to be laid down for all degrees, 
diplomas and certificates of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985245</tid>
<number>c</number>the medium of instruction and examination;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>563382</tid>
<number>d</number>the award of degrees, diplomas, certificates and other 
academic distinctions, the qualifications for the same and the 
means to be taken relating to the granting and obtaining of the 
same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>47348</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
University and for admission to the examinations, degrees and 
diplomas of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>106252</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions for award of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>767996</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of examinations, including the term of 
office and manner of appointment and the duties of examining 
bodies, examiners and moderators;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1838863</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of the students of the 
University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1551963</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for 
the residence, discipline and teaching of women students and the 
prescribing of special courses of studies for them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1454210</tid>
<number>j</number>the appointments and emoluments of employees other than 
those for whom provision has been made in the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1153359</tid>
<number>k</number>the establishment of Centres of Studies. Boards of 
Studies, Special Centres, Specialised Laboratories and other 
Committees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1571637</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of co- operation and collaboration with other 
Universities and authorities including learned bodies or 
associations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>995456</tid>
<number>m</number>the creation, composition and functions of any other 
body which is considered necessary for improving the academic 
life of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>689220</tid>
<number>n</number>such other terms and conditions of service of teachers 
and other academic staff as are not prescribed by the Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1951743</tid>
<number>o</number>the management of Colleges and Institutions established 
by the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1200929</tid>
<number>p</number>the setting up of a machinery for redressal of 
grievances of employees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>225391</tid>
<number>q</number>all other matters which by this Act or the Statutes may 
be provided for by the Ordinances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>581960</tid>
<number>2</number>The first Ordinances shall be made by the Vice- Chancellor 
with the previous approval of the Central Government and the 
Ordinances so made may be amended, repealed or added to at any time by 
the Board of Management in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975921</tid>
<number>28</number>Regulations. The authorities of the University may make 
Regulations, consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances 
for the conduct of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

their own business and that of the Committees, if any, appointed by 
them and not provided for by this Act, the Statutes or the Ordinances, 
in the manner prescribed by the Statutes.



</article>



<article><tid>1539725</tid>
<number> 29</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>832151</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University shall  
be prepared under the direction of the Board of Management, which 
shall include, among other matters, the steps taken by the University 
towards the fulfilment of its objects.

</section>

<section><tid>912504</tid>
<number>2</number>The annual report so prepared shall be submitted to the 
Visitor on or before such date as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1107097</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the annual report as prepared under sub- section 
 (1), shall also be submitted to the Central Government, which shall, 
as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both Houses of 
Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1919545</tid>
<number> 30</number> Annual accounts.
<section><tid>1197546</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of  
the University shall be prepared under the directions of the Board of 
Management and shall, once at least every year and at intervals of not 
more than fifteen months, be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor- 
General of India or by such persons as he may authorise in this 
behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>120903</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report 
thereon shall be submitted to the Vistor.

</section>

<section><tid>124244</tid>
<number>3</number>Any observations made by the Visitor on the annual accounts 
shall be brought to the notice of the Board of Management and the 
observations of the Board of Management, if any, shall be submitted to 
the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1411776</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the annual accounts together with the audit report 
as submitted to the Visitor, shall also be submitted to the Central 
Government, which shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to be laid 
before both Houses of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>1970398</tid>
<number>5</number>The audited annual accounts after having been laid before 
both Houses of Parliament shall be published in the Gazette of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1856295</tid>
<number> 31</number> Conditions of service of employees.
<section><tid>1643052</tid>
<number>1</number>Every employee of the  
University shall be appointed under a written contract, which shall be 
lodged with the University and a copy of which shall be furnished to 
the employee concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1690002</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of the contract between the 
University and any employee shall, at the request of the employee, be 
referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration consisting of one member 
appointed by the Board of Management, one member nominated by the 
employee concerned and an umpire appointed by the Visitor.

</section>

<section><tid>1212076</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Tribunal in such matters shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1013654</tid>
<number>4</number>Every request made by the employee under sub- section (2), 
shall be deemed to be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of 
this section within the meaning of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (2 of  
  <year>1940</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>553261</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure for regulating the work of the Tribunal shall 
be prescribed by the Statutes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1272141</tid>
<number> 32</number> Procedure of appeal and arbitration in disciplinary cases 
against students.
<section><tid>1376012</tid>
<number>1</number>Any student or candidate for an examination  
whose name has been removed from the rolls of the University by the 
orders or resolution of the Vice- Chancellor, Discipline Committee or 
Examination Committee, as the case may be, and who has been debarred 
from appearing at the examinations of the University for more than one 
year, may, within ten days of the date of receipt of such orders or 
copy of such resolution by him, appeal to the Board of Management and 
the Board of Management may confirm modify or reverse the decision of 
the Vice- Chancellor or the Committee, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1323697</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute arising out of any disciplinary action taken by 
the University against a student shall, at the request of such 
student, be referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration and the provisions 
of sub- sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) of section 31 shall, as far as 
may be, apply to a reference made under this sub- section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>732207</tid>
<number>33</number>Right to appeal. Every employee or student of the University 
or of a College or Institution maintained by the University shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, have a right to appeal 
within such time as may be prescribed by the Statutes, to the Board of 
Management against the decision of any officer or authority of the 
University or of the Principal of any College or Institution, as the 
case may be, and thereupon the Board of Management may confirm, modify 
or reverse the decision appealed against.


</article>



<article><tid>1492219</tid>
<number> 34</number> Provident and pension funds.
<section><tid>1903161</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall  
constitute for the benefit of its employees such provident or pension 
fund or provide such insurance schemes as it may deem fit in such 
manner and subject to such conditions as may be presoribed by the 
Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1691187</tid>
<number>2</number>Where such provident fund or pension fund has been so 
constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provision of 
the Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of <year>1925</year>), shall apply to such fund, 
as if it were a Government provident fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>662401</tid>
<number>35</number>Disputes as to constitution of University authorities and 
bodies. If any question arises as to whether any person has been duly 
elected or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any 
authority or other body of the University, the matter shall be 
referred to the Visitor whose decision thereon shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1358295</tid>
<number>36</number>Constitution of Committees. Where any authority of the 
University is given power by this Act or the Statutes to appoint 
Committees, such Committees shall, save as otherwise provided, consist 
of the members of the authority concerned and of such other person, if 
any, as the authority in each case may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>810744</tid>
<number>37</number>Filling of casual vacancies. All casual vacancies among the 
members (other than ex officio members) of any authority or other body 
of the University shall be filled, as soon as may be, by the person or 
body who appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose place has 
become vacant and the person appointed, elected or co- opted to a 
casual vacancy shall be a member of such authority or body for the 
residue of the term for which the person whose place he fills would 
have been a member.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>365310</tid>
<number>38</number>Proceedings of University authorities or bodies not 
invalidated by vacancies. No act or proceedings of any authority or 
other body of the University shall be invalid merely by reason of the 
existence of a vacancy or vacancies among its members.


</article>



<article><tid>181933</tid>
<number>39</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceedings shall lie against any officer or other employee of 
the University for anything which is in good faith done or intended to 
be done in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, the 
Statutes or the Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>471765</tid>
<number>40</number>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt, 
application, notice order proceeding resolution of any authority or 
Committee of the University, or other documents in possession of the 
University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the 
University, if certified by the Registrar, shall be received as prima 
facie evidence of such receipt, application, notice, order, 
proceeding, resolution or documents or the existence of entry in the 
register and shall be admitted as evidence of the matters and 
transactions therein where the original thereof would, if produced, 
have been admissible in evidence, notwithstanding anything contained 
in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>) or in any other law for 
the time being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>261979</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>1098396</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such provisions, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to 
be necessary of expedient for removing the difficulty.
Provided that no such order shall be made under this section 
after the expiry of three years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>134649</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>683316</tid>
<number> 42</number> Transitional provisions. Notwithstanding anything contained 
in this Act and the Statutes--
<section><tid>359853</tid>
<number>a</number>the first Vice- Chancellor shall be appointed by the 
Visitor and the said officer shall hold office for a term of five 
years;

</section>

<section><tid>1612394</tid>
<number>b</number>the first Registrar and the first Finance Officer shall 
be appointed by the Visitor and each of the said officers shall 
hold office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>754387</tid>
<number>c</number>the first Board of Management shall consist of not more 
than eleven members who shall be nominated by the Visitor and 
they shall hold office for a term of three years;

</section>

<section><tid>981408</tid>
<number>d</number>the first Academic Council and the first Planning Board 
shall be nominated by the Visitor for a term of three years:
Provided that if any vacancy occurs in the above offices or 
authorities, the same shall be filled by appointment or nomination, as 
the case may be,


<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

by the Visitor, and the persons so appointed or nominated shall hold 
office for so long as the officer or member in whose place he is 
appointed or nominated would have held that office, if such vacancy 
had not occurred.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1353188</tid>
<number> 43</number> Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations to be published in the 
Official Gazette and to be laid before Parliament.
<section><tid>1705008</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Statute,  
Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act shall be published in the 
Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>896140</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Statute, Ordinance or Regulation made under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the 
Statute, Ordinance or Regulation or both Houses agree that the 
Statute, Ordinance or Regulation should not be made, the Statute, 
Ordinance or Regulation shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that Statute, Ordinance 
or Regulation.

</section>

<section><tid>563673</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to make Statutes, Ordinances or Regulations shall 
include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier 
than the date of commencement of this Act, to the Statutes, Ordinances 
or Regulations or any of them but no retrospective effect shall be 
given to any Statute, Ordinance or Regulation so as to prejudicially 
affect the interests of any person to whom such Statute, Ordinance or 
Regulation may be applicable.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>