<act><tid>1691761</tid>
<title>THE RAILWAYS (EMPLOYMENT OF MEMBERS OF THEARMED FORCES) ACT, <year>1965</year></title>

ACT NO. 40 OF <year>1965</year>
[ 3rd December, <year>1965</year>.]

An Act to make certain provisions relating to the employment of 
members of the Armed Forces of the Union in the working and management 
of railways.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Sixteenth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1934823</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>543446</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Railways (Employment of Members of the Armed Forces) Act, <year>1965</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>498132</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1425160</tid>
<number>2</number>Interpretation. Words and expressions used in this Act and 
defined in the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>), shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>219462</tid>
<number> 3</number> Employment of members of Armed Forces of the Union to 
assist a railway administration in connection with the service of a 
railway.
<section><tid>1642704</tid>
<number>1</number>When any member of the Armed Forces of the Union is  
employed to assist a railway administration in connection with the 
service of a railway, then, whether such employment was before or is 
after the commencement of this Act,-

<subsection><tid>366073</tid>
<number>a</number>any provision of the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of  
  <year>1890</year>), or of the rules made thereunder, which confers a 
power, status or immunity, or imposes a duty or liability, 
upon a railway servant, in connection with the working, use, 
management and maintenance of railways, shall be construed 
as conferring the same power, status or immunity or imposing 
the same duty or liability, as the case may be, upon such 
member of the Armed Forces of the Union when so employed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>23560</tid>
<number>b</number>the employment of a member of the Armed Forces of the 
Union, in addition to or in the place of any railway servant, 
shall not affect any liability that would have attached to 
the railway administration had such member been a railway 
servant.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>281238</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be construed as making 
applicable to the members of the Armed Forces of the Union 
employed to assist a railway administration the provisions of Chapter 
VIA of the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>), or as derogating 
from any provision





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1680929</tid>
<number>4</number>Employment of members of Armed Forces of the Union to 
replace railway administration in working a railway. If at any time the 
whole of the working, management and maintenance of a railway or of a 
specific, portion or section of a railway, is assumed by the Armed 
Forces of the Union, the Central Government may notify the fact of 
such assumption in the Official Gazette and thereupon, so long as 
such assumption continues, the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of  
  <year>1890</year>), shall cease to be applicable to the Railway or the portion or 
section of the Railway concerned.


</article>



<article><tid>1286015</tid>
<number> 5</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>590715</tid>
<number>1</number>The Railways (Employment of Members of   
  the Armed Forces) Ordinance, <year>1965</year> (4 of <year>1965</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1846210</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under this Act as if this Act had commenced on the 29th day of 
September, <year>1965</year>.


</section>

</article>



 </act>