<act><title>

The Societies 
    Registration Act, 1860</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Societies formed by memorandum of association and registration.—Any 
    seven or more persons associated for any literary, scientific, or charitable 
    purpose, or for any such purpose as is described in section 20 of this Act, 
    may, by subscribing their names to a memorandum of association, and filing 
    the same with the Registrar of Joint-stock Companies 

    1[***] form themselves 
    into a society under this Act.
 

State Amendments
 
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 1,—
 <section>
<number>i</number>  for the words “the 
      Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies” substitute “the Inspector-General of 
      Registration (hereinafter referred to as the Inspector-General)”;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>  add the following 
      Explanation namely:—
 
          “Explanation.—‘Inspector-General 
      of Registration’ means the Inspector-General of Registration appointed by 
      the State Government under section 3 of the Indian Registration Act, 1908 
      (XVI of 1908) and includes any officer subordinate to the 
      Inspector-General, not below the rank of District Registrar, or 
      sub-registrar holding the charge of the officer of the District Registrar 
      to whom the State Government may delegate the functions of the 
      Inspector-General under this Act.”
 
[Vide President’s Act 
      10 of 1954, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1954), as re-enacted by A.P. Act 6 of 
      1956, sec. 4 and Sch. III (w.r.e.f. 1-10-1954).]
 
Assam: Manipur: Tripura.—(i) 
      In its application to the State of Assam in section I, for the words 
      “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute “Registrar of Societies 
      appointed by the State Government.”
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Said Act has been 
      extended to Manipur and Tripura with necessary modifications in the title 
      and section 2.
 
[Vide Assam Act 7 of 
      1957, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 17-7-1957); G.S.Rs. 85 and 86, published in the 
      Gazette of India, 1960, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i).]
 <subsection>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 1, 
      for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the words 
      “Inspector-General of Registration”.
 
[Vide Bihar Act 19 of 
      1956, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 21-12-1955).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as for 
      that of Maharashtra.
 
Himachal Pradesh.—Same 
      as that of Punjab.
 
[Vide H.P. Act 23 of 
      1973, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 4-12-1973).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In its 
      application to the whole of the State of Bombay, in section 1, omit the 
      words “of Joint-Stock Companies”.
 
[Vide Bombay Acts 11 of 
      1956, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956) and 76 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 7-10-1958).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—(a) After the 
      Preamble and before the existing section 1, insert the following new 
      section, namely:—
 
“1. Application of 
      Registrar of Societies.—†[(1)] The State Government may, by 
      notification, appoint a person to be called the Registrar of Societies and 
      he shall exercise such powers and perform such duties and functions as are 
      conferred by or under the provisions of this Act, and shall subject to 
      such general or special order as the State Government may from time to 
      time make, superintend the administration and carry out the provisions of 
      this Act throughout the State of Orissa.”
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 
      1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-1-1961).]
 
[† Existing section 1 
      renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof and after the section so renumbered 
      sub-sections (2) and (3) inserted by the Orissa Act 9 of 1979,  
      sec. 2 (w.e.f. 3-4-1979).]
 
“(2) The State Government may 
      by notification, appoint one or more Additional Registrars with such local 
      jurisdiction as may be assigned to them by the State Government.
 <subsubsection>
<number>3</number> The Additional Registrars 
      so appointed shall, subject to the control of the Registrar of Societies, 
      exercise such of the powers and perform such of the function of the 
      Registrar of Societies as the State Government may authorise in that 
      behalf.”
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number> Original section 1 
      renumbered as section 1A and in this section as so renumbered for the 
      words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies” substitute the words “Registrar 
      of Societies”.
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 
      1958, secs. 2 and 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1961).]
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—In section 
      1, for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the 
      words, “Registrar of Companies”.
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 9 
      of 1969, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1971).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh: 
      Delhi.—(i) In its application to the State of Punjab as it existed 
      immediately before the 1st November, 1956, in section 1, for the words “of 
      Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the words “to be appointed by the State 
      Government by notification in the Official Gazette, for carrying out the 
      purposes of this Act.”
 
[Vide Punjab Act 31 of 
      1957, sec. 2: Central Act 31 of 1966, sec. 89.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number> The Punjab Act has been 
      applied to the Union territories of Delhi and Himachal Pradesh (now a 
      State) by G.S.Rs. 83 and 84, dated 16th January, 1960, with the 
      modifications to suit their status.
 
[Vide Gazette of India, 
      1960, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i), pp. 144, 145.]
 
Tamil Nadu.—In section 
      1,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  for the words “the 
      Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the words and brackets 
      “the Inspector-General of Registration (hereinafter in this Act referred 
      to as the Inspector-General)”;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  add the following 
      Explanation, namely.—
 
“Explanation.—‘Inspector-General 
      of Registration’ means the Inspector-General of Registration appointed by 
      the State Government under section 3 of the Indian Registration Act, 1908 
      (Central Act XVI of 1908), or any of the district authorities subordinate 
      to the Inspector-General of Registration not below the rank of the 
      District Registrar to whom powers may be delegated in respect of this 
      Act.”
 
[Vide T.N. Act 24 of 
      1954, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-9-1954).]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 1, for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute 
      the word “Registrar”.
 
[Vide U.P. Act 25 of 
      1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 25-8-1958).]
 
Section 
      1A
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—Renumber 
      the existing section 1 as section 1A and:
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>i</number>  before section 1A as so 
      renumbered, insert the following section, namely:—
 
“I. Definitions.—In 
      this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “Inspector-General” 
      means the Inspector-General of Registration appointed under section 3 of 
      the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (Central Act 16 of 1908) and includes 
      any of the District Authorities subordinate to the Inspector-General of 
      Registration not below the rank of a District Registrar to whom powers may 
      be delegated in respect of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “notification” means 
      notification published in the Official Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   “prescribed” means 
      prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   “Registration of 
      Societies Order” means the Registration of Societies Order, issued by the 
      Lieutenant Governor of Goa Daman and Diu under clause 2 of the Goa, Daman 
      and Diu (Administration Removal of Difficulties) Order, 1962.”
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number>  in section 1A as so 
      renumbered, for the words “the Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, 
      substitute the words “the Inspector-General”.
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 <subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—In section 
      1 for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies” substitute the words, 
      “Registrar of Companies”.
 
[Vide Pondichery Act 9 
      of 1969, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1971).]
 
Section 
      1A and IB
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—The amendments 
      made are the same as those of Maharashtra except that in sub-section (1) 
      of section 1B, for the words “throughout the State of Maharashtra”, 
      substitute the words “throughout the State of Gujarat”.
 
[Vide Gujarat A.L.O. 
      1961 (w.r.e.f. 1-5-1960).]
 
Section 
      1A
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—After 
      section 1, insert the following section, namely:—
 
“1A. Interpretation.—In 
      this Act, unless there is anything repugnant to the subject or context, 
      the expression ‘Registrar’ means the Registrar of Societies appointed 
      under section 1B and includes other officers appointed under the said 
      section to exercise the powers and to perform the duties and functions of 
      the Registrar of Societies.
 </subsection></section>
 
 
 
 



 



</article><article>
<number>1B</number> Registrar of Societies 
      and Assistant Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, appoint a person, to be called the Registrar of 
      Societies who shall exercise such power and shall perform such duties and 
      functions as are conferred by or under the provision of this Act and 
      shall, subject to such general or special orders as the State Government 
      may make, superintend the administration and carry out the provisions of 
      this Act throughout the State of Maharashtra.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government may 
      also by like notification appoint persons to be called ‘Assistant 
      Registrars of Societies’ for such areas as may be specified in the 
      notification and empower them to exercise powers and to perform duties and 
      function under all or such provisions of this Act as may be specified in 
      the notification.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 11 of 
      1956, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956) read with Bombay Act 76 of 1958, sec. 2. (w.e.f. 
      7-10-1958): Act 11 of 1960.]
 <subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—Renumber the 
      existing section 1 as section 1A, and in the section so renumbered for the 
      words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies” substitute the words “Registrar 
      of Societies”.
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 
      1958, secs. 2 and 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1961).]
  
 
COMMENTS
 
The Societies 
      established for charitable purpose which also includes the religious 
      purpose can be registered under Act; Hindu Public v. Rajdhani 
      Puja Samithee, AIR 1999 SC 964. 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Memorandum of association.—The 
    memorandum of association shall contain the following things, that is to 
    say,— 
 
the name of the society;  
 
the objects of the society;  
 
the names, addresses, and occupations of 
    the governors, council, directors, committee, or other governing body to 
    whom, by the rules of the society, the management of its affairs is 
    entrusted. 
 
 
A copy 
    of the rules and regulations of the society, certified to be a correct copy 
    by not less than three of the members of the governing body, shall be filed 
    with the memorandum of association.  
 
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—(i) Renumber 
      section 2 as sub-section (1) thereof and in sub-section (1) as so 
      renumbered after and below the words “the name of the society”, insert the 
      following, namely:—
 
“the place of situation of the 
      registered office of the society;
 
the addresses and occupations 
      of the persons who have subscribed their names to the memorandum of 
      association under section 1;”
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> after sub-section (1) as 
      so renumbered, insert the following sub-sections, namely:—
 
“(2) A society may, by a 
      special resolution passed by a majority of not less than three fifths of 
      the total membership of the society, after its memorandum of association.
 <subsubsection>
<number>3</number> The alteration of the 
      memorandum of association shall not take effect until, and except in so 
      far as, it is sanctioned by the Registrar who shall, before granting such 
      sanction, satisfy himself that the alteration is not such as would have 
      the effect of making the society ineligible for registration under this 
      Act.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
  
 
COMMENTS
 
Under the Act, a 
      committee of management can be framed to manage the affairs of society and 
      the committee is to manage the affairs of the society for a period as 
      specified in its Rules, Bye-laws or Regulations as the case may be. 
      Therefore, if a society runs not only a college but an institution like 
      hospital also the committee of management, constituted under the Act will 
      be managing the affairs of the hospital while the committee of management 
      which has to be formed under the scheme of Administration will have to 
      manage the affairs of the college. That necessarily means that the 
      committee so constituted under different statutes have separate identities 
      and separate duties to perform depending upon the nature and extent of 
      activities of the society. Where the society in question runs only the 
      college and that both the Committees of Management constituted under the 
      Act and under the scheme of Administration were the same, with the expiry 
      of the term of the committee constituted for the society would also expire 
      because it had no affairs to manage; Ram Sajiwan v. The II 
      Additional District Judge, Fatehpur, AIR 1994 NOC 273 (All).  
 
The rules and 
      regulations given in the memorandum of association form a contract amongst 
      the members of the society and they are necessarily required to be 
      registered under statute, these rules or regulations do not acquire any 
      statutory character. And even if rules or bye-laws do not provide for the 
      observance of the rules of natural justice before an expulsion, the courts 
      will imply them in the contract which is a body of rules or bye-laws; 
      State Bank of India Staff Association v Mohindra Bhattacharyya, 
      AIR 1991 Cal 378.  
 
The Registrar can refuse 
      to register a society in case all the necessary requirements as 
      contemplated in the Act are not fulfilled; Shanti Sarup v. 
      Radhaswami Satsang Sabha, Dayalbagh, Agra, AIR 1969 All 248. 
 
</subsubsection></subsection></section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Registration and fees.—Upon 
    such memorandum and certified copy being filed, the Registrar shall certify 
    under his hand that the society is registered under this Act. There shall be 
    paid to the Registrar for every such registration a fee of fifty rupees, or 
    such smaller fees as 

    1[the State 
    Government] may, from time to time, direct; and all fees so paid shall be 
    accounted for to 

    1[the State 
    Government.]  
 
 

State Amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 3, for the words “the Registrar” wherever they occur, substitute 
      the words “the Inspector-General”.
 
[President’s Act 10 of 1954, 
      sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-10-1954).]
 <section>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 3, 
      for the word “Registrar” wherever it occurs, substitute the words 
      “Inspector-General of Registration.”
 
[Vide Bihar Act 19 of 
      1956, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 21-12-1955).]
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 3,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  for the words “the 
      Registrar shall certify”, substitute the words “the Inspector-General 
      shall subject to the provisions of section 3A, certify”;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>  for the words “the 
      Registrar for”, substitute the words “the Inspector-General for”.
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 16-8-1979).]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as that 
      of Maharashtra.
 
In section 3, for the words 
      “the Registrar shall certify”, substitute the words, figure and letter 
      “the Registrar shall, subject to the provisions of section 3A, certify”.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
      section 3, for the full stop at the end of section, substitute a colon and 
      add thereafter the following proviso,—
 
“Provided that the State 
      Government may by notification in Official Gazette exempt any particular 
      society or class of societies from the payment of registration fee.”
 
[Vide H.P. Act 8 of 
      1965, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 26-11-1965); Act 23 of 1973, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
      4-12-1973).]
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—(i) In 
      section 3, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:—
 
“Provided that no such fee 
      shall be payable for the registration of a society formed with the object 
      of running an educational institution in any area in which, the Central 
      Provinces and Berar Vidya Mandir Act, 1939, is in force, if the objects 
      are similar to the objects of a Vidya Mandir established under Part I of 
      that Act.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 76 of 
      1958, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 7-10-1958).]
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Vidarbha Region.—In 
      its application to the Vidarbha region of the State of Maharashtra the 
      amendment made in section 3 by C.P. and Berar Act III of 1940 shall cease 
      to have effect and is repealed.
 
[Vide Bombay Act 76 of 
      1958, sec. 2 (b) (w.e.f. 7-10-1958).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> In section 3, after the 
      words “the Registrar shall”, insert the words “subject to the provisions 
      of section 3A”.
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 
      11 of 1968, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1968).]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Orissa</number>— In section 3, 
      for the word “Registrar”, substitute the words “Registrar of Societies.”
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 
      1958, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1961).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In 
      its application to the State of Punjab, in section 3 add the following 
      proviso, namely:—
 
“Provided that in the case of 
      society which had prior to the 15th August, 1947 been registered by the 
      Registrar, Joint-Stock Companies at Lahore, the State Government may grant 
      exemption from payment of the whole or any part of the registration fee.”
 
[Vide E.P. Act 32 of 
      1948, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 12-11-1948); Central Act 31 of 1966, sec. 89.]
 
Tamil Nadu.—In its 
      application to the State of Madras, the amendment made in section 3 is the 
      same as that in Andhra Pradesh.
 
[Vide T.N. Act 24 of 
      1954, sec. 2 (iii) (w.e.f. 1-9-1954).]
 
Uttar Pradesh.— For 
      section 3, substitute the following section, namely:—
 
“3. (1) Upon such memorandum 
      and certified copy being filed along with particulars of the address of 
      the Society as office which shall be in registered address, by the 
      Secretary of the Society on behalf of the persons subscribing to the 
      memorandum, the Registrar shall certify under his hand that the society is 
      registered under this Act. There shall be paid to the Registrar for every 
      such registration a fee of one thousand or such smaller fee as the State 
      Government may notify in respect of any class of societies:
 
Provided that the Registrar 
      may in his discretion, issue public notice or issue notice to such persons 
      as he thinks fit inviting objections, if any, against the proposed 
      registration and consider all objections that may be received by him 
      before registering the Society.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
      in sub-section (1) the Registrar shall refuse to register a society, if 
      after giving it an opportunity of showing cause against such refusal, he 
      is satisfied that—
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   the name of the society 
      is identical with that of any other society previously registered under 
      this Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   the name of the society 
      sought to be registered uses any of the words namely ‘Union’, ‘State’, 
      ‘Land Mortgage’, ‘Land Development’. ‘Co-operative, ‘Gandhi’, ‘Reserve 
      Bank’ or any words expressing or implying the sanction, approval or 
      patronage of the Central or any State Government or any word which 
      suggests or is calculated to suggest any connection with any local 
      authority or any corporation or body constituted by or under any law for 
      the time being in force or is such as is otherwise likely to deceive the 
      public or the members of any other society previously registered under 
      this Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>   any one or more of the 
      objects of the society sought to be registered is not an object mentioned 
      in sections 1 and 20; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>d</number>   its objects are contrary 
      to any other law for the time being in force:
 
Provided that the State 
      Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, increase from 
      time to time the fee payable under this sub-section:
 
Provided further that the 
      Registrar may, in his discretion, issue public notice or issue notices to 
      such persons as he thinks fit inviting objections, if any, against the 
      proposed registration and consider all objections that may be received by 
      him before registering the society.”
 
[Vide U.P. Acts 52 of 
      1975, sec. 2; 13 of 1978, sec. 3; 26 of 1979, sec. 2; 23 of 1994 and 8 of 
      2000, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 25-11-1993).]
 

Section 
      3A
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>Assam</number>—After section 3 
      insert the following:—
 
“3A. Name of Society.—(1) 
      No society shall be registered under a name which is identical with, or 
      too nearly resembles, the name of any other society or any body corporate 
      which has been previously registered or incorporated under this Act or any 
      other law for the time being in force, as the case may be.
 
No society shall use in its 
      nomenclature any of the words, namely:—
 
‘Union’, ‘State’, ‘Land 
      Mortgage’, ‘Gandhi’, ‘Reserve Bank’ or any word expressing or implying the 
      sanction, approval or patronage of Central or any State Government or any 
      word which suggest or is calculated to suggest connection with any local 
      authority or any corporation or body constituted by the Government under 
      any law for the time being in force except when the State Government 
      signifies its consent to the use of such words as part of the name of a 
      society by order in writing.”
 
[Vide Assam Act 13 of 
      1967, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 18-8-1967).]
 
Section 
      3A
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—After 
      section 3, insert the following section, namely:—
 
                   “3A. 
      Prohibition against registration of societies with undesirable names.—No 
      society, shall be registered by a name which, in the opinion of the 
      Inspector- General, is undesirable, being a name which is identical with, 
      or which in the opinion of the Inspector-General so nearly resembles the 
      name by which any other existing society has been previously registered as 
      to be likely to deceive the public or members of either society, or which 
      is being used without the previous permission of the Government concerned, 
      and which suggests or is calculated to suggest the patronage of any 
      Government or connection with any body constituted by any Government or 
      local authority, or which may, subject to any rules made in this behalf, 
      be deemed to be undesirable by the Inspector-General:
 
                   Provided 
      that no order shall be passed under section 3A unless the party against 
      whom such order is proposed to be passed is heard on the matter.”
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 

Section 
      3A
 </section><section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—After section 
      3, insert following, namely:—
 
                   “3A. 
      Prohibition against registration of societies with undesirable names.—No 
      Society shall be registered by a name which, in the opinion of the 
      Registrar, is undesirable, being a name which is identical with, or which 
      in the opinion of the Registrar, so nearly resembles the name by which any 
      other existing society has been previously registered, as to be likely to 
      deceive the public or members of either society, or which, without the 
      previous permission of the Government concerned, suggests or is calculated 
      to suggest the patronage of that Government or connection with any body 
      constituted by that Government or any local authority, or which may, 
      subject to any rules made in this behalf, be deemed to be undesirable by 
      the Registrar.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
 

Section 
      3A
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—After 
      section 3 insert the following, namely:—
 
                   “3A. 
      Prohibition against registration of societies with undesirable names.—No 
      Society shall be registered by a name which, in the opinion of the 
      Registrar is undesirable, being a name which is identical with, or which 
      in the opinion of the Registrar so nearly resembles the name by which any 
      other existing society has been previously registered, as to be likely to 
      deceive the public or member of either society, or which without the 
      previous permission of the Government concerned, suggests or is calculated 
      to suggest the patronage of that Government or connection with any body 
      constituted by that Government or any local authority, or which may, 
      subject of any rules made in that behalf, be deemed to be undesirable by 
      the Registrar.”
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 
      11 of 1968, sec. 3 (1-10-1968).]
 

Section 
      3A and 3B
 
Uttar Pradesh.—After 
      section 3, insert the following section, namely:—
 
“3A. Renewal of certificate 
      of registration.—(1) Subject to the provision of such section (2), a 
      certificate of registration issued under section 3 shall remain in force 
      for a period of two years from the date of issue:
 
Provided that a certificate 
      issued before the commencement of the Societies Registration (Uttar 
      Pradesh Amendment) Act, 1984 (hereinafter in this section referred to as 
      the said Act), shall remain in force for a period of five years from the 
      date of such commencement on payment of the difference of the fees 
      specified under sub-section (3) and the fees already paid.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> A Society registered under 
      section 3, whether before or after the commencement of the said Act, shall 
      on application made to the Registrar within one month of the expiration of 
      the period referred, to in sub-section (1) and on payment of the fee 
      specified in sub-section (3) be entitled to have its certificate of 
      registration renewed for five years at a time:
 
Provided that in the case of a 
      society registered before the commencement of the Act, the Registrar shall 
      refuse to renew the certificate of registration if after giving it, an 
      opportunity of showing cause against such refusal, he is satisfied that 
      any of the grounds mentioned in sub-section (2) of section 3 exist in 
      respect thereof.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> There shall be paid to the 
      Registrar with every application for renewal of the certificate of 
      registration—
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   a fee equal to the 
      registration fee payable under section 3 or rupees two hundred, whichever 
      is less, if such application is filed within the period specified in 
      sub-section (2):
 
Provided that the State 
      Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, increase from 
      time to time the fee payable under this clause subject to the condition 
      that the fee so increased shall not exceed the registration fee payable 
      under section 3;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   an additional fee of 
      forty rupees or such higher fee not exceeding one-fifth of the fee payable 
      under clause (a) as may be notified by the State Government, if such 
      application is filed within one month of the date of expiration of the 
      period specified in sub-section (2); and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>   an additional fee at the 
      rate of twenty rupees per month or part thereof, or such higher additional 
      fee per month not exceeding half of the additional fee payable under 
      clause (b) as may be notified by the State Government, if such application 
      is filed beyond one month of the expiration of the period specified in 
      sub-section (2).”
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> Every application for 
      renewal of the certificate shall be accompanied by a list of members of 
      the managing body elected after the registration of the society or after 
      the renewal of certificate of registration and also the certificate sought 
      to be renewed unless dispensed with by the Registrar on the ground of its 
      loss or destruction or other sufficient cause.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number> A society which fails to 
      get its certificate of registration renewed in accordance with this 
      section with one year from the expiration of the period for which the 
      certificate was operative shall become an unregistered society:
 
Provided that the Registrar 
      may, for sufficient cause allow an application for renewal more than one 
      year after the expiration of the period for which the certificate was 
      operative on payment of a fee of four hundred rupees or such higher fee 
      not exceeding ten times of the additional fee payable under clause (b) of 
      sub-section (3) as may be notified by the State Government from time to 
      time.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>6</number> Where a certificate of 
      registration is renewed in accordance with sub-section (2) or sub-section 
      (5) such renewal shall operate from the date of expiration of the period 
      for which the certificate was operative.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975); 13 of 1978, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f 27-2-1978); 
      11 of 1984, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 30-11-1984), 23 of 1994 and 8 of 2000) sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 
      25-11-1999).]
 
Section 
      3B
 
After section 3A, insert the 
      following, namely:—
 
                   “3B. 
      Reference to the State Government.—If any question arises whether any 
      Society is entitled to get itself registered in accordance with section 3 
      or to get its certificate of registration renewed in accordance with 
      section 3A the matter shall be referred to the State Government and the 
      decision of the State Government there on shall be final.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 26 of 
      1979, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 16-7-1979).]
  
 
COMMENTS  
 
A Society registered 
      under the Act has been held to have the presumption of being a ‘person’ 
      within the purview of section 236 of the Indian Succession Act, 1925; 
      Ganga Sahai v. Bharat Bhan, AIR 1950 All 480.  
 
A Society whose primary 
      object is religious cannot be registered under this Act; Md. Yunus 
      v. The Inspector General of Registration, AIR 1980 Pat 138.  
</subsection></section>
 

 
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Annual list of managing body to be filed.—Once 
    in every year, on or before the fourteenth day succeeding the day on which, 
    according to the rules of the Society, the annual general meeting of the 
    society is held, or, if the rules do not provide for an annual general 
    meeting, in the month of January, a list shall be filed with the Registrar 
    of Joint-Stock Companies, of the names, addresses and occupations of the 
    governors, council, directors, committee, or other governing body then 
    entrusted with the management of the affairs of the society.  
 
 

State Amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 4, for the words “the Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, 
      substitute the words “the Inspector-General of Registration.” 
 
[Vide President’s Act 
      10 of 1954, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-10-1954).]
 
Assam: Manipur: Tripura.—In 
      its application to the State of Assam, in section 4, for the words 
      “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute “Registrar of Societies”.
 
[Vide Assam Act 7 of 
      1957, sec. 2(ii) (w.e.f. 17-7-1957) and G.S.Rs. 85 and 86 of 1960, 
      published in the Gazette of India, 1960, Pt. II, Sec. 3
<section><number>i</number>, pp. 145, 146.]
 <subsection>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 4, 
      for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the words, 
      “Inspector-General of Registration.”
 
[Vide Bihar Act 19 of 
      1956, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 21-12-1955).]
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 4, for the words “the Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, 
      substitute the words “the Inspector-General”.
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as that 
      of Maharashtra.
 
Himachal Pradesh.—Same 
      as that of Punjab.
 
[Vide H.P. Act 23 of 
      1973, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 4-12-1973).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In its 
      application to the whole of the State of Bombay, in section 4, omit the 
      words “of Joint-Stock Companies.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 11 of 
      1956, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-7-1956) and Act 76 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
      7-10-1958).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—In section 4, 
      for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the words 
      “Registrar of Societies”.
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 
      1958, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1961).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh: 
      Delhi: Himachal Pradesh.—In its application to the State of Punjab, in 
      section 4.—
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>i</number>  Add the following 
      words, namely:—
 
“If a society makes default in 
      complying with the requirements of this section, it shall be liable to a 
      fine not exceeding fifty rupees.” 
 
[Vide E.P. Act 6 of 
      1949, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 8-2-1949); Central Act 31 of 1966, sec. 89.]
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>  Omit the words 
      “of Joint-Stock Companies”.
 
[Vide Punjab Act 31 of 
      1957, sec. 3; Chandigarh Act 31 of 1966 and G.S.Rs. 83 and 84 of 1960, 
      published in the Gazette of India, 1960, Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), pp. 144, 145.]
 
Tamil Nadu.—Section 4 
      is the same as that of Andhra Pradesh.
 
[Vide T.N. Act 24 of 
      1954, sec. 2(iv) (w.e.f. 1-9-1954).]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 4, for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute 
      the word “Registrar”.
 
[Vide U.P. Act 25 of 
      1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 25-8-1958).]
 </section><section>
<number>i</number> Renumber section 4 as 
      sub-section (1) thereof, and after sub-section (1) as renumbered insert 
      the following sub-section namely:—
 
“(2) Together with list 
      mentioned in sub-section (1) there shall be sent to the Registrar a copy 
      of the memorandum of association including any alteration, extension or 
      abridgement of purposes made under section 12, and of the rules of the 
      society corrected up to date and certified by not less than three of the 
      members of the said governing body to be a correct copy and also a copy of 
      the balance-sheet for the proceeding year of account.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975).]
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> in sub-section (1) insert 
      the following proviso:
 
Provided that if the managing 
      body is elected after the last submission of the list, the counter 
      signature of the old members, shall as far as possible, be obtained on the 
      list. If the old office bearers do not counter sign the list, the 
      Registrar may is his discretion, issue a public notice to such persons as 
      he thinks fit inviting objections within a specified period and shall 
      decide all objections received within the said period.
 
[Vide U.P. Act 11 of 
      1984, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 30-4-1984).]
 

Sections 
      4A and 4B
 <subsection>
<number>Assam</number>—(i) In its 
      application to the State of Assam, after section 4 insert the following 
      new section, namely:—
 
“4A. Changes in managing 
      body and rules to be filed.—(1) Together with the list mentioned in 
      section 4, there shall be sent to the Registrar of Societies a statement 
      showing changes during the year to which the list relates in the personnel 
      of the governors, council, directors, committee or other governing body to 
      whom the management of the affairs of the Society is entrusted and also a 
      copy of the rules of the society corrected up-to-date and certified to be 
      a correct copy by not less than three of the members of the governing 
      body.
 <subsubsection>
<number>2</number> A copy of ever alteration 
      made in the rules of the society, certified to be a correct copy by not 
      less than three members of the governing body, shall be sent to the 
      Registrar of Societies within fifteen days of the making of such 
      alteration.”
 
[Vide Assam Act 11 of 
      1952, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-10-1952); Act 7 of 1957, sec. 2 (ii) (w.e.f. 
      17-7-1957).]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number> After section 4A insert 
      the following:—
 
“4B. Balance-sheet and 
      auditor’s report to be forwarded to Registrar.—(1) Within thirty days 
      after the holding of every annual general meeting there shall be filed 
      with the Registrar of Societies a copy each of the balance-sheet and 
      auditor’s report certified by the auditor under sub-section (2) of section 
      5A.
 <subsection>
<number>2</number> If the President, 
      Secretary or any other person authorised in this behalf by a resolution of 
      the governing body of the society fails to comply with the provisions of 
      sub-section (1) he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
      hundred rupees.
 
[Vide Assam Act 13 of 
      1967, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 18-8-1967).]
 

Section 
      4A
 <subsubsection>
<number>Bihar</number>—Section 4A, 
      inserted after section 4, is the same as that of Assam, subject to the 
      following modifications, namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>a</number>  for the words “Registrar 
      of Societies” wherever they occur, substitute the words “Inspector-General 
      of Registration”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>b</number>  for the words “showing 
      changes” substitute the words “showing all changes”;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>c</number>  in sub-section (2), for 
      the words “than three members”, substitute the words “than three of the 
      members” and for “alteration” occurring at the end substitute the word 
      “alteration”.
 
[Vide Bihar Act 4 of 
      1951, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 7-3-1951); Act 19 of 1956, sec. 5 (w.r.e.f. 
      21-12-1955).]
 

Section 
      4A
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—After 
      section 4, insert the following section, namely:—
 
“4A. Power of 
      Inspector-General to call for Information or returns from governing body 
      of society and provisions relating thereto.—(1) The Inspector- General 
      may serve or cause to be served, on the governing body entrusted with the 
      management of the affairs of any society registered under this Act a 
      notice requiring it to furnish in such manner as may be prescribed, 
      information or returns relating to person employed by the society, their 
      conditions of employment (including their emoluments, any contributions, 
      concessions or other benefits and amenities provided for employees) and 
      such other matters relating thereto, as may be prescribed.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number> The form in which such 
      information or returns shall be furnished, the particulars which they 
      shall contain and the intervals (if any) in which such information or 
      returns shall be furnished, shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number> The notice referred to in 
      sub-section (1) may be served by post.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number> No information or returns 
      collected for the purposes of this section, shall without the previous 
      consent in writing of the society in relation to which the information or 
      returns was given or made be published in such manner as would enable any 
      particulars to be identified as referring to a particular society.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number> Except for the purposes of 
      a prosecution under section 11A or under the Indian Penal Code (Central 
      Act 45 of 1860), no person other than the Inspector-General or any person 
      duly specified by him in this behalf, shall be permitted to see any 
      information or returns furnished as aforesaid.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>6</number> No suit or other legal 
      proceeding shall lie against the Inspector-General or any person acting 
      under the authority of the Inspector-General in respect of anything in 
      good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this section.”
      
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 

Sections 
      4A and 4B
 <subsubsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—After section 
      4, insert the following namely:—
 
“4A. Changes in Managing 
      body and rules to be filed.—(1) Together with the list mentioned in 
      section 4, there shall be sent to the Registrar a statement showing 
      changes during the year to which the list relates in the personnel, of 
      Governors, Councils, Directors, Committee or other governing body to whom 
      the management of the affairs of the society is entrusted and also a copy 
      of the rules of the society correct up-to-date and certified to be correct 
      copy by not less than three of the member of the governing body.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number> A copy of every alteration 
      made in rules of the society certified to be a correct copy by not less 
      than three members of the governing body shall be sent to the Registrar 
      within thirty days of the making of such alteration.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 14 of 
      1965, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
 </subsection></section>

 
  


</article><article>
<number>4B</number> Power of Registrar to 
      call for information or returns from governing body of society and 
      provisions relating thereto.—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar may serve, or caused or 
      be served, on the authorised officer of any society registered under this 
      Act, a notice requiring him to furnish in such manner as may be prescribed 
      by rules, information or return relating to persons employed by the 
      society, their conditions of employment (including their emoluments, any 
      contributions, concessions or other benefits and amenities provided for 
      employees and matters relating thereto, as may be prescribed by such rules 
      and the authorised officer of the society on whom, such notice is served, 
      shall be bound to comply with the requirement stated therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The form in which such 
      information or returns shall be furnished, the particulars which may they 
      shall contain and the intervals (if any) at which such information or 
      returns shall be furnished shall be such as may be prescribed by rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The notice referred to in 
      sub-section (1) may be served by post.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No information or return 
      collected for the purposes of this shall, without the previous consent in 
      writing of the society in relation to which the information or return was 
      giving or made, be published in such manner as would enable any 
      particulars to be identified as referring to a particular society.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Except for the purposes of 
      a prosecution for an offence under section 11A or under the Indian Penal 
      Code, no person other than the Registrar or any person duly authorised by 
      him in this behalf, shall be permitted to see or to have access to any 
      information or return furnished as aforesaid.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No suit or other legal 
      proceeding shall lie against the Registrar or any person acting under the 
      authority of the Registrar in respect of anything in good faith done or 
      intended to be done in pursuance of this section.
 
Explanation.—In this 
      section “authorised officer”, in relation to any society means, such 
      officer or employee of the society as may be authorised for the purposes 
      of this section, by the rules and regulation of the society and in default 
      of such authorisation by rules and regulation by a resolution in writing 
      by the society, and shall include,—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   where any officer or 
      employee so authorised is unable to perform his duties by reason of 
      absence due to leave or any other cause or any other officer or employee 
      of the society who is in charge of the duties of the officer or employee 
      so authorised during his absence, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   where no such officer 
      or employee has been so authorised any member of the governing body of the 
      society.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
 

Section 
      4A
 <subsubsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—After 
      section 4, insert the following, namely:—
 
“4A. Power of Registrar to 
      call for information or return from governing body of society and 
      provisions relating thereto.—(1) The registrar may serve or cause to 
      be served, on the governing body entrusted with the management of the 
      affairs of any society registered under this Act, a notice requiring to 
      furnish in such manner as may be prescribed by rules, information or 
      returns relating to persons employed by the society, their conditions of 
      employment (including their emoluments, any contribution, concessions or 
      other benefits and amenities provided for employees) and matters relating 
      thereto, as may be prescribed by rules.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The forms in which such 
      information or return should be furnished, the particulars which they 
      should contain and the intervals (if any) in which such information or 
      returns should be furnished, shall be such as may be prescribed by such 
      rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The notice referred to in 
      sub-section (1) may be served by post.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No information or return 
      collected for the purposes of this section shall, without the previous 
      consent in writing of the society in relation to which the information or 
      return was given or made be published in such manner as would enable any 
      particulars to be identified as referring to a particular society.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Except for the purposes of 
      a prosecution under section 11A or under the Indian Penal Code, no person 
      other than the Registrar or any person duly specified by him in this 
      behalf, shall be permitted to see any information or return furnished as 
      aforesaid.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No suit or other legal 
      proceedings shall lie against the Registrar or any person acting under the 
      authority of the Registrar in respect of anything in good faith done or 
      intended to be done in pursuance of this section.”
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 
      11 of 1968, sec. 4 (1-1-1968).]
 

Sections 
      4A, 4B and 4C
 <subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—After section 
      4, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
                   “4A. 
      Changes in the list mentioned in section 4 and rules to be filed.—(1) 
      Without prejudice to the provisions of section 4 and change in personnel 
      on the list filed under said section occurring during the year to which 
      such list relates shall be intimated to the Registrar of Societies within 
      two months of the making of such changes.
 </subsection></section><section>
                   <number>2</number> A copy 
      of every alteration made in the rules and regulation of the society, 
      certified to be a correct copy by not less than three of the Governors, 
      Directors or members of governing body, as the case may be, shall be sent 
      to the Registrar of Societies within two months of such alteration.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>4B</number> 
      Persons by whom lists, etc., are to be sent.—It shall be the duty—
 <section>
                   <number>a</number>   of 
      the Chairman or, as the case may be, the President, the Secretary or any 
      other person authorised in that behalf by the rules and regulations of the 
      society or by a resolution of the governing body of the society; or
 </section><section>
                   <number>b</number>   of 
      the Chairman, or as the case may be, the President of the governing body 
      of the society where there is no such authorisation,
 
             to file the list 
      mentioned in section 4 or to send the intimation, or as the case may be, 
      the copy mentioned in section 4A to the Registrar or Societies.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>4C</number> 
      Offence.—
<section><number>1</number> If any person who is required so to do under the 
      preceding section fails without reasonable cause to comply with the 
      provisions thereof, he shall, on conviction, be punishable with fine which 
      may extend to one hundred rupees.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> If any 
      person wilfully makes or causes to be made any false entry or alteration 
      in, or any omission from, the list filed under section 4 or any statement 
      or copy of rules and regulations sent to the Registrar of Societies under 
      section 4A, he shall on, conviction, be punishable with fine which may 
      extend to five hundred rupees.”
 
[Vide Orissa Act 8 of 
      1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 15-4-1969).]
 

Section 
      4A
 <subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—(i) In 
      section 4, for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies” words 
      “Registrar of Companies” be substituted.
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> After section 4, the 
      following section shall be inserted:—
 
                   “4A. 
      Filing of Annual Accounts.—(1) A copy of the balance-sheet together 
      with a statement of receipts and expenditure duly certified by at least 
      two members of the governing body and audited by a person who has been 
      granted a certificate by the Government under the Chartered Accountants 
      Act, 1949 or by a special auditor approved by the Government shall also be 
      filed with the Registrar of companies, at the same time as required by 
      section 4.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
                   <number>2</number> A 
      filing fee of Rs. 3 each shall be paid along with the list and the 
      balance-sheet and copy of alteration to rules respectively referred to in 
      the 
      section 4 and sub-sections (1) and (6) of section 4A. The said fee may be 
      paid either by cash or crediting the amount to Government Treasury and by 
      attaching the duplicate challan to the documents.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> All 
      Societies registered under this Act shall hold every year a general 
      meeting at which the report of the management of the institution for the 
      previous year, together with the audited copy of the balance-sheet, 
      receipts and expenditure statement and the auditor’s report shall be 
      submitted for approval.
 </section><section>
                   <number>4</number> A 
      special meeting may be convened at any time on requisition of the 
      President or the Chairman of the Executive Committee, if any, or on the 
      requisition of not less than three members of the Executive Committee or 
      seven members of the general body of the society, who shall state in 
      writing the business for which they wish the meeting to be convened. The 
      Secretary shall convene a meeting of the society before the laps at ten 
      days from the date of receipt of the requisition.
 </section><section>
                   <number>5</number> If a 
      member has no registered address in the Union Territory and has not 
      furnished to the society an address within the Union Territory for serving 
      notice to him, a notice advertised in two newspapers (one in English and 
      the other in any of the vernacular languages) circulating in the 
      neighbourhood of registered office of the society shall be deemed to be 
      duly given to him on the day on which the advertisement appears.
 </section><section>
                   <number>6</number> A copy 
      of every alteration made in the rules and regulations of the society, 
      certified to be a correct copy in the manner prescribed as aforesaid shall 
      be sent to the Registrar within fifteen days of making of such 
      alterations.
 </section><section>
                   <number>7</number> If the 
      society makes default in complying with the requirements of sections 4 and 
      4A, it shall be liable to a fine not exceeding fifty rupees.”
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 9 
      of 1969, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-1-1970).]
 

Section 
      4A
 
Uttar Pradesh.—After 
      section 4, insert the following section, namely:—
 
                   “4A. 
      Changes etc. in rules to be intimated to Registrar.—A copy of every 
      change made in rules of the society and intimation of every change of 
      address of the society, certified by not less than three of the members of 
      the governing body shall be sent to the Registrar within thirty days of 
      the change.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975).]
  
 
COMMENTS  
 
The Assistant Registrar 
      had no jurisdiction to decide the present dispute in exercise of powers 
      under section 4 of the Societies Registration Act as the dispute has not 
      arisen in the context of the submission of the annual list of the managing 
      body but the election of the office bearers of the society and there is a 
      claim of existence of two rival executive bodies of the society and this 
      has to be decided by section 25 of the Societies Registration Act; All 
      Muslim Welfare Society v. Assistant Registrar, Firms, Societies &amp; 
      Chits, Varanasi, AIR 1992 All 43.  
 
Under section 4, the 
      Registrar deals with only such matters as may arise in the context of 
      submission of the annual list of the managing body. Section 4 of the 
      Societies Registration Act is not applicable to the present case as the 
      dispute has not arisen in the context of the submission of the annual list 
      of the managing body but with the election of the office-bearers of the 
      society; All India Council v. Assistant Registrar, Firms, 
      Societies &amp; Chits, Varanasi, AIR 1988 All 236.  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Property of society how vested.—The 
    property, movable and immovable, belonging to a society 
    registered under this Act, if not vested in trustees, shall be deemed to be 
    vested, for the time being, in the governing body of such society, and in 
    all proceedings, civil and criminal, may be described as the property of the 
    governing body of such society for their proper title.  
 
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 5, 
      for the words “civil and criminal” the words “civil, criminal and revenue” 
      shall be, and shall be deemed always to have been, substituted.
 
[Vide Bihar Act 2 of 
      1960, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 8-2-1960).]
 

Section 
      5A
 </section><section>
<number>Assam</number>—After section 5, 
      insert the following new section, namely:—
 
                   “5A. 
      Books of account and audit.—(1) Every society shall keep at its 
      registered office proper books of account in which shall be entered 
      accurately—
 <subsection>
                   <number>a</number>   all 
      sums of money received and the source thereof and all sums of money 
      expended by the society and the object or purpose for which such sums are 
      expended,
 </subsection><subsection>
                   <number>b</number>   the 
      assets and liabilities of the society.
 <subsubsection>
                   <number>2</number> Every 
      society shall have its account audited once every year by a duly qualified 
      auditor and have a balance-sheet prepared by him. The auditor shall also 
      submit a report showing the exact state of the financial affairs of the 
      society. Three copies of the balance-sheet and the auditor’s report shall 
      be certified by the auditor.
 
                   
      Explanation.—A duly qualified auditor means a Chartered Accountant 
      within the meaning of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 or a person 
      approved by the Registrar of Societies in this behalf.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                   <number>3</number> If the 
      President, Secretary or any other person authorised in this behalf by a 
      resolution of the governing body of the society fails to comply with the 
      provisions of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) he shall be punishable 
      with fine which may extend to twenty rupees for every day after the 
      detection of the default during which the default continues.”
 
[Vide Assam Act 13 of 
      1967, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 18-8-1967).]
 

Section 
      5A
 
Uttar Pradesh.—After 
      section 5, insert section 5A as follows:—
 
                   “5A. 
      Restriction on transfer of property.—(1) Notwithstanding anything 
      contained in any law, contract or other instrument to the contrary, it 
      shall not be lawful for the governing body of a society registered under 
      this Act or any of its members to transfer without the previous approval 
      of the Court, any immovable property belonging to such society.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                   <number>2</number> Every 
      transfer made in contravention of sub-section (1) shall be void.
 
                   
      Explanation I.—The word ‘Court’ shall have the meaning assigned to it 
      in section 13.
 
                   
      Explanation II.—The expression ‘transfer’ shall for the purposes of 
      this section mean—
 <subsubsubsection>
                   <number>a</number>   a 
      mortgage, charge, sale gift, of exchange;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                   <number>b</number>   lease 
      for a term exceeding five years: or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
                    <number>c</number>   
      “irrevocable licence.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 26 of 
      1979, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 16-7-1979).]
  
 

comments  
 
The right of the members 
      over the property of a registered society is not personal but merely of 
      management over it in the capacity analogus to that of trustees; 
      Pamulapati Buchinaidu College Committee, Nidubrolu v. Government of 
      Andhra Pradesh, AIR 1958 AP 773.  
</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Suits by and against societies.—Every 
    society registered under this Act may sue or be sued in the name of the 
    president, chairman, or principal secretary, or trustees, as shall be 
    determined by the rules and regulations of the society and, in default of 
    such determination, in the name of such person as shall be appointed by the 
    governing body for the occasion:  
 
Provided 
    that it shall be competent for any person having a claim, or demand against 
    the society, to sue the president or chairman, or principal secretary or the 
    trustees thereof, if on application to the governing body some other officer 
    or person be not nominated to be the defendant.  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Suits not to abate.—No 
    suit or proceeding in any Civil Court shall abate or discontinue by reason 
    of the person, by or against whom such suit or proceedings shall have been 
    brought or continued, dying or ceasing to fill the character in the name 
    whereof he shall have sued or been sued, but the same suit or proceeding 
    shall be continued in the name of or against the successor of such person.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Enforcement of judgment against society.—If 
    a judgment shall be recovered against the person or officer named on behalf 
    of the society, such judgment shall not be put in force against the 
    property, movable or immovable, or against the body of such person or 
    officer, but against the property of the society.  
 
The 
    application for execution shall set forth the judgment, the fact of the 
    party against whom it shall have been recovered having sued or having been 
    sued, as the case may be, on behalf of the society only, and shall require 
    to have the judgment enforced against the property of the society.  
 
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 8, 
      after the word “judgment” wherever it occurs, insert the words “or 
      decree”.
 
[Vide Bihar Act 20 of 
      1960, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 3-2-1960).]
  
 
COMMENTS  
 
A judgment or decree is 
      not enforceable against the individual members constituting a registered 
      society in as much as the society has a legal entity separate from its 
      members; K.C. Thomas v. R.L. Godeok, AIR 1970 Pat 163.  
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Recovery of penalty accruing under bye-law.—Whenever 
    by any bye-law duly made in accordance with the rules and regulations of the 
    society, or, if the rules do not provide for the making of bye-laws, by any 
    bye-law made at a general meeting of the members of the society convened for 
    the purpose (for the making of which the concurrent votes of three-fifths of 
    the members present at such meeting shall be necessary), any pecuniary 
    penalty is imposed for the breach of any rule or bye-law of the society, 
    such penalty, when accrued, may be recovered in any Court having 
    jurisdiction where the defendant shall reside, or the society shall be 
    situate, as the governing body thereof shall deem expedient.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Members liable to be sued as strangers.—Any 
    member who may be in arrear of a subscription which according to the rules 
    of the society he is bound to pay, or who shall possess himself of or detain 
    any property of the society in a manner or for a time contrary to such 
    rules, or shall injure or destroy and property of the society, may be sued 
    for such arrear or for the damage accruing from such detention, injury, or 
    destruction of the property in the manner hereinbefore provided.  
 

    Recovery by successful defendant of costs adjudged.—But 
    if the defendant shall be successful in any suit or other proceedings 
    brought against him at the instance of the society, and shall be adjudged to 
    recover his costs, he may elect to proceed to recover the same from the 
    officer in whose name the suit shall be brought, or from the society, and in 
    the latter case shall have process against the property of the said society 
    in the manner above described. 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Members guilty of offences punishable as strangers.—Any 
    member of the society who shall steal, purloin, or embezzle any money or 
    other property, or wilfully and maliciously destroy or injure any property 
    of such society, or shall forge any deed, bond, security for money, receipt, 
    or other instrument, whereby the funds of the society may be exposed to 
    loss, shall be subject to the same prosecution, and, if convicted, shall be 
    liable to be punished in like manner, as any person not a member would be 
    subject and liable to in respect of the like offence. 
 
 
 

State Amendments
 

Sections 
      11A, 11B and 11C
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—After 
      section 11, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
“11A. Penalty for 
      contravening section 4A.—If the governing body entrusted with the 
      management of the affairs of any society registered under this Act 
      required to furnish any information or returns—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   wilfully refuses or 
      without lawful excuse neglects to furnish such information or returns as 
      may be required under section 4A; or
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   wilfully furnishes or 
      causes to be furnished any information or returns which it knows to be 
      false; or
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   refuses to answer or, 
      wilfully gives a false answer to any question necessary for obtaining any 
      information required to be furnished under section 4A,
 
such governing body shall, for 
      each such offence on conviction, be punished with fine which may extend to 
      fifty rupees.
 </section>

 
  


</article><article>
<number>11B</number> Penalty for improper 
      disclosure or information or return.—If the Inspector-General or any 
      person duly authorised by him in connection with the collection of any 
      information or returns under this Act wilfully discloses any information 
      or contents of any returns given or made under this Act otherwise than in 
      the execution of his duties under this Act or for the purpose of 
      prosecution, of an offence under this Act or the Indian Penal Code 
      (Central Act 45 of 1860), he shall, on conviction, be punished for such 
      offence with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.
 </article><article>
<number>11C</number> Cognizance of 
      offences.—No prosecution for an offence under section 11A shall be 
      instituted, except by, or with the sanction of, the Inspector-General, and 
      no prosecution for an offence under section 11B shall be instituted except 
      by, or with the consent of, the Government.”
 
[Vide Goa, Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 

Sections 
      11A, 11B and 11C
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—After section 
      11, insert the following new sections, namely:—
 
“11A. Penalty for 
      contravening section 4B.—If any authorised officer of a society who is 
      required to furnish any information or return under sub-section (1) of 
      section 4B.—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   wilfully refuses or 
      without lawful excuse neglects to furnish such information or return as 
      may be required under section 4B; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   wilfully furnishes or 
      cause to be furnished any information or return which he knows to be 
      false; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   refuses to answer or 
      wilfully gives a false answer to any question necessary for obtaining any 
      information required to be furnished under section 4B.
 
such authorised officer shall, 
      on conviction, be punished for each such offence with fine which may 
      extend to two hundred rupees.
 </subsection></section></article><article>
<number>11B</number> Penalty for improper 
      disclosure of information or return.—If the Registrar or any person 
      duly authorised by him in connection with the collection of any 
      information or returns under this Act wilfully discloses any information 
      or the contents of any return given or made under this Act otherwise than 
      in the execution of his duties under this Act or under the Indian Penal 
      Code he shall, on conviction, be punished for such offence with fine which 
      may extend to two hundred rupees.
 </article><article>
<number>11C</number> Sanction for 
      prosecution.—No prosecution for an offence under 
      section 11A shall be instituted, except by, or with the sanction of, the 
      Registrar, and no prosecution for an offence under section 11B shall be 
      instituted except by, or with the consent of, the State Government.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
 

Sections 
      11A, 11B and 11C
 <section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—After 
      section 11, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
“11A. Penalty for 
      contravening section 4A—If the governing body entrusted with the 
      management of the affairs of any society registered under this Act 
      required to furnish any information or return—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   wilfully refuses or 
      without lawful excuse neglects to furnish such information or return as 
      may be required under section 4A; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   wilfully furnishes or 
      causes to be furnished any information or return which it knows to be 
      false; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   refuses to answer or 
      wilfully gives a false answer to any question necessary for obtaining any 
      information required to be furnished under section 4A,
 
such governing body shall, for 
      each offence on conviction, be punished with fine, which may extend to 
      fifty rupees.
 </subsection></section></article><article>
<number>11B</number> Penalty for improper 
      disclosure of information or return.—If the Registrar or any person 
      duly authorised by him in connection with the collection of any 
      information or returns under this Act wilfully discloses any information 
      or the contents of any returns given or made under this Act otherwise than 
      in the execution of his duties under this Act or for the purposes of the 
      prosecution, of an offence under this Act or the Indian Penal Code, he 
      shall, on conviction, be punished for such offence with fine which may 
      extend to two hundred rupees.
 </article><article>
<number>11C</number> Cognizance of 
      offences.—No prosecution for an offence under section 11A shall be 
      instituted except by or with the sanction of the Registrar, and 
      prosecution for an offence under section 11B shall be instituted except 
      by, or with the consent of, the State Government.”
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 
      11 of 1968, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-10-1968).]
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Societies enabled to alter, extend or abridge their purposes.—Whenever
it shall appear to the governing body of any society registered under 
    this Act, which has been established for any particular purpose or purposes, 
    that it is advisable to alter, extend, or a bridge such purpose to or for 
    other purposes within the meaning of this Act, or to amalgamate such society 
    either wholly or partially with any other society, such governing body may 
    submit the proposition to the members of the society in a written or printed 
    report, and may convene a special meeting for the consideration thereof 
    according to the regulations of the society;  
 
but no 
    such proposition shall be carried into effect unless such report shall have 
    been delivered or sent by post to every member of the society ten days 
    previous to the special meeting convened by the governing body for the 
    consideration thereof, nor unless such proposition shall have been agreed to 
    by the votes of three-fifths of the members delivered in person or by proxy, 
    and confirmed by the votes of three-fifths of the members present at a 
    second special meeting convened by the governing body at an interval of one 
    month after the former meeting.  
 
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Delhi</number>—In section 12, 
      after the words “other society” insert the words “or whenever the 
      governing body of any society registered under this Act decides to change 
      the name of the society”.
 
[Vide Delhi Act 9 of 
      1954, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 30-10-1954).]
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 12, after the words “either wholly or partially with any other 
      society,” insert the words “or to change the name of the society”.
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 1979, 
      sec. 8 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 </section><section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as that 
      of Maharashtra.
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
      section 12, after the words “other society” insert the words “or whenever 
      the governing body of any society registered under this Act decides to 
      change the name of the society.”
 
[Vide H.P. Act 23 of 
      1973, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 4-12-1973).]
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In its 
      application to the State of Bombay, in section 12, after the words “other 
      society”, insert the words “or whenever the governing body of any society 
      registered under this Act decides to change the name of the society”.
 
[Vide Bombay Act 53 of 
      1948, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 5-12-1948) and Bombay Act 76 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
      7-10-1958).]
 </section><section>
<number>Orissa</number>—In section 12,—
 <subsection>
                    <number>i</number>   in 
      first paragraph, after the words “any other society”, insert the words “or 
      whenever the governing body of any such society decides to change the name 
      of the society”; and
 </subsection><subsection>
                   <number>ii</number>   
      after second paragraph insert the following proviso:—
 
                   “Provided 
      that no proposition for amalgamation shall be carried into effect unless 
      it has been considered, agreed to and confirmed by all concerned societies 
      in the manner prescribed in this section.”
 
[Vide Orissa Act 8 of 
      1969, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 15-4-1969).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In 
      its application to the State of Punjab, the amendment made in section 12 
      is the same as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide E.P. Act 6 of 
      1949, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 8-4-1949); Central Act 31 of 1966, sec. 89).]
 
West Bengal.—Same as 
      that of Maharashtra. 
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 
      16 of 1950, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 30-3-1950).]
 

Sections 
      12A, 12B and 12C
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Assam</number>—After section 
      12, insert the following new sections, namely:—
 
                   “12A. 
      Change of name.—Any society registered under this Act may, with the 
      consent of not less than two-thirds of the total number of its members by 
      a resolution at a general meeting convened for the purpose of subject to 
      the provisions of section 12B, change its name.
 </section>

 
  


</article><article>
                   <number>12B</number> 
      Notice of change of name.—
<section><number>1</number> Notice in writing of every change of 
      name, signed by the Secretary and by seven members of the society changing 
      its name, shall be sent to the Registrar.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> If the 
      proposed name is identical with that by which any other existing society 
      has been registered or, in the opinion of the Registrar, nearly resembles 
      such name as to be likely to deceive the public, the Registrar shall 
      refuse to register the change of name.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> Save as 
      provided in sub-section (2), the Registrar shall, if he is satisfied that 
      the provisions of this Act in respect of change of name have been complied 
      with, register the change of name and the change of name shall have effect 
      from the date of such registration.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12C</number> 
      Effects of change of name.—The change in the name of a society 
      registered under this Act shall not affect any right or obligations of the 
      society or render defective any legal proceeding by or against the 
      society, and any legal proceeding which might have been continued or 
      commenced by or against it by its former name may be continued or 
      commenced by or against it by its new name.”
 
[Vide Assam Act 14 of 
      1943, sec. 2.]
 

Sections 
      12A and 12B
 <section>
<number>Bihar</number>—After section 
      12, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
                   “12A. 
      Change of name.—Any number not less than three-fifths of the members 
      of any society registered under section 3 may, subject to the provisions 
      of section 12B, change its name.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12B</number> 
      Notice of change in name.—
<section><number>1</number> Notice in writing of every change of 
      name signed by the Secretary and any seven members of the society changing 
      its name shall be sent to the Registrar.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> If the 
      proposed name is identical with that by which any other existing society 
      has been registered or, in the opinion of the Registrar, so nearly 
      resembles such name as to be likely to deceive the public or the members 
      of either society, the Registrar shall refuse to register the change of 
      name.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> Save as 
      provided in sub-section (2) the Registrar shall if he is satisfied that 
      the provisions of this Act in respect of change of name have been complied 
      with, register the change of name and the change of name shall have effect 
      from the date of such registration.”
 
[Vide Bihar Act 30 of 
      1948, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 21-7-1948).]
 

Sections 
      12A, 12B, 12C
 <subsection>
<number>Delhi</number>—After section 
      12, insert following new sections, namely.—
 
                   “12A. 
      Registration of change of name.—(1) Where a proposition for change of 
      name has been agreed to and confirmed in the manner prescribed by 
      section 12, a copy of the proposition so agreed to and confirmed shall be 
      forwarded to the Registrar for registering the change of name. If the 
      proposed name is identical with that by which any other existing society 
      has been registered, or in the opinion of the Registrar so nearly 
      resembles such name as to be likely to deceive the public or the members 
      of either society, the Registrar shall refuse to register the change the 
      name.
 </subsection></section><section>
                   <number>2</number> Save as 
      provided in sub-section (1), the Registrar shall, if he is satisfied that 
      the provisions of this Act in respect of change of name have been complied 
      with, register the change of name and issue a certificate of registration 
      altered to meet the circumstances of the case. On the issue of such a 
      certificate the change of name shall be complete.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> The 
      Registrar shall charge for any copy of a certificate issue under 
      sub-section (2) a fee of rupee one or such large fee and exceeding rupees 
      five as the State Government may from time to time, direct; and all fees 
      so paid shall form part of the Consolidated Fund of India.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12B</number> 
      Effect of Change.—The change in the name of a society shall not affect 
      any rights or obligations of the society or render defective any legal 
      proceeding by or against the society; and any legal proceeding which might 
      have been continued or commenced by or against it by the former name may 
      be continued or commenced by or against it by the new name.
 </article><article>
                   <number>12C</number> 
      Registration of change of names effected before coming into force of Delhi 
      Act 9 of 1954.—If any society registered under this Act has, before 
      the date of the coming into force of the Societies Registration (Delhi 
      Amendment) Act, 1954, intimated to the Registrar the change of its name 
      and if the Registrar has recorded such change, the Registrar may, 
      notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, on an application made by 
      the society in this behalf and on payment of a fee as provided for in 
      sub-section (3) of section 12A, register the change of such name and issue 
      a certificate to the society under sub-section (2) of the said section 
      12A. One of the issue of such certificate the change shall be deemed to be 
      complete from the date on which such change was recorded by the Registrar, 
      notwithstanding the fact that the society had not followed the procedure 
      prescribed in sections 12 and 12A.”
 
[Vide Delhi Act 9 of 
      1954, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 30-10-1954).]
 

Sections 
      12A to 12D
 
Goa Daman and Diu.—After 
      section 12, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
                   “12A. 
      Registration of change of name.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a proposition for change of 
      name of a society has been agreed to and confirmed in the manner specified 
      in section 12, a copy of the proposition so agreed to and confirmed shall 
      be forwarded to the Inspector-General for registering the change of name.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> If the 
      proposed change of name is in his opinion undesirable for any of the 
      reasons mentioned in section 3A, the Inspector-General shall refuse to 
      register the change of name.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> Save as 
      provided in sub-section (2), the Inspector-General shall, if he is 
      satisfied that the provisions of the Act in respect of the change of name 
      have been complied with, register the change of name and issue a 
      certificate of registration altered to meet the circumstances of the case 
      and on the issue of such a certificate, the change of name shall be 
      complete.
 </section><section>
                   <number>4</number> The 
      Inspector-General shall charge for any copy of a certificate issued under 
      sub-section (3), a fee of one rupee and all fees so paid shall be 
      accounted for to the Government.
 </section><section>
                   <number>5</number> If, 
      through inadvertence or otherwise, a society is registered by a name which 
      should not have been registered (due regard being had to the provisions of 
      section 3A), the Inspector-General, may, after hearing the party 
      concerned, direct the society to change the name, and the society shall 
      change its name within a period of three months from the date of such 
      direction or such longer period as the Inspector-General may think fit to 
      allow, in accordance with the provisions of this Act.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12B</number> 
      Effect of change of name.—The change of name of society shall not 
      affect any right or obligation of the society or render defective any 
      legal proceeding by or against the society, and any legal proceeding which 
      might have been continued or commenced by or against it by its former name 
      may be continued or commenced by or against it by its new name.
 </article><article>
                   <number>12C</number> 
      Maintenances of accounts, and their balancing and accounting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Every governing body entrusted with the management of the affairs of a 
      society registered under this Act shall keep regular accounts.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> Such 
      accounts shall be kept in such from as may be approved by the 
      Inspector-General and shall contain such particulars as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> The 
      accounts of a society shall be balanced each year on the 31st day of March 
      or such other date as may be fixed by the Inspector-General.
 </section><section>
                   <number>4</number> The 
      accounts of a society shall be audited annually in such manner as may be 
      prescribed and by a person who is a Chartered Accountant within the 
      meaning of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (Central Act 38 of 1949), 
      or by such persons as may be authorised in this behalf by the Government.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12D</number> 
      Auditors duty to report irregularity.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be the duty of 
      every auditor, auditing the accounts of a society under section 12C to 
      prepare a reprint relating to auditing such account and forward a copy of 
      the same to the Inspector-General.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> The 
      auditor shall, in his report, specify all case of irregular, illegal or 
      improper expenditure, or failure or omission to recover moneys or other 
      property thereof, and state whether such expenditure, failure, omission, 
      loss or waste was caused in consequence of breach of trust, or 
      misappropriation or any other misconduct on the part of the governing body 
      or any other person.”
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 

Sections 
      12A and 12E
 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as that 
      of Maharashtra except sub-section (4) of section 12A, sections 12D and 
      12E.
 
[Vide Bombay Act 76 of 
      1958 and Act 11 of 1960, sec. 83.]
 
In section 12A, in sub-section 
      (1) for the portion beginning with the words “if the proposed name” and 
      ending with the words “or the members of either society”, substitute the 
      words, figure and letter “If the proposed change in name is in the opinion 
      of the Registrar undesirable for any of the reasons mentioned in section 
      3A”.
 
After sub-section (3), add the 
      following sub-section, namely:—
 
                   “(4) If, 
      through inadvertence or otherwise, a society is registered by a name, by 
      which it should not have been registered having regard to the provisions 
      of section 3A, the Registrar may, after hearing the society concerned, 
      direct the society to change the name; and the society shall change its 
      name within a period of three months from the date of the direction or 
      within such longer period as the Registrar may think fit to allow in 
      accordance with the provisions of this Act.”
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
 
After section 12C, insert 
      following sections, namely:—
 
                   “12D. 
      Maintenance of account and their balancing and auditing.—(1) Every 
      governing body entrusted with the management or the affairs of a society 
      registered under this Act (not being a public trust within the meaning of 
      the Bombay Public Trusts Act, 1950) shall keep regular accounts.
 </subsection></section><section>
                   <number>2</number> Such 
      accounts shall be kept in such form as may be approved by the Registrar 
      and shall contain such particulars as may be prescribed by rules.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> The 
      accounts shall be balanced each year on the thirty-first day of March or 
      such other day as may be fixed by the Registrar.
 </section><section>
                   <number>4</number> The 
      accounts shall be audited annually in such manner as may be prescribed by 
      rules, by a person who is a Chartered Accountant within the meaning of the 
      Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 or by such other persons as may be 
      authorised in this behalf by the State Government.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12E</number> 
      Auditor’s duty to prepare balance-sheet and report irregularities, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      It shall be the duty of every auditor auditing the accounts of a society 
      under section 12D to prepare an income and expenditure account and a 
      balance-sheet and to forward a copy of the same to the Registrar.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> The 
      auditor shall in his report specify all cases of irregular, illegal or 
      improper expenditure, or failure or omission to recover money or other 
      property belonging to the society, or of loss or waste of money or other 
      property thereof; and state whether such expenditure, failure, omission, 
      loss or waste was caused in consequence of breach of trust, or 
      misapplication of money or other property belonging to the society or may 
      other misconduct on the part of the governing body or any other person”.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
 

Section 
      12A
 
Himachal Pradesh.—Same 
      as that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide H.P. Act 23 of 
      1973, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 4-12-1973).]
 

Sections 
      12A to 12E
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—After 
      section 12 of the Act, in its application to the whole of the State of 
      Bombay, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
                   “12A. 
      Registration of change of name.—(1) Where a proposition for change of 
      name has been agreed to and confirmed in the manner prescribed by section 
      12, a copy of the proposition so agreed to and confirmed shall be 
      forwarded to the Registrar for registering the change of name. If the 
      proposed change in the name is in his opinion undesirable for any of the 
      reasons mentioned in section 3A the Registrar shall refuse to register the 
      change of name.
 </subsection></section><section>
                   <number>2</number> Save as 
      provided in sub-section (1), the Registrar shall, if he is satisfied that 
      the provisions of this Act in respect of change of name have been complied 
      with, register the change of name and issue a certificate of registration 
      altered to meet the circumstances of the case. On the issue of such a 
      certificate the change of name shall be complete.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> The 
      Registrar shall charge for any copy of a certificate issued under 
      sub-section (2) a fee of rupee one and all fees so paid shall be accounted 
      for to the State Government.
 </section><section>
                   <number>4</number> If, 
      through inadvertence or otherwise, a society is registered by a name which 
      should not have been registered (due regard being had to the provisions of 
      section 3A), the Registrar may, after hearing the party concerned direct 
      the society to change the name; and the society shall change its name 
      within a period of three months from the date of the direction in 
      accordance with the provisions of this Act, or such longer period as the 
      Registrar may think fit to allow.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12B</number> 
      Effect of change of name.—The change in the name of society shall not 
      affect any rights or obligations of the society or render defective any 
      legal proceeding by or against the society and any legal proceeding which 
      might have been continued or commenced by or against it by its former name 
      may be continued or commenced by or against it by its new name.
 </article><article>
                   <number>12C</number> 
      Registration of change of names effected before coming into force of 
      Bombay Act LIII of 1948.—If any society registered under this Act has, 
      before the date the coming into force of the Societies Registration Bombay 
      (Amendment) Act, 1948, intimated to the Registrar of Companies the change 
      of its name and if the Registrar has recorded such change, the Registrar 
      may, notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, on an application 
      made by the society in this behalf and on payment of a fee as provided for 
      in sub-section (3) of section 12A, register the change of such name and 
      issue a certificate to the society under sub-section (2) of the said 
      section 12A. On the issue of such certificate the change shall be deemed 
      to be complete from the date on which such change was recorded by the 
      Registrar, notwithstanding the fact that the society had not followed the 
      procedure prescribed in sections 12 and 12A.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 53 of 
      1948, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 5-11-1948) read with Act 76 of 1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
      7-10-1958).]
 
                   “12D. 
      Maintenance of accounts and their balancing and accounting.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
      governing body entrusted with the management of the affairs of a society 
      registered under this Act (not being a public trust within the meaning of 
      Bombay Public Trusts Act, 1950) shall keep regular accounts.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> Such 
      accounts shall be kept in such form as may be approved by the Registrar, 
      and shall contain such particulars as may be prescribed by rules.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> The 
      accounts shall be balanced each year on the 31st day of March or such 
      other day as may be fixed by the Registrar.
 </section><section>
                   <number>4</number> The 
      accounts shall be audited annually in such manner as may be prescribed by 
      rules and by a person who is a Chartered Accountant within the meaning of 
      the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949, or by such persons as may be 
      authorised in this behalf by the State Government.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12E</number> 
      Auditor’s duty to prepare balance sheet and report irregularities, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      It shall be the duty of every auditor auditing the accounts of a society 
      under section 12D to prepare balance-sheet and income and expenditure 
      account and to forward a copy of the same to the Registrar.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> The 
      auditor shall in his report specify all cases of irregular, illegal or 
      improper expenditure or failure or omission to recover money or other 
      property belonging to the society or of loss or waste of money or other 
      property thereof, and state whether such expenditure, failure, omission, 
      loss or waste caused in consequence of branch of trust or misapplication 
      or any other misconduct on the part of the governing body or any other 
      person.”
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 
      11 of 1968, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-11-1968).]
 

sections 
      12A to 12C
 <subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—Same as in 
      Maharashtra with the following modifications:—
 <subsubsection>

            (i)  In section 
      12A(1), for the words “If the proposed change in the name is in his 
      opinion undesirable for any reasons mentioned in section 3A”, read “if the 
      proposed name is identical with that by which any other existing society 
      has been registered or in the opinion of the Registrar so nearly resembles 
      the name of such other society as is likely to deceive the public or 
      members of either society”;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           <number>ii</number> omit 
      sub-section (4);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>iii</number> in section 12C 
      for the words “Bombay Act LIII of 1948” read “Orissa Amendment Act, 1969” 
      and for the words “Societies Registration (Bombay Amendment) Act, 1948” 
      read “S.R. (Orissa Amendment) Act, 1969”; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
          <number>iv</number> in section 12B, 
      for the words “by its new name” read “by the new name.
 
[Vide Orissa Act 8 of 
      1969, sec. 4 (15-4-1969).]
 

Sections
      12A to 
      12C
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—After 
      section 12, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
                   “12A. 
      Change of name.—Any number not less than three-fifths of the members 
      of any society registered under section 3 may subject to the provisions of 
      section 12B, by a resolution or otherwise change its name.
 </subsection></section></article><article>
                   <number>12B</number> 
      Registration of change of name.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a proposition for change of 
      name has been agreed to and confirmed in the manner prescribed by section 
      12A, a copy of the proposition so agreed to and confirmed shall be 
      forwarded to the Registrar of Companies for registering the change of 
      name.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> Save as 
      provided in section 18A, the Registrar shall, if he is satisfied that the 
      provisions of this Act in respect of change of name have been complied 
      with, register the change of name and issue a certificate of registration 
      altered to meet the circumstances of the case. On the issue of such a 
      certificate, the change of the name shall be complete.
 </section><section>
                   <number>3</number> The 
      Registrar shall charge for any copy of a certificate issued under 
      sub-section (2), a fee of rupee one and fees so paid shall be accounted 
      for to the Government.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12C</number> 
      Effect of change of name.—The change in the name of society shall not 
      affect any rights or obligations of the society or render defective any 
      legal proceeding by or against the society, and any legal proceeding which 
      might have been continued or commenced by or against it by its former name 
      may be continued or commenced by or against it by its name.”
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 9 
      of 1969, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-1-1970).]
 

sections 
      12A and 12B
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In 
      its application to the State of Punjab new sections 12A and 12B are the 
      same as sections 12A and 12B of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide E.P. Act 6 of 
      1949, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 8-4-1949); Central Act 31 of 1966, sec. 89.]
 

Sections 
      12A to 12D
 
Uttar Pradesh.—After 
      section 12, insert the following sections, namely:—
 
                   “12A. 
      Change of name.—Any society registered under this Act may, with the 
      consent of less than two-thirds of the total number of its members, and 
      with the previous approval of the Registrar in writing change its name by 
      resolution passed as a general meeting convened for the purpose.
 </article><article>
                   <number>12B</number> 
      Notice of change of name or objects.—
<section><number>1</number> Notice in writing of every 
      change of objects made under section 12 of name made under section 12A 
      signed by the secretary and any three members of the society shall he sent 
      to the Registrar.
 </section><section>
                   <number>2</number> Where 
      the Registrar is satisfied that the provisions of this Act in respect of 
      objects or name of society and in respect of change of objects or of name, 
      as the case may be, have been complied with, he may subject to the 
      provisions of section 12C register the change of name which shall have 
      effect from the date of such registration.
 </section></article><article>
                   <number>12C</number> 
      Effect of change of name or objects.—The change in the objects or name 
      of a society shall not affect any rights or obligations of the society, 
      nor render defective any legal proceedings by or against the society, and 
      any legal proceeding which might have been continued or commenced by or 
      against it by its former name may be continued or commenced by or against 
      it by its new name.
 </article><article>
                   <number>12D</number> 
      Registrar’s power to cancel registration in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Registrar may, by 
      order in writing, cancel the registration of any society on any of the 
      following grounds:—
 <subsection>
                   <number>a</number>   that 
      the registration of the society or of its name or change of name is 
      contrary to the provisions of this Act or of any other law for the time 
      being in force;
 </subsection><subsection>
                   <number>b</number>   that 
      its activities or proposed activities have been or are or will be 
      subversive of the objects of the society or opposed to public policy;
 
 
a[(c)   
      that the registration or the certificate of renewal has been obtained by 
      misrepresentation or fraud]:
 
                   Provided 
      that no order of cancellation of registration of any society shall be 
      passed until the society has been given a reasonable opportunity of 
      altering its name or object or of showing cause against the action 
      proposed to be taken in regard to it.
 


                                  b[(2) An 
      appeal against an order made under sub-section (1) may be preferred to the 
      Commissioner of the Division in whose jurisdiction the Headquarter of the 
      society lies, within one month from the date of communication of such 
      order.
 </subsection></section><section>
                   <number>3</number> The 
      decision of the Commissioner under sub-section (2), shall be final and 
      shall not be called in question in any court.]
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975); Act 26 of 1979, secs. 5 and 6 
      (w.e.f. 16-7-1979).]
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>   Inserted by U.P. 
      Act 11 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 30-4-1984).  
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>   Substituted by 
      U.P. Act 11 of 1984, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 30-4-1984).  
 

Sections 
      12A to 12C
 
West Bengal.—New 
      sections 12A and 12B are the same as sections 12A and 12B of Maharashtra: 
      the new section 12C is as follows, namely:—
 
                   “12C. 
      Registration of change of name effected in certain cases.—If any 
      society registered under this Act has before the date of the coming into 
      force of the Societies Registration (West Bengal Amendment) Act, 1950 
      intimated to the Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies the change of its name 
      and if the Registrar has recorded such change, the Registrar may, 
      notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, on an application made by 
      the society in this behalf and on payment of a fee as provided for in 
      sub-section (3) of section 12A, register the change of such name and issue 
      a certificate to the society under sub-section (2) of the said section 
      12A. On of the issue of such certificate the change shall deemed to be 
      complete from the date on which such change was recorded by the Registrar, 
      notwithstanding the fact that the society had not followed the procedure 
      prescribed in sections 12 and 12A.”
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 
      16 of 1950, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 30-3-1950).]
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Provision for dissolution of societies and adjustment of their affairs.—Any 
    number not less than three-fifths of the members of any society may 
    determine that it shall be dissolved, and thereupon it shall be dissolved 
    forthwith, or at the time then agreed upon, and all necessary steps shall be 
    taken for the disposal and settlement of the property of the society, its 
    claims and liabilities, according to the rules of the said society 
    applicable thereto, if any, and if not, then as the governing body shall 
    find expedient, provided that, in the event of any dispute arising among the 
    said governing body or the members of the society, the adjustment of its 
    affairs shall be referred to the principal Court of original civil 
    jurisdiction of the district in which the chief building of the society is 
    situate; and the Court shall make such order in the matter as it shall deem 
    requisite. 
 
 

    Assent required.—Provided 
    that no society shall be dissolved unless three-fifths of the members shall 
    have expressed a wish for such dissolution by their votes delivered in 
    person, or by proxy, at a general meeting convened for the purpose:  
 

    Government consent.—Provided 
    that 

    1[whenever any 
    Government] is a member of, or a contributor to, or otherwise interested in 
    any society registered under this Act, such society shall not be dissolved
    

    2[without the consent 
    of the Government of the 

    3[State] of 
    registration.]  
 
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Assam</number>—In section 13—
 <subsection>
            <number>i</number>  after the 
      words “as the governing body” insert the words “or special committee 
      formed to replace the governing body in respect of all matters affecting 
      the winding up of the affairs of the society”.
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>ii</number>  after the 
      words “the said governing body” insert the words “should it not have been 
      replaced by the aforesaid special committee in respect of all matters 
      affecting the winding up of the society or the said special committee;”
 </subsection><subsection>
          <number>iii</number>  after section 
      13, insert the following as the first proviso—
 
                        
      “Provided that any matter decided by three-fifths of those present either 
      in person or by proxy at any meeting of the members of the society of the 
      governing body thereof or of any special Committee appointed at a general 
      meeting for the purpose of winding up of the affairs of a society shall 
      not be deemed to be a matter of dispute within the meaning of this 
      section.”
 
[Vide Assam Act 15 of 
      1948, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 20-10-1948).]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 13, for the words “chief building of the society” substitute the 
      words “registered office of the society”.
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975).]
 

Sections 
      13A and 13B
 
After section 13, insert 
      following new sections, namely:—
 
“13A. Power of Registrar to 
      apply for dissolution.—(1) Where in the opinion of Registrar, there 
      are reasonable grounds to believe in respect of a society registered under 
      this Act that any of the grounds mentioned in clauses (a) to (e) of 
      sub-section (1) of section 13B exists he shall send to the society, a 
      notice calling upon it to show cause within such time as may be specified 
      in the notice why the society be not dissolved.
 <subsubsection>
<number>2</number> if on or before the date 
      specified in the notice or within such extended period as the Registrar 
      may allow the society fails to show any cause or if the cause shown is 
      considered by the Registrar to be unsatisfactory, the Registrar, may move 
      the Court referred to in section 13 for making an order of the dissolution 
      of the society.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section>
 

 





 



</article><article>
<number>13B</number> Dissolution by Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      On the application of the Registrar under section 13A or under section 24 
      or on an application made by not less than one- tenth of the members of a 
      society registered under this Act, the Court referred to in section 13 may 
      make an order for the dissolution of the society on any of the following 
      grounds, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the society has 
      contravened any provision of this Act or of any other law for the time 
      being in force and it is just and equitable that the society should be 
      dissolved:
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the number of the 
      members of the society is reduced below seven;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that the society has 
      ceased to function for more than three years preceding the date of such 
      application;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that the society is 
      unable to pay its debts or meet its liabilities; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   that the registration of 
      the society has been cancelled under section 12D on the ground that its 
      activities or proposed activities have been or are or will be opposed to 
      public policy.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to the 
      provisions of sub-section (1) or of section 12D, the Court may on an 
      application of the District Magistrate in this behalf make an order for 
      the dissolution of a society on the ground that the activities of the 
      society constitute a public nuisance or are otherwise opposed to public 
      policy.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When an order for the 
      dissolution of a society is made under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), 
      all necessary steps for the disposal and the settlement of the property of 
      the society, its claims and liabilities and any other adjustment of its 
      affairs take place in manner as the Court may direct.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975).]
  
 
Comments
 
Section 15 of the 
      Societies Registration Act postulates that a person may resign from the 
      membership of the society. A member has to be served with notice before 
      expulsion and in the absence of notice the plaintiff would be deemed to be 
      a member of the society. He will not be entitled to vote at the meeting 
      until the up-to-date subscription has not been paid, he can therefore 
      bring suit in the court by virtue of section 13 of the Societies 
      Registration Act; Sarbjit Singh v. All India Fine Arts &amp; Crafts 
      Society, AIR 1990 NOC 26 Del. tc 
      "Section 15 of the Societies 
      Registration Act postulates that a person may resign from the membership 
      of the society. A member has to be served with notice before expulsion and 
      in the absence of notice the plaintiff would be deemed to be a member of 
      the society. He will not be entitled to vote at the meeting until the 
      up-to-date subscription has not been paid, he can therefore bring suit in 
      the court by virtue of section 13 of the Societies Registration Act; 
      Sarbjit Singh v. All India Fine Arts &amp; Crafts Society, AIR 1990 
      NOC 26 Del." 
 
The jurisdiction to 
      adjudicate disputes with respect to dissolution and adjustment of the 
      affairs of the society is vested in the principal Court of original 
      jurisdiction of the district where the society’s registration officers is 
      situated and the rest of the matters arising between the society and third 
      person are out of the purview of this section; M/s. Potti Swami &amp; Bros.
      v. Rao Saheb D. Govindarajulu, AIR 1960 AP 605.  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Upon a dissolution no member to receive profit.—If 
    upon the dissolution of any society registered under this Act there shall 
    remain, after the satisfaction of all its debts and liabilities, any 
    property whatsoever, the same shall not be paid to or distributed among the 
    members of the said society or any of them, but shall be given to some other 
    society, to be determined by the votes of not less than three-fifths of the 
    members present personally or by proxy at the time of the dissolution, or, 
    in default thereof, by such Court as aforesaid:  
 

    Clause not to apply to Joint-Stock Companies.—Provided, 
    however, that this clause shall not apply to any society which has been 
    founded or established by the contributions of share-holders in the nature 
    of a Joint-Stock Company.  
 
 

State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Assam</number>—In section 14, 
      after the words “some other society”, insert the words “whether registered 
      under this Act or not”.
 
[Vide Assam Act 15 of 
      1948, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 20-10-1948).]
 </section><section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as that 
      of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide Gujarat A.L.O. 
      1961 and Act 11 of 1960, sec. 83.]
 </section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—The 
      following is an amendment of section 14, namely:—
 
                   
      “Notwithstanding anything contained in section 14 of the Societies 
      Registration Act, 1860, hereinafter called ‘the said Act’, it shall be 
      lawful for the members of any society dissolved under section 13 of the 
      said Act to determine by a majority of the votes of the members present 
      personally or by proxy at the time of dissolution of such society that any 
      property whatsoever remaining after the satisfaction of all its debts and 
      liabilities shall be given to Government to be utilised for any of the 
      purposes referred to in section 1 of the said Act.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 2 of 
      1912, sec. 1 (w.e.f. 29-5-1912).]
 

Section 
      14A
 </section><section>
<number>Bihar</number>—After section 
      14, insert the following new section, namely:—
 
                   “14A. 
      Disposal of property of a dissolved society.—Notwithstanding anything 
      contained in section 14 it shall be lawful for the members of any society 
      dissolved under section 13 to determine by a majority of the votes of the 
      members present personally or by proxy at the time of the dissolution of 
      such society that any property whatsoever remaining after the satisfaction 
      of all the debts and liabilities shall be given to Government to be 
      utilised for any of the purposes referred to in section 1.”
 
[Vide Bihar Act 2 of 
      1960, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 8-2-1960).]
 

Section 
      14A
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—After 
      section 14, insert the following section, namely.—
 
                   “14A. 
      Disposal of property of a dissolved society.—Notwithstanding anything 
      contained in section 14, it shall be lawful for the members of any society 
      dissolved under section 13 to determine by a majority of the votes of the 
      members present personally or by proxy at the time of dissolution of such 
      society that any property whatsoever remaining after the satisfaction of 
      all its debts and liabilities shall be given to Government to be utilised 
      for any of the purposes referred to in section 1A.”
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 10-10-1979).]
 

Section 
      14A
 
Uttar Pradesh.—After 
      section 14, insert following section, namely:—
 
                   “14A. 
      Disposal of property of a dissolved society.—Notwithstanding anything 
      contained in section 14, it shall be lawful for the members of any society 
      dissolved under section 13 to determine by a majority of the votes of the 
      members present personally or by proxy at the time of the dissolution of 
      such society that any property whatsoever remaining after the satisfaction 
      of all the debts and liabilities shall be given to the Government to be 
      utilised for any of the purposes referred to in section 1.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975).]
  
 
Comments
 
Tax liability of the 
      society cannot be enforced against its members; Swami Satchitanand 
      v. 2nd Additional Income-tax Officer, AIR 1964 Ker 118.  
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Member defined.—For 
    the purposes of this Act a member of a society shall be a person who, having 
    been admitted therein according to the rules and regulations thereof, shall 
    have paid a subscription, or shall have signed the roll or list of members 
    thereof, and shall not have resigned in accordance with such rules and 
    regulations;  
 

    Disqualified members.—But 
    in all proceedings under this Act no person shall be entitled to vote or be 
    counted as a member whose subscription at the time shall have been in 
    arrears for a period exceeding three months.  
 
 

State Amendments
 
Uttar Pradesh.—Existing 
      section 15 of the principal Act shall be renumbered as sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> 
      thereof and after sub-section (1) so renumbered, the following sub-section 
      (2) shall be inserted:—
 
                   “(2) Every 
      society shall maintain a register of members giving such particulars as 
      may be prescribed.”
 
[Vide U.P. Act 11 of 
      1984, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 30-4-1984).]
  
 

      Comments
 
The Act does not 
      contemplate expulsion of any member from the society. The only provision 
      is that a member may resign from the membership of the society. Before any 
      such member is expelled from the society he must be served with a notice 
      in case he has failed to pay the subscription. Even if the subscription is 
      not paid for a period exceeding 3 months he still remains a member but 
      without right to vote. A suit be such a member against society is 
      maintainable; Sarabjit Singh v. All India Fine Arts and Crafts 
      Society, AIR 1990 NOC 26 (Del). tc 
      "The Act does not contemplate 
      expulsion of any member from the society. The only provision is that a 
      member may resign from the membership of the society. Before any such 
      member is expelled from the society he must be served with a notice in 
      case he has failed to pay the subscription. Even if the subscription is 
      not paid for a period exceeding 3 months he still remains a member but 
      without right to vote. A suit be such a member against society is 
      maintainable; Sarabjit Singh v. All India Fine Arts and Crafts 
      Society, AIR 1990 NOC 26 (Del)." 
 
Due to the fight between 
      two rival groups, for appointment of managing committee, the High Court 
      appointed a commissioner to hold valid annual general meeting for the very 
      purpose; Geong Apang v. Sanjoy Tassar, AIR 2001 Gau 1.  
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Governing body defined.—The 
    governing body of the society shall be the governors, council, directors, 
    committee, trustees or other body to whom by the rules and regulations of 
    the society the management of its affairs is entrusted.  
 
 

State Amendments
 

Section 
      16A
 
Uttar Pradesh.—After 
      section 16, insert the following section, namely:—
 
                   “16A. 
      Disqualification for holding office in society.—A person who is an 
      undischarged insolvent or who has been convicted of any offence in 
      connection with the formation, promotion, management or conduct of the 
      affairs of a society, or of a body corporate, or of an offence involving 
      moral turpitude shall be disqualified for chosen as and for being a member 
      of the governing body or the President, Secretary or any other 
      office-bearer of a society”.
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975).]


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>17</number> Registration of societies formed before 
      Act.—Any 
      company or society established for a literary, scientific or charitable 
      purpose, and registered under Act 43 of 1850*, or any such society 
      established and constituted previously to the passing of this Act but not 
      registered under the said Act 43 of 1850*, may at any time hereafter be 
      registered as a society under this Act;  
 Assent required.—Subject to the proviso that no 
      such company or society shall be registered under this Act unless an 
      assent to its being so registered has been given by three-fifths of the 
      members present personally, or by proxy, at some general meeting convened 
      for that purpose by the governing body.  
 In the case of a company or society registered under Act 43 of 
      1850*, the directors shall be deemed to be such governing 
      body.  
 In the case of a society not so registered, if no such body shall 
      have been constituted on the establishment of the society, it shall be 
      competent for the members thereof, upon due notice, to create for itself a 
      governing body to act for the society thenceforth.  
 
 State 
        Amendments
 <section><number>Bihar</number>—For section 17, substitute the following, 
        namely:—
                    
        “17. Registration of society formed under other Acts.—Any company or 
        society established for a literary, scientific or charitable purpose and 
        registered under the Indian Companies Act 1913 (VII of 1913), or under 
        the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) and not registered under this Act 
        may, at any time hereafter be registered as a society under this 
        Act:
                    
        Provided that no such company or society shall be registered under this 
        Act unless an assent to its being so registered has been given by 
        three-fifths of the members present there personally or by proxy, at 
        some general meeting convened for the purpose by governing 
        body.
                    
        In case of a company or society registered under the Indian Companies 
        Act, 1913 (VII of 1913), or the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the 
        directors of the said company or society, as the case may be, shall be 
        deemed to be such governing body.
                    
        In the case of a society not so registered, if no such body shall have 
        been constituted on the establishment of the society, it shall be 
        competent for the members thereof, upon due notice, to create for itself 
        a governing body to act for the society thenceforth.”
 [Vide 
        Bihar Act 2 of 1960, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 8-2-1960).]
 Goa, Daman 
        and Diu.—In section 17—
 <subsection><number>i</number>  for 
        the words and figures “Act 43 of 1850”, wherever they occur substitute 
        the words “the Registration of Societies Order”;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>  for 
        the words “passing of this Act” substitute the words “commencement of 
        this Act in this Union Territory”,
 [Vide Goa 
        Act 6 of 1979, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 </subsection></section><section><number>Gujarat</number>—Same as that of Maharashtra.
 [Vide 
        Gujarat A.L.O. 1961 and Act 11 of 1960, sec. 83.]
 </section><section><number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 17, for the words and 
        figures “passing of this Act but not registered under the said Act XLII 
        1850”, substitute the words and figures “commencement of this Act in the 
        relevant part of the State but not registered under Act XLIII of 1850 or 
        any law for registration of societies or companies in force immediately 
        before such commencement, as the case may be.”
 [Vide 
        Bombay Act 86 of 1956, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 7-10-1958).]
  </section>
  



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Such societies to file memorandum, etc., with Registrar of Joint-Stock 
    Companies.—In 
    order to any such society as is mentioned in the last preceding section 
    obtaining registry under this Act, it shall be sufficient that the governing 
    body file with the Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies 

    1[***] a memorandum 
    showing the name of the society, the objects of the society, and the names, 
    addresses and occupations of the governing body, together with a copy of the 
    rules and regulations of the society certified as provided in section 2, and 
    a copy of the report of the proceedings of the general meeting at which the 
    registration was resolved on.  
 
 

State Amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 18, for the words “the Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, 
      substitute the words “the Inspector-General”.
 
[Vide President Act 10 
      of 1954, sec. 3 (w.e.f 1-10-1954) as re-entered by Andhra Pradesh Act 6 of 
      1956 (w.r.e.f. 1-10-1954).]
 
Assam: Manipur: Tripura.—In 
      section 18, for the words “Registration of Joint-Stock Companies”, 
      substitute “Registrar of Societies,”
 
[Vide Assam Act 7 of 
      1957, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 17-7-1957) and G.S.Rs. 85 and 86 of 1960, published 
      in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3
<section><number>i</number>, pp. 145, 146.]
 <subsection>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 18, 
      for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the words 
      “Inspector-General of Registration”.
 
[Vide Bihar Act 19 of 
      1956, sec. 6 (w.r.e.f. 21-12-1955).]
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 18, for the words “the Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, insert 
      the words “the Inspector-General”.
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—Same as that 
      of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide Gujarat A.L.O. 
      1961 and Act 11 of 1960, sec. 83.]
 
Himachal Pradesh.—Same 
      as that of Punjab.
 
[Vide H.P. Act 23 of 
      1973, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 4-12-1973).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 
      18 (including the marginal note thereto) omit the words, “of Joint-Stock 
      Companies”.
 
[Vide Bombay Act 76 of 
      1958, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 7-10-1958).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—In section 18, 
      for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute the words 
      “Registrar of Societies”.
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 
      1958, sec 3 (w.e.f. 1-1-1961).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—(i) In 
      section 18, for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute 
      the words “Registrar of Companies”.
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 9 
      of 1969, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-1-1970).]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number> After section 18, insert 
      the following new section, namely:—
 
                   “18A. 
      Power of Registrar to refuse registration in certain cases.—(1) The 
      Registrar shall refuse to register—
 <subsection>
                   <number>a</number>   a 
      society under section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
                   <number>b</number>   the 
      change of names made under section 12A; or
 </subsection><subsection>
                    <number>c</number>   a 
      society under section 17;
 
             if the proposed 
      name of such society is undesirable or identical with that by which any 
      other existing society has been registered or in the opinion of the 
      Registrar so nearly resembles such other name as to be likely to deceive 
      the public or the members of either party.
 <subsubsection>
                   <number>2</number> If any 
      two or more societies which have been registered with identical names, or 
      with names, which in the opinion of the Registrar, so nearly resemble each 
      other as to be likely to deceive the public or the members of such 
      societies the society which was so registered first of all shall continue 
      to function under its original name and other such societies shall change 
      and may be required by the Registrar to change their name suitably within 
      a period of six months from the commencement of this Act.”
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 9 
      of 1969, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-1-1970).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh: 
      Delhi and Himachal Pradesh.—In its application to the State of Punjab 
      in section 18 omit the words “of Joint-Stock Companies”.
 
[Vide Punjab Act 31 of 
      1957, sec. 3 and G.S.Rs. 83 and 84 of 1960, published in the Gazette of 
      India, 1960, Pt. III, Sec. 3(i), pp. 144, 145.]
 
Tamil Nadu.—Same as 
      that of Andhra Pradesh.
 
[Vide T. N. Act 24 of 
      1954, sec. 2 (iv) (w.e.f. 1-1-1954).]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 18, for the words “Registrar of Joint-Stock Companies”, substitute 
      the word “Registrar”.
 
[Vide U.P. Act 25 of 
      1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 25-8-1958).]
</subsubsection></subsection></section>
 

 
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Inspection of documents.—Any 
    person may inspect all documents filed with the Registrar under this Act on 
    payment of a fee of one rupee for each inspection; and any person may 
    require a copy or extract of any document or any part of any document, to be 
    certified by the Registrar, on payment of two annas for every hundred words 
    of such copy or extract; and such certified copy shall be prima facie 
    evidence of the matters therein contained in all legal proceedings whatever.  
 
 

State Amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 19, for the words “the Registrar”, substitute the words “the 
      Inspector-General”.
 
[Vide President’s Act 
      10 of 1954, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-10-1954) as re-enacted by Andhra Pradesh Act 
      6 of 1956, sec. 4 and Sch. III (w.r.e.f. 1-10-1954).]
 
Assam: Manipur: Tripura.—In 
      its application to the State of Assam, in section 19, for the words “two 
      annas” in between the words “payment of” and “for every hundred” words, 
      substitute the words, “fifteen naye paise”.
 
[Vide Assam Act 11 of 
      1958, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-4-1958) and G.S.Rs. 85 and 86 of 1960, published in 
      the Gazette of India, 1960, Pt. II, Sec. 3
<section><number>i</number>, pp. 144, 145.]
 <subsection>
<number>Bihar</number>—In section 19, 
      for the words “Registrar” wherever it occurs, substitute the words 
      “Inspector-General of Registration”.
 
[Vide Bihar Act 19 of 
      1956, sec. 7 (w.r.e.f. 21-12-1955).]
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 19,—
 </subsection></section><section>
            <number>i</number>  for the words 
      “Any person may inspect,” substitute the words “Except as otherwise 
      provided by section 4A, any person may inspect;”
 </section><section>
           <number>ii</number>  for the words 
      “and any person may require a copy or extract of any document or any part 
      of any document, to be certified by the Registrar, on payment of two annas 
      for every hundred words of such copy or extract”, substitute the words “or 
      may require the Inspector-General to give him a certified copy or extract 
      of any document or any part thereof on payment of such fee as the 
      Government or any officer authorised by it may by notification in the 
      Official Gazette fix in that behalf”.
 
[Vide Goa Act 6 of 
      1979, sec. 13 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—(i) Same as 
      that of Maharashtra.
 
[Vide Bombay Act 76 of 
      1958; Gujarat A.L.O. 1961 and Act 11 of 1960, sec. 83.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number> In section 19, for the 
      words “Any person may inspect”, substitute the words, figure and letter 
      “Except as otherwise provided by section 4B, any person may inspect”.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 17 of 
      1978, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-4-1978).]
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
      section 19, for the words “two annas”, substitute the words “twenty-five 
      paise”.
 
[Vide H.P. Act 23 of 
      1973, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 4-12-1973).]
 <subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In section 
      19,—
 </subsection></section><section>
            <number>i</number>  for the words 
      “and any person may require a copy or extract of any document or any part 
      of any document to be certified by the Registrar on payment of two annas 
      for every hundred words of such copy or extract”, substitute the words “or 
      may require the Registrar to give him a certified copy or extract or any 
      document or any part thereof on payment of such fee as the State 
      Government or any officer authorised by it may by notification in the 
      Official Gazette fix in that behalf”.
 
[Vide Bombay Act 76 of 
      1958, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 7-10-1958).]
 </section><section>
           <number>ii</number>  for the words 
      “Any person may inspect” substitute the words, “Except as otherwise 
      provided by section 4A, any person may inspect”.
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 
      11 of 1968, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-10-1968).]
 <subsection>
<number>Orissa</number>—In section 19, 
      for the words “Registrar”, substitute the words “Registrar of Societies”.
 
[Vide Orissa Act 21 of 
      1958, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-1-1961).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Pondicherry</number>—In section 
      19, for the words “two annas”, substitute the words, “fifteen paise”.
 
[Vide Pondicherry Act 9 
      of 1969, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-1-1970).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh: 
      Delhi.—In its application to the State of Punjab, in section 19, for 
      the words “two annas”, substitute the words “twenty-five naye paise”.
 
[Vide Punjab Act 14 of 
      1961, sec. 2, Act 31 of 1966; G.S.Rs. 83 and 84, published in the Gazette 
      of India, 1960, Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), pp. 144, 145.]
 
Tamil Nadu.—In its 
      application to the State of Madras, in section 19,—
 </subsection></section><section>
            <number>i</number>  the amendment 
      made is the same as that of Andhra Pradesh.
 
[Vide Madras Act 24 of 
      1954, sec. 2(iii) (w.e.f. 1-9-1954).]
 </section><section>
           <number>ii</number>  for the words 
      “two and for every hundred words”, substitute the words “twenty-five naye 
      paise of every two hundred words or part thereof”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Act 9 
      of 1960, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 1-4-1961).]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 19,—
 </section><section>
            <number>i</number>  for the words 
      “on payment of a fee of one rupee for each inspection”, substitute the 
      words “on payment of such fee as the State Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, fix”; and
 </section><section>
           <number>ii</number>  for the words 
      “on payment of two annas for every hundred words of such copy or extract” 
      substitute the words “on payment of such fee as the State Government may, 
      by notification in the Official Gazette, fix”.
 
[Vide U.P. Act 52 of 
      1975, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 11-10-1975).]
</section>
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number> To what societies Act applies.—The following societies may be 
      registered under this Act:—  
 Charitable societies, the military orphan funds or societies 
      established at the several presidencies of India, societies established 
      for the promotion of science, literature, or the fine arts for 
      instruction, the diffusion of useful knowledge, 1[the diffusion of political 
      education], the foundation or maintenance of libraries or reading-rooms 
      for general use among the members or open to the public, or public museums 
      and galleries of paintings and other works of art, collections of natural 
      history, mechanical and philosophical inventions, instruments, or 
      designs.  
 
 State 
        Amendments
 <section><number>Bihar</number>—In 
        section 20, after the words “science, literature”, insert the words 
        “industry, agriculture”.
 [Vide 
        Bihar Act 2 of 1960, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 8-2-1960).]
 </section><section><number>Delhi</number>—In 
        section 20, for the words “promotion of science, literature, or the fine 
        arts”, substitute the words “promotion of social welfare, activities 
        conducive to the promotion and improvement of the natural environment 
        (including forests, rivers and wild life), compassion for living 
        creatures, literature, science, sports, games or the fine 
        arts”.
 [Vide Act 
        26 of 1983, sec. 2(c) (w.r.e.f. 22-6-1983).]
 </section><section><number>Haryana</number>—In section 20, for the words “instruments, 
        or designs”, substitute the words “instruments or designs, promotion of 
        the interest or welfare of the public and any other object as may be 
        notified by the Government as beneficial to the public”.
 [Vide 
        Haryana Act 23 of 1974, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 5-8-1974).]
 Himachal 
        Pradesh.—In section 20, after the words “established for the 
        promotion of” and before the word “science” the words “Khadi and Village 
        Industry, Rural Development”, be inserted.
 [Vide 
        H.P. Act 7 of 1992, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 10-4-1992).]
 </section><section><number>Maharashtra</number>—In its application to the whole of the 
        State of Bombay, section 29 shall be renumbered as sub-section (1) of 
        that section and after sub-section (1) so renumbered, the following 
        sub-section shall be added, namely:—
                    
        “(2) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), any society 
        registered under the Public Societies Registration Act for any public or 
        religious purpose and operating in the Hyderabad area of the State of 
        Bombay at the commencement of the Societies Registration (Bombay 
        Extension and Amendment) Act, 1958 shall be deemed to be and continue to 
        be registered under this Act”.
 [Vide 
        Bombay Act 76 of 1958, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 7-10-1958).]
 </section><section><number>Pondicherry</number>—In section 20, after the words 
        “instruments or designs” the words “the dissemination of social economic 
        education, promotion of the interest or welfare of the public or a 
        section of the public or of non-trading associations with objects 
        confined to the Union territory and any other objects as may be notified 
        by the Government as being beneficial to the public or to a section or 
        the public”, shall be inserted.
 [Vide 
        Pondicherry Act 9 of 1969, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-1-1970).]
 Uttar 
        Pradesh.—In section 20, after the words “established for the 
        promotion of” and before the word “science”, insert the words “Khadi and 
        Village Industry, Panchayat Industry, Rural Development”.
 [Vide 
        U.P. Act 11 of 1984, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 30-4-1984).]
 Andhra 
        Pradesh.—
 Sections 21 to 24
 <subsection><number>1</number> After 
        section 20, insert the following, namely:—
 “Chapter II
 Special 
        provisions in respect of Societies financed wholly or substantially 
        from the funds of the Government.
 </subsection></section>
  
  



 
</article><article><number>21</number> 
        Definitions.—In this Chapter,—
 <section><number>i</number>   
        ‘Government’ means State Government of Andhra Pradesh:
 </section><section><number>ii</number>   
        ‘society’ means a society either wholly or substantially financed from 
        out of the funds of the Government.
 </section></article><article><number>22</number> Chapter 
        to override other provisions of the Act.—The provisions of this 
        Chapter shall have effect notwithstanding anything contained in Chapter 
        I of this Act or any other law for the time being in force.
 </article><article><number>23</number> 
        Dissolution of society.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be competent for the 
        Government, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, to 
        dissolve a society with effect from such date as may be specified in the 
        order:
 Provided that 
        the Government shall before issuing an order dissolving a society, 
        communication to the governing body of the society the proposal to 
        dissolve, fix a reasonable time for the governing body for making a 
        representation against the proposal and consider its representation, if 
        any:
 Provided further 
        that the Government may, after settling the liabilities, if any, of the 
        dissolved society, make over its properties, whether movable or 
        immovable, to any other society having identical or similar objects, and 
        where there is no such society, the property shall vest in such officer 
        or authority, as may be specified by the Government in this behalf, 
        until a society having identical or similar object is formed where after 
        the properties shall stand transferred to such society.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On the date 
        fixed for the dissolution of a society under sub-section (1), the 
        registration of the society shall stand cancelled and the society shall 
        cease to exist as a corporate body.
 </section></article><article><number>24</number> Power to 
        divide or amalgamate societies.—
<section><number>1</number> Where in the opinion of the 
        Government it is necessary to divide a society or amalgamate two or more 
        societies, they may, by order and form a date fixed therein, direct the 
        division or amalgamation, as the case may be, and issue the necessary 
        certificates of registration:
 Provided that 
        the Government shall, before issuing an order either dividing a society 
        or amalgamating two or more societies, communicate to the governing body 
        or bodies concerned the proposal to divide or, as the case may be, to 
        amalgamate the society or societies, fix a reasonable time for the 
        governing body or bodies for making a representation against the 
        proposal and consider the representations, if any, received from the 
        body or bodies.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a 
        society is divided or where two or more societies are amalgamated, the 
        registration of the society or societies divided or, as the case may be, 
        amalgamated shall stand cancelled and the concerned society or societies 
        shall cease to exist as corporate bodies.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The order 
        referred to in sub-section (1) shall contain the particulars of 
        constitution, authorities, property, rights and interests, liabilities, 
        duties and obligations of the societies or society 
concerned.”
 [Vide AP 
        Act 12 of 1984, sec. 2(2) (w.r.e.f. 2-12-1983).]
 Assam: 
        Manipur: Tripura.—
 Sections 21 and 22
 In its 
        application to the State of Assam, after section 20 insert the following 
        new sections, namely:—
 “21. 
        Penalties.—(1) If the President, Secretary or any other person 
        authorised in this behalf by a resolution of the governing body of the 
        society fails to comply with the provisions of section 4, he shall, on 
        conviction be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred 
        rupees and in case of a continuing breach, shall also be punishable with 
        fine not exceeding fifty rupees for each day, during the period the 
        breach continues after first conviction for such offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any 
        person wilfully makes or causes to be made any false entry in, or any 
        omission from, the list required by section 4, or in or from any 
        statement or copy of rules or of alterations in rules sent to the 
        Registrar of Societies under section 4A, he shall, on conviction, be 
        punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.
 “22. 
        Procedure.—(1) No Court inferior to that of a Magistrate of the 
        First Class shall try an offence punishable under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No Court 
        shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act except 
        upon complaint made by the Registrar of Societies or any other person 
        authorised in writing by him in this behalf.”
 [Vide 
        Assam Act 11 of 1952, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 15-10-1952), Act 7 of 1957, sec. 2 
        (w.e.f. 17-7-1957); G.S.Rs. 83 and 84 of 1960, published in the Gazette 
        of India, Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), pp. 144, 145.]
 <subsection><number>Bihar</number>—
 Sections 21 to 24
 After section 
        20, insert the following sections, namely:—
 “21. Penalty 
        for non-compliance of section 4 or making a false entry.—(1) If the 
        President, Secretary or any person authorised in this behalf by a 
        resolution of the governing body of the society fails to comply with the 
        provisions of section 4, he shall be punished with fine which may extend 
        to five hundred rupees and to a further fine not exceeding fifty rupees 
        for each day during which the default is continued after conviction for 
        such offence.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> If any 
        person wilfully makes or causes to be made any false entry in or any 
        omission from the list required by section 4, or in or from any 
        statement or copy of rules or of alterations in rules sent to the 
        Inspector-General of Registration under section 4A, he shall be punished 
        with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.
 </section><section><number>22</number> Trial of 
        offences.—No Court inferior to that of a Magistrate of the first 
        class shall try any offence under this Act.”
 [Vide 
        Bihar Act IV of 1951, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 7-3-1951); Act 19 of 1956, sec. 8 
        (w.r.e.f. 21-12-1955).]
 After section 
        22, add the following sections, namely:—
 “23. 
        Cancellation of registration in certain cases.—(1) Notwithstanding 
        anything contained in this Act the Inspector-General of Registration 
        may, by order in writing, cancel the registration of any society 
        registered under this Act whose office has ceased to be in the State of 
        Bihar by reason of the reorganisation of States or change of the office 
        from the State of Bihar to another State or whose activities are 
        subversive to the objects of the society:
 Provided that 
        the Inspector-General of Registration shall, before passing an order, 
        make such inquiry as he consider necessary:
 Provided further 
        that no order of cancellation of registration of any society on the 
        ground of the activities of the society being subversive to the objects 
        of the society shall be passed until the society has been given a 
        reasonable opportunity of showing cause against action proposed to be 
        taken in regard to it.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An appeal 
        against an order made under sub-section (1) may be preferred in such 
        manner, within such time and to such authority, as may be prescribed, 
        and such authority shall consider and dispose of such appeals in the 
        prescribed manner.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The decision 
        of the appellate authority under sub-section (2) shall be 
        final.
 </section></article><article><number>24</number> Power of 
        the State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Government may 
        after previous publication make rules not inconsistent with the Act for 
        carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In 
        particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
        power, the State Government may make rules—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  
        prescribing the form of the Register of Societies and the mode in which 
        entries relating to registration are to be made therein, and the mode in 
        which such entries are to be amended or notices made therein;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  
        regulating the filing of documents received by the Inspector-General of 
        Registration;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  
        prescribing the authority before whom and the time within which an 
        appeal shall be preferred under sub-section (2) of section 23 and the 
        manner in which such appeal shall be considered and disposed 
        of;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  
        prescribing conditions for the inspection of original 
        documents;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>  
        regularising the grant of copies of documents; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>  
        providing for any other matter for which there is no provision or 
        insufficient provision in this Act and for which provision is, in the 
        opinion of the State Government, necessary for giving effect to the 
        purposes of this Act.”
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every rule 
        made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is 
        made, before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session 
        for a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one 
        session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the 
        session in which, it is so laid or the session immediately following 
        both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both the 
        Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall, 
        thereafter have effect, only in such modified from or be of no effect, 
        as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment 
        shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
        under that  rule.”
 [Vide 
        Bihar Act 2 of 1960, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 8-2-1960) and Act 12 of 1963, secs. 
        2, 3(w.e.f. 20-6-1963).]
 Goa, Daman 
        and Diu.—
 Section 21
 After section 
        20, insert the following section, namely:—
 </section><section><number>21</number> Powers to 
        make rules.—(1) The Government may, subject to the condition of 
        previous publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this 
        Act;
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every rule 
        made this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, 
        before the Legislative Assembly of Goa, Daman and Diu, while it is in 
        session for a total period of thirty days, which may be comprised in one 
        session or in two or more successive sessions and if before the expiry 
        of the sessions immediately following the session or the successive 
        sessions aforesaid, the Assembly agrees in making any modification in 
        any such rule or the Assembly agrees that the rule should not be made, 
        the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be 
        of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification 
        or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
        previously done under the rule.”
 [Vide Goa 
        Act 6 of 1979, sec. 14 (w.e.f. 18-10-1979).]
 <subsection><number>Gujarat</number>—
 Sections 21 to 24
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Section 21 
        is the same as in Maharashtra.
 [Vide Act 
        11 of 1960, sec. 83.]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Sections 22 
        and 23 are the same as sections 21 and 22 in Assam, respectively except 
        marginal note of section 22 of Assam Act.
 [Vide 
        Gujarat Act 14 of 1965, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-5-1966).]
 In section 23, 
        in sub-section (2), after the words “punishable under this Act”, insert 
        the words, figures and letter “other than an offence punishable under 
        section 11B”.
 After section 
        23, insert the following new section, namely:—
 “24. Power to 
        make rules.—(1) The State Government may by notification in the 
        Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this 
        Act.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In 
        particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
        provision, such rules may be made for all or any of the matters 
        expressly required or allowed by this Act to be prescribed by 
        rules.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The power to 
        make rules conferred by this section is subject to the condition of the 
        rules being made after previous publication.
 </section><section><number>4</number> All rules 
        made under this section shall be laid for not less than thirty days 
        before the State Legislature as soon as possible after they are made and 
        shall be subject to rescission by the State Legislature or to such 
        modification as the State Legislature may make during the session in 
        which they are so laid or the session immediately following.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any 
        recession or modification so made by the State Legislature shall be 
        published in the Official Gazette and shall thereupon take 
        effect.”
 [Vide 
        Gujarat Act 17 of 1978, secs. 13 and 14 respectively (w.e.f. 
        4-4-1979).]
 Himachal 
        Pradesh.—
 Section 21
 After section 
        20, insert new section 21, as follows:—
                    
        “21. Cognizance of offence.—No Court inferior to that of a 
        Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence under this Act, nor 
        shall cognizance of any such offence be taken except on a complaint in 
        writing by the Registrar or any person authorised by him in writing in 
        this behalf.”
 [Vide 
        H.P. Act 23 of 1973, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 4-12-1973).]
 <subsection><number>Maharashtra</number>—
 Sections 20A to 22
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> After 
        section 20, insert following new sections, namely:—
 “*[20A. 
        Definition of Special Society.—For the purposes of this Act, ‘a 
        special society’ means a society formed for the purposes of the 
        Maharashtra Educational Institutions (Transfer of Management) Act, 
        1971.
 *[20B.] Power 
        to modify Act in relation to special societies.—(1) The State 
        Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any 
        of the provisions of this Act specified in the notification—
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number>  shall 
        not apply to a special society; or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number>  shall 
        apply to the special society with such exceptions, modifications and 
        adaptations as may be specified in the notification.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> A copy of 
        every notification proposed to be issued under sub-section (1) shall be 
        laid in draft before both the Houses of the Legislature of the State for 
        a period of not less than thirty days while they are in session, and if 
        within that period, either House disapproves of the issue of the 
        notification or approves of such issue only with modifications, the 
        notification shall not be issued or, as the case may require, shall be 
        issued only with such modifications as may be agreed on by both the 
        Houses.
 *[Sections 21 
        and 22 were inserted by Maharashtra Act 49 of 1971, sec. 17 (w.e.f. 
        1-4-1973) and were renumbered as sections 20A and 20B by Maharashtra Act 
        11 of 1976, sec. 39 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 14-4-1993).]
 <subsection><number>ii</number> After 
        section 20, insert the following new section, namely:—
                    
        “21. Pending proceedings and construction of references to Registrar of 
        companies in instruments issued or made before 1st May, 1957 in Kutch, 
        Madhya Pradesh or Saurashtra area of Bombay State.—(1) All 
        proceedings under this Act in its application to the Kutch, Madhya 
        Pradesh and Saurashtra areas of the State of Bombay, pending before the 
        Registrar of Companies immediately before the 1st day of May, 1957, 
        shall stand transferred to the Registrar of Societies and any such 
        proceeding shall be continued and disposed of by such Registrar, as if 
        it had been originally instituted before him under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>                   
        <number>2</number> In all certificates of registration and in all rules or bye-laws of 
        societies and in other instruments issued or made under this Act before 
        the 1st day of May, 1957, references to the Registrar of Joint Stock 
        Companies or the Registrar of Companies shall be deemed to be and be 
        construed as reference to the Registrar of Societies.”
 [Vide 
        Societies Registration Act (Bombay Adaptation) Order, 1957 (w.e.f. 
        1-5-1957).]
 <subsection><number>iii</number> After 
        section 21, insert the following, namely:—
                    
        “22. Rules.—(1) The State Government may, subject to the condition 
        of previous publication, make rules for carrying out the purposes of 
        this Act.”
 </subsection></section><section>                   
        <number>2</number> Same as sub-section (3) of section 24 in Bihar infra.
 [Vide 
        Maharashtra Act 1 of 1968, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-10-1968).]
 <subsection><number>Pondicherry</number>—
 Sections 21 to 25
 After section 
        20, insert the following sections,—
 “21. 
        Inspection and Investigation.—(1) Every society shall be inspected 
        at least once in two years by the Registrar or an officer authorised by 
        him in this behalf who shall be entitled to inspect the premises of any 
        society and shall also be entitled to call for such information or 
        explanation within such time as may be specified.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where it 
        appears to the Registrar that the affairs of a society call for 
        investigation the Registrar may appoint a certified officer to 
        investigate the affairs of such society and may fix his remuneration 
        which shall be borne by the society.
 </section><section><number>22</number> Defunct 
        action.—Where default is made by a society in filing with the 
        Registrar any change in the Memorandum of Association (or in filing with 
        him the returns required by sections 4 and 4A), a Registrar may, after 
        calling upon such society to furnish details of such change (or to 
        submit such returns) within a specified time and on the failure of the 
        society to do so, treat the society as having become defunct (and cause 
        a notification of such decision to be published in the Official 
        Gazette), whereupon the incorporation of the society under this Act 
        shall cease:
 Provided that 
        the liability, if any, of the members of the governing body or members 
        of the society, as the case may be, shall continue and may be enforced 
        as if the society had not become defunct.
 </section><section><number>23</number> 
        Penalties.—If any person wilfully makes or causes to be made any 
        false entry in, or any omission from, the list required by section 4, or 
        in or from any statement of copy of rules or of alterations in rules 
        sent to the Registrar of Companies under section 4A, he shall, on 
        conviction, be punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand 
        rupees.
 </section></article><article><number>24</number> 
        Cognizance of offences.—No Court inferior to that of a Magistrate of 
        the first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act, nor 
        shall cognizance of any such offence be taken except on a complaint in 
        writing by the Registrar or any person authorised by him in writing in 
        this behalf.
 </article><article><number>25</number> Power to 
        make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Government may make rules for carrying out the 
        purposes of the Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In 
        particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
        power, such rules may prescribe—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  the 
        maintenance of the register of societies and other books, if any, by the 
        Registrar;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  the 
        forms under which the Registrar shall issue certificates of registration 
        of a society, change of name, etc;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  the 
        forms and notices under which every society shall intimate the Registrar 
        regarding the amendment to its memorandum or rules and regulations, 
        and;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>  any 
        other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> All rules 
        made under this Act shall, as soon as may be after the are made, be laid 
        before the Legislative Assembly, Pondicherry, while it is in session for 
        a total period of fourteen days which may be comprised in one session or 
        in two successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session in 
        which it is so laid or the session immediately following, the Assembly 
        makes any modification in the rule or decides that the rule should not 
        be made, the rules shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
        form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, however, that any such 
        modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
        anything previously done under that rule.”
 [Vide 
        Pondicherry Act 9 of 1969, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-1-1970).]
 Punjab: 
        Haryana: Chandigarh.—
 Section 21
 After section 
        20, insert the following new section, namely:—
                    
        “21. Cognizance of offence.—No Court inferior to that of a Judicial 
        Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence under this Act nor 
        shall cognizance of any such offence be taken except on a complaint in 
        writing by the Registrar or any person authorised by him in writing in 
        this behalf.”
 [Vide 
        East Punjab Act 6 of 1949, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 8-4-1949); Punjab Act 25 of 
        1964, sec. 2 and Sch., Pt. II (w.e.f. 2-10-1964) and Central Act 31 of 
        1966, sec. 89.]
 Uttar 
        Pradesh.—
 Sections 21 to 33
 For section 21, 
        substitute the following section, namely:—
                    
        “21. In this Act, the word “Registrar” means a person appointed as such 
        by the State Government, and includes any Additional Registrar, a Joint 
        Registrar, Deputy Registrar, or Assistant Registrar, on whom all or any 
        of the powers of the Registrar under this Act are conferred by general 
        or special order of the State Government.”
 [Vide 
        U.P. Act 26 of 1979, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 16-7-1979). Section 21 was 
        previously added by U.P. Act 25 of 1958, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
        25-8-1958).]
 <subsection><number>ii</number> After 
        section 21, insert following sections, namely:—
 “22. Power of 
        Registrar to call for information.—(1) The Registrar may, by written 
        order, require any society to furnish in writing such information or 
        document within such time, being ordinarily not less than two weeks from 
        the date of receipt of the order by the society, as he may specify in 
        the order in connection with the affairs of the society or any documents 
        filed by the society under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> On receipt 
        by the society of an order under sub-section (1), it shall be the duty 
        of the President, Secretary or any other person authorised in this 
        behalf to furnish such information or documents.
 </section><section><number>23</number> 
        Audit.—Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (2) of 
        section 4 or of section 22, where the Registrar is of opinion that it is 
        necessary or expedient so to do, he may, by written order, require any 
        society to furnish its accounts or a copy of a statement of receipts and 
        expenditure for any particular year duly audited by a Chartered 
        Accountant:
 Provided that 
        the Registrar may, at the request of society permit it to have such 
        accounts and statements audited by any other person approved by 
        him.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the 
        society fails to furnish the documents referred to in sub-section (1) 
        within the period specified in the order or within such extended period 
        as the Registrar may from time to time allow, the Registrar may cause 
        the accounts of such society audited for the said year and may recover 
        the cost of such audit from that society.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the 
        society neglects or refuses to make its accounts or other documents 
        available for audit under sub-section (2) or, in the opinion of the 
        Registrar, otherwise fails to provide requisite facilities to have the 
        audit made with due expedition, the Registrar may proceed to take action 
        under section 24.
 </section><section><number>24</number> 
        Investigation of affairs of a society.—(1) Where on information 
        received under section 22 or otherwise, or in circumstances referred to 
        in sub-section (3) of section 23, the Registrar is of opinion that there 
        is apprehension that the affairs of a society registered under this Act 
        are being so conducted as to defeat the objects of the society or that 
        the society or its governing body, by whatever name called, or any 
        officer thereof in actual effective control of the society is guilty of 
        mismanaging its affairs or of any breach of fiduciary or other like 
        obligations, the Registrar may, either himself or by any person 
        appointed by him in that behalf, inspect or investigate into the affairs 
        of the society or inspect any institution managed by the 
        society.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall be 
        the duty of every officer of the society when so required by the 
        Registrar or other person appointed under sub-section (1) to produce any 
        books of account and other records of or relating to the society which 
        are in his custody and to give him all assistance in connection with 
        such inspection or investigation.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The 
        Registrar or other person appointed under sub-section (1) may call upon 
        and examine on oath any officer, member or employee of the society in 
        relation to the affairs of the society and it shall be the duty of every 
        officer, member or employees, when called upon, to appear before him for 
        such examination.
 *[(3A) The 
        Registrar or other person appointed under sub-section (1), may, if in 
        this opinion it is necessary for the purpose of inspection or 
        investigation, seize any or all the records including account books of 
        the society:
 Provided that 
        any person from whose custody such records are seized shall be entitled 
        to make copies thereof in the presence of the person having the custody 
        of such records.]
 </section><section><number>4</number> On the 
        conclusion of the inspection or investigation, as the case may be, the 
        person if any appointed by the Registrar to inspect or investigate shall 
        make a report to the Registrar on the result of his inspection or 
        investigation.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The 
        Registrar may, after such inspection or investigation, give such 
        directions to the society or to its governing body or any officer 
        thereof, as he may think fit, for the removal of any defects or 
        irregularities, within which as may be specified and in the event of 
        default in taking action according to such directions, the Registrar may 
        proceed to take action under section 12D or section 13B, as the case may 
        be.
 [*Ins. by U.P. 
        Act 11 of 1984, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 30-4-1984).]
 </section></article><article><number>25</number> Dispute 
        regarding election of office-bearers.—
<section><number>1</number> The prescribed authority 
        may, on a reference made to it by the Registrar or by at least 
        one-fourth of the members of a society registered in Uttar Pradesh, hear 
        and decide in a summary manner any doubt or dispute in respect of the 
        election or continuance in office of an office-bearers of such society, 
        and may pass such orders in respect thereof as it deems fit:
 †[Provided that 
        the election of an office-bearer shall be set aside where the prescribed 
        authority is satisfied—
 <subsection><number>a</number>  that 
        any corrupt practice has been committed by such office-bearer; 
        or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>  that 
        the nomination of any candidate has been improperly rejected; 
        or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>  that 
        the result of the election in so far as it concerns such office-bearer 
        has been materially affected by the improper acceptance of any 
        nomination or by the improper reception, refusal or rejection of any 
        vote or the reception of any vote which is void or by any non-compliance 
        with the provisions of any rules of the Society.
 Explanation.—A person shall be deemed to have 
        committed a corrupt practice who, directly or indirectly, by himself or 
        by any other person—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>  
        induces, or attempts to induce, by fraud, international 
        misrepresentation, coercion or threat of injury, any elector to give or 
        to refrain from giving a vote in favour of any candidate, or any person 
        to stand or not to stand as, or to withdraw or not to withdraw from 
        being, a candidate at the election;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>  with 
        a view to inducing any elector to give or refrain from giving a vote in 
        favour of any candidate, or to inducing any person to stand or not to 
        stand as, or to withdraw or not to withdraw from being a candidate at 
        the election, offers or gives any money, or valuable consideration, or 
        any place or employment, or holds out any promise of individual 
        advantage or profit to any person;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number>  
        abets (within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code) the doing of any of 
        the acts specified in clauses (i) and (ii);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number>  
        induces or attempts to induce a candidate or elector to believe that he 
        or any person in whom he is interested will become or will be rendered 
        an object of divine displeasure or spiritual censure;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number>  
        canvasses on grounds of caste, community, sect or religion;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>vi</number>  
        commits such other practice as the State Government may prescribe to be 
        a corrupt practice.
 Explanation 
        II.—A promise of individual advantage or profit to a person includes 
        a promise for the benefit of the person himself or of any one in whom he 
        is interested.
 Explanation 
        III.—The State Government may prescribe the procedure for hearing 
        and decision of doubts or disputes in respect of such elections and make 
        provision in respect of any other matter relating to such elections for 
        which insufficient provision exists in this Act or in the rules of the 
        society.]
 [†Ins. by U.P. 
        Act 13 of 1978, sec. 4 (w.r.e.f. 27-2-1978).]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Where by an 
        order made under sub-section (1), an election is set aside or an 
        office-bearer is held no longer entitled to continue in office or where 
        the Registrar is satisfied that any election of office-bearers of a 
        society has not been held within the time specified in the rules of that 
        society, he may call a meeting of the general body of such society for 
        electing such office-bearer or office-bearers, and such meeting shall be 
        presided over and be conducted by the Registrar or by any officer 
        authorised by him in this behalf, and the provisions in the rules of the 
        society relating to meetings and elections shall apply to such meeting 
        and election with necessary modifications.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a 
        meeting is called by the Registrar under sub-section (2), no other 
        meeting shall be called for the purpose of election by any other 
        authority or by any person claiming to be an office-bearer of the 
        society.
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this section, the 
        expression ‘prescribed authority’ means an officer or court authorised 
        in this behalf by the State Government by notification published in the 
        Official Gazette.”
 </section></article><article><number>26</number> Terms of 
        gift to be observed.—Where a society accepts a gift or donation of 
        money or property of any other kind from any person for a specific 
        purpose, it shall not use the money or other property gifted or donated 
        or any part thereof for any other purpose without the written consent of 
        the Registrar who shall refuse such consent except when he is satisfied 
        that the purpose for which the gift was made is incapable of execution 
        by the society.
 </article><article><number>27</number> 
        Penalties.—Any person who—
 *[
<section><number>a</number>  
        fails to furnish the list of managing body or other information required 
        to be furnished under section 4 or 4 A or wilfully makes or causes to be 
        made a false entry in, or any omission from, the list or any statement 
        or copy or rules or of alteration in rules or other information sent to 
        the Registrar under the said section 4 or section 4A.] 
 </section><section><number>b</number>  
        wilfully fails to furnish any account or statement referred to in 
        sub-section (1) of section 23 or furnishes in compliance with the said 
        sub-section particulars which are false and which he either knows or 
        believes to be false or does not believe to be true;
 </section><section><number>c</number>  
        neglects or refuses to make its accounts or other documents available 
        for audit as required by sub-section (3) of section 23;
 </section><section><number>d</number>  
        wilfully fails to produce any books of accounts or other records as 
        required by sub-section (2) of section 24;
 </section><section><number>e</number>  
        wilfully fails to appear before the Registrar or other person appointed 
        by him or otherwise contravenes the provisions of sub-section (3) of 
        section 24;
 shall be 
        punishable with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.
 [* Subs. by U.P. 
        Act 11 of 1984 (w.e.f. 30-4-1984).
 </section></article><article><number>28</number> 
        Procedure.—No Court inferior to that of a Magistrate of the first 
        class shall try an offence punishable under this Act nor shall 
        cognizance of any such offence be taken except on a complaint made by 
        the Registrar or any other person authorised in writing by him by 
        general or special order in that behalf. 
 </article><article><number>29</number> 
        Compounding of offences.—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar may accept from any 
        person against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has committed 
        any offence punishable under section 27 or against whom a prosecution 
        under that section has been instituted, a sum of money by way of 
        composition fee for the offence which such person is suspected or 
        accused to have committed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> On the 
        payment of such composition fee the suspected person if in custody, 
        shall be discharged and no further proceeding shall be taken against 
        him, and if prosecution of such person had been instituted, the 
        composition shall have the effect of his acquittal.
 </section></article><article><number>30</number> Manner of 
        payment of fees.—Fees payable under the provisions of this Act shall 
        be paid in such manner as may be prescribed by rules.
 </article><article><number>31</number> 
        Indemnity.—No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie 
        in any Court against the State Government, the Registrar or against any 
        person appointed for inspection or investigation under section 24, for 
        anything in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or the 
        rules made thereunder.
 </article><article><number>32</number> Mode of 
        service of notice, etc. by Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> Any notice, order or 
        requisition meant for a society or for the governing body thereof to be 
        issued by the Registrar may be served on the Secretary of the Society 
        and service on the Secretary be as effectual as if the same had been 
        served on every member of the society or, as the case may be, on every 
        member of the governing body thereof, unless the Registrar otherwise 
        directs.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The sending 
        of such notice, order or requisition to the Secretary of the society by 
        registered post at its registered office shall amount to sufficient 
        service thereof on the society.
 </section></article><article><number>33</number> Power to 
        make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The State Government may, by notification in the 
        Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this 
        Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All rules 
        made under this Act shall, as soon as may be, after they are made, be 
        laid before each House of the State Legislature while it is in session, 
        for a total period of thirty days extending in its one session or more 
        that one successive sessions and shall unless some later date is 
        appointed, take effect from the date of their publication in the 
        Official Gazette, subject to such modifications or annulments as the two 
        Houses of the Legislature may, during the said period agree to make, so 
        however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
        prejudice to validity of anything previously done thereunder.
 [Vide 
        U.P. Act 52 of 1975, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 10-10-1975).]</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>