<act><title>

The 
    Prevention of Cruelty to Animals 
    (Licensing of Farriers) Rules, 19651</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Licensing of 
    Farriers) Rules, 1965. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force in any State on such date as the State Government may, by 
    notification in the official Gazette, appoint, and different dates may be 
    appointed for different areas of the State.  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “cattle” means buffaloes, bullocks, 
    horses, mules or donkeys and includes other animals used for draught, pack 
    or carriage purpose, which require shoeing;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “farrier” means a person who carries on 
    the business of shoeing cattle;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “licence” means a licence granted under 
    these rules;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “licensing authority” means such 
    officer of the veterinary department of the State or a local authority or 
    any organisation for the welfare of animals as the State Government may, by 
    general or special order, specify in this behalf.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Farriers 
    to be licensed.—No person shall, 
    after the commencement of these rules, begin to carry on the business of a 
    farrier, and no person carrying on the business of a farrier at the 
    commencement of these rules, shall, after the expiration of three months 
    from such commencement, continue to carry on such business, except under a 
    licence.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Farriers 
    to be licensed.—No person shall, 
    after the commencement of these rules, begin to carry on the business of a 
    farrier, and no person carrying on the business of a farrier at the 
    commencement of these rules, shall, after the expiration of three months 
    from such commencement, continue to carry on such business, except under a 
    licence.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Persons 
    entitled to apply for licence.—Every 
    person who—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    has completed the age of eighteen 
    years; and  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    has undergone any such training in the 
    business of showing cattle as may be approved by the licensing authority; or  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    has been carrying on the business of 
    a farrier for not less than two years before the commencement of these 
    rules;  
 
shall be entitled to a licence.
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Application for licence.—Every 
    person who at the commencement of these rules is carrying on the business of 
    a farrier and who intends to carry on such business after such commencement 
    and every person who intends to begin such business after such commencement 
    shall apply in writing to the licensing authority for a licence giving his 
    name, place of residence, place of business, his qualifications for the 
    licence and such other particulars as the licensing authority may require.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Grant of 
    licence.—The licensing authority 
    shall after satisfying himself as to whether the applicant is a fit and 
    proper person to be granted a licence and whether he has equipped himself or 
    has made arrangements for equipping himself with proper tools and other 
    implements for the purpose of his business, grant to every applicant who is 
    duly qualified in this behalf a licence in the form prescribed in the 
    Annexure to these rules.  
 

    Explanation.—The tools and other 
    implements which a person carrying on or intending to carry on the business 
    of a farrier shall ordinarily have in his possession the following, namely:—  
 <section>
       <number>1</number>   Driving hammer with claws.  
 </section><section>
       <number>2</number>   Hand hammer.  
 </section><section>
       <number>3</number>   Drawing knife.  
 </section><section>
       <number>4</number>   Scorcher knife.  
 </section><section>
       <number>5</number>   Pincers.  
 </section></article><article>
       <number>6</number>   Buffer.  
 </article><article>
       <number>7</number>   Rasp.  
 </article><article>
       <number>8</number>   Chisel for cutting bar iron.  
 </article><article>
       <number>9</number>   Punch for making nail holes.  
 </article><article>
     <number>10</number>   Nails for shoeing.  
 </article><article>
     <number>11</number>   Twitch.  
 </article><article>
     <number>12</number>   Wooden plank for finishing work  
 </article><article>
     <number>13</number>   Iron anvil.  
 </article><article>
     <number>14</number>   Good quality wrought iron for 
    shoes.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Term of 
    licence and renewal thereof.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A licence shall be valid for a period of two years from the date of its 
    grant, but it may be renewed from time to time on application made by the 
    licensee stating the period from which the licence is to be renewed:  
 
Provided that 
    no licence shall be renewed for a period exceeding two years at a time.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    renewal of a licence shall be made by inscribing, in the columns provided 
    for the purpose in the licence, the date of renewal, the date of expiry of 
    the renewed licence and the signature of the licensing authority.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Issue of 
    duplicate licence.—If a licence 
    is defaced, lost or destroyed, the licensing authority may after making such 
    inquiry into the matter as he thinks fit, issue a duplicate licence.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Farriers 
    to exercise reasonable care and skill.—Every 
    licensee under these rules shall exercise a reasonable degree of care and 
    skill in the shoeing of cattle.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Cancellation of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> It 
    shall be lawful for the licensing authority to enter the place of business 
    of any licensee during normal working hours for the purpose of inspection; 
    and if, in the opinion of the licensing authority the licensee is unable to 
    exercise a reasonable degree of care and skill in the shoeing of cattle or 
    is not properly equiped for the purposes of his business, he may, after 
    giving the licensee a reasonable opportunity of being heard, cancel the 
    licence.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A licence 
    may also be cancelled if the licensing authority is satisfied, after giving 
    the licensee a reasonable opportunity of being heard, that there has been a 
    breach of any of the conditions of the licence.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>10A</number> An appeal shall lie 
      from any order refusing or cancelling in licence under these rules to such 
      authority as the State Government may, by notification in the official 
      Gazette, specify for the purpose.]  
  








 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Issue 
    of fresh licence after cancellation.—A 
    person whose licence has been cancelled under rule 10 may be granted a fresh 
    licence on application made in this behalf if the licensing authority is 
    satisfied that having regard to the circumstances obtaining at the time of 
    such application, there is no reason why the applicant should not be granted 
    a fresh licence.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The fees payable on every application for a licence shall be one rupee and 
    that on every application for renewal of the licence or for a duplicate 
    thereof shall be fifty paise.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such fees 
    may be paid either in cash or by affixing non-judicial stamps of equivalent 
    value to the application.  
 
 
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Maintenance of register.—The 
    licensing authority shall maintain a register containing full particulars 
    relating to every licence.  
  
 
Farrier’s Licence
 
Licence No.........................
 <section>
             <number>1</number>  Name of Licensee
 </section><section>
             <number>2</number>  Place of residence and full 
    postal address
 </section><section>
             <number>3</number>  Place of business
 </section><section>
             <number>4</number>  Duration of licence
 
From .................................... to 
    .................................
  
 
CONDITIONS OF LICENCE
 </section><section>
<number>1</number> This licence is valid for two years only 
    from the date of its grant, unless renewed, on application made under rule 7 
    of the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals (Licensing of Farriers) Rules, 1965, 
    within one month before the date of expiry of the original or earlier 
    licence.
 

1[(2) 
    During the continuance of the licence, the licensee shall be bound to 
    produce for inspection during normal working hours and at his place of 
    business all the tools and other implements in his possession and kept for 
    the purpose of his business if a demand for the production of the same is 
    made by the licensing authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The licensee shall afford all reasonable 
    facilities for the purpose of enabling the licensing authority to inspect 
    the place of business of the licensee and the manner in which he is carrying 
    on his business.
  
 
RENEWAL ENDORSEMENT
 
 
 Date of 
        Renewal
 Date of 
        Expiry
 Signature 
        of Licensing Authority
 Remarks

 
 1
 2
 3
 4

 
    
  
  
  
  


  
  







 


 
  
  
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>