<act><title>

The
Prevention of Blackmarketing And Maintenance of supplies of essential
commodities Act, 1980</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Prevention of Blackmarketing and Maintenance of
Supplies of Essential Commodities Act, 1980.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall be deemed to have come into
force on the 5th day of October, 1979.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the
context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number> “appropriate Government” means, as respects a detention order made by
the Central Government or by an officer of the Central Government or person
detained under such order, the Central Government, and as respects a detention
order made by a State Government or by an officer of a State Government or as 
respects a person detained under such order, the State Government;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
“detention order” means an order made under section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
“State Government”, in relation to a Union Territory, means the
administrator thereof.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Power to make orders detaining certain persons.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government or a State
Government or any officer of the Central Government, not below the rank of a
Joint Secretary to that Government specially empowered for the purposes of this
section by that Government, or any officer of a State Government, not below the
rank of a Secretary to that Government specially empowered for the purposes of
this section by that Government, may, if satisfied, with respect to any person
that with a view to preventing him from acting in any manner prejudicial to the
maintenance of supplies of the commodities essential to the community it is
necessary so to do, make an order directing that such person be detained.
 Explanation.—For
the purposes of this sub-section, the expression “acting in any manner
prejudicial to the maintenance of supplies of commodities essential to the
community” means—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
committing or instigating any person to commit any offence punishable
under the Essential Commodities Act, 1955 (10 of 1955) or under any other law
for the time being in force relating to the control of the production, supply or
distribution of, or trade and commerce in, any commodity essential to the
community; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
dealing in any commodity—
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> which
is an essential commodity as defined in the Essential Commodities Act, 1955 (10
of 1955), or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> with
respect to which provisions have been made in any such other law as is referred
to in clause (a),
 with
a view to making gain in any manner which may directly or indirectly defeat or
tend to defeat the provisions of that Act or other law aforesaid.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Any of the following officers, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
District Magistrates;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
Commissioners of Police, wherever they have been appointed,
 may
also if satisfied as provided in sub-section (1), exercise the powers conferred
by the said sub-section.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
When any order is made under this section by an officer mentioned in sub-section
(2) he shall forthwith report the fact to the State Government to which he is
subordinate together with the grounds on which the order has been made and such
other particulars as in his opinion have a bearing on the matter, and no such
order shall remain in force for more than twelve days after the making thereof
unless in the meantime it has been approved by the State Government:
 Provided
that where under section 8 the grounds of detention are communicated
by the authority making the order after five days but not later than ten
days from the date of detention, this sub-section shall apply subject to the
modification that for the words “twelve days”, the words “fifteen days”
shall be substituted.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
When any order is made or approved by the State Government under this section or
when any order is made under this section by an officer of the State Government
not below the rank of Secretary to that Government specially empowered under
sub-section (1) the State Government shall, within seven days, report
the fact to the Central Government together with the grounds on which the
order has been made and such other particulars as, in the opinion of the State
Government, have a bearing on the necessity for the order.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Execution of detention orders.—A
detention order may be executed at any place in India in the manner
provided for the execution of warrants of arrest under the Code of
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Power to regulate place and conditions of detention.—Every
person in respect of whom a detention order has been made shall be liable—
 <section><number>a</number>
to be detained in such place and under such conditions, including
conditions as to maintenance, discipline and punishment for breaches of 
discipline, as the appropriate Government may, by general or special order, 
specify; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
to be removed from one place of detention to another place of detention, 
whether within the same State or in another State, by order of the appropriate 
Government:
 Provided
that no order shall be made by a State Government under clause (b) for the
removal of a person from one State to another State except with the consent of
the Government of that other State. 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Detention orders not to be invalid or in-operative on certain grounds.—No
detention order shall be invalid or inoperative merely by reason—
 <section><number>a</number>
that the person to be detained thereunder is outside the limits of the
territorial jurisdiction of the Government or officer making the order, or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
that the place of detention of such person is outside the said limits.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Powers in relation to absconding persons.—
<section><number>1</number>
If <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[the
appropriate Government or an officer mentioned in sub-section (2) of section 3,
as the case may be,] has reason to believe that a person in respect of whom a
detention order has been made has absconded or is concealing himself so that the
order cannot be executed, that Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[or
officer] may—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
make a report in writing of the fact to a Metropolitan Magistrate or a
Judicial Magistrate of the First Class having jurisdiction in the place where
the said person ordinarily resides; and thereupon the provisions of sections 82,
83, 84 and 85 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), shall apply
in respect of the said person and his property as if the order directing that he
be detained were a warrant issued by the Magistrate;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
by order notified in the Official Gazette
direct the said person to appear before such officer, at such place and within
such period as may be specified in the order; and if the said person fails to
comply with such direction he shall, unless he proves that it was not possible
for him to comply therewith and that he had, within the period specified in the
order, informed the officer mentioned in the order, of the reason which rendered
compliance therewith impossible and of his whereabouts, be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year or with fine or with both.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of
1974), every offence under clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall be cognizable.
   


  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Grounds of order of detention to be disclosed to person affected by the order.—
<section><number>1</number>
When a person is detained in pursuance of a detention order, the authority
making the order shall, as soon as may be, but ordinarily not later than five
days and in exceptional circumstances and for reasons to be recorded in writing,
not later than ten days from the date of detention, communicate to him the
grounds on which the order has been made and shall afford him the earliest
opportunity of making a representation against the order to the appropriate
Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Nothing in sub-section (1) shall require the authority to disclose facts which
it considers to be against the public interest to disclose.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>9</number>
Constitution of Advisory Boards.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Central Government and each State Government shall, whenever necessary,
constitute one or more Advisory Boards for the purposes of this Act.
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[2
Every such Board shall consist of three persons who are, or have been or are
qualified to be appointed as, Judges of a
High Court, and such persons shall be appointed by the appropriate Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The appropriate Government shall appoint one of the members of the Advisory
Board who is, or has been, a Judge of a High Court to be its Chairman, and in
the case of a Union Territory, the appointment to the Advisory Board of any
person who is a Judge of the High Court of a State shall be with the previous
approval of the State Government concerned.]
  
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>10</number>
Reference to Advisory Boards.—Save
as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, in every case where a detention
order has been made under this Act, the appropriate Government shall, within
three weeks from the date of detention of a person under the order, place before
the Advisory Board constituted by it under section 9, the grounds on which the
order has been made and the representation, if any, made by the person affected
by the order and in case where the order has been made by an officer referred to
in sub-section (2) of section 3, also the report by such officer under
sub-section (3), of that 
section.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>11</number>
Procedure of Advisory Boards.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Advisory Board shall, after considering the materials placed before it and,
after calling for such further information as it may deem necessary from the
appropriate Government or from any person called for the purpose through the
appropriate Government or from the person concerned, and if, in any particular
case, it considers it essential so to do or if the person concerned desires to
be heard, after hearing him in person, submit its report to the appropriate
Government within seven weeks from the date of detention of the person
concerned.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The report of Advisory Board shall specify in separate part thereof the opinion
of the Advisory Board as to whether or not there is sufficient cause for the
detention of the person concerned.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
When there is a difference of opinion among the members forming the Advisory
Board, the opinion of the majority of such
members shall be deemed to be the opinion of the Board.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
Nothing in this section shall entitle any person against whom a detention order
has been made to appear by any legal practitioner in any matter connected with
the reference to the Advisory Board, and the proceedings of the Advisory Board,
and its report, excepting that part of the report in which the opinion of the
Advisory Board is specified, shall be confidential.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number> Action upon the report of Advisory 
      Board.—
<section><number>1</number> In any case where 
      the Advisory Board has reported that there is, in its opinion, sufficient 
      cause for the detention of a person, the appropriate Government may 
      confirm the detention order and continue the detention of the concerned 
      for such period as it thinks fit.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In any case where the Advisory Board has 
      reported that there is, in its opinion, no sufficient cause for the 
      detention of the person concerned, the appropriate Government shall revoke 
      the detention order and cause the person to be released forthwith.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>13</number>
Maximum period of detention.—
<section><number>1</number> The
maximum period for which any person may be detained in pursuance of any
detention order which has been confirmed under section 12, shall be six months
from the date of detention:
 Provided
that nothing contained in this section shall affect the power of the appropriate
Government to revoke or modify the detention order at any earlier time.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>14</number>
Revocation of detention orders.—
<section><number>1</number>
Without prejudice to the provisions of section 21 of the General Clauses Act,
1897 (10 of 1897), a detention order may, at any time, be revoked or modified—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> notwithstanding that the order has been made by an officer of the State
Government, by that State Government or by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> notwithstanding that the order has been made by an officer of the Central
Government or by a State Government, by the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The revocation or expiry of a detention order shall not bar the making of a
fresh detention order under section 3 against the same person in any case where
fresh facts have arisen after the date of revocation or expiry on which the
Central Government or a State Government or an officer, as the case may be, is
satisfied that such an order should be made.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>15</number>
Temporary release of persons detained.—
<section><number>1</number>
The appropriate Government may, at any time, direct that any person detained in
pursuance of a detention order may be released for any specified period either
without conditions or upon such conditions specified in the direction as the
person accepts, and may, at any time, cancel his release.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
In directing the release of any person under sub-section (1), the appropriate
Government may require him to enter into a bond with or without sureties for the
due observance of the conditions specified in the direction.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Any person released under sub-section (1) shall surrender himself at the time
and place, and to the authority, specified in the order directing his release or
cancelling his release, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
If any person fails without
sufficient cause to surrender himself in the manner specified in sub-section
(3), he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two
years or with fine, or with both.
 </section><section><number>5</number>
If any person released under
sub-section (1) fails to fulfil any of the conditions imposed upon him under the
said sub-section or in the bond entered into by him, the bond shall be declared
to be forfeited and any person bound thereby shall be liable to pay the penalty
thereof.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>16</number>
Protection of action taken in good faith.—No
suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or a
State Government, and no suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie
against any person, for any thing in good faith done or intended to be done in
pursuance of this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>17</number>
Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Prevention of Blackmarketing and Maintenance of Supplies of Essential
Commodities Ordinance, 1979 (10 of 1979), is hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Notwithstanding such repeal anything done or any action taken under the
Ordinance so repealed shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the
corresponding provisions of this Act.

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by Act 27 of 1982, sec. 2, for "appropirate Government" (w.e.f.
5-8-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Ins. by Act 27 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 5-8-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 19 of 1981, sec. 2, for sub-sections (2) and
(3) (w.e.f. 2-9-1981).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>