<act><tid>1702728</tid>
<title>THE SCHEDULED CASTES AND SCHEDULED TRIBES ORDERS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 7th January, <year>2003</year>]

An Act to provide for the inclusion in the lists of Scheduled Tribes, 
of certain tribes or tribal communities or parts of or groups within 
tribes or tribal communities, equivalent names or synonyms of such 
tribes or communities, removal of area restricti ns and bifurcation 
and clubbing of entries; imposition of area restriction in respect of 
certain castes in the lists of Scheduled Castes, and the exclusion of 
certain castes and tribes from the lists of Scheduled Castes and 
Scheduled Tribes, in relation o the States of Andhra Pradesh, 
Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Bihar, Goa, Gujarat, Himachal Pradesh, 
Jharkhand, Karnataka, Kerala, Madhya Pradesh, Maharashtra, Manipur, 
Mizoram, Orissa, Sikkim, Tamil Nadu, Tripura, Uttar Pradesh and West 
Bengal.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1795486</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Scheduled Castes and 
Scheduled Tribes Orders (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1317266</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1437031</tid>
<number>a</number>" Scheduled Castes Order" means the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) 
Order, <year>1950</year>, made by the President under article 341 of the 
Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>949264</tid>
<number>b</number>" Scheduled Tribes Orders" means the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>, the Constitution (Uttar Pradesh) Scheduled Tribes 
Order, <year>1967</year> and the Constitution (Sikkim) Scheduled Tribes Order, <year>1978</year>, 
made by the President under article 342 of the C nstitution.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1591954</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of Scheduled Castes Order.- The Scheduled Castes Order is 
hereby amended in the manner and to the extent specified in the First 
Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>382096</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of Scheduled Tribes Orders.- The Scheduled Tribes Orders 
are hereby amended in the manner and to the extent specified in the 
Second Schedule.

</article>



 </act>