<act><tid>1715987</tid>
<title>THE LEGAL SERVICES AUTHORITIES (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 37 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 11th June, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Legal Services Authorities Act, <year>1987</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>259077</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Legal Services Authorities 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>199433</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 11A.- In the Legal Services Authorities Act, 
 <year>1987</year> (39 of <year>1987</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in 
section 11A, in sub- section (2), in clause (a), for the words" senior 
Civil Judge", the words" senior- most Judicial O ficer" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>73718</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 22.- In section 22 of the principal Act, for 
the words" Lok Adalat", wherever they occur, the words" Lok Adalat or 
Permanent Lok Adalat" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1369355</tid>
<number>4</number>Insertion of new Chapter VIA.- After Chapter VI of the principal 
Act, the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
' CHAPTER VIA

PRE- LITIGATION CONCILIATION AND SETTLEMENT

</article>



<article><tid>1603124</tid>
<number> 22A</number> Definitions.- In this Chapter and for the purposes of sections 22 
and 23, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1205175</tid>
<number>a</number>" Permanent Lok Adalat" means a Permanent Lok Adalat established 
under sub- section (1) of section 22B;

</section>

<section><tid>1014787</tid>
<number>b</number>" public utility service" means any-

<subsection><tid>781993</tid>
<number>i</number>transport service for the carriage of passengers or goods by air, 
road or water; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>722801</tid>
<number>ii</number>postal, telegraph or telephone service; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>343059</tid>
<number>iii</number>supply of power, light or water to the public by any 
establishment; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1880302</tid>
<number>iv</number>system of public conservancy or sanitation; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>854270</tid>
<number>v</number>service in hospital or dispensary; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1452895</tid>
<number>vi</number>insurance service,
and includes any service which the Central Government or the State 
Government, as the case may be, may, in the public interest, by 
notification, declare to be a public utility service for the purposes 
of this Chapter.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1284933</tid>
<number> 22B</number> Establishment of Permanent Lok Adalats.-
<section><tid>491237</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in section 19, the Central Authority or, as the 
case may be, every State Authority shall, by notification, establish 
Permanent Lok Adalats at such places and for exercising such 
jurisdiction in respect of one or more public utility services and for 
such areas as may be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1015737</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Permanent Lok Adalat established for an area notified under 
sub- section (1) shall consist of-

<subsection><tid>653148</tid>
<number>a</number>a person who is, or has been, a district judge or additional 
district judge or has held judicial office higher in rank than that of 
a district judge, shall be the Chairman of the Permanent Lok Adalat; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>626486</tid>
<number>b</number>two other persons having adequate experience in public utility 
service to be nominated by the Central Government or, as the case may 
be, the State Government on the recommendation of the Central 
Authority or, as the case may be, the State Autho ity,
appointed by the Central Authority or, as the case may be, the State 
Authority, establishing such Permanent Lok Adalat and the other terms 
and conditions of the appointment of the Chairman and other persons 
referred to in clause (b) shall be such as may e prescribed by the 
Central Government.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1991169</tid>
<number> 22C</number> Cognizance of cases by Permanent Lok Adalats.-
<section><tid>769950</tid>
<number>1</number>Any party to a  
dispute may, before the dispute is brought before any court, make an 
application to the Permanent Lok Adalat for the settlement of dispute:
Provided that the Permanent Lok Adalat shall not have jurisdiction in 
respect of any matter relating to an offence not compoundable under 
any law:

Provided further that the Permanent Lok Adalat shall also not have 
jurisdiction in the matter where the value of the property in dispute 
exceeds ten lakh rupees:

Provided also that the Central Government, may, by notification, 
increase the limit of ten lakh rupees specified in the second proviso 
in consultation with the Central Authority.


</section>

<section><tid>569622</tid>
<number>2</number>After an application is made under sub- section (1) to the 
Permanent Lok Adalat, no party to that application shall invoke 
jurisdiction of any court in the same dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>92527</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an application is made to a Permanent Lok Adalat under 
sub- section (1), it-

<subsection><tid>1356951</tid>
<number>a</number>shall direct each party to the application to file before it a 
written statement, stating therein the facts and nature of dispute 
under the application, points or issues in such dispute and grounds 
relied in support of, or in opposition to, such poin s or issues, as 
the case may be, and such party may supplement such statement with any 
document and other evidence which such party deems appropriate in 
proof of such facts and grounds and shall send a copy of such 
statement together with a copy of such ocument and other evidence, if 
any, to each of the parties to the application;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>503101</tid>
<number>b</number>may require any party to the application to file additional 
statement before it at any stage of the conciliation proceedings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1434312</tid>
<number>c</number>shall communicate any document or statement received by it from 
any party to the application to the other party, to enable such other 
party to present reply thereto.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1887947</tid>
<number>4</number>When statement, additional statement and reply, if any, have been 
filed under sub- section (3), to the satisfaction of the Permanent Lok 
Adalat, it shall conduct conciliation proceedings between the parties 
to the application in such manner as it thin s appropriate taking into 
account the circumstances of the dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>1658333</tid>
<number>5</number>The Permanent Lok Adalat shall, during conduct of conciliation 
proceedings under sub- section (4), assist the parties in their attempt 
to reach an amicable settlement of the dispute in an independent and 
impartial manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1079206</tid>
<number>6</number>It shall be the duty of every party to the application to 
cooperate in good faith with the Permanent Lok Adalat in conciliation 
of the dispute relating to the application and to comply with the 
direction of the Permanent Lok Adalat to produce eviden e and other 
related documents before it.

</section>

<section><tid>69534</tid>
<number>7</number>When a Permanent Lok Adalat, in the aforesaid conciliation 
proceedings, is of opinion that there exist elements of settlement in 
such proceedings which may be acceptable to the parties, it may 
formulate the terms of a possible settlement of the dispu e and give 
to the parties concerned for their observations and in case the 
parties reach at an agreement on the settlement of the dispute, they 
shall sign the settlement agreement and the Permanent Lok Adalat shall 
pass an award in terms thereof and fur ish a copy of the same to each 
of the parties concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>569219</tid>
<number>8</number>Where the parties fail to reach at an agreement under sub- section 
 (7), the Permanent Lok Adalat shall, if the dispute does not relate to 
any offence, decide the dispute.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>293573</tid>
<number>22D</number>Procedure of Permanent Lok Adalat.- The Permanent Lok Adalat 
shall, while conducting conciliation proceedings or deciding a dispute 
on merit under this Act, be guided by the principles of natural 
justice, objectivity, fair play, equity and other prin iples of 
justice, and shall not be bound by the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> 
 (5 of <year>1908</year>) and the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>).
</article>



<article><tid>206998</tid>
<number> 22E</number> Award of Permanent Lok Adalat to be final.-
<section><tid>28305</tid>
<number>1</number>Every award of  
the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act made either on merit or in 
terms of a settlement agreement shall be final and binding on all the 
parties thereto and on persons claiming under the.

</section>

<section><tid>712172</tid>
<number>2</number>Every award of the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act shall be 
deemed to be a decree of a civil court.

</section>

<section><tid>87197</tid>
<number>3</number>The award made by the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act shall be 
by a majority of the persons constituting the Permanent Lok Adalat.

</section>

<section><tid>287906</tid>
<number>4</number>Every award made by the Permanent Lok Adalat under this Act shall 
be final and shall not be called in question in any original suit, 
application or execution proceeding.

</section>

<section><tid>1285967</tid>
<number>5</number>The Permanent Lok Adalat may transmit any award made by it to a 
civil court having local jurisdiction and such civil court shall 
execute the order as if it were a decree made by that court.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>347288</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 23.- In section 23 of the principal Act, for 
the words" members of the Lok Adalats", the words" members of the Lok 
Adalats or the persons constituting Permanent Lok Adalats" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1921496</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 27.- In section 27 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), after clause (l), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (la) the other terms and conditions of appointment of the Chairman 
and other persons under sub- section (2) of section 22B;".

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>