<act><title>


The Judges (Inquiry) Act, 1968</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This 
    Act may be called the Judges (Inquiry) Act, 1968.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Chairman” means the Chairman of the 
    Council of States;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Committee” means a Committee 
    constituted under section 3;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Judge” means a Judge of the Supreme 
    Court or of a High Court and includes the Chief Justice of India and the 
    Chief Justice of a High Court; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “Speaker” means the Speaker of the 
    House of the People. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Investigation into misbehaviour or incapacity of Judge by Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If notice is given of a motion for presenting an address to the President 
    praying for the removal of a Judge signed,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in the case of a notice given in the 
    House of the People, by not less than one hundred members of that House; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in the case of a notice given in the 
    Council of States, by not less, than fifty members of that Council, then, 
    the Speaker or, as the case may be, the Chairman may, after consulting such 
    persons, if any, as he thinks fit and after considering such materials, if 
    any, as may be available to him either admit the motion or refuse to admit 
    the same. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    motion referred to in sub-section (1) is admitted, the Speaker or, as the 
    case maybe, the Chairman shall keep the motion pending and constitute as 
    soon as may be for the purpose of making an investigation into the grounds 
    on which the removal of a Judge is prayed for, a Committee consisting of 
    three members of whom— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    one shall be chosen from among the 
    Chief Justice and other Judges of the Supreme Court; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    one shall be chosen from among the 
    Chief Justices of the High Courts; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    one shall be a person who is in the 
    opinion of the Speaker or, as the case may be, the Chairman, a distinguished 
    jurist:  
 
Provided that 
    where notices of a motion referred to in sub-section (1) are given on the 
    same day in both Houses of Parliament, no Committee shall be constituted 
    unless the motion has been admitted in both Houses and where such motion has 
    been admitted in both Houses, the Committee shall be constituted jointly by 
    the Speaker and the Chairman: Provided further that where notices of a 
    motion as aforesaid are given in the Houses of Parliament on different 
    dates, the notice which is given later shall stand rejected. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Committee shall frame definite charges against the Judge on the basis of 
    which the investigation is proposed to be held. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Such 
    charges together with a Statement of the grounds on which each such Charge 
    is based shall be communicated to the Judge and he shall be given a 
    reasonable opportunity of presenting a written Statement of defence within 
    such time as may be specified in this behalf by the Committee. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where it is 
    alleged that the Judge is unable to discharge the duties of his office 
    efficiently due to any physical or mental incapacity and the allegation is 
    denied, the Committee may arrange for the medical examination of the Judge 
    by such Medical Board as may be appointed for the purpose by the Speaker or, 
    as the case may be, the Chairman or, where the Committee is constituted 
    jointly by the Speaker and the Chairman, by both of them, for the purpose 
    and the Judge shall submit himself to such medical examination within the 
    time specified in this behalf by the Committee. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Medical 
    Board shall undertake such medical examination of the Judge as may be 
    considered necessary and submit a report to the Committee stating therein 
    whether the incapacity is such as to render the Judge unfit to continue in 
    office. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> If the 
    Judge refuses to undergo medical examination considered necessary by the 
    Medical Board, the Board shall submit a report to the Committee stating 
    therein the examination which the Judge has refused to undergo, and the 
    Committee may, on receipt of such report, presume that the Judge suffers 
    from such physical or mental incapacity as is alleged in the motion referred 
    to in sub-section (1). 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The 
    Committee may, after considering the written Statement of the Judge and the 
    medical report, if any, amend the charges framed under sub-section (3) and 
    in such a case, the Judge shall be given a reasonable opportunity of 
    presenting a fresh written Statement of defence. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Central 
    Government may, if required by the Speaker or the Chairman, or both, as the 
    case may be, appoint an advocate to conduct the case against the Judge. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Report of 
    Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to any 
    rules that may be made in this behalf, the Committee shall have power to 
    regulate its own procedure in making the investigation and shall give a 
    reasonable opportunity to the Judge of cross-examining witnesses, adducing 
    evidence and of being heard in his defence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At the 
    conclusion of the investigation, the Committee shall submit its report to 
    the Speaker or, as the case may be, to the Chairman, or where the Committee 
    has been constituted jointly by the Speaker and the Chairman, to both of 
    them, stating therein its findings on each of the charges separately with 
    such observations on the whole case as it thinks fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Speaker 
    or the Chairman, or, where the Committee has been constituted jointly by the 
    Speaker and the Chairman, both of them, shall cause the report submitted 
    under sub-section (2) to be laid, as soon as may be, respectively before the 
    House of the People and the Council of States. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Powers of 
    Committee.—For the purpose of 
    making any investigation under this Act, the Committee shall have the powers 
    of a civil court, while trying a suit, under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
    1908, in respect of the following matters, namely:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    summoning and enforcing the attendance 
    of any person and examining him on oath; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    requiring the discovery and production 
    of documents; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    receiving evidence on oath; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    issuing commissions for the examination 
    of witnesses or documents; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    such other matters as may be 
    prescribed. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Consideration of report and procedure for presentation of an address for 
    removal of Judge.—
<section><number>1</number> If the 
    report of the Committee contains a finding that the Judge is not guilty of 
    any misbehaviour or does not suffer from any incapacity, then, no further 
    Steps shall be taken in either House of Parliament in relation to the report 
    and the motion pending in the House or the Houses of Parliament shall not be 
    proceeded with. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    report of the Committee contains a finding that the Judge is guilty of any 
    misbehaviour or suffers from any incapacity, then, the motion referred to in 
    sub-section (l) of section 3 shall, together with the report of the 
    Committee, be taken up for consideration by the House or the Houses of 
    Parliament in which it is pending. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the 
    motion is adopted by each House of Parliament in accordance with the 
    provisions of clause (4) of article 124 or, as the case may be, in 
    accordance with that clause read with article 218 of the Constitution, then, 
    the misbehaviour or incapacity of the Judge shall be deemed to have been 
    proved and an address praying for the removal of the Judge shall be 
    presented in the prescribed manner to the President by each House of 
    Parliament in the same session in which the motion has been adopted. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power to 
    make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be 
    constituted a Joint Committee of both Houses of Parliament in accordance 
    with the provisions hereinafter contained for the purpose of making rules to 
    carry out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Joint 
    Committee shall consist of fifteen members of whom ten shall be nominated by 
    the Speaker and five shall be nominated by the Chairman. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Joint 
    Committee shall elect its own Chairman and shall have power to regulate its 
    own procedure. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the provisions of sub-section (1), the Joint 
    Committee may make rules to provide for the following among other matters, 
    namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the manner of transmission of a motion 
    adopted in one House to the other House of Parliament; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the manner of presentation of an 
    address to the President for the removal of a Judge; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the travelling and other allowances 
    payable to the members of the Committee and the witnesses who may be 
    required to attend such Committee; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the facilities which may be accorded to 
    the Judge for defending himself; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    any other matter which has to be, or 
    may be, provided for by rules or in respect of which provision is, in the 
    opinion of the Joint Committee, necessary. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Any rules 
    made under this section shall not take effect until they are approved and 
    confirmed both by the Speaker and the Chairman and are published in the 
    Official Gazette, and such publication of the rules shall be conclusive 
    proof that they have been duly made.
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Came 
    into force on 1st January, 1969 vide G.S.R. 35, dated 1st January, 
    1969, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), p. 5.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>