<act><title>


THE EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES (COMPULSORY 
NOTIFICATION OF VACANCIES) RULES, 19601</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Employment Exchanges (Compulsory Notification of 
Vacancies) Rules, 1960.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the 1st day of May, 1960.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>1</number> “Act” means the 
Employment Exchanges (Compulsory Notification of Vacancies) Act, 1959 (31 of 
1959);
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> “Central Employment 
Exchange” means 

1[any Employment 
Exchange] established by the Government of India, Ministry of Labour and 
Employment;
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> “Director” means the 
officer-in-charge of the Directorate administering Employment Exchanges in a 
State or a Union Territory;
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Form means a form 
appended to these rules;
 

2[(5) “Local 
Employment Exchange” means—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number> in the whole 
of India except the Union territory of Chandigarh that Employment Exchange 
(other than the Central Employment Exchange) notified in the Official Gazette by 
the State Government or the Administration of the Union territory as having 
jurisdiction over the area in which the establishments concerned is situated or 
over specified classes or categories of establishments or vacancies; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number> in the Union 
territory of Chandigarh that Employment Exchange established either by the Union 
territory Administration of Chandigarh or by the State Government of Punjab or 
Haryana notified in the States respective Official Gazette as having 
jurisdiction over specified clauses or categories of establishments, or 
vacancies, provided that the employment exchanges established by the State 
Government of Punjab or Haryana shall not have jurisdiction over—
 <subsubsection>
               <number>i</number> the 
public sector offices/establishments other than those belonging to the 
respective States; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              <number>ii</number> private 
sector establishments.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> “section” means 
section of the Act.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Employment Exchanges 
to which vacancies are to be notified.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The following vacancies, namely:—
 

          1[(a) 
vacancies in posts of a technical and scientific nature carrying a basic pay of


2[Rs. 1,400] or 
more per month occurring in establishments in respect of which the Central 
Government is the appropriate Government under the Act, and]
 <subsection>
         <number>b</number> vacancies 
which an employer may desire to be circulated to the Employment Exchanges 
outside the State or Union Territory in which the establishment is situated,
 
shall be notified to


3[such Central 
Employment Exchange as may be specified by the Central Government, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, in this behalf].
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Vacancies other than 
those specified in sub-rule (1) shall be notified to the local Employment 
Exchange concerned.
 
 





</section></article> 
 THE EMPLOYMENT EXCHANGES (COMPULSORY NOTIFICATION OF 
VACANCIES) RULES, 1960
 

 <article><number>5</number> Time limit for the 
notification of vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Vacancies required to be notified to the local Employment Exchange, shall be 
notified at least 

1[fifteen days] before the date on which 
applicants will be interviewed or tested where interviews or tests are held, or 
the date on which vacancies are intended to be filled, if no interviews or tests 
are held.
 

2[(2) Vacancies required to be notified 
to the Central Employment Exchange shall be notified, giving at least 60 days, 
time to the Central Employment Exchange from the date of receipt of the 
notification to the date of despatch of particulars or applications of the 
prospective candidates for purpose of appointment or taking interview or test 
against the vacancies notified.]
 

3[(3) An employer shall furnish to the 
concerned Employment Exchange, the results of selection within 15 days from the 
date of selection.]
 
 





</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Submission of 
returns.—An 
Employer shall furnish to the Local Employment Exchange 

1[quarterly returns 
in Form ER1 and biennial returns in Form ERII]. Quarterly returns shall be 
furnished within thirty days of the due dates, namely, 31st March, 30th June, 
30th September and 31st December. Biennial returns shall be furnished within 
thirty days of the due date as notified in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Officer for purposes 
of section 6.—The 
Director is hereby prescribed as the officer who shall exercise the rights 
referred to in section 6, or authorise any person in writing to exercise those 
rights.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Prosecution under the 
Act.—1[The Director of Employment of the 
State in which the establishment is located] is hereby prescribed as the officer 
who may institute or sanction the institution of prosecution for an offence 
under the Act, or authorise any person in writing to institute or sanction the 
institution of such prosecution.]
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>