<act><tid>1726334</tid>
<title>THE SUPPRESSION OF UNLAWFUL ACTS AGAINST SAFETY OF MARITIME 
NAVIGATIONAND FIXED PLATFORMS ON CONTINENTAL SHELF ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 69 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 20th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to give effect to the International Maritime Organisation 
Convention for Suppression of Unlawful Acts Against the Safety of 
Maritime Navigation and the Protocol for the Suppression of Unlawful 
Acts Against the Safety of Fixed Platforms Located on the Continental 
Shelf and for matters connected therewith.

WHEREAS a Convention for the Suppression of Unlawful Acts Against the 
Safety of Maritime Navigation and the Protocol for the Suppression of 
Unlawful Acts Against the Safety of Fixed Platforms Located on the 
Continental Shelf were signed at Rome on the 10 h day of March, <year>1988</year>;

AND WHEREAS India, having acceded to the said Convention and the 
Protocol, should make provisions for giving effect thereto and for 
matters connected therewith;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1331525</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent, application and commencement.-
<section><tid>553568</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act  
may be called the Suppression of Unlawful Acts Against Safety of 
Maritime Navigation and Fixed Platforms on Continental Shelf Act, 
<year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>19044</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India including the limit of the 
territorial waters, the continental shelf, the exclusive economic zone 
or any other maritime zone of India within the meaning of section 2 of 
the Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Excl sive Economic Zone and 
other Maritime Zones Act, <year>1976</year> (80 of <year>1976</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1136403</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided, it shall apply-

<subsection><tid>364159</tid>
<number>a</number>to any offence under section 3 committed outside India by any 
person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1697502</tid>
<number>b</number>to a ship, if that ship is navigating or scheduled to navigate 
into, through or from waters beyond the outer limits of the 
territorial waters of India, or the lateral limits of its territorial 
waters with adjacent States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1069598</tid>
<number>c</number>when the offence is committed on board a ship in the territorial 
waters of India or against a fixed platform located on the Continental 
Shelf of India.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1794008</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (3), this Act 
shall apply only to offences committed by an offender or alleged 
offender,-

<subsection><tid>817187</tid>
<number>a</number>when such an offender is found in the territory of a Convention 
State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>670967</tid>
<number>b</number>when such an offender is found in the territory of a Protocol 
State in whose internal water or territorial waters or continental 
shelf the fixed platform is located; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>897876</tid>
<number>c</number>when such an offender is found in the territory of a State other 
than the State referred to in clause (a) or clause (b).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>941226</tid>
<number>5</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1966660</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>583742</tid>
<number>a</number>" Code" means the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1508903</tid>
<number>b</number>" Continental Shelf of India" shall have the meaning assigned to it 
in the Territorial Waters, Continental Shelf, Exclusive Economic Zone 
and other Maritime Zones Act, <year>1976</year> (80 of <year>1976</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1127597</tid>
<number>c</number>" Convention" means the Convention for the Suppression of Unlawful 
Acts Against the Safety of Maritime Navigation, signed at Rome on the 
 10th day of March, <year>1988</year> as amended from time to time;

</section>

<section><tid>503196</tid>
<number>d</number>" Convention State" means a State Party to the Convention;

</section>

<section><tid>624716</tid>
<number>e</number>" fixed platform" means an artificial island, installation or 
structure permanently attached to the seabed for the purpose of 
exploration for, or exploitation of resources or for other economic 
purposes;

</section>

<section><tid>214271</tid>
<number>f</number>" Protocol" means the Protocol for the Suppression of Unlawful Acts 
Against the Safety of Fixed Platforms Located on the Continental Shelf 
adopted at Rome on the 10th day of March, <year>1988</year> as amended from time to 
time;

</section>

<section><tid>193335</tid>
<number>g</number>" Protocol State" means a State Party to the Protocol;

</section>

<section><tid>1373001</tid>
<number>h</number>" ship" means a vessel of any type whatsoever not permanently 
attached to the seabed and includes dynamically supported craft, 
submersibles, or any other floating craft.
CHAP

OFFENCES

CHAPTER II

OFFENCES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1456262</tid>
<number> 3</number> Offences against ship, fixed platform, cargo of a ship, maritime 
navigational facilities, etc.-
<section><tid>66720</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever unlawfully and  
intentionally-

<subsection><tid>1375645</tid>
<number>a</number>commits an act of violence against a person on board a fixed 
platform or a ship which is likely to endanger the safety of the fixed 
platform or, as the case may be, safe navigation of the ship shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years 
and shall also be liable to fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>108831</tid>
<number>b</number>destroys a fixed platform or a ship or causes damage to a fixed 
platform or a ship or cargo of the ship in such manner which is likely 
to endanger the safety of such platform or safe navigation of such 
ship shall be punished with imprisonment for lif;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1363566</tid>
<number>c</number>seizes or exercises control over a fixed platform or a ship by 
force or threatens or in any other form intimidates shall be punished 
with imprisonment for life;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1069800</tid>
<number>d</number>places or causes to be placed on a fixed platform or a ship, by 
any means whatsoever, a device or substance which is likely to destroy 
that fixed platform or that ship or cause damage to that fixed 
platform or that ship or its cargo which endangers o is likely to 
endanger that fixed platform or the safe navigation of that ship shall 
be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen 
years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1053486</tid>
<number>e</number>destroys or damages maritime navigational facilities or interferes 
with their operation if such act is likely to endanger the safe 
navigation of a ship shall be punished with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to fourteen years;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>964231</tid>
<number>f</number>communicates information which he knows to be false thereby 
endangering the safe navigation of a ship shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years and shall 
also be liable to fine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>398072</tid>
<number>g</number>in the course of commission of or in attempt to commit, any of the 
offences specified in clauses (a) to (d) in connection with a fixed 
platform or clauses (a) to (f) in connection with a ship-

<subsubsection><tid>1910453</tid>
<number>i</number>causes death to any person shall be punished with death;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>958944</tid>
<number>ii</number>causes grievous hurt to any person shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>271214</tid>
<number>iii</number>causes injury to any person shall be punished with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1956113</tid>
<number>iv</number>seizes or threatens a person shall be punished with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to ten years; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1620118</tid>
<number>v</number>threatens to endanger a ship or a fixed platform shall be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>812356</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever attempts to commit, or abets the commission of, an offence 
punishable under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have committed 
such offence and shall be punished with the punishment provided for 
such offence.

</section>

<section><tid>1379729</tid>
<number>3</number>Whoever unlawfully or intentionally threatens a person to compel 
that person to do or refrain from doing any act or to commit any 
offence specified in clause (a), clause (b) or clause (c) of 
sub- section (1), if such threat is likely to endanger the s fe 
navigation of a ship or safety of a fixed platform shall be punished 
with the punishment provided for such offence.

</section>

<section><tid>1084127</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any act referred to in sub- section (1) is committed,-

<subsection><tid>273137</tid>
<number>a</number>against or on board-

<subsubsection><tid>1590493</tid>
<number>i</number>an Indian ship at the time of commission of the offence; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1123203</tid>
<number>ii</number>any ship in the territory of India including its territorial 
waters;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1731928</tid>
<number>b</number>by a stateless person,
such act shall be deemed to be an offence committed by such person for 
the purposes of this Act.

Explanation.- In this sub- section, the expression" stateless person" 
means a person whose habitual residence is in India but he does not 
have nationality of any country.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1255868</tid>
<number>5</number>Where an offence under sub- section (1) is committed and the person 
accused of or suspected of the commission of such offence is present 
in the territory of India and is not extradited to any Convention 
State or Protocol State, as the case may be, s ch person shall be 
dealt with in India in accordance with the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>552565</tid>
<number>6</number>On being satisfied that the circumstances so warrant, the Central 
Government or any other authority designated by it shall take the 
person referred to in sub- section (5) and present in the territory of 
India into custody or take measures, in accorda ce with the law for 
the time being in force, to ensure his presence in India for such time 
as is necessary to enable any criminal or extradition proceeding to be 
instituted:
Provided that when a person is taken into custody under this 
sub- section, it shall be necessary for the Central Government or any 
other authority designated by it to notify the Government of any 
jurisdiction over the offence committed or suspected to have been 
committed by the person in custody. Convention State or Protocol 
State which have also establi hed


</section>

<section><tid>478170</tid>
<number>7</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (8), where an offence 
under sub- section (1) is committed outside India, the person 
committing such offence may be dealt with in respect thereof as if 
such offence had been committed at any place within India at which he 
may be found.

</section>

<section><tid>1219911</tid>
<number>8</number>No court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this 
section which is committed outside India unless-

<subsection><tid>1615284</tid>
<number>a</number>such offence is committed on a fixed platform or on board a ship 
flying the Indian flag at the time the offence is committed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1289227</tid>
<number>b</number>such offence is committed on board a ship which is for the time 
being chartered without crew to a lessee who has his principal place 
of business, or where he has no such place of business, his permanent 
residence, is in India; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>689088</tid>
<number>c</number>the alleged offender is a citizen of India or is on a fixed 
platform or on board a ship in relation to which such offence is 
committed when it enters the territorial waters of India or is found 
in India.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1114484</tid>
<number> 4</number> Conferment of powers of investigation.-
<section><tid>1599163</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in the Code, for the purpose of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
confer on any gazetted officer of the Coast Guard or any other 
gazetted officer of the Central Government powers of arrest, 
investigation and prosecution exercisable by a police officer under 
the Code.

</section>

<section><tid>819860</tid>
<number>2</number>All officers of police and all officers of Government are hereby 
required and empowered to assist the officer of the Central Government 
referred to in sub- section (1), in the execution of provisions of this 
Act.
Explanation.- For the purpose of this section," officer of the Coast 
Guard" means an officer as defined in clause (q) of section 2 of the 
Coast Guard Act, <year>1978</year> (30 of <year>1978</year>).




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1558913</tid>
<number> 5</number> Designated Courts.-
<section><tid>1073406</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of providing for speedy  
trial, the State Government shall, with the concurrence of the Chief 
Justice of the High Court, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
areas as may be specified in the notification. specify a Court of 
Session to be a Designated Cour for such area or

</section>

<section><tid>225227</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code, a Designated Court 
shall, as far as practicable, hold the trial on a day- to- day basis.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1362847</tid>
<number> 6</number> Offence triable by Designated Court.-
<section><tid>1295810</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the Code,-

<subsection><tid>769476</tid>
<number>a</number>all offences under this Act shall be triable only by the 
Designated Court specified under sub- section (1) of section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>696796</tid>
<number>b</number>where a person accused of or suspected of the commission of an 
offence under this Act is forwarded to a Magistrate under sub- section 
 (2) or sub- section (2A) of section 167 of the Code, such Magistrate 
may authorise the detention of such person in suc custody as he thinks 
fit for a period not exceeding fifteen days in the whole where such 
Magistrate is a Judicial Magistrate and seven days in the whole where 
such Magistrate is an Executive Magistrate:
Provided that where such Magistrate considers,-


<subsubsection><tid>1285684</tid>
<number>i</number>when such person is forwarded to him as aforesaid; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>985643</tid>
<number>ii</number>upon or at any time before the expiry of the period of detention 
authorised by him,
that the detention of such person is unnecessary, he shall order such 
person to be forwarded to the Designated Court having the 
jurisdiction;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>548976</tid>
<number>c</number>the Designated Court may exercise, in relation to the person 
forwarded to it under clause (b), the same power which a Magistrate 
having jurisdiction to try a case may exercise under section 167 of 
the Code, in relation to an accused person in such ca e who has been 
forwarded to him under that section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1343912</tid>
<number>d</number>a Designated Court may, upon a perusal of a complaint made by an 
officer of the Central Government or the State Government, as the case 
may be, authorised in this behalf, take cognizance of that offence 
without the accused being committed to it for rial.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1172157</tid>
<number>2</number>When trying an offence under this Act, a Designated Court may also 
try an offence other than an offence under this Act, with which the 
accused may, under the Code, be charged at the same trial.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>999186</tid>
<number>7</number>Application of Code to proceedings before a Designated Court.- Save 
as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of the Code shall 
apply to the proceedings before a Designated Court and the person 
conducting a prosecution before a Designated Court shall be deemed to 
be a Public Prosecutor.


</article>



<article><tid>61569</tid>
<number> 8</number> Provision as to bail.-
<section><tid>313091</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything in the Code, no  
person accused of an offence punishable under this Act shall, if in 
custody, be released on bail or on his own bond unless-

<subsection><tid>317833</tid>
<number>a</number>the Public Prosecutor has been given an opportunity to oppose the 
application for such release; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>150864</tid>
<number>b</number>where the Public Prosecutor opposes the application, the Court is 
satisfied that there are reasonable grounds for believing that he is 
not guilty of such offence and that he is not likely to commit any 
offence while on bail.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1171539</tid>
<number>2</number>The limitations on granting of bail specified in sub- section (1) 
are in addition to the limitations under the Code or any other law for 
the time being in force on granting of bail.

</section>

<section><tid>814067</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the 
special powers of the High Court regarding bail under section 439 of 
the Code.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER III

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1076065</tid>
<number> 9</number> Provisions as to extradition.-
<section><tid>223121</tid>
<number>1</number>The offences under section 3  
shall be deemed to have been included as extraditable offences and 
provided for in all the extradition treaties made by India with 
Convention States or Protocol States and which extend to and are 
binding on, India on the date of commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>348454</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of the application of the Extradition Act, <year>1962</year> 
 (34 of <year>1962</year>) to offences under this Act, any ship registered in a 
Convention State or Protocol State shall, at any time while that ship 
is plying, be deemed to be within the jurisdictio of that Convention 
State or Protocol State, whether or not it is for the time being also 
within the jurisdiction of any other country.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1452055</tid>
<number>10</number>Contracting parties to Convention or Protocol.- The Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, certify as to 
which are the Convention States or Protocol States and to what extent 
such States have availed themselves of the provisi ns of the 
Convention or Protocol, as the case may be, and any such notification 
shall be conclusive evidence of the matters certified therein.


</article>



<article><tid>494453</tid>
<number>11</number>Power to treat certain ships to be registered in Convention 
States.- If the Central Government is satisfied that the requirements 
of the Convention have been satisfied in relation to any ship, it may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, direct th t such ship shall, 
for the purposes of this Act, be deemed to be registered in such 
Convention State as may be specified in the notification.


</article>



<article><tid>465444</tid>
<number>12</number>Previous sanction necessary for prosecution.- No prosecution for 
an offence under this Act shall be instituted except with the previous 
sanction of the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>1201025</tid>
<number> 13</number> Presumptions as to offences under section 3.- In a prosecution for 
an offence under sub- section
<section><tid>762658</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3, if it is proved- 

<subsection><tid>647326</tid>
<number>a</number>that the arms, ammunition or explosives were recovered from the 
possession of the accused and there is reason to believe that such 
arms, ammunition or explosives of similar nature were used in the 
commission of such offence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1743227</tid>
<number>b</number>that there is evidence of use of force, threat of force or any 
other form of intimidation caused to the crew or passengers in 
connection with the commission of such offence; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507233</tid>
<number>c</number>that there is evidence of an intended threat of using bomb, fire, 
arms, ammunition, or explosives or committing any form of violence 
against the crew, passengers or cargo of a ship or fixed platform 
located on the Continental Shelf of India,
the Designated Court shall presume, unless the contrary is proved, 
that the accused had committed such offence.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1563315</tid>
<number> 14</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.-
<section><tid>850742</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1596132</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused for anything 
which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of the 
provisions of this Act.
SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>