<act><tid>1736847</tid>
<title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> THE PRESIDENCY MAGISTRATES (COURT- FEES) ACT, <year>1877</year>]</title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1877</year>
[ 28th February, <year>1877</year>.]

An Act to regulate the procedure and increase the jurisdiction 
of 
the Courts of Magistrates in the Presidency- towns.

Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to consolidate and amend 
the 
law regulating the procedure of the Courts of Magistrates in 
the 
Presidency- towns and to increase the jurisdiction of such Courts. 
It 
is hereby enacted as follows:-

 1 to 56. Rep. by the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1882</year> (Act 10  
of 
  <year>1882</year>).



<article><tid>770151</tid>
<number>57</number>Fees for summonses and warrants.- A fee of eight annas shall 
be 
paid for every summons or warrants issued by a Presidency 
Magistrate, 
except in the case of a summons to attend and give evidence or 
to 
produce documents, in which case they shall be paid a fee of 
four 
annas:
Power to remit fees.- Provided that such Magistrate may in 
any 
case remit any such fee, if he is satisfied that the complainant 
is 
unable to pay the same, and shall remit it when the complaint is 
made 
by a public servant in the execution of his duty.

 58 to end. Rep. by the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1882</year> (Act 

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

  of <year>1882</year>).


<pagefootnote><pagenum>326</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sort title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of <year>1897</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

 1 to

Rep. by the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1882</year> (Act 10 of <year>1882</year>).

 1 to 56. Rep. by the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1882</year> (Act 10 of  
  <year>1882</year>).



</article>



<article><tid>770151</tid>
<number>57</number>Fees for summonses and warrants. A fee of eight annas shall 
be paid for every summons or warrant issued by a Presidency 
Magistrate, except in the case of a summons to attend and give 
evidence or to produce documents, in which case they shall be paid a 
fee of four annas:
Power to remit fees. Provided that such Magistrate may in any 
case remit any such fee, if he is satisfied that the complainant is 
unable to pay the same, and shall remit it when the complaint is made 
by a public servant in the execution of his duty.





<pagefootnote><pagenum>327</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>