<act><title>

    THE IDENTIFICATION OF PRISONERS ACT, 1920</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
    may be called the Identification of
    Prisoners Act, 1920.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> It extends to 
    the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[the territories 
    which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B 
    States].]
  
 
STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In its 
    application to the areas comprised in the Former Part B State of Hyderabad, 
    (now forming part of Andhra Pradesh) for sub-section (2) substitute the 
    following, namely:—
 
                   "(2) It 
    extends to the whole of the Hyderabad area of the State of Andhra Pradesh."
 
[Vide Hyderabad Act 27 of 
    1956. Sec. 2 and Sch. as adapted by Andhra Pradesh A.L.O., 1957.]
 <subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—In sub-section 
    (2), add the following after the words 'Part B States':—
 
                   'other than 
    the territories specified in clause (a) and clause (c) of sub-section (1) of 
    section 7 of the States Reorganisation Act, 1956.
 
[Vide Karnataka Act 29 of 
    1975, sec. 4 (1) (w.e.f. 12-8-1975).]
 
Madhya Pradesh.—In 
    sub-section (2), after the words and letter "Part B States", insert the 
    words "other than the Madhya Bharat and Sironj regions of the State of 
    Madhya Pradesh".
 
[Vide M.P. Act 40 of 
    1961, sec. 3 and Sch. Pt. A (w.e.f. 1-2-1962).]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In 
    sub-section (2), after the words and letter "in Part B States" insert the 
    words" other than the Hyderabad Area of the State of Maharashtra."
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 35 
    of 1970, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 4-9-1956.]
 

 








 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “measurements” include 
    finger impressions and foot-print impressions; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “police officer” means an 
    officer in-charge of a police-station, a police officer making an 
    investigation under Chapter XIV of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 
    of 1898)* or any other police officer not below the rank of Sub-Inspector; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “prescribed” means 
    prescribed by rules made under this Act.
 

 
STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Madhya Pradesh.—In clause (a) of 
    section 2, for the words "finger impressions", substitute the words "finger 
    impressions, palm impressions".
 
[Vide M.P. Act 40 of 1961, sec. 3 and 
    Sch., Pt. A (w.e.f. 1-2-1962).]
 
Tamil Nadu.—In clause (a) of section 2, 
    after the words "Sub-Inspector" the words "and includes Finger Print Experts 
    of the Finger Print Bureau, Madras and of the Single Digit Finger Print 
    Sections in the State of Tamil Nadu" shall be inserted.
 
[Vide T. N. Act 44 of 1981, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    27-7-1981)].
 
 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Taking 
    of measurements, etc., of convicted persons.—Every 
    person who has been— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    convicted of any offence 
    punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or upwards, or 
    of any offence which would render him liable to enhanced punishment on a 
    subsequent conviction; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    ordered to give security 
    for his good behaviour under section 118 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1898 (5 of 1898)*,
 
shall, if so required, allow his measurements 
    and photograph to be taken by a police officer in the prescribed manner.
 

 
STATE AMENDMENTS
 <subsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In clause (b) of section 3, 
    add the following at the end, namely:—
 
        "or under section 93 of the Bombay 
    Prohibition Act, 1949."
 
[Vide Bombay Act 58 of 1953, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    2-11-1953); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87.]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—For section 3, substitute 
    the following:—
 
"3. Taking of 
    measurements, etc., of convicted persons.—Every person who has been—
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   convicted of any 
    offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or 
    upwards or of any offence punishable under section 19 of the Dangerous Drugs 
    Act, 1930, or of any offence which would render him liable to enhanced 
    punishment on a subsequent conviction, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   ordered to give 
    security for his good behaviour under section 118 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1898, or under section 93 of the Bombay Prohibition Act, 1949, or 
    to give security for abstaining from commission of certain offences under 
    section 18 of the Dangerous Drugs Act, 1930.
 
shall, if so required, allow his measurements 
    and photographs to be taken by a police officer in the prescribed manner."
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 35 of 1970, sec. 
    4 (w.e.f. 1-3-1971).]
 










 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Taking 
    of measurements, etc., of non-convicted persons.—Any 
    person who has been arrested in connection with an offence punishable with 
    rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or upwards shall, if so 
    required by a police officer, allow his measurements to be taken in the 
    prescribed manner.
 

 
State Amendments
 <section>
<number>Gujarat</number>—For section 4 the following 
    shall be substituted, namely:—
 
 "4. Taking of measurements or 
    photographs of unconvicted persons.—Any person—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   who has been 
    arrested—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   under section 55 of 
    the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898, or under section 4 of the Bombay 
    Beggars Act, 1945,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   in connection 
    with an offence punishable under section 122 of the Bombay Police Act, 1951, 
    or under section 6 or 9 of the Bombay Beggars Act, 1945, or in connection 
    with an offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year 
    or upwards, or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in respect of 
    whom a direction or order under section 55 or 56 of the Bombay Police Act, 
    1951, or under sub-section (1) or (2) of section 23 of the Bombay Beggars 
    Act, 1945, or under section 2 of the Bombay Public Security Measures Act, 
    1947, has been made,
 
shall, if so required by a police officer, 
    allow his measurements or photograph to be taken in the prescribed manner."
    
 
[Vide Bombay Act 15 of 1948, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    24-3-1948) and 21 of 1954, sec. 3 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 8-4-1954), Act 11 of 
    1960, sec. 87.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Karnataka</number>—For section 4, substitute 
    the following:—
 
"4. Taking of measurements or 
    photographs of unconvicted persons.—Any person—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   who has been arrested 
    in connection with an offence punishable under 
    section 96 of the Karnataka Police Act, 1963, or in connection with an 
    offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or 
    upward or in connection with an offence for the commission of which on a 
    second or subsequent occasion enhanced penalties have been provided for 
    under any law for the time being in force; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in respect of 
    whom direction or order under section 54 or 55 of the Karnataka Police Act, 
    1963, has been made.,
 
shall if so required by a police officer, 
    allow his measurements or photographs to be taken in the prescribed manner."
 
[Vide Karnataka Act 29 of 1975, sec. 4 
    (2) (w.e.f. 12-8-1975)].
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—For section 4, substitute 
    the following:—
 
"4. Any person arrested—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   who has been 
    convicted—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   in connection with 
    an offence punishable under section 19 of the Dangerous Drugs Act, 1930; or 
    section 66, 69 or 85 of the Bombay Prohibition Act, 1949; or section 122 of 
    the Bombay Police Act, 1951; or section 7 of the Drugs and Magic Remedies 
    (Objectionable Advertisements) Act, 1954; or section 8 of the Suppression of 
    the Immoral Traffic in Women and Girls Act, 1956; or section 6 or 11 of the 
    Bombay Prevention of Begging Act, 1959; or any other offence punishable with 
    rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or upwards, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   under section 54, 55 
    or 151 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 or
    section 4 of the Passport (Entry into India) Act, 1920, or
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in respect of 
    whom a direction or order under section 5 of the Passport (Entry into India) 
    Act, 1920, or under sections 55, 56 or 57 of the Bombay Police Act, 1951, 
    has been made, or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   to whom a pardon 
    has been tendered under section 337 or 338 or who has been acquitted under 
    section 339A of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898.
 
shall, if so required by a Police Officer, 
    allow his measurements or photograph to be taken in the prescribed manner."
 
[Vide Maharashtra Act 35 of 1970, sec. 
    5 (w.e.f. 1-3-1971).]
 

 


    Section 4A " 
 
Gujarat: Maharashtra.—In its 
    application to the State of Bombay, after section 4, insert the following:—
 
"4A. Taking of 
    measurements, etc., of habitual offenders against whom restriction order is 
    made.—Any person against whom an order of restriction has been made 
    under the provisions of the Bombay Habitual Offenders Act, 1959, shall, if 
    so required, allow his measurements and photographs to be taken by a police 
    officer in the prescribed manner."
 
[Vide Bombay Act 58 of 1953, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
    2-11-1953) and Maharashtra Act 35 of 1970,
    sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-3-1971); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87.]
 

 
Section 4A and 4B
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>Karnataka</number>—After section 4, insert the 
    following:—
 </section></article><article>
<number>4A</number> Taking of 
    Measurements, etc., of habitual offenders against whom restriction order is 
    made.—Any person against whom an order of restriction has been made 
    under the provisions of the Karnataka Habitual Offenders Act, 1961, shall if 
    so required by a police officer, allow his measurements or photograph to be 
    taken in the prescribed manner."
 
[Vide Karnataka Act 29 of 1975, sec. 
    4(2) (w.e.f. 12-8-1975).]
 
After section 4A, insert the following:—
 </article><article>
<number>4B</number> Taking of 
    measurements etc., of beggars under the Karnataka Prohibition of Beggary 
    Act, 1975.—Any person who has been arrested and not released under 
    sub-section (2) of section 11 of the Karnataka Prohibition of Beggary Act, 
    1975 (Karnataka Act 27 of 1975) or against whom an order of detention has 
    been made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12 of the said Act, shall, if so 
    required by an officer incharge of a receiving centre or relief centre allow 
    his measurements and photographs to be taken in the prescribed manner.
 
[Vide Karnataka Act 1 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    16-1-1982)].
 


 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4A</number> Taking of Measurements, etc., of habitual offenders against whom restriction order is made.</title>—Any person against whom an order of restriction has been made under the provisions of the Karnataka Habitual Offenders Act, 1961, shall if so required by a police officer, allow his measurements or photograph to be taken in the prescribed manner."

 [Vide Karnataka Act 29 of 1975, sec. 4(2) (w.e.f. 12-8-1975).]
 After section 4A, insert the following:—

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4B</number> Taking of measurements etc., of beggars under the Karnataka Prohibition of Beggary Act, 1975.</title>—Any person who has been arrested and not released under sub-section (2) of section 11 of the Karnataka Prohibition of Beggary Act, 1975 (Karnataka Act 27 of 1975) or against whom an order of detention has been made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 12 of the said Act, shall, if so required by an officer incharge of a receiving centre or relief centre allow his measurements and photographs to be taken in the prescribed manner.
 [Vide Karnataka Act 1 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 16-1-1982)].
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Power of 
    Magistrate to order a person to be measured or photographed.—If 
    a Magistrate is satisfied that, for the purposes of any investigation or 
    proceeding under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)† it is 
    expedient to direct any person to allow his measurements or photograph to be 
    taken, he may make an order to that effect, and in that case the person to 
    whom the order relates shall be produced or shall attend at the time and 
    place specified in the order and shall allow his measurements or photograph 
    to be taken, as the case may be, by a police officer:
 
Provided that 
    no order shall be made directing any person to be photographed except by a 
    Magistrate of the First Class:
 
Provided 
    further, that no order shall be made under this section unless the person 
    has at some time been arrested in connection with such investigation or 
    proceeding. 
 

 
 STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Gujarat: Maharashtra.—In its 
    application to these States, in section 5—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   in the first 
    proviso, for the words "except by a Magistrate of the first class" 
    "substitute the words "except by the District Magistrate, a Sub-Divisional 
    Magistrate, a Magistrate of the first class."
 
[Vide Bombay Act 8 of 1954 sec. 2 and 
    Sch., Part II (w.e.f. 10-2-1954) and Maharashtra Act 35 of 1970, sec. 3, (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1971); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87.]
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   to the first 
    proviso, add the words "or a Presidency Magistrate"*
 
[Vide Bombay Act 11 of 1922, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
    14-12-1922), as amended by Bombay Act 17 of 1945; Maharashtra Act 35 of 
    1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-3-1971); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87.]
 
*This institution has been replaced by that of 
    the Metropolitan Magistrate. Besides Bombay, Calcutta and Madras, Ahmedabad 
    has such Magistrate—See Code of Criminal Procedure 1973, sections 8 
    and 16.
 <subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—In section 5, substitute the 
    following for first proviso:—
 
"Provided that no order shall be 
    made directing any person to be photographed except by a District 
    Magistrate, a Sub-Divisional Magistrate or a Magistrate of the First Class."
 
[Vide Karnataka Act 29 of 1975, sec. 4 
    (3) (w.e.f. 12-8-1975)].
 










 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Resistance to the taking of measurements, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any person who under this Act is required to allow his measurements or 
    photograph to be taken resists or refuses to allow the taking of the same, 
    it shall be lawful to use all means necessary to secure the taking thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Resistance 
    to or refusal to allow the taking of measurements or photograph under this 
    Act shall be deemed to be an offence under section 186 of the Indian Penal 
    Code (45 of 1860). 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Destruction of photographs and records of measurements, etc., on acquittal.—Where 
    any person who, not having been previously convicted of an offence 
    punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or upwards, has 
    had his measurements taken or has been photographed in accordance with the 
    provisions of this Act is released without trial or discharged or acquitted 
    by any court, all measurements and all photographs (both negatives and 
    copies) so taken shall, unless the court or (in a case where such person is 
    released without trial) the District Magistrate or Sub-Divisional Officer 
    for reasons to be recorded in writing otherwise directs, be destroyed or 
    made over to him.
 

 
STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Gujarat: Maharashtra.—In 
    section 7, after the words 'Officer' insert the words "or in any area for 
    which a Commissioner of Police has been appointed by the Commissioner of 
    Police".
 
[Vide Bombay Act 11 of 
    1922 sec. 4 (w.e.f. 14-12-1922), as amended by Bombay Acts 17 of 1945; 21 of 
    1954 and 56 of 1959; Maharashtra Act 35 of 1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-3-1971); 
    Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87.]
 
Note.—Cities of Nagpur, 
    Pune, Thana etc. also have Commissioners of Police now.
 <section>
<number>Karnataka</number>—For section 7, 
    substitute the following:—
 
                   
    "7. Destruction of photographs and records of measurements etc., on 
    acquittal.—Where any person who not having been previously convicted of 
    an offence punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term of one year or 
    upwards has had his measurements taken or has been photographed in 
    accordance with the provisions of this Act is released without trial or 
    discharged or acquitted by any Court, all measurements and all photographs 
    (both negatives and copies) so taken shall, unless the Court or in a case 
    where a person is released without trial, the District Magistrate or the 
    Sub-Divisional Magistrate, or in any area where a Commissioner of Police has 
    been appointed, the Commissioner of Police, for reasons to be recorded in 
    writing otherwise directs, be destroyed or made over to him."
 
[Vide Karnataka Act 29 of 
    1975, sec. 4(4) (w.e.f. 12-8-1975)].
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, 

    1[by notification in 
    the Official Gazette,] make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect 
    the provisions of this Act.—(1) 
    The State Government may, 

    1[by notification in 
    the Official Gazette,] make rules for the purpose of carrying into effect 
    the provisions of this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    provision, such rules may provide for— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    restrictions on the 
    taking of photographs of persons under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the places at which 
    measurements and photographs may be taken;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the nature of the 
    measurements that may be taken;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the method in which any 
    class or classes of measurements shall be taken;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the dress to be worn by 
    a person when being photographed undersection 3; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the preservation, safe 
    custody, destruction and disposal of records of measurements and 
    photographs.
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it 
    is made, before State Legislature.]
 

 
STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Gujarat: Maharashtra.—In 
    clause (e) of sub-section (2), for the words "under section 3" substitute 
    the words "in accordance with the provisions of this Act."
 
[Vide Bombay Act 58 of 
    1953, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-11-1953) Maharashtra Act 35 of 1970, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
    1-3-1971); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87.]
 <subsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—In clause (e) 
    of sub-section (2) of section 8, for the words "under section 3", substitute 
    the words "in accordance with the provisions of this Act."
 
[Vide Karnataka Act 29 of 
    1975, sec. 4(5) (w.e.f. 12-8-1975).]
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Bar of 
    suits.—No suit or other 
    proceeding shall lie against any person for anything done, or intended to be 
    done, in good faith under this Act or under any rule made thereunder. 
 



 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by the 
    Adaptation of Laws Order, 1950, for sub-section (2). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws 
    Order, 1950, for sub-section (2)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by the 
    Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, 1956, for “Part B States”. tc 
    " 3. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws 
    (No. 3) Order, 1956, for “Part B States”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986). tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and 
    Sch. (w.e.f. 15-5-1986)."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>