<act><tid>1751970</tid>
<title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> THE <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> COASTING- VESSELS ACT, <year>1838</year>]</title>

ACT NO. 19 OF <year>1838</year> 
[ 27th August, <year>1838</year>]




<article><tid>609888</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Extent.-- This Act extends in the first instance <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> to 
the territories which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were 
comprised in the States] of Bombay, Saurashtra and Kutch, but the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
extend it to any other State <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or part of a State] which has a 
sea- coast.]


</article>



<article><tid>117449</tid>
<number>2</number>Rules as to coasting and other vessels belonging to any 
citizen of India.-- <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> The following rules shall be in force with 
respect to vessels belonging to <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> any citizen of India] <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>, and 
employed on the coasts of <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> any State <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> or part of a State] to 
which this Act extends] or in trading coastwise, as also with respect 
to fishing- vessels and harbour- craft belonging to <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> any such 
citizen].


</article>



<article><tid>661498</tid>
<number>3</number>Marking or branding vessels with name of place and number.-- 11 
Every such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and 
harbour- craft shall be marked or branded with the name of the place to 
which she belongs, and also with a number assigned for the same by the 
officer authorised to make such registry as is hereinafter mentioned;
Owner to paint name and number-- and the owner or owners of such 
vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and harbour- craft shall 
cause such name and number to be painted in black paint upon a white 
ground on each quarter of such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- 
vessel and harbour- craft, in English figures and letters, each figure 
and letter being six inches in length.



</article>



<article><tid>1417578</tid>
<number>4</number>Registry of name, number and burthen.-- <footcitenum>11</footcitenum> The name and 
number of every such vessels employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and 
harbour- craft, and her burthen, and also the name or names of the 
owner or owners thereof, shall be registered in a book to be kept for 
that purpose by the person hereinafter directed to make such registry.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Bombay Short Titles Act, <year>1921</year> (Bom. Act  
  2 of <year>1921</year>).

This Act was declared by the Laws Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15  
  of <year>1874</year>), s. 5, to be in force in the whole of the Bombay 
Presidency, except the Scheduled Districts.

This Act has been repealed in so far as it applies to sea- 
going ships fitted with mechanical means of propulsion and to 
sailing vessels by the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44 of <year>1958</year>), 
s. 461 and Sch.

The Act came into force in Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>)

The Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with 
modifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year> and Sch. and to Laccadive, 
Minicoy and Amindivi Islands by Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1968</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The word" Bombay" omitted by Act 22 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 4, ibid. Original s. 1 was rep. by Act 14 of <year>1870</year>, s. 
1 and Sch., Pt. II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" to the 
States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins., ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>The words and figures" And it is hereby enacted, that from the 
said first day of November, <year>1838</year>" rep. by Act 16 of <year>1874</year>, s. 1 
and Sch., Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" any of Her Majesty' s subjects".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>The words" residing within the State of Bombay" Omitted by Act 22 of 
<year>1952</year>, s. 5.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" the said State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>10</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" any of the same Her Majesty' s 
subjects".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>11</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" rep. by Act 16 of 
<year>1874</year>, s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Registry by whom to be made. Fresh registration.-- At Bombay such 
registry shall be made by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[ Principal Officer, Mercantile 
Marine Department], and at other places <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by the Collector of Sea- 
customs at such places respectively, or by such other person as shall 
be appointed by the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Central Government] to act at such places 
respectively, in the execution of this Act; and whenever any change 
shall take place in the burthen of such vessel employed as aforesaid, 
fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, or in the name or names of the owner 
or owners thereof, such registry shall be made again:

Provided, however, that it shall not be lawful to give any name 
to such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, 
other than that by which she was first registered.



</article>



<article><tid>394532</tid>
<number>5</number>Owners to apply for registry.-- <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The owner or owners of 
every such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and harbour- 
craft shall apply to the person authorised to make such registry in 
respect of the same, in order to have such registry as aforesaid made, 
or in order to have such registry made again as aforesaid.
Information of registry at subordinate port.-- And whenever such 
vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft is 
registered at a subordinate port, information thereof, and of the 
number there assigned to her, shall immediately be given by the 
registering officer to the[ Principal Officer, Mercantile Marine 
Department] at Bombay.



</article>



<article><tid>1283150</tid>
<number>6</number>Officers to perform duty of marking and branding.-- <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The 
duty of marking or branding and of ascertaining the burthen of such 
vessels employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessels and harbour- craft, at 
Bombay, shall be performed by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Principal Officer, Mercantile 
Marine Department]; and at all other places <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the duty of marking 
or branding and of ascertaining the burthen of such vessels employed 
as aforesaid, fishing- vessels and harbour- craft shall be performed by 
the Collector of Sea- customs at such places respectively, or by such 
other persons as shall be appointed by the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Central Government] 
to act at such places respectively, in the execution of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1037400</tid>
<number>7</number>Owner to obtain certificate of registry Replacing lost 
certificate.-- <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> The owner or owners of every such vessel employed 
as aforesaid, fishing- vessel and harbour- craft shall apply for and 
obtain a certificate of registry from the person authorised to make 
such registry as aforesaid, and such certificate shall be in the form 
specified in the Schedule appended to this Act; and in the case of any 
certificate being lost or destroyed, a renewed certificate may be 
obtained in the same manner and on payment of the fees hereinafter 
mentioned.

</article>



<article><tid>338367</tid>
<number>8</number>Sealing certificate.-- <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Such certificate of registry shall 
be sealed with the seal of the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Government of India], and shall 
be signed by the person authorised to make such registry.




</article>



<article><tid>839320</tid>
<number>10</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Fees for certificate.-- The owner or owners of such 
vessels employed as aforesaid (fishing- vessels and harbour- craft being  
  excepted) on being registered as aforesaid, shall pay-
for each certificate of registry for a vessel not exceeding 5 
tons burthen, the fee of... 1 rupee;

for each certificate for a vessel exceeding 5 tons burthen and 
not exceeding 25 tons burthen, the fee of.... 5 rupees;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> (as amended by C. O. 29, dated 4- 4- <year>1951</year>), 
for" Master- Attendant" (w. e. f. 26- 1- <year>1950</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" within the said State" omitted by Act 22 of <year>1952</year>, s. 
6.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" Government of Bombay".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" rep. by Act 16 of 
<year>1874</year>, s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The words" within the State of Bombay" omitted by Act 22 of <year>1952</year>, 
s. 7.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" East India Company".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1952</year>, s. 8, for the original section.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


for each certificate for a vessel exceeding 25 tons burthen and 
not exceeding 100 tons burthen, the fee of 7 rupees;

and for each certificate for a vessel of 100 tons or greater 
burthen, per ton, the fee of... 2 annas.]



</article>



<article><tid>1798453</tid>
<number>11</number>Fees to be credited to Government.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The person or 
persons so authorised to make such registry as aforesaid shall receive 
the fees payable for the same, and shall pay such fees to such officer 
as <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Central Government] shall appoint; the same to be carried 
to the credit of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Central Government]:
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided that any such fees as immediately before the 
commencement of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the Constitution] were, under this Act as then 
in force to be carried to the credit of the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Provincial 
Government] shall be paid to such officer as the State Government may 
appoint and be carried to the credit of that Government.]



</article>



<article><tid>1586159</tid>
<number>12</number>Production of certificate on demand.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The owner or 
owners or commander of every such Vessel employed as aforesaid, 
fishing- vessel and harbour- craft shall produce, on demand thereof by 
any officer of the Customs <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> or by any officer of the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Navy, the 
certificate so directed to be applied for and obtained in respect of 
such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, as 
above mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>1810869</tid>
<number>13</number>Penalty for neglect to comply with rules.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> In case any 
such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft 
shall not be so marked or branded in all respects as hereinbefore 
directed, or in case the name and number of any such vessel employed 
as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft shall not be so painted, 
or shall not continue so painted on such vessel employed as aforesaid, 
fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, in all respects as hereinbefore 
directed;
or in case any such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel 
or harbour- craft shall not be furnished with such certificate as 
hereinbefore specified, or in case the owner or owners or commander of 
any such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft 
shall not produce such certificate on demand thereof as hereinbefore 
directed;

the owner or owners of every such vessel employed as aforesaid 
shall be subject to a fine of ten times the amount of the fees payable 
in respect of the certificate of registry of such vessel, the same 
being a vessel for the certificate of the registration of which any 
fee is payable; and the owner or owners of any such fishing- vessel or 
harbour- craft shall be subject to a fine of ten rupees;

Recovery of penalties-- which fines may be recovered on conviction 
before any Magistrate <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> Having jurisdiction, <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> by sale of such 
vessel, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft, her furniture, ammunition, 
tackle and apparel;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" And it is hereby enacted, that" rep. by Act 16 of 
<year>1874</year>, s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the Governor of Bombay in Council".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for" the Government of Bombay".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins., ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Part III of the Government of India 
Act, <year>1935</year>".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs., ibid., for" Local Government".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>The words" within the said State" omitted by Act 22 of <year>1952</year>, s. 
6.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>The word" Indian" rep. by Act 12 of <year>1876</year>, s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>The words" Justice of the Peace, or person exercising the powers 
of a Magistrate" rep. by Act 12 of <year>1876</year>, s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Penalty on repetition of default-- and such fines shall be payable 
as often as the owner or owners or commander of any such vessel 
employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel or harbour- craft shall make such 
default as aforesaid: Provided every such subsequent default be made 
after the expiration of one month from the date of the last 
conviction.



</article>



<article><tid>645527</tid>
<number>14</number>Power to direct compensation for trouble in seizing.-- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] may direct compensation for trouble and 
diligence in seizing such vessel employed as aforesaid, fishing- vessel 
or harbour- craft, guns, furniture, tackle, ammunition and apparel, as 
last mentioned, to be made, out of the proceeds of such seizure to the 
person or persons who shall have seized the same, to such amount, in 
such manner and in such shares or proportions, as to the said 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Central Government] shall seem meet.
</article>



<article><tid>106421</tid>
<number>15</number>[ Port- clearance.] Rep. partly by the Repealing Act, <year>1874</year> (16 of <year>1874</year>), 
s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I, and partly by the Repealing Act, <year>1876</year> (12 of  
  <year>1876</year>), s. 1 and Sch., Pt. I.

</article>



 </act>