<act><tid>17541</tid>
<title>THE VISVA- BHARATI ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 29 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 9th May, <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to declare the institution known as" Visva- Bharati" to be an 
institution of national importance and to provide for its functioning 
as a unitary teaching and residential university.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>105812</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>522583</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Visva- Bharati Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1299761</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1447957</tid>
<number>2</number>Declaration of Visva- Bharati as an institution of national 
importance. Whereas the late Rabindranath Tagore (Thakur) founded an 
institution known as Visva- Bharati at Santiniketan in the district of 
Birbhum in West Bengal the objects of which are such as to make the 
institution one of national importance, it is hereby declared that the 
institution known as" Visva- Bharati" aforesaid is an institution of 
national importance <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and is as such hereby constituted as a 
University].


</article>



<article><tid>1573335</tid>
<number> 3</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> In this Act, and in all Statutes made hereunder, unless the 
context otherwise requires,--
<section><tid>1832833</tid>
<number>a</number>" academic staff" means such categories of staff as are 
designated as academic staff by the statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>395380</tid>
<number>b</number>" Acharya (Chancellor)" and" Upacharya (Vice-  
  Chancellor)" mean, respectively, the Acharya (Chancellor) and the 
Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>777887</tid>
<number>c</number>" adhyapaka" includes a Professor, Reader, Lecturer and 
any other person engaged in imparting instruction in relation to 
any learning process and designated as an adhyapaka by the 
Ordinances;

</section>

<section><tid>533652</tid>
<number>d</number>" Alumni Association" means the Association of the 
Alumni of the University, constituted under the provisions of 
this Act and the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>544193</tid>
<number>e</number>" approved institution" means an institution (not being  
  an institution maintained by the University) of higher learning 
or studies approved by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1546781</tid>
<number>f</number>" Bhavana" means an academic institution maintained by 
the University and named as such;

</section>

<section><tid>184736</tid>
<number>g</number>" campus" means a unit established or constituted by the 
University for imparting instruction or supervising research, for 
both;

</section>

<section><tid>159622</tid>
<number>h</number>" Chatravasa" means a unit of residence, or of corporate 
life, for the students of the University provided, maintained or 
recognised by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1205042</tid>
<number>i</number>" Department" means a Department of Studies and includes 
a centre of studies established by, or under, the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>1562039</tid>
<number>j</number>" employee of the University" means any person appointed 
by the University or any Institution, and includes an employee of 
a Bhavana;

</section>

<section><tid>808800</tid>
<number>k</number>" Institute Board" means a Board constituted by the 
University for the management of an Institute;

</section>

<section><tid>1394432</tid>
<number>l</number>" Institution" means an institution maintained by the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>573480</tid>
<number>m</number>" Karma- Samiti (Executive Council)" means the Karma- 
Samiti (Executive Council) of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1939663</tid>
<number>n</number>" Patha- Samiti (Board of Studies)" means a Board 
constituted by the University for the regulation of studies;

</section>

<section><tid>958861</tid>
<number>o</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by the Statutes, 
Ordinances or Regulations;

</section>

<section><tid>1984927</tid>
<number>p</number>" Samsad (Court)" means the Samsad (Court) of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1466948</tid>
<number>q</number>" Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council)" means the Siksha- 
Samiti (Academic Council) of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>776111</tid>
<number>r</number>" Statutes"," Ordinances" and" Regulations" mean, 
respectively, such Statutes, Ordinances and Regulations of the 
University as are for the time being in force;

</section>

<section><tid>888512</tid>
<number>s</number>" University" means the institution known as Visva- 
Bharati and incorporated as a University under this Act.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>80</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 14th May, <year>1951</year>, vide Notification No. F. 40- 5 50-G. 3, dated the 
10th May, <year>1951</year>, Gazette of India, <year>1951</year>, Pt. I, Sec. 1, p. 196. 
2. Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1961</year>, s. 2 (retrospectively). 
3. Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

THE UNIVERSITY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1398129</tid>
<number>4</number>Incorporation. The first Acharya (Chancellor) and Upacharya 
 (Vice- Chancellor) of the University who shall be the persons appointed 
in this behalf by the Central Government by notification in the 
Official Gazette, and the first members of the Samsad (Court) and all 
persons, who may hereafter become or be appointed as such officers or 
members, so long as they continue to hold such office or membership; 
are hereby constituted a body corporate <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as a unitary, teaching and 
residential University] by the name of Visva- Bharati, and shall have 
perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall sue and be sued by 
that name.


</article>



<article><tid>390767</tid>
<number> 5</number> Effect of incorporation of the University in certain cases. On 
and from the commencement of this Act,--
<section><tid>108136</tid>
<number>i</number>all references in any enactment to the Society of the 
name of Visva- Bharati registered on the 16th May, <year>1922</year>, 
under the Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of  
  <year>1860</year>), shall be construed as references to the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1142309</tid>
<number>ii</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> all property, assets, rights and liabilities of 
the said Society shall be the property, assets, rights 
and liabilities of the University and any will, deed or 
other document, whether made or executed before or 
after the commencement of this Act, which contains or 
purports to contain any bequest, gift, trust, payment 
of money or transfer or assignment of any right or 
property, movable or immovable, in favour of the said 
Society shall be construed
<pagefootnote><pagenum>81</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1961</year>, s. 4 (retrospectively). 
2. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for cl. (ii)  (retrospectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


as if the University was therein named instead of the 
said Society;]


</section>

<section><tid>1057947</tid>
<number>iii</number>subject to the provisions of this Act, every 
person employed immediately before the commencement of 
this Act in the said Society shall hold employment in 
the University by the same tenure and upon the same 
terms and conditions and with the same rights and 
privileges as to pension and gratuity as he would have 
held under the said Society, if this Act had not been 
passed:
Provided that if the University decides to alter the terms and 
conditions of service of any such employee, a fresh contract shall be 
executed for the purpose, and if the employee is not agreeable to 
serve under the new terms and conditions, his services may be 
terminated in accordance with his original contract of employment or, 
if no provision is made therein in this behalf, on payment to him by 
way of compensation of an amount equal to his salary for six months.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>854689</tid>
<number> 5A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The objects of the University.
<section><tid>1930950</tid>
<number>1</number>The objects of the  
University shall be to disseminate and advance knowledge and 
understanding by providing instructional, extension and research 
facilities and by the example and influence of its corporate life, and 
the University shall, in organising its activities, have due regard to 
the following objects for which the Visva- Bharati at Santiniketan was 
founded by Rabindranath Tagore, as expressed in his own words, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>715344</tid>
<number>i</number>to study the mind of Man in its realisation of 
different aspects of truth from diverse points of view;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1938274</tid>
<number>ii</number>to bring into more intimate relations with one another, 
through patient study and research, the different cultures of the 
East on the basis of their underlying unity;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1216297</tid>
<number>iii</number>to approach the West from the standpoint of such a 
unity of the life and thought of Asia;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>278376</tid>
<number>iv</number>to seek to realise in a common fellowship of study the 
meeting of the East and the West, and thus ultimately to 
strengthen the fundamental conditions of world peace through the 
establishment of free communication of ideas between the two 
hemispheres; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>188165</tid>
<number>v</number>with such ideals in view to provide at Santiniketan 
aforesaid a Centre of Culture where research into and study of 
the religion, literature, history, science and art of Hindu, 
Buddhist, Jain, Islamic, Sikh, Christian and other civilisations 
may be pursued along with the culture of the West, with that 
simplicity in externals which is necessary for true spiritual 
realisation in amity, good fellowship and co- operation between 
the thinkers and scholars of both Eastern and Western countries, 
free from all antagonisms of race, nationality, creed or caste 
and in the name of the One Supreme Being who is Shantam, Shivam, 
Advaitam.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>228508</tid>
<number>2</number>The objects of the University shall also include harmonising 
the cultures of India, the East and the West by, among other things, 
the admission of students and appointment of adhyapakas from various 
regions of India and various countries of the world, and by providing 
incentives therefor.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>640549</tid>
<number>5B</number>Principles to be followed in organising activities of the 
University. The University shall, in organising its activities and the 
implementation of its academic programmes, have due regard to the 
pattern of education envisaged by Rabindranath Tagore in his 
writings."]


</article>



<article><tid>1487337</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Powers of the University. The University shall have the 
following powers, namely:--
<section><tid>105814</tid>
<number>1</number>to provide facilities for studies, instruction, socially 
useful productive work and community service and research in such 
branches of learning as may be deemed desirable and found practicable 
by the University and for the promotion of understanding of cultures 
between the East and the West and for the advancement of learning and 
dissemination of knowledge generally;

</section>

<section><tid>1283852</tid>
<number>2</number>to undertake educational experiments and evolve contents, 
systems and methods of education for the furtherance of the objects of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>9868</tid>
<number>3</number>to make provision for research and advisory services; and for 
that purpose, to enter into such arrangements with other institutions 
or bodies as the University may deem necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>268497</tid>
<number>4</number>to co- operate, collaborate or associate with any other 
University, authority or institution of learning in such manner and 
for such purposes as the University may determine;

</section>

<section><tid>1783955</tid>
<number>5</number>to approve any institution of higher learning or studies for 
such purposes as the University may determine, and to withdraw such 
approval;

</section>

<section><tid>1666696</tid>
<number>6</number>to establish and maintain such Bhavanas, Schools of Studies 
and Research, Chatravasas, Gymnasia and such other institutions as are 
deemed necessary, from time to time, for the development of a healthy 
corporate life in the University and to abolish any such Bhavana, 
School, Chatravasa, Gymnasium or other institution;

</section>

<section><tid>1232453</tid>
<number>7</number>to establish, at any place in India, campuses, special 
centres, specialised laboratories or other units for research and 
instruction as are, in the opinion of the University, necessary for 
the furtherance of its objects;

</section>

<section><tid>35995</tid>
<number>8</number>to organise the application of class room, library and 
laboratory learning to problems of the villages as part of the 
curriculum;

</section>

<section><tid>678416</tid>
<number>9</number>to undertake the promotion of adult education, rural re- 
construction, co- operative organisations, social welfare, development 
of cottage industries and all other nation- building activities and 
works for the benefit of the public;

</section>

<section><tid>165442</tid>
<number>10</number>to establish such examination centres and to recognise such 
certificates as may be necessary to give effect to the provisions of 
section 7A;

</section>

<section><tid>538019</tid>
<number>11</number>to grant, subject to such conditions as the University may 
determine, diplomas or certificates to, and confer degrees or other 
academic distinctions (on the basis of examinations, evaluation or  
  other modes of testing) on, persons;

</section>

<section><tid>1081608</tid>
<number>12</number>to confer honorary degrees or other distinctions in the 
manner prescribed by the Statutes;

</section>

<section><tid>1368</tid>
<number>13</number>to determine the standards for admission and the methods of 
admission to courses of the University, which methods shall include 
examinations, evaluation and other modes of testing;

</section>

<section><tid>1393514</tid>
<number>14</number>to supervise the residences of students of the University 
and to make arrangements for promoting their health and general 
welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>283283</tid>
<number>15</number>to make such special arrangements in respect of women 
students as the University may consider desirable;

</section>

<section><tid>520784</tid>
<number>16</number>to regulate the conduct of students of the University, and 
to take such disciplinary measures in this regard as may be deemed 
necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>1050133</tid>
<number>17</number>to create such teaching and other academic posts as may be 
required by the University and to appoint persons to such posts;

</section>

<section><tid>1457055</tid>
<number>18</number>to appoint Visiting Professors, Emeritus Professors, 
Fellows, Scholars, Resident Artists, Resident Writers or such other 
persons who may contribute to the achievement of the objects of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1054781</tid>
<number>19</number>to appoint or recognise persons as Professors, Readers or 
Lecturers or otherwise as adhyapakas of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1852305</tid>
<number>20</number>to approve persons working in-

<subsection><tid>78116</tid>
<number>a</number>any institution co- operating, collaborating or 
associating with the University; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>521443</tid>
<number>b</number>any approved institution,
for imparting instruction or supervising research, or both, and to 
withdraw such approval;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>959967</tid>
<number>21</number>to undertake publication of literary, scientific, 
educational and scholarly works and books on art, aesthetics and other 
subjects aimed at better understanding of the different cultures of 
the world and furthering thereby the objectives of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1503015</tid>
<number>22</number>to appoint persons working in any other University, 
institution or organisation as adhyapakas of the University for a 
specified period;

</section>

<section><tid>1326848</tid>
<number>23</number>to create administrative, ministerial and other posts in the 
University and to make appointments thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>736051</tid>
<number>24</number>to provide for the terms and conditions of service of 
employees, whether employed by the University or any institution;

</section>

<section><tid>1702301</tid>
<number>25</number>to regulate the conduct and duties of the employees of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>1986767</tid>
<number>26</number>to regulate and enforce discipline among the employees of 
the University and to take such disciplinary measures in this regard 
as may be deemed necessary;

</section>

<section><tid>310736</tid>
<number>27</number>to make arrangements for promoting the health and general 
welfare of the employees of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>639166</tid>
<number>28</number>to demand and receive payment of fees and other charges;

</section>

<section><tid>11451</tid>
<number>29</number>to institute and award fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1678953</tid>
<number>30</number>to receive benefactions, donations and gifts, and to 
acquire, hold, manage and dispose of any property, movable or 
immovable, including trust and endowment properties, for the purposes 
of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>927889</tid>
<number>31</number>to borrow, with the approval of the Central Government, 
whether on the security of the property of the University or 
otherwise, money for the purposes of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1179076</tid>
<number>32</number>to establish campuses within the territorial limits of the 
University specified in the Second Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>755250</tid>
<number>33</number>to admit students of any other University or College whether 
in India or outside to any examination of the University subject to 
such conditions as the University may lay down for the purpose;

</section>

<section><tid>360126</tid>
<number>34</number>to do all such acts and things as may be necessary or 
incidental to the exercise of all or any of the powers of the 
University or as are necessary or conducive to the attainment of all 
or any of the objects of the University."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>82</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1961</year>, s. 6, for" Bhavans (Halls)". 
2. Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>. s. 4 (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>102974</tid>
<number>7</number>Territorial jurisdiction of the University. Save as otherwise 
provided in this Act, the powers of the University conferred by or 
under this Act shall be restricted to the area specified in the Second 
Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1344283</tid>
<number>7A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Maintenance of examination centres outside territorial 
limits. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 7, the 
University may establish and maintain, at any place in India 
examination centres for home study courses conducted by its Loka 
Shiksha Samsad (People' s Education Council) and recognise, for such 
purposes as may be provided in the Ordinances, the certificates 
awarded by the said Loka Shiksha Samsad (People' s Education Council) 
on the results of examinations conducted by it.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>83</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 60 of 19961, s. 7.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1333015</tid>
<number>8</number>University to be open to all races, creeds and classes. The 
University shall be open to all persons irrespective of sex, 
nationality, race, creed, caste or class, and no test or condition 
shall be imposed as to religious belief or profession in admitting or 
appointing members, students, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> adhyapakas] workers, or in any other 
connection whatsoever, except in respect of any particular benefaction 
accepted by the University of which such test is made a condition by 
the instrument creating such benefaction:
Provided that no benefaction shall hereafter be accepted which in 
the opinion of the authorities of the University involves conditions 
or obligations opposed to the spirit and object of this section:

Provided further that nothing in this section shall be deemed to 
prevent religious instruction being given in any manner approved of by 
the authorities concerned to those who have given their consent 
thereto by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> adhyapakas] duly and properly authorised for that 
purpose.



</article>



<article><tid>1166034</tid>
<number>9</number>Teaching at the University. All teaching in the University 
shall be conducted by and in the name of the University in accordance 
with the Statutes and Ordinances made in this behalf.
THE PARIDARSAKA (VISITOR)



</article>



<article><tid>1928201</tid>
<number> 10</number> The Paridarsaka (Visitor).
<section><tid>1633425</tid>
<number>1</number>The President of India  
shall be the Paridarsaka (Visitor) of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1714579</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4), the 
Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall have the right to cause an inspection to 
be made, by such person or persons as he may specify, of the 
University, its buildings, laboratories and equipment, and of any 
Bhavana or other Institution, and also of the examinations, teaching 
and other work conducted or done by the University, Bhavana or other 
Institution; and to cause an inquiry to be made in like manner in 
respect of any matter connected with the administration or finances of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1509894</tid>
<number>3</number>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall give notice to the University 
of his intention to cause an inspection or inquiry to be made and the 
University shall, on receipt of such notice, have the right to make, 
within thirty days or such other period as the Paridarsaka (Visitor) 
may determine, from the date of receipt of the notice, such 
representations to the Paridarsaka (Visitor) as it may consider 
necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1250214</tid>
<number>4</number>After considering the representations, if any, made by the 
University, the Paridarsaka (Visitor) may cause to be made such 
inspection or inquiry as is referred to in sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>821113</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any inspection or inquiry has been caused to be made by 
the Paridarsaka (Visitor), the University shall be entitled to appoint 
a representative who shall have the right to be present and to be 
heard at such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>287342</tid>
<number>6</number>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) may address the Upacharya (Vice-  
  Chancellor) with reference to the results of such inspection or 
inquiry together with such views and advice with regard to the action 
to be taken thereon as the Paridarsaka (Visitor) may be pleased to 
offer, and on receipt of the address made by the Paridarsaka 
 (Visitor), the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) shall communicate forthwith 
to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) the results of the inspection 
or inquiry and the views of the Paridarsaka (Visitor) and the advice 
tendered by him upon the action to be taken thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1085870</tid>
<number>7</number>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall communicate 
through the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) to the Paridarsaka (Visitor) 
such action, if any, as it proposes to take or has been taken by it 
upon the results of such inspection or inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>755000</tid>
<number>8</number>Where the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) does not, within a 
reasonable time, take action to the satisfaction of the Paridarsaka 
 (Visitor), the Paridarsaka (Visitor) may, after considering any 
explanation furnished or representation made by the Karma- Samiti 
 (Executive Council), issue such directions as he may think fit and 
Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall be bound to comply with such 
directions.

</section>

<section><tid>788640</tid>
<number>9</number>Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this 
section, the Paridarsaka (Visitor may, be order in writing, annual any  
proceeding of the University which is not in conformity with this Act, 
  the Statutes or the Ordinances:)
Provided that before making any such order he shall call upon the 
University to show cause why such an order should not be made and, if 
any cause is shown within a reasonable time, he shall consider the 
same.


</section>

<section><tid>1097273</tid>
<number>10</number>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall have such other powers as 
may be specified in the Statutes."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>84</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>. s. 6 (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


THE PRADHANA (RECTOR)




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>461615</tid>
<number>11</number>The Pradhana (Rector.) The Government of West Bengal shall be 
the Pradhana (Rector) of the University.
OFFICERS OF THE UNIVERSITY



</article>



<article><tid>1037079</tid>
<number> 12</number> Officers of the University. The following shall be the 
officers of the University, namely:--
<section><tid>1368915</tid>
<number>1</number>The Acharya (Chancellor);

</section>

<section><tid>166469</tid>
<number>2</number>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor);

</section>

<section><tid>1416006</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director of Studies, Educational Innovations and 
Rural Reconstruction;

</section>

<section><tid>944494</tid>
<number>4</number>The Director of Culture and Cultural Relations;

</section>

<section><tid>304277</tid>
<number>5</number>The Director of Physical Education, Sports, National 
Service and Student Welfare;

</section>

<section><tid>1241251</tid>
<number>6</number>The Karma- Sachiva (Registrar);

</section>

<section><tid>1184094</tid>
<number>7</number>The Vitta- Adhikari (Finance Officer);

</section>

<section><tid>985214</tid>
<number>8</number>Adhyakshas of Bhavanas; and

</section>

<section><tid>53073</tid>
<number>9</number>such other officers as may be declared by the Statutes 
to be officers of the University.]

</section>

<section><tid>1368915</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Acharya (Chancellor) shall, by virtue of his office, 
be the Head of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>166469</tid>
<number>2</number>The Acharya (Chancellor) shall be appointed by the 
Paridarsaka (Visitor) from out of a panel of persons prepared and 
recommended by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) under sub- section 
 (2A).

</section>

<section><tid>1091169</tid>
<number>2A</number>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall prepare and 
recommend a panel of not less than three persons each of whom shall be 
a person of eminence in the academic or public life of the country, 
and is in the opinion of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) a fit 
and proper person to be appointed as the Acharya (Chancellor) of the 
University:
Provided that if the Paridarsaka (Visitor) does not approve of 
any of the persons specified in the panel prepared and recommended by 
the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), he may call upon the Karma- 
Samiti (Executive Council) to prepare a fresh panel of persons.


</section>

<section><tid>1324299</tid>
<number>2B</number>The Acharya (Chancellor) shall hold office for a term of 
three years and shall be eligible for re- appointment:
Provided that the Acharya (Chancellor) shall, notwithstanding the 
expiry of the term of his office, continue to hold such office until 
his successor is appointed and has entered upon his office."]


</section>

<section><tid>1416006</tid>
<number>3</number>The Acharya (Chancellor), shall, if present, preside at the 
Convocation of the University and at meetings of the Samsad (Court) 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and the Karma Samiti (Executive Council)].

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>105812</tid>
<number> 1</number> Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 8, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1961</year>, s. 8.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>85</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<section><tid>1912789</tid>
<number>4</number>Every proposal for the conferment of an honorary degree shall 
be subject to the confirmation of the Acharya (Chancellor).

</section>

<section><tid>1754223</tid>
<number>5</number>The Acharya (Chancellor) shall have such other powers as may 
be conferred on him by this Act or the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1836907</tid>
<number> 14</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor).
<section><tid>585729</tid>
<number>1</number>The Upacharya (Vice-   
  Chancellor) shall be appointed by the Paridarsaka (Visitor) in such 
manner, for such term and on such emoluments and other conditions of 
service as may be prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1269418</tid>
<number>2</number>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) shall be the principal 
executive and academic officer of the University, and shall exercise 
general supervision and control over the academic affairs of the 
University and all Bhavanas and other Institutions and give effect to 
the decisions of all the authorities of the University.

</section>

<section><tid>1872578</tid>
<number>3</number>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) may, if he is of opinion that 
immediate action is necessary on any matter, exercise any power 
conferred on any authority of the University by or under this Act and 
shall report to such authority the action taken by him on such matter:
Provided that if the authority concerned is of opinion that such 
action ought not to have been taken, it may refer the matter to the 
Paridarsaka (Visitor) whose decision thereon shall be final:

Provided further that an employee of the University, who is 
aggrieved by the action taken by the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) under 
this sub- section, shall have the right to appeal against such action 
to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) within ninety days from the 
date on which such action is communicated to him and thereupon the 
Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) may confirm, modify or reverse the 
action taken by the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor).


</section>

<section><tid>79100</tid>
<number>4</number>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) shall exercise such other 
powers and perform such other functions as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes and the Ordinances."]
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1922419</tid>
<number> 16</number> 
<section><tid>1398193</tid>
<number>1</number>The Karma- Sachiva (Registrar) shall be appointed in  
such manner, and on such emoluments and other conditions of service, 
as may be prescribed by the statutes and the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>904164</tid>
<number>2</number>The Karma- Sachiva (Registrar) shall have the power to enter 
into agreements, sign documents and authenticate records on behalf of 
the University and shall exercise such other powers and perform such 
other functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1073539</tid>
<number> 17</number> Other officers.
<section><tid>256579</tid>
<number>1</number>All officers of the University, other  
than the Acharya (Chancellor), the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) and the 
Karma- Sachiva (Registrar), shall be appointed in such manner, for such 
term and on such emoluments and other conditions of service as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>909364</tid>
<number>2</number>The powers and functions of the officers appointed under sub- 
section (1) shall be such as may be prescribed by the Statutes."]
AUTHORITIES OF THE UNIVERSITY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1735494</tid>
<number> 18</number> Authorities of the University. The following shall be 
authorities of the University:-
<section><tid>685491</tid>
<number>1</number>the Samsad (Court),

</section>

<section><tid>891105</tid>
<number>2</number>the Karma Samiti (Executive Council),

</section>

<section><tid>202141</tid>
<number>3</number>the Shiksha Samiti (Academic Council), <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>

</section>

<section><tid>1606139</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> The Artha- Samiti (Finance Committee);

</section>

<section><tid>894721</tid>
<number>5</number>The Institute Board; and]

</section>

<section><tid>798579</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> such other authorities as may be declared by the 
Statutes to be authorities of the University.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>86</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
2. Omitted by s. 10. ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 11 ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
4. Omitted by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
5. Ins. by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
6. Re- numbered by s. 12, ibid. (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1838215</tid>
<number> 19</number> The Samsad (Court).
<section><tid>1235541</tid>
<number>1</number>The constitution of the Samsad  
 (Court) and the term or office of its members shall be such as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>737363</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the Samsad 
 (Court) shall have the following powers and functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1554729</tid>
<number>a</number>to review, from time to time, the broad policies and 
programmes of the University, including the maintenance of 
standards and adherence to the objectives of the University and 
to suggest measures for the development and improvement of the 
University which shall be considered by the appropriate 
authorities of the University;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>290242</tid>
<number>b</number>to consider and pass resolutions on the annual report 
and annual accounts of the University and the report of its 
auditors on such accounts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>930174</tid>
<number>c</number>to advice the Paridarsaka (Visitor) in respect of any 
matter which may be referred to it for advice; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>629145</tid>
<number>d</number>to exercise such other powers and perform such other 
functions as may be prescribed by the Statutes."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>87</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>833350</tid>
<number> 22</number> The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).
<section><tid>1508223</tid>
<number>1</number>The Karma-  
Samiti (Executive Council) shall be the principal executive body of 
the University.

</section>

<section><tid>850559</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) and 
the term of office of its members shall be such as may be prescribed 
by the Statutes.

</section>

<section><tid>1177108</tid>
<number>3</number>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall exercise the 
following powers and perform the following functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1243052</tid>
<number>a</number>to manage and administer the revenue and property of 
the University and to conduct all administrative affairs of the 
University not otherwise provided for in this act or the 
Statutes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>314152</tid>
<number>b</number>to create teaching and academic posts and to define the 
duties and conditions of service of Professor, Readers, Lecturers 
and other adhyapakas and academic staff employed by the 
University:
Provided that before determining the number, qualifications 
and emoluments of adhyapakas and other academic staff, the Karma- 
Samiti (Executive Council) shall consider the recommendations of 
the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council);


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>109394</tid>
<number>c</number>to appoint such Professors, readers, Lecturers and 
other adhyapakas and academic staff as may be necessary on the 
recommendation of the Selection Committees constituted for the 
purpose and to fill up temporary vacancies therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>208618</tid>
<number>d</number>to provide for the appointment of Visiting Professors, 
Emeritus Professors, Fellows, Scholars, Resident Artists and 
Resident Writers and to determine the terms and conditions of 
such appointment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>366019</tid>
<number>e</number>to manage and regulate the finances, accounts, 
investments, property, business and all other administrative 
affairs of the University, and for that purpose, to appoint such 
agents as it may think fit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>617047</tid>
<number>f</number>to invest any money belonging to the University, 
including any unapplied income, in such stocks, funds, shares or 
securities as it thinks fit, or in the purchase of immovable 
property in India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>261715</tid>
<number>g</number>to exercise such other powers and perform such other 
functions as may be conferred or specified by this Act or the 
Statutes."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>88</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year> s. 14 (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>903721</tid>
<number> 24</number> The Shiksha Samiti (Academic Council). The Shiksha Samiti 
 (Academic Council) shall be[" the principal academic body] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of the 
University, and shall, subject to the provisions of this Act, the 
Statutes and the Ordinances, have the control and general regulation, 
and be responsible for the maintenance of standards of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> learning, 
education, instruction, evaluation and examination"] within the 
University, and shall exercise such other powers and perform such 
other duties as may be conferred or imposed upon it by the Statutes 
and shall have the right to advise the Karma Samiti (Executive  
  Council) on all academic matters.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>89</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<section><tid>1961152</tid>
<number>2</number>The constitution of the Shiksha Samiti (Academic Council) and 
the terms of office of its members shall be prescribed by the 
Statutes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>471550</tid>
<number>25</number>Other authorities of the University. The constitution, 
powers and functions of the Artha- Samiti (Finance Committee), the 
Institute Board and of such other authorities as may be declared by 
the Statutes to be authorities of the University shall be such as may 
be prescribed by the Statutes."]


</article>



<article><tid>1697353</tid>
<number>26</number>Alumni Association. The University shall have an Alumni 
Association open to past students and past workers of the University, 
including members of the Asramika Sangha of the former Visva- Bharati 
Society, on such conditions as may be laid down in the Statutes.
STATUTES, ORDINANCES AND REGULATIONS



</article>



<article><tid>470230</tid>
<number> 27</number> Statutes. Subject to the provisions of this Act, the 
Statutes may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>1146532</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of appointment, of the Upacharya (Vice-  
  Chancellor), the term of his appointments, emoluments and other 
conditions of his service;

</section>

<section><tid>1584</tid>
<number>b</number>the powers that may be exercised and the functions that 
may be performed by the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor);

</section>

<section><tid>1531071</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner of appointment of the Karma- Sachiva 
 (Registrar), the emoluments and other conditions of his service 
and the powers that may be exercised and the functions that may 
be performed by him;

</section>

<section><tid>1726069</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner of appointment of all other officers, the 
terms of their appointment, emoluments and other conditions of 
their service and the powers and functions of such officers;

</section>

<section><tid>1596625</tid>
<number>e</number>the constitution of the Samsad (Court), the term of 
office of its members and its powers and functions;

</section>

<section><tid>1436114</tid>
<number>f</number>the constitution of the Karma- Samiti (Executive  
  Council), the term of office of its members and its powers and 
functions;

</section>

<section><tid>1753652</tid>
<number>g</number>the constitution of other authorities or bodies of the 
University, the term of office of their members and their powers 
and functions;

</section>

<section><tid>1256340</tid>
<number>h</number>the election and continuance in office of the members 
the said authorities and bodies, the filling up of vacancies of 
members and all other matters relating to those authorities and 
other bodies for which it may be necessary or desirable to 
provide;

</section>

<section><tid>1078868</tid>
<number>i</number>the appointment of adhyapakas and other academic staff 
and other employees of the University and their emoluments and 
other conditions of service;
Provided that where any person who had held any post and is 
in receipt of a pension or other form of retirement benefits is 
appointed as an adhyapaka of the University or to any other 
academic post, the salary of such person together with the 
pension and other benefits shall not exceed the salary payable to 
him in accordance with the Statutes;


</section>

<section><tid>774268</tid>
<number>j</number>the appointment of adhyapakas and other academic staff 
working in any other University, institution or organisation for 
a specified period for undertaking a joint project;

</section>

<section><tid>626732</tid>
<number>k</number>the appointment of Visiting Professors, Emeritus 
Professors, Fellows, Scholars, Resident Artists and Resident 
Writers, and terms and conditions of such appointment;

</section>

<section><tid>391463</tid>
<number>l</number>the constitution of a pension or provident fund or the 
establishment of an insurance scheme for the benefit of the 
employees of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1843944</tid>
<number>m</number>the principles governing seniority of service of the 
employees of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1341495</tid>
<number>n</number>the procedure in relation to any appeal or application 
for review by any employee or student of the University, against 
the action of any officer or authority of the University, 
including the time within which such appeal or application for 
review may be preferred or made;

</section>

<section><tid>1466227</tid>
<number>o</number>the procedure for the settlement of disputes between 
employees of the University, or students of the University, and 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>178264</tid>
<number>p</number>the conferment of honorary degrees;

</section>

<section><tid>1329116</tid>
<number>q</number>the institution of fellowships, scholarships, 
studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>189260</tid>
<number>r</number>the maintenance of discipline among the employees and 
students of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1839957</tid>
<number>s</number>the establishment and abolition of Bhavanas, 
Departments, Chatravasas and other institutions and their 
management, supervision and inspection;

</section>

<section><tid>289833</tid>
<number>t</number>the regulation of the conduct and duties of the 
employees of the University and the conduct of the students of 
the University;

</section>

<section><tid>908170</tid>
<number>u</number>the establishment of campuses, special centres, 
specialised laboratories or other units for research and 
instruction;

</section>

<section><tid>902532</tid>
<number>v</number>the administration and regulation of the funds received 
in trust or otherwise by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>575401</tid>
<number>w</number>the delegation of powers vested in the officers or 
authorities of the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1343418</tid>
<number>x</number>the constitution and activities of the Alumni 
Association;

</section>

<section><tid>685904</tid>
<number>y</number>the categories of misconduct for which any action may 
be taken under this Act, or the Statutes or the Ordinances; and

</section>

<section><tid>1690856</tid>
<number>z</number>all other matters which, by this Act, are to be, or may 
be, provided for by the Statutes."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>90</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 17, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1924001</tid>
<number> 28</number> Statutes, how made.
<section><tid>1186268</tid>
<number>1</number>On the commencement of the Visva-  
Bharati (Amendment) Act, <year>1984</year> (31 of <year>1984</year>), the Statutes in force 
immediately before such commencement, as amended by that Act, 
shall be the Statutes of the University."]

</section>

<section><tid>1630572</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Statutes may be amended, repealed or added to by 
Statutes made by the Karma Samiti (Executive Council).

</section>

<section><tid>1538565</tid>
<number>3</number>The Karma Samiti (Executive Council) shall not propose the 
draft of any Statute affecting the status, powers or constitution of 
any authority of the University until such authority has been given an 
opportunity of expressing the opinion upon the proposal and any 
opinion so expressed shall be in writing and shall be submitted to the 
Paridarsaka (Visitor).

</section>

<section><tid>1349215</tid>
<number>4</number>Every new Statute or addition to a Statute or any amendment 
or repeal of a Statute shall be submitted to the Paridarsaka (Visitor) 
who may assent to it or withhold his assent therefrom or remit it to 
the Karma Samiti (Executive Council) for further consideration.

</section>

<section><tid>171771</tid>
<number>5</number>A Statute passed by the Karma Samiti (Executive Council) 
shall have no validity until it has been assented to by the 
Paridarsaka (Visitor).]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>404814</tid>
<number> 29</number> Matters to be provided for in the Ordinances. Subject to 
the provisions of this Act and the Statutes, the Ordinances may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
<section><tid>753367</tid>
<number>a</number>the admission of students to the University and their 
enrolment as such;

</section>

<section><tid>333294</tid>
<number>b</number>the pattern of learning process, courses of study to be 
laid down for all degrees, diplomas and certificates of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>832879</tid>
<number>c</number>the degrees, diplomas, certificates and other academic 
distinctions to be awarded by the University, the qualifications 
for the same and the means to be adopted relating to the granting 
and obtaining of the same;

</section>

<section><tid>153970</tid>
<number>d</number>the purposes for which certificates awarded by the Lok 
Siksha- Samsad (People' s Education Council) of the University may 
be recognised by the University;

</section>

<section><tid>1541537</tid>
<number>e</number>the fees to be charged for courses of study in the 
University and for admission to the examinations, and processes 
of evaluation, degrees, diplomas and certificates of the 
University;

</section>

<section><tid>955801</tid>
<number>f</number>the conditions of the award of fellowships, 
scholarships, studentships, medals and prizes;

</section>

<section><tid>1009746</tid>
<number>g</number>the conduct of tests, evaluations and examinations, 
including the terms of office and manner of appointment and 
duties of examining bodies, examiners, moderators and persons 
entrusted with the responsibility of evaluation;

</section>

<section><tid>1500014</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions of residence of the students of the 
University and the special arrangements, if any, for the 
residence of women students;

</section>

<section><tid>3967</tid>
<number>i</number>the special arrangements, if any, which may be made for 
the discipline and teaching of women students, and prescribing 
for them special courses of study;

</section>

<section><tid>1137882</tid>
<number>j</number>the terms and conditions of service of the employees of 
the University other than those prescribed by the Statutes 
 (including the emoluments of the non- teaching staff):
Provided that where any person who had held any post and is 
in receipt of a pension or other form of retirement benefits is 
appointed to a non- teaching post of the University, the salary 
such person together with the pension and other benefits shall 
not exceed the salary payable to him in accordance with the 
Ordinances;


</section>

<section><tid>1588588</tid>
<number>k</number>the terms and conditions of approval of institutions of 
higher learning and its withdrawal;

</section>

<section><tid>381072</tid>
<number>l</number>the manner of co- operation or collaboration or 
association with other Universities, authorities or institutions 
of learning;

</section>

<section><tid>651648</tid>
<number>m</number>the terms and conditions on which persons working in an 
approved institution, or in any institution co- operating, 
collaborating or associating with the University, may be approved 
as adhyapakas and for withdrawing such approval;

</section>

<section><tid>1846875</tid>
<number>n</number>the educational experimentation and the creation, 
composition and functioning of any other body which is considered 
necessary for improving the academic life of the University; and

</section>

<section><tid>1935751</tid>
<number>o</number>all other matters which, by this Act or the Statutes, 
are to be, or may be, provided for by the Ordinances.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1614178</tid>
<number> 30</number> Power to make Ordinances.
<section><tid>1792696</tid>
<number>1</number>The Ordinances in force  
immediately before the commencement of the Visva- Bharati (Amendment) 
Act, <year>1984</year> (31 of <year>1984</year>), may be amended, repealed or added to, at any 
time by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council);
Provided that no Ordinance shall be made in respect of matters 
enumerated in section 29, other than those enumerated in clauses (e), 
 (h), (j), (m) and (o) thereof, unless a draft of such Ordinance has 
been proposed by the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council).


</section>

<section><tid>866461</tid>
<number>2</number>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall not have power to 
amend any draft proposed by the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) under 
the provisions of sub- section (1), but may reject the proposal or 
return the draft to the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) for 
reconsideration either in whole or in part, together with any 
amendments which the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) may suggest.

</section>

<section><tid>25014</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) has rejected or 
returned the draft of an Ordinance proposed by the Siksha- Samiti 
 (Academic Council), the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) may consider 
the question afresh and in case the original draft is reaffirmed by a 
majority of not less than one- half of the total membership of the 
Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) and by a majority of not less than 
two- thirds of the members of the Siksha- Samiti (Academic Council) 
present and voting, the draft may be sent back to the Karma- Samiti 
 (Executive Council), which shall either adopt it or refer it to the 
Paridarsaka (Visitor) whose decision thereon shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>927680</tid>
<number>4</number>Every Ordinance made by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) 
shall come into effect immediately.

</section>

<section><tid>1425930</tid>
<number>5</number>Every Ordinance made by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) 
shall be submitted to the Paridarsaka (Visitor) within four weeks of 
the date of the meeting of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), and 
the Paridarsaka (Visitor) shall have the power to direct the 
University, within six weeks from the date of the receipt of the 
Ordinance, to suspend the operation of any Ordinance and he shall, as 
soon as possible, inform the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) about 
his objection to the proposed Ordinance.

</section>

<section><tid>1061441</tid>
<number>6</number>The Paridarsaka (Visitor) may, after receiving the comments 
of the University, either withdraw the order directing the suspension 
of the Ordinance or disallow the Ordinance and his decision thereon 
shall be final."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>92</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, S. 18 (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1971</year>, s. 7, for sub- section (2) to (8)  (w. e. f.  
  3- 11- <year>1971</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 19 (w. e. f. 8- 8- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1585030</tid>
<number> 31</number> Regulations.
<section><tid>556546</tid>
<number>1</number>The authorities of the University may make  
Regulations consistent with this Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances- 
-

<subsection><tid>1004080</tid>
<number>a</number>laying down the procedure to be observed at their 
meetings and the number of members required to form a 
quorum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1471815</tid>
<number>b</number>providing for all matters which by this Act, the 
Statutes or the Ordinances are to be prescribed by the 
Regulations; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1925229</tid>
<number>c</number>providing for all other matters solely concerning the 
authorities or committees appointed by them and not 
provided for by this Act, the Statutes and the 
Ordinances.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>93</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1406979</tid>
<number>2</number>Every authority of the University shall make Regulations 
providing for the giving of notice to the members of such authority of 
the dates of meetings and of the business to be considered at meetings 
and for the keeping of a record of the proceedings of meetings.

</section>

<section><tid>1328823</tid>
<number>3</number>The Karma Samiti (Executive Council) may direct the 
amendment, in such manner as it may specify, of any Regulation made 
under this section or the amendment of any Regulation made under sub- 
section (1).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>510871</tid>
<number>32</number>Residence. Every student of the University <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> other than a 
student of its Loka Shiksha Samsad (People' s Education Council)] shall 
reside in a[ Chatravasa] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or under such conditions as may be 
prescribed by the Statutes and the Ordinances.
ADMISSION AND EXAMINATIONS



</article>



<article><tid>792722</tid>
<number>33</number>Admission. Admission of students to the University shall be 
made in such manner as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>161438</tid>
<number>34</number>Examinations. Subject to the provisions of the Statutes, all 
arrangements for the conduct of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> tests, evaluations and 
examinations] shall be made by the Karma Samiti (Executive Council) in 
such manner as may be prescribed by the Ordinances.
ANNUAL REPORTS AND ACCOUNTS



</article>



<article><tid>370561</tid>
<number> 35</number> Annual report.
<section><tid>325153</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual report of the University  
shall be prepared under the directions of the Karma- Samiti (Executive  
  Council) which shall include, among other matters, the steps taken by 
the University to promote socially relevant research in physical and 
social sciences, weaker sections' need oriented extension activities 
and integration of the community life of the University with that of 
the wider world.

</section>

<section><tid>78450</tid>
<number>2</number>The annual report so prepared shall be submitted to the 
Samsad (Court) on or before such date as may be prescribed by the 
Statutes and shall be considered by the Samsad (Court) in its annual 
meeting.

</section>

<section><tid>796399</tid>
<number>3</number>The Samsad (Court) may communicate its comments on the annual 
report to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) and the Paridarsaka 
 (Visitor).

</section>

<section><tid>1368705</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the annual report, as prepared under sub- section 
 (1) shall also be submitted to the Central Government which shall, as 
soon as may be, cause the same to be laid before both the Houses of 
Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1999193</tid>
<number> 36</number> Annual Accounts.
<section><tid>765095</tid>
<number>1</number>The annual accounts and balance- sheet of  
the University shall be prepared under the direction of the 
Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) and shall once at least every year 
and at intervals of not more than fifteen months, be audited by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or by such person or persons 
as he may authorise in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>613248</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of the accounts together with the audit report shall 
be submitted to the Samsad (Court) and the Paridarsaka (Visitor) along 
with the observations of the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).

</section>

<section><tid>1364820</tid>
<number>3</number>Any observations made by the Paridarsaka (Visitor) on the 
annual accounts shall be brought to the notice of the Samsad (Court) 
and the observations of the Samsad (Court), if any, shall, after being 
considered by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), be submitted to 
the Paridarsaka (Visitor).

</section>

<section><tid>586315</tid>
<number>4</number>A copy of the accounts together with the audit report, as 
submitted to the Paridarsaka (Visitor), shall also be submitted to the 
Central Government, which shall, as soon as may be, cause the same to 
be laid before both the Houses of Parliament.

</section>

<section><tid>265799</tid>
<number>5</number>The audited annual accounts, after having been laid before 
both the Houses of Parliament, shall be published in the Gazette of 
India."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>94</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 60 of <year>1961</year>, s. 13. 
2. Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 20, (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 21, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 22, ibid. (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


SUPPLEMENTARY PROVISIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1534502</tid>
<number> 37</number> Adhyapakas of the University to be appointed under a 
written contract.
<section><tid>1630799</tid>
<number>1</number>No adhyapaka of the University shall be  
appointed to a permanent post, except under a written contract and 
such contract shall not be inconsistent with the provisions of this 
Act, the Statutes and the Ordinances.

</section>

<section><tid>327772</tid>
<number>2</number>The contract referred to in sub- section (1) shall be lodged 
with the University and a copy thereof shall be furnished to the 
adhyapaka concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1937597</tid>
<number>3</number>In the case of an adhyapaka appointed by the University 
before the commencement of the Visva- Bharati (Amendment) Act, <year>1984</year> 
 (31 of <year>1984</year>), the contract in force immediately before such 
commencement, in relation to his emoluments, shall, to the extent of 
any inconsistency with the provisions of this Act or the Statutes or 
the Ordinances, be deemed to have been modified by the said provisions 
and where there is no such contract and the adhyapaka is a salaries 
adhyapaka appointed to a permanent post, a written contract shall be 
executed by, and between, such adhyapaka and the University within a 
period of six months from the commencement of the Visva- Bharati 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1984</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1743391</tid>
<number> 38</number> Tribunal of Arbitration.
<section><tid>1118538</tid>
<number>1</number>Any dispute arising out of a  
contract of employment referred to in section 37, including a dispute 
relating to the noncompliance of the provisions of this Act, the 
Statutes or the Ordinances, shall, at the request of the adhyapaka, be 
referred to a Tribunal of Arbitration which shall consist of one 
member nominated by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council), one member 
nominated by the adhyapaka concerned and one member (who shall act as  
  umpire) nominated by the Paridarsaka (Visitor).

</section>

<section><tid>255754</tid>
<number>2</number>Every request made under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to 
be a submission to arbitration upon the terms of this section within 
the meaning of the Arbitration Act, <year>1940</year> (10 of <year>1940</year>), and all the 
provisions of that Act, with the exception of section 2 thereof, 
shall apply accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1862897</tid>
<number>3</number>If, for any reason, a vacancy occurs in the office of a 
member of the Tribunal of Arbitration, the appropriate body or person 
concerned shall nominate another person in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- section (1) to fill the vacancy and the proceedings 
may be continued before the Tribunal from the stage at which the 
vacancy is filled.

</section>

<section><tid>1887483</tid>
<number>4</number>The decision of the Tribunal of Arbitration shall be final 
and binding on the parties.

</section>

<section><tid>354590</tid>
<number>5</number>The Tribunal of Arbitration shall have the power--

<subsection><tid>540502</tid>
<number>a</number>to regulate its own procedure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1988022</tid>
<number>b</number>to order reinstatement of the adhyapaka concerned; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>745794</tid>
<number>c</number>to award salary to the adhyapaka concerned, after 
deducting therefrom such income, not being income from property, 
as such adhyapaka might have derived during the period of his 
suspension or during the period intervening between the date on 
which he was removed or dismissed from service or, as the case 
may be, his service was terminated, and the date on which he is 
reinstated:
Provided that the income which could have been derived by the 
adhyapaka concerned shall not be taken into account if, at the time 
when the income was derived, he could have derived such income had he 
not been suspended or removed or dismissed from service or if his 
service had not been terminated.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>870319</tid>
<number>6</number>No suit or other proceedings shall lie in any court in 
respect of any matter which is required by sub- section (1) to be 
referred to the Tribunal of Arbitration.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>83050</tid>
<number> 38A</number> Power to suspend adhyapaka or other member of academic 
staff.
<section><tid>760224</tid>
<number>1</number>The Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) may, by order in writing,  
place and adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff under 
suspension--

<subsection><tid>1865301</tid>
<number>a</number>where a disciplinary proceeding against such adhyapaka 
or other member is contemplated or is pending; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1919427</tid>
<number>b</number>where a case against him in respect of any criminal 
offence is under investigation or trial.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>610862</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any order of suspension is made under sub- section (1), 
the circumstances in which such order has been made shall be reported 
forthwith to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).

</section>

<section><tid>1932898</tid>
<number>3</number>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) may, within fifteen days 
from the date of receipt of the report referred to in sub- section (2), 
revoke the order of suspension if it is of opinion that the 
circumstances of the case do not warrant the suspension.

</section>

<section><tid>716977</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person aggrieved by an order of suspension, which has not 
been revoked under sub- section (3), may prefer an appeal to the Karma- 
Samiti (Executive Council) within thirty days from the date on which 
such order is communicated to him and the Karma- Samiti (Executive  
  Council) may confirm modify or reverse the order appealed against.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>801141</tid>
<number> 38B</number> Authorities by whom order for removal or dismissal or 
adhyapaka, etc., may be made and the procedure therefor.
<section><tid>1799738</tid>
<number>1</number>No  
adhyapaka, or other member of the academic staff, appointed by the 
University shall be dismissed or removed from service or punished in 
any other manner by any authority other than the Karma- Samiti 
 (Executive Council).

</section>

<section><tid>226339</tid>
<number>2</number>No adhyapaka, or other member of the academic staff, 
appointed by the University shall be dismissed or removed from service 
or punished in any other manner except after an inquiry in which he 
has been informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard in respect of those charges:
Provided that where it is proposed after such inquiry, to impose 
upon the adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff any 
punishment, such punishment may be imposed on the basis of the 
evidence adduced during such inquiry and it shall not be necessary to 
give such adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff any 
opportunity of making representation on the punishment proposed.


</section>

<section><tid>1138080</tid>
<number>3</number>The Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) shall be entitled to 
dismiss or remove from service, without holding any such inquiry as is 
referred to in sub- section (2), an adhyapaka, or other member of the 
academic staff, of the University, where the Karma- Samiti (Executive  
  Council), for reasons to be recorded in writing, is satisfied that 
such adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff-

<subsection><tid>1855654</tid>
<number>a</number>is of unsound mind or is a deaf- mute or suffers from 
contagious leprosy; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>287278</tid>
<number>b</number>is an undischarged insolvent; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>963548</tid>
<number>c</number>has been convicted, by a court of law, of an offence 
involving moral turpitude.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1778183</tid>
<number>4</number>The dismissal or removal from service of, or any other 
punishment imposed on, an adhyapaka, or other member of the academic 
staff, appointed by the University shall take effect from the date on 
which the order of dismissal or removal from service is made or other 
punishment is imposed:
Provided that, where the adhyapaka or other member of the 
academic staff is under suspension at the time when the order for his 
dismissal or removal from service is made or other punishment is 
imposed, such order may, if the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) so 
directs, take effect from the date on which he was placed under 
suspension.


</section>

<section><tid>474117</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding the terms of contract between the University 
and an adhyapaka, or other member of the academic staff, appointed by 
the University, such adhyapaka or other member of the academic staff 
may resign his office--

<subsection><tid>1041343</tid>
<number>a</number>where he is permanent, by giving three months' notice 
in writing to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) or by paying 
to the University three months' salary in lieu of such notice; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>813270</tid>
<number>b</number>where he is not permanent, one month' s notice in 
writing to the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) or by paying to 
the University one month' s salary in lieu of such notice:
Provided that if the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council) so permits, 
the period of three months' notice or of one month' s notice, as the 
case may be, may be reduced or waived:

Provided further that such resignation shall take effect from the 
date on which it is accepted by the Karma- Samiti (Executive Council).

Explanation.--" Suspension" shall not be deemed to be a punishment 
within the meaning of this section."]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>636902</tid>
<number> 39</number> Pension and provident funds.
<section><tid>803048</tid>
<number>1</number>The University shall  
constitute, for the benefit of its officers[ including the Upacharya 
 (Vice- Chancellor)],[ teachers'], and other servants, in such manner 
and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed by the Statutes, 
such pension, insurance and provident funds as it may deem fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1501335</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any such pension, insurance or provident fund has been 
so constituted, the Central Government may declare that the provisions 
of the Provident Funds Act, <year>1925</year> (19 of <year>1925</year>), shall apply to such 
fund as if it were a Government Provident Fund.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>407335</tid>
<number> 40</number> Filling of casual vacancies.
<section><tid>406984</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any provision in  
this Act and in the Statutes, the Karma Samiti (Executive Council) 
shall appoint, with the approval of the Paridarsaka (Visitor), a 
person to fill a casual vacancy
<pagefootnote><pagenum>95</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>. s. 23 (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


in the office of the Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor), and the person so 
appointed shall hold office <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> until his successor enters upon his 
office].


</section>

<section><tid>1181531</tid>
<number>2</number>All casual vacancies among the members (other than ex officio  
  members) of any authority or other body of the University shall be 
filled, as soon as conveniently may be, by the person or body who 
appointed, elected or co- opted the member whose place has become 
vacant, and the Person appointed, clected or co- opted to a casual 
vacancy shall be member of such authority or body for the residue of 
the term for which the person whose place he fills would have been a 
member.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1274733</tid>
<number>41</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Removal from membership of the University. The Karma 
Samiti (Executive Council) may, on the recommendation of not less than 
two- thirds of its members remove any person from the membership of any 
authority or board of the University if such a person is guilty of a 
serious offence involving moral turpitude, or if he has been guilty of 
scandalous conduct and for the same reasons may withdraw any degree or 
diploma conferred on, or granted to, any person by the University:
Provided that no action shall be taken under this section against 
any person except after giving him a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard with regard to the proposed action.]



</article>



<article><tid>1790207</tid>
<number>42</number>Disputes as to constitution of any University authority or 
body. If any question arises whether any person has been duly elected 
or appointed as, or is entitled to be, a member of any authority or 
other body of the University, the matter shall be referred to the 
Paridarsaka (Visitor), whose decision thereon shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>291981</tid>
<number>43</number>Constitution of committees. Where any authority of the 
University is given power by this Act or by the Statutes to appoint 
committees, such committee shall, unless there is some special 
provision to the contrary, consist of members of the authority 
concerned and of such other persons (if any) as the authority in each 
case may think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>676836</tid>
<number>44</number>Proceedings of the University authorities not invalidated by 
vacancies. No act or proceeding of any authority or other body of the 
University shall be invalidated merely by reason of the existence of a 
vacancy or vacancies among its members.


</article>



<article><tid>67327</tid>
<number>44A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or 
other legal proceeding shall lie against any officer or employee of 
the University for anything which is in good faith done, or intended 
to be done, in pursuance of the provisions of this Act, the Statutes 
or the Ordinances.


</article>



<article><tid>1970872</tid>
<number>44B</number>Mode of proof of University record. A copy of any receipt, 
application, notice, order, proceeding or resolution of any authority 
or committee of the University, or other documents in the possession 
of the University, or any entry in any register duly maintained by the 
University, if certified by the Karma- Sachiva (Registrar), shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> 
 (1 of <year>1872</year>), or in any other law for the time being in force, be 
admitted as evidence of the matters and transactions specified therein 
where the original thereof would, if produced, have been admissible in 
evidence."]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>96</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 60 of <year>1961</year>, s. 15, for" till the next meeting of the 
Samsad (Court)". 
2. Subs. by Act 57 of <year>1971</year>, s. 11, for s. 41 (w. e. f. 3- 11- <year>1971</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 31 of <year>1984</year>, s. 24 (w. e. f. 8. 8. <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>806514</tid>
<number>45</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises with 
respect to the establishment of the University or any authority of the 
University or in connection with the first meeting of any authority of 
the University, the Paridarsaka (Visitor) in consultation with the 
Upacharya (Vice- Chancellor) may, by order, make any appointment or do 
anything which appears to him necessary or expedient for the proper 
establishment of the University or any authority thereof or for the 
first meeting of any authority of the University.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>97</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</article>



 </act>