<act><title>


The Foreign Recruiting Act, 1874</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—This 
    Act may be called the Foreign Recruiting Act, 1874. 
 

    Local extent.—It 
    extends to the whole of India 

    1[***]. 
 


    2[***]  
 


    3[***]  
  
  









 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    “Foreign State” defined.—In 
    this Act, “Foreign State” includes any person or persons exercising or 
    assuming to exercise the powers of Government in or over any country, 
    colony, province or people beyond the limits of 

    1[India].  
  
  







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Power to prohibit or permit recruiting.—If 
    any person is, within the limits of (r) 

    1[India], obtaining 
    or attempting to obtain recruits for the service of any Foreign State in any 
    capacity, the Central Government may, by order in writing 

    2[***], either 
    prohibit such person from so doing, or permit him to do so subject to any 
    conditions which the Central Government thinks fit to impose.
  
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Power to impose conditions.—The 
    Central Government may, from time to time, by general order notified in the 
    Official Gazette, either prohibit recruiting for the service of any Foriegn 
    State or impose upon such recruiting any conditions which it thinks fit.  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Power to rescind or vary orders.—The 
    Central Government may rescind or vary any order made under this Act in such 
    manner as it thinks fit.  
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Offences.—Whoever, 
    in violation of the prohibition of the Central Government, or of any 
    condition subject to which permission to recruit may have been accorded,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   induces or attempts 
    to induce any person to accept or agree to accept or to proceed to any place 
    with a view to obtaining any commission or employment in the service of any 
    Foreign State, or 
tc " (a) induces or attempts to induce any 
    person to accept or agree to accept or to proceed to any place with a view 
    to obtaining any commission or employment in the service of any Foreign 
    State, or " 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   knowingly aids in 
    the engagement of any person so induced, by forwarding or conveying him or 
    by advancing money or in any other way whatever,  
 
shall be liable to 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years, or to fine to such 
    amount as the court thinks fit or to both.
  
  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Place of trial.—Any 
    offence against this Act may be inquired into and tried, as well in any 
    district in which the person accused may be found as in any district in 
    which it might be enquired into and tried under the provisions of the Code 
    of Criminal Procedure8.
  
  







 



</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>