<act><tid>1762890</tid>
<title>THE MULTIMODAL TRANSPORTATION OF GOODS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 44 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 5th December, <year>2000</year>.]

An Act to amend the Multimodal Transportation of Goods Act, <year>1993</year>.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>835075</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Multimodal Transportation 
of Goods (Amendment) Act, <year>2000</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1886654</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Multimodal 
Transportation of Goods Act, <year>1993</year> (28 of <year>1993</year>)  (hereinafter referred  
  to as the principal Act),-
<section><tid>398861</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (a), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>718392</tid>
<number>a</number>" carrier" means a person who performs or undertakes to perform 
for hire, the carriage or part thereof, of goods by road, rail, inland 
waterways, sea or air;';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1376525</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (i), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-

</section>

<section><tid>398861</tid>
<number>i</number>" goods" means any property ncluding live animals, containers, 
pallets or such other articles of transport or packaging supplied by 
the consignor, irrespective of whether such property is to be or is 
carried on or under the deck;';

</section>

<section><tid>793188</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (j), for the words" road, rail", the words" road, air, 
rail" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1476612</tid>
<number>iv</number>for clauses (k) and (l), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1098977</tid>
<number>k</number>" multimodal transportation" means carriage of goods, by at least 
two different modes of transport under a multimodal transport 
contract, from the place of acceptance of the goods in India to a 
place of delivery of the goods outside India;';

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1681954</tid>
<number>l</number>" multimodal transport contract" means a contract under which a 
multimodal transport operator undertakes to perform or procure the 
performance of multimodal transportation against payment of freight;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>876418</tid>
<number>la</number>" multimodal transport document" means a negotiable or 
non- negotiable document evidencing a multimodal transport contract and 
which can be replaced by electronic data interchange messages 
permitted by applicable law;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>317458</tid>
<number>v</number>in clause (m), in sub- clause (ii), for the words" not as an agent 
either of the consignor or of the carrier", the words" not as an agent 
either of the consignor, or consignee or of the carrier" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>810663</tid>
<number>vi</number>after clause (q), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>467725</tid>
<number>r</number>" special drawing rights" means such units of accounts as are 
determined by the International Monetary Fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>731521</tid>
<number>s</number>" taking charge" means that the goods have been handed over to and 
accepted for carriage by the multimodal transport operator;'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1920069</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>426921</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (3), for clause (a), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (a) 


</section>

<section><tid>426921</tid>
<number>i</number>that the applicant is a company, firm or proprietary concern, 
engaged either in the business of shipping, or freight forwarding in 
India or abroad with a minimum annual turnover of fifty lakh rupees 
during the immediately preceding financial yea or an average annual 
turnover of fifty lakh rupees during the preceding three financial 
years as certified by a Chartered Accountant within the meaning of the 
Chartered Accountants Act, <year>1949</year> (38 of <year>1949</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>673230</tid>
<number>ii</number>that if the applicant is a company, firm or proprietary concern 
other than a company, firm or proprietary concern, specified in 
sub- clause (i), the subscribed share capital of such company or the 
aggregate balance in the capital account of partners f the firm, or 
the capital of the proprietor is not less than fifty lakh rupees.";

</section>

<section><tid>673230</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (3), after the proviso, the following provisos 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided further that any applicant who is not a resident of India 
and who is not engaged in the business of shipping shall not be 
granted registration unless he has established a place of business in 
India:

Provided also that in respect of any applicant who is not a resident 
of India, the turnover may be certified by any authority competent to 
certify the accounts of a company in that country.";


</section>

<section><tid>253626</tid>
<number>iii</number>for sub- sections (4) and (5), the following sub- sections shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" (4) A certificate granted under sub- section (3) shall be valid for a 
period of three years and may be renewed from time to time for a 
further period of three years at a time.


<subsection><tid>778529</tid>
<number>5</number>An application for renewal shall be made in such form as may be 
prescribed and shall be accompanied by such amount of fees as may be 
notified by the Central Government:
Provided that such fees shall not be less than rupees ten thousand and 
shall not exceed rupees twenty thousand.


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1013731</tid>
<number>6</number>The competent authority shall renew the registration certificate 
granted under sub- section (3) if the applicant continues to fulfil the 
conditions as laid down at the time of registration.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>389613</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 6.- In section 6 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) Any person aggrieved by, refusal of the competent authority to 
grant or renew registration under section 4 or by cancellation of 
registration under section 5, may prefer an appeal to the Central 
Government within such period as may be prescribed.".



</article>



<article><tid>710516</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 7.- In section 7 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the multimodal transport operator shall issue the 
multimodal transport document only after obtaining, and during the 
subsistence of a valid insurance cover.".



</article>



<article><tid>214393</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 9.- In section 9 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>934889</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (a), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (a) the general nature of the goods, the leading marks necessary for 
identification of the goods, the character of the goods (including  
  dangerous goods), the number of packages or units and the gross weight 
and quantity of the goods as declared by the c nsignor;";


</section>

<section><tid>705014</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (h), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (h) the date or the period of delivery of the goods by the multimodal 
transport operator as expressly agreed upon between the consignor and 
the multimodal transport operator;";


</section>

<section><tid>1566890</tid>
<number>iii</number>for clause (k), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (k) freight payable by the consignor or the consignee, as the case 
may be, to be mentioned only if expressly agreed by both the consignor 
and the consignee;";


</section>

<section><tid>1065757</tid>
<number>iv</number>after clause (o), the following proviso shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" Provided that the absence of any of the particulars listed above 
shall not affect the legal character of the multimodal transport 
document.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>805978</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the second proviso, the following proviso shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" Provided further that the multimodal transport operator shall not be 
liable for loss or damage arising out of delay in delivery including 
any consequential loss or damage arising from such delay unless the 
consignor had made a declaration of interest in timely delivery which 
has been accepted by the multimodal transport operator.".



</article>



<article><tid>1778363</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 14.- In section 14 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the Explanation, the following Explanation shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" Explanation.- For the purpose of this sub- section, where a container, 
pallet or similar article is stuffed with more than one package or 
units, the packages or units enumerated in the multimodal transport 
document, as packed in such container, pallet or imilar article of 
transport shall be deemed as packages or units.".



</article>



<article><tid>1064110</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of section 15.- In section 15 of the principal Act, the 
following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the multimodal transport operator shall not be liable 
for any loss, damage or delay in delivery due to a cause for which the 
carrier is exempted from liability in accordance with the applicable 
law.".



</article>



<article><tid>447377</tid>
<number>10</number>Insertion of new section 20A.- After section 20, the following 
section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 20A. Period of responsibility.- The responsibility of the multimodal 
transport operator for the goods under this Act shall cover the period 
from the time he has taken the goods in his charge to the time of 
their delivery.".



</article>



<article><tid>435981</tid>
<number>11</number>Amendment of Act 26 of <year>1925</year>.- In the Indian Carriage of Goods by 
Sea Act, <year>1925</year>, in Schedule, in Article I, for clause (c), the 
following clause shall be substituted, namely:-
' (c)" Goods" includes any property including live animals as well as 
containers, pallets or similar articles of transport or packaging 
supplied by the consignor, irrespective of whether such property is to 
be or is carried on or under deck;'.

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>