<act><tid>1769128</tid>
<title>THE ESSO (ACQUISITION OF UNDERTAKINGS IN INDIA) ACT, <year>1974</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1974</year>
[ 13th March, <year>1974</year>.] W

An Act to provide for the acquisition and transfer of the right, title 
and interest of Esso Eastern Inc. in relation to its undertakings in 
India with a view to ensuring co- ordinated distribution and 
utilisation of petroleum products distributed and marketed in India by 
Esso Eastern Inc. and for matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1802745</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Esso (Acquisition of  
  Undertakings in India) Act, <year>1974</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1565444</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1257236</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>887252</tid>
<number>b</number>" Esso" means Esso Eastern Inc., a foreign company within 
the meaning of section 591 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (1 of <year>1956</year>), incorporated under the laws of the State 
of Delaware

<pagefootnote><pagenum>436</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

in the United States of America, and having its 
principal office at 2401 South Gessner, City of 
Houston, State of Texas, in the United States of 
America;


</section>

<section><tid>1250660</tid>
<number>c</number>" Esso Standard" means Esso Standard Refining Company of 
India Limited, being a company as defined in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and having its 
registered office at Administration Building, Mahul, 
Bombay 400 074;

</section>

<section><tid>8874</tid>
<number>d</number>" Government company" means a company as defined in 
section 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>511850</tid>
<number>e</number>" Lube India" means Lube India Limited, being a company 
as defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and 
having its registered office at Administration 
Building, Corridor Road, Mahul, Bombay 400 074;

</section>

<section><tid>1845090</tid>
<number>f</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1235417</tid>
<number>g</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.
CHAP

ACQUISITION OF THE UNDERTAKINGS IN INDIA OF ESSO

CHAPTER II

ACQUISITION OF THE UNDERTAKINGS IN INDIA OF ESSO




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1517670</tid>
<number>3</number>Transfer and vesting in the Central Government of the 
undertakings of Esso in India. On the appointed day, the right, title 
and interest of Esso, in relation to its undertakings in India, shall 
stand transferred to, and shall vest in, the Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>170709</tid>
<number> 4</number> General effect of vesting.
<section><tid>1242548</tid>
<number>1</number>The undertakings referred to in  
section 3 shall be deemed, save as otherwise provided in sub- section 
 (2), to include all assets, rights, powers, authorities and privileges 
and all property, movable and immovable, cash balances, reserve funds, 
investments and all other rights and interests in, or arising out of, 
such property as were, immediately before the appointed day, in the 
ownership, possession, power or control of Esso, in relation to its 
undertakings in India, and all books of account, registers, records 
and all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto and shall 
also be deemed to include all borrowings, liabilities and obligations 
of whatever kind then subsisting of Esso in relation to its 
undertakings in India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>437</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1536286</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertakings referred to in sub- section (1) shall not 
include the following, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1637001</tid>
<number>a</number>any share held by Esso in the equity capital of Esso 
Standard or Lube India;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>468734</tid>
<number>b</number>any trade mark, and any right of Esso to use any trade 
mark in India, specified in the First Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>72885</tid>
<number>c</number>all patents and designs registered in India in the name 
of Esso.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1055786</tid>
<number>3</number>Unless otherwise expressly provided by this Act, all deeds, 
bonds, agreements, powers of attorney, grants of legal representation 
and other instruments of whatever nature in relation to the 
undertakings of Esso in India, subsisting or having effect immediately 
before the appointed day, and to which Esso is a party or which are in 
favour of Esso shall be of as full force and effect against or in 
favour of the Central Government and may be enforced or acted upon as 
fully and effectually as if in the place of Esso the Central 
Government had been a party thereto or as if they had been issued in 
favour of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>602428</tid>
<number>4</number>If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other 
proceeding of whatever nature, in relation to the undertakings of Esso 
in India, which have been transferred to and vested in the Central 
Government under section 3, is pending by or against Esso, the same 
shall not abate, be discontinued or be, in any way, prejudicially 
affected by reason of the transfer of the undertakings of Esso or of 
anything contained in this Act, but the suit, appeal or other 
proceeding may be continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the 
Central Government, or, where any undertaking is directed under 
section 7 to vest in any Government company, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by or against the 
concerned Government company].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>586752</tid>
<number> 5</number> Central Government to be lessee or tenant under certain 
circumstances.
<section><tid>392161</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any property is held in India by Esso under  
any lease or under any right of tenancy, the Central Government shall, 
on and from the appointed day, be deemed to have become the lessee or 
tenant, as the case may be, in respect of such property as if the 
lease or tenancy in relation to such property had been granted to the 
Central Government, and thereupon all the rights under such lease or 
tenancy shall be deemed to have been transferred to and vested in the 
Central Government.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>438</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 38 of <year>1978</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" against the 
concerned Government company".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1986565</tid>
<number>2</number>On the expiry of the term of any lease or tenancy referred to 
in sub- section (1), such lease or tenancy shall, if so desired by the 
Central Government, be renewed on the same terms and conditions on 
which the lease or tenancy was held by Esso immediately before the 
appointed day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1367841</tid>
<number> 6</number> Removal of doubts.
<section><tid>1811047</tid>
<number>1</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby  
declared that the provisions of sections 3, 4 and 5 shall apply to the 
extent to which any property appertains to the business carried on by 
Esso in India; and to the rights and powers acquired, and to debts, 
liabilities and obligations incurred, and to contracts, agreements and 
other instruments made, by Esso in India, and to legal proceedings 
relating to those matters pending in any court or tribunal in India.

</section>

<section><tid>1211788</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any property appertains, 
on the appointed day, to any business of Esso in India, or, whether 
any rights, powers, liabilities or obligations were acquired or 
incurred or any contract, agreement or other instrument was made by 
Esso for the purposes of its business in India, or whether any 
documents relate to those purposes, the question shall be referred to 
the Central Government which shall, after giving an opportunity of 
being heard to the persons interested in the matter, decide it in such 
manner as it may think fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>62587</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power of Central Government to direct vesting of the 
undertakings of Esso in a Government company.
<section><tid>521439</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in sections 3, 4 and 5, the Central Government may, 
if it is satisfied that a Government company is willing to comply, or 
has complied, with such terms and conditions as that Government may 
think fit to impose, direct, by notification, that the right, title 
and interest and the liabilities of Esso in relation to any 
undertaking in India shall, instead of continuing to vest in the 
Central Government, vest in the Government company either on the date 
of the notification or on such earlier or later date (not being a date  
  earlier than the appointed day) as may be specified in the 
notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1225121</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the right, title and interest and the liabilities of 
Esso in relation to its undertakings in India vest in a Government 
company under sub- section (1), the Government company shall, on and 
from the date of such vesting, be deemed to have become the owner, 
tenant or lessee, as the case may be, in relation to such 
undertakings, and all the rights and liabilities of the Central 
Government in relation to such undertakings shall, on and from the 
date of such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>439</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

vesting, be deemed to have become the rights and liabilities, 
respectively, of the Government company.


</section>

<section><tid>1828270</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of sub- section (2) of section 5 shall apply to 
a lease or tenancy, which vests in a Government company, as they apply 
to a lease or tenancy vested in the Central Government and reference 
therein to the" Central Government" shall be construed as a reference 
to the Government company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1879707</tid>
<number> 8</number> Payment of amount.
<section><tid>234501</tid>
<number>1</number>For the transfer and vesting in the  
Central Government, under sections 3 and 4, of the right, title and 
interest of Esso in relation to its undertakings in India, and for the 
vesting in the Central Government, under section 5, of the rights 
specified therein, there shall be paid by the Central Government to 
Esso an amount of rupees two crores and fifty- nine lakhs in such 
instalments and in such manner as is specified in the Second Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>1177302</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount specified in sub- section (1) shall carry interest, 
free of income- tax, at the rate of six and a half per cent. per annum 
from the appointed day till the date of payment in the manner 
specified in the Second Schedule.
CHAP

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF ESSO

CHAPTER III

PROVISIONS RELATING TO EMPLOYEES OF ESSO




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1013955</tid>
<number> 9</number> Transfer of service of existing employees of Esso.
<section><tid>1133561</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
whole- time officer or other employee of Esso who was, immediately 
before the appointed day, employed by Esso in connection with its 
undertakings in India, and every whole- time officer or other employee 
of Esso who was, immediately before the appointed day, temporarily 
holding any assignment outside India, shall, on the appointed day, 
become an officer or other employee, as the case may be, of the 
Central Government or, as the case may be, the Government company in 
which the right, title and interest of Esso, in relation to its 
undertakings in India have vested under this Act and shall hold office 
or service under the Central Government or the Government company, as 
the case may be, on the same terms and conditions and with the same 
rights to pension, gratuity and other matters as would have been 
admissible to him if there had been no such vesting and shall continue 
to do so unless and until his employment under the Central Government 
or the Government

<pagefootnote><pagenum>440</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

company, as the case may be, is duly terminated or until his 
remuneration and conditions of service are duly altered by the Central 
Government or the Government company, as the case may be.


</section>

<section><tid>137562</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any person was a whole- 
time officer or other employee or as to whether any officer or other 
employee was employed wholly or mainly in connection with the 
undertakings of Esso in India immediately before the appointed day, or 
whether any whole- time officer or other employee of Esso was 
temporarily holding any assignment outside India, the question shall 
be referred, within a period of two years from the appointed day and 
not thereafter, to the Central Government which shall, after giving an 
opportunity of being heard to the person concerned in the matter, 
decide it in such manner as it thinks fit and such decision shall be 
final.

</section>

<section><tid>159609</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), the Payment of Gratuity Act, <year>1972</year> (39 of  
  <year>1972</year>), or in any other law for the time being in force, the transfer 
of the services of any officer or other employee under sub- section (1) 
shall not entitle any such officer or other employee to any 
compensation or gratuity under those Acts or such other law, and no 
such claim shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other 
authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>345452</tid>
<number> 10</number> Provident, superannuation, welfare fund, etc.
<section><tid>1321163</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a  
provident, superannuation, welfare or other fund has been established 
by Esso for the benefit of the persons employed by it in connection 
with its undertakings in India, the moneys relatable to the employees, 
whose services are transferred by or under this Act to the Central 
Government or a Government company, shall, out of the moneys standing, 
on the appointed day, to the credit of such provident, superannuation, 
welfare or other fund, stand transferred to and vest in the Central 
Government or the Government company, as the case may be, free from 
any trust that may have been constituted by Esso in respect thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>1418937</tid>
<number>2</number>The moneys which stand transferred, under sub- section (1), to 
the Central Government or a Government company shall be dealt with by 
the Central Government or that company, as the case may be, in such 
manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>734830</tid>
<number>3</number>The Government company in which the undertakings of Esso in 
India are directed to be vested shall, as soon as may be after the 
date of vesting, constitute, in respect of the moneys and other assets 
which are transferred to and vested in it under this section,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>441</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

one or more trusts having objects as similar to the objects of the 
existing trusts as in the circumstances may be practicable, so, 
however, that the rights and interests of the beneficiaries of the 
trust referred to in sub- section (1) are not, in any way, prejudiced 
or diminished.


</section>

<section><tid>895431</tid>
<number>4</number>Where all the moneys and other assets belonging to an 
existing trust are transferred to and vested in the Central Government 
or a Government company under this section, the trustees of such trust 
shall, as from the date of such vesting, stand discharged from the 
trust except as respects things done or omitted to be done before the 
date of such vesting.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>623798</tid>
<number>11</number>Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained 
in any other law for the time being in force or in any instrument 
having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act or in any 
decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>13273</tid>
<number> 12</number> Duty to deliver possession of properties, etc.
<section><tid>791796</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
property, appertaining to any undertaking of Esso in India has been 
transferred to, and vested in, the Central Government or a Government 
company under this Act:--

<subsection><tid>598950</tid>
<number>a</number>every person in whose possession, custody or control any 
such property may be, shall, on a demand by the Central 
Government or the Government company, as the case may 
be, deliver the property to the Central Government or 
the Government company, as the case may be, forthwith;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>3884</tid>
<number>b</number>any person who, immediately before such vesting, has in 
his possession, custody or control any books, documents 
or other papers relating to the undertakings of Esso in 
India, shall be liable to account for the said books, 
documents and papers to the Central Government or the 
Government company, as the case may be, and shall 
deliver them up to the Central Government or that 
company or to such person as the Central Government or 
that company may authorise in this behalf.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>442</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>329552</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the other provisions contained in this 
section, it shall be lawful for the Central Government or the 
Government company to take all necessary steps for taking possession 
of all properties which have been transferred to and vested in it 
under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1549618</tid>
<number> 13</number> Contracts to continuee unless terminated by Central 
Government.
<section><tid>1725098</tid>
<number>1</number>Every contract entered into by Esso for any service,  
sale or supply in India, and in force immediately before the appointed 
day, shall, unless terminated, under sub- section (2), within <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> one 
year] from the appointed day, continue to be of full force and effect 
against or in favour of the Central Government or the Government 
company in which the undertakings of Esso in India have vested under 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>644047</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, if it is satisfied that any 
contract referred to in sub- section (1) is unduly onerous or has been 
entered into in bad faith or is detrimental to the interests of that 
Government or the Government company, by order in writing, either 
terminate such contract or make such alterations or modifications 
therein as it may think fit:
Provided that the Central Government shall not terminate any 
contract or make any alteration or modification therein except after 
giving to the parties to the contract a reasonable opportunity of 
being heard and except after recording, in writing, its reasons for 
such termination, alteration or modification, as the case may be.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>409355</tid>
<number> 14</number> Penalties. Any person who,--
<section><tid>1358190</tid>
<number>a</number>having in his possession, custody or control any 
property forming part of any undertaking of Esso in 
India, wrongfully withholds such property from the 
Central Government or the Government company; or

</section>

<section><tid>184470</tid>
<number>b</number>wrongfully obtains possession of or retains any property 
forming part of any undertaking of Esso in India; or

</section>

<section><tid>1616238</tid>
<number>c</number>wilfully withholds or fails to furnish to the Central 
Government or the Government company or any person 
specified by the Central Government or that company, 
any books, documents or other papers relating to any 
undertaking of Esso in India which may be in his 
possession, custody or control; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>443</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1974</year>, s. 2, for" one hundred and eighty days".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1923548</tid>
<number>d</number>fails to deliver to the Central Government or the 
Government company any assets, books of account, 
registers or other documents in his possession, iustody 
or control relating to any undertaking of Esso in 
India; or

</section>

<section><tid>807466</tid>
<number>e</number>wrongfully removes or destroys any property pertaining 
to any undertaking of Esso in India; or

</section>

<section><tid>110993</tid>
<number>f</number>wrongfully uses any property forming part of the 
undertakings of Esso in India,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years, or with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, or 
with both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1019542</tid>
<number> 15</number> Officer by companies.
<section><tid>1790330</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act has  
been committed by a company, every person who at the time the offence 
was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company 
for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>582053</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>1826272</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>327343</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>444</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1794309</tid>
<number>16</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or the Government company or any of its officers or other 
employees for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
done under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1634469</tid>
<number>17</number>Cognizance of offences. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>), no court shall take 
cognizance of any offence against this Act except on a complaint, in 
writing, made by the Central Government or any officer authorised in 
this behalf by that Government.


</article>



<article><tid>22789</tid>
<number>18</number>Indemnity. Every officer of the Central Government and every 
officer or other employees of the Government company shall be 
indemnified by the Central Government or the Government company, as 
the case may be, against all losses and expenses incurred by him in, 
or in relation to, the discharge of his duties under this Act except 
such as have been caused by his own wilful act or default.


</article>



<article><tid>236298</tid>
<number>19</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, 
remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the appointed day.



</article>



<article><tid>1451752</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>57937</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>750939</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>445</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>