<act><tid>1770188</tid>
<title>THE ELECTRICITY REGULATORY COMMISSIONS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 21 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 29th August, <year>2001</year>]

An Act to amend the Electricity Regulatory Commissions Act, <year>1998</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>436895</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Electricity Regulatory 
Commissions (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>733584</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In the Electricity Regulatory Commissions 
Act, <year>1998</year> (14 of <year>1998</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), 
in section 2,-
<section><tid>1488939</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (c), for the words" or the State Commission", the words 
" or the State Commission or the Joint Electricity Regulatory 
Commission" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>334670</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (e), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (ea)" Joint Electricity Regulatory Commission" means the Joint 
Electricity Regulatory Commission constituted under section 21A;'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>99590</tid>
<number>3</number>Insertion of new Chapter IVA.- After Chapter IV of the principal 
Act, the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
" CHAPTER IVA

JOINT ELECTRICITY REGULATORY COMMISSION

</article>



<article><tid>1317672</tid>
<number> 21A</number> Constitution of Joint State Commission.-
<section><tid>1105658</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in this Act, an agreement may be entered into-

<subsection><tid>1157770</tid>
<number>a</number>by two or more State Governments,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1413155</tid>
<number>b</number>by the Central Government (in respect of one or more Union  
  territories) and one or more State Governments, to be in force for 
such period and to be subject to renewal for such further period, if 
any, as may be specified in the agreement to provide for the 
constitution of a Joint Electricity Regulatory Commission,-

<subsubsection><tid>1558958</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case referred to in clause (a), for all the participating 
States; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>12184</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case referred to in clause (b), for the participating Union 
territory or Union territories and the State or States.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1002533</tid>
<number>2</number>The Joint Electricity Regulatory Commission shall consist of one 
Member from each of the participating States and Union territories and 
the Chairperson shall be appointed from amongst the Members by 
consensus, failing which by rotation.

</section>

<section><tid>703872</tid>
<number>3</number>An agreement under sub- section (1) shall contain provisions as to 
the name of the Joint Electricity Regulatory Commission, the manner in 
which the participating States may be associated in the selection of 
the Chairperson and Members of the Joint Ele tricity Regulatory 
Commission, manner of appointment of Chairperson and Members by 
consensus, failing which by rotation, places at which the Commission 
shall sit, apportionment among the participating States of the 
expenditure in connection with the Join Electricity Regulatory 
Commission and may also contain such other supplemental, incidental 
and consequential provisions not inconsistent with this Act as may be 
deemed necessary or expedient for giving effect to the agreement.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>266146</tid>
<number> 21B</number> Special provision relating to giving of 
directions.- Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, where any 
Joint Electricity Regulatory Commission is constituted under section 
21A,-
<section><tid>304823</tid>
<number>a</number>the Government of the State for which the Joint Electricity 
Regulatory Commission is constituted shall be competent to give any 
direction under this Act only in cases where such direction relates to 
a matter within the exclusive territorial jurisdict on of the State;

</section>

<section><tid>736800</tid>
<number>b</number>the Central Government alone shall be competent to give any 
direction under this Act where such direction relates to a matter 
within the territorial jurisdiction of two or more States or pertains 
to a Union territory if the participating Governments ail to reach an 
agreement or the participating States or majority of them request the 
Central Government to issue such directions.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1598966</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 29.- In section 29 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that in States or Union territories where Joint Electricity 
Regulatory Commission has been constituted, such Joint Electricity 
Regulatory Commission shall determine different tariff for each of the 
participating States or Union territories.".

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>