<act><title>

The Border 
    Security Force (Deductions
    from Pay and Allowances) Rules, 19781</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Border Security Force (Deductions from Pay and 
    Allowances) Rules, 1978. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    These rules shall apply to all persons subject to the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> They 
    shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Border Security Force 
    Act, 1968 (47 of 1968); 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    Words and expressions used herein and 
    not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the meanings 
    assigned to them in the Act. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Deductions from pay and allowances of officers.—The 
    following deductions may be made from the Pay and Allowances of an officer, 
    that is to say:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    all pay and allowances due to an 
    officer every day is absents himself without leave, unless a satisfactory 
    explanation has been given and accepted by the Inspector General under whom 
    he is for the time being serving; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any sum required to make good the pay 
    of any person subject to this Act which the officer has unlawfully retained 
    or unlawfully refused to pay; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    any sum required to be paid as fine 
    imposed by a Criminal Court or a Security Force Court; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    any sum required to make good any loss, 
    damage or destruction of public property or property belonging to the Force 
    which, after due investigation, appears to the Inspector General under whom 
    the officer is for the time being serving, to have been occasioned by 
    wrongful act or negligence on the part of the officer; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    all pay and allowances forfeited by an 
    order of the Central Government if the officer is found by a Court of 
    Inquiry constituted by the Director General, Border Security Force, in this 
    behalf, to have deserted to the enemy, or while in enemy’s hands, to have 
    served with or under the orders of the enemy, or in any manner to have aided 
    the enemy or to have allowed himself to be taken prisoner by the enemy 
    through want of precaution or through disobedience of orders, wilful neglect 
    of duty or having been taken prisoner by the enemy, to have failed to rejoin 
    his service when it was possible to do so; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    any sum required by an order of the 
    Central Government to be paid for the maintenance of his wife or his 
    legitimate or illegitimate child or step child or towards the cost of any 
    relief given by the said Government to the said wife or child. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Deductions from the pay and allowances of persons other than Officer.—Subject 
    to the provisions of Rule 6, the following deductions may be made from the 
    pay and allowances of persons subject to the Act, other than an officer, 
    that is to say:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    all pay and allowances for every day of 
    absence either on desertion or without leave, or as a Prisoner of War, and 
    for every day of imprisonment awarded by a Criminal Court, a Security Force 
    Court or an officer exercising authority under section 53 of the Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    all pay and allowances for every day 
    between the date of his recovery from the enemy and his dismissal from the 
    service in consequence of his conduct when being taken prisoner, by or while 
    in the hands of the enemy; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    any sum required to make good the pay 
    of any person subject to the Act which he has unlawfully retained or 
    unlawfully refused to pay; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    any sum required to make good such 
    compensation for any expenses, loss, damage or destruction caused by him to 
    the Central Government or to any building or property or any private fund of 
    the Force, as may be awarded by his commandant; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    any sum required to be paid as fine 
    imposed by a Criminal Court, a Security Force Court or an officer exercising 
    authority under section 53 of the Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    any sum required by an order of the 
    Central Government to be paid for maintenance of his wife, legitimate or 
    illegitimate child or step child or towards the cost of any relief given by 
    the said Government to the said wife or child. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Computation of time of absence or imprisonment for the purpose 
      of clause 
<section><number>a</number> of rule 4.—(1) No person shall be treated as absent or 
      imprisonment has lasted, whether wholly in one day or partly in one day 
      and partly in another, for six consecutive hours or 
      upward. 
 <subsection><number>2</number> Any absence or imprisonment for less than a day may be reckoned 
      as absence or imprisonment for a day if such absence or imprisonment 
      prevented the absence from fulfilling any duty as a member of the Force 
      which was thereby thrown upon some other member. 
  
  
  
  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Computation of time of absence or imprisonment for the purpose 
      of clause 
<section><number>a</number> of rule 4.—(1) No person shall be treated as absent or 
      imprisonment has lasted, whether wholly in one day or partly in one day 
      and partly in another, for six consecutive hours or 
      upward. 
 <subsection><number>2</number> Any absence or imprisonment for less than a day may be reckoned 
      as absence or imprisonment for a day if such absence or imprisonment 
      prevented the absence from fulfilling any duty as a member of the Force 
      which was thereby thrown upon some other member. 
  
  
  
  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Limit of certain deductions.—The 
    total deductions from pay and allowances of a person made under clauses (c) 
    to (f) of rule 4 shall not, except where he is sentenced to dismissal, 
    exceed in any one month one half of his pay and allowances for that month. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Deductions from public money due to person.—Any 
    sum authorised by these rules to be deducted from the pay and allowances of 
    any person may, without prejudice to any other mode of recovering the same, 
    be deducted from any public money due to him other than a person. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Pay and Allowances of Prisoner of War during the inquiry into his conduct.—Whether 
    the conduct of any person subject to the Act, then being taken prisoner by, 
    or in hands of the enemy, is to be inquired into under the Act or any other 
    law, the Central Government or the Director General or any officer 
    authorised by the Director General may order that the whole or any part of 
    the pay and allowances of such person shall be held pending the result of 
    such inquiry. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Provision for dependents of prisoner of war from remitted deductions.—In 
    the case of persons subject to the Act, being prisoner of war, whose pay and 
    allowances have been forfeited under clause (e) of rule 3 or clause 
<section><number>a</number> of 
    rule 4, but in respect of whom a remission has been made under rule 13, it 
    shall be lawful for the proper provision to be made by the Central 
    Government out of such persons, and any such remission shall, in that case, 
    be deemed to apply only to the balance remaining thereafter of such pay and 
    allowances. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Provision for dependents of prisoner of war from his pay and allowances.—It 
    shall be lawful for proper provision to be made by the Central Government or 
    by the Director General when so authorised by the Central Government for any 
    dependents of any person subject to the Act who is a prisoner of war or is 
    missing, out of his pay and allowances. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> 
      Period during which a person is deemed to be prisoner of war for the 
      purposes of rules 9 and 10 and a person shall be deemed to continue to be 
      a prisoner of war until the conclusion of any inquiry into his conduct 
      referred to in rule 8, and if he is dismissed from the service, in 
      consequence of such conduct, until the date of such 
      dismissal. 
  
  
  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Authority competent to order deductions.—The 
    following shall be the authorities competent to order deductions from pay 
    and allowances under these rules, namely:— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    Commandants, in the case of subordinate 
    officers and enrolled persons; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    Director General, in the case of 
    officers; 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    Central Government in the case of 
    officers above the rank of a commandant. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Remission of deductions.—Any 
    authority superior to the one awarding any deductions under these rules 
    shall be competent to remit the whole or part of the said deductions. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Powers to be exercised by a superior officer or authority.—Any 
    power conferred by the provisions of these rules on an officer may be 
    exercised by an officer or authority superior in command to be first 
    mentioned officer. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Transitory provisions.—Any 
    rule or order applicable to the member of the Force on the date of 
    commencement of these rules shall, unless it is repugnant to these rules, 
    continue to apply unless and until it is abrogated or modified by the 
    Central Government or any other competent authority. 
  
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>