<act><title>

The 
    Public servants (Inquiries) Act, 1850</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Repeal 
    of Acts.—[Repealed by the 
    Repealing Act, 1870 (14 of 1870), sec. 1 and Sch, Part II.]
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Articles of charge to be drawn out for public inquiry into conduct of 
    certain public servants.—Whenever 
    the 

    1Government shall be 
    of opinion that there are good grounds for making a formal and public 
    inquiry into the truth of any imputation of misbehaviour by any person in 
    the service of 

    2[the Government, 
    non-removable from his appointment without the sanction of the Government,] 
    it 

    3[may] cause the 
    substance of the imputations to be drawn into distinct articles of charge, 
    and 

    3[may] order a formal 
    and public inquiry to be made into the truth thereof.—Whenever 
    the 

    1Government shall be 
    of opinion that there are good grounds for making a formal and public 
    inquiry into the truth of any imputation of misbehaviour by any person in 
    the service of 

    2[the Government, 
    non-removable from his appointment without the sanction of the Government,] 
    it 

    3[may] cause the 
    substance of the imputations to be drawn into distinct articles of charge, 
    and 

    3[may] order a formal 
    and public inquiry to be made into the truth thereof."
 
 

 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Authorities to whom inquiry may be committed—Notice 
    to accused.—The inquiry may be committed either to the Court, Board or 
    other authority to which the person accused is subordinate or to any other 
    person or persons, to be specially appointed by the Government, 
    commissioners for the purpose: notice of which commission shall be given to 
    the person accused ten days at least before the beginning of the inquiry. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Conduct 
    of Government prosecution.—When 
    the Government shall think fit to conduct the prosecution, it shall nominate 
    some person to conduct the same on its behalf.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Charge 
    by accuser to be written and verified—Penalty 
    for false accusation—Institution of inquiry by Government.—When 
    the charge shall be brought by an accuser, the Government shall require the 
    accusation to be reduced to writing, and verified by the oath or solemn 
    affirmation of the accuser; and every person who shall wilfully and 
    maliciously make any false accusation under this Act, upon such oath or 
    affirmation, shall be liable to the penalties of perjury; but this enactment 
    shall not be construed to prevent the Government from instituting any 
    inquiry which it shall think fit, without such accusation on oath or solemn 
    affirmation as aforesaid.
 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Charge 
    by accuser to be written and verified—Penalty 
    for false accusation—Institution of inquiry by Government.—When 
    the charge shall be brought by an accuser, the Government shall require the 
    accusation to be reduced to writing, and verified by the oath or solemn 
    affirmation of the accuser; and every person who shall wilfully and 
    maliciously make any false accusation under this Act, upon such oath or 
    affirmation, shall be liable to the penalties of perjury; but this enactment 
    shall not be construed to prevent the Government from instituting any 
    inquiry which it shall think fit, without such accusation on oath or solemn 
    affirmation as aforesaid.
 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Security 
    from accuser left by Government to prosecute.—Where 
    the imputations shall have been made by an accuser, and the Government shall 
    think fit to leave to him the conduct of the prosecution, the Government 
    before appointing the commission shall require him to furnish reasonable 
    security that he will attend and prosecute the charge thoroughly and 
    effectually, and also will be forthcoming to answer an counter-charge or 
    action which may be afterwards brought against him for malicious prosecution 
    or perjury or subornation of perjury, as case may be. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power of 
    Government to abandon prosecution and to allow accuser to continue it.—At 
    any subsequent stage of the proceedings, the Government may, if it think 
    fit, abandon the prosecution, and in such case, may, if it think fit, on the 
    application of the accuser, allow him to continue the prosecution, if he is 
    desirous of so doing, on his furnishing such security as is hereinbefore 
    mentioned. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Powers of commissioners,—Their 
    protection. Service of their process—Powers of Court, etc., 
    acting under commission.—The commissioners shall have the same power of 
    punishing contempts and obstructions to their proceedings, as is given to 
    Civil and Criminal Courts by 

    1[the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)]2, 
    and shall have the same powers for the summons of witnesses, and for 
    compelling the production of documents, and for the discharge of their duty 
    under the commission, and shall be entitled to the same protection as the 
    Zila and City Judges, except that all process to cause the attendance of 
    witnesses or other compulsory process, shall be served through and executed 
    by the Zila or City Judge in whose jurisdiction the witness or other person 
    resides, on whom the process is to be served, and if he resides within 
    Calcutta, Madras or Bombay, then through the Supreme Court of Judicature 
    thereto. When the commission has been issued to a court, or other person or 
    persons having power to issue such process in the exercise of their ordinary 
    authority, they may also use all such power for the purposes of the 
    commission. 
 
 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Powers of commissioners,—Their 
    protection. Service of their process—Powers of Court, etc., 
    acting under commission.—The commissioners shall have the same power of 
    punishing contempts and obstructions to their proceedings, as is given to 
    Civil and Criminal Courts by 

    1[the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)]2, 
    and shall have the same powers for the summons of witnesses, and for 
    compelling the production of documents, and for the discharge of their duty 
    under the commission, and shall be entitled to the same protection as the 
    Zila and City Judges, except that all process to cause the attendance of 
    witnesses or other compulsory process, shall be served through and executed 
    by the Zila or City Judge in whose jurisdiction the witness or other person 
    resides, on whom the process is to be served, and if he resides within 
    Calcutta, Madras or Bombay, then through the Supreme Court of Judicature 
    thereto. When the commission has been issued to a court, or other person or 
    persons having power to issue such process in the exercise of their ordinary 
    authority, they may also use all such power for the purposes of the 
    commission. 
 
 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Penalty 
    for disobedience to process.—All 
    persons disobeying any lawful process issued as aforesaid for the purposes 
    of the commission shall be liable to the same penalties as if the same had 
    issued originally from the Court or other authority through whom it is 
    executed. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Copy of 
    charge and list to be furnished to accused.—A 
    copy of the articles of charge, and list of the documents and witnesses by 
    which each charge is to be sustained, shall be delivered to the person 
    accused, at least three days before the beginning of the inquiry, exclusive 
    of the day of delivery and the first day of the inquiry. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Procedure at beginning of inquiry—Non-appearance 
    of accused and admission of charge.—At the beginning of the inquiry the 
    prosecutor shall exhibit the articles of charge to the commissioners, which 
    shall be openly read, and the person accused shall thereupon be required to 
    plead “guilty” or “not guilty” to each of them, which pleas shall be 
    forthwith recorded with the articles of charge. If the person accused 
    refuses, or without reasonable cause neglects, to appear to answer the 
    charge either personally or by his counsel or agent, he shall be taken to 
    admit the truth of the articles of charge.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Procedure at beginning of inquiry—Non-appearance 
    of accused and admission of charge.—At the beginning of the inquiry the 
    prosecutor shall exhibit the articles of charge to the commissioners, which 
    shall be openly read, and the person accused shall thereupon be required to 
    plead “guilty” or “not guilty” to each of them, which pleas shall be 
    forthwith recorded with the articles of charge. If the person accused 
    refuses, or without reasonable cause neglects, to appear to answer the 
    charge either personally or by his counsel or agent, he shall be taken to 
    admit the truth of the articles of charge.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Prosecutor’s right of address.—The 
    prosecutor shall then be entitled to address the commissioners in 
    explanation of the articles of charge, and of the evidence by which they are 
    to be proved: his address shall not be recorded. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Prosecutor’s right of address.—The 
    prosecutor shall then be entitled to address the commissioners in 
    explanation of the articles of charge, and of the evidence by which they are 
    to be proved: his address shall not be recorded. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Evidence for prosecution and examination of witnesses—Re-examination 
    by prosecutor.—The oral and documentary evidence for the prosecution 
    shall then be exhibited; the witnesses shall be examined by or on behalf of 
    the prosecutor and may be cross-examined by or on behalf of the person 
    accused. The prosecutor shall be entitled to re-examine the witnesses on any 
    points on which they have been cross-examined, but not on any new matter, 
    without leave of the commissioners, who also may put such questions as they 
    think fit. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Power 
    to admit or call for new evidence or prosecution—Accused’s 
    right to adjournment—.If it shall appear necessary before the 
    close of the case for the prosecution, the commissioners may in their 
    discretion allow the prosecutor to exhibit evidence not included in the list 
    given to the person accused, or may themselves call for new evidence; and in 
    such case the person accused shall be entitled to have, if he demands it, an 
    adjournment of the proceedings for three clear days, before the exhibition 
    of such new evidence exclusive of the day of adjournment and of the day to 
    which the proceedings are adjourned. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Defence 
    of accused—To be recorded only 
    when written.—When the case for the prosecution is closed, the person 
    accused shall be required to make his defence, orally or in writing, as he 
    shall prefer. If made orally, it shall not be recorded; if made in writing, 
    it shall be recorded, after being openly read, and in that case a copy shall 
    be given at the same time to the prosecutor. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Defence 
    of accused—To be recorded only 
    when written.—When the case for the prosecution is closed, the person 
    accused shall be required to make his defence, orally or in writing, as he 
    shall prefer. If made orally, it shall not be recorded; if made in writing, 
    it shall be recorded, after being openly read, and in that case a copy shall 
    be given at the same time to the prosecutor. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Evidence for defence and examination of witnesses.—The 
    evidence for the defence shall then be exhibited, and the witnesses 
    examined, who shall be liable to cross-examination and re-examination and to 
    examination by the commissioners according to the like rules as the 
    witnesses for the prosecution. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Examination of witnesses and evidence by prosecutor.—[Repealed 
    by the Repealing Act, 1876 (12 of 1876), sec. 2 and Sch. Part I.] 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Notes 
    of oral evidence.—The 
    commissioners or some person appointed by them shall take notes in English 
    of all oral evidence which shall be read aloud to each witness by whom the 
    same was given, and, if necessary, explained to him in the language in which 
    it was given, and shall be recorded with the proceedings. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Inquiry 
    when closed with defence—Prosecutor 
    when entitled to reply and give evidence—Accused not entitled to 
    adjournment.—If the person accused makes only an oral defence, and 
    exhibits no evidence, the inquiry shall end with his defence; if he records 
    a written defence, or exhibits evidence, the prosecutor shall be entitled to 
    a general oral reply on the whole case, and may also exhibit evidence to 
    contradict any evidence exhibited for the defence, in which case the person 
    accused shall not be entitled to any adjournment of the proceedings, 
    although such new evidence were not included in the list furnished to him. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Inquiry 
    when closed with defence—Prosecutor 
    when entitled to reply and give evidence—Accused not entitled to 
    adjournment.—If the person accused makes only an oral defence, and 
    exhibits no evidence, the inquiry shall end with his defence; if he records 
    a written defence, or exhibits evidence, the prosecutor shall be entitled to 
    a general oral reply on the whole case, and may also exhibit evidence to 
    contradict any evidence exhibited for the defence, in which case the person 
    accused shall not be entitled to any adjournment of the proceedings, 
    although such new evidence were not included in the list furnished to him. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Power 
    to require amendment of charge and to adjourn—Reason 
    for refusing adjournment to be recorded.—When the commissioners shall be 
    of opinion that the articles of charge, or any of them are not drawn with 
    sufficient clearness and precision, the commissioners may, in their 
    discretion, require the same to be amended, and may thereupon, on the 
    application of the person accused, adjourn the inquiry for a reasonable 
    time. The commissioners may also, if they think fit, adjourn the inquiry 
    from time to time, on the application of either the prosecutor or the person 
    accused, on the ground of sickness or unavoidable absence of any witness or 
    other reasonable cause. When such application is made and refused, the 
    commissioners shall record the application, and their reasons for refusing 
    to comply with it. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Power 
    to require amendment of charge and to adjourn—Reason 
    for refusing adjournment to be recorded.—When the commissioners shall be 
    of opinion that the articles of charge, or any of them are not drawn with 
    sufficient clearness and precision, the commissioners may, in their 
    discretion, require the same to be amended, and may thereupon, on the 
    application of the person accused, adjourn the inquiry for a reasonable 
    time. The commissioners may also, if they think fit, adjourn the inquiry 
    from time to time, on the application of either the prosecutor or the person 
    accused, on the ground of sickness or unavoidable absence of any witness or 
    other reasonable cause. When such application is made and refused, the 
    commissioners shall record the application, and their reasons for refusing 
    to comply with it. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Report 
    of commissioners proceedings.—After 
    the close of the inquiry the commissioners shall forthwith report to 
    Government their proceedings under the commission, and shall send with the 
    record thereof their opinion upon each of the articles of charge separately, 
    with such observation as they think fit on the whole case. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Power 
    to call for further evidence or explanation. Inquiry into additional 
    articles of charge—Reference 
    of report of special commissioners’ final orders.—The Government, on 
    consideration of the report of the commissioners, may order them to take 
    further evidence, or give further explanation of their opinions. It may also 
    order additional articles of charge to be framed, in which case the inquiry 
    into the truth of such additional articles shall be made in the same manner 
    as is herein directed with respect to the original charges. When special 
    commissioners have been appointed, the Government may also, if it thinks 
    fit, refer the report of the commissioners to the Court or other authority 
    to which the person accused is subordinate, for their opinion on the case; 
    and will finally pass such orders thereon as appear just and consistent with 
    its powers in such cases. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Power 
    to call for further evidence or explanation. Inquiry into additional 
    articles of charge—Reference 
    of report of special commissioners’ final orders.—The Government, on 
    consideration of the report of the commissioners, may order them to take 
    further evidence, or give further explanation of their opinions. It may also 
    order additional articles of charge to be framed, in which case the inquiry 
    into the truth of such additional articles shall be made in the same manner 
    as is herein directed with respect to the original charges. When special 
    commissioners have been appointed, the Government may also, if it thinks 
    fit, refer the report of the commissioners to the Court or other authority 
    to which the person accused is subordinate, for their opinion on the case; 
    and will finally pass such orders thereon as appear just and consistent with 
    its powers in such cases. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>23</number> 
    ‘Definition of “Government”.—In this Act, “the Government” means the 
    Central Government in the case of persons employed under that Government and 
    the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[State] Government in the case of persons employed under 
    that Government.]
 
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>23</number> 
    ‘Definition of “Government”.—In this Act, “the Government” means the 
    Central Government in the case of persons employed under that Government and 
    the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[State] Government in the case of persons employed under 
    that Government.]
 
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum><number>24</number> 
    Saving of enactments as to dismissal of certain officers—Commission 
    under Act for their trial.— Nothing in this Act shall be construed to 
    repeal any Act or Regulation in force for the suspension or dismissal of 
    Principal and other Sadr. Amins. or of Deputy Magistrates or Deputy 
    Collectors, but a commission may be issued for the trial of any charge 
    against any of the said officers, under this Act, in any case in which the 
    Government shall think it expedient.324. 
    Saving of enactments as to dismissal of certain officers—Commission 
    under Act for their trial.— Nothing in this Act shall be construed to 
    repeal any Act or Regulation in force for the suspension or dismissal of 
    Principal and other Sadr. Amins. or of Deputy Magistrates or Deputy 
    Collectors, but a commission may be issued for the trial of any charge 
    against any of the said officers, under this Act, in any case in which the 
    Government shall think it expedient." 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum><number>24</number> 
    Saving of enactments as to dismissal of certain officers—Commission 
    under Act for their trial.— Nothing in this Act shall be construed to 
    repeal any Act or Regulation in force for the suspension or dismissal of 
    Principal and other Sadr. Amins. or of Deputy Magistrates or Deputy 
    Collectors, but a commission may be issued for the trial of any charge 
    against any of the said officers, under this Act, in any case in which the 
    Government shall think it expedient.324. 
    Saving of enactments as to dismissal of certain officers—Commission 
    under Act for their trial.— Nothing in this Act shall be construed to 
    repeal any Act or Regulation in force for the suspension or dismissal of 
    Principal and other Sadr. Amins. or of Deputy Magistrates or Deputy 
    Collectors, but a commission may be issued for the trial of any charge 
    against any of the said officers, under this Act, in any case in which the 
    Government shall think it expedient." 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Saving 
    of power of removal without inquiry under Act.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall be construed to affect the authority of Government, for 
    suspending or removing any public servant for any cause without an inquiry 
    under this Act. 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for the former section. tc " 1. Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for the former section."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial”. tc " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1937, for the former section. tc " 1. Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for the former section."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial”. tc " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “Provincial”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Repealed 
    as to the Lower Provinces and North-Western Provinces of Bengal by Act 16 of 
    1868, sec. 1 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Repealed 
    as to the Lower Provinces and North-Western Provinces of Bengal by Act 16 of 
    1868, sec. 1 and Sch.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>