<act><title>


    The Seeds Rules, 1968</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>1</number> Short 
    title.—These 
    rules may be called the Seeds Rules, 1968.
 
 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    “Act” means the Seeds Act, 1966 (54 of 1966);  
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    “advertisement’ means all representations other than those on the label, 
    disseminated in any manner or by any means relating to seed for the purposes 
    of the Act;  
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>    
    “certification sample” means a sample of seed drawn by a certification 
    agency or by a duly authorised representative of a certification agency 
    established under section 8 or recognized under section 18 of the Act;  
 </section><section>

<number>d</number>    
    “certification tag” means a tag or label of certain design to be specified 
    by the certification agency and shall constitute the certificate granted by 
    the certification agency;  
 </section><section>

<number>e</number>    
    “certified seed” means seed that fulfils all requirements for certification 
    provided by the Act and these rules and to the container of which the 
    certification tag is attached;  
 </section><section>

<number>f</number>    
    “certified seed producer” means a person who grows or distributes certified 
    seed in accordance with the procedure and standards of the certification 
    agency;  
 </section><section>

<number>g</number>    
    “complete record” means the information which relates to the origin, veriety, 
    kind, germination and purity of seed of any notified kind or variety offered 
    for sale, sold or otherwise supplied;  
 </section><section>

<number>h</number>    
    “Form” means a form appended to these rules;  
 </section><section>

<number>i</number>    
    “origin” means the State, Union Territory or foreign country where the seed 
    is grown and in case seeds of different origin are blended the label shall 
    show the percentage of seed of each origin;  
 </section><section>

<number>j</number>    
    “processing” means cleaning, drying, treating, grading and other operations 
    which would change the purity and germination of the seed and thus requiring 
    re-testing to determine the quality of the seed, but does not include 
    operations such as packaging and labelling;  
 </section><section>

<number>k</number>    
    “section” means a section of the Act;  
 </section><section>

<number>l</number>    
    “service sample” means a sample submitted to the Central Seed Laboratory or 
    to a State Seed Laboratory for testing, the results to be used as 
    information for seeding, selling or labelling purposes;  
 </section><section>

<number>m</number>    
    “treated” means that the seed has been subjected to an application of a 
    substance or process in such a manner as to reduce, control or repel certain 
    disease, organisms, insects, or any other pests attacking such seeds or 
    seedlings growing therefrom and for other purposes.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>3</number> 
    Functions of the Central Seed Committee.—In 
    addition to the functions entrusted to the Committee by the Act, the 
    Committee shall,—
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    recommend the rate of fees to be levied for analysis of samples by the 
    Central and State Seed Testing Laboratories and for certification by the 
    certification agencies;
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    advise the Central or State Governments on the suitability of Seed Testing 
    Laboratories;  
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>    
    send its recommendations and other concerning records to the Central 
    Government;  
 </section><section>

<number>d</number>    
    recommend the procedure and standards for certification, tests and analysis 
    of seeds; and   
 </section><section>

<number>e</number>    
    carry out such other functions as are supplemental, incidental or 
    consequential to any of the functions conferred by the Act or these rules.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>4</number> 
    Travelling and daily allowances payable to members of the committee and its 
    sub-committees.—The 
    members of the committee and its sub-committees shall be entitled to draw 
    travelling and daily allowances as specified below when they are called upon 
    to attend a meeting of the committee or a sub-committee thereof:
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    An official member of the committee or its sub-committee shall be entitled 
    to draw travelling and daily allowances in accordance with the rules of the 
    Government under which he is for the time being employed and from the same 
    source from which his pay and allowances are drawn:  
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    A non-official member shall be allowed travelling and daily allowances in 
    accordance with the general orders issued in this behalf by the Central 
    government from time to time.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>5</number> 
    Functions.—In 
    addition to the functions entrusted to the Central Seed laboratory by the 
    Act, the Laboratory shall carry out the following functions, namely:—  
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    initiate testing programmes in collaboration with the State Seed 
    Laboratories designed to promote uniformity in test results between all seed 
    laboratories in India;  
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    collect data continually on the quality of seeds found in the market and 
    make this data available to the Committee; and 
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>    
    carry out such other functions as may be assigned to it by the Central 
    Government from time to time.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>6</number> 
    Functions of the Certification Agency.—In 
    addition to the functions entrusted to the certification agency by the Act, 
    the Agency shall,—  
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    certify seeds of any notified kinds or varieties;  
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    outline the procedure for submission of applications and for growing, 
    harvesting, processing, storage and labelling of seeds intended for 
    certification till the end to ensure that seed lots finally approved for 
    certification are true to variety and meet prescribed standards for 
    certification under the Act or these rules;  
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>    
    maintain a list of recognised breeders of seeds;  
 </section><section>

<number>d</number>    
    verify, upon receipt of an application for certification that the variety is 
    eligible for certification, that the seed source used for planting was 
    authenticated and the record of purchase is in accordance with these rules 
    and the fees have been paid;  
 </section><section>

<number>e</number>    
    take sample and inspect seed lots produced under the procedure laid down by 
    the certification agency and have such samples tested to ensure that the 
    seeds conform to the prescribed standards of certification;  
 </section><section>

<number>f</number>    
    inspect seed processing plants to see that the admixtures of other kinds and 
    varieties are not introduced;  
 </section><section>

<number>g</number>    
    ensure that action at all stages, e.g., field inspection, seed 
    processing plant inspection, analysis of samples taken and issue of 
    certificates  (including tags, marks, labels and seals) is taken 
    expeditiously;  
 </section><section>

<number>h</number>    
    carry out educational programmes designed to promote the use of certified 
    seed including a publication listing certified seed growers and sources of 
    certified seed;  
 </section><section>

<number>i</number>    
    grant certificates (including tags, labels, seals, etc.) in accordance with 
    the provisions of the Act and these rules;  
 </section><section>

<number>j</number>    
    maintain such records as may be necessary to verify that seed plants for the 
    production of certified seed were eligible for such planting under these 
    rules;  
 </section><section>

<number>k</number>    
    inspect fields to ensure that the minimum standards for isolation, roguing 
    (where applicable) use of male sterility (where applicable) and similar 
    factors are maintained at all times, as well as ensure that seedborne 
    diseases are not present in the field to a greater extent than those 
    provided in the standards for certification.  
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>7</number> 
    Responsibility for marking or labelling.—When 
    seed of a notified kind or variety is offered for sale under section 7, each 
    container shall be marked or labelled in the manner hereinafter specified. 
    The person whose name appears on the mark or label shall be responsible for 
    the accuracy of the information required to appear on the mark or label so 
    long as seed is contained in the unopened original container:  
 

Provided, 
    however, that such person shall not be responsible for the accuracy of the 
    statement appearing on the mark or label if the seed is removed from the 
    original unopened container, or he shall not be responsible for the accuracy 
    of the germination statement beyond the date of validity indicated on the 
    mark or label.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>8</number> Contents 
    of the mark or label.—There 
    shall be specified on every mark or label,—  
 <section>

<number>i</number>    
    particulars, as specified by the Central Government under clause (b) of 
    section 6 of the Act;  
 </section><section>

<number>ii</number>    
    a correct statement of the net content in terms of weight and expressed in 
    metric system;  
 </section><section>

<number>iii</number>    
    date of testing;  
 </section><section>

<number>iv</number>    
    if the seed in container has been treated,—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    a statement indicating that the seed has been treated;   
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    the commonly accepted chemical or abbreviated chemical (generic) name of the 
    applied substance; and  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    if the substance of the chemical used for treatment, and present with the 
    seed is harmful to human beings or other vertebrate animals, a caution 
    statement such as “Do not use for food, feed or oil purposes”. The caution 
    for mercurials and similarly toxic substance shall be the word “Poison” 
    which shall be in type size, prominently displayed on the label in red;  
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>v</number>    
    the name and address of the person who offers for sale, sells or otherwise 
    supplies the seed and who is responsible for its quality;   
 </section><section>

<number>vi</number>    
    the name of the seed as notified under section 5 of the Act.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>9</number> Manner 
    of marking or labelling the container under clause (c) of section 6 and 
    clause (b) of section 17.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The mark or label containing the particulars of the seed as specified under 
    clause (b) of section 6 shall appear on each container of seed or on a tag 
    or mark or label attached to the container in a conspicuous place on the 
    innermost container in which the seed is packed and on every other covering 
    in which that container is packed and shall be legible.   
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Any 
    transparent cover or any wrapper, case or other covering used solely for the 
    purpose of packing of transport or delivery need not be marked or labelled.
      
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Where 
    by a provision of these rules, any particulars are required to be displayed 
    on a label on the container, such particulars may, instead of being 
    displayed on a label be etched, painted or otherwise indelibly marked on the 
    container.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

 <number>10</number> 
    Mark or label not to contain false or misleading statement.—The mark or 
    label shall not contain any statement, claim, design, device, fancy name or 
    abbreviation which is false or misleading in any particular concerning the 
    seed contained in the container.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>11</number> Mark or 
    label not to contain reference to the Act or Rules contradictory to required 
    particulars.—The 
    mark or label shall not contain any reference to the Act, or any of these 
    rules or any comment on, or reference to, or explanation of any particulars 
    or declaration required by the Act or any of these rules which directly or 
    by implication contradicts, qualifies or modifies such particulars or 
    declaration.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>12</number> Denial 
    of responsibility for mark or label content prohibited.—Nothing 
    shall appear on the mark or label or in any advertisement pertaining to any 
    seed of any notified kind or variety which shall deny responsibility for the 
    statement required by or under the Act to appear on such mark, label or 
    advertisement.   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>13</number> 
    Requirements to be complied with by a person carrying on the business 
    referred to in section 7.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person shall sell, keep for sale, offer to sell, barter or otherwise 
    supply any seed of any notified kind or variety, after the date recorded on 
    the container, mark or label as the date upto which the seed may be expected 
    to retain the germination not less than that prescribed under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of 
    section 6 of the Act.   
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> No 
    person shall alter, obliterate or deface any mark or label attached to the 
    container of any seed.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Every 
    person selling, keeping for sale, offering to sell, bartering or otherwise 
    supplying any seed of notified kind or variety under section 7, shall keep 
    over a period of three years a complete record of each lot of seed sold 
    except that any seed sample may be discarded one year after the entire lot 
    represented by such sample has been disposed of.  The sample of seed 
    kept as part of the complete record shall be as large as the size notified 
    in the Official Gazette.  This sample, if required to be tested, shall 
    be tested only for determining the purity.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>14</number> Classes 
    and sources of certified seed.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    There shall be three classes of certified seed, namely, foundation, 
    registered and certified and each class shall meet the following standards 
    for that class:—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    Foundation seed shall be the progeny of breeder’s seed, or be produced from 
    foundation seed which can be clearly traced to breeder’s seed. Production 
    shall be supervised and approved by a seed certification agency and be so 
    handled as to maintain specific genetic purity and identity and shall be 
    required to meet certification standards for the crop being certified;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    Registered seed shall be the progeny of foundation seed that is so handled 
    as to maintain its genetic identity and purity according to standard 
    specified for the particular crop being certified;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    Certified seed shall be the progeny of registered or foundation seed that is 
    so handled to maintain genetic identity and purity according to standards 
    specified for the particular crop being certified.   
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> At the 
    discretion of the certification agency (when considered necessary to 
    maintain adequate seed supplies) certified seed may be the progeny of 
    certified seed provided this reproduction may not exceed three generations 
    and provided further that it is determined by the seed certification agency, 
    that the genetic purity will not be significantly altered.  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>15</number> 
    Application for the Grant of a Certificate.—Every 
    application for the grant of a certificate under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
    9 shall be made in Form I in accordance with the procedure outlined by the 
    certification agency for submission of applications and contain the 
    following particulars, namely:—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    the name, profession, and place of residence of the applicant;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    the name of the seed to be certified; its notified kind or variety;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    class of the seed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>    
    source of the seed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>    
    limits of germination and purity of the seed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>    
    mark or label of the seed.   
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>16</number> Fees.—Every 
    application under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 9 shall be accompanied by a fee 
    of Rs. 25 in cash.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>17</number> 
    Certificate.—Every 
    certificate granted under sub-section (3) of section 9 shall be in Form II 
    and shall be granted by the certification agency, after making enquiries and 
    satisfying itself in accordance with the provisions of the said sub-section 
    on the following conditions, for the period to be specified by the 
    certification agency, namely:—  
 <section>

<number>i</number>    
    The person to whom the certificate is granted under sub-section (3) of 
    section 9 shall attach a certification tag to every container of the 
    certified seed and shall follow the provisions in respect of marking or 
    labelling provided by or under the Act.   
 </section><section>

<number>ii</number>    
    The certification tag shall contain the following particulars, namely:—
      
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    name and address of the certification agency;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    kind and variety of the seed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    lot number or other mark of the seed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>    
    name and address of the certified seed producer;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>    
    date of issue of the certificate and of its validity;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>    
    an appropriate sign to designate certified seed;  
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>g</number>    
    an appropriate word denoting the class designation of the seed.   
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>iii</number>    
    The colour of the certification tag shall be white for foundation seed, 
    purple for registered seed and blue for certified seed;  
 </section><section>

<number>iv</number>    
    The container of the certified seed shall carry a seal of such material and 
    in such form as the certification agency may determine and no container 
    carrying a certification tag shall be sold by the person if the tag or seal 
    has either been tampered with or removed.   
 </section><section>

<number>v</number>    
    The certification tag on the container shall specify,—  
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>    
    the period during which the seed shall be used for sowing or planting;
      
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>    
    that the use of seed after the expiry of the validity period by any person 
    is entirely at his risk and the holder of the certificate shall not be 
    responsible for any damage to the buyer of the seed;   
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>    
    that no one should purchase the seed if the seal or the certification tag 
    has been tampered with.   
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>vi</number>    
    The holder of the certificate shall keep record of the details of each lot 
    of the seed which is issued for sale in such form as to be available for 
    inspection and to be easily identified by reference to the number of the lot 
    as shown in the certification tag of each container and such records shall 
    be retained in the case of a seed for which expiry date is fixed for a 
    period of two years from the expiry of such date;  
 </section><section>

<number>vii</number>    
    The holder of the certificate shall allow any Seed Inspector, authorised in 
    writing by the certification agency in that behalf, to enter with or without 
    prior notice the premises where the seeds are grown processed and sold and 
    to inspect premises, plant and the process of processing at all reasonable 
    hours;  
 </section><section>

<number>viii</number>    
    The holder of the certificate shall allow the Seed Inspector, authorised in 
    writing by the certification agency, to inspect all registers and records 
    maintained under these rules and to take samples of the seeds and shall 
    supply to the Seed Inspector such information as he may require for the 
    purposes of ascertaining whether the conditions subject to which the 
    certificate has been granted, have been complied with.   
 </section><section>

<number>ix</number>    
    The holder of the certificate shall on request furnish to the certification 
    agency from every lot of the seed or from such lot or lots as the said 
    agency may from time to time specify, a sample of such quantity as the 
    agency may consider adequate for any examination required to be made. 
 
 </section><section>

<number>x</number>    
    If the certification agency so directs, the holder of the certificate shall 
    not sell or offer for sale any lot in respect of which a sample is furnished 
    under the preceding clause until the agency authorises the sale of such lot;  
 </section><section>

<number>xi</number>    
    The holder of the certificate shall on being directed by the certification 
    agency that any part of a lot has been found by the said agency not to 
    conform to prescribed standards of quality or purity specified by or under 
    the Act, withdraw the remainder of that lot from sale and so far as may, in 
    the particular circumstances of the case, be practicable, recall all issues 
    already made from that lot;  
 <subsection>

<number>xii</number>    
    The holder of the certificate shall comply with the provisions of the Act 
    and these rules and with the directions given after not less than one 
    month’s notice by the certification agency to such holder.   
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>17A</number>
    The Certification agency shall, before granting the certificate, ensure 
    that the seed conforms to the standards laid down in the Manual known as 
    “Indian Minimum Seed Certification Standards” published by the Central Seed 
    Committee, as amended from time to time.] 
 

 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>18</number> The 
    form and manner in which and the fee on payment of which the appeal may be 
    preferred.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every memorandum of appeal under sub-section (1) of section 11 shall be in 
    writing and shall be accompanied by a copy of the decision of the 
    certification agency against which it has been preferred and shall set forth 
    concisely and under distinct heads the grounds of objection to such decision 
    without any argument, or narrative. 
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Every 
    such memorandum of appeal shall be accompanied by a treasury receipt for a 
    sum of Rs. 100.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Every 
    such memorandum of appeal may be presented either in person or through an 
    agent duly authorised in writing in this behalf by the appellant or may be 
    sent by the registered post. 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>19</number> 
    Procedure to be followed by the appellate authority.—In 
    deciding appeals under the Act the appellate authority 

    1[***] 
    shall follow the same procedure which a Court follows in deciding appeals 
    from the decree or order of an original court under the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908). 
 

 



 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>20</number> 
    Qualifications of Seed Analysts.—A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as Seed Analyst unless he—  
 <section>

<number>i</number>    
    possesses a Master’s or equivalent degree in Agriculture or Agronomy or 
    Botany or Horticulture of a University recognised for this purpose by the 
    Government and has had not less than one year’s experience in seed 
    technology; or 
 </section><section>

<number>ii</number>    
    possesses a Bachelor’s degree in Agriculture or Botany of a University 
    recognised for this purpose by the Government and has had not less than 
    three years’ experience in seed technology.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>21</number> Duties 
    of a Seed Analyst.—On 
    receipt of a sample for analysis the Seed Analyst shall first ascertain that 
    the mark and the seal or fastening as provided in clause (b) of sub-section 
    
<section><number>1</number> of section 15 are intact and shall note the condition of the seals 
    thereon.   
 


    1[(2) 
    The Seed Analyst shall analyse the samples in accordance with the procedures 
    laid down in the Seed Testing Manual published by the Indian Council of 
    Agricultural Research as amended from time to time.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The 
    Seed Analyst shall deliver in From VII, a copy of the report of the result 
    of analysis to the persons specified in sub-section (1) of section 16, as 
    soon as may be but not later than 30 days from the date of receipt of 
    samples sent by the Seed Inspector under sub-section (2) of the section 15.]  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> The 
    Seed Analyst shall from time to time forward to the State Government the 
    reports giving the result of analytical work done by him.   
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>22</number> 
    Qualifications of Seed Inspectors.—A 
    person shall not be qualified for appointment as Seed Inspector unless he is 
    a graduate in Agriculture of a University recognised for the purpose by the 
    Government and has had not less than one year’s experience in seed 
    production, or seed development or seed analysis or testing in a seed 
    testing laboratory. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>23</number> Duties 
    of a Seed Inspector.—In 
    addition to the duties specified by the Act the Seed Inspector shall,—  
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    inspect as frequently as may be required by certification agency all places 
    used for growing, storage or sale of any seed of any notified kind or 
    variety;   
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    satisfy himself that the conditions of the certificates are being observed;
      
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>    
    procedure and send for analysis, if necessary, samples of any seeds, which 
    he has reason to suspect are being produced, stocked or sold or exhibited 
    for sale in contravention of the provisions of the Act or these rules;
      
 </section><section>

<number>d</number>    
    investigate any complaint, which may be made to him in writing in respect of 
    any contravention of the provisions of the Act or these rules;   
 </section><section>

<number>e</number>    
    maintain a record of all inspections made and action taken by him in the 
    performance of his duties including the taking of samples and the seizure of 
    stocks and submit copies of such record to the Director of Agriculture or 
    the certification agency as may be directed in this behalf;   
 </section><section>

<number>f</number>    
    when so authorised by the State Government detain imported containers which 
    he has reason to suspect contain seeds, import of which is prohibited except 
    and in accordance with the provisions of the Act and these rules;   
 </section><section>

<number>g</number>    
    institute prosecutions in respect of breaches of the Act and these rules; 
    and   
 </section><section>

<number>h</number>    
    perform such other duties as may be entrusted to him by the 

    1[State 
    Government].
 

 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>


    1[<number>23A</number> 
    Action to be taken by the Seed Inspector if a complaint is lodged with him.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If farmer has lodged a complaint in writing that the failure of the crop is 
    due to the defective quality of seeds of any notified kind or variety 
    supplied to him, the Seed Inspector shall take in his possession the marks 
    or labels, the seed containers and a sample of unused seeds to the extent 
    possible from the complaint for establishing the source of supply of seeds 
    and shall investigate the causes of the failure of his crop by sending 
    samples of the lot to the Seed Analyst for detailed analysis at the State 
    Seed Testing Laboratory. He shall thereupon submit the report of his 
    findings as soon as possible to the competent authority.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> In 
    case, the Seed Inspector comes to the conclusion that the failure of the 
    crop is due to the quality of seeds supplied to the farmer being less than 
    the minimum standards notified by the Central Government, he shall launch 
    proceedings against the supplier for contravention of the provisions of the 
    Act or these rules.]
 

 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>24</number> Manner 
    of taking samples.—Samples 
    of any seed of any notified kind or variety for the purpose of analysis 
    shall be taken in a clean dry container which shall be closed sufficiently 
    tight to prevent leakage and entrance of moisture and shall be carefully 
    sealed.   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>25</number> 
    Containers to be labelled and addressed.—All 
    containers containing samples for analysis shall be properly labelled and 
    the parcels shall be properly addressed.  The label on any sample of 
    seed sent for analysis shall bear,—  
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    serial number;  
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    name of the sender with official designation, if any;  
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>    
    name of the person from whom the sample has been taken;  
 </section><section>

<number>d</number>    
    date and place of taking the sample;  
 </section><section>

<number>e</number>    
    kind or variety of the seed for analysis;  
 </section><section>

<number>f</number>    
    nature and quantity of preservative, if any, added to the sample.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>26</number> Manner 
    of packing, fastening and sealing the samples.—All 
    samples of seeds sent for analysis shall be packed, fastened and sealed in 
    the following manner:—
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    The stopper shall first be securely fastened so as to prevent leakage of the 
    containers in transit.  
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    The container shall then be completely wrapped in fairly strong thick paper.  
    The ends of the paper shall be neatly folded in and affixed by means of gum 
    or other adhesive.  
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>    
    The paper cover shall be further secured by means of strong twine or thread 
    both above and across the container, and the twine or thread shall then be 
    fastened on the paper cover by means of sealing wax on which there shall be 
    at least four distinct and clear impressions of the seal of the sender, of 
    which one shall be at the top of the packet, one at the bottom and the other 
    two on the body of the packet.  The knots of the twine or thread shall 
    be covered by means of sealing wax bearing the impression of the seal of the 
    sender. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>27</number> Form of 
    Order.—The 
    order to be given in writing by the Seed Inspector under clause (c) of 
    sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 14 shall be in Form III.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>28</number> Form of 
    Receipt for Records.—When 
    a Seed Inspector seizes any record, register, document or any other material 
    object under clause (d) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 14, he shall issue a 
    receipt in Form IV to the person concerned.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>29</number> Samples 
    how to be sent to the Seed Analyst.—The 
    container of sample for analysis shall be sent to the Seed Analyst by 
    registered post or by hand in a sealed packet enclosed together with a 
    memorandum in Form V in an outer cover addressed to the Seed Analyst. 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>30</number> 
    Memorandum and impression of seal to be sent separately.—A 
    copy of the memorandum and a specimen impression of the seal used to seal 
    the packet shall be sent to the Seed Analyst separately by registered post 
    or  delivered to him or to any person authorised by him.   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>31</number> 
    Addition of preservatives to samples.—Any 
    person taking a sample of seed for the purpose of analysis under the Act may 
    add a preservative as may be specified from time to time to the sample for 
    the purpose of maintaining it in a condition suitable for analysis.   
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>32</number> Nature 
    and quantity of the preservative to be noted on the label.—Whenever 
    any preservative is added to a sample, the nature and quantity of the 
    preservative added shall be clearly noted on the label to be affixed to the 
    container. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>33</number> 
    Analysis of the sample.—On 
    receipt of the packet, it shall be opened either by the Seed Analyst or by 
    an officer authorised in writing in that behalf by the Seed Analyst, who 
    shall record the condition of the seal on the packet.  Analysis of the 
    sample shall be carried out at the State Seed Laboratory in accordance with 
    the procedure laid down by the Central Government. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>34</number> Form of 
    Notice.—The 
    notice to be given under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of section 15 to the 
    person from whom the Seed Inspector intends to take sample shall be in Form 
    VI. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>35</number> Form of 
    Report.—The 
    report of the result of the analysis under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> or sub-section 
    (2) of section 16 shall be delivered or sent in Form VII. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>36</number> Fees.—The 
    fees payable in respect of the report from the Central Seed Laboratory under 
    sub-section (2) of section 16 shall be Rs. 10/- per sample of the seed 
    analysed.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

<number>38</number> 
    Records.—A 
    person carrying on the business referred to in section 7 shall maintain the 
    following records, namely:—
 <section>

<number>a</number>    
    stock record of seed;
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>    
    record of the sale of seeds; 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 




    FORM I 
 




    Form of application for seed production under  

    the seed certification programme
 



1. Name (in 
    Block Letters) 
    ................................................................................
 



2. Complete 
    Address 
    .........................................................................................
 



(In Block 
    Letters) 
 



Village 
    ...........................................
 



Post Office 
    ....................................
 



District 
    .........................................
 



State 
    ...........................................
 



Telegraph 
    Office ..........................
 



Nearest Rly. 
    Station ....................
 



Telephone No. 
    .............................
 



3. Nearest 
    town ....................................its distance from your farm,  
    Highway No. or Route ....................................
 



4.  Name 
    of variety/kind of seed offered for certification.  
 



5. Area under 
    each variety/kind offered for certification.  
 



6. Class of 
    seed desired to be produced Foudation/Registered/Certified.  
 



7. Source of 
    seed for Item 6 above (also mention Tag No. and other particulars on the 
    tag).  
 



8. “Isolation 
    distance” (in  metres) from other varieties of the same crop North to 
    South: East to West.  
 



9. Actual or 
    proposed date of  planting.  
 




    Signature...........................
 




    Date..................................
 



(To be filled 
    in by the office of the Seed Certification Agency).
 



1.     
    Number of field inspections made 
    ............................................................
 



        
    Dates of Inspection
 



        
    (Copy of inspection reports to be attached).
 



2.     
    Report of Seed Analyst (copy to be attached).
 



3.     
    Certificate issued.
 



        
    Tag No.....................................
 



        
    Date of issue....................................
 



        
    Issued by  ....................................
 



  
    Signature               
    
 



                                                                                                              
    Director,               
    
 



Seed 
    Certification Agency.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 



    FORM II
 

Seed Certification 
    Agency ..................................................................
 

Tag No.  
    .........................................................................................
 


                                                                                                                       
    Director
 

Seed 
    Certification Agency
 

Kind 
    .................................. Variety 
    ...............................................
 

Lot No. 
    ..............................................................
 

Germination 
    ....................................% Not below  ....................%
 

Date of test 
    .............................................................................
 

Certification valid 
    upto ..........................................
 

Minimum pure 
    seed....................................................................%
 

Innert matter 
    .........................% Not more than ..........................%
 

Weed seeds 
    (Max)......................................................................%
 

Other crop seeds 
    ...................... Not more than ...........................%
 

Producer 
    .......................... (Name and Full Address) ........................
 

Class of seed 
    ...............................................................................
    
 

N.B.-—  
    1.  A white tag shall be used for foundation seed. 
 

            2.  A 
    purple tag shall be used for registered seed.   
 

            3.  A 
    blue tag shall be used for certified seed.   
 


            4.  
    Certification shall be valid for the period indicated on the tag provided 
    seed is stored under cool dry environment.
    
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


 

 
</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 




    FORM III
 



To, 

 



(Name and 
    address of the vendor)  
 




    ......................................................  
 




    ......................................................  
 




    ......................................................  
 



Whereas I 
    have reason to believe that the stock of seeds in your possession detailed 
    below contravenes the provisions of section 6 of the Seeds Act, 1966 (54 of 
    1966).  
 



I hereby 
    direct you under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 14 of the Seeds 
    Act, 1966 (54 of 1966) not to dispose of the said stock for a period of  
    ...................from this date and take action to remove the following 
    defects:—  
 



                   
    ..................................................
 



                   
    ..................................................
 



                   
    ..................................................
 



Place 
    ....................................                                                               
    Seed Inspector
 



Date   
    ....................................                                                              
    Area 
 



  
    Details of stock of seeds
 



   
    ............................................
 



  
    ............................................ 
 



Date 
    ....................................                                                                
    Seed Inspector.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 




    FORM IV
 



 To,  
 



        
    ....................................................  
 



        
    ....................................................  
 



        
    ....................................................   
 



The records 
    detailed below have this day been seized by me under the provisions of 
    clause (4) of sub-section (1) of section 14 of the Seeds Act, 1966 (54 of 
    1966) from the premises of 
    ................................................................... situated 
    at ..............................
 




    Place..........................................                                                     
    Seed Inspector
 




    Date............................................                                                    
    Area
 



Details of 
    records seized
 




    ............................................................
 




    ............................................................
 



Date 
    ....................................                                                         
    
 



                                                                                                        
    Seed Inspector.
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 




    FORM V 
 




    Memorandum to Seed Analyst
 



Serial   
    No.  of   Memorandum....................................
 



From:  
 



     
    ............................................................
 



        
    .........................................................
 



 To 

 



     
    The Seed Analyst
 



     
    ......................................................
 



        
    ...................................................... 
 



The sample 
    described below is sent herewith for test and analysis under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (1) of section 14 and/or clauses (b) and (c) of sub-section (2) 
    of section 15 of the Seeds Act, 1966. 
 



             
    1.  Serial No. of the sample.
 



             
    2.  Date and place of collection.
 



             
    3.  Nature of the articles submitted for analysis/test.
 



2. A copy of 
    this memo and specimen impression of the seal used to seal the packet of 
    samples is being sent separately by post/hand.* 
 




    Place.......................................
 



Date 
    ..........................................                                                          
    Seed Inspector 
 



                                                                                                           
    Area 
 



*Strike out 
    whichever is not applicable  


 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 






    FORM VI
 



To
 



        
    ....................................................
 



        
    ....................................................
 



     
    .................................................... 
 



I hereby give 
    you the notice of my intention of taking a sample of seed from your stocks 
    for the purposes of tests or analysis.
 



Date 
    ..................................                                                                   
    Seed Inspector 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 




    FORM VII
 




    Certificate of test and/or analysis by the Seed Analyst
 



Certified 
    that the sample(s) bearing number 
    .............................................. purporting to be a sample of 
    ........................................... received on 
    ............................................................ Memorandum No 
    ........................ dated .................... from .............. 
    has/have been tested/analysed and that the result/results of such test(s)/analysis 
    is/are as stated below.
 




    ......................................................................................................................................
 




    ......................................................................................................................................
 



2. The 
    condition of the seals on the packet and the outer covering on receipt was 
    as follows:—
 




    .......................................................................................................................................
 




    .......................................................................................................................................
 



Place 
    ........................                                                                          
    Seed Analyst
 



Date 
    ........................                                                                           
    Central Laboratory 
 



If opinion is 
    required on any other matter suitable paragraph(s) may be added.
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Seeds Rules, 1968
 

 
 




    FORM VIII
 



To
 



      
    ....................................................
 



     
    ....................................................
 



     
    ................................................... 
 



I have this 
    day taken from the premises of 
    .......................................................... situated at 
    .......................................................... samples of seeds 
    specified below to have the same tested/ analysed by Seed Analyst. 

 



Date 
    ..................................                                                                   
    Seed Inspector
 



Details of 
    samples taken
 




    ....................................................
 




    ....................................................
 




    .................................................... 
 



Whether cost 
    of sample damanded?
 



Cost of 
    sample ........................Rs................................................. 
    paid.
 



Date 
    ............................                                                             
    
 



                                                                                                           
    Seed Inspector
 



                                                                                                           
    Area 
 



Signature of 
    the party from whose 
 



premises 
    samples taken and payment made.
 

 
 
 

 

 
  
  
  


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 389(E), dated 10th June, 1981 (w.e.f. 
    10-6-1981).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Omitted by G.S.R. 329(E), dated 30th June, 1973.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 329(E), dated 30th June, 1973.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 329(E), 30th June, 1973.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 211(E), dated 29th April, 1975 and corrigendum 
    G.S.R. 52(E), dated 30th January, 1976.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>