<act><title>


The Road Transport Corporations Act, 1950</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Road Transport Corporations Act, 1950. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India 

    1[***] 
    2[***]: 
 


    3[Provided that on and 
    from the commencement of the Delhi Road Transport Laws (Amendment) Act, 
    1971, this Act, as amended by the said Act, shall extend to, and be in force 
    in the Union territory of Delhi:]  
 


    4[Provided further 
    that on and from the commencement of the Road Transport Corporations 
    (Amendment) Act, 1982, this Act as amended by the said Act, shall extend to 
    the Union territory of Mizoram.]  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in a State on such date5 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    in this behalf for such State and different dates may be appointed for 
    different States.  
 
 
 
 






 
 
 
 
State or 
        Union Territory
 
Date of 
        Commencement
 

        Notification No.
 
Where 
        Published

 
 
1
 
2
 
3
 
4

 
  

 
 Andhra
 
01-12-1957
 
S.R.O. 3813
 Gazette of 
        India, 1957, Pt. II Sec. 3, p. 2776

 
 Assam
 
10-3-1970
 
S.O. 968
 Gazette of 
        India, 1970, Pt. II Sec. 3(ii), p. 1311

 
 Bihar
 
01-08-1952
 
S.R.O. 1526
 Gazette of 
        India, 1952, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 1386

 
 Bombay (Gujrat 
        and Maharashtra)
 
06-12-1950
 
S.R.O. 1061
 Gazette of 
        India, 1950, Pt. II Sec. 3, p. 1089

 
 Delhi
 
03-11-1971
 
S.O. 5081
 Gazette of 
        India, Extra., 1971, Pt. II, Sec. 3(i) p. 3057

 
 Himachal 
        Pradesh
 
28-03-1958
 
S.O. 372A
 Gazette of 
        India, Extra., 1958, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 421

 
 Jammu and 
        Kashmir
 
01-04-1976
 
S.O.263(E)
 Gazette of 
        India, 1976, Pt. II, Sec. 3, 3(i) p. 719

 
 Kerala
 
01-01-1965
 
S.O. 38
 Gazette of 
        India, 1965, Pt. II, Sec. 3(iii), p. 20

 
 Madhya 
        Pradesh
 
01-04-1961
 
S.O. 524
 Gazette of 
        India, 1961, Pt. II Sec. 3(ii), p. 583

 
 Mysore
 
01-08-1958
 
S.R.O. 1410
 Gazette of 
        India, 1958, Pt. II, Sec 3(iii), p. 1229

 
 Orissa
 
01-06-1956
 
S.R.O. 1204
 Gazette of 
        India, 1956, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 764

 
 Punjab (Haryana 
        and Chandigarh)
 
10-08-1954
 
S.R.O. 2629
 Gazette of 
        India, 1954 Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 1959

 
 Rajasthan
 
05-09-1964
 
S.O. 3049
 Gazette of 
        India, 1964, Pt. II Sec. 3, p. 3417

 
 Tripura
 
01-03-1961
 
S.O. 491
 Gazette of 
        India, 1961, Pt. II Sec. 3(ii), p. 567

 
 Uttar 
        Pradesh
 
01-04-1972
 
S.O. 1074
 Gazette of 
        India, 1972, Pt. II, Sec 3(ii), p. 1698

 
 Uttaranchal
 
01-10-2002
 
S.O. 998(E)
 Gazette of 
        India, 2002, Pt. II, Sec 3(ii), p. 1

 
 West Bengal
 
02-03-1953
 
S.R.O. 375
 Gazette of 
        India, 1953, Pt. II, Sec 3, p. 249






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “ancillary service” means any 
    subsidiary service which provides amenities or facilities to persons making 
    use of any road transport service of a Corporation;  
 

1[(aa)    
    “Board” means the Board of Directors of a Corporation;]  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Corporation” means a Road 
    Transport Corporation established under section 3;  
 

1[(bb)    
    “Director” means a member of the Board;]  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “extended area” means any area or 
    route to which the opera­tion of any road transport service of a Corporation 
    has been extended in the manner provided in section 20;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “road transport service” means a 
    service carrying passengers or goods or both by road in vehicles for hire or 
    reward;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “vehicle” means any mechanically 
    propelled vehicles, used or capable of being used for the purpose of road 
    transport, and includes a tram-car, a trolley-vehicle and a trailer;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    words and expressions used but 
    not defined in this Act and defined in the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 
    1939), have the meaning assigned to them in that Act.  
 


    2[***]
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Establishment of Road Transport Corporations in the States.—The 
    State Government, having regard to—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    the advantages offered 
    to the public, trade and industry by the development of road transport;
    
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the desirability of co-ordinating 
    any form of road transport with any other form of transport; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    the desirability of 
    extending and improving the facilities for road transport in any area and of 
    providing an efficient and economical system of road transport service 
    therein,
 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    establish a Road Transport Corporation for the whole or any part of the 
    State under such name as may be specified in the notification.
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Incorporation.—Every 
    Corporation shall be a body corporate by the name notified under section 3 
    having perpetual succession and a common seal, and shall by the said name 
    sue and be sued.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>5</number> Management of 
    Corporation and Board of Directors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The general superintendence, direction and management of the affairs and 
    business of a Corporation shall vest in a Board of Directors which, with the 
    assistance of its committees and Managing Direc­tor, may exercise all such 
    powers and do all such acts and things as may be exercised or done by the 
    Corporation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Board shall consist of a Chairman and such other Direc­tors, being not less 
    than five and not more than seventeen, as the State Government may think fit 
    to appoint.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    State Government may, if it so thinks fit appoint one of the other Directors 
    as the Vice-Chairman of the Board.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Rules made under this Act shall provide for the representa­tion, both of the 
    Central Government and of the State Government concerned, on the Board in 
    such proportion as may be agreed to by both the Government and of 
    appointment by each Government of its own representatives thereto and where 
    the capital of a Corpora­tion is raised by the issue of shares to other 
    parties under sub-section (3) of section 23, provision shall also be made 
    for the representation of such shareholders on the Board and the manner in 
    which the representatives shall be elected by such sharehold­ers.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    term of office and the manner of filling casual vacan­cies among the 
    Directors shall be such as may be prescribed.]  
 
 

 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Disqualification for being chosen as, or being, a 

    1[Direc­tor of 
    a Corporation].—2[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    A person shall be disqualified for being chosen as, or for being, a 


    1[Director of a 
    Corporation]—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if he is found to be a lunatic or 
    a person of unsound mind; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if he has been adjudged 
    insolvent; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    if he has been convicted of an 
    offence involving moral turpi­tude; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    if he has, directly or 
    indirectly, any interest in any sub­sisting contract made with, or in any 
    work being done, for, the Corporation except as a shareholder (other than a 
    director) in an incorporated company, provided that where he is a 
    shareholder he shall disclose to the State Government the nature and extent 
    of shares held by him in such company; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    if he has any financial interest 
    in any other road transport undertaking.  
 


    3[(2) Nothing in 
    clause (d) of sub-section (1) shall be deemed to disqualify the 


    4[Managing Director] 
    of a Corporation for being chosen as, or for being, a 

    5[Director] thereof.  
 


    6[(3) Nothing in 
    clause (e) of sub-section (1) shall be deemed to disqualify,—  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    any officer or other employee of 
    the Government for being chosen as, or for being, a Director of a 
    Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any officer or other employee of a 
    Corporation for being chosen as, or for being, a Director of another 
    Corporation.]
 
 











 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Resignation of office by the Chairman or a 

    1[Director].—The 
    Chairman or any other 

    1[Director] of a 
    Corporation may resign his office by giving notice in writing to the State 
    Government and, on such resignation being accepted by that Government, shall 
    be deemed to have vacated his office.  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Removal of Chairman and 

    1[Directors] from 
    office.—2[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    The State Government may remove from office the Chairman or any other 


    1[Director] of the 
    Corporation who—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    is or becomes 
    subject to any of the disqualifications men­tioned in section 6; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    without excuse 
    sufficient in the opinion of the State Govern­ment, is absent from more than 
    four consecutive meetings of the 
3[Board]:  
 
Provided 
    that no 

    4[Director appointed] 
    by the Central Government shall be removed from office without the 
    concurrence of that Government.  
 


    5[(2) The State 
    Government may terminate the appointment of any Director after giving him 
    notice for such period (being not less than one month) as may be prescribed:  
 
Provided 
    that the appointment of a Director appointed by the Central Government shall 
    not be terminated under this sub-section without the concurrence of that 
    Government.]  
 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Vacancies amongst members or defect in the constitution not to invalidate 
    acts or proceedings of a 

    1[Corporation or its 
    Board].—No 
    act or proceeding of a 

    1[Corporation or its 
    Board] shall be invalid by reason only of the existence of any vacancy2[in 
    its Board] or any defect in the constitution thereof.  
 
 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Temporary association of persons with a 

    1[Board] for 
    particu­lar purposes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A 

    1[Board] may associate 
    with itself for any particular purpose in such manner as may be determined 
    by regula­tions made under this Act any person whose assistance or advice it 
    may desire.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    person associated with it by the 

    1[Board] under 
    sub-section (1) for any purpose shall have a right to take part in the 
    dis­cussions of the 

    1[Board] relevant to 
    that purpose, but shall not have a right to vote at a meeting of the 


    1[Board].  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Meetings of 

    1[Board].—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A 

    1[Board] shall meet at 
    such times and places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub-sections 
    (2) and (3) observe such rules of procedure in regard to transaction of 
    business at its meetings as may be provided by regulations made under this 
    Act:  
 
Provided 
    that the 

    1[Board] shall meet at 
    least once in every three months.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    person to preside at a meeting of a 

    1[Board] shall be the 
    Chairman thereof, or in his absence from any meeting, the Vice-Chairman if 
    any, or in the absence of both the Chairman and the Vice-Chairman, 


    2[such Director as may 
    be chosen by the Directors present] from among themselves to preside.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    questions at a meeting of a 

    1[Board] shall be 
    decided by a majority of votes of the members present, and in the case of 
    equality of votes, the Chairman or, in his absence, any other person 
    presiding shall have a second or casting vote.  
 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Power to appoint committees and delegate functions.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    A 

    2[Board] may, from 
    time to time, by resolution passed at a meeting—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    appoint committees
    3[consisting 
    of Directors] for performing such function as may be specified in the 
    resolution; 
6[consisting 
    of Directors] for performing such function as may be specified in the 
    resolution;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    delegate to any 
    such committee or to the Chairman or Vice-Chairman, subject to such 
    conditions and limitations, if any, as may be specified in the resolution, 
    such of its powers and duties as it may think fit;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    authorise the
    4[Managing 
    Director] 
5[or 
    any other officer of the Corporation], subject to such conditions and 
    limitations, if any, as may be specified in the resolution to exercise such 
    powers and perform such duties as it may deem necessary for the efficient 
    day to day administration of its business. 
1[Managing 
    Director] 
2[or 
    any other officer of the Corporation], subject to such conditions and 
    limitations, if any, as may be specified in the resolution to exercise such 
    powers and perform such duties as it may deem necessary for the efficient 
    day to day administration of its business." 
 


    6[(2) The Chairman, 
    Vice-Chairman or Managing Director may dele­gate any of his powers and 
    duties [including powers and duties delegated to him under sub-section (1)] 
    to any officer of the Corporation, and the officer to whom such powers and 
    duties are delegated, shall exercise and perform such powers and duties 
    under the control and supervision of the Managing Director.]
 
 











 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>13</number> Authentication 
    of orders and other instruments.—All 
    orders and decisions of the board shall be authenticated by the signa­ture 
    of the Secretary or by any such other officer of the Corpo­ration as may be 
    authorised in this behalf by the Board or under the regulations made under 
    section 45 and all other instruments issued by a Board shall be 
    authenticated by the signature of the Managing Director or any other officer 
    of the Corporation author­ised in like manner in this behalf.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Officers and servants of the Corporation.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Corpo­ration shall have a Managing Director, a Chief Accounts Officer 
    and a Financial Adviser, appointed by the State Government: 
 
 
Provided 
    that the same person may be appointed as the Chief Accounts Officer and the 
    Financial Adviser.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    Corporation may appoint 

    2[a Secretary and such 
    other offic­ers and employees] as it considers necessary for the efficient 
    performance of its functions.  
 


    3[(3) The conditions 
    of appointment and service and the scales of pay of the officers and 
    employees of a Corporation shall—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    as respects the Managing 
    Director, the Chief Accounts Offic­er and the Financial Adviser, or, as the 
    case may be, the Chief Accounts Officer-cum-Financial Adviser, be such, as 
    may be prescribed, and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    as respects the other 
    officers and employees, be such, as may, subject to the provisions of 
    section 34, be determined by regulations made under this Act.]
 
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>15</number> Managing 
    Director, Chief Accounts Officer and Financial Adviser.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Managing Director shall be the executive head of the Corporation and all 
    other officers and employees of the Corporation shall be subordinate to him.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Managing Director shall obtain the views of the Chief Accounts Officer and 
    the Financial Adviser or, as the case may be, the Chief Accounts 
    Officer-cum-Financial Adviser, on every proposal involving revenues, or 
    expenditure from the fund, of the Corporation and shall cause such views to 
    be placed before the Board prior to the consideration of such proposal by 
    the Board.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    General disqualification of all officers and servants.—No 
    person who has directly or indirectly, by himself or his partner or agent, 
    any share or interest in any contract, by or on behalf of a Corporation, or 
    in any other road transport undertaking shall become or remain an 


    1[officer or other 
    employee] of the Corporation. 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Appointment of Advisory Council.—The 
    State Government may, after ascertaining the views of the Corporation, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, constitute one or more Advisory 
    Councils consisting of such number of persons, on such terms, and for the 
    purpose of advising the Corporation on such matters, as may be specified in 
    that notification. 
 
 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
*<number>17A</number> 
    Establishment of subsidiary corporation.—
<section><number>1</number>Where 
    a Corpo­ration (hereafter in this section referred to as the parent 
    Corporation) is satisfied that it is expedient or necessary so to do for the 
    more efficient discharge of its functions under this Act, it may, with the 
    concurrence of the State Government and the Central Government, frame by 
    notification in the Official Gazette a scheme or schemes providing for the 
    establishment of one or more subsidiary corporations. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    scheme framed under sub-section (1) shall specify the sub­sidiary 
    corporation or corporations which shall become estab­lished thereunder, the 
    date or dates with effect from which they shall be so established, the 
    powers and functions of the parent Corporation which such subsidiary 
    corporation or corporations may exercise and discharge, the conditions and 
    limitations subject to which such powers may be exercised, the management of 
    the affairs of each such subsidiary corporation by a Board of Directors, the 
    capital of each such subsidiary corporation and all other matters relating 
    to such subsidiary corporations corresponding to the various matters for 
    which provisions have been made in this Act with respect to the parent 
    Corporation:  
 
Provided 
    that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    no subsidiary 
    corporation shall start operation on any new route without the previous 
    approval of the parent Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the 
    representatives of the Central Government on the Board of Directors of a 
    subsidiary corporation shall be in proportion to its contribution to the 
    capital of the parent Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the liability of 
    the Central Government to provide contribution to the capital of the 
    subsidiary corporation to the parent Corporation shall not be increased 
    without the appro­val of the Central Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a subsidiary 
    corporation shall have a Managing Director, a Chief Accounts Officer and a 
    Financial Adviser or a Chief Ac­counts Officer-cum-Financial Adviser, and 
    such officers shall be appointed by the State Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the State 
    Government and the parent Corporation shall have power to give directions to 
    a subsidiary corporation in respect of any matter, including directions 
    relating to recruitment, conditions of service and training of the employees 
    of the sub­sidiary corporation, wages to be paid to such employees, reserves 
    to be maintained by the subsidiary corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the capital 
    budget, the revenue budget and the annual devel­opment plans of a subsidiary 
    corporation shall be submitted for approval to the parent Corporation and 
    where such budget or plan involves any deficit, also to the State 
    Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every subsidiary corporation established under a scheme framed under 
    sub-section (1) shall be a body corporate, by the name specified in the 
    scheme having perpetual succession and a common seal and shall by the said 
    name sue and be sued.
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    General duty of Corporation.—It 
    shall be the general duty of a Corporation so to exercise its powers, as 
    progressively to provide or secure or promote the provision of, an 
    efficient, adequate, economical and properly co-ordinated system of road 
    transport services in the State or part of the State for which it is 
    estab­lished and in any extended area:  
 
Provided 
    that nothing in this section shall be construed as imposing on a 
    Corporation, either directly or indirectly, any form of duty or liability 
    enforceable by proceedings before any Court or Tribunal to which it would 
    not otherwise be subject.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Powers of Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, a Corporation shall have power—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to operate road 
    transport services in the State and in any extended area;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to provide for any 
    ancillary service;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to provide for its 
    employees suitable conditions of service including fair wages, establishment 
    of provident fund, living accommodation, places for rest and recreation and 
    other amenities;  
 

1[(d)    
    to authorise the issue of passes to its employees and other persons either 
    free of cost or at concessional rates and on such condi­tions as it may deem 
    fit to impose;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    to authorise the 
    grant of refund in respect of unused tickets and concessional passes.]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the powers conferred by sub-section 
    (1) shall include power—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    to manufacture, 
    purchase, maintain and repair rolling stock, vehicles, appliances, plant, 
    equipment or any other thing required for the purpose of any of the 
    activities of the Corporation referred to in sub-section (1).  
 
Explanation.—In 
    this clause, the expression “manufacture” does not include the construction 
    of the complete unit of a motor vehicle except for purposes of experiment or 
    research;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    to acquire and 
    hold such property, both movable and immov­able, as the Corporation may deem 
    necessary for the purpose of any of the said activities, and to lease, sell 
    or otherwise transfer any property held by it;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    to prepare schemes 
    for the acquisition of, and to acquire, either by agreement or compulsorily 
    in accordance with the law of acquisition for the time being in force in the 
    State concerned and with such procedure as may be prescribed, whether 
    absolutely or for any period, the whole or any part of any undertaking of 
    any other person to the extent to which the activities thereof consist of 
    the operation of road transport services in that State or in any extended 
    area;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    to purchase by 
    agreement or to take on lease or under any form of tenancy any land and to 
    erect thereon such buildings as may be necessary for the purpose of carrying 
    on its undertaking;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    to authorise the 
    disposal of scrap vehicles, old tyres, used oils,2[any 
    other stores of scrap value, or such other stores as may be declared to be 
    obsolete in the prescribed manner];  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    to enter into and 
    perform all such contracts as may be neces­sary for the performance of its 
    duties and the exercise of its powers under the Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    to purchase 
    vehicles of such type as may be suitable for use in the road transport 
    services operated by the corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    to purchase or 
    otherwise secure by agreement vehicles, garages, sheds, office buildings, 
    depots, land, workshops, equip­ment, tools, accessories to and spare parts 
    for vehicles, or any other article owned or possessed by the owner of any 
    other under­taking for use thereof by the Corporation for the purposes of 
    its undertaking;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    to do anything for 
    the purpose of advancing the skill of persons employed by the Corporation or 
    the efficiency of the equipment of the Corporation or of the manner in which 
    that equipment is operated, including the provisions by the Corporation, and 
    the assistance by the Corporation to others for the provision of facilities 
    for training, education and research;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    to enter into and 
    carry out agreement with any person carrying on business as a carrier of 
    passengers or goods providing for the carriage of passengers or goods on 
    behalf of the Corporation by that other person at a thorough fare or 
    freight;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    to provide 
    facilities for the consignment, storage and deliv­ery of goods;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    to enter into 
    contracts for exhibition of posters and adver­tising boards on and in the 
    vehicles and premises of the Corpora­tion and also for advertisement on 
    tickets and other forms issued by the Corporation to the public;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    with the prior 
    approval of the State Government to do all other things to facilitate the 
    proper carrying on of the business of the Corporation.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Nothing in this section shall be construed as authorising a Corporation 
    except with the previous approval of the State Gov­ernment—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    to manufacture or 
    maintain anything which is not required directly or indirectly for use for 
    the purpose of the undertaking of the Corporation or to repair, store, or 
    provide any service for, any vehicle which does not belong to the 
    Corporation or is not used directly or indirectly for the purpose of its 
    undertak­ing;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    to purchase any 
    vehicle for the purpose of sale to another person;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    to sell or 
    supply to any person lubricants, spare parts, or equipment for or 
    accessories to, vehicles;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    to let vehicles 
    on hire for the carriage of passengers or goods except as expressly provided 
    by or under this Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Except as otherwise provided by this Act nothing in the fore­going 
    provisions shall be construed as authorising the Corpora­tion to disregard 
    any law for the time being in force.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Where a Corporation acquires the whole or any part of an undertaking of any 
    other person, the Corporation shall, in ap­pointing its 

    3[officers and other 
    employees], take into consider­ation the claims of employees employed in 
    that undertaking.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    provisions of this section shall not be construed as limiting any power of a 
    Corporation conferred by or under any subsequent provision of this Act.  
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Extension of the operation of the road transport service of a Corporation to 
    areas within another State.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a Corporation considers it to be expedient in the public interest to 
    extend the operation of any of its road transport services to any route or 
    area situated within another State, it may, with the permission of the State 
    Government, negotiate with the Government of the other State regarding the 
    proposed extension.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    the Government of the other State approves the proposed extension, the 
    Corporation shall prepare a scheme for the purpose and forward the same to 
    the other Government for its consent, and after such consent has been 
    received, the Corporation may, with the previous approval of the State 
    Government, sanction the scheme.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    After the scheme has been so sanctioned, it shall be competent for the 
    Corporation to extend the operation of its road transport service to such 
    route or area and when the operation of such service is so extended, the 
    Corporation shall operate the service on that route or in that area subject 
    to the provisions of any law in force in the other State within which such 
    route or area is situated.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Corporation may, from time to time, alter or extend the scheme sanctioned 
    under sub-section (2) by a supplementary scheme prepared and sanctioned in 
    the manner provided in the foregoing provisions of this section.  
 
  
 
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Carriage of mails.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 1939), a 
    Corporation shall, if so required by the Central Government, carry mails at 
    such rates and on such terms and conditions as may be specified in this 
    behalf by the Central Government in consultation with the State Govern­ment.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    General principle of Corporation’s finance.—It 
    shall be the general principle of a Corporation that in carrying on its 
    under­taking it shall act on business principles.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    General principle of Corporation’s finance.—It 
    shall be the general principle of a Corporation that in carrying on its 
    under­taking it shall act on business principles.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Capital of the Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government and the State Government, may provide to a 
    Corporation established by the State Government, in such proportion as may 
    be agreed to by both the Governments, any capital that may be required by 
    the Corporation for the purpose of carrying on the undertaking or for 
    purposes connected therewith on such terms and conditions, not inconsistent 
    with the provisions of this Act, as the State Gov­ernment may, with the 
    previous approval of the Central Govern­ment, determine.
 


    1[(2) The Corporation 
    may, whether or not any capital is provided to it under sub-section (1), 
    raise by the issue of shares such capital (hereafter in this section 
    referred to as the “authorised share capital”) as may be authorised in this 
    behalf by the State Government:  
 
Provided 
    that where any capital is provided to the Corporation under sub-section (1), 
    no capital may be raised under this sub-section without the previous 
    approval of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2A</number> Any 
    capital raised under sub-section (2) with the previous approval of the 
    Central Government may be,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    in addition to the 
    capital provided to the Corporation under sub-section (1);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    subscribed to by 
    the Central Government or the State Govern­ment, as the case may be, by 
    converting the whole or any part of the capital provided [whether before or 
    after the commencement of the Road Transport Corporations (Amendment) Act, 
    1982] to the Corporation by that Government under sub-section (1).]  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The
    

    2[authorised share 
    capital] of the Corporation shall be divided into such number of shares as 
    the State Government may determine; and the number of shares which shall be 
    subscribed by the State Government, the Central Government and other parties 
    (including persons whose undertakings have been acquired by the Corporation) 
    shall also be determined by the State Government in consultation with the 
    Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    allotment of shares to other parties mentioned in sub-section (3) shall be 
    made by the Corporation in such manner as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    shares of the Corporation shall not be transferable except in accordance 
    with the rules made under this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Corporation may at any time, with the previous approval of the State 
    Government, redeem the shares issued to the other parties under sub-section 
    (4) in such manner as may be pre­scribed.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Additional capital of the Corporation.—If, 
    after the issue of shares under section 23 a Corporation requires any 
    further capital, the Corporation may, with the previous sanction of the 
    State Government, raise such additional capital by the issue of new shares 
    and the provisions of sub-sections (2), 

    1[(2A)], (3), (4), (5) 
    and (6) of the said section shall apply to the issue of such shares.  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Guarantee by the State Government.—The 
    shares of a Corpora­tion shall be guaranteed by the State Government as to 
    the pay­ment of the principal and the payment of the annual dividend at such 
    minimum rate as may be fixed by the State Government by notification 
    published in the Official Gazette at the time of issuing the shares.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>26</number> Borrowing 
    powers.—A 
    Corporation may, with the previous approval of the State Government, borrow 
    money for the purpose of raising its working capital or meeting any 
    expenditure of a capital nature in the open market or from a corresponding 
    new bank constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies (Acqui­sition 
    and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970), or section 3 of the 
    Banking Companies (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 
    of 1980), a State Finance Corporation, established under section 3 of the 
    State Financial Corporations Act, 1951 (63 of 1951), the Industrial Finance 
    Corporation of India, established under section 3 of the Industrial Finance 
    Corporation Act, 1948 (15 of 1948), the Industrial Development Bank of 
    India, established under section 3 of the Industrial Development Bank of 
    India Act, 1964 (18 of 1964), the Life Insurance Corporation of India, 
    established under section 3 of the Life Insurance Corporation Act, 1956 (31 
    of 1956), or any other financial institution providing credit which is 
    subject to the control of the Reserve Bank of India.]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Fund of the Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Corporation shall have its own fund and all receipts of the 
    Corporation shall be carried thereto and all payments by the Corporation 
    shall be made there­from.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Except as otherwise directed by the State Government, all moneys belonging 
    to that fund shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank of India or with the 
    agents of the Reserve Bank of India 

    1[or with the 
    corresponding new banks constituted under section 3 of the Banking Companies 
    (Acquisition and Transfer of Undertak­ings) Act, 1970 (5 of 1970), or 
    section 3 of the Banking Compa­nies (Acquisition and Transfer of 
    Undertakings) Act, 1980 (40 of 1980),] or invested in such securities as may 
    be approved by the State Government.  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Payment of interest and dividend.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where 

    1[the whole or part of 
    the capital of a Corporation] is provided by the Central Government and the 
    State Government under sub-section (1) of section 23, the Corporation shall 
    pay interest on such capital at such rate as may, from time to time, be 
    fixed by the State Gov­ernment in consultation with the Central Government 
    and such interest shall be deemed to be a part of the expenditure of the 
    Corporation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where the Corporation 

    2[raises the whole or 
    any part of its Capital] by issue of shares, it shall pay dividend on such 
    shares at such rate as may, from time to time, be fixed by the Corpora­tion, 
    subject to any general limitations which may have been imposed by the State 
    Government in consultation with the Central Government, and such dividend 
    shall be deemed to be a part of the expenditure of the Corporation.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>29</number> Provision for depreciation and reserve and 
    other funds.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Corporation shall make such provisions for depreciation and for reserve 
    and other funds as the State Government may, from time to time, direct. tc 
    "29. 
    Provision for depreciation and reserve and other funds.—(1) 
    A Corporation shall make such provisions for depreciation and for reserve 
    and other funds as the State Government may, from time to time, direct." 
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The management of the said funds, the sums 
    to be carried from time to time to the credit thereof and the application of 
    the moneys comprised therein shall be determined by the Corporation: tc 
    "(2) The 
    management of the said funds, the sums to be carried from time to time to 
    the credit thereof and the application of the moneys comprised therein shall 
    be determined by the Corporation\:" 
 

Provided that no fund shall be utilised for any 
    purpose other than that for which it was created without the previous 
    approval of the State Government. tc 
    "Provided 
    that no fund shall be utilised for any purpose other than that for which it 
    was created without the previous approval of the State Government." 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>30</number> Disposal of net profits.—
After making provision for payment of interest and dividend under 
    section 28 and for depreciation, reserve and other funds under section 29, a 
    Corporation may utilise such percentage of its net annual profits as may be 
    specified in this behalf by the State Government for the provi­sion of 
    amenities to the passengers using the road transport services, welfare of 
    labour employed by the Corporation and for such other purposes as may be 
    prescribed with the previous appro­val of the Central Government, 


    1[and 
    out of the balance such amount as may, with the previous approval of the 
    State Government and the Central Government, be specified in this behalf by 
    the Corporation, may be utilised for financing the expansion programmes of 
    the Corpo­ration and the remainder, if any, shall be made over to the State 
    Government for the purpose of road development].
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

<number>31</number> Power of the Corporation to spend.— 
    A Corporation shall have power to spend such sums as it thinks fit on 
    objects authorised under this Act and such sums shall be treated as 
    expenditure payable out of the fund of the Corporation. tc 
    "31. 
    Power of the Corporation to spend.— 
    A Corporation shall have power to spend such sums as it thinks fit on 
    objects authorised under this Act and such sums shall be treated as 
    expenditure payable out of the fund of the Corporation." 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<number>32</number> Budget.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Corporation shall, by such date in each year as may be prescribed, 
    prepare and submit to the State Govern­ment for approval a budget for the 
    next financial year showing the estimated receipts and expenditure during 
    that financial year in such form as may be prescribed.  
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-sections 
    (3) and (4), no sum shall be expended by or on behalf of a Corporation 
    unless the expenditure of the same is covered by a current budget grant 
    approved by the State Government.  
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> 

    1[Subject 
    to such conditions and restrictions as may be specified in this behalf by 
    the State Government, a Corporation may sanction] any re-appropriation 
    within the grant from one head of the expenditure to another or from a 
    provision made for one scheme to that in respect of another, subject to the 
    condition that the aggregate budget grant is not exceeded.  
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> A Corporation may, within such limits and 
    subject to such conditions as may be prescribed, incur expenditure in excess 
    of the limit provided in the budget approved by the State Government under 
    any head of expenditure or in connection with any particu­lar scheme.  
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>33</number> Accounts and 
    audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Corporation shall maintain proper accounts and other records and prepare 
    an annual statement of accounts including the profit and loss account and 
    the bal­ance sheet in such form as may be prescribed by the State 
    Govern­ment in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of 
    India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of a Corporation shall be audited annually by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India or his nominee and any expenditure incurred by him 
    in connection with such audit shall be payable by the Corporation to the 
    Comptroller and Audi­tor-General of India.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India and any person appointed by him in 
    connection with the audit of the accounts of a Corpora­tion shall have the 
    same rights, privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General of India has in connection with the audit of 
    the Government accounts, and, in particular, shall have the right to demand 
    the production of books, accounts, connected vouchers and other documents 
    and papers and to inspect any of the offices of the Corporation.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the Corporation as certified by the Comp­troller and 
    Auditor-General of India or any person appointed by him in this behalf 
    together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the 
    State Government and that Govern­ment shall cause the same to be laid before 
    the Legislature of the State.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Direction by the State Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, after consultation with a Corporation 
established by such Government, give to the 
    Corporation general instructions to be followed by the Corporation, and such 
    instructions may include directions relating to the recruitment, conditions 
    of service and training of its employees, wages to be paid to the employees, 
    reserves to be maintained by it and disposal of its profits or stocks. tc 
    "34. 
    Direction by the State Government.—(1) 
    The State Government may, after consultation with a Corporation established 
    by such Government, give to the Corporation general instructions to be 
    followed by the Corporation, and such instructions may include directions 
    relating to the recruitment, conditions of service and training of its 
    employees, wages to be paid to the employees, reserves to be maintained by 
    it and disposal of its profits or stocks." 
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> In the exercise of its powers and 
    performance of its duties under this Act, the Corporation shall not depart 
    from any general instructions issued under sub-section (1) except with the 
    previ­ous permission of the State Government. tc 
    "(2) 
    In the exercise of its powers and performance of its duties under this Act, 
    the Corporation shall not depart from any general instructions issued under 
    sub-section (1) except with the previ­ous permission of the State 
    Government." 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Returns and reports.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Corporation shall furnish to the State Government such returns, 
    statistics, accounts and other information with respect to its property or 
    activities or in regard to any proposed scheme as the State Government may, 
    from time to time, require.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), a Corporation shall, 
    as soon as possible after the end of each financial year, submit to the 
    Central and the State Governments a report on the exercise and performance 
    by it of its powers and duties under this Act during that year and on its 
    policy and programme.  
 


    1[(3) The State 
    Government shall cause the annual report referred to in sub-section (2) to 
    be laid before the Legislature of the State.]  
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Power to order inquiries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government, with a view to satisfy itself that the powers and 
    duties of a Corpora­tion established by that Government are being exercised 
    and performed properly, may, at any time, appoint any person or persons to 
    make inquiries into all or any of the activities of the Corporation and to 
    report to the State Government the result of such inquiries.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Corporation shall give to the person or persons so ap­pointed all facilities 
    for the proper conduct of the inquiries and shall produce before, or furnish 
    to the person or persons any document, account or information in the 
    possession of the Corporation which such person or persons demand for the 
    purpose of the inquiries.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Power to control a part of the undertaking of a Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If on receipt of the report of any inquiry held under section 36 or 
    otherwise, the State Government is satisfied that it is necessary so to do 
    in the public interest, the State Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, author­ise any person to take over from the Corporation, 
    and so long as that notification is in force, to administer in accordance 
    with such directions as may be issued from time to time by the State 
    Government such part of the undertaking of the Corporation as may be 
    specified in the notification, and any person so authorised may, for the 
    purpose of so administering the said part of the undertaking, exercise all 
    or any of the powers of the Corporation or of any officer of the Corporation 
    under this Act, issue such directions as he thinks fit to the 

    1[officers or other 
    employees] of the Corporation and employ any outside agency.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Government may by such notification direct that all charges and 
    expenses incurred by the person so authorised togeth­er with such 
    remuneration as the State Government may allow from time to time to such 
    person shall be paid within such time as may be fixed by the State 
    Government from the fund of the Corpora­tion, and if the expenses are not so 
    paid, the State Government may make an order directing the persons having 
    the custody of that fund to pay to the person so authorised such expenses in 
    priority to any other charges against such fund and he shall, so far as the 
    funds to the credit of the Corporation admit, comply with the order of the 
    State Government.  
 


    2[(3) Every 
    notification issued under this section together with a report on the 
    circumstances leading to its issue shall be laid before the Legislature of 
    the State, as soon as may be, after it is issued.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Power to supersede a Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the State Govern­ment is of opinion that a Corporation established by 
    that Govern­ment is unable to perform, or has persistently made default in 
    the performance of the duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of 
    this Act or has exceeded or abused its powers, the State Government may, 
    with the previous approval of the Central Government, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, supersede the Corporation for such period as may be 
    specified in the no­tification:  
 
Provided 
    that before issuing a notification under this sub-sec­tion the State 
    Government shall give a reasonable time to the Corporation to show cause why 
    it should not be superseded and shall consider the explanations and 
    objections, if any, of the Corporation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    the publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding a 
    Corporation—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all the 
1[Directors] 
    of the Corporation shall, as from the date of supersession, vacate their 
    offices as such 
1[Directors];  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all the powers and 
    duties which may, by or under the provi­sions of this Act or of any other 
    law, be exercised or performed by or on behalf of the Corporation shall, 
    during the period of supersession, be exercised and performed by such person 
    or per­sons as the State Government may direct;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all property 
    vested in the Corporation shall, during the period of supersession, vest in 
    the State Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification 
    issued under sub-section (1), the State Govern­ment may—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    extend the period 
    of supersession for such further term as it may consider necessary; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    reconstitute the 
    Corporation in the manner provided in sec­tion 5.  
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Liquidation of a Corporation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No provision of any law relating to the winding up of companies or 
    corporations shall apply to a Corporation and no Corporation shall be placed 
    in liquidation save by order of the State Government concerned and save in 
    such manner as may be directed by that Government:  
 
Provided 
    that no such order shall be made by any State Government except with the 
    previous approval of the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    the event of a Corporation being placed in liquidation the assets of the 
    Corporation, after meeting the liabilities, if any, shall be divided among 
    the Central and the State Government and such other parties, if any, as may 
    have subscribed to the capital in proportion to the contribution made by 
    each of them to the total capital of the Corporation.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>40</number> 
    Compensation for acquisition of road transport undertakings.—Whenever 
    a Corporation acquires under this Act the whole or any part of any 
    undertaking, there shall be paid by the Corporation compensation the amount 
    of which shall be determined in the manner and in accordance with the 
    procedure hereinafter set out, that is to say,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    where the amount of compensation 
    can be fixed by agreement, it shall be paid in accordance with such 
    agreement;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    where no such agreement can be 
    reached, the amount shall be determined by an arbitral tribunal consisting 
    of one nominee of the Corporation, one nominee of the person to be 
    compensated, and a Chairman to be nominated by the Chief Justice of the High 
    Court exercising jurisdiction in relation to the State concerned;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    an appeal shall lie to the High 
    Court against the decision of the tribunal and the order of the High Court 
    on such appeal shall be final.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Corporation to be deemed to be a local authority and provi­sion as to third 
    party risks.—[Rep. 
    by the Road Transport Corpo­rations (Amendment) Act, 1959 (28 of 1959),
    sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-9-1959).]  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Power of entry.— 
    Whenever it is necessary for a Corporation to carry out any of its works or 
    to make any survey, examination or investigation, preliminary or incidental 
    to the exercise of powers or the performance of duties by the Corporation 
    under this Act, any 

    1[officer or other 
    employee] of the Corporation general­ly or specially empowered by the 
    Corporation may, with the previ­ous permission of the district magistrate, 
    enter upon any land or premises between sunrise and sunset, after giving 
    reasonable notice of the intention to make such entry to the owner or 
    occup­ier of such land or premises, and at any other time, with the consent 
    in writing of the owner or occupier of such land or premises, for the 
    purpose of the carrying out of such works or the making of such survey, 
    examination or investigation.
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number>
    

    1[Directors], 


    2[officers and other 
    employees] of a Corporation to be public servants.—All
    

    1[Directors] of a 
    Corporation and all 

    2[officers and other 
    employees] of a Corporation, whether appointed by the State Government or 
    the Corporation, shall be deemed, when acting or purporting to act in 
    pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act or of any other law, to be 
    public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 
    (45 of 1860).  
  
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by no­tification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules to give effect to the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 

1[(a)    
    the conditions and manner of appointment of Directors of a Corporation, the 
    representation in the Board of the Central and State Governments, and where 
    shares are issued to other parties under sub-section (3) of section 23 of 
    such shareholders and generally all matters relating to the constitution of 
    the Board;]  
 

2[(b)    
    remuneration, allowances or fees paid to the Directors of the Corporation or 
    other persons associated with the Board under section 10;]
 <subsection>
<number>c</number>    the term of office 
    of, the manner of filling casual vacan­cies among, 
3[Directors] 
    of the Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the number of
    3[Directors] 
    necessary to constitute a quorum at a meeting of the 
4[Board];  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the conditions of 
    appointment and service and the scales of pay of the 
5[Managing 
    Director, the Chief Accounts Officer, the Financial Adviser or, as the case 
    may be, the Chief Accounts Officer-cum-Financial Adviser] of the 
    Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the number and 
    term of office of, the allowances to be paid to, the procedure to be 
    followed by, and the manner of filling casual vacancies among, members of an 
    Advisory Council;  
 

6[(ff)    
    the procedure in accordance with which any stores may be declared obsolete 
    under sub-section (2) of section 19;]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the manner in 
    which the shares of the Corporation shall be allotted, transferred or 
    redeemed;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the manner in 
    which the net profits of the Corporation shall be utilised;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the date by which, and 
    the form in which, the budget shall be prepared and submitted in each year 
    under sub-section (1) of section 32;
 

7[(j)    
    the form in which the annual statement of accounts shall be prepared;]  
 

8[***]  
 <subsubsection>
<number>1</number>    the form in which 
    the returns, statistics or reports shall be submitted under section 35;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the procedure to be 
    followed by an arbitral tribunal under section 40;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    any other matter 
    which has to be, or may be, prescribed.  
 
 












 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Power to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Corporation may, with the previous sanction of 

    1[the State Government 
    and by notification in the Official Gazette], make regulations, not 
    inconsistent with this Act and the rules made thereunder, for the 
    administration of the affairs of the Corporation. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
    namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the manner in 
    which, and the purposes for which, persons may be associated with the 
2[Board] 
    under section 10;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the time and place 
    of meetings of the 
3[Board] 
    and the proce­dure to be followed in regard to transaction of business at 
    such meetings;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the conditions of 
    appointment and service and the scales of pay of officers and 
4[other 
    employees of the Corporation other than the Managing Director, the Chief 
    Accounts Officer and the Financial Adviser or, as the case may be, the Chief 
    Accounts Officer-cum-Financial Adviser];  
 

5[(d)    
    the issue of passes to the employees of the Corporation and other persons 
    under section 19;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the grant of 
    refund in respect of unused tickets and conces­sional passes under section 
    19.]  
  
 
 
 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>45A</number> Every rule and 
    regulation to be laid before State Legislature.—Every 
    rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before the State Legislature.]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>46</number> 
    Penalty for breach of rules.—The 
    State Government may, by rule, provide that the breach of any rules made by 
    it under section 44 shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
    hundred rupees, and when the breach is a continuing one, with a further fine 
    not exceeding twenty rupees for every day after the date of the first 
    conviction during which the offender is proved to have persisted in the 
    offence.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>47</number> 
    Special provisions relating to Bombay.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The body known as the Bombay State Road Transport Corporation and the Board 
    there­of, referred to in the notification of the Government of Bombay, No. 
    1780/5, dated the 16th November, 1949 (hereinafter referred to as “the 
    existing Corporation” and “Board” respectively) shall, notwithstanding any 
    defect in, or invalidity of, the enactment or order under which they were 
    constituted, be deemed for all pur­poses to have been validly constituted as 
    if all the provisions of the said notification had been included and enacted 
    in this section and this section had been in force continuously on and from 
    the said date, and accordingly—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all action by, and all 
    transactions with, the existing Corpo­ration or Board, including any action 
    or transaction by which any property, asset or right was acquired or any 
    liability or obliga­tion, whether by contract or otherwise, was incurred, 
    shall be deemed to have been validly and lawfully taken or done; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    no suit, prosecution or other 
    legal proceeding shall lie against the Government of Bombay or any member of 
    the Board or any officer or servant of the existing Corporation in respect 
    of any action taken by, or in relation to the setting up of, the existing 
    Corporation or Board merely on the ground of any defect in, or invalidity 
    of, the enactment or order under which the existing Corporation or Board was 
    constituted.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    the establishment of a Corporation under section 3 in the State of Bombay 
    (hereinafter referred to as “the new Corpora­tion”),—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the existing Corporation and 
    Board shall be deemed to be dissolved and shall cease to function;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all property and assets vesting 
    in the existing Corporation shall vest in the new Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all rights, liabilities and 
    obligations of the existing Corporation, whether arising out of any contract 
    or otherwise, shall be rights, facilities and obligations, respectively, of 
    the new Corporation; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    all licences and permits granted 
    to, all contracts made with, and all instruments executed on behalf of, the 
    existing Corpora­tion or Board shall be deemed to have been granted to, made 
    with, or executed on behalf of, the new Corporation and shall have effect 
    accordingly.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>47A</number> Special 
    provision for reconstitution or dissolution of certain Corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where on account of the reorganisation of States under the States 
    Reorganisation Act, 1956 (37 of 1956), 

    2[or any other 
    enactment relating to reorganisation of States, the whole or any part of a 
    State in respect of which a Corporation was, immediately before the day on 
    which the reor­ganisation takes place,] functioning and operating, is 
    trans­ferred on that day to another State and by reason of such trans­fer, 
    it appears to the State Government necessary or expedient that the 
    Corporation should be reconstituted or reorganised in any manner whatsoever 
    or that it should be dissolved, the State Government may frame a scheme for 
    the reconstitution, reorganisa­tion or dissolution of the Corporation 
    including proposals re­garding the formation of new Corporations, the 
    amalgamation of the Corporation with any other Corporation, body corporate 
    or a commercial undertaking of another State Government, the transfer of the 
    assets, rights and liabilities of the Corporation in whole or in part to any 
    other Corporation, body corporate or a commer­cial undertaking of another 
    State Government, and the transfer or re-employment of any workmen of the 
    Corporation, and the State Government may forward the scheme to the Central 
    Government for approval.  
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of framing any scheme under this sub-section, “State 
    Government”,—  
 

3[(i)    
    in relation to the Bombay State Road Transport Corporation, shall mean the 
    Government of the State of Maharashtra or of Gujarat as formed under the 
    Bombay Reorganisation Act, 1960 (11 of 1960);]
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>    in relation to the 
    PEPSU Road Transport Corporation, shall mean the Government of the State of 
    Punjab, as formed under the provisions of the State Reorganisation Act, 1956 
    (37 of 1956);
 

4[(iii)    
    in relation to the Assam State Road Transport Corpora­tion, shall mean the 
    Government of the State of Assam or of Meghalaya as formed under the 
    North-Eastern Areas (Reorganisa­tion) Act, 1971 (81 of 1971).]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of any such scheme, the Central Government may, after consultation 
    with the State Governments concerned, approve the scheme with or without 
    modifications and for the purpose of giving effect to the approved scheme, 
    the Central Government may, from time to time, make such order in relation 
    thereto as it thinks fit and every order so made shall have effect 
    notwith­standing anything contained in this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    order made under sub-section (2) may provide for all or any of the following 
    matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the dissolution of 
    the Corporation, notwithstanding anything contained in section 39;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the reconstitution 
    or reorganisation, in any manner whatsoev­er, of the Corporation including 
    the establishment, where neces­sary, of more than one Corporation in any 
    State;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the amalgamation 
    of two or more Corporations, or of one Corporation with any other body 
    corporate or a commercial under­taking of any other State Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the extension of 
    the area for which the Corporation is estab­lished, or the exclusion of any 
    area therefrom;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the transfer, in 
    whole or in part, of the assets, rights and liabilities of the Corporation 
    including the transfer of any licences or permits granted to the 
    Corporation, to any other Corporation, body corporate or a commercial 
    undertaking of any other State Government; and the terms and conditions of 
    such transfer;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the transfer on 
    re-employment of any workmen of the Corpora­tion to, or by, any such 
    transferee, and, subject to the provi­sions of section 111 of the State 
    Reorganisation Act, 1956 (37 of 1956), 
5[or 
    any other enactment relating to reorganisation of States], the terms and 
    conditions of service applicable to such workmen after such transfer or 
    re-employment;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    such incidental, 
    consequential and supplemental matters as may be necessary to give effect to 
    the approved scheme.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where an 
    order is made under this section transferring the assets, rights and 
    liabilities of any Corporation, then, by virtue of that order, such assets, 
    rights and liabilities of the Corporation shall vest in, and be the assets, 
    rights and liabili­ties of the transferee.]
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>48</number> Transitional 
    provision relating to Bombay State Road Trans­port Corporation.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 47A, it shall be lawful for the Government of 
    the State of Bombay to frame a scheme under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> thereof and 
    forward the same to the Central Government before the 1st day of May, 1960, 
    and in such case, the power conferred on the Central Government to make an 
    order under sub-section (2) thereof may be exercised before that day but no 
    order so made shall take effect till that day.]
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>48</number> Transitional 
    provision relating to Bombay State Road Trans­port Corporation.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 47A, it shall be lawful for the Government of 
    the State of Bombay to frame a scheme under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> thereof and 
    forward the same to the Central Government before the 1st day of May, 1960, 
    and in such case, the power conferred on the Central Government to make an 
    order under sub-section (2) thereof may be exercised before that day but no 
    order so made shall take effect till that day.]
  






 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>