<act><title>

THE 
    POLICE ACT, 1949</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Police Act, 1949.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to all the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Union Territories].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in a <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Union Territory] on such date as the 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint in 
    this behalf  for <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[such territory].
 
 
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In this Act “general 
    police-district” means the general police-district constituted under section 
    3. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of general police-district embracing two or more 
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Union 
    Territories].—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Police Act, 1861 (V of 1861), the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a 
    general police-district embracing two or more <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Union 
    Territories].
  








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Constitution of one police-force for general police district.—The 
    entire police establishment in a general police-district shall be one police 
    force and shall consist of such number of officers and men and shall be 
    constituted in such manner as the Central Government may, by order, direct.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Superintendence and administration of police.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The superintendence of the police throughout a general police-district shall 
    vest in, and be exercised by, the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    administration of the said police-force shall vest in an officer, appointed 
    in this behalf by the Central Government, who shall exercise in respect of 
    that police- force such of the powers exercisable by an Inspector-General of 
    Police under the Police Act, 1861 (5 of 1861), as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.  
  


 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Application of the Police Act, 1861.—Save as otherwise expressly 
      provided in this Act, the provisions of the Police Act, 1861 (5 of 1861), 
      shall apply to the police-force constituted for the general 
      police-district as if it were one police force constituted for a State, 
      and members of the said police force shall have, in every part of 
      <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[any territory] which is included in the general police 
      distict the same powers, duties and privileges, and shall be subject to 
      the same liabilities, as they would have had, or would have been subject 
      to, as police-officers if they had formed a police-establishment under one 
      State Government.
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Saving.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall be deemed to affect the provisions contained in the Delhi 
    Special Police Establishment Act, 1946 (25 of 1946).
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by the A.O. (No. 
    3) 1956, for “Part C States’.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by the A.O. (No. 
    3) 1956, for “Part C State”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by the A.O. (No. 
    3) 1956, for “such State”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by the A.O. (No. 
    3) 1956, for “Chief Commissioners’ Provinces”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
      (No. 3) 1956, for “any State”.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>