<act><tid>1790298</tid>
<title>THE SHIPPING DEVELOPMENT FUND COMMITTEE (ABOLITION) ACT, <year>1986</year></title>

ACT NO. 66 OF <year>1986</year>
[ 24th December, <year>1986</year>.]

An Act to abolish the Shipping Development Fund Committee constituted 
under the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> and to provide for certain 
matters incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1001917</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>208656</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Shipping Development Fund Committee (Abolition) Act, <year>1986</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>774811</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1486419</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1840255</tid>
<number>a</number>" Act" means the Merchant Shipping Act, <year>1958</year> (44 of  
  <year>1958</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1439450</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the date of commencement of this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1744565</tid>
<number>c</number>" Committee" means the Shipping Development Fund 
Committee constituted under section 15 of the Act;

</section>

<section><tid>870995</tid>
<number>d</number>" desinated person" means the person appointed as such 
under section 16 of this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1688591</tid>
<number>e</number>" Fund" means the Shipping Development Fund formed under 
section 14 of the Act;

</section>

<section><tid>972725</tid>
<number>f</number>" notified order" means an order notified in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1806543</tid>
<number>g</number>" shipowner" means a person of the description mentioned 
in section 21 of the Act or who had obtained loans or financial 
assistance in any other form from the Committee;

</section>

<section><tid>1367495</tid>
<number>h</number>" shipping concern" means any concern engaged in the 
business of shipping, owned, controlled or managed by a 
shipowner.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1316</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 3. 4. <year>1987</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 304 (E), dated 3. 4. <year>1987</year>, 
Gazette of India, Extraordinery, <year>1987</year>, Part. II, Section 3 (ii).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

ABOLITION OF THE SHIPPING DEVELOPMENT FUND COMMITTEE AND VESTING OFASSETS 
AND LIABILITIES OF THE COMMITTEE IN THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT

CHAPTER II

ABOLITION OF THE SHIPPING DEVELOPMENT FUND COMMITTEE AND VESTING 
OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES OF THE COMMITTEE IN THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1954843</tid>
<number> 3</number> Abolition of the Shipping Development Fund Committee and 
consequential amendments in the Act. On and from the appointed day, 
the Shipping Development Fund Committee constituted under section 15 
of the Act shall stand abolished, and accordingly the Act shall stand 
amended as follows:--
<section><tid>815992</tid>
<number>a</number>in the long title, the words" and a Shipping Development 
Fund" shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>38618</tid>
<number>b</number>Part IV shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1779708</tid>
<number> 4</number> Consequential provisions. On the abolition of the Committee,--
<section><tid>1737413</tid>
<number>a</number>all the rights and privileges of the Committee shall 
become the rights and privileges of the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>558446</tid>
<number>b</number>all properties, movable and immovable, including cash 
balance, reserve funds, instruments and moneys lying to the 
credit of the Committee and all rights and interests in, or 
arising out of, such properties as were immediately before the 
appointed day, in the ownership, possession, power or control of 
the Committee, and all books of account, registers, records and 
all other documents of whatever nature relating thereto, shall 
vest in the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1453065</tid>
<number>c</number>all borrowings, liabilities and obligations of the 
Committee of whatever kind and subsisting immediately before the 
appointed day, shall be deemed, on and from such day, to be the 
borrowings, liabilities and obligations, as the case may be, of 
the Central Government; and

</section>

<section><tid>1149061</tid>
<number>d</number>all contracts entered into, and all matters and things 
engaged to be done by, with or for, the Committee and subsisting 
immediately before the appointed day shall be deemed, on and from 
such day, to have been entered into, or engaged to be done by, 
with or for, the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>549987</tid>
<number> 5</number> Continuation of suits, etc., against Central Government.
<section><tid>883940</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If, on the appointed day, any suit, appeal or other proceeding of 
whatever nature in relation to the Fund or the Committee is pending by 
or against such Committee, the same shall not abate, be discontinued, 
or be in any way prejudicially affected by reason of the abolition of 
the Committee; but such suit, appeal or other proceeding may be 
continued, prosecuted and enforced by or against the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1075624</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, before the appointed day, no cause of action for any 
suit or proceeding or any right to appeal arose in favour of, or 
against the Committee and the institution of any suit or proceeding on 
such cause of action or the filing of such appeal was not barred 
before the appointed day, such suit or proceeding may be instituted or 
appeal may be filed by or against the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1317</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1655501</tid>
<number>6</number>Moneys, etc., of the Committee to be credited to the 
Consolidated Fund of India. On the appointed day, all moneys and cash 
balances lying in the credit of the Committee shall become part of, 
and be credited to, the Consolidated Fund of India.


</article>



<article><tid>1261226</tid>
<number> 7</number> Transfer of services of existing employees of the Committee.

<section><tid>1945572</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person, who has been, immediately before the appointed day,  
employed under the Committee, shall become, on and from the appointed 
day, an employee of the Central Government and shall hold office under 
the Central Government with the same rights and privileges as to 
pension, gratuity and other matters as would have been admissible to 
him if there had been no such vesting and shall continue to do so 
unless and until his employment under the Central Government is duly 
terminated or until his remuneration and other conditions of service 
are duly altered by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>105762</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial Disputes 
Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>), or in any other law for the time being in 
force, the transfer of the services of any officer or other person 
employed under the Committee shall not entitle such officer or other 
employee to any compensation under this Act or under any other law for 
the time being in force and no such claim shall be entertained by any 
court, tribunal or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1577052</tid>
<number>3</number>Where, under the terms of any contract of service or 
otherwise, any person, whose services stand transferred to the Central 
Government by reason of the provisions of this Act, is entitled to any 
arrears of salary or wages or any payments for any leave not availed 
of, or to any other payment, not being payment by way of gratuity or 
pension, such person may enforce his claim against the Central 
Government.
CHAP

SPECIAL POWERS OF THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT

CHAPTER III

SPECIAL POWERS OF THE CENTRAL GOVERNMENT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1625234</tid>
<number> 8</number> Power of Central Government to call for repayment before 
agreed period. Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for 
the time being in force or anything in any agreement to the contrary, 
the Central Government may, by notice in writing, require a shipowner 
to whom the Committee had granted any financial assistance at any time 
before the appointed day, to discharge forthwith in full his entire 
dues and also discharge his other liabilities to the Central 
Government, if--
<section><tid>901406</tid>
<number>a</number>it appears to the Central Government that false or 
misleading information in any material particular was given by 
the shipowner for the purpose of procuring or for continuing to 
procure the benefit of such financial assistance; or

</section>

<section><tid>622742</tid>
<number>b</number>the shipowner has failed to comply with the terms of his 
agreement with the Committee; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1318</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1222106</tid>
<number>c</number>there is a reasonable apprehension that the shipowner is 
unable to pay his debts or, that proceedings for liquidation have 
been or may be commenced against the shipowner; or

</section>

<section><tid>1530171</tid>
<number>d</number>the Central Government has reason to believe that the 
shipowner has not used or applied the financial assistance 
granted by the Committee strictly for the purpose for which it 
was granted or has otherwise misapplied or misappropriated the 
same for wrongful gain; or

</section>

<section><tid>1500884</tid>
<number>e</number>the property assigned, charged, hypothecated, mortgaged 
or pledged to the Committee as security for financial assistance 
is not insured or kept insured by the shipowner to the 
satisfaction of the Central Government, or if such property has 
depreciated in value to such an extent that, in the opinion of 
the Central Government, further security to the satisfaction of 
the Central Government should be given and such security is not 
given; or

</section>

<section><tid>132214</tid>
<number>f</number>without the permission of the Central Government any 
ship, machinery, plant or other property, whether forming part of 
the security or otherwise, is removed by such shipowner without 
being replaced; or

</section>

<section><tid>169084</tid>
<number>g</number>for any other reason, it is necessary so to do to 
protect the interests of the Central Government.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this Act," financial 
assistance" shall include any loan, advance or monetary assistance 
including any guarantee or counter- guarantee given to the shipowner by 
the Committee at any time before the appointed day.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>994779</tid>
<number> 9</number> Appointment of receiver without intervention of court.
<section><tid>1367216</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where the Central Government issues a notice under section 8 and the 
shipowner fails to company with such notice, the Central Government 
may, notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force or anything contrary contained in any agreement, deed 
or other instrument in the nature of any guarantee or 
counterguarantee, appoint, without intervention of the court, a 
receiver to detain and take possession of any ship or other assets 
belonging to the shipowner whether mortgaged, hypothecated or charged, 
with power to--

<subsection><tid>574827</tid>
<number>i</number>sell such ship or other assets by public auction 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in section 51 
of the Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1637510</tid>
<number>ii</number>demand and recover all the income in respect of which 
he is appointed receiver of any such ship or other assets and to 
appropriate the same in the discharge of rents, taxes and other 
dues and outgoings affecting the same and in payment of the 
liabilities of the shipowner under any mortgage, hypothecation or 
charge to the Central Government; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1262793</tid>
<number>iii</number>use, operate, charter or lease such ship or other 
assets to generate incomes, rents or profits to meet the 
liabilities of the shipowner to the Central Government under the 
mortgage, hypothecation or charge, and pay the residue, if any, 
of the money received by him to the person who, but for the 
appointment of the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1319</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

receiver, would have been entitled to receive the income of which 
he is appointed receiver, or who is otherwise entitled to such 
property.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>941768</tid>
<number>2</number>A receiver appointed under this section shall be deemed to be 
the agent of the shipowner and the shipowner shall be solely 
responsible for the receiver' s acts or defaults unless such acts or 
defaults are due to any improper intervention on the part of the 
Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1238911</tid>
<number> 10</number> Appointment of directors and administrators.
<section><tid>387248</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the  
Central Government requires a shipowner to discharge his dues and 
liabilities pursuant to a notice issued under section 8 and the 
shipowner fails to comply with such notice, the Central Government 
may, notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, or anything contrary contained in any agreement, deed 
or other instrument in the nature of any guarantee or 
counterguarantee, and without prejudice to anything contained in 
section 9, by notified order, appoint as many persons as it thinks 
fit,--

<subsection><tid>828486</tid>
<number>a</number>to be directors of the company, if the shipowner is a 
company, as defined in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1646309</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, to be the administrators of the 
shipping concern.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1973443</tid>
<number>2</number>The power to appoint directors or administrators under this 
section includes the power to appoint any individual, firm or body 
corporate to be the directors or, as the case may be, administrators, 
on such terms and conditions as the Central Government may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1155509</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that the 
power to appoint directors or administrators include the power to 
remove or replace the persons so appointed.

</section>

<section><tid>1101522</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or in any 
other law for the time being in force, or in any instrument relating 
to the shipowner, if it is a company shall, in so far as it makes, in 
relation to a director, any provision for the holding of any share 
qualification, age limit, restriction on the number of directors or 
directorships, retirement by rotation or removal from office, apply to 
any director appointed by the Central Government under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>856168</tid>
<number> 11</number> Effect of notified order.
<section><tid>75594</tid>
<number>1</number>On the issue of a notified  
order under section 10--

<subsection><tid>1263259</tid>
<number>a</number>if the shipowner is a company as defined in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), all persons holding office as 
directors of the shipowner, and in any other case, all persons 
holding any office having the powers of superintendence, 
direction and control immediately before the issue of the 
notified order, shall be deemed to have vacated their offices as 
such;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>720611</tid>
<number>b</number>any contract of management between the shipowner and any 
director or person referred to in clause (a) holding office as 
such immediately before the issue of the notified order shall be 
deemed to have been terminated.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>281509</tid>
<number>2</number>The directors or administrators appointed under section 10 
shall take such steps as may be necessary to take into their custody 
or under their control, the property, effects and actionable claims to 
which the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1320</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

shipowner is, or appears to be, entitled, and all the property and 
effects of the shipowner shall be deemed to be in the custody of the 
directors or administrators, as the case may be, as from the date of 
the notified order.


</section>

<section><tid>735244</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the directors 
appointed under section 10, shall, for all purposes, be the directors 
of such company duly constituted under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>), and such directors shall alone be entitled to exercise all the 
powers of such directors.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>386202</tid>
<number>12</number>Powers and duties of directors and administrators. Subject to 
the control of the Central Government, the directors, or, as the case 
may be, the administrators appointed under section 10, shall take such 
steps as may be necessary for the purpose of efficiently managing the 
business of the shipowner and shall exercise such powers and discharge 
such duties as may be exercisable by persons in charge of managing the 
said business.


</article>



<article><tid>371297</tid>
<number> 13</number> No right to compensation for termination of contract of 
management, etc.
<section><tid>1367370</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary  
contained in any contract or in any law for the time being in force, 
no managing or whole- time director or any other director or a manager 
or any person in charge of management of a shipowner which is a 
company shall be entitled to any compensation for the loss of office 
or for the premature termination, under this Act, of any contract of 
management entered into by him with such company.

</section>

<section><tid>1254584</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (1) shall affect the right 
of any such managing or whole- time director, or any other director or 
manager or any such person in charge of management to recover from the 
shipowner moneys recoverable otherwise than by way of such 
compensation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>500196</tid>
<number> 14</number> Application of Act 1 of <year>1956</year>.
<section><tid>1997648</tid>
<number>1</number>Where directors have been  
appointed under section 10 in relation to a company, then, 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> or in 
the memorandum or articles of association of such company,--

<subsection><tid>599259</tid>
<number>a</number>it shall not be lawful for the shareholders of such 
company or any other person to nominate or appoint any person to 
be a director of the company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1201472</tid>
<number>b</number>no resolution passed at any meeting of the shareholders 
of such company shall be given effect to unless approved by the 
Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1131203</tid>
<number>c</number>no proceeding for the winding up of such company or for 
the appointment of a receiver in respect thereof shall lie or be 
continued in any court, except with the consent of the Central 
Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>970325</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act and subject to 
such other exceptions, restrictions and limitations, if any, as the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf, the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), shall 
continue to apply to a shipowner which is a company in the same manner 
as it applied thereto before the issue of the notified order under 
section 10.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1321</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1457940</tid>
<number> 15</number> Recovery of dues as arrear of land revenue.
<section><tid>546258</tid>
<number>1</number>Any amount  
payable to the Central Government by the shipowner pursuant to a 
notice issued under section 8 may be recovered in the same manner as 
an arrear of land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>250461</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, for purposes of sub- section (1), 
appoint an officer to prepare a certificate specifying the amount due 
from such shipowner and send it to the Collector of the district in 
which the shipowner owns any property or carries on business provided 
that the officer so appointed shall, before sending the certificate to 
the Collector, give an opportunity of being heard to the shipowner.

</section>

<section><tid>1385144</tid>
<number>3</number>The Collector shall, on receipt of such certificate, proceed 
to recover from such shipowner the amount specified in the 
certificate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>635874</tid>
<number> 16</number> Delegation of powers to the designated person.
<section><tid>1087083</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, and 
subject to such conditions, restrictions and limitations as may be 
specified therein or otherwise, delegate all or any of its powers and 
functions under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> this Act] to a designated person.

</section>

<section><tid>1373079</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any notification has been issued under sub- section (1), 
the provisions of this Act shall apply in relation to the designated 
person as they apply in relation to the Central Government in respect 
of any matter in relation to which the powers and functions of the 
Central Government have been delegated to the designated person.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1250167</tid>
<number>17</number>Effect of the Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any other law for the time being in force or in the 
memorandum or articles of association of any company which is a 
shipowner or in any agreement, deed or other instrument having effect 
by virtue of any law other than this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>782909</tid>
<number>18</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or any 
director or administrator appointed by the Central Government or the 
designated person or any officer or other employee of the Central 
Government or the designated person for any loss or damage caused or 
likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any other law or 
provision having the force of law.


</article>



<article><tid>676647</tid>
<number>19</number>Indemnification of directors, etc. Every director or 
administrator appointed under section 10 and the designated person 
appointed under section 16 shall be indemnified by the Central 
Government against all losses and expenses incurred by him in relation 
to the discharge of his duties, except such as are caused by his own 
wilful act or default.


</article>



<article><tid>175456</tid>
<number>20</number>Directors, etc., to be public servants. Every director or 
administrator appointed under section 10 and the designated person 
appointed under section 16 shall be deemed to be a public servant 
within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>).
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1322</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 41 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>