<act><title>THE ARMY AND AIR FORCE (DISPOSAL 
OF PRIVATE PROPERTY) RULES, 19531
</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title. </title>These rules may be called The Army and Air 
Force (Disposal of Private Property) Rules, 1953. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In this rule, unless the context otherwise 
requires: 
 <section><number>1</number> the Act means the Army and Air Force (Disposal of Property) Act, 1950; 

 </section><section><number>2</number> commanding officer; means the officer commanding the corps, department, 
detachment or unit to which the deceased or deserter belonged; 
 </section><section><number>3</number> corps means as prescribed by sub-rule (c) of the rule 161 of the Indian 
Army Act Rules, 1911; 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Officer includes a Warrant Officer subject to the Air Force Act, 1950; 

 </section><section><number>5</number> section means a section of the Army and Air Force (Disposal of Private 
Property) Act, 1950; 
 </section><section><number>6</number> sub-section means a sub section of the Army and Air Force (Disposal of 
Private Property) Act, 1950. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Securing of property. </title>The commanding officer shall keep 
the property secured by him under section 3 in a place of security. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Inventory. </title>The commanding officer shall also prepare an 
inventory of any moveable property left in camp or quarters of the deceased 
which for some reason cannot be collected, stating sufficient details and 
estimated value thereof and the reasons for its non-collection. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Saving as to the securing of property and preparation of 
inventory. </title>Where payment of the debts and expenses recoverable under 
the Act has been secured by a representative, or a person appearing to the 
commanding officer to be entitled to receive or to administer the estate or 
where there are no such debts and expenses to be recovered, the commanding 
officer may abstain from securing and making an inventory of the property of the 
deceased, if so requested by the representative, or such person. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Drawing of pay and allowances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The commanding 
officer may require the appropriate paying authority either to pay to him the 
pay and allowances due to the deceased or to hold the same on his behalf until 
disposed of by such commanding officer. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the pay and allowances have been required under sub-rule (1) to be 
held on behalf of the commanding officer, the appropriate paying authority shall 
not effect any recoveries therefrom on account of any public claim against the 
deceased after the receipt of such requisition from the commanding officer. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Listing of regimental and other debts in camp or quarters. 
</title>The commanding officer shall ascertain and verify and prepare a list 
of all the regimental and other debts in camp or quarters of the deceased and 
shall, before providing for their payment, have any doubt or difference about 
them settled. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Funeral expenses. </title>The actual and necessary expenses of 
the funeral, in or out of India of any person subject to the Army Act, 1950, or 
the Air Force Act, 1950 shall be borne by the Government to such extent as may 
be provided for in the relevant regulations issued under the authority of the 
Government of India from time to time. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Security for the payment of debts and expenses recoverable, under 
the Act. </title>The security required to be given under sub-section (4) of 
section 3 shall be a bond in the form given in Forms I and II Schedule I to 
these rules accompanied by a surety if considered necessary by the commanding 
officer. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Time limit for securing debts and expenses recoverable under the 
Act. </title>If payment of the debts and expenses recoverable under the Act is 
not made or secured by a representative under sub-section (4) of the section 3, 
or by other person appearing to the prescribed person to be entitled under 
section 10, within there months from the date of death, the commanding officer 
shall proceed to provide for their payment himself. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Custody of moneys. </title>Any cash collected or moneys 
realized by sale or conversion of property or from any bank shall be deposited, 
if practicable, in the civil treasury of nearest branch of the Reserve Bank of 
India or of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[State Bank] of India, in a current account to the 
credit of the commanding officer, otherwise in a regimental treasure chest or 
unit imprest account. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Saving of certain property from sale or conversion. </title>The 
commanding officer may if he thinks fit, postpone any sale or conversion of the 
property of the deceased until such time as a representative or a person 
appearing to the prescribed person to be entitled under section 10 has had an 
opportunity of notifying his wishes regarding the sale or conversion or the 
withholding from sale or conversion of any portion of the property. 
 <section><number>2</number> The commanding officer may comply with the wishes of a representative or 
such other person, but if he considers any such demand unreasonable, having 
regard to the insolvency of the estate or other similar reason, he may refuse to 
comply. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Mode of sale. </title>The property to be sold will be disposed 
of in the most advantageous manner either by private sale, or by public auction. 
When property is sold by a public auction, a representative of the commanding 
officer shall be present at the auction, and shall furnish a certified statement 
of the particulars of the sale to the commanding officer. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Disposal of private firearms and ammunition. </title>Private 
firearms and ammunition forming part of the property of the deceased shall not 
be delivered to a representative or to other person to whom the property or 
surplus of the property is handed over under section 10, or to a purchaser not 
being duly licensed, or authorised without licence to possess them. When the 
firearms and ammunition are not so delivered, they shall, be deposited at the 
nearest police station, or with a licensed dealer with the sanction of the 
District Magistrate concerned. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Disposal of medals, orders and decorations. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Medals 
and decorations of the deceased, whether issued before or after his death, shall 
not be sold for the purpose of paying the debts and expenses recoverable under 
the Act, nor shall they be handed over to the Administrator General when an 
estate is handed over to him for administration under section 7. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When secured by the commanding officer, medals shall be disposed of as 
follows: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> If the deceased has left any directions about their disposal whether in 
  his will or otherwise, according to those directions; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> if he has not, they may be sent to the widow, or next-of-kin of the 
  deceased in the following order of relationship; eldest surviving son or 
  grandson; eldest surviving daughter or daughter's son; father mother; elder 
  surviving brother or sister; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> if medals cannot be disposed of as above, they may be sent to any 
  relative or other person, who in the opinion of the prescribed person will 
  preserve them with due care as a memorial to the deceased. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Orders and decorations, other than medals, shall also be disposed of in 
the manner aforesaid, except where the rules or terms of the order and 
decoration provide otherwise. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Expenses of administration. </title>Only necessary and 
reasonable expenses will be incurred by the commanding officer in relation to 
the disposal of an estate. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Property of deceased officers. </title>The provisions of the 
preceding rules shall also apply to the property of deceased officers subject to 
the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, but with the following 
modifications, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> references to the commanding officers shall be construed as references 
  to a committee of adjustment or a standing committee of adjustments, as the 
  case may be, constituted in this behalf in the manner provided hereinafter; 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> references to sub-section (4) of section 3 in rules 9 and 10 shall be 
  construed as references to section 4. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Committee of Adjustment. </title>A committee of adjustment 
shall consist of three officers. Where practicable, the president should not be 
below the rank of Major or Squadron Leaders. 
 <section><number>2</number> A committee of adjustment shall be constituted by the following 
officers: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> if the deceased was serving with his corps, department, detachment, or 
  unit, by the commanding officer of the corps, department or unit, not being 
  below the rank of Lieutenant Colonel or Wing Commander if he is below that 
  rank, then by the Brigade or equivalent Commander, the Air Officer Commanding, 
  Command, or in the case of persons subject to the Army Act, 1950, the Station 
  Commander; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> if the death occurred at sea, by the officer commanding the troops on 
  board the ship; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> in all other cases, by the Brigade or equivalent Commander. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where a committee cannot be constituted on board a ship, it shall be 
constituted as soon as possible after the ship reaches its destination, in 
accordance with the provisions of sub-rule (2). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the officer authorised by sub-rule (2) or (3) to constitute a 
committee is, from any reason, unable to do so, he shall apply to superior 
authority. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Standing Committee of Adjustment. </title>
<section><number>1</number> <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[The 
Standing Committee of Adjustment shall consist of three persons, such persons 
being officers or officers and civilian Gazetted officers not below the grade of 
officer supervisor]. Where practicable, the president should not be below the 
rank of Major or Squadron Leader. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Standing Committee of Adjustment shall be constituted by order of the 
[Chief of the Air Staff]<footcitenum>10</footcitenum> or of such other officer as he may 
authorize in this behalf at any such time and place as is thought fit by the 
[Chief of the Air Staff]<footcitenum>10</footcitenum> or the officer so authorized. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Standing Committee of Adjustment may be dissolved at any time by the 
authority which constituted it. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> Constitution of committees when Standing Committee constituted 
</title>.No committee of adjustment shall be constituted so long as the 
Standing Committee of Adjustment remains constituted, and all references to a 
committee in these rules shall, during the period the Standing Committee remains 
constituted, be construed as references to the Standing Committee. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Property of deserters. </title>The provisions of the presiding 
rules except Rules 5, 8, 9, 10 and 12, shall apply, to the property of a 
deserter subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, with the 
following modifications namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> private arms and ammunition shall be deliverable only to a purchaser; 
  
 </section><section><number>b</number> the medals, orders and decorations of the deserter shall, if secured, 
  be sent to the Adjutant General. Army Headquarters, in the case of a deserter 
  subject to the Army Act, 1950, and to the <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[Director of Personal 
  Services], Air Headquarters in the case of a deserter subject to the Air Force 
  Act, 1950, for disposal according to the relevant regulations or orders to the 
  Government of India. </section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Property of persons of unsound mind. </title>The provisions of 
the preceding rules, except rules 8 and 21, shall reply to the property of a 
person subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, who is 
ascertained to be of unsound mind in the manner hereinafter provided, as they 
apply to the property of a deceased person, with the following modification, 
namely: 
 Whenever possible, the sale or conversion of his property may be deferred 
until he is removed from the active list or discharged from service. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Property of missing persons. </title>The provisions of the 
preceding rules, except rules 8, 21 and 22, shall apply to the property of a 
person subject to the Army Act, 1950 or the Air Force Act, 1950, who, while on 
active service, is officially reported missing, as they apply to the property of 
a deceased person, with the proviso that no action beyond the securing of his 
property, the drawing of his pay and allowances and ascertaining the regimental 
and other debts in camp or quarters shall be taken until he is officially 
presumed to be dead. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> Prescribed person for purposes of sections 3, 4, 5, 7, 8, 9, 11, 
12 and 13. </title>The prescribed person for purposes of sections 3, 4, 5, 7, 
8, 9, 11, 12 and 13 shall be: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> in relation to the estates of officers subject to the Army Act, 1950, 
  <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[the Joint Secretary Ministry of Defence;] 
 </section><section><number>b</number> in relation to the estates of officers subject to the Air Force Act, 
  1950, <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[the Joint Secretary, Ministry of Defence; ] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>c</number> in relation to the estates of persons, other than 
  officers, subject to the Army Act, 1950 (i) Brigade or equivalent Commander or 
  Military Attached to the Indian Embassy at NEPAL or Recruiting Officer. 
  KUNRAGHAT or Deputy Recruiting Officer, GHOOM <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[or Assistant 
  Military and Air Attachee, Embassy of India, NEPAL or the Officer-in-Charge 
  Pension Paying Officers POKHRA and DHANKOTTA,] in respect of persons domiciled 
  in NEPAL, and (ii) Brigade or equivalent Commander in respect of others; and] 
  
 </section><section><number>d</number> in relation to the estates of person other than officers, subject to 
  the Air Force Act, 1950, the air or other officer in charge of a Command or 
  Group Headquarters in respect of persons under their respective Commands, and 
  the Director of Personnel, Air Headquarters, in respect of persons in any of 
  the units directly administered by Air Headquarters. </section>




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number> Prescribed person for the purpose of section 10. </title>The 
prescribed person for the purpose of section 10 shall be the persons referred to 
in rule 24 and, so long as the commanding officer has under the Act the control 
of the property of a person, not being an officer or a deserter, or of the 
proceeds of the sale or conversion of such property, shall also include such 
commanding officer provided the total amount of or value of the said property 
does not exceed one thousand rupees. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>26</number> Payment of surplus by commanding officer or Committee of 
adjustment to the prescribed person under section 3 or section 4. </title>
<section><number>1</number> 
The surplus of an estate shall be paid to the prescribed person by deposit in an 
imprest account or deposit in the civil treasury to the credit of the officer 
maintaining the pay accounts of the deceased. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On receipt of the statement of the imprest account or the treasury 
receipt as the case may be, the authority to whose credit the surplus has been 
deposited shall hold the amount until disposed of by the prescribed person. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The part of the surplus which does not consist of money shall be kept by 
the commanding officer of the committee, as the case may be, in a place of 
security until disposed of by the prescribed person. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>27</number> Payment of surplus by the Administrator General to the prescribed 
person under section 7. </title>The surplus in the hands of an Administrator 
General shall be made over to the prescribed person in the manner provided for 
in  rule 26. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>28</number> Circumstances in which estate to be handed over to the 
Administrator General. </title>The Central Government may direct that the 
estate of a person not being a deserter, liable to be dealt with under the Act, 
shall be handed over to the Administrator General having jurisdiction in 
relation to the estate, in case it is apprehended that considerable difficulty 
or delay may arise in or about the collection or realisation of the effects in 
consequence of the character of any investment, or in consequence of it being 
requisite to institute some action or suit in relation to the property, or in 
case there is some other peculiar circumstances connected with the property 
making it, in the judgment of the Central Government, expedient to take that 
course. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>29</number> Form of Notice under section 8. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The notice required 
to be published under section 8 shall be in the form given in Form III in 
Schedule I to these rules, with such variation as circumstances may require. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The notice will be published in the Gazette of India and the 
Gazette of the State to which the deceased belonged. If considered necessary by 
the prescribed person, it may also be published once yearly in two newspapers to 
be selected by him. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>30</number> Delivery of property or surplus under section 10. </title>In 
determining the person to whom the property or surplus may be delivered or paid 
under section 10, the prescribed person shall take into consideration the law or 
custom of succession applicable to the person whose property is under disposal 
and the wishes, if any, of such person in this respect. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>31</number> Mode of delivering property or surplus to a representative or 
other person. </title>Property deliverable and money payable to a 
representative under section 3, 4 or 8, or to any other person under section 10, 
may be either handed over to him personally, or despatched or remitted to his 
last known address according to the procedure specified in this respect in the 
relevant regulations of the Government of India. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Manner in which a person may be ascertained to be of unsound 
mind. </title>The manner in which a person subject to the Army Act, 1950, or 
the Air Force Act, 1950 shall be ascertained to be of unsound mind for the 
purposes of the Act shall be by the finding of a medical board according to the 
procedure specified in this respect in the relevant regulations of the 
Government of India. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Reports. </title>
<section><number>1</number> When the commanding officer or a committee 
of adjustment conclude the disposal of an estate in so far as they are empowered 
by the Act and these rules, he or it shall send to the person prescribed in rule 
24 a detailed report of such disposal as soon thereafter as possible. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When an estate is handed over to an Administrator-General under the Act, 
he shall submit to the Central Government a return every six months of the 
estate handed over to him under section 7 and the manner in which they have been 
disposed of. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The reports referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by all the 
necessary documents and papers including those given in Schedule II to these 
rules. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> When an estate or surplus thereof is finally handed over under the Act to 
a representative or other person, a copy of the report referred to in sub-rule 
(1) or (2) shall be supplied to him free of charge. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If the commanding officer or a committee of adjustment does not dispose 
of an estate to the extent he or it is concerned herewith, within twelve months 
in the case of subjects of Nepal and five months in all other cases of the date 
of death, or desertion, or the date on which the person whose estate is being 
dealt with is ascertained to be of unsound mind, or on which he is officially 
presumed dead, he or it will after that period submit to the Adjutant General, 
Army Headquarters, in the case of persons subject to the Army Act, 1950, or to 
the <footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[Director of Personal Services], Air Headquarters, in the case 
of persons subject to the Air Force Act, 1950, a report, showing the stage of, 
and the cause of delay in the disposal of an estate. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Standing Committee of Adjustment shall submit to the person 
prescribed in Rule 24 a return, every six months, of all the estates being dealt 
with by it, showing in brief important details thereof including stage of 
disposal and the progress made. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>34</number> Exercise of powers of commanding officer in certain case. 
</title>
<section><number>1</number> Where a person not being an officer, subject to the Army Act, 
1950, or the Air Force Act, at the time of his death, or desertion, or being 
ascertained under the Act to be of unsound mind, or being officially reported 
missing while on active service, was surving outside India, he shall for the 
purpose of the Act, be also deemed to have belonged to his record office, depot 
or regimental centre, as the case may be, at the said time but the commanding 
officer of only one of them will dispose of the property of such person in 
India. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a corps, department, detachment or unit to which a person, not 
being an officer, subject to the Army Act, 1950, or the Air Force Act, 1950, 
belonged at the time of his death, or desertion or being ascertained to be of 
unsound mind or being officially reported missing while on active service, 
ceases to exit, such person shall, for the purposes of the Act, be deemed to 
have belonged to his record officer, depot or regimental centre, as the case may 
be, at the said time, but the commanding officer of only one of them will 
dispose of the property of such person. 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by S.R.O. 271, dated 14th July, 1964.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by S.R.O. 189, dated 9th July, 1982.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by S.R.O. 110, dated 28th March, 1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by S.R.O. 350, dated 1st December, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Ins. by S.R.O. 94, dated 5th March, 1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 272.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> Subs. by S.R.O. 256, dated 14th September, 
1962.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> Vide S.R.O. 308, dated 11th July, 1953, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 4, dated 11th July, 1953, p. 
272.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>