<act><title>THE MERCHANT SHIPPING (CONTROL OF POLLUTION BY NOXIOUS LIQUID 
  SUBSTANCES IN BULK) RULES, 20101</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Merchant Shipping (Control of Pollution by Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk) Rules. 2010. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>1A</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> anniversary date means the day and the month of each year which will correspond to the date of expiry of the International Pollution Prevention Certificate for the Carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> associated piping means the pipeline from the suction point in a cargo tank to the shore connection used for unloading the cargo and includes ship's piping, pumps and filters which are in open connection with the cargo unloading line; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> ballast water includes, 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> clean ballast which means ballast water carried in a tank which, since it was last used to carry a cargo containing a substance in Category X,Y or Z, referred to in rule 6, has been thoroughly cleaned and the residues resulting therefrom have been discharged and the tank emptied in accordance with the provisions of these rules; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> segregated ballast means ballast water introduced into a tank permanently allocated to the carriage of ballast or cargoes other than oil or noxious liquid substances and which is completely separated from the cargo and oil fuel system; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Category X, Y or Z means the categories specified in clauses (a), (b) and (c) respectively of rule 6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> certifying authority means the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> Chemical Codes includes 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Bulk Chemical Code which means the Code for the Construction and Equipment of Ships carrying Dangerous Chemicals in Bulk adopted by the Marine Environment Protection Committee of the Organization; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> International Bulk Chemical Code which means the International Code for the Construction and Equipment of Ships Carrying Dangerous Chemicals in Bulk adopted by the Marine Environment Protection Committee of the Organisation; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> Convention shall have the same meaning as assigned to it in  
    clause (e) of section 356B; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> Depth of water means the charted depth; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> En route means that the ship is under way at sea on a course or courses, including deviation from the shortest direct route, which as far as practicable for navigational purposes, shall cause any discharge to be spread over as great an area of the sea as reasonable and practicable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> Government ship means the ship owned by the Central Government or the State Government; 
 <subsubsection><number>L</number> liquid substances means such liquid substances having a vapour pressure not exceeding 0.28 MPa absolute at a temperature of 37.8°C; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>m</number> Manual means the Procedures and Arrangements Manual as per Schedule II; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> nearest land, with all grammatical variations, means the baseline from which the territorial sea of the territory in question is established in accordance with international law except that, for the purposes of the of north-eastern coast of Australia, it shall mean from a line drawn from a point on the coast of Australia in 
 
 latitude 11°00'S, longitude 142°08'E 
 to a point in latitude 10°35'S, longitude 141°55'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 10°00'S, longitude 142°00'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 09°10'S, longitude 143°52'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 09°00'S, longitude 144°30'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 10°41'S, longitude 145°00'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 13°00'S, longitude 145°00'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 15°00'S, longitude 146°00'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 17°30'S, longitude 147°00'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 21°00'S, longitude 152°55'E, 
 thence to a point latitude 24°30'S, longitude 154°00'E, 
 thence to a point on the coast of Australia in latitude 24° 42' S, longitude 153° 15' E. 

 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> noxious liquid substance means the substance indicated in the pollution category column of Chapter 17 or 18 of the International Bulk Chemical Code or falling under any of the categories specified in clauses (a), (b), and (c) of paragraph 6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> Organization means International Maritime Organization; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> ppm means ml/m 3 ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> residue means any noxious liquid substance which remains for disposal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>s</number> residue/water mixture means residue to which water has been added for any purpose including tank cleaning, ballasting or bilge slops; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>t</number> Schedule means the Schedule annexed to these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>u</number> ship construction includes ship constructed' and similar stage of construction. 
</subsection>
 Explanation. (i) ship constructed means a ship the keel of which is laid or which is at a similar stage of construction and a ship converted to a chemical tanker, irrespective of the date of construction, shall be treated as chemical tanker constructed on the date on which such conversion commenced but it does not include modification of a ship which complies with all of the following conditions: 
 
 <subsection><number>A</number> the ship is constructed before 1st July 1986; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>B</number> the ship is certified under the Bulk Chemical Code to carry only those products identified by that Code as substances with pollution hazards only; 
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> similar stage of construction means the stage at which 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>A</number> construction identifiable with a specific ship begins; and 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>B</number> assembly of that ship has commenced comprising at least fifty tonnes or one per cent of the estimated mass of all structural material, whichever is less. 
</subsubsubsection>
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>v</number> solidifying/non-solidifying substance includes solidifying substance and non-solidifying substance. 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 Explanation. (i) solidifying substance means a noxious liquid substance which in the case of a substance with a melting point 
 
 <subsection><number>A</number> of less than 15°C, is at a temperature of less than 5°C above its melting point at the time of unloading; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>B</number> equal to or greater than 15°C, is at a temperature of less than 10°C above its melting point at the time of unloading; 
 
 <subsubsection><number>ii</number> non-solidifying substance means a noxious liquid substance, which is not a solidifying substance; 
</subsubsection>
 <subsubsection><number>w</number> State Party means the State which is a party to the Convention; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>x</number> tanker includes Chemical tanker and NLS tanker. 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 Explanation. (i) Chemical tanker means a ship constructed  
  or adapted for the carriage in bulk of any liquid product listed in Chapter 17 of the International Bulk Chemical Code; 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> NLS tanker means a ship constructed or adapted to carry a cargo of noxious liquid substances in bulk and includes an oil tanker as defined in clause (1) of section 356B when certified to carry a cargo or part cargo of noxious liquid substances in bulk. 
 <subsubsection><number>y</number> viscosity includes High-viscosity substance and Low-viscosity substance. 
</subsubsection></subsection>
 Explanation. (i) high-viscosity substance means a noxious liquid substance in category X or Y with a viscosity equal to or greater than 50 mPa.s at the unloading temperature; 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> low-viscosity substance means a noxious liquid substance which is not a high-viscosity substance . 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Obligation to prevent pollution of sea by noxious liquid substances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Unless otherwise expressly provided, all ships certified to carry Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk shall be under obligation to prevent pollution of sea by noxious liquid substances and for that purpose comply with the provisions of these rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a cargo subject to the provisions of the Merchant Shipping (Prevention of Pollution by Oil from Ships) Rules, 2009 is carried in a cargo space of an NLS tanker, the requirements provided under the said Merchant Shipping (Prevention of Pollution by Oil from Ships) Rules shall also apply. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Exceptions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The requirements relating to discharge under these rules shall not apply to the discharge into the sea of noxious liquid substances or mixtures containing such substances when such discharge 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> is necessary for the purpose of securing the safety of a ship or saving life at sea; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> results from damage to a ship or its equipment provided that all reasonable precautions for the purpose of preventing or minimizing such discharge have been taken after the occurrence of the damage or discovery of the discharge and except where the owner or the master has acted either with intent to cause the damage, or recklessly with knowledge that the damage would probably result; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> is approved by the Central Government, when being used for the purpose of combating specific pollution incidents in order to minimize the damage from pollution: 
</subsection>
 Provided that any such discharge shall be subject to the approval of any Government in whose jurisdiction it is contemplated such discharge shall occur. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Exemptions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where the provisions relating to carriage are required to be amended on account of upgrading of the categorization of a substance, the following shall apply, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> where any amendment to these rules and the International Bulk Chemical Code or the Bulk Chemical Code involves changes to the structure, equipment and fittings due to the upgrading of the requirements for the carriage of certain substances, the Central Government may, having regard to each substance, either modify the requirements for their carriage or delay application of such requirements, to ships constructed before such amendment has come into force, for a specified period, if it deems that application of such amendments is unreasonable or impracticable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> when the Central Government relaxes application of amended rules under clause (a), it shall submit a report giving details of the ship or ships concerned, the cargoes certified to carry, the trade in which each ship is engaged and the justification for such relaxation, to the Organization for circulation to the State Parties for their information and appropriate action, if any, and reflect such relaxation on the Certificate referred to in rule 7 or 9; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> notwithstanding anything contained in clauses (a) and (b), the Central Government may exempt ships from the carriage requirements under rule 11 for ships certified to carry individually identified vegetable oils, identified by relevant footnote in Chapter 17 of the International Bulk Chemical Code, provided the ships comply with the following conditions, namely: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> subject to the provisions of this rule, the NLS tanker shall meet all requirements for ship type 3 as identified in the International Bulk Chemical Code except for cargo tank location; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> under this rule, cargo tanks shall be located at the following distances inboard and the entire cargo tank length shall be protected by ballast tanks or spaces other than tanks that carry oil as follows, namely: 
 
 <subsubsubsection><number>A</number> wing tanks or spaces shall be arranged such that cargo tanks are located inboard of the moulded line of the side shell plating not less than 760 mm; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>B</number> double bottom tanks or spaces shall be arranged such that the distance between the bottom of the cargo tanks and the moulded line of the bottom shell plating measured at right angles to the bottom shell plating is not less than B/15 (m) or 2.0 m at the centerline, whichever is the less, and the minimum distance shall be 1.0 m; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>C</number> the relevant certificate shall indicate the exemptions so granted. 
</subsubsubsection>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-rule (3), the provisions of sub-rule (1) of rule 12 shall not apply to ship constructed before 1st July, 1986 which is engaged in restricted voyages as determined by the Central Government between 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> ports or terminals within a State Party; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> ports or terminals of States Parties. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The provisions of sub-rule (2) shall only apply to a ship constructed before 1st July, 1986, if 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> each time a tank containing category X, Y or Z substances or mixtures is to be washed or ballasted, the tank is washed in accordance with a pre-wash procedure in accordance with Schedule IV and the tank washings are discharged to a reception facility; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> subsequent washings or ballast water are discharged to a reception facility or at sea in accordance with other provisions of these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the adequacy of the reception facilities at the ports or terminals referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of sub-rule (2), for the purpose of this rule, is approved by the Central Government within India or, as the case may be, by the Government of Stale Party within which such ports or terminals are situated; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> in the case of ships engaged in voyages to ports or terminals under the jurisdiction of other States Parties, the Central Government communicates to the Organization, for circulation to the State Parties, particulars of the exemption, for their information and appropriate action, if any; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the certificate required under these rules is endorsed to the effect that the ships is solely engaged in such restricted voyages. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> For a ship whose constructional and operational features are such that ballasting of cargo tanks is not required and cargo tank washing is only required for repair or dry-docking, the Central Government may allow exemption from the provisions of rule 12, provided that all of the following condition are complied with, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the design, construction and equipment of the ship are approved by the Central Government, having regard to the service for which it is intended; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any effluent from tank washings which may be carried out before a repair or dry-docking is discharged to a reception facility, the adequacy of which is ascertained by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the certificate required under these rule indicates 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> that each cargo tank is certified for the carriage of a restricted number of substances which are comparable and can be carried alternately in the same tank without intermediate cleaning; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the particulars of the exemption; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the ship carries a Manual approved by the Central Government; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> in the case of ships engaged in voyages to ports or terminals under the jurisdiction of other States Parties, the Central Government communicates to the Organization, for circulation to the State Parties, particulars of the exemption, for their information and appropriate action, if any. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Equivalents. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may allow any fitting, material, appliance or apparatus to be fitted in a ship as an alternative to that required by these rules if such fitting, material, appliance or apparatus is at least as effective as that required by these rules: 
 Provided that this authority of the Central Government shall not extend to the substitution of operational methods to effect the control of discharge of Noxious Liquid Substances as equivalent to those design and construction features which are prescribed by these rules. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the Central Government allows a fitting, material, appliance or apparatus as an alternative under sub-rule (1), it shall communicate to the Organization particulars thereof, for circulation to the State Parties, for their information and appropriate action, if any. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding the provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2), the construction and equipment of liquefied gas carriers certified to carry Noxious Liquid Substances listed in the applicable Gas Carrier Code, shall be deemed to be equivalent to the construction and equipment requirements under rules 11 and 12: 
 Provided that the gas carrier meets all of the following conditions, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> hold a Certificate of Fitness in accordance with the appropriate Gas Carrier Code for ships certified to carry liquefied gases in bulk; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> hold an International Pollution Prevention Certificate for the Carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk, in which it is certified that the gas carrier may carry only those Noxious Liquid Substances identified and listed in the appropriate Gas Carrier Code; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> be provided with segregated ballast arrangements; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> be provided with pumping and piping arrangements, which, to the satisfaction of the Central Government, ensure that the quantity of cargo residue remaining in the tank and its associated piping after unloading does not exceed the applicable quantity of residue as required by sub-rules (1), (2), (3) of rule 12; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> be provided with a Manual, approved by the Central Government or by a certifying authority duly authorized, ensuring that no operational mixing of cargo residues and water shall occur and that no cargo residues shall remain in the tank after applying the ventilation procedures prescribed in the Manual. 
</subsection>


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Categorization and listing of Noxious Liquid Substances and other substances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of these rules, noxious liquid substances shall be divided into four categories as follows, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Category X: Category X is the category of noxious liquid substances which, if discharged into the sea from tank cleaning or de-ballasting operations, are deemed to present a major hazard to either marine resources or human health and justify its prohibition from discharge into the marine environment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Category Y: Category Y is the category of noxious liquid substances which, if discharged into the sea from tank cleaning or de-ballasting operations, are deemed to present a hazard to either marine resources or human health or cause harm to amenities or other legitimate uses of the sea and justify a limitation on the quality and quantity of its discharge into the marine environment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Category Z: Category Z is the category of noxious liquid substances which, if discharged into the sea from tank cleaning or de-ballasting operations, are deemed to present a minor hazard to either marine resources or human health and justify less stringent restrictions on the quality and quantity of its discharge into the marine environment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Other Substances: Other substances include substances indicated .as OS (Other Substances) in the pollution category column of chapter 18 of the International Bulk Chemical Code which have been evaluated and found to fall outside Category X, Y or Z because, at present, they are considered to present no harm to marine resources, human health, amenities or other legitimate uses of the sea when discharged into the sea from tank cleaning of de-ballasting operations and the discharge of bilge or ballast water or other residues or mixtures containing only substances referred to as Other Substances' shall not be subject to any requirements of these rules. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Guidelines for use in the categorization of noxious liquid substances are given in Schedule I. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where it is proposed to carry a liquid substance in bulk which has not been categorized under sub-rule (1), the Central Government, in co-operation with the Governments of other State Parties involved in such proposed operation, shall establish and agree on a provisional assessment for the proposed operation on the basis of the Guidelines as per Schedule I and no such substance shall be carried until full agreement has been reached amongst all the Governments involved: 
 Provided that the Central Government shall as soon as may be but not later than thirty days after such agreement has been reached, notify the Organization and provide details of the substance and the provisional assessment for annual circulation to all State Parties for their information. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Survey and certification of chemical tankers. </title>Notwithstanding the provisions of rules 8,9, and 10, chemical tankers which have been surveyed by the Surveyors or, as the case may be, authorised persons and certified by the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Parties, in accordance with the provisions of the International Bulk Chemical Code or the Bulk Chemical Code, as applicable, shall be deemed to have complied with the provisions of the said rules, and the certificate issued under that Code shall have the same force and receive the same recognition as the certificate issued under rule 9. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Surveys. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Ships carrying noxious liquid substances in bulk shall be subject to the surveys specified below, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> an initial survey shall be conducted before the ship is put in service or before the Certificate required under rule 9 is issued for the first time and such survey shall include a complete survey of its structure, equipment, systems, fittings, arrangements and material so as to ensure that they fully comply with the requirements of these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a renewal survey shall be conducted at an interval not exceeding  
    five years except where the provisions of sub-rule (2), (5), (6) or (7) of rule 10 are applicable and the renewal survey shall be such as to ensure that the structure, equipment, systems, fittings, arrangements and materials fully comply with the requirements of these rules. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> an intermediate survey within three months before or after the second anniversary date or within three months before or after the third anniversary date of the Certificate which shall take the place of one of the annual surveys specified in clause (d) and the intermediate survey shall be such as to ensure that the equipment and the associated pump and piping systems fully comply with the requirements of these rules and are in good working order: 
</subsection>
 Provided that such intermediate survey shall be endorsed on the Certificate issued under rule 9. 
 
 <subsection><number>d</number> an annual survey shall be conducted within three months before or after each anniversary date of the Certificate, including a general inspection of the structure, equipment, fittings, arrangements and materials referred to in clause (a) to ensure that they have been maintained in accordance with the provisions of sub-rule (6) and that they remain satisfactory for this service for which the ship is intended: 
 Provided that such annual surveys shall be endorsed on the Certificate issued under rule 9. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> an additional survey, either general or partial, according to the circumstances, shall be made after a repair resulting from investigations prescribed in sub-rule (8) or whenever important repairs or renewals are made and such survey shall be such as to ensure that necessary repairs or renewals have, been effectively made, that the material and workmanship of such repairs or renewals are in all respects satisfactory and that the ship complies in all respects with the requirements of these rules. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Surveys of ships for the purposes of enforcement of the provisions of these rules shall be carried out by a surveyor appointed under section 9 or, as the case may be, a person authorised for that purpose under sub-section (1) of section 356G of the Act, by the Central Government, in accordance with the provisions of the said section 356G and the Central Government shall empower such surveyor or authorised person to 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> require repairs to a ship; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> carry out surveys if requested by the appropriate authorities of a port State: 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government shall inform the Organisation of the specific responsibilities and conditions of the authority delegated to such surveyor or authorised person for circulation to the State Parties for the information of their officers. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> When the surveyor or the authorised person determines that the condition of the ship or its equipment does not correspond substantially with the particulars of the Certificate or is such that, the ship is not fit to proceed to sea without presenting an unreasonable threat of harm to the marine environment, such surveyor or authorised person shall immediately ensure that corrective action is taken and shall also, in due course, notify the Central Government: 
 Provided that if such corrective action is not taken, the Certificate shall be withdrawn and the Central Government shall be notified immediately: 
 Provided further that if the ship is in a port of another State Party, the appropriate authorities of that Port State shall also be notified immediately: 
 Provided also that when any officer of the Central Government or surveyor or the authorised person has notified the appropriate authorities of the port State, the Government of that port State shall give such officer, surveyor or authorised person necessary assistance to carry out their obligations under these rules and shall take such steps as to ensure that such ship shall not sail until it can proceed to sea or leave the port for the purpose of proceeding to the nearest appropriate repair yard available, without presenting any unreasonable threat of harm to the marine environment. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> In every case, the Central Government shall fully guarantee the completeness and efficiency of each such survey and shall take necessary steps to satisfy such obligation. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The condition of the ship and its equipment shall be maintained to conform to the provisions of the Convention to ensure that the ship shall remain, in all respects, fit to proceed to sea without presenting any unreasonable threat of harm to the marine environment. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> After any survey of the ship under sub-rule (1) has been completed, no change shall be made in the structure, equipment, systems, fittings, arrangements or material covered by such survey, without the sanction of the Central Government except the direct replacement of such equipment and fittings. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Whenever an accident occurs to a ship or a defect is discovered which substantially affects the integrity of the ship or the efficiency or completeness of its equipment as covered by these rules, the master or owner of the ship shall report at the earliest opportunity to the Central Government responsible for issuing the Certificate, who shall cause investigations to be initiated by the surveyor or the authorised person to determine whether a survey as required by sub-rule (1) is necessary: 
 Provided that if the ship is in the port of another State Party, the master or owner shall also report immediately to the appropriate authorities of that Port State and the surveyor or the authorised person shall also ascertain that such report has been made. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Issue, or endorsement of Certificate. </title>
<section><number>1</number> After satisfactory completion of an initial or renewal survey in accordance with the provisions of rule 8, the Central Government shall issue an International Pollution Prevention Certificate for Carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk in Form I to any ship intending to carry noxious liquid substances in bulk and which is engaged in voyages to Ports and terminals under its jurisdiction. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a Certificate is issued under sub-rule (1), the Central Government shall, in every case, assume full responsibility for that Certificate. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government may, on the request of the Government of a State Party, cause survey of the ship and if satisfied that the provisions of these rules are complied with, issue an International Oil Pollution Prevention Certificate for Carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk to that ship and the copy of the Certificate and of the survey report shall be transmitted as soon as possible to the requesting Government of the State Party: 
 Provided that the Certificate so issued shall contain a statement to the effect that it has been issued at the request of the Government of the State Party and it shall have the same force and receive the same recognition as the Certificate issued under sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Government of a State Party may, at the request of the Central Government, cause a ship to be surveyed and if satisfied that the provisions of these rules are complied with, shall issue or authorise the issue of an International Pollution Prevention Certificate for Carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk to the ship and where appropriate, endorse or authorise the endorsement of that Certificate on the ship, in accordance with these rules and a copy of the Certificate and of the survey report shall be transmitted as soon as possible to the Central Government making such request: 
 Provided that a Certificate so issued shall contained a statement to the effect that it has been issued at the request of the Central Government and it shall have the same force and receive the same recognition as the Certificate is issued under sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section><number>5</number> No International Pollution Prevention Certificate for Carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk shall be issued to a ship which is entitled to fly the flag of a State which is not a party to the Convention. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Central Government shall issue an Indian Pollution Prevention Certificate for Carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk in Form II to any ship which is engaged in voyages to ports or offshore terminals in Indian waters. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Duration and validity of Certificate. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The International Pollution Prevention Certificate for the carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk or, as the case may be, the Indian Pollution Prevention Certificate for the carriage of Noxious Liquid Substances in Bulk issued under rule 9 shall be valid for a period of five years. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (I), when the renewal survey is completed 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> within three months before the expiry date of the existing certificate, the new certificate issued shall be valid from the date of completion of such renewal survey for a maximum period of five years from the date of expiry of the existing certificate; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> after the expiry date of the existing certificate, the new certificate issued shall be valid from the date of completion of such renewal survey for a maximum period of five years from the date of expiry of the existing certificate;

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> more than three months before the expiry date of the existing certificate, the new certificate issued shall be valid from the date of completion of the renewal survey for a period of five years from the date of completion of such renewal survey. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> If a Certificate is issued for a period of less than five years, the Central Government may extend the validity of the Certificate beyond the expiry date to the maximum period specified in sub-rule (1): 
 Provided that the surveys referred in clauses (c) and (d) of sub rule (I) of rule 8, which are required to be carried out when a Certificate is issued for a period of five years, shall also be carried out as may be appropriate. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> If a renewal survey has been completed and a new certificate cannot be issued or placed on board the ship before the expiry date of the existing certificate, the Central Government may endorse the existing certificate and such certificate shall be accepted as valid for a further period of five months from the expiry date. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If, at a time when the Certificate expires, a ship is not in the port in which it is to be surveyed, or in such other cases as it deems proper and reasonable so to do, the Central Government may, extend the period of validity of the certificate: 
 Provided that such extension shall be granted only for the purpose of allowing the ship to complete its voyage to the port in which it is to surveyed: 
 Provided further that such extension shall not be granted for a period longer than three months: 
 Provided also that a ship to which an extension is granted shall not, on its arrival in the port in which it is to be surveyed, be entitled to leave that port without having a new Certificate and such new Certificate issued after the renewal survey is completed, shall be valid for a maximum period of five years from the date of expiry of the existing Certificate before the extension was granted. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where a certificate issued to a ship engaged on short voyages has not been extended under the provisions of sub-rule (5), the Central Government may extend the period of grace up to one month from the date of its expiry and the new certificate issued after the renewal survey is completed shall be valid for a maximum period of five years from the date of expiry of the existing certificate before the extension was granted. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Under such special circumstances as may be determined by the Central Government, the new certificate shall be issued for a maximum period of five years from the date of completion of the renewal survey and not from the date of expiry of the existing certificate as provided in clause (b) of sub-rule (2), sub-rule (5) and sub-rule (6). 
 </section><section><number>8</number> If an annual or intermediate survey is completed before the period specified in rule 8, then 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the anniversary date shown on the Certificate shall be amended by endorsement to a date which shall not be more than three months later than the date on which the survey was completed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the subsequent annual or intermediate survey required by rule 8 shall be completed at the intervals specified in that rule using the new anniversary date; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the expiry date may remain unchanged provided one or more annual or intermediate surveys, as appropriate, are carried out so that the maximum intervals between the surveys specified in rule 8 are not exceeded. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>9</number> A certificate issued under rule 9 shall cease to be valid in any of the following cases, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> where the relevant surveys are not completed within the periods specified under sub-rule (1) of rule 8; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where a Certificate is not endorsed in accordance with the provisions of clauses (c) and (d) of sub-rule (1 ) of rule 8; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> upon a transfer of the ship to the flag of another State Party: 
</subsection>
 Provided that no new certificate shall be issued by any Government required so to do unless it is fully satisfied that the ship is in full compliance of the requirements of sub-rules (6) and (7) of rule 8: 
 Provided further that in the case of a transfer between State Parties, if a request is made within three months after such transfer has taken place, the Government of the State Party whose flag the ship was formerly entitled to fly shall, as soon as possible, transmit to the Central Government copies of the certificate carried by the ship before such transfer and copies of survey reports, if available. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Design, construction, equipment and operations. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The design, construction, equipment and operation of ships certified to carry noxious liquid substances in bulk identified in Chapter 17 of the International Bulk Chemical Code, shall be in compliance with the following provisions to minimize the uncontrolled discharge into the sea of such substances, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the International Bulk Chemical Code when the chemical tanker is constructed on or after 1st July, 1986; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Bulk Chemical Code as referred to in paragraph 1.7.2 of that Code for 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> ships for which the building contract is placed on or after 2nd November, 1973 but constructed before 1st July, 1986, and which are engaged on voyages to ports or terminals under the jurisdiction of other States Parties; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> ships constructed on or after 1st July, 1983 but before 1st July, 1986, which are engaged solely on voyages between ports or terminals within the State the flag of which the ship is entitled to fly. 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The Bulk Chemical Code as referred to in paragraph 1.7.3 of that Code for 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> ships for which the building contract is placed before 2nd November, 1973 and which are engaged on voyages to ports or terminals under the jurisdiction of other States Parties; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> ships constructed before 1st July, 1983, which are solely engaged on, voyages between ports or terminals within the State the flag of which the ship is entitled to fly. 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> In respect of ships other than chemical tankers or liquefied gas carriers certified to carry noxious liquid substances in bulk identified in Chapter 17 of the International Bulk Chemical Code, the Central Government shall establish appropriate measures based on the Guidelines developed by the Organization in order to ensure that the provisions shall be such as to minimize the uncontrolled discharge into the sea of such substances. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Control of discharges of residues of noxious liquid substances. </title> Subject to the provisions of rule 3, the control of discharges of residues of noxious liquid substances or ballast water, tank washings or other mixtures containing such substances shall be in compliance with the following requirements, namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Discharge provisions 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the discharge into the sea of residues of substances assigned to Category X, Y or Z or of those provisionally assessed as such or ballast water tank washings or other mixtures containing such substances shall be prohibited unless such discharges are made in full compliance with the applicable operational requirements contained in these rules; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> before any pre-wash or discharge procedure is carried out in accordance with this rule, the relevant tank shall be emptied to the maximum extent <title></title>in accordance with the procedures specified in the Manual; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The carriage of substances which have not been categorised, provisionally assessed or evaluated as referred to in rule 6 or of ballast water, tank washings or other mixtures containing such residues shall be prohibited along with any consequential discharge of such substances into the sea; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>b</number> Discharge standards 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> where the provisions of this pule allow the discharge into the sea of residues of substances in Category X, Y or Z or of those provisionally assessed as such or ballast water, tank washings or other mixtures containing such substances, the following discharge standards shall apply, namely: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>A</number> the ship is proceeding en route at a speed of at least seven knots in the case of self-propelled ships or at least four knots in the case of ships which are not self-propelled; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>B</number> the discharge is made below the waterline through the underwater discharge outlet not exceeding the maximum rate for which the underwater discharge outlet is designed; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>C</number> the discharge is made at a distance of not less than twelve nautical miles from the nearest land in a depth of water of not leas than twenty-five metres; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> for ships constructed befoer 1st January, 2007, the discharge into the sea of residues of substances in Category Z of those provisionally assessed as such or ballast water, tank washings or other mixtures containing such substances below the waterline is not mandatory; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the Central Government may waive the requirements of item (C) of sub-clause (i) of clause (b) above, for substances in Category Z, regarding the distance of not less than twelve nautical miles from the nearest land for ships solely engaged in voyages within waters subject to sovereignty or jurisdiction of the State the flag, of which, the ship is entitled to fly and the Central Government may also waive the same requirements regarding the discharge distance of not less than twelve nautical miles from the nearest land for a particular ship entitled to fly the flag of their State, when engaged in voyages within waters subject to the sovereignty or jurisdiction of one adjacent State after the establishment of an agreement, in writing, of a waiver between the two coastal States involved provided that no third party will be affected: 
</subsection>
</section>
 Provided that information on such agreement shall be communicated to the Organization within thirty days for further circulation to the State Parties for their information and appropriate action if any. 
 
 <section><number>c</number> Ventilation of cargo residues 
 
 Ventilation procedures approved by the Central Government may be used to remove cargo residues from a tank and such procedures shall be in accordance with Schedule V: 
 Provided that any water subsequently introduced into the tank shall be regarded as clean and shall not be subject to the discharge requirements of these rules. 

 </section><section><number>d</number> Exemption for a pre-wash 
 
 On request of the ship's master, an exemption for a pre-wash may be granted by the Central Government, where it is satisfied that 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the unloaded tank is to be reloaded with the same substance or another substance compatible with the previous one and that the tank will not be washed or ballasted prior to loading; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the unloaded tank is neither washed nor ballasted at sea and the pre-wash, in accordance with the applicable rule shall be carried out at another port provided that it has been confirmed in writing that a reception facility at that port is available and is adequate for such a purpose; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the cargo residues shall be removed by a ventilation procedure approved by the Central Government in accordance with  
    Schedule V; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>e</number> the use of cleaning agents or additives 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> when a washing medium other than water, such as mineral oil or chlorinated solvent, is used instead of water to wash a tank, its discharge shall be governed by the provisions of the Merchant Shipping (Prevention of Pollution by Oil from Ships) rules, 2009 or, as the case may be, these rules, which would apply to the medium had it been carried as cargo: 
 Provided that tank washing procedures involving the use of such a medium shall be set out in the Manual approved by the Central Government; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> when small amounts of cleaning additives (detergent products) are added to water in order to facilitate tank washing, no additives containing Pollution Category X components shall be used except those components that arc readily biodegradable and present in a total concentration of less than ten per cent of the cleaning additive: 
 Provided that no restrictions, in addition to those applicable to the tank due to the previous cargo, shall apply; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>f</number> discharge of residues of Category X 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> subject to the provisions of clause (a), the following provisions shall apply, namely: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>A</number> a tank from Which a substance in Category X has been unloaded, shall be pre-washed before the ship leaves the port of unloading and the resulting residues shall be discharged to a reception facility until the concentration of the substance in the effluent to such facility, as indicated by analyses of samples of the effluent taken by the surveyor, is at or below 0.1% by weight and when the required concentration level has been achieved, remaining tank washings shall continue to be discharged to the reception facility until the tank is empty: 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 Provided that appropriate entries of these operations shall be made in the Cargo Record Book and endorsed by the surveyor or the authorised person referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 16; 
 
 <subsection><number>B</number> any water subsequently introduced into the tank may be discharged into the sea in accordance with the discharge standards in clause (b) above; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>C</number> where the Central Government is satisfied that it is impracticable to measure the concentration of the substance in the effluent without causing undue delay to the ship, then it may accept an alternative procedure as being equivalent to obtain the required concentration in item (A) of sub-clause (i) of clause (f) provided that­ 
 
 <subsubsection><number>I</number> the tank is pre-washed in accordance with a procedure approved by the Central Government in compliance with Schedule IV; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> appropriate entries shall be made in the Cargo Record Book and endorsed by the surveyor or the authorised person referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 16; 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>g</number> discharge of residues of Category Y and Z 
 subject to the provision of clause (a), the following provisions shall apply 
 
 <subsection><number>A</number> with respect to the residue discharge procedures for substances in Category Y or Z, the discharge standards in clause (b) shall apply; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>B</number> if the unloading of a substance of Category Y or Z is not carried out in accordance with the Manual, a pre-wash shall be carried out before the ship leaves the port of unloading, unless alternative measures are taken to the satisfaction of the surveyor or the authorised person referred to in sub-rule (1) of rule 16 to remove the cargo residues from the ship to quantities specified in this rule and the resulting tank washings of the pre-wash shall be discharged to a reception facility at the port of unloading or another port with a suitable reception facility: 
</subsection>
 Provided that it has been confirmed in writing that a reception facility at that port is available and is adequate for such a purpose; 
 
 <subsection><number>C</number> for high-viscosity or solidifying substances in Category Y, the following shall apply, namely: 
 
 <subsubsection><number>I</number> a pre-wash procedure as specified in Schedule IV shall be applied; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>II</number> the residue/water mixture generated during the pre-wash shall be discharged to a reception facility until the tank is empty; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>III</number> any water subsequently introduced into the tank may be discharged into the sea in accordance with the discharge standards in clause (b); 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>h</number> operational requirements for ballasting and de-ballasting 
 
 
 Provided that the ship is not less than twelve nautical miles from the nearest land and in water that is not less than twenty-five metres deep and the required degree of cleanliness has been achieved when a pre-wash as specified in Schedule IV has been carried out and the tank has been subsequently washed with a complete cycle of the cleaning machine for ships built before 1st July, 1994 or with a water quantity not less than that calculated with k=1 .0; 
 
 <subsection><number>iii</number> the discharge into the sea of clean or segregated ballast shall not be subject to the requirements of these rules; 
 
 
</subsection><subsection><number>i</number> discharges in the Antarctic Area 
 
 <subsubsection><number>A</number> Antarctic Area means the sea area south of latitude 60°S; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>B</number> in the Antarctic Area any discharge into the sea of noxious liquid substances or mixtures containing such substances is prohibited. 
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
</section><section><number>i</number> after unloading, and, if required, after a pre-wash, a cargo tank may be ballasted and procedures for the discharge of such ballast shall be as provided in clause (b); 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> ballast introduced into a cargo tank which has been washed to such an extent that the ballast contains less than 1 pm of the substance previously carried, may be discharged into the sea without regard to the discharge rate, ship's speed and discharge outlet location: 
</subsection></section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Procedures and Arrangements Manual. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every ship certified to carry substances of Category X, Y or Z shall have on board a Manual approved by the Central Government and such Manual shall have a standard format as in Schedule II. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The main purpose of the Manual is to identify for the ship's officers the physical arrangements and all the operational procedures with respect to cargo handling, tank cleaning, slops handling and cargo tank ballasting and de-ballasting which must be followed in order to comply with the requirements of these rules. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Cargo record book. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every ship to which these rules apply shall be provided with a Cargo Record Book, whether as part of the ship's official logbook or otherwise, in Form III. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> After completion of any operation specified in the Form III, the operation shall be promptly recorded in the Cargo Record Book. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the event of an accidental discharge of a noxious liquid substance or a mixture containing such a substance or a discharge under the provisions of rule 3, an entry shall be made in the Cargo Record Book stating the circumstances of, and the reason for, such discharge. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Each entry shall be signed by the officer or officers in charge of the operation concerned and each page shall be signed by the master of the ship and the entries in the Cargo Record Book for ships holding an International Certificate or an Indian Certificate referred to in rule 9 or a certificate referred to in rule 7 shall be in English at least: 
 Provided that where entries in an official national language of the State whose flag the ship is entitled to fly is also used, this shall prevail in the case of a dispute or discrepancy. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Cargo Record Book shall be kept in such a place as to be readily available for inspection and, except in the case of unmanned ships under tow, shall be kept on board the ship and it shall be retained for a period of three years after the last entry has been made. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The authority authorised by the Central Government may inspect the Cargo Record Book on board any ship to which these rules apply while the ship is in its port, and may make a copy of any entry in that book and may require the master of the ship to certify that the copy is a true copy of such entry and such copy shall be made admissible in any judicial proceedings as evidence of the facts stated therein: 
 Provided that the inspection of a Cargo Record Book and the taking of a certified copy by the said authority shall be performed as expeditiously as possible without causing the ship to be unduly delayed. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Measures of control. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall appoint surveyors or authorise any person for the purpose of implementing the provisions of these rules and such surveyor or, as the case may be, the authorise person shall execute control in accordance with control procedures developed by the Organization. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a surveyor appointed or the person authorised by the Central Government has verified that an operation has bee carried out in accordance with the requirements of the Manual, or has granted an exemption for a pre-wash, then, he shall make an appropriate entry in the Cargo Record Book. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The master of a ship certified to carry noxious liquid substances in bulk shall ensure that the provisions of rule 13 and of this rule have been complied with and that the Cargo Record Book is completed in accordance with rule 15 whenever operations as referred to in that rule take place. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A tank which has carried a Category X substance shall be pre-washed in accordance with clause (f) of rule 13 and appropriate entries of these operations, shall be made in the Cargo Record Book and endorsed by the Surveyor or the person referred to in sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where the Central Government is satisfied that it is impracticable to measure the concentration of the substance in the effluent without causing undue delay to the ship, it shall accept an alternative procedure referred to in sub-  
  clause i(C) of clause (f) of rule 13 provided that the surveyor or the authorised person referred to in sub-rule (1) certifies in the Cargo Record Book that 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the tank, its pump and piping systems have been emptied; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the pre-wash has been carried out in accordance with the provisions of Schedule IV; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the tank washing resulting from such pre-wash have been discharged to a reception facility and the tank is empty. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> At the request of the ship's master, the Central Government may exempt the ship from the requirements for a pre-wash referred to in the applicable provisions of rule 13, when one of the conditions of clause (d) of rule 13 is met. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> An exemption referred to in sub-rule (6) may only be granted by the Central Government to a ship engaged in voyages to ports or terminals under the jurisdiction of other State Parties and when such an exemption has been granted, the appropriate entry made in the Cargo Record Book shall be endorsed by the surveyor or the authorised person referred to in sub-rule (1). 
 </section><section><number>8</number> If the unloading is not carried out in accordance with the pumping conditions for the tank approved by the Central Governments and based on Schedule III, alternative measures may be taken to the satisfaction of the surveyor or the authorised person referred to in sub-rule (1) to remove the cargo residues from the ship to quantities specified in rule 12 as applicable and appropriate entries shall be made in the Cargo Record Book. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Control on operational requirements.(1) During inspection of a foreign ship in Indian port under section 356G, the surveyor, or as the case may be, any other person authorised thereunder, has clear grounds to believe that the master or crew of that ship are not familiar with operational requirements and procedures relating to the prevention of pollution by noxious liquid substances, the Director-General or any officer authorised by him, shall, on the recommendation of the surveyor or the authorised person, take such steps as provided in section 356H. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing in this rule shall be construed to limit the rights and obligations of the Central Government carrying out control over operational requirements specifically provided for in the Convention. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Shipboard marine pollution emergency plan for noxious liquid substances. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every ship of one hundred and fifty gross tonnage and above certified to carry noxious liquid substances in bulk shall carry on board a shipboard marine pollution emergency plan for noxious liquid substances approved by the Central Government. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The plan referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be based on the Guidelines developed by the Organization and written in a working language or languages understood by the master and officers and such plan shall consist at least of 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the procedure to be followed by the master or other persons having charge of the ship to report a Noxious Liquid Substances pollution incident, as required in Article 8 and Protocol 1 of the Convention, based on the Guidelines developed by the Organization; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the list of authorities or persons to be contacted in the event of a noxious liquid substances pollution incident; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a detailed description of the action to be taken immediately by persons on board to reduce or control the discharge of noxious liquid substances following the incident; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the procedures and point of contact on the ship for coordinating shipboard action with national and local authorities in combating the pollution. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the case of ships to which the provisions of the Merchant Shipping (Prevention of Pollution by Oil from Ships) Rules, 2009 also applies, such a plan may be combined with the shipboard oil pollution emergency plan required thereunder and in such case, the title of such a plan shall be Shipboard marine pollution emergency plan. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Reception facilities and cargo unloading terminal arrangements. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall ensure the provision of reception facilities according to the needs of ships using its ports, terminals or repair ports as follows, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> ports and terminals involved in ships' cargo handling shall have adequate facilities for the reception of residues and mixtures containing such residues of noxious liquid substances resulting from compliance with these rules, without undue delay for the ships involved; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> ship repair ports undertaking repairs to NLS tankers shall provide facilities adequate for the reception of residues and mixtures containing noxious liquid substances for ships calling at that port. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall determine the types of facilities provided for the purpose of sub-rule (1) at each cargo loading and unloading port, terminal and ship repair port in its territories and notify the Organization thereof. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government, collectively with the State Party or Parties, the coastlines of which border on any given special area, shall agree and establish a date, by which time, the requirement of sub-rule (1) shall be fulfilled and from which date the requirements of rule 13 in respect of such special area shall take effect, and notify the Organization of the date so established, at least six months in advance of that date, for enabling the Organization to promptly notify all State Parties of that date. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government shall undertake to ensure that cargo unloading terminals shall provide arrangements to facilitate stripping of cargo tanks of ships unloading noxious liquid substances at these terminals: 
 Provided that cargo hoses and piping systems of the terminal, containing noxious liquid substances received from ships unloading these substances at the terminal, shall not be drained back to the ship. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Central Government shall notify the Organization, for transmission to the State Parties concerned, of any case where facilities required under sub-rule (1) or arrangements required under sub-rule (3) are alleged to be inadequate. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Fees. </title>The fees to be levied for the purposes of conducting survey under the provisions of the Act and the rules made thereunder shall be such as is specified in the Schedule VI. 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> Penalty . </title>Whoever contravenes any of the provisions of these rules shall be punished with fine in accordance with the provisions clause (b) of sub-rule 2 of section 458 of the Act. 


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 7-1-2010.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>