<act><title>

THE ADVOCATES' 
    WELFARE FUND ACT, 2001</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 2001.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification, appoint; and different dates 
    may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and for different 
    States, and any reference in any such provision to the commencement of this 
    Act shall be construed in relation to any State as a reference to the coming 
    into force of that provision in that State.

 
 


  


</section></article><article>

<number>1</number> Came 
      into force w.e.f. 1-11-2001 in the whole of India except the states in 
      which the enactments specified in Schedule II of the Act are applicable,
      Vide S.O. 946 (E), dated 26th September, 2001.
</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section><number>a</number>    
      “advocate” means an advocate whose name has been entered in the State roll 
      prepared and maintained by a State Bar Council under section 17 of the 
      Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961) and who is a member of a State Bar 
      Association or State Advocates’ Association;
 </section><section><number>b</number>    
      “appropriate Government” means,—
 
 <subsection><number>i</number>    
        in the case of advocates admitted on the roll of a Bar Council of a 
        State, the State Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>    in the case of advocates admitted on the roll of a Bar Council 
        of a Union territory, the Central Government;
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>c</number>    
      “cessation of practice” means removal of the name of an advocate from the 
      State roll under section 26A of the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961);
 </section><section><number>d</number>    
      “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Trustee Committee referred to 
      in clause (a) of sub-section (3) of section 4;
 </section><section><number>e</number>    
      “chartered accountant” means a chartered accountant as defined in clause 
      (b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 
      (38 of 1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under 
      sub-section (1) of section 6 of that Act;
 </section><section><number>f</number>    
      “dependants” means the spouse, parents or minor children of a member of 
      the Fund;
 </section><section><number>g</number>    
      “Fund” means the Advocates’ Welfare Fund constituted under sub-section (1) 
      of section 3;
 </section><section><number>h</number>    
      “insurer” shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (9) of section 2 
      of the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938);
 </section><section><number>i</number>    
      “member of the Fund” means an advocate admitted to the benefits of the 
      Fund and who continues to be a member thereof under the provisions of this 
      Act;
 </section><section><number>j</number>    
      “notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette of 
      the appropriate Government and the expression “notified” shall be 
      construed accordingly;
 </section><section><number>k</number>    
      “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section><number>l</number>    
      “Schedule” means a Schedule to this Act;
 </section><section><number>m</number>    
      “scheduled bank” shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (e) of 
      section 2 of the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);
 </section><section><number>n</number>    
      “stamp” means the Advocates’ Welfare Fund Stamp printed and distributed 
      under section 26;
 </section><section><number>o</number>    
      “State” means a State specified in the First Schedule to the Constitution 
      and shall include a Union territory;
 </section><section><number>p</number>    
      “State Advocates’ Association” means an association of advocates in a 
      State recognised by the Bar Council of that State under section 16;
 </section><section><number>q</number>    
      “State Bar Association” means an association of advocates recognised by 
      the Bar Council of that State under section 16;
 </section><section><number>r</number>    
      “State Bar Council” means a Bar Council referred to in section 3 of the 
      Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961);
 </section><section><number>s</number>    
      “suspension of practice” means voluntary suspension of practice as an 
      advocate or suspension of an advocate by a State Bar Council for 
      misconduct;
 </section><section><number>t</number>    
      “Trustee Committee” means the Advocates’ Welfare Fund Trustee Committee 
      established under sub-section (1) of section 4;
 </section><section><number>u</number>    
      “Vakalatnama” includes memorandum of appearance or any other document by 
      which an advocate is empowered to appear or plead before any court, 
      tribunal or other authority;
 </section><section><number>v</number>    
      words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the 
      Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961), shall have the meanings respectively 
      assigned to them in that Act.
</section>
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Advocates’ Welfare Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    appropriate Government shall constitute a fund to be called the “Advocates’ 
    Welfare Fund”.
 
 

 
 
Advocates’ Welfare Fund is to 
      be constituted by State Governments for the advocates admitted on the 
      rolls of the Bar Councils of the respective States and by the Central 
      Government for the advocates admitted on the rolls of the Bar Councils of 
      the Union territories.


  


</section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall be credited to the Fund—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    
        all amounts paid by a State Bar Council under section 15;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    
        any other contribution made by a State Bar Council;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    
        any voluntary donation or contribution made to the Fund by the Bar 
        Council of India, any State Bar Association, any State Advocates’ 
        Association or other association or institution, or any advocate or 
        other person;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>    
        any grant which may be made by the Central Government or a State 
        Government to the Fund after due appropriation made in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>    
        any sums borrowed under section 12;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>    
        all sums collected under section 18;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>    
        all sums received from the Life Insurance Corporation of India or any 
        other insurer on the death of any member of the Fund under any Group 
        Insurance Policy;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>    
        any profit or dividend or refund received from the Life Insurance 
        Corporation of India or any other insurer in respect of policies of 
        Group Insurance of the members of the Fund;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>    
        any interest or dividend or other return on any investment made out of 
        any part of the Fund;
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>    
        all sums collected by way of sale of stamps under section 26.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The sums specified in sub-section (2) 
      shall be paid to, or collected by, such agencies, at such intervals and in 
      such manner, as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Establishment of Trustee Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    With effect from such date as the appropriate Government may, by 
    notification, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established a Trustee 
    Committee to be called the “Advocates’ Welfare Fund Trustee Committee”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Trustee Committee shall be a body 
    corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal with power to 
    acquire, hold and dispose of property and shall, by the said name, sue and 
    be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Trustee Committee shall consist of—
 

 
 
 (a) the 
          Advocate-General of a State 
          Provided that where there is no Advocate-General of a State, the 
          appropriate Government shall nominate a senior advocate to be a 
          chairperson.
  -   
          Chairperson, ex officio

 
  
  

 
 (b)  
          the Secretary to the appropriate Government in its Law Department or 
          ministry
  -  
          Member, ex officio

 
  
  

 
 (c)  
          the Secretary to the appropriate Government in its Home Department or 
          Ministry
  - 
          Member, ex officio

 
  
  

 
 (d)  
          the Chairman of the State Bar Council
  - 
          Member, ex officio

 
  
  

 
 (e)  
          the Government Pleader or the Public Prosecutor, as may be nominated 
          by the appropriate Government
  - 
          Member

 
  
  

 
 (f)  
          two advocates to be nominated by the State Bar Council
  - 
          Member

 
  
  

 
 (g) the 
          Secretary of the State Bar Council
  - 
          Secretary, ex officio

 
  
  




 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairperson nominated under the 
    proviso to clause (a) of sub-section (3) shall hold office for a period not 
    exceeding three years from the date on which he enters upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every Member of the Trustee Committee 
    nominated under clause (e) or clause (f) of sub-section (3) shall hold 
    office for a period not exceeding three years from the date on which he 
    enters upon his office.

 
 
Advocates’ Welfare Fund 
      Trustee Committee is to be established which shall be a body corporate 
      having perpetual succession and a common seal and with power to acquire, 
      hold and dispose of property and shall, by the said name, sue and be sued. 
      The Committee shall consist of a Chairperson, five members and a 
      Secretary.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Disqualifications and removal of Chairperson or Member of Trustee Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The appropriate Government shall remove from office the Chairperson or any 
    Member of the Trustee Committee, who—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number>    is, or at any 
      time has been, adjudged as an insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    has become 
      physically or mentally incapable of acting as the Chairperson or a Member 
      of the Trustee Committee; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>    has been 
      convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the appropriate 
      Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>    has acquired such 
      financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his 
      functions as the Chairperson or a Member of the Trustee Committee; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>    has so abused his 
      position as to render his continuation in office detrimental to the public 
      interest; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>    is, or at any 
      time has been, absent without leave of the Trustee Committee for more than 
      three consecutive meetings of the Trustee Committee:
 
Provided that the Trustee Committee may, on 
      sufficient ground, condone the absence of such Chairperson or Member.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such Chairperson or Member of the 
    Trustee Committee shall be removed under clause (d) or clause (e) of 
    sub-section (1) unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
    heard.

 
 
The appropriate Government has 
      been empowered to remove the Chairperson or any Member of the Trustee 
      Committee who (i) is, or at any time has been, adjudged as an insolvent, 
      or (ii) has become physically or mentally incapable; or (iii) has been 
      convicted of an offence which involves moral turpitude; or (iv) has 
      acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
      prejudicially his functions; (v) has so abused his position as to render 
      his continuation in office detrimental to the public interest; or (vi) is, 
      or at any time has been absent without leave of the Trustee Committee for 
      more than three consecutive meetings of the Trustee Committee.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Resignation by nominated Chairperson and Members of Trustee Committee and 
    filling up of casual vacancy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson referred to in sub-section (4) of section 4 or a Member 
    nominated under clause (e) of sub-section (3) of that section may resign his 
    office by giving three months’ notice in writing to the appropriate 
    Government and on such resignation being accepted by the appropriate 
    Government such Chairperson or Member shall vacate his office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member 
    nominated under clause (f) of sub-section (3) of section 4 may resign his 
    office by giving three months’ notice in writing to the State Bar Council 
    and on such resignation being accepted by the State Bar Council such Member 
    shall vacate his office.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A casual 
    vacancy in the office of the Chairperson or a Member referred to in 
    sub-section (1) who has resigned may be filled up, as soon as may be, by the 
    appropriate Government and the Chairperson or a Member so nominated shall 
    hold office only so long as the Chairperson or the Member in whose place he 
    is nominated would have been entitled to hold office if the vacancy did not 
    occur.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A casual 
    vacancy in the office of a Member referred to in sub-section (2) who has 
    resigned may be filled up, as soon as may be, by the State Bar Council and a 
    Member so nominated shall hold office only so long as the Member in whose 
    place he is nominated would have been entitled to hold office if the vacancy 
    did not occur.
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Trustee Committee.—No 
    act or proceeding of the Trustee Committee shall be invalid merely by reason 
    of—
 
 <section><number>a</number>    
      any vacancy in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Trustee 
      Committee; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number>    
      any defect or irregularity in the nomination of a person acting as the 
      Chairperson or a Member of the Trustee Committee; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>    
      any irregularity in the procedure of the Trustee Committee not affecting 
      the merits of the case.
</section>

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Meetings 
    of Trustee Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Trustee Committee shall meet at least once in every three calendar months 
    and at least four such meetings shall be held in every year to transact 
    business under this Act and the rules made thereunder.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Three 
    Members of the Trustee Committee shall form the quorum for a meeting of the 
    Trustee Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairperson of the Trustee Committee or, if for any reason, he is unable to 
    attend a meeting of the Trustee Committee, any other Member chosen by the 
    Members of the Trustee Committee present from amongst themselves at the 
    meeting shall preside at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    questions which come up in a meeting of the Trustee Committee shall be 
    decided by a majority vote of the Members of the Trustee Committee present 
    and voting, and, in the event of an equality of votes, the Chairperson, or 
    in his absence, the Member of the Trustee Committee presiding, shall have a 
    second or casting vote.
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Travelling and daily allowances to nominated Chairperson and Members of 
    Trustee Committee.—The Chairperson 
    referred to in sub-section (4) of section 4 and Members of the Trustee 
    Committee referred to in clauses (e) and (f) of sub-section (3) of that 
    section shall be entitled to be paid such travelling and daily allowances as 
    are admissible to the members of the State Bar Council.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Vesting 
    and application of Fund.—The Fund 
    shall vest in, and be held and applied by, the Trustee Committee subject to 
    the provisions, and for the purposes, of this Act.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Functions of Trustee Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act and any other law for the time being 
    in force, the Trustee Committee shall administer the Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in sub-section (1), 
    the Trustee Committee shall—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    hold the amounts and assets belonging 
      to the Fund in trust;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    receive applications for admission or 
      re-admission as members to the Fund, and dispose of such applications 
      within ninety days from the date of receipt thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    receive applications from the members 
      of the Fund, their nominees or legal heirs, as the case may be, for 
      payment out of the Fund, conduct such enquiry as it deems necessary and 
      dispose of the applications within five months from the date of receipt 
      thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    record in the minutes book of the 
      Trustee Committee, its decisions on the applications;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    pay to the members of the Fund or 
      their nominees or legal heirs, as the case may be, the amounts at the 
      rates specified in Schedule I;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    send such periodical and annual 
      reports as may be prescribed, to the appropriate Government and the State 
      Bar Council;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    communicate to the applicants, by 
      registered post with acknowledgment due or through electronic mode, the 
      decisions of the Trustee Committee in respect of applications for 
      admission or re-admission as members to the Fund or claims to the benefit 
      of the Fund;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    do such other acts as are, or may be, 
      required to be done under this Act and the rules made thereunder.
</subsection>

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Borrowing and investment.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Trustee Committee may, with the prior approval of the appropriate Government 
    and the State Bar Council, borrow, from time to time, any sum required for 
    carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Trustee 
    Committee shall deposit all monies and receipts forming part of the Fund in 
    any scheduled bank or invest the same in debt instruments of any corporation 
    owned or controlled by the appropriate Government or in loans floated by the 
    appropriate Government or in any other manner as the State Bar Council may, 
    from time to time, direct with the prior approval of the appropriate 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All amounts 
    due and payable under this Act and all expenditure relating to the 
    management and administration of the Fund shall be paid out of the Fund.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Accounts 
    and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The Trustee 
    Committee shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts and annual report in such form and 
    in such manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Trustee Committee shall be audited annually by a chartered 
    accountant appointed by the State Bar Council.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    accounts of the Trustee Committee as audited by the chartered accountant 
    together with his audit report shall be forwarded to the State Bar Council 
    by that Committee and the State Bar Council may issue such directions, as it 
    deems fit, to the Trustee Committee in respect thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Trustee 
    Committee shall comply with the directions issued by the State Bar Council 
    under sub-section (3).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Trustee 
    Committee shall pay from the Fund the charges for the audit as may be fixed 
    by the State Bar Council.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Powers 
    and duties of Secretary.—The 
    Secretary of the Trustee Committee shall—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    be the chief executive authority of 
      the Trustee Committee and responsible for carrying out its decisions;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    represent the Trustee Committee in 
      all suits and proceedings for and against the Trustee Committee;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    authenticate by his signature all 
      decisions and instruments of the Trustee Committee;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    operate bank account of the Trustee 
      Committee jointly with the Chairperson;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    convene meetings of the Trustee 
      Committee and prepare minutes of such meetings;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    attend meetings of the Trustee 
      Committee with all the necessary records and information;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    maintain such forms, registers and 
      other records as may be prescribed from time to time and do all 
      correspondence relating to the Trustee Committee;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    prepare an annual statement of 
      business transacted by the Trustee Committee during a financial year;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    do such other acts as are or may be 
      directed by the Trustee Committee and the State Bar Council.
</section>

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Payment 
    of certain monies to Fund by State Bar Council.—The 
    State Bar Council shall pay to the Fund annually an amount equal to twenty 
    per cent. of the enrolment fee received by it under clause (f) of section 24 
    of the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 1961).
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Recognition by a State Bar Council of any association of advocates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any association of advocates known by any name which is registered as an 
    association before the date of commencement of this Act may, before the date 
    to be notified by a State Bar Council in this behalf, apply for recognition 
    to the State Bar Council in such form as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any 
    association of advocates known by any name which is registered as an 
    association on or after the date of commencement of this Act may, within 
    three months from the date of its registration as an association, apply for 
    recognition to the State Bar Council in such form as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    application for recognition under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall 
    be accompanied by,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a copy of the rules or bye-laws of 
      the association;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    names and addresses of office bearers 
      of the association;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a list of members of the association 
      containing the name, address, age, enrolment number and date of enrolment 
      with the State Bar Council and the ordinary place of practice of each 
      member.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State 
    Bar Council may, after such enquiry as it deems necessary, recognise the 
    association and issue a certificate of recognition in such form as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    decision of the State Bar Council on any matter regarding recognition of an 
    association under sub-section (4) shall be final.
 
Explanation.—In 
    this section, “registered” means registered or deemed to be registered under 
    the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), or any other law for the 
    time being in force.
  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Duties 
    of State Bar Associations and State Advocates’ Associations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every State Bar Association and State Advocates’ Association shall, on or 
    before the 15th day of April of every year, furnish to the State Bar Council 
    a list of its members as on the 31st day of March of that year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every State 
    Bar Association and State Advocates’ Association shall inform the State Bar 
    Council of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any change in the membership 
      including admissions and re-admissions within thirty days of such change;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the death or other cessation of 
      practice or voluntary suspension of practice of any of its members within 
      thirty days from the date of occurrence thereof;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    such other matters as may be required 
      by the State Bar Council from time to time.
</subsection>

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Membership in Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    advocate practising, before the commencement of this Act, in any court, 
    tribunal or other authority in a State and being a member of a State Bar 
    Association or a State Advocates’ Association in that State, shall apply, 
    within six months of the commencement of this Act, to the Trustee Committee 
    for admission as a member of the Fund, in such form as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    person,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    admitted as an advocate on the roll 
      of a State Bar Council, after the commencement of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    practising in any court, tribunal or 
      other authority in a State and being a member of a State Bar Association 
      or a State Advocates’ Association in that State, 
</subsection>
 shall 
    apply, within six months of his enrolment as an advocate, to the Trustee 
    Committee, for admission as a member of the Fund in such form as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt 
    of an application under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), the Trustee 
    Committee shall make such enquiry as it deems fit and either admit the 
    applicant to the Fund or, for reasons to be recorded in writing, reject the 
    application:
 
Provided that no order rejecting an 
    application shall be passed unless the applicant has been given an 
    opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    applicant shall pay an application fee of two hundred rupees along with the 
    application to the account of the Trustee Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every 
    advocate, being a member of the Fund, shall pay an annual subscription of 
    fifty rupees to the Fund on or before the 31st day of March of every year:
 
Provided that every advocate, who makes an 
    application under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), shall pay his first 
    annual subscription within three months of his becoming a member of the 
    Fund:
 
Provided further that a senior advocate shall 
    pay an annual subscription of one thousand rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Any member 
    of the Fund, who fails to pay the annual subscription for any year before 
    the 31st day of March of that year, shall be liable to be removed from the 
    membership in the Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A member of 
    the Fund removed from the membership in the Fund under sub-section (6) may 
    be re-admitted to the Fund, on payment of arrears along with re-admission 
    fee of ten rupees, within six months from the date of such removal.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Every 
    member of the Fund shall, at the time of admission to the membership in the 
    Fund, make nomination conferring on one or more of his dependants the right 
    to receive, in the event of his death, any amount payable to the member 
    under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> If a member 
    of the Fund nominates more than one person under sub-section (8), he shall 
    specify in the nomination, the amount or share payable to each of the 
    nominees.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> A member 
    of the Fund may, at any time, cancel a nomination by sending a notice in 
    writing to the Trustee Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> Every 
    member of the Fund, who cancels his nomination under sub-section (10), shall 
    make a fresh nomination along with registration fee of five rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>12</number> Every 
    member of the Fund, whose name has been removed from the State roll under 
    section 26A of the Advocates Act, 1961, (25 of 1961), or who voluntarily 
    suspends practice, shall, within fifteen days of such removal or suspension, 
    intimate such removal or suspension to the Trustee Committee and if any 
    member of the Fund fails to do so without sufficient reason, the Trustee 
    Committee may reduce, in accordance with such principles as may be 
    prescribed, the amount payable to that member under this Act.

 
 
Every advocate practising in 
      any court, tribunal or other authority in a State and being a member of a 
      State Bar Association or a State Advocates’ Association in that State is 
      to apply to the Trustee Committee for admission as a member of the Fund. 
      Every applicant has to pay an application fee of two hundred rupees along 
      with the application. Every advocate being admitted as member of the Fund 
      is required to pay an annual subscription of fifty rupees to the Fund on 
      or before the 31st day of March of every year. Failure to pay the annual 
      subscription before 31st day of March of that year, shall make him liable 
      to be removed from the membership of the Fund.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Ex 
    gratia grant to a member of Fund.—The 
    Trustee Committee on an application made to it by a member of the Fund, and 
    after being satisfied about the genuineness of the claim, may allow ex 
    gratia grant to such member from the Fund—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in the case of his hospitalisation or 
      involving major surgical operation; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    if he is suffering from tuberculosis, 
      leprosy, paralysis, cancer, unsoundness of mind or from such other serious 
      disease or disability.
</section>

 
 
Every member of the Fund is 
      entitled to an ex gratia grant from the Fund 
<section><number>i</number> in the case of his 
      hospitalisation or involving major surgical operation; or (ii) if he is 
      suffering from tuberculosis, leprosy, paralysis, cancer, unsoundness of 
      mind or from such other serious disease or disability.
</section>

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Review.—The 
    Trustee Committee may, on its own motion or on an application received from 
    any person interested, within ninety days of the passing of any order by it 
    under the provisions of this Act, review such order, if it was passed under 
    any mistake, whether of fact or of law or in ignorance of any material fact:
 
Provided that 
    the Trustee Committee shall not pass any order under this section adversely 
    affecting any person unless such person has been given an opportunity of 
    being heard.
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>21</number> Payment of amount on 
      cessation of practice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Every advocate who has been a member of the Fund for a period of not less 
      than five years shall, on his cessation of practice, be paid an amount at 
      the rate specified in Schedule I:
 Provided that where the Trustee 
      Committee is satisfied that a member of the Fund ceases to practice within 
      a period of five years from the date of his admission as a member of such 
      Fund as a result of any permanent disability, the Trustee Committee may 
      pay such member an amount at the rate specified in Schedule 
      I.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a member of the Fund dies 
      before receiving the amount payable under sub-section (1), his nominee or 
      legal heir, as the case may be, shall be paid the amount payable to the 
      deceased member of the Fund.
  </section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Restriction on alienation, attachment, etc., of interest of member in Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The interest of any member in the Fund, or the right of a member of the Fund 
    or his nominee or legal heir to receive any amount from the Fund, shall not 
    be assigned, alienated, or charged and shall not be liable to attachment 
    under any decree or order of any court, tribunal or other authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No creditor 
    shall be entitled to proceed against the Fund or the interest therein of any 
    member of the Fund or his nominee or legal heir.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “creditor” includes the State or an official 
    assignee or official receiver appointed under the law relating to insolvency 
    for the time being in force.

 
 
The interest of any member in 
      the Fund, or the right of a member of the Fund or his nominee or legal 
      heir to receive any amount from the Fund cannot be assigned, alienated, or 
      charged and cannot be attached under any decree or order of any court, 
      tribunal or other authority. No creditor can proceed against the Fund or 
      the interest therein of any member of the Fund or his nominee or legal 
      heir.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Exemption from income-tax.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), or any other 
    enactment for the time being in force relating to tax on income, profits or 
    gains, the income accrued to the Fund constituted under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
    section 3 shall be exempt from income-tax.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Group 
    Life Insurance for members of Fund and other benefits.—The 
    Trustee Committee may, for the welfare of the members of the Fund,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    obtain, from the Life Insurance 
      Corporation of India or any other insurer, policies of Group Insurance on 
      the life of the members of the Fund; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    provide, in such manner as may be 
      prescribed, for medical and educational facilities for the members of the 
      Fund and their dependants; or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    provide monies to the members of the 
      Fund for purchase of books; or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    provide monies to construct or 
      maintain common facilities for the members of the Fund:
 
Provided that the Trustee Committee shall 
      spend ten per cent. of the total annual subscription received under 
      sub-section (5) of section 18 on the construction or maintenance of common 
      facilities for the members of the Fund practising in the subordinate 
      courts; or "
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    provide funds for any other purpose 
      which the Trustee Committee may specify; or 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    provide for such other benefits as 
      may be prescribed.
</section>

 
 
The Trustee Committee may for 
      the welfare of the members of the Fund, 
<section><number>i</number> obtain policies of Group 
      Insurance on the life of the members of the Fund; or (ii) provide for 
      medical and educational facilities for the members of the Fund and their 
      dependants; or (iii) provide monies for the purchase of books; or (iv) 
      provide monies to construct or maintain common facilities for the members, 
      or (v) provide funds for any other specified purpose; or (vi) provide for 
      other specified benefits.
</section>

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Appeal 
    against decision or order of Trustee Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An appeal against any decision or order of the Trustee Committee shall lie 
    to the State Bar Council.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The appeal 
    shall be in the prescribed form and shall be accompanied by—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a copy of the decision or order 
      appealed against;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a receipt evidencing payment of 
      twenty-five rupees to the credit of the State Bar Council in any of the 
      branches of a scheduled bank.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The appeal 
    shall be filed within thirty days from the date of receipt of the decision 
    or order appealed against.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    decision of the State Bar Council on such appeal shall be final.

 
 
Appeal against any decision or 
      order of the Trustee Committee is to be filed before the State Bar Council 
      within thirty days from the receipt of the decision or order appealed 
      against. The decision of the State Bar Council on such appeal shall be 
      final.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Printing 
    and distribution of Advocates’ Welfare Fund Stamps by State Bar Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The appropriate Government shall, on a request made by the State Bar Council 
    in this behalf, cause to be printed and distributed Advocates’ Welfare Fund 
    Stamps of the value of five rupees or such other value, which may be 
    prescribed, inscribing therein “Advocates’ Welfare Fund Stamp”, in such 
    design as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every stamp 
    referred to in sub-section (1) shall be of the size 2.54 c.m. by 5.08 c.m. 
    and sold to the advocates.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The custody 
    of the stamps shall be with the State Bar Council. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State 
    Bar Council shall control the distribution and sale of the stamps through 
    the State Bar Associations and the State Advocates’ Associations.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The State 
    Bar Council, the State Bar Associations and the State Advocates’ 
    Associations shall keep proper accounts of the stamps in such form and 
    manner as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The State 
    Bar Associations and State Advocates’ Associations shall purchase the stamps 
    from the State Bar Council after paying the value thereof as reduced by ten 
    per cent. of such value towards incidental expenses.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Vakalatnama to bear stamps.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every advocate shall affix stamp of a value of—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    five rupees on every Vakalatnama 
      filed by him in a District Court or a court subordinate to the District 
      Court; ;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    ten rupees on every Vakalatnama filed 
      by him in a tribunal or other authority or a High Court or the Supreme 
      Court:
 
Provided that 
      the appropriate Government may prescribe the value of the stamps not 
      exceeding twenty-five rupees to be affixed under this sub-section:
</subsection>
 
Provided 
    further that the appropriate Government may prescribe different value of the 
    stamps to be affixed on every Vakalatnama to be filed in a District Court, 
    or a court subordinate to the District Court or a tribunal or other 
    authority or a High Court or the Supreme Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The value 
    of the stamp shall neither be the cost in a case nor be collected in any 
    event from the client. ." 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    contravention of the provisions of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) by any 
    advocate shall disentitle him either in whole or in part to the benefits of 
    the Fund and the Trustee Committee shall report such contravention to the 
    State Bar Council for appropriate action.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every stamp 
    affixed on every Vakalatnama filed before a District Court or a court 
    subordinate to the District Court or a tribunal or other authority or a High 
    Court or the Supreme Court shall be cancelled in such manner as may be 
    prescribed.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Certain 
    persons not to be eligible for benefits.—No 
    senior advocate or a person, in receipt of pension from the Central 
    Government or a State Government, shall be entitled to ex gratia 
    grant under section 19 or payment of amount on his cessation of practice 
    under section 21 or any benefit under clause 
<section><number>a</number> or clause (b) or clause (c) 
    of section 24.

 
 
Senior advocates or persons, 
      in receipt of pension from the Central Government or a State Government 
      are not entitled to ex-gratia grant, or payment of amount on their 
      cessation of practice or any benefit.


  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>29</number> Protection of action taken 
      in good faith.—No suit, 
      prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the appropriate 
      Government or the Trustee Committee or the Chairperson or a Member or the 
      Secretary of the Trustee Committee or the State Bar Council or any person 
      for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
      Act or the rules made thereunder.
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Bar of 
    jurisdiction of civil courts.—No 
    civil court shall have jurisdiction to settle, decide or deal with any 
    question or to determine any matter which is by or under this Act required 
    to be settled, decided or dealt with or to be determined by the Trustee 
    Committee or the State Bar Council.
  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Power to 
    summon witnesses and take evidence.—The 
    Trustee Committee and the State Bar Council shall, for the purpose of any 
    enquiry under this Act, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court 
    while trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), in 
    respect of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    enforcing the attendance of any 
      person or examining him on oath;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    requiring the discovery and 
      production of documents;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    receiving evidence on affidavit;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    issuing commissions for the 
      examination of witnesses;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    any other matter which may be 
      prescribed.
</section>

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Power to 
    amend Schedules I and II.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    appropriate Government may, on the recommendation of the Trustee Committee, 
    by notification, and having due regard to the availability of the amount in 
    the Fund, amend the rates specified in Schedule I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Government may, as and when considered necessary, by notification, amend 
    Schedule II.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Power of 
    appropriate Government to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing provisions of this Act, 
    the Trustee Committee shall, in exercise of the powers or the performance of 
    its functions under this Act, be bound by such directions on questions of 
    policy, other than those relating to professional and administrative 
    matters, as the appropriate Government may give in writing to it from time 
    to time:
 
Provided that 
    the Trustee Committee shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity 
    to express its views before any direction is given under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    decision of the appropriate Government, whether a question is one of policy 
    or not, shall be final.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Power of 
    appropriate Government to supersede Trustee Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any time the appropriate Government is of the opinion—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that, on account of circumstances 
      beyond the control of the Trustee Committee, it is unable to discharge the 
      functions or perform the duties imposed on it by or under the provisions 
      of this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the Trustee Committee has 
      persistently defaulted in complying with any direction given by the 
      appropriate Government under this Act or in the discharge of the functions 
      or performance of the duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of 
      this Act; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that circumstances exist which render 
      it necessary in the public interest so to do,
</subsection>
 
the appropriate Government may, by 
    notification and for reasons to be specified therein, supersede the Trustee 
    Committee for such period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified in 
    the notification and appoint, in consultation with the Chief Justice of the 
    High Court having jurisdiction, a Judge of the High Court to be the 
    Controller of the Trustee Committee:
 
Provided that 
    before issuing any such notification, the appropriate Government shall give 
    a reasonable opportunity to the Trustee Committee to make representations 
    against the proposed supersession and shall consider the representations, if 
    any, of the Trustee Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon the 
    publication of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the Trustee 
    Committee,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Chairperson, Members and the 
      Secretary of the Trustee Committee shall, as from the date of supersession, 
      vacate their offices as such;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all powers, functions and duties 
      which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, be exercised or 
      discharged by or on behalf of the Trustee Committee shall, until the 
      Trustee Committee is reconstituted under sub-section (3), be exercised and 
      discharged by the Controller of the Trustee Committee; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    all properties and Fund owned or 
      controlled by the Trustee Committee shall, until the Trustee Committee is 
      reconstituted under sub-section (3), vest in the appropriate Government.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On or 
    before the expiration of the period of supersession specified in the 
    notification issued under sub-section (1), the appropriate Government shall 
    reconstitute the Trustee Committee by a fresh appointment of its 
    Chairperson, Members and Secretary of such Committee and in such case a 
    person who had vacated his office under clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall 
    not be deemed to be disqualified for reappointment.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    appropriate Government shall cause a copy of the notification issued under 
    sub-section (1) and a full report of any action taken under this section and 
    the circumstances leading to such action to be laid before each House of 
    Parliament or before each House of the State Legislature, where it consists 
    of two Houses or where such Legislature consists of one House, before that 
    House, as the case may be, at the earliest.
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Power of 
    Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government, being the appropriate Government, may, by 
    notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the periodical and annual reports to 
      be sent under clause (f) of section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the form and the manner in which the 
      annual statement of accounts and annual report shall be prepared under 
      sub-section (1) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the forms, registers and other 
      records to be maintained under clause (g) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the form in which an association of 
      advocates may apply for recognition to the State Bar Council under 
      sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the form in which a certificate of 
      recognition shall be issued by the State Bar Council under sub-section (4) 
      of section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the form in which an advocate shall 
      apply for admission as a member of the Fund under sub-section (1) or 
      sub-section (2) of section 18;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the principles in accordance with 
      which the amount payable to a member of the Fund be reduced under 
      sub-section (12) of section 18;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the manner of providing medical and 
      educational facilities for the members of the Fund and their dependants 
      under clause (b) of section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the other benefits to be provided 
      under clause (f) of section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the form of appeal under sub-section 
      (2) of section 25;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the value and design of stamps to be 
      printed and distributed under sub-section (1) of section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the form and the manner in which 
      accounts of the stamps shall be kept under sub-section (5) of section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the value of stamps not exceeding 
      twenty-five rupees as may be prescribed under the first proviso to 
      sub-section (1) of section 27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the value of stamps to be affixed on 
      every Vakalatnama under the second proviso to sub-section (1) of section 
      27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the manner of cancellation of stamps 
      under sub-section (4) of section 27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    any other matter which is to be, or 
      may be, prescribed.
</subsection>

  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Power of 
    State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government, being the appropriate Government, may, by 
    notification, make rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act and not 
    inconsistent with the rules, if any, made by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the periodical and annual reports to 
      be sent under clause (f) of section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the form and the manner in which the 
      annual statement of accounts and annual report shall be prepared under 
      sub-section (l) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the forms, registers and other 
      records to be maintained under clause (g) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the form in which an association of 
      advocates may apply for recognition to the State Bar Council under 
      sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) of section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the form in which a certificate of 
      recognition shall be issued by the State Bar Council under sub-section (4) 
      of section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    the form in which an advocate shall 
      apply for admission as a member of the Fund under sub-section (1) or 
      sub-section (2) of section 18;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    the principles in accordance with 
      which the amount payable to a member of the Fund be reduced under 
      sub-section (12) of section 18;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    the manner of providing medical and 
      educational facilities for the members of the Fund and their dependants 
      under clause (b) of section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    the other benefits to be provided 
      under clause (f) of section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    the form of appeal under sub-section 
      (2) of section 25;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    the value and design of stamps to be 
      printed and distributed under sub-section (1) of section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    the form and the manner in which 
      accounts of the stamps shall be kept under sub-section (5) of section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    the value of stamps not exceeding 
      twenty-five rupees as may be prescribed under the first proviso to 
      sub-section (1) of section 27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    the value of stamps to be affixed on 
      every Vakalatnama under the second proviso to sub-section (1) of section 
      27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    the manner of cancellation of stamps 
      under sub-section (4) of section 27;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    any other matter which is to be or 
      may be prescribed.
</subsection>

  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Rules 
    and notifications to be laid before Parliament or State Legislature.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government and every 
    notification issued under section 32, shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
    it is made or issued, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
    notification or both Houses agree that the rule or notification should not 
    be made or issued, the rule or notification shall thereafter have effect 
    only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, 
    however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
    to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every rule 
    made under this Act by a State Government and every notification issued 
    under section 32 shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
    each House of State Legislature where it consists of two Houses, or where 
    such Legislature consists of one House, before that House.
  
  


  
</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Saving.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall not apply to the States in which the enactments 
    specified in Schedule II are applicable.
  


  
</article><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

THE 
      ADVOCATES' 
      WELFARE FUNDS ACT, 2001
 

 
 

SCHEDULE 1 
[ See Section 21(1) and 
      32(1)]
 
 
 
 
 

 
  
 Number of 
            years as member of the Fund
  
 Rate at 
            which amount payable
  
 
 
 

 
  
 
 

(1)
  
 
 

(2)
  
 
 
 

 
  
 30
 ----
 Rs. 
            30,000
  
 
  
 29
 ----
 Rs. 
            29,000
  
 
  
 28
 ----
 Rs. 
            28,000
  
 
  
 27
 ----
 Rs. 
            27,000
  
 
  
 26
 ----
 Rs. 
            26,000
  
 
  
 25
 ----
 Rs. 
            25,000
  
 
  
 24
 ----
 Rs. 
            24,000
  
 
  
 23
 ----
 Rs. 
            23,000
  
 
  
 22
 ----
 Rs. 
            22,000
  
 
  
 21
 ----
 Rs. 
            21,000
  
 
  
 20
 ----
 Rs. 
            20,000
  
 
  
 19
 ----
 Rs. 
            19,000
  
 
  
 18
 ----
 Rs. 
            18,000
  
 
  
 17
 ----
 Rs. 
            17,000
  
 
  
 16
 ----
 Rs. 
            16,000
  
 
  
 15
 ----
 Rs. 
            15,000
  
 
  
 14
 ----
 Rs. 
            14,000
  
 
  
 13
 ----
 Rs. 
            13,000
  
 
  
 12
 ----
 Rs. 
            12,000
  
 
  
 11
 ----
 Rs. 
            11,000
  
 
  
 10
 ----
 Rs. 
            10,000
  
 
  
 9
 ----
 Rs. 
            9,000
  
 
  
 8
 ----
 Rs. 
            8,000
  
 
  
 7
 ----
 Rs. 
            7,000
  
 
  
 6
 ----
 Rs. 
            6,000
  
 
  
 5
 ----
 Rs. 
            5,000
  
 
  
 4
 ----
 Rs. 
            4,000
  
 
  
 3
 ----
 Rs. 
            3,000
  
 
  
 2
 ----
 Rs. 
            2,000
  
 
  
 1
 ----
 Rs. 
            1,000
  
 
 
 

  </form><form>
 
 
 
  
 
 

THE 
      ADVOCATES' 
      WELFARE FUNDS ACT, 2001
 

 
 

SCHEDULE II 
[ See Section 32(2) and 38]
 
 
 
 

The Uttar Pradesh 
          Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 1974 (6 of 1974). 
 
 

The Bihar State 
          Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 1983 (16 of 1983). 
 
 

The Madhya Pradesh 
          Adhivakata Kalyan Nidhi Adhiniyam, 1982 (9 of 1982). 
 
 

The Andhra Pradesh 
          Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 1987 (33 of 1987). 
 
 

The Orissa Advocates’ 
          Welfare Fund Act, 1987 (18 of 1987). 
 
 

The Rajasthan Advocates’ 
          Welfare Fund Act, 1987 (15 of 1987). 
 
 

The Tamil Nadu 
          Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 1987 (49 of 1987). 
 
 

The Gujarat Advocates’ 
          Welfare Fund Act, 1991 (14 of 1991). 
 
 

The Goa Advocates’ 
          Welfare Fund Act, 1995 (2 of 1997). 
 
 

The Assam Advocates’ 
          Welfare Fund Act, 1998 (XVIII of 1999). 
 
 

The Maharashtra 
          Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 1981 (LXI of 1981). 
 
 

The Himachal Pradesh 
          Advocates’ Fund Act, 1996 (14 of 1996). 
 
 

The Kerala Advocates’ 
          Welfare Fund Act, 1980 (21 of 1980). 
 
 

The Karnataka Advocates’ 
          Welfare Fund Act, 1983 (2 of 1985). 
 
 

The West Bengal 
          Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 1991 (XIII of 1991). 
 
 

The Jammu and Kashmir 
          Advocates’ Welfare Fund Act, 1997 (XXVI of 1997). 
      
 
 
  </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>