<act><title>THE INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (PROCEDURE AND SAFEGUARD 
FOR MONITORING AND COLLECTING TRAFFIC DATA OR INFORMATION) RULES, 
20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules 
may be called the Information Technology (Procedure and Safeguard for Monitoring 
and Collecting Traffic Data or Information) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> communication means dissemination, transmission, carriage of 
  information or signal in some manner and include both a direct communication 
  and an indirect communication; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> communication link means the use of satellite, microwave, radio, 
  terrestrial line, wire, wireless or any other communication media to 
  inter-connect computer resource; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> competent authority means the Secretary to the Government of India in 
  the Department of Information Technology under the Ministry of Communications 
  and Information Technology; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> computer resource means computer resource as defined in clause (k) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> cyber security incident means any real or suspected adverse event in 
  relation to cyber security that violates an explicitly or implicitly 
  applicable security policy resulting in unauthorized access, denial of 
  service/disruption, unauthorised use of a computer resource for processing or 
  storage of information or changes to data, information without authorisation; 
  
 </section><section><number>g</number> cyber security breaches means unauthorised acquisition or 
  unauthorised use by a person of data or information that compromises the 
  confidentiality, integrity or availability of information maintained in a 
  computer resource; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> information means information as defined in clause (v) of sub-section 
  (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> information security practices means implementation of security 
  policies and standards in order to minimize the cyber security incidents and 
  breaches; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> intermediary means an intermediary as defined in clause (w) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> monitor with its grammatical variations and cognate expressions, 
  includes to view or inspect or record or collect traffic data or information 
  generated, transmitted, received or stored in a computer resource by means of 
  a monitoring device; 
 <subsection><number>I</number> monitoring device means any electronic, mechanical, 
  electro-mechanical, electro-magnetic, optical or other instrument, device, 
  equipment or apparatus which is used or can be used, whether by itself in 
  combination with any other instrument, device, equipment or apparatus, to view 
  or inspect or record or collect traffic data or information; 
 </subsection></section><section><number>m</number> port or application port means a set of software rules which 
  identifies and permits communication between application to application, 
  network to network, computer to computer, computer system to computer system; 
  
 </section><section><number>n</number> Review Committee means the Review Committee constituted under rule 
  419A of the Indian Telegraph Rules, 1951; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> security policy means documented business rules and processes for 
  protecting information and the computer resource; (p) traffic data means 
  traffic data as defined in Explanation (ii) to section 69B of the 
  Act. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Directions for monitoring. </title>
<section><number>1</number> No directions for 
monitoring and collection of traffic data or information under sub-section (3) 
of section 69B of the Act shall be issued, except by an order made by the 
competent authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The competent authority may issue directions for monitoring for any or 
all of the following purposes related to cyber security, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> forecasting of imminent cyber incidents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> monitoring network application with traffic data or information on 
  computer resource; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> identification and determination of viruses or computer contaminant; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> tracking cyber security breaches or cyber security incidents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> tracking computer resource breaching cyber security or spreading virus 
  or computer contaminants; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> identifying or tracking of any person who has breached, or is suspected 
  of having breached or being likely to breach cyber security; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> undertaking forensic of the concerned computer resource as a part of 
  investigation or internal audit of information security practices in the 
  computer resource; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> accessing a stored information for enforcement of any provisions of the 
  laws relating to cyber security for the time being in force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> any other matter relating to cyber security. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any direction issued by the competent authority under sub-rule (2) shall 
contain reasons for such direction and a copy of such direction shall be 
forwarded to the Review Committee within a period of seven working days. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The direction of the competent authority for monitoring and collection of 
traffic data or information may include the monitoring and collection of traffic 
data or information from any person or class of persons or relating to any 
particular subject whether such traffic data or information, or class of traffic 
data or information, are received with one or more computer resources, being a 
computer resource likely to be used for the generation, transmission, receiving, 
storing of traffic data or information from or to one particular person or one 
or many set of premises. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Authorised agency of Government for monitoring and collection of 
traffic data or information. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The competent authority may authorise 
any agency of the government for monitoring and collection of traffic data or 
information generated, transmitted, received or stored in any computer resource. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> The agency authorised by the competent authority under sub-rule (1) shall 
designate one or more nodal officer, not below the rank of the Deputy Secretary 
to the Government of India, for the purpose to authenticate and send the 
requisition conveying direction issued under rule 3 to the designated officers 
of the concerned intermediary or person in-charge of computer resources. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The requisition under sub-rule (2) shall specify the name and designation 
of the officer or the agency to whom the monitored or collected traffic data or 
information is to be disclosed. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The intermediaries or person in-charge of computer resource shall 
designate one or more officers to receive requisition and to handle such 
requisition from the nodal officer for monitoring or collection of traffic data 
or information. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The requisition conveying directions for monitoring shall be conveyed to 
the designated officers of the intermediary or person in-charge of computer 
resources, in writing through letter or fax by the nodal officer or delivered, 
(including delivery by e-mail signed with electronic signature), by an officer 
not below the rank of under Secretary or officer of the equivalent rank. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The nodal officer issuing the requisition conveying directions for 
monitoring under sub-rule (2) shall also make a request in writing to the 
designated officer of intermediary or person in-charge of computer resource for 
monitoring in accordance with the format indicated in such requisition and 
report the same to the officer designated under sub-rule (3). 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The nodal officer shall also make a request to the officer of 
intermediary or person in-charge of computer resource designated under sub-rule 
(4) to extend all facilities, co-operation and assistance in installation, 
removal and testing of equipment and also enable on-line access or to secure and 
provide online access to the computer resource for monitoring and collecting 
traffic data or information. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> On receipt of requisition under sub-rule (2) conveying the direction 
issued under sub-rule (2) of rule 3, the designated, officer of the intermediary 
or person in-charge of computer resource designated under sub-rule (4) shall 
acknowledge the receipt of requisition by way of letter or fax or electronically 
signed e-mail to the nodal officer within a period of two hours from the time of 
receipt of such requisition. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The officer of the intermediary or person in-charge of computer resource 
designated under sub-rule (4) shall maintain proper records of the requisitions 
received by him. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The designated officer of the intermediary or person in-charge of 
computer resource shall forward in every fifteen days a list of requisition 
conveying direction for monitoring or collection of traffic data or information 
to the nodal officer which shall include details such as the reference and date 
of requisition conveying direction of the concerned competent authority. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Intermediary to ensure effective check in handling monitoring or 
collection of traffic data or information </title>.The intermediary or person 
in-charge of computer resources shall put in place adequate and effective 
internal checks to ensure that unauthorised monitoring or collection of traffic 
data or information does not take place and extreme secrecy is maintained and 
utmost care and precaution is taken in the matter of monitoring or collection of 
traffic data or information as it affects privacy of citizens and also that this 
matter is handled only by the designated officer of the intermediary or person 
in- charge of computer resource. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Responsibility of intermediary. </title>The intermediary or 
person in-charge of computer resource shall be responsible for the actions of 
their employees also, and in case of violation of the provision of the Act and 
rules made thereunder pertaining to maintenance of secrecy and confidentiality 
of information or any unauthorised monitoring or collection of traffic data or 
information, the intermediary or person in-charge of computer resource shall be 
liable for any action under the relevant provision of the laws for the time 
being in force. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Review of directions of competent authority </title>.The Review 
Committee shall meet at least once in two months and record its findings whether 
the directions issued under sub-rule (2) of rule 3 are in accordance with the 
provisions of sub-section (3) of section 69B of the Act and where the Review 
Committee is of the opinion that the directions are not in accordance with the 
provisions referred to above, it may set aside the directions and issue order 
for destruction of the copies, including corresponding electronic record of the 
monitored or collected traffic data or information. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Destruction of records. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every record, including 
electronic records pertaining to such directions for monitoring or collection of 
traffic data shall be destroyed by the designated officer after the expiry of a 
period of nine months from the receipt of direction or creation of record, 
whichever is later, except in a case where the traffic data or information is, 
or likely to be, required for functional requirements. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Save as otherwise required for the purpose of any on going investigation, 
criminal complaint or legal proceedings the intermediary or the person in-charge 
of computer resource shall destroy records pertaining to directions for 
monitoring or collection of information within a period of six months of 
discontinuance of the monitoring or collection of traffic data and in doing so 
they shall maintain extreme secrecy. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Prohibition of monitoring or collection of traffic data or 
information without authorisation. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person who, intentionally 
or knowingly, without authorisation under sub-rule (2) of rule 3 or sub-rule (1) 
of rule 4, monitors or collects traffic data or information, or attempts to 
monitor or collect traffic data or information, or authorises or assists any 
person to monitor or collect traffic data or information in the course of its 
occurrence or transmission at any place within India, shall be proceeded 
against, punished accordingly under the relevant provisions of the law for the 
time being in force. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The monitoring or collection of traffic data or information in computer 
resource by the employee of an intermediary or person in-charge of computer 
resource or a person duly authorised by the intermediary, may be undertaken in 
course of his duty relating to the services provided by that intermediary, if 
such activities are reasonably necessary for the discharge his duties as per the 
prevailing industry practices, in connection with the following matters, 
namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> installation of computer resource or any equipment to be used with 
  computer resource; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> operation or maintenance of computer resource; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> installation of any communication link or software either at the end 
  of the intermediary or subscriber, or installation of user account on the 
  computer resource of intermediary and testing of the same for its 
  functionality; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> accessing stored information from computer resource relating to the 
  installation, connection or maintenance of equipment, computer resource or a 
  communication link or code; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> accessing stored information from computer resource for the purpose of 
  
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> implementing information security practices in the computer resource; 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> determining any security breaches, computer contaminant or computer 
    virus; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> undertaking forensic of the concerned computer resource as a part of 
    investigation or internal audit; or </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> accessing or analysing information from a computer resource for the 
  purpose of tracing a computer resource or any person who has contravened, or 
  is suspected of having or being likely to contravene, any provision of the Act 
  that is likely to have an adverse impact on the services provided by the 
  intermediary. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Intermediary or the person in-charge of computer resource and its 
employees shall maintain strict secrecy and confidentiality of information while 
performing the actions as specified under sub-rule (2). 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The details of monitored or collected traffic data or information shall 
not be used or disclosed by intermediary or person in-charge of computer 
resource or any of its employees to any person other than the intended recipient 
of the said information under sub-rule (2) of rule 4. Any intermediary or its 
employees or person in-charge of computer resource who contravenes the 
provisions of this rule shall be proceeded against and punished accordingly 
under the relevant provisions of the Act or any other law for the time being in 
force. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Prohibition of disclosure of traffic data or information by 
authorised agency. </title>The details of monitored or collected traffic 
<title></title>data or information shall not be used or disclosed by the 
agency authorised under sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 4 for any other purpose, except for 
forecasting imminent cyber threats or general trend of port-wise traffic on 
Internet, or general analysis of cyber incidents, or for investigation or in 
judicial proceedings before the competent court in India. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Maintenance of confidentiality. </title>Save as otherwise 
provided in rule 10, strict confidentiality shall be maintained in respect of 
directions for monitoring or collection of traffic data or information issued by 
the competent authority under these rules. 

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 27-10-2009.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>