<act><tid>1802029</tid>
<title>THE GOA, DAMAN AND DIU JUDICIAL COMMISSIONER' S COURT (DECLARATION  
  AS HIGH COURT) ACT, <year>1964</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1964</year> AN ACT TO DECLARE THE JUDICIAL COMMISSIONER' S COURT F 
OR GOA, DAMAN AND
[ 16th May, <year>1964</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifteenth Year of the 
Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1513338</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>544264</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Goa, Daman and Diu Judicial Commissioner' s Court (Declaration as High  
  Court), Act, <year>1964</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1926616</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the date of 
commencement of the Goa, Daman and Diu (Judicial Commissioner' s Court) 
Regulation, <year>1963</year>. (10 of <year>1963</year>)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>247582</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," article" means an article of the 
Constitution.


</article>



<article><tid>1321769</tid>
<number>3</number>Declaration of Goa, Daman and Diu Judicial Commissioner' s 
Court as High Court for certain purposes. The Court of the Judicial 
Commissioner for the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu 
 (hereinafter referred to, as the Judicial Commissioner' s Court) is 
hereby declared to be a High Court for the purposes of articles 132, 
 133 and 134.


</article>



<article><tid>1522781</tid>
<number>4</number>Appeals to the Supreme Court not to be barred on account of 
judgement etc., being of a single Judge. An appeal shall lie to the 
Supreme Court under the provisions of article 133 from any judgment, 
decree or final order of, the Judicial Commissioner' s Court 
notwithstanding that such judgment, decree or final order is that of a 
single Judge.


</article>



<article><tid>164799</tid>
<number>5</number>Appeals to Supreme Court from judgment, decree, etc., passed 
or made Judicial Commissioner' s court. Subject to any rules made under 
article 145 or any other law as to the time within which appeals to 
the Supreme Court are to be entered, an appeal shall lie to that Court 
from a judgment, decree or final order of the Judicial Commissioner' s 
Court, under the provisions of article 132 or article 133, or from a 
judgment, final order or sentence of such Court under the provisions 
of article 134:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>130</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that an appeal may be preferred within ninety days from 
the date of passing of this Act from a judgment, decree, final order 
or sentence passed or made by the Judicial Commissioner' s Court before 
that date.



</article>



<article><tid>1793072</tid>
<number> 6</number> Exceptions and modifications subject to which the provisions 
of Chapter V of Part VI of the Constitution apply to the Judicial 
Commissioner' s court. The provisions of Chapter V of Part VI of the 
Constitution shall in their application to the Judicial Commissioner' s 
Court have effect subject to the following exceptions and 
modifications, namely:-
<section><tid>1496786</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of articles 216, 217, 218, 220, 221, 
222, 223, 224, 224A, 225, 230 and 231 shall not apply;

</section>

<section><tid>1582253</tid>
<number>b</number>references-

<subsection><tid>1591687</tid>
<number>i</number>in article 219, in the proviso to clause (3) of 
article 227 and in article 229 to the Governor shall be 
construed as references to the administrator of the 
Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>894945</tid>
<number>ii</number>in articles 219 and 229 to the State (except in the  
  expression" the State Public Service Commission") 
shall be construed as references to the Union territory 
of Goa, Daman and Diu;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1485197</tid>
<number>c</number>the reference to the State Public Service Commission in 
the proviso to clause (1) of article 229 shall be construed 
as a reference to the Union Public Service Commission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1392715</tid>
<number> 7</number> Appeals to lie to the Supreme Court from judgment, decree, 
etc., passed or made by Tribunal de Relacao. Any person aggrieved-
<section><tid>1576419</tid>
<number>a</number>by any judgment, decree, order or sentence of the 
Tribunal de Relacao passed or made before the 20th December, 
<year>1961</year>, against which an appeal would lie to a superior court 
in Portugal in accordance with law but could not be preferred 
by reason of Goa, Daman and Diu becoming part of the 
territory of India, or against which an appeal having been 
preferred to a superior court in Portugal in accordance with 
law had not been disposed of before the said date; or

</section>

<section><tid>1100119</tid>
<number>b</number>by any judgment, decree, order or sentence of the 
Tribunal de Relacao passed or made on or after the 20th 
December, <year>1961</year>,
may, within ninety days from the date of passing of this Act, prefer 
an appeal from such judgment, decree, order or sentence to the Supreme 
Court as if such judgment, decree, order or sentence had been passed 
or made by the Judicial Commissioner' s Court.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1461430</tid>
<number>8</number>Repeal of section 7 of Act 1 of <year>1962</year>. Section 7 of the Goa, 
Daman and Diu (Administration) Act, <year>1962</year> is hereby repealed.

</article>



 </act>