<act><tid>1806623</tid>
<title>THE WORKMEN' S COMPENSATION ACT, <year>1923</year></title>

ACT NO. 8 OF <year>1923</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 5th March, <year>1923</year>.]

An Act to provide for the payment by certain classes of employers to 
their workmen of compensation for injury by accident.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the payment by certain 
classes of employers to their workmen of compensation for injury by 
accident; It is hereby enacted as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1032090</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>1692336</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Workmen' s Compensation Act <year>1923</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>907771</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>.]

</section>

<section><tid>620554</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on the first day of July, <year>1924</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>322467</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.-
<section><tid>325699</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless there is anything  
repugnant in the subject or context,--
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


<subsection><tid>943666</tid>
<number>b</number>" Commissioner" means a Commissioner for Workmen' s 
Compensation appointed under section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>254062</tid>
<number>c</number>" compensation" means compensation as provided for by 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>103289</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" dependant" means any of the following relatives of a 
deceased workman, namely:--

<subsubsection><tid>1195783</tid>
<number>i</number>a widow, a minor legitimate son, and unmarried 
legitimate daughter, or a widowed mother; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1227921</tid>
<number>ii</number>if wholly dependent on the earnings of the 
workman at the time of his death, a son or a daughter 
who has attained the age of 18 years and who is infirm;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, s. 3 and Sch.; Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 
2 and Sch. I; Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I 
and Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands by Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 
3 and Sch. This Act has been modified in its application to 
apprentices under the Apprentices Act, <year>1961</year> (52 of <year>1961</year>) by s. 16 
and Sch. to that Act. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for sub- section (2). 
3. The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
51 of <year>1970</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1971</year>). 
4. Cl. (a) omitted by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
5. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for the former clause (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>971305</tid>
<number>iii</number>if wholly or in part dependent on the 
earnings of the workman at the time of his 
death, 
 (a) a widower, 
 (b) a parent other than a widowed mother, 
 (c) a minor illegitimate son, an unmarried 
illegitimate daughter or a daughter 
legitimate or illegitimate if married and 
a minor or if widowed and a minor, 
 (d) a minor brother or a unmarried sister or 
a widowed sister if a minor, 
 (e) a widowed daughter- in- law, 
 (f) a minor child of a pre- deceased son, 
 (g) a minor child of a pre- deceased daughter 
where no parent of the child is alive, or 
 (h) a paternal grandparent if no parent of 
the workman is alive;]

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1184541</tid>
<number>e</number>" employer" includes any body of persons whether 
incorporated or not and any managing agent of an 
employer and the legal representative of a deceased 
employer, and, when the services of workman are 
temporarily lent or let on hire to another person by 
the person with whom the workman has entered into a 
contract of service or apprenticeship means such other 
person while the workman is working for him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1548055</tid>
<number>f</number>" managing agent" means any person appointed or acting as 
the representative of another person for the purpose of 
carrying on such other person' s trade or business, but 
does not include an individual manager subordinate to 
an employer <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1504842</tid>
<number>ff</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" minor" means a person who has not attained the age 
of 18 years;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1713237</tid>
<number>g</number>" partial disablement" means, where the disablement is of 
a temporarp nature, such disablement as reduces the 
earning capacity of a workman in any employment in 
which he was engaged at the time of the accident 
resulting in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>In the application of the Act to Bengal, a new clause (ff) has 
been ins. here by the Workmen' s Compensation (Bengal Amendment) 
Act, <year>1942</year> (Ben. 6 of <year>1942</year>), s. 3. 
2. Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the disablement, and, where the disablement is of a 
permanent nature, such disablement as reduces his 
earning capacity in every employment which he was 
capable of undertaking at that time: provided that 
every injury specified <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in Part II of Schedule I] 
shall be deemed to result in permanent partial 
disablement;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>795298</tid>
<number>h</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1520001</tid>
<number>i</number>" qualified medical practitioner" means any person 
registered <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> under any <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Central Act, Provincial 
Act or an Act of the Legislature of a <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State]] 
providing for the maintenance of a register of medical 
practitioners, or, in any area where no such last- 
mentioned Act is in force, any person declared by the 
State Government, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, to be a qualified medical practitioner for the 
purposes of this Act;
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1247908</tid>
<number>j</number>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>917448</tid>
<number>k</number>" seaman" means any person forming part of the crew of 
any <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> ship, but does not include the master of 
 <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> the] ship;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1997886</tid>
<number>l</number>" total disablement" means such disablement, whether of a 
temporary or permanent nature, as incapacitates a 
workman for all work which he was capable of performing 
at the time of the accident resulting in such 
disablement:
<footcitenum>8</footcitenum> Provided that permanent total disablement shall be deemed 
to result from every injury specified in Part I of 
Schedule I or from any combination of injuries 
specified in Part II thereof where the aggregate 
percentage of the loss of earning capacity, as 
specified in the said Part II against those injuries, 
amounts to one hundred per cent or more;]


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>68394</tid>
<number>m</number>" wages" includes any privilege or benefit which is 
capable of being estimated in money, other than a 
travelling allowance
<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 64 of <year>1962</year>, s. 2, for" in Schedule I" (w. e. f. 1- 2-  
  <year>1963</year>). 
2. The words" under the Medical Act, <year>1858</year>, or any Act amending the 
same, or" omitted by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Act of the Central Legislature or 
of any Legislature in a Province of India". 
4. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part A 
State or Part B State". 
5. Cl. (j) rep. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 2. 
6. The word" registered" omitted by s. 2, ibid. 
7. Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" any such". 
8. Subs. by Act 64 of <year>1962</year>, s. 2, for the proviso (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or the value of any travelling concession or a 
contribution paid by the employer of a workman towards 
any pension or provident fund or a sum paid to a 
workman to cover any special expenses entailed on him 
by the nature of his employment;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1534310</tid>
<number>n</number>" workman" means any person (other than a person whose  
employment is of a casual nature and who is employed 
otherwise than for the purposes of the employer' s trade 
  or business) who is--

<subsubsection><tid>1655997</tid>
<number>i</number>a railway servant as defined in section 3 of 
the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>), not 
permanently employed in any administrative, district or 
sub- divisional office of a railway and not employed in 
any such capacity as is specified in Schedule II, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>136946</tid>
<number>ii</number>employed <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> in any such capacity as 
is specified in Schedule II.
whether the contract of employment was made before or 
after the passing of this Act and whether such contract 
is expressed or implied, oral or in writing; but does 
not include any person working in the capacity of a 
member of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Armed Forces of the Union] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>; 
and any reference to a workman who has been injured 
shall, where the workman is dead, include a reference 
to his dependants or any of them.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1695026</tid>
<number>2</number>The exercise and performance of the powers and duties of a 
local authority or of any department <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> acting on behalf of 
the Government] shall, for the purposes of this Act, unless a 
contrary intention appears, be deemed to be the trade or business 
of such authority or department.

</section>

<section><tid>894493</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> The <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> State Government], after giving, by notification <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> 
in the Official Gazette, not less than three months' notice of its 
intention
<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" either by way of manual labour or" rep. by Act 15 of 
<year>1933</year>, s. 2. 
2. Omitted by Act 22 of <year>1984</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f 1- 7- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" His Majesty' s naval, military or 
air forces". 
4. The words" or of the Royal Indian Marine Service" rep. by the 
A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
5. Subs., ibid., for" of the Government". 
6. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 2, for the original sub- section. 
7. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C". 
8. For such a notification, see Gazette of India, <year>1935</year>. Pt. I. 
p. 745.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


so to do, may, by a like notification, add to Schedule II any class of 
persons employed in any occupation which it is satisfied is a 
hazardous occupation, and the provisions of this Act shall thereupon 
apply <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> within the State] to such classes of persons:

Provided that in making such addition the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> State Government] 
may direct that the provisions of this Act shall apply to such classes 
of persons in respect of specified injuries only.]

CHAP

WORKMEN' S COMPENSATION

CHAPTER II

WORKMEN' S COMPENSATION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1850559</tid>
<number> 3</number> Employer' s liability for compensation.-
<section><tid>1648422</tid>
<number>1</number>If personal injury  
is caused to a workman by accident arising out of and in the course of 
his employment, his employer shall be liable to pay compensation in 
accordance with the provisions of this Chapter:
Provided that the employer shall not be so liable--


<subsection><tid>1500806</tid>
<number>a</number>in respect of any injury which does not result in the 
total or partial disablement of the workman for a 
period exceeding <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> three] days;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>881308</tid>
<number>b</number>in respect of any <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> injury, not resulting in death, 
caused by] an accident which is directly attributable 
to--

<subsubsection><tid>565531</tid>
<number>i</number>the workman having been at the time thereof 
under the influence of drink or drugs, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>258270</tid>
<number>ii</number>the wilful disobedience of the workman to an 
order expressly given, or to a rule expressly framed, 
for the purpose of securing the safety of workmen, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1039469</tid>
<number>iii</number>the wilful removal or disregard by the 
workman of any safety guard or other device which he 
knew to have been provided for the purpose of securing 
the safety of workmen. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>184182</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> If a workman employed in any employment specified in Part 
A of Schedule III contracts any disease specified therein as an 
occupational disease peculiar to that employment, or if a workman, 
whilst in the service of an employer in whose service he has been
<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
2. Subs., ibid., for" G. G. in C.". 
3. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 3, for" seven" (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 3, for" injury to a workman resulting 
from". 
5. The word" or" and cl. (c) rep. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 2. 
6. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 3, for sub- sections (2) and (3) 
 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


employed for a continuous period of not less than six months (which  
period shall not include a period of service under any other employer 
  in the same kind of employment) in any employment specified in Part B 
of Schedule III, contracts any disease specified therein as an 
occupational disease peculiar to that employment, or if a workman 
whilst in the service of one or more employers in any employment 
specified in Part C of Schedule III for such continuous period as the 
Central Government may specify in respect of each such employment, 
contracts any disease specified therein as an occupational disease 
peculiar to that employment, the contracting of the disease shall be 
deemed to be an injury by accident within the meaning of this section 
and, unless the contrary is proved, the accident shall be deemed to 
have arisen out of, and in the course of, the employment:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that if it is proved,--


<subsection><tid>1931997</tid>
<number>a</number>that a workman whilst in the service of one or more 
employers in any employment specified in Part C of 
Schedule III has contracted a disease specified therein 
as an occupational disease peculiar to that employment 
during a continuous period which is less than the 
period specified under this sub- section for that 
employment, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1591517</tid>
<number>b</number>that the disease has arisen out of and in the course of 
the employment;
the contracting of such disease shall be deemed to be an injury by 
accident within the meaning of this section:

Provided further that if it is proved that a workman who having 
served under any employer in any employment specified in Part B of 
Schedule III or who having served under one or more employers in any 
employment specified in Part C of that Schedule, for a continuous 
period specified under this sub- section for that employment and he has 
after the cessation of such service contracted any disease specified 
in the said Part B or the said Part C, as the case may be, as an 
occupational disease peculiar to the employment and that such disease 
arose out of the employment, the contracting of the disease shall be 
deemed to be an injury by accident within the meaning of this 
section.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>939638</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> If a workman employed in any employment specified in Part 
C of Schedule III contracts any occupational disease peculiar to that 
employment, the contracting whereof is deemed to be an injury by 
accident within the meaning of this section, and such employment
<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 64 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1963</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for sub- section (2A)  (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


was under more than one employer, all such employers shall be liable 
for the payment of the compensation in such proportion as the 
Commissioner may, in the circumstances, deem just.]


</section>

<section><tid>1249751</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Government in the case of employments specified in 
Part A and Part B of Schedule III, and the Central Government in the 
case of employments specified in Part C of that Schedule, after 
giving, by notification in the Official Gazette, not less than three 
months' notice of its intention so to do, may, by a like notification, 
add any description of employment to the employments specified in 
Schedule III, and shall specify in the case of employments so added 
the diseases which shall be deemed for the purposes of this section to 
be occupational diseases peculiar to those employments respectively, 
and thereupon the provisions of sub- section (2) shall apply <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as if 
such diseases had been declared by this Act to be occupational 
diseases peculiar to those employments.]

</section>

<section><tid>1305047</tid>
<number>4</number>Save as provided by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> sub- sections (2), (2A)] and (3), no 
compensation shall be payable to a workman in respect of any disease 
unless the disease is <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> directly attributable to a specific injury 
by accident arising out of and in the course of his employment.

</section>

<section><tid>194176</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing herein contained shall be deemed to confer any right 
to compensation on a workman in respect of any injury if he has 
instituted in a Civil Court a suit for damages in respect of the 
injury against the employer or any other person; and no suit for 
damages shall be maintainable by a workman in any Court of law in 
respect of any injury--

<subsection><tid>1809709</tid>
<number>a</number>if he has instituted a claim to compensation in respect 
of the injury before a Commissioner; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>418165</tid>
<number>b</number>if an agreement has been come to between the workman and 
his employer providing for the payment of compensation 
in respect of the injury in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>176854</tid>
<number> 4</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Amount of compensation.-
<section><tid>1306642</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of  
this Act, the amount of compensation shall be as follows, namely:--

<subsection><tid>99964</tid>
<number>a</number>where death results an amount equal to forty per 
from the injury cent. of the monthly wages 
of the deceased workman 
multiplied by the relevant 
factor;
or

an amount of twenty thousand 
rupees, 
whichever is more;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>724414</tid>
<number>b</number>Where permanent total an amount equal to fifty per 
disablement results from cent. of the monthly wages 
the injury of the injured workman 
multiplied by the relevant 
factor; 
or
an amount of twenty- four 
thousand rupees,

whichever is more;

Explanation I.-- For the purposes of clause (a) and clause (b), 
" relevant factor", in relation to a workman means the factor specified 
in the second column of Schedule IV against the entry in the first 
column of that Schedule specifying the number of years which are the 
same as the completed years of the age of the workman on his last 
birthday immediately preceding the date on which the compensation fell 
due;

Explanation II.-- Where the monthly wages of a workman exceed one 
thousand rupees, his monthly wages for the purposes of clause (a) and 
clause (b) shall be deemed to be one thousand rupees only,


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>338024</tid>
<number>c</number>Where parmanent partial (i) in the case of an injury 
disablement results from specified in Part II of Schedule 
the injury I, such percentage of the 
compensation which would have 
been payable in the case of 
permanent total disablement as 
is specified therein as being 
the percentage of the loss of 
earning capacity caused by that 
injury, and

<subsubsection><tid>1014250</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of an injury not 
pecified in Schedule I, such 
percentage of the compensation 
payable in the case of permanent 
total disablement as is propor- 
tionate to the loss of earning 
capacity (as assessed by the  
  qualified medical practitioner) 
permanently caused by the inj- 
ury;
Explanation I.-- Where more injuries than one are caused by the 
same accident, the amount of compensation payable under this head 
shall be aggregated but not so in any case as to exceed the amount 
which would have been payable if permanent total disablement had 
resulted from the injuries;

Explanation II.-- In assessing the loss of earning capacity for 
the purposes of sub- clause (ii), the qualified medical practitioner 
shall have due regard to the percentages of loss of earning capacity 
in relation to different injuries specified in Schedule I;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1843314</tid>
<number>d</number>Where temporary disable- a half- monthly payment of the 
ment, whether total or sum equivalent to twenty- five 
partial result from the per cent. of monthly wages of 
injury the workman, to be paid in accor- 
dance with the provisions of sub- 
section 2. 
 (2) The half- monthly payment referred to in clause (d) of sub- 
section (1) shall be payable on the sixteenth day--

<subsubsection><tid>878399</tid>
<number>i</number>from the date of disablement where such disablement 
lasts for a period of twenty- eight days or more, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>53969</tid>
<number>ii</number>after the expiry of a waiting period of three days from 
the date of disablement where such disablement lasts for a period 
of less than twenty- eight days; and thereafter half- monthly 
during the disablement or during a period of five years, 
whichever period is shorter:
Provided that--


<subsubsubsection><tid>492155</tid>
<number>a</number>there shall be deducted from any lump sum or half- 
monthly payments to which the workman is entitled the amount of 
any payment or allowance which the workman has received from the 
employer by way of compensation during the period of disablement 
prior to the receipt of such lump sum or of the first half- 
monthly payment, as the case may be; and

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>673411</tid>
<number>b</number>no half- monthly payment shall in any case exceed the 
amount, if any, by which half the amount of the monthly wages of 
the workman before the accident exceeds half the amount of such 
wages which he is earning after the accident.
Explanation.-- Any payment or allowance which the workman has 
received from the employer towards his medical treatment shall not be 
deemed to be a payment or allowance received by him by way of 
compensation within the meaning of clause (a) of the proviso.


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1769875</tid>
<number>3</number>On the ceasing of the disablement before the date on which 
any half- monthly payment falls due, there shall be payable in respect 
of that half- month a sum proportionate to the duration of the 
disablement in that half- month.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Certain words omitted by Act 51 of <year>1970</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1-  
  9- <year>1971</year>). 
2. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 3, for" sub- sections (2)" (w. e. f. 1- 6-  
  <year>1959</year>). 
3. The words" solely and" rep. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 3. 
4. Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1984</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>307575</tid>
<number> 4A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Compensation to be paid when due and penalty for default.-

<section><tid>1541335</tid>
<number>1</number>Compensation under section 4 shall be paid as soon as it falls  
due.

</section>

<section><tid>1710230</tid>
<number>2</number>In cases where the employer does not accept the liability for 
compensation to the extent claimed, he shall be bound to make 
provisional payment based on the extent of liability which he accepts, 
and, such payment shall be deposited with the Commissioner or made to 
the workman, as the case may be, without prejudice to the right of the 
workman to make any further claim.

</section>

<section><tid>558219</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any employer is in default in paying the compensation 
due under this Act within one month from the date it fell due, the 
Commissioner may direct that, in addition to the amount of the 
arrears, simple interest at the rate of six per cent. per annum on the 
amount due together with, if in the opinion of the Commissioner there 
is no justification for the delay, a further sum not exceeding fifty 
per cent. of such amount, shall be recovered from the employer by way 
of penalty.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1493140</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Method of calculating wages.- <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> In this Act and for the 
purposes thereof the expression" monthly wages" means the amount of 
wages deemed to be payable for a month' s service (whether the wages  
are payable by the month or by whatever other period or at piece 
  rates), and calculated] as follows, namely:--
<section><tid>627287</tid>
<number>a</number>where the workman has, during a continuous period of not 
less than twelve months immediately preceding the 
accident, been in the service of the employer who is 
liable to pay compensation, the monthly wages of the 
workman shall be one- twelfth of the total wages which 
have fallen due for payment to him by the employer in 
the last twelve months of that period;

</section>

<section><tid>1716813</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> where the whole of the continuous period of service 
immediately preceding the accident during which the 
workman was in the service of the employer who is 
liable to pay the compensation was less than one month, 
the monthly wages of the workman shall be <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the 
average monthly amount which, during the twelve
<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
2. The original s. 5 renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section 
by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 3. The brackets and figure" (1)" rep. by Act 
9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 4. 
3. Subs. by Act 13 of <year>1939</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 30- 6- <year>1934</year>), for" For the 
purposes of this Act the monthly wages of a workman shall 
be calaucated" the words in italics subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 
5, for" section 4". 
4. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 5. 
5. The words" deemed to be" rep. by Act 13 of <year>1939</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 30-  
  6- <year>1934</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


months immediately preceding the accident, was being 
earned by a workman employed on the same work by the 
same employer, or, if there was no workman so employed, 
by a workman employed on similar work in the same 
locality];


</section>

<section><tid>911022</tid>
<number>c</number>in other cases[ including cases in which it is 
not possible for want of necessary information to 
calculate the monthly wages under clause (b)]], the 
monthly wages shall be thirty times the total wages 
earned in respect of the last continuous period of 
service immediately preceding the accident from the 
employer who is liable to pay compensation, divided by 
the number of days comprising such period.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

Explanation.-- A period of service shall, for the purposes of 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> this <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> section]] be deemed to be continuous which has not been 
interrupted by a period of absence from work exceeding fourteen days.

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1850878</tid>
<number> 6</number> Review.-
<section><tid>505720</tid>
<number>1</number>Any half- monthly payment payable under this Act,  
either under an agreement between the parties or under the order of a 
Commissioner, may be reviewed by the Commissioner, on the application 
either of the employer or of the workman accompanied by the 
certificate of a qualified medical practitioner that there has been a 
change in the condition of the workman or, subject to rules made under 
this Act, on application made without such certificate.

</section>

<section><tid>571029</tid>
<number>2</number>Any half- monthly payment may, on review under this section, 
subject to the provisions of this Act, be continued, increased, 
decreased or ended, or if the accident is found to have resulted in 
permanent disablement, be converted to the lump sum to which the 
workman is entitled less any amount which he has already received by 
way of half- monthly payments.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1036957</tid>
<number>7</number>Commutation of half- monthly payments.- Any right to receive 
half- monthly payments may, by agreement between the parties or, if the 
parties cannot agree and the payments have been continued for not less 
than six months, on the application of either party to the 
Commissioner be redeemed by the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The original cl. (b) relettered (c) by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 5. 
2. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 6, for" in other cases" (w. e. f. 1- 6-  
  <year>1959</year>). 
3. The proviso rep. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 5. 
4. Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 3 for" this section". 
5. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 4, for" sub- section". 
6. Sub- section (2) ins. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 3, rep. by Act 15 of 
<year>1933</year>, s. 5.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


payment of a lump sum of such amount as may be agreed to by the 
parties or determined by the Commissioner, as the case may be.



</article>



<article><tid>1170117</tid>
<number> 8</number> Distribution of compensation.- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>437123</tid>
<number>1</number>No payment of  
compensation in respect of a workman whose injury has resulted in 
death, and no payment of a lump sum as compensation to a woman or a 
person under a legal disability, shall be made otherwise than by 
deposit with the Commissioner, and no such payment made directly by an 
employer shall be deemed to be a payment of compensation:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that, in the case of a deceased workman, an employer 
may make to any dependant advances on account of compensation not 
exceeding an aggregate of one hundred rupees, and so much of such 
aggregate as does not exceed the compensation payable to that 
dependant shall be deducted by the Commissioner from such compensation 
and repaid to the employer.]


</section>

<section><tid>848543</tid>
<number>2</number>Any other sum amounting to not less than ten rupees which is 
payable as compensation may be deposited with the Commissioner on 
behalf of the person entitled thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>3183</tid>
<number>3</number>The receipt of the Commissioner shall be a sufficient 
discharge in respect of any compensation deposited with him.]

</section>

<section><tid>449900</tid>
<number>4</number>On the deposit of any money under sub- section (1) <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> as 
compensation in respect of a deceased workman] the Commissioner 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> shall deduct] therefrom the actual cost of the workman' s funeral 
expenses, to an amount not exceeding <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> fifty rupees] and pay the same 
to the person by whom such expenses were incurred, and shall, if he 
thinks necessary, cause notice to be published or to be served on each 
dependant in such manner as he thinks fit, calling upon the dependants 
to appear before him on such date as he may fix for determining the 
distribution of the compensation. If the Commissioner is satisfied 
after any inquiry which he may deem necessary, that no dependant 
exists, he shall repay the balance of the money to the employer by 
whom it was paid. The Commissioner shall, on application by the 
employer, furnish a statement showing in detail all disbursements 
made.

</section>

<section><tid>1557385</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Compensation deposited in respect of a deceased workman 
shall, subject to any deduction made under sub- section (4), be
<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 4, for original sub- sections (1) to 
 (3). 
2. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 6, for the original proviso. 
3. Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 4. 
4. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 6, for" may deduct". 
5. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 7, for" twenty- five rupees" (w. e. f. 1-  
  6- <year>1959</year>). 
6. Sub- sections (5) to (7) subs. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 4, for the 
original sub- section (5).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


apportioned among the dependants of the deceased workman or any of 
them in such proportion as the Commissioner thinks fit, or may, in the 
discretion of the Commissioner, be allotted to any one dependant.


</section>

<section><tid>643760</tid>
<number>6</number>Where any compensation deposited with the Commissioner is 
payable to any person, the Commissioner shall, if the person to whom 
the compensation is payable is not a woman or a person under a legal 
disability, and may, in other cases, pay the money to the person 
entitled thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>1883052</tid>
<number>7</number>Where any lump sum deposited with the Commissioner is payable 
to a woman or a person under a legal disability, such sum may be 
invested, applied or otherwise dealt with for the benefit of the 
woman, or of such person during his disability, in such manner as the 
Commissioner may direct; and where a half- monthly payment is payable 
to any person under a legal disability, the Commissioner may, of his 
own motion or on an application made to him in this behalf, order that 
the payment be made during the disability to any dependant of the 
workman or to any other person, whom the Commissioner thinks best 
fitted to provide for the welfare of the workman.]

</section>

<section><tid>196402</tid>
<number>8</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] Where, on application made to him in this behalf or 
otherwise, the Commissioner is satisfied that, on account of neglect 
of children on the part of a parent or on account of the variation of 
the circumstances of any dependant or for any other sufficient cause, 
an order of the Commissioner as to the distribution of any sum paid as 
compensation or as to the manner in which any sum payable to any such 
dependant is to be invested, applied or otherwise dealt with, ought to 
be varied, the Commissioner may make such orders for the variation of 
the former order as he thinks just in the circumstances of the case:
Provided that no such order prejudicial to any person shall be 
made unless such person has been given an opportunity of showing cause 
why the order should not be made, or shall be made in any case in 
which it would involve the repayment by a dependant of any sum already 
paid to him.


</section>

<section><tid>712023</tid>
<number>9</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where the Commissioner varies any order under sub- section 
 (8) by reason of the fact that payment of compensation to any person 
has been obtained by fraud, impersonation or other improper means, any 
amount so paid to or on behalf of such person may be recovered in the 
manner hereinafter provided in section 31.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The original sub- section (6) renumbered (8) by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, 
s. 4. 
2. Ins. by s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1245579</tid>
<number>9</number>Compensation not to be assigned, attached or charged.- Save as 
provided by this Act, no lump sum or half- monthly payment payable 
under this Act shall in any way be capable of being assigned or 
charged or be liable to attachment or pass to any person other than 
the workman by operation of law, nor shall any claim be set off 
against the same.


</article>



<article><tid>887738</tid>
<number> 10</number> Notice and claim.-
<section><tid>1998413</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> No claim for compensation shall be  
entertained by a Commissioner unless notice of the accident has been 
given in the manner hereinafter provided as soon as practicable after 
the happening thereof and unless the claim is preferred before him 
within <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> two years] of the occurrence of the accident or, in case of 
death, within <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> two years] from the date of death:]
Provided that, where the accident is the contracting of a disease 
in respect of which the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 3 are 
applicable, the accident shall be deemed to have occurred on the first 
of the days during which the workman was continuously absent from work 
in consequence of the disablement caused by the disease:

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided further that in case of partial disablement due to 
the contracting of any such disease and which does not force the 
workman to absent himself from work, the period of two years shall be 
counted from the day the workman gives notice of the disablement to 
his employer:

Provided further that if a workman who, having been employed in 
an employment for a continuous period, specified under sub- section (2) 
of section 3 in respect of that employment, ceases to be so employed 
and develops symptoms of an occupational disease peculiar to that 
employment within two years of the cessation of employment, the 
accident shall be deemed to have occurred on the day on which the 
symptoms were first detected:]

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Provided further that the want of or any defect or 
irregularity in a notice shall not be a bar to the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> entertainment of 
a claim]--


<subsection><tid>1764168</tid>
<number>a</number>if the claim is <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> preferred] in respect of the death of 
a workman resulting from an accident which occurred on 
the premises of the employer, or at any place where the 
workman at the time of the accident was working under
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 5, for the original words. 
2. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 8, for" one year" (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 64 of <year>1962</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1963</year>). 
4. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 7. 
5. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 5, for" maintenance of proceedings". 
6. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" made".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the control of the employer or of any person employed 
by him, and the workman died on such premises or at 
such place, or on any premises belonging to the 
employer, or died without having left the vicinity of 
the premises or place where the accident occurred, or


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>208889</tid>
<number>b</number>if the employer <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or any one of several employers or 
any person responsible to the employer for the 
management of any branch of the trade or business in 
which the injured workman was employed] had knowledge 
of the accident from any other source at or about the 
time when it occurred:
Provided further, that the Commissioner may <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> entertain] and 
decide any claim to compensation in any case notwithstanding that the 
notice has not been given, or the claim has not been <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> preferred], in 
due time as provided in this sub- section, if he is satisfied that the 
failure so to give the notice or <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> prefer] the claim, as the case may 
be, was due to sufficient cause.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>554673</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such notice shall give the name and address of the 
person injured and shall state in ordinary language the cause of the 
injury and the date on which the accident happened, and shall be 
served on the employer or upon <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> any one of] several employers, or 
upon any person <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> responsible to the employer for the management 
of any branch of the trade or business in which the injured workman 
was employed.

</section>

<section><tid>1275608</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> The State Government may require that any prescribed class 
of employers shall maintain at their premises at which workmen are 
employed a notice- book, in the prescribed form, which shall be readily 
accessible at all reasonable times to any injured workman employed on 
the premises and to any person acting bona fide on his behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1992558</tid>
<number>4</number>A notice under this section may be served by delivering it 
at, or sending it by registered post addressed to, the residence or 
any office or place of business of the person on whom it is to be 
served, or, where a notice- book is maintained, by entry in the notice- 
book.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 5. 
2. Subs. by s 5, ibid., for" admit". 
3. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" instituted". 
4. Subs. by s. 5, ibid., for" institute". 
5. Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1924</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, for" any one or". 
6. The word" directly" rep. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 5. 
7. Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 7, for the original sub- section (3).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>660224</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to require from employers statements regarding 
fatal accidents.-
<section><tid>165497</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a Commissioner receives information from  
any source that a workman has died as a result of an accident arising 
out of and in the course of his employment, he may send by registered 
post a notice to the workman' s employer requiring him to submit, 
within thirty days of the service of the notice, a statement, in the 
prescribed form, giving the circumstances attending the death of the 
workman, and indicating whether, in the opinion of the employer, he is 
or is not liable to deposit compensation on account of the death.

</section>

<section><tid>830784</tid>
<number>2</number>If the employer is of opinion that he is liable to deposit 
compensation, he shall make the deposit within thirty days of the 
service of the notice.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ss. 10A and 10B ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 8.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>72466</tid>
<number>3</number>If the employer is of opinion that he is not liable to 
deposit compensation, he shall in his statement indicate the grounds 
on which he disclaims liability.

</section>

<section><tid>110602</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the employer has so disclaimed liability, the 
Commissioner, after such enquiry as he may think fit, may inform any 
of the dependants of the deceased workman, that it is open to the 
dependants to prefer a claim for compensation, and may give them such 
other further information as he may think fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1332585</tid>
<number> 10B</number> Reports of fatal accidents and serious bodily injuries.-
<section><tid>293542</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where, by any law for the time being in force, notice is required to 
be given to any authority, by or on behalf of an employer, of any 
accident occurring on his premises which results in death <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or 
serious bodily injury], the person required to give the notice shall, 
within seven days of the death <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or serious bodily injury], send a 
report to the Commissioner giving the circumstances attending the 
death <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or serious bodily injury]:
Provided that where the State Government has so prescribed the 
person required to give the notice may instead of sending such report 
to the Commissioner send it to the authority to whom he is required to 
give the notice.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.--" Serious bodily injury" means an injury which 
involves, or in all probability will involve the permanent loss of the 
use of, or permanent injury to, any limb, or the permanent loss of or 
injury to the sight or hearing, or the fracture of any limb, or the 
enforced absence of the injured person from work for a period 
exceeding twenty days.]


</section>

<section><tid>1455947</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, extend the provisions of sub- section (1) to any class of 
premises other than those coming within the scope of that sub- section, 
and may, by such notification, specify the persons who shall send the 
report to the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>241618</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Nothing in this section shall apply to factories to which 
the Employees' State Insurance Act, <year>1948</year>, (34 of <year>1948</year>.) applies.]]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>377829</tid>
<number> 11</number> Medical examination.-
<section><tid>740051</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a workman has given notice of  
an accident, he shall, if the employer, before the expiry of three 
days from the time at which service of the notice has been effected, 
offers to have him examined free of charge by a qualified medical 
practitioner, submit himself for such examination, and any workman who 
is in receipt of a half- monthly payment under this Act shall, if so 
required, submit himself for such examination from time to time:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 9 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that a workman shall not be required to submit himself 
for examination by a medical practitioner otherwise than in accordance 
with rules made under this Act, or at more frequent intervals than may 
be prescribed.


</section>

<section><tid>175420</tid>
<number>2</number>If a workman, on being required to do so by the employer 
under sub- section (1) or by the Commissioner at any time, refuses to 
submit himself for examination by a qualified medical practitioner or 
in any way obstructs the same, his right to compensation shall be 
suspended during the continuance of such refusal or obstruction 
unless, in the case of refusal, he was prevented by any sufficient 
cause from so submitting himself.

</section>

<section><tid>1461883</tid>
<number>3</number>If a workman, before the expiry of the period within which he 
is liable under sub- section (1) to be required to submit himself for 
medical examination, voluntarily leaves without having been so 
examined the vicinity of the place in which he was employed, his right 
to compensation shall be suspended until he returns and offers himself 
for such examination.

</section>

<section><tid>645611</tid>
<number>4</number>Where a workman, whose right to compensation has been 
suspended under sub- section (2) or sub- section (3), dies without 
having submitted himself for medical examination as required by either 
of those sub- sections, the Commissioner may, if he thinks fit, direct 
the payment of compensation to the dependants of the deceased workman.

</section>

<section><tid>981442</tid>
<number>5</number>Where under sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) a right to 
compensation is suspended, no compensation shall be payable in respect 
of the period of suspension, and, if the period of suspension 
commences before the expiry of the waiting period referred to in 
clause (d) of sub- section (1) of section 4, the waiting period shall 
be increased by the period during which the suspension continues.

</section>

<section><tid>132684</tid>
<number>6</number>Where an injured workman has refused to be attended by a 
qualified medical practitioner whose services have been offered to him 
by the employer free of charge or having accepted such offer has 
deliberately disregarded the instructions of such medical 
practitioner, then, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> if it is proved that the workman has not 
thereafter been regularly attended by a qualified medical practitioner 
or having been so attended has deliberately failed to follow his 
instructions and that such refusal, disregard or failure was 
unreasonable] in the circumstances of the case and that the injury has 
been aggravated thereby, the injury and resulting disablement shall be 
deemed to be of the same nature and duration as they might reasonably 
have
<pagefootnote><pagenum>29</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 6, for the original words.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


been expected to be if the workman had been regularly attended by a 
qualified medical practitioner <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> whose instructions he had followed], 
and compensation, if any, shall be payable accordingly.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378966</tid>
<number> 12</number> Contracting.-
<section><tid>397660</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any person (hereinafter in this   
  section referred to as the principal) in the course of or for the 
purposes of his trade or business contracts with any other person 
 (hereinafter in this section referred to as the contractor) for the 
execution by or under the contractor of the whole or any part of any 
work which is ordinarily part of the trade or business of the 
principal, the principal shall be liable to pay to any workman 
employed in the execution of the work any compensation which he would 
have been liable to pay if that workman had been immediately employed 
by him; and where compensation is claimed from the principal, this Act 
shall apply as if references to the principal were substituted for 
references to the employer except that the amount of compensation 
shall be calculated with reference to the wages of the workman under 
the employer by whom he is immediately employed.

</section>

<section><tid>1272891</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the principal is liable to pay compensation under this 
section, he shall be entitled to be indemnified by the contractor, 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or any other person from whom the workman could have recovered 
compensation and where a contractor who is himself a principal is 
liable to pay compensation or to indemnify a principal under this 
section he shall be entitled to be indemnified by any person standing 
to him in the relation of a contractor from whom the workman could 
have recovered compensation,] and all questions as to the right to and 
the amount of any such indemnity shall, in default of agreement, be 
settled by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1597391</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall be construed as preventing a 
workman from recovering compensation from the contractor instead of 
the principal.

</section>

<section><tid>1996963</tid>
<number>4</number>This section shall not apply in any case where the accident 
occurred elsewhere than on, in or about the premises on which the 
principal has undertaken or usually undertakes, as the case may be, to 
execute the work or which are otherwise under his control or 
management.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1813508</tid>
<number>13</number>Remedies of employer against stranger.- Where a workman has 
recovered compensation in respect of any injury caused under 
circumstances creating a legal liability of some person other than the 
person by whom the compensation was
<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 6. 
2. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 9.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


paid to pay damages in respect thereof, the person by whom the 
compensation was paid and any person who has been called on to pay an 
indemnity under section 12 shall be entitled to be indemnified by the 
person so liable to pay damages as aforesaid.



</article>



<article><tid>1367820</tid>
<number> 14</number> Insolvency of employer.-
<section><tid>1542349</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any employer has entered  
into a contract with any insurers in respect of any liability under 
this Act to any workman, then in the event of the employer becoming 
insolvent or making a composition or scheme of arrangement with his 
creditors or, if the employer is a company, in the event of the 
company having commenced to be wound up, the rights of the employer 
against the insurers as respects that liability shall, notwithstanding 
anything in any law for the time being in force relating to insolvency 
or the winding up of companies, be transferred to and vest in the 
workman, and upon any such transfer the insurers shall have the same 
rights and remedies and be subject to the same liabilities as if they 
were the employer, so, however, that the insurers shall not be under 
any greater liability to the workman than they would have been under 
to the employer.

</section>

<section><tid>1939010</tid>
<number>2</number>If the liability of the insurers to the workman is less than 
the liability of the employer to the workman, the workman may prove 
for the balance in the insolvency proceedings or liquidation.

</section>

<section><tid>869910</tid>
<number>3</number>Where in any case such as is referred to in sub- section (1) 
the contract of the employer with the insurers is void or voidable by 
reason of non- compliance on the part of the employer with any terms or 
conditions of the contract (other than a stipulation for the payment  
  of premia), the provisions of that sub- section shall apply as if the 
contract were not void or voidable, and the insurers shall be entitled 
to prove in the insolvency proceedings or liquidation for the amount 
paid to the workman:
Provided that the provisions of this sub- section shall not apply 
in any case in which the workman fails to give notice to the insurers 
of the happening of the accident and of any resulting disablement as 
soon as practicable after he becomes aware of the institution of the 
insolvency or liquidation proceedings.


</section>

<section><tid>429372</tid>
<number>4</number>There shall be deemed to be included among the debts which 
under section 49 of the Presidency- towns Insolvency Act, <year>1909</year> (3 of  
  <year>1909</year>), or under section 61 of the Provincial Insolvency Act, <year>1920</year> (5  
  of <year>1920</year>), or under section 230 of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7  
  of <year>1913</year>), are in the distribution of the property of an insolvent or 
in the distribution of the assets
<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of a company being wound up to be paid in priority to all other debts, 
the amount due in respect of any compensation the liability where for 
accrued before the date of the order of adjudication of the insolvent 
or the date of the commencement of the winding up, as the case may be, 
and those Acts shall have effect accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>1448838</tid>
<number>5</number>Where the compensation is a half- monthly payment, the amount 
due in respect thereof shall, for the purposes of this section, be 
taken to be the amount of the lump sum for which the half- monthly 
payment could, if redeemable, be redeemed if application were made for 
that purpose under section 7, and a certificate of the Commissioner as 
to the amount of such sum shall be conclusive proof thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>736614</tid>
<number>6</number>The provisions of sub- section (4) shall apply in the case of 
any amount for which an insurer is entitled to prove under sub- section 
 (3), but otherwise those provisions shall not apply where the 
insolvent or the company being wound up has entered into such a 
contract with insurers as is referred to in sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1056255</tid>
<number>7</number>This section shall not apply where a company is wound up 
voluntarily merely for the purposes of reconstruction or of 
amalgamation with another company.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>681330</tid>
<number>14A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Compensation to be first charge on assets transferred by 
employer.- Where an employer transfers his assets before any amount due 
in respect of any compensation, the liability wherefor accrued before 
the date of the transfer, has been paid, such amount shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being 
in force, be a first charge on that part of the assets so transferred 
as consists of immovable property.]


</article>



<article><tid>840664</tid>
<number> 15</number> Special provisions relating to masters and seamen.- This Act 
shall apply in the case of workmen who are masters of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> ships
or seamen subject to the following modifications, namely:--

<section><tid>496038</tid>
<number>1</number>The notice of the accident and the claim for compensation 
may, except where the person injured is the master of the ship, be 
served on the master of the ship as if he were the employer, but where 
the accident happened and the disablement commenced on board the ship 
it shall not be necessary for any seaman to give any notice of the 
accident.

</section>

<section><tid>1478047</tid>
<number>2</number>In the case of the death of a master or seaman, the claim for 
compensation shall be made within <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> one year] after the news of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
2. The word" registered" rep. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 10. 
3. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 11, for" six months" (w. e. f. 1- 6-  
  <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the death has been received by the claimant or, where the ship has 
been or is deemed to have been lost with all hands, within eighteen 
months of the date on which the ship was, or is deemed to have been, 
so lost:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that the Commissioner may entertain any claim to 
compensation in any case notwithstanding that the claim has not been 
preferred in due time as provided in this sub- section, if he is 
satisfied that the failure so to prefer the claim was due to 
sufficient cause.]


</section>

<section><tid>252263</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an injured master or seaman is discharged or left 
behind in any part of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India or] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in any foreign country] any 
depositions taken by any Judge or Magistrate in that part or by any 
Consular Officer in the foreign country and transmitted by the person 
by whom they are taken to the Central Government or any State 
Government shall, in any proceedings for enforcing the claim, be 
admissible in evidence--

<subsection><tid>1118692</tid>
<number>a</number>if the deposition is authenticated by the signature of 
the Judge, Magistrate or Consular Officer before whom 
it is made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1064971</tid>
<number>b</number>if the defendant or the person accused, as the case may 
be, had an opportunity by himself or his agent to 
crossexamine the witness; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>330376</tid>
<number>c</number>if the deposition was made in the course of a criminal 
proceeding, on proof that the deposition was made in 
the presence of the person accused;
and it shall not be necessary in any case to prove the signature or 
official character of the person appearing to have signed any such 
deposition and a certificate by such person that the defendant or the 
person accused had an opportunity of cross- examining the witness and 
that the deposition if made in a criminal proceeding was made in the 
presence of the person accused shall, unless the contrary is proved, 
be sufficient evidence that he had that opportunity and that it was so 
made.

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1401247</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> No <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> half- monthly payment] shall be payable in respect of 
the period during which the owner of the ship is, under any law
<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Added by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 11 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
2. Ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1984</year>, s. 4. (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1984</year>) 
4. The original cl. (4) rep., and the original cl. (5) renumbered 
 (4) by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 7. 
5. Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1924</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, for" monthly payment".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


in force for the time being <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> relating to merchant shipping, liable 
to defray the expenses of maintenance of the injured master or seaman.


</section>

<section><tid>709827</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> No compensation shall be payable under this Act in respect 
of any injury in respect of which provision is made for payment of a 
gratuity, allowance or pension under the War Pensions and Detention 
Allowances (Mercantile Marine, etc.) Scheme, <year>1939</year>, or the War Pensions 
and Detention Allowances (Indian Seamen, etc.) Scheme, <year>1941</year>, made 
under the Pensions (Navy, Army, Air Force and Mercantile Marine) Act, 
 <year>1939</year> (2 and 3 Geo. 6, c. 83), or under the War Pensions and Detention 
Allowances (Indian Seamen) Scheme <year>1942</year>, made by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1747694</tid>
<number>6</number>Failure to give a notice or make a claim or commence 
proceedings within the time required by this Act shall not be a bar to 
the maintenance of proceedings under this Act in respect of any 
personal injury, if--

<subsection><tid>435917</tid>
<number>a</number>an application has been made for payment in respect of 
that injury under any of the schemes referred to in the 
preceding clause, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>163507</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Government certifies that the said application 
was made in the reasonable belief that the injury was 
one in respect of which the scheme under which the 
application was made makes provision for payments, and 
that the application was rejected or that payments made 
in pursuance of the application were discontinued on 
the ground that the injury was not such an injury, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1063672</tid>
<number>c</number>the proceedings under this Act are commenced within one 
month from the date on which the said certificate of 
the State Government was furnished to the person 
commencing the proceedings.]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>527161</tid>
<number>16</number>Returns as to compensation.- The <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> State Government] may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that every person 
employing workmen, or that any specified class of such persons, shall 
send at such time and in such form and to such authority, as may be 
specified in the notification, a correct return specifying the number 
of injuries in respect of which
<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" in Part A States and Part C States" omitted by Act 3 
of <year>1951</year>, s. 3, and Sch. 
2. Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1942</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 3- 9- <year>1939</year>), for the former 
cl. which had been ins. by Act 42 of <year>1939</year>, s. 2 with effect from 
the same date. 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" G. G. in C.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


compensation has been paid by the employer during the previous year 
and the amount of such compensation together with such other 
particulars as to the compensation as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may 
direct.



</article>



<article><tid>1627014</tid>
<number>17</number>Contracting out.- Any contract or agreement whether made 
before or after the commencement of this Act, whereby a workman 
relinquishes any right of compensation from the employer for personal 
injury arising out of or in the course of the employment, shall be 
null and void in so far as it purports to remove or reduce the 
liability of any person to pay compensation under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>115373</tid>
<number>18</number>[ Proof of age.]- Rep. by the Workmen' s Compensation 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1959</year> (8 of <year>1959</year>), s. 12 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>982402</tid>
<number> 18A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Penalties.-
<section><tid>794455</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever-- 

<subsection><tid>513395</tid>
<number>a</number>fails to maintain a notice- book which he is required to 
maintain under sub- section (3) of section 10, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1681383</tid>
<number>b</number>fails to send to the Commissioner a statement which he 
is required to send under sub- section (1) of section 
10A, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1821911</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to send a report which he is required to send 
under section 10B, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>288271</tid>
<number>d</number>fails to make a return which he is required to make 
under section 16,
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> five hundred] 
rupees.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>860323</tid>
<number>2</number>No prosecution under this section shall be instituted except 
by or with the previous sanction of a Commissioner, and no Court shall 
take cognizance of any offence under this section, unless complaint 
thereof is made <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> within six months of the date on which the alleged 
commission of the offence came to the knowledge of the Commissioner].]
CHAP

COMMISSIONERS

CHAPTER III

COMMISSIONERS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1945389</tid>
<number> 19</number> Reference to Commissioners.-
<section><tid>903228</tid>
<number>1</number>If any question arises in any  
proceedings under this Act as to the liability of any person to pay 
compensation (including any 
<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" G. G. in C.". 
2. S. 18A ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 11. 
3. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 13, for" one hundred" (w. e. f. 1- 6-  
  <year>1959</year>). 
4. Subs. by Act 64 of <year>1962</year>, s. 6, for certain words (w. e. f. 1- 2-  
  <year>1963</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  question as to whether a person injured is or is not a workman) or as 
to the amount or duration of compensation (including any question as  
  to the nature or extent of disablement), the question shall, in 
default of agreement, be settled by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a Commissioner].


</section>

<section><tid>428838</tid>
<number>2</number>No Civil Court shall have jurisdiction to settle, decide or 
deal with any question which is by or under this Act required to be 
settled, decided or dealt with by a Commissioner or to enforce any 
liability incurred under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>385099</tid>
<number> 20</number> Appointment of Commissioners.-
<section><tid>1419709</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint any person to be a 
Commissioner for Workmen' s Compensation for such <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> area as may be 
specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1716228</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Where more than one Commissioner has been appointed for 
any <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> area, the State Government may, by general or special order, 
regulate the distribution of business between them.]

</section>

<section><tid>36575</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>] Any Commissioner may, for the purpose of deciding any 
matter referred to him for decision under this Act, choose one or more 
persons possessing special knowledge of any matter relevant to the 
matter under inquiry to assist him in holding the inquiry.

</section>

<section><tid>200962</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>] Every Commissioner shall be deemed to be a public servant 
within the meaning of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>953132</tid>
<number> 21</number> Venue of procedings and transfer.-
<section><tid>1776481</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any matter is  
under this Act to be done by or before a Commissioner, the same shall, 
subject to the provisions of this Act and to any rules made hereunder, 
be done by or before <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> a Commissioner] for the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> area in which the 
accident took place which resulted in the injury:
Provided that, where the workman is the master of a <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> ship or 
a seaman, any such matter may be done by or before <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> a Commissioner] 
for the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> area in which the owner or agent of the ship resides or 
carries on business.


</section>

<section><tid>804778</tid>
<number>2</number>If a Commissioner is satisfied <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> that any matter arising out 
of any proceedings pending before him] can be more conveniently dealt 
with by any other Commissioner, whether in the same State
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 12, for" the Commissioner". 
2. The word" local" omitted by Act 64 of <year>1962</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 1- 2-  
  <year>1963</year>). 
3. Sub- section (2) ins., and the original sub- sections (2) and (3) 
renumbered (3) and (4) by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 13. 
4. Subs. by s. 14, ibid., for" the Commissioner". 
5. The word" registered" omitted by s. 14, ibid. 
6. Subs. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 9, for" by any party to any 
proceedings under this Act pending before him that such matter".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


or not, he may subject to rules made under this Act, order such matter 
to be transferred to such other Commissioner either for report or for 
disposal, and, if he does so, shall forthwith transmit to such other 
Commissioner all documents relevant for the decision of such matter 
and, where the matter is transferred for disposal, shall also transmit 
in the prescribed manner any money remaining in his hands or invested 
by him for the benefit of any party to the proceedings:

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that the Commissioner shall not, where any party to 
the proceedings has appeared before him, make any order of transfer 
relating to the distribution among dependants of a lump sum without 
giving such party an opportunity of being heard:]

Provided <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> further] that no matter other than a matter relating 
to the actual payment to a workman or the distribution among 
dependants of a lump sum shall be transferred for disposal under this 
sub- section to a Commissioner in the same State save with the previous 
sanction of the State Government or to a Commissioner in another State 
save with the previous sanction of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the State Government of that 
State], unless all the parties to the proceedings agree to the 
transfer.


</section>

<section><tid>241339</tid>
<number>3</number>The commissioner to whom any matter is so transferred shall, 
subject to rules made under this Act, inquire thereinto and, if the 
matter was transferred for report, return his report thereon or, if 
the matter was transferred for disposal, continue the proceedings as 
if they had originally commenced before him.

</section>

<section><tid>1979247</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of a report from a Commissioner to whom any matter 
has been transferred for report under sub- section (2), the 
Commissioner by whom it was referred shall decide the matter referred 
in conformity with such report.

</section>

<section><tid>144681</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The State Government may transfer any matter from any 
Commissioner appointed by it to any other commissioner appointed by 
it.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>380348</tid>
<number> 22</number> Form of application.-
<section><tid>10004</tid>
<number>1</number>No application for the settlement of  
any matter by a Commissioner, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> other than an application by a 
dependant or dependants for compensation] shall be made unless and 
until some question has arisen between the parties in connection 
therewith which they have been unable to settle by agreement.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 9 of <year>1938</year>, s. 9. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" the G. G. in C.". 
3. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 14. 
4. Ins. by s. 15, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>424621</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> An application to a Commissioner] may be made in such form 
and shall be accompanied by such fee, if any, as may be prescribed, 
and shall contain, in addition to any particulars which may be 
prescribed, the following particulars, namely:--

<subsection><tid>992827</tid>
<number>a</number>a concise statement of the circumstances in which the 
application is made and the relief or order which the 
applicant claims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>130855</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a claim for compensation against an 
employer, the date of service of notice of the accident 
on the employer and, if such notice has not been served 
or has not been served in due time, the reason for such 
omission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>973650</tid>
<number>c</number>the names and addresses of the parties; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1696368</tid>
<number>d</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> except in the case of an application by dependants 
for compensation] a concise statement of the matters on 
which agreement has and <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> of] those on which agreement 
has not been come to.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>919503</tid>
<number>3</number>If the applicant is illiterate or for any other reason is 
unable to furnish the required information in writing, the application 
shall, if the applicant so desires, be prepared under the direction of 
the Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>165102</tid>
<number> 22A</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Power of Commissioner to require further deposit in cases 
of fatal accident.-
<section><tid>1150998</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any sum has been deposited by an employer  
as compensation payable in respect of a workman whose injury has 
resulted in death, and in the opinion of the Commissioner such sum is 
insufficient, the Commissioner may, by notice in writing stating his 
reasons, call upon the employer to show cause why he should not make a 
further deposit within such time as may be stated in the notice.

</section>

<section><tid>164688</tid>
<number>2</number>If the employer fails to show cause to the satisfaction of 
the Commissioner, the Commissioner may make an award determining the 
total amount payable, and requiring the employer to deposit the 
deficiency.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1207550</tid>
<number>23</number>Powers and procedure of Commissioners.- The Commissioner shall 
have all the powers of a Civil Court under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), for the purpose of taking evidence on 
oath (which such Commissioner is hereby empowered 
<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 15, for" where any such question has 
arisen, the application". 
2. Ins. by s. 15, ibid. 
3. Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1925</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, for" on". 
4. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 16.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


  to impose) and of enforcing the attendance of witnesses and compelling 
the production of documents and material objects, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and the 
Commissioner shall be deemed to be a Civil Court for all the purposes 
of section 195 and of Chapter XXXV of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
 <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>)].



</article>



<article><tid>43381</tid>
<number> 24</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Appearance of parties.- Any appearance, application or act 
required to be made or done by any person before or to a Commissioner 
 (other than an appearance of a party which is required for the purpose  
  of his examination as a witness) may be made or done on behalf of such 
person by a legal practitioner or by an official of an Insurance 
Company or a registered Trade Union or by an Inspector appointed under 
sub- section
<section><tid>719452</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 8 of the Factories Act, <year>1948</year> (63 of <year>1948</year>)  
or under sub- section (1) of section 5 of the Mines Act, <year>1952</year> (35 of  
  <year>1952</year>), or by any other officer specified by the State Government in 
this behalf, authorised in writing by such person, or, with the 
permission of the Commissioner, by any other person so authorised.] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1260677</tid>
<number>25</number>Method of recording evidence.- The Commissioner shall make a 
brief memorandum of the substance of the evidence of every witness as 
the examination of the witness proceeds, and such memorandum shall be 
written and signed by the Commissioner with his own hand and shall 
form part of the record:
Provided that, if the Commissioner is prevented from making such 
memorandum, he shall record the reason of his inability to do so and 
shall cause such memorandum to be made in writing from his dictation 
and shall sign the same, and such memorandum shall form part of the 
record:

Provided further that the evidence of any medical witness shall 
be taken down as nearly as may be word for word.



</article>



<article><tid>1017672</tid>
<number>26</number>Costs.- All costs, incidental to any proceedings before a 
Commissioner, shall, subject to rules made under this Act, be in the 
discretion of the Commissioner.


</article>



<article><tid>1637849</tid>
<number>27</number>Power to submit cases.- A Commissioner may, if he thinks fit, 
submit any question of law for the decision of the High Court and, if 
he does so, shall decide the question in conformity with such 
decision.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 5. 
2. Subs. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 14, for the former section (w. e. f. 1-  
  6- <year>1959</year>). 
3. In the application of the Act to Bengal, new ss. 24A and 24B have 
been ins here by Ben. Act 6 of <year>1942</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1104271</tid>
<number> 28</number> Registration of agreements.-
<section><tid>90101</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the amount of any lump  
sum payable as compensation has been settled by agreement, whether by 
way of redemption of a half- monthly payment or otherwise, or where any 
compensation has been so settled as being payable <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to a woman or a 
person under a legal disability] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> a memorandum thereof shall be 
sent by the employer to the Commissioner, who shall, on being satisf- 
ied as to its genuineness, record the memorandum in a register 
in the prescribed manner:
Provided that--


<subsection><tid>872259</tid>
<number>a</number>no such memorandum shall be recorded before seven days 
after communication by the Commissioner of notice to 
the parties concerned;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>214749</tid>
<number>c</number>the Commissioner may at any time rectify the register;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>718871</tid>
<number>d</number>where it appears to the Commissioner that an agreement 
as to the payment of a lump sum whether by way of 
redemption of a half- monthly payment or otherwise, or 
an agreement as to the amount of compensation payable 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to a woman or a person under a legal disability] 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> ought not to be registered by reason of the inade- 
quacy of the sum or amount, or by reason of the 
agreem agreement having been obtained by fraud or 
undue influence or other improper means, he may refuse 
to record the memorandum of the agreement <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and may 
make such order] including an order as to any sum 
already paid under the agreement, as he thinks just in 
the circumstances.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1468917</tid>
<number>2</number>An agreement for the payment of compensation which has been 
registered under sub- section (1) shall be enforceable under this Act 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Contract Act, <year>1872</year> 
 (9 of <year>1872</year>), or in any other law for the time being in force.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1746534</tid>
<number>29</number>Effect of failure to register agreement.- Where a memorandum 
of any agreement the registration of which is required by section 28, 
is not sent to the Commissioner as required by that section, the 
employer shall be liable to pay the full amount of compensation which 
he is liable to pay under the provisions of this Act, and 
notwithstanding anything contained in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 6, for certain words. 
2. The words" or to a dependant" rep. by Act 7 of <year>1924</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. II. 
3. Cl. (b) rep. by Act 5 of <year>1929</year>, s. 6. 
4. The words" or to any dependant" rep. by Act 7 of <year>1924</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. II. 
5. Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1924</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I, for" or may make such 
order".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the proviso to sub- section (1) of section 4, shall not, unless the 
Commissioner otherwise directs, be entitled to deduct more than half 
of any amount paid to the workmen by way of compensation whether under 
the agreement or otherwise.



</article>



<article><tid>307321</tid>
<number> 30</number> Appeals.-
<section><tid>1342622</tid>
<number>1</number>An appeal shall lie to the High Court from the  
following orders of a Commissioner, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1360095</tid>
<number>a</number>an order awarding as compensation a lump sum whether by 
way of redemption of a half- monthly payment or 
otherwise or disallowing a claim in full or in part for 
a lump sum;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>364986</tid>
<number>aa</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> an order awarding interest or penalty under section 
4A;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>927856</tid>
<number>b</number>an order refusing to allow redemption of a half- monthly 
payment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1900658</tid>
<number>c</number>an order providing for the distribution of compensation 
among the dependants of a deceased workman, or 
disallowing any claim of a person alleging himself to 
be such dependant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1149557</tid>
<number>d</number>an order allowing or disallowing any claim for the 
amount of an indemnity under the provisions of sub- 
section (2) of section 12; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>134099</tid>
<number>e</number>an order refusing to register a memorandum of agreement 
or registering the same or providing for the 
registration of the same subject to conditions:
Provided that no appeal shall lie against any order unless a 
substantial question of law is involved in the appeal and, in the case 
of an order other than an order such as is referred to in clause (b), 
unless the amount in dispute in the appeal is not less than three 
hundred rupees:

Provided, further, that no appeal shall lie in any case in which 
the parties have agreed to abide by the decision of the Commissioner, 
or in which the order of the Commissioner gives effect to an agreement 
come to by the parties:

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided further that no appeal by an employer under clause 
 (a) shall lie unless the memorandum of appeal is accompanied by a 
certificate by the Commissioner to the effect that the appellant has 
deposited with him the amount payable under the order appealed 
against.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 15 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 17.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1211173</tid>
<number>2</number>The period of limitation for an appeal under this section 
shall be sixty days.

</section>

<section><tid>16675</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of section 5 of the Indian Limitation Act, 
 <year>1908</year> (9 of <year>1908</year>), shall be applicable to appeals under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>660013</tid>
<number> 30A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Withholding of certain payments pending decision of 
appeal.- Where an employer makes an appeal under clause (a) of sub- 
section
<section><tid>1173595</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 30, the Commissioner may, and if so directed by  
the High Court shall, pending the decision of the appeal, withhold 
payment of any sum in deposit with him.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>335943</tid>
<number>31</number>Recovery.- The Commissioner may recover as an arrear of land- 
revenue any amount payable by any person under this Act, whether under 
an agreement for the payment of compensation or otherwise, and the 
Commissioner shall be deemed to be a public officer within the meaning 
of section 5 of the Revenue Recovery Act, <year>1890</year> (1 of <year>1890</year>). <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
CHAP

RULES

CHAPTER IV

RULES



</article>



<article><tid>1936732</tid>
<number> 32</number> Power of the State Government to make rules.-
<section><tid>623355</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> State  
Government] may make rules <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1087194</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>832006</tid>
<number>a</number>for prescribing the intervals at which and the 
conditions subject to which an application for review 
may be made under section 6 when not accompanied by a 
medical certificate;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>461543</tid>
<number>b</number>for prescribing the intervals at which and the 
conditions subject to which a workman may be required 
to submit himself for medical examination under sub- 
section (1) of section 11;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1479743</tid>
<number>c</number>for prescribing the procedure to be followed by 
Commissioners in the disposal of cases under this Act 
and by the parties in such cases;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 18. 
2. In the application of the Act to Bengal, a new s. 31A has been 
ins. here by the Bengal Touts Act, <year>1942</year> (Ben. 5 of <year>1942</year>), s. 12. 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C.". 
4. For the Workmen' s Compensation Rules, <year>1924</year>, see Gazette of India, 
<year>1924</year>, Pt. I, p. 586.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1427243</tid>
<number>d</number>for regulating the transfer of matters and cases from 
one Commissioner to another and the transfer of money 
in such cases;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>235669</tid>
<number>e</number>for prescribing the manner in which money in the hands 
of a Commissioner may be invested for the benefit of 
dependants of a deceased workman and for the transfer 
of money so invested from one Commissioner to another;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>647985</tid>
<number>f</number>for the representation in proceedings before 
Commissioners of parties who are minors or are unable 
to make an appearance; <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1460884</tid>
<number>g</number>for prescribing the form and manner in which memoranda 
of agreements shall be presented and registered;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>422854</tid>
<number>h</number>for the withholding by Commissioners, whether in whole 
or in part of half- monthly payments pending decision on 
applications for review of the same; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>391478</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for regulating the scales of costs which may be 
allowed in proceedings under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1182537</tid>
<number>j</number>for prescribing and determining the amount of the fees 
payable in respect of any proceedings before a 
Commissioner under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>294466</tid>
<number>k</number>for the maintenance by Commissioners of registers and 
records of proceedings before them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1400856</tid>
<number>l</number>for prescribing the classes of employers who shall 
maintain notice- books under sub- section (3) of section 
10, and the form of such notice- books;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1474803</tid>
<number>m</number>for prescribing the form of statement to be submitted by 
employers under section 10A; <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>54612</tid>
<number>n</number>for prescribing the cases in which the report referred 
to in section 10B may be sent to an authority other 
than the Commissioner;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1698753</tid>
<number>o</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> for prescribing abstracts of this Act and requiring 
the employers to display notices containing such 
abstracts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>809538</tid>
<number>p</number>for prescribing the manner in which diseases specified 
as occupational diseases may be diagnosed;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>43</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>In the application of the Act of Bengal, new clauses (ff), (ff 1) 
and (ff 2) have been ins. here by Ben. Act 6 of <year>1942</year>, s. 5. 
2. The word" and" at the end of cl. (h) and the original cl. (i) 
rep., and the new cls. (i) to (n), which were the same as cls. 
 (a) to (f) of s. 33, ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
3. The word" and" omitted by Act 58 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II. 
4. Ins. by Act 8 of <year>1959</year>, s. 16 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1959</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1231124</tid>
<number>q</number>for prescribing the manner in which diseases may be 
certified for any of the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1508309</tid>
<number>r</number>for prescribing the manner in which, and the standards 
by which, incapacity may be assessed.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>600260</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1509626</tid>
<number>33</number>[ Power of Local Government to make rules.] Rep. by the A. O. 
<year>1937</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>494102</tid>
<number> 34</number> Publication of rules.-
<section><tid>1128086</tid>
<number>1</number>The power to make rules conferred  
by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> section 32] shall be subject to the condition of the rules being 
made after previous publication.

</section>

<section><tid>26990</tid>
<number>2</number>The date to be specified in accordance with clause (3) of 
section 23 of the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>), as that 
after which a draft of rules proposed to be made under section 32 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
will be taken into consideration, shall not be less than three months 
from the date on which the draft of the proposed rules was published 
for general information.

</section>

<section><tid>1034061</tid>
<number>3</number>Rules so made shall be published in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Official Gazette 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and, on such publication, shall have effect as if enacted in this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1335736</tid>
<number> 35</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Rules to give effect to arrangements with other countries 
for the transfer of money paid as compensation.- <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>
<section><tid>922602</tid>
<number>1</number>] The Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for the transfer <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> to any foreign country] of money <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> deposited 
with] a Commissioner under this Act <footcitenum>11</footcitenum> which has been awarded to or 
may be due to], any person residing or about to reside in <footcitenum>9</footcitenum> such 
foreign country] and for
<pagefootnote><pagenum>44</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" sections 32 and 33". 
3. The words and figures" or section 33" rep., ibid. 
4. The words" the Gazette of India or" rep., ibid. 
5. The words" as the case may be" rep., ibid. 
6. Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1933</year>, s. 20. 
7. The original s. 35 renumbered as sub- section (1) of that section 
by Act 7 of <year>1937</year>, s. 2. 
8. The words" to any Part B State or" ins. by the A. O. <year>1948</year>, 
omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
9. Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1984</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1984</year>). 
10. Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1937</year>, s. 2, for" paid to". 
11. Subs. by 2, ibid., for" for the benefit of".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the receipt <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> distribution] and administration in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any State] of 
any money <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> deposited] under the law relating to workmen' s 
compensation <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> in any foreign country], <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> which has been awarded 
to, or may be due to] any person residing or about to reside in <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any 
State]:]

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that no sum deposited under this Act in respect of 
fatal accidents shall be so transferred without the consent of the 
employer concerned until the Commissioner receiving the sum has passed 
orders determining its distribution and apportionment under the 
provisions of sub- sections (4) and (5) of section 8.


</section>

<section><tid>1288086</tid>
<number>2</number>Where money deposited with a Commissioner has been so 
transferred in accordance with the rules made under this section, the 
provisions elsewhere contained in this Act regarding distribution by 
the Commissioner of compensation deposited with him shall cease to 
apply in respect of any such money.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>423254</tid>
<number>36</number><footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Rules made by Central Government to be laid before 
Parliament.- Every rule made under this Act by the Central Government 
shall be laid as soon as may be after if is made before each House of 
Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of that the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so however that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>45</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 7 of <year>1937</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" a Part A State or 
Part C State". 
3. Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1937</year>, s. 2, for" awarded". 
4. Of the words" in any Part B State or" ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, 
first five words were omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., 
and the word" or" was omitted by Act 36 of <year>1957</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
II. 
5. Subs. by act 22 of <year>1984</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1984</year>). 
6. Subs. by Act 7 of <year>1937</year>, s. 2, for" and applicable for the benefit 
of". 
7. Ins. by Act 64 of <year>1962</year>, s. 8 (w. e. f. 1- 2- <year>1976</year>). 
8. Subs. by Act 65 of <year>1976</year>, s. 3, for certain words (w. e. f. 21- 5-  
  <year>1976</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>