<act><title>
THE WORKING 
    JOURNALISTS AND OTHER
    NEWSPAPER 
    EMPLOYEES TRIBUNAL RULES, 19791</title> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title.—These 
    rules may be called the Working Journalists and Other Newspaper Employees 
    Tribunal Rules, 1979. 
 





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Calling of parties.—A 
    Tribunal constituted under section 13AA or, as the case may be, under 
    section 13DD of the Working Journalists and Other Newspaper Employees 
    (Conditions of Service) and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1955 (45 of 1955), 
    shall subject to the provisions of rule 3 call at such date, time and place, 
    as may be appointed by it, from time to time, the parties representing 
    employers in a newspaper establishment and the parties representing the 
    working journalists, or, as the case may be, the non-journalist newspaper 
    employees in such newspaper establishment.
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> Notice.—Not 
    less than ten days before the date fixed by the Tribunal for calling the 
    parties, a notice containing the date, time and place of the meeting, 
    together with a list of business to be conducted at the meeting, shall be 
    sent to both the parties referred to in rule 2 by registered post by an 
    officer authorised by the Tribunal in this behalf. 
 


  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Proceedings before the Tribunal.—The 
    proceedings before the Tribunal shall ordinarily be open to the public:
 


    Provided that the Tribunal may, at any stage, direct that any witness shall 
    be examined, or its proceedings shall be held, in camera.  

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Summoning of witnesses and production of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Tribunal may summon any person to appear as a witness in the course of 
    any inquiry. Such summons may require the witness to appear before it on a 
    date specified therein and to produce any books, papers or other documents 
    and information in his possession or under his control relating in any 
    manner to the inquiry. 
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A summons under sub-rule (1) may be addressed to an individual or an 
    organisation of employers or a trade union of working jounalists or, as the 
    case may be, of non-journalist newspaper employees, or other workmen as the 
    tribunal may think fit.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> A summons under this rule may be served—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>   in the case of an individual, by being delivered or sent to him by 
    registered post; and  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>   in the case of an organisation or, as the case may be, trade union, 
    referred to in sub-rule (2), by being delivered or sent by registered post 
    to the Secretary or other principal officer of the organisation or trade 
    union, as the case may be.  

  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>6</number> Expenses of witnesses.—Every 
    person who is summoned and appears beofre the Tribunal shall be paid by the 
    Tribunal such sum of money as appears to the Tribunal to be sufficient to 
    defray the travelling and other expenses incurred by the person so summoned 
    in passing to and from the place where he is required to attend. 
 


  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>