<act><tid>1809283</tid>
<title>THE SEAWARD ARTILERY PRACTICE ACT, <year>1949</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum></title>

ACT NO. 8 OF <year>1949</year> 
[ 17th February, <year>1949</year>.]
An Act to provide facilities for carrying out seaward artillery 
practice.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide facilities for carrying out 
seaward artillery practice;

It is hereby enacted as follows:-




<article><tid>1639254</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and application.
<section><tid>131563</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Seaward Artillery Practice Act, <year>1949</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>304491</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to all the State <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> which have a sea coast, and 
applies also to, and to persons on, any vessel which is registered in 
India or which belongs to any person domiciled in India, wherever it 
may be.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>768703</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation.
<section><tid>102962</tid>
<number>1</number>In this Act, unless there is anything  
repugnant in the subject or context,-

<subsection><tid>1247748</tid>
<number>a</number>" notified area" means any part of the area of the sea 
and the shores adjoining that area which may be specified in 
this behalf by notification under section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1013136</tid>
<number>b</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1750175</tid>
<number>c</number>" seaward artillery practice" means artillery practice 
or coastal firing towards the sea, whether within or beyond 
the territorial waters and includes air armament practice;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>793022</tid>
<number>d</number>" vessel" includes any ship, boat, country craft or any 
other description of vessel.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1624568</tid>
<number> 3</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Power of Central Government. to authorise seaward artillery 
practice.
<section><tid>252087</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the  
Official Gazette, authorise the carrying out of seaward artillery 
practice

<pagefootnote><pagenum>118</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been extended to- 
Goa, Daman and Diu with midifications by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. and comes into force in Pondicherry vide Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 
3 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1963</year>);

the whole of the Union territory of Lakshadweep vide Reg. 8 of 
<year>1965</year>, s.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1967</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" and Acceding States of India" rep. by the A. O. 
<year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Sub- section (2) was omitted by the Adaption of Laws (No. 3) 
Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1973</year>, s. 2, for the former s. 3 (w. e. f. 21- 1-  
  <year>1978</year>).








</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

over such area and during such period or periods as may be specified 
in the notification:

Provided that there shall be an interval of at least fourteen 
days between the date of publication of such notification in the 
Official Gazette and the date of carrying out of seaward artillery 
practice.


</section>

<section><tid>774321</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall, as soon as may be, after the 
publication of a notification under sub- section (1), cause the 
substance thereof to be published-

<subsection><tid>1028844</tid>
<number>a</number>in some newspaper circulating in, and in the language 
commonly understood in, the area specified in the noti- 
fication; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>993986</tid>
<number>b</number>in such other manner as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1269941</tid>
<number>3</number>If any question arises whether the substance of a 
notification under sub- section (1) was published as required by sub- 
section (2), a certificate by the Collector of the district in which 
the notified area is situate that the substance of the notification 
was so published, shall be conclusive.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1787186</tid>
<number>3A</number>Power to delegate. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the power to issue 
notifications under section 3 shall, subject to such conditions, if 
any, as may be specified in the notification, be exercisable also by 
such State Government as may be specified therein.]

</article>



<article><tid>350623</tid>
<number> 4</number> Powers exercisable for purpose of seaward artillery 
practice.
<section><tid>466047</tid>
<number>1</number>After a notification under sub- section (1) of section 3  
has been issued, such persons as are included in the forces engaged in 
seaward artillery practice may within the notified area and during the 
period or periods specified in the notification-

<subsection><tid>1062111</tid>
<number>a</number>give directions prohibiting or restricting the use of 
the notified area or any part thereof including the use of 
any part of the area of the sea by any vessel, and take such 
further measures as may be necessary to ensure that no 
unauthorised person enters, passes over or remains in the 
notified area or part thereof, as the case may be, during 
such practice, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>954536</tid>
<number>b</number>carry out seaward artillery practice with lethal 
missiles.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>630605</tid>
<number>2</number>The Officer Commanding the forces engaged in any such prac- 
tice may declare any portion of the notified area to be a danger zone, 
and thereupon the Collector shall, on application made to him by the 
Officer Commanding the forces engaged in the practice, prohibit the 
entry into and secure, with the assistance of the naval or military 
authorities concerned, the removal from such danger zone of any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>119</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

person, property or vessel during the times when the discharge of 
lethal missiles is taking place or there is danger to life or 
property.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1974593</tid>
<number>5</number>Compensation. Where by reason of a notification issued 
under section 3 the carrying out of seaward artillery practice is 
authorised in any notified area, compensation shall be payable for any 
damage to person or property or interference with rights or privileges 
arising from such practice, including expenses reasonably incurred in 
protecting person, property, rights or privileges.

</article>



<article><tid>1639791</tid>
<number> 6</number> Method of assessing compensation.
<section><tid>1905940</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of  
determining the amount of any compensation payable under section 5, 
the Collector of the district in which any notified area is situate 
shall depute one or more Revenue Officers to accompany the forces 
engaged in the practice.

</section>

<section><tid>172693</tid>
<number>2</number>The Revenue Officer so deputed shall consider all claims for 
compensation under section 5 and determine, on local investigation and 
after affording the claimant an opportunity of being heard, the amount 
of compensation, if any, which shall be awarded in each case; and 
shall disburse on the spot to the claimant compensation so determined 
as payable.

</section>

<section><tid>17440</tid>
<number>3</number>Compensation payable under sub- section (2) shall include 
compensation for the removal from any portion of a notified area 
declared to be a danger zone of any person, property or vessel and for 
any damage sustained in the course of any such removal. The compen- 
sation for removal will be disbursed on the spot at not less than the 
minimum prescribed rates before the removal is enforced.

</section>

<section><tid>1455839</tid>
<number>4</number>Any claimant dissatisfied with the refusal of the Revenue 
Officer to award him compensation or with the amount of compensation 
awarded to him by the Revenue Officer, may, at any time within one 
month of the communication to him of the decision of the Revenue 
Officer, prefer an appeal to the Collector against the decision.

</section>

<section><tid>1515525</tid>
<number>5</number>The decision of the Collector on such appeal shall be final 
and no suit shall lie in any Civil Court in respect of any matter 
decided by the Collector under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>91581</tid>
<number>6</number>No fee shall be charged in connection with any claim, 
notice, appeal, application or document filed before the Revenue 
Officer or the Collector under this section.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1056466</tid>
<number> 7</number> Offences. If within a notified area and during any period 
specified in a notification issued under sub- section
<section><tid>501306</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 3,  
any person-

<subsection><tid>1935302</tid>
<number>a</number>wilfully obstructs or interferes with the carrying out 
of seaward artillery practice, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>120</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1001901</tid>
<number>b</number>without due authority enters or remains in any camp, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1708755</tid>
<number>c</number>without due authority enters or remains in any area 
declared to be a danger zone at a time when entry thereto is 
prohibited, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>747326</tid>
<number>d</number>without due authority interferes with any flag or mark 
or target or buoy or any apparatus used for the purposes of 
seaward artillery practice,
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to twenty rupees or 
with imprisonment which may extend to fifteen days, or with both.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>971462</tid>
<number> 8</number> Protection of action taken under this act.
<section><tid>1909832</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
procesution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or any rules made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>524452</tid>
<number>2</number>Except as otherwise provided in this Act, no suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or the State 
Government in respect of any damage caused or likely to be caused by 
anything in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of 
this Act or any rules made thereunder.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>762165</tid>
<number> 9</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>985313</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for giving effect to 
the provisions of this Act and different rules may be made for 
different State or for different areas thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>821189</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>143938</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which the substance of a notification 
under section 3 may be published;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1442489</tid>
<number>b</number>regulating the use under this Act of the notified area 
for seaward artillery practice in such manner as to secure 
the public against danger, and to enable the practice to be 
carried out with the minimum inconvenience to the inhabitants 
of the area affected;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>153466</tid>
<number>c</number>the minimum rates at which compensation shall be 
payable under sub- section (3) of section 6, and generally 
regarding the making of claims for compensation, the 
procedure to be followed by the authorities granting the 
compensation, the expeditious settlement of claims and the 
filing of appeals from original awards of compensation;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>120A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1973</year>, s. 3, for the former s. 9 (w. e. f. 21- 1-  
  <year>1978</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1096714</tid>
<number>d</number>the principles to be followed in assessing the amount of 
compensation to be awarded under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>810794</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1981818</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.].


</section>

</article>



 </act>