<act><tid>806295</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN DIVORCE ACT, <year>1869</year></title>

ACT No. 4 OF <year>1869</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 26th February, <year>1869</year>.]

An Act to amend the law relating to Divorce and Matrimonial 
Causes <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to amend the law relating to 
the divorce of persons professing the Christian religion, and to 
confer upon certain Courts jurisdiction in matters matrimonial; it is 
hereby enacted as follows:-

I.- PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1269822</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. Commencement of Act.- This Act may be called 
the Indian Divorce Act, and shall come into operation on the first 
day of April, <year>1869</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1730045</tid>
<number>2</number>Extent of Act.- <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> This Act extends to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the whole of 
India <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> except the State of Jammu and Kashmir]].]
Extent of power to rant relief generally,

Extent of power to grant relief generally,- <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Nothing hereinafter 
contained shall authorise any Court to grant any relief under this Act 
except where the petitioner <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> or respondent] professes the Christian 
religion,

and to make decrees of dissolution,

and to make decrees of dissolution,- or to make decrees of 
dissolution of marriage except where the parties to the marriage are 
domiciled in India at the time when the petition is presented,

or of nullity.

or of nullity.- or to make decrees of nullity of marriage except 
where the marriage has been solemnized in India and the petitioner is 
resident in India at the time of presenting the petition,

or to grant any relief under this Act, other than a decree of 
dissolution of marriage or of nullity of marriage, except where the 
petitioner resides in India at the time of presenting the petition.]



</article>



<article><tid>25919</tid>
<number> 3</number> Interpretation- clause.- In this Act, unless there be 
something repugnant in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1736163</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>" High Court".-" High Court" means with reference to any 
area:

<subsection><tid>496135</tid>
<number>a</number>in a State, the High Court for that State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1289490</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>9</footcitenum> in Delhi, the High Court of Delhi;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1169907</tid>
<number>bb</number>in Himachal Pradesh, the High Court of Punjab and Haryana 
up to and inclusive of the 30th April, <year>1967</year> and the High Court of 
Delhi thereafter;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1135562</tid>
<number>c</number>in Manipur and Tripura, the High Court of Assam;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1181724</tid>
<number>d</number>in the Andaman and Nicobar Islands, the High Court at 
Calcutta;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1279473</tid>
<number>e</number>in <footcitenum>10</footcitenum> Lakshadweep], the High Court of Kerala;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>322572</tid>
<number>ee</number><footcitenum>11</footcitenum> in Chandigarh, the High Court of Punjab and Haryana;]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>54</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For Statement of Objects and Reasons, see Calcutta Gazette, <year>1863</year>, 
p. 173; for Report of Select Committee, see Gazette of India, <year>1869</year>, p. 
192; for Proceedings in Council, see Calcutta Gazette, <year>1862</year>, 
Supplement, p. 463, ibid., <year>1863</year>, Supplement, p. 43, and Gazette of 
India, <year>1869</year>, Supplement, p. 291.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" in India" omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by A. O. <year>1948</year>, for the original first para.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by A. O. <year>1950</year>, for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" except Part B 
States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 25 of <year>1926</year>, s. 2, for paras. 2, 3 and 4.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Ins. by Act 30 of <year>1927</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Subs. by A. O. (No. 2) <year>1956</year>, for the former.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Subs. by the Himachal Pradesh (Adaptation of Laws on State and  
  Concurrent Subjects) Order, <year>1968</year>. for sub- clause (b)  (w. e. f 1- 11-  
  <year>1966</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>10</number>Subs. by the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (Alteration  
  of Name) Adaptation of Laws Order, <year>1974</year>, for" the Laccadive, Minicoy 
and Amindivi Islands" (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1973</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>11</number>ins' by the Punjab Reorganisation (Chandigarh)  (Adaptation of  
  Laws on State and Concurrent Subjects) Order, <year>1968</year> (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1966</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

and in the case of any petition under this Act," High Court" means the 
High Court for the area where the husband and wife reside or last 
resided together:]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>142626</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" District Judge."-" District Judge" means a Judge of a 
principal civil court of original jurisdiction however designated:]

</section>

<section><tid>110936</tid>
<number>3</number>" District Court."-" District Court" means, in the case of any 
petition under this Act, the Court of the District Judge within the 
local limits of whose ordinary jurisdiction, or of whosejurisdiction 
under this Act, the husband and wife reside or last resided together:

</section>

<section><tid>1586215</tid>
<number>4</number>" Court."-" Court" means the High Court or the District Court, as 
the case may be:

</section>

<section><tid>1483957</tid>
<number>5</number>" Minor children."-" minor children" means, in the case of sons of 
Native fathers, boys who have not completed the age of sixteen years, 
and, in the case of daughters of Native fathers, girls who have not 
completed the age of thirteen years. In other cases it means 
unmarried children who have not completed the age of eighteen years:

</section>

<section><tid>16812</tid>
<number>6</number>" Incestuous adultery."-" incestuous adultery" means adultery 
committed by a husband with a woman with whom, if his wife were dead, 
he could not lawfully contract marriageby reason of her being within 
the prohibited degrees of consanguinity (whether natural or legal) or 
affinity:

</section>

<section><tid>603600</tid>
<number>7</number>" Bigamy with adultery."-" bigamy with adultery" means adultery with 
the same woman with whom the bigamy was committed:

</section>

<section><tid>1774958</tid>
<number>8</number>" Marriage with another woman."-" marriage with another woman" means 
marriage of any person, being married, to any other person, during the 
life of the former wife, whether the second marriage shall have taken 
place within <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] or elsewhere:

</section>

<section><tid>1769843</tid>
<number>9</number>" Desertion."-" desertion" implies an abandonment against the wish of 
the person charging it; and

</section>

<section><tid>1083966</tid>
<number>10</number>" Property."-" property" includes in the case of a wife any 
property to which she is entitled for an estate in remainder or 
reversion or as a trustee, executrix or administratrix; and the date 
of the death of the testator or intestate shall be deemed to be the 
time at which any such wife becomes entitled as executrix or 
administratrix.
JURISDICTION

II.- JURISDICTION

II.- JURISDICTION




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>861327</tid>
<number>4</number>Matrimonial jurisdiction of High Courts to be exercised 
subject to Act. Exception.- The jurisdiction now exercised by the High 
Courts in respect of divorce a mensa et toro, and in all other causes, 
suits and matters matrimonial, shall be exercised by such Courts and 
by the District Courts subject to the provisions in this Act 
contained, and not otherwise: except so far as relates to the 
granting of marriage- licenses, which may be granted as it this Act had 
not been passed.


</article>



<article><tid>1259490</tid>
<number>5</number>Enforcement of decrees or orders made heretofore by Supreme or 
High Court.- Any decree or order of the late Supreme Court of 
Judicature at Calcutta, Madras or Bombay sitting on the ecclesiastical 
side, or of any of the said High Courts sitting in the exercise of 
their matrimonial jurisdiction, respectively, in any cause or matter 
matrimonial, may be enforced and dealt with by the said High Courts, 
respectively, as herein after mentioned, in like manner as if such 
decree or order had been originally made under this Act by the Court 
so enforcing or dealing with the same.


</article>



<article><tid>1779859</tid>
<number>6</number>Pending suits.- All suits and proceedings in causes and matters 
matrimonial, which when this Act comes into operation are pending in 
any High Court, shall be dealt with and decided by such Court, so far 
as may be, as if they had been originally instituted therein under 
this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>823354</tid>
<number>7</number>Court to act on principles of English Divorce Court.- Subject 
to the provisions contained in this Act, the High Courts and District 
Courts shall, in all suits and proceedings hereunder, act and give 
relief on principles and rules which, in the opinion of the said 
Courts, are as nearly as may be conformable to the principles and 
rules on which the Court for Divorce and Matrimonial Causes in England 
for the time being acts and gives relief:
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that nothing in this section shall deprive the said 
Courts of jurisdiction in a case where the parties to a marriage 
professed the Christian religion at the time of the occurrence of the 
facts on which the claim to relief is founded.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>55</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former clause.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs,[ bid., for" the dominions of Her Majesty".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Added by Act 10 of <year>1912</year>, s. 2.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>525692</tid>
<number>8</number>Extraordinary jurisdiction of High Court.- The High Court 
may, whenever it thinks fit, remove and try and determine as a Court 
of original jurisdiction any suit or proceeding instituted under this 
Act in the Court of any District Judge within the limits of its 
jurisdiction under this Act.
Power to transfer suits.

Power to transfer suits.- The High Court may also withdraw any 
such suit or proceeding, and transfer it for trial or disposal to the 
Court of any other such District Judge.



</article>



<article><tid>918430</tid>
<number>9</number>Reference to High Court.- When any question of law or usage 
having the force of law arises at any point in the proceedings 
previous to the hearing of any suit under this Act by a District Court 
or at any subsequent stage of such suit, or in the execution of the 
decree therein or order thereon,
the Court may, either of its own motion or on the application of 
any of the parties, draw up a statement of the case and refer it, with 
the Court' s own opinion thereon, to the decision of the High Court.

If the question has arisen previous to or in the hearing, the 
District Court may either stay such proceedings, or proceed in the 
case pending such reference, and pass a decree contingent upon the 
opinion of the High Court upon it.

If a decree or order has been made, its execution shall be stayed 
until the receipt of the order of the High Court upon such reference.

DISSOLUTION OF MARRIAGE

III.- DISSOLUTION OF MARRIAGE

III.- DISSOLUTION OF MARRIAGE



</article>



<article><tid>1387951</tid>
<number>10</number>When husband may petition for dissolution.- Any husband may 
present a petition to the District Court or to the High Court, praying 
that his marriage may be dissolved on the ground that his wife has, 
since the solemnization thereof, been guilty of adultery.
When wife may petition for dissolution.

When wife may petition for dissolution.- Any wife may present a 
petition to the District Court or to the High Court, praying that her 
marriage may be dissolved on the ground that, since the solemnization 
thereof, her husband has exchanged his profession of Christianity for 
the profession of some other religion, and gone through a form of 
marriage with another woman;

or has been guilty of incestuous adultery,

or of bigamy with adultery,

or of marriage with another woman with adultery, or of rape, 
sodomy or bestiality,

or of adultery coupled with such cruelty as without adultery 
would have entitled her to a divorce a mensa et toro,

or of adultery coupled with desertion, without reasonable excuse, 
for two years or upwards.

Contents of petition.

Contents of petition.-- Every such petition shall state, as 
distinctly as the nature of the case permits, the facts on which the 
claim to have such marriage dissolved is founded.



</article>



<article><tid>478130</tid>
<number> 11</number> Adulterer to be co- respondent.- Upon any such petition 
presented by a husband, the petitioner shall make the alleged 
adulterer a co- respondent to the said petition, unless he is excused 
from so doing on one of the following grounds, to be allowed by the 
Court:-
<section><tid>1060217</tid>
<number>1</number>that the respondent is leading the life of a prostitute, and 
that the petitioner knows of no person with whom the adultery has been 
committed;

</section>

<section><tid>1806233</tid>
<number>2</number>that the name of the alleged adulterer is unknown to the 
petitioner, although he has made due efforts to discover it;

</section>

<section><tid>618563</tid>
<number>3</number>that the alleged adulterer is dead.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1712363</tid>
<number>12</number>Court to be satisfied of absence of collusion.- Upon any such 
petition for the dissolution of a marriage, the Court shall satisfy 
itself, so far as it reasonably can, not only as to the facts alleged, 
but also whether or not the petitioner has been in any manner 
accessory to, or conniving at, the going though of the said form of 
marriage, or the adultery, or has condoned the same, and shall also 
enquire into any countercharge which may be made against the 
petitioner.


</article>



<article><tid>1806277</tid>
<number>13</number>Dismissal of petition.- In case the Court, on the evidence in 
relation to any such petition, is satisfied that the petitioner' s case 
has not been proved, or is not satisfied that the alleged adultery has 
been committed,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>56</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or finds that the petitioner has, during the marriage, been 
accessory to, or conniving at, the going through of the said form of 
marriage, or the adultery of the other party to the marriage, or has 
condoned the adultery complained of,

or that the petition is presented or prosecuted in collusion with 
either of the respondents,

then and in any of the said cases the Court shall dismiss 
the petition.

When a petition is dismissed by a District Court under this 
section, the petitioner may, nevertheless, present a similar petition 
to the High Court.



</article>



<article><tid>1175464</tid>
<number>14</number>Power to Court to pronounce decree for dissolving marriage.- 
In case the Court is satisfied on the evidence that the case of the 
petitioner has been proved,
and does not find that the petitioner has been in any manner 
accessory to, or conniving at, the going through of the said form of 
marriage, or the adultery of the other party to the marriage, or has 
condoned the adultery complained of,

or that the petition is presented or prosecuted in collusion with 
either of the respondents,

the Court shall pronounce a decree declaring such marriage to be 
dissolved in the manner and subject to all the provisions and 
limitations in sections sixteen and seventeen made and declared:

Provided that the Court shall not be bound to pronounce such 
decree if it finds that the petitioner has, during the marriage, been 
guilty of adultery,

or if the petitioner has, in the opinion of the Court, been 
guilty of unreasonable delay in presenting or prosecuting such 
petition,

or of cruelty towards the other party to the marriage,

or of having deserted or wilfully separated himself or herself 
from the other party before the adultery complained of, and without 
reasonable excuse,

or of such wilful neglect or misconduct of or towards the other 
party as has conduced to the adultery.

Condonation.

Condonation.- No adultery shall be deemed to have been condoned 
within the meaning of this Act unless where conjugal cohabitation has 
been resumed or continued.



</article>



<article><tid>1821611</tid>
<number>15</number>Relief in case of opposition on certain grounds.- In any suit 
instituted for dissolution of marriage, if the respondent opposes the 
relief sought on the ground, in case of such a Suit instituted by a 
husband, of his adultery, cruelty, or desertion without reasonable 
excuse, or, in case of such a suit instituted by a wife, on the ground 
of her adultery and cruelty, the Court may in such suit give to the 
respondent, on his or her application, the same relief to which he or 
she would have been entitled in case he or she had presented a 
petition seeking such relief, and the respondent shall be competent to 
give evidence of or relating to such cruelty or desertion.


</article>



<article><tid>645462</tid>
<number>16</number>Decrees for dissolution to be nisi.- Every decree for a 
dissolution of marriage made by a High Court not being a confirmation 
of a decree of a District Court, shall, in the first instance, be a 
decree nisi, not to be made absolute till after the expiration of such 
time, not less than six months from the pronouncing thereof, as the 
High Court, by general or special order from time to time, directs.
Collusion.

Collusion.- During that period any person shall be at liberty, in 
such manner as the High Court by general or special order from time to 
time directs, to show cause why the said decree should not be made 
absolute by reason of the same having been obtained by collusion or by 
reason of material facts not being brought before the Court.

On cause being so shown, the Court shall deal with the case by 
making the decree absolute, or by reversing the decree nisi, or by 
requiring further inquiry, or otherwise as justice may demand.

The High Court may order the costs of Counsel and witnesses and 
otherwise arising from such cause being shown, to be paid by the 
parties or such one or more of them as it thinks fit, including a wife 
if she have separate property.

Whenever a decree nisi has been made, and the petitioner fails, 
within a reasonable time, to move to have such decree made absolute, 
the High Court may dismiss the suit.



</article>



<article><tid>1439858</tid>
<number>17</number>Confirmation of decree for dissolution by District Judge.- 
Every decree for a dissolution of marriage made by a District Judge 
shall be subject to confirmation by the High Court.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>57</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


Cases for confirmation of a decree' for dissolution of marriage 
shall be heard (where the number of the Judges of the High Court is  
  three or upwards) by a Court composed of three such Judges, and in 
case of difference the opinion of the majority shall prevail, or 
 (where the number of the Judges of the High Court is two) by a Court 
composed of such two Judges, and in case of difference the opinion of 
the Senior Judge shall prevail.

The High Court, if it thinks further enquiry or additional 
evidence to be necessary, may direct such enquiry to be made, or such 
evidence to be taken.

The result of such enquiry and the additional evidence shall be 
certified to the High Court by the District Judge, and the High Court 
shall thereupon make an order confirming the decree for dissolution of 
marriage, or such other order as to the Court seems fit:

Provided that no decree shall be confirmed under this section 
till after the expiration of such time, not less than six months from 
the pronouncing thereof, as the High Court by general or special order 
from time to time directs.

During the progress of the suit in the Court of the District 
Judge, any person suspecting that any parties to the suit are or have 
been acting in collusion for the purpose of obtaining a divorce, shall 
be at liberty, in such manner as the High Court by general or special 
order from time to time directs. to apply to the High Court to remove 
the suit under section eight, and the High Court shall thereupon, if 
it thinks fit, remove such suit and try and determine the same as a 
Court of original jurisdiction, and the provisions contained in 
section sixteen shall apply to every suit so removed: or it may direct 
the District Judge to take such steps in respect of the alleged 
collusion as may be necessary to enable him to make a decree in 
accordance with the justice of the case.



</article>



<article><tid>232260</tid>
<number>17A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Appointment of officer to exercise duties of King' s 
Proctor.- <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Government of the State within which any High Court 
exercises jurisdiction], may appoint an officer who shall, within the 
jurisdiction of the High Court in that State, have the like right of 
showing cause why a decree for the dissolution of a marriage should 
not be made absolute or should not be confirmed, as the case may be, 
as is exercisable in England by the King' s Proctor; and the said 
Government may make rules regulating the manner in which the right 
shall be exercised and all matters incidental to or consequential on 
any exercise of the right.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>]

NULLITY OF MARRIAGE

IV.- NULLITY OF MARRIAGE

IV.- NULLITY OF MARRIAGE



</article>



<article><tid>530436</tid>
<number>18</number>Petition for decree of nullity.- Any husband or wife may 
present a petition to the District Court or to the High Court, praying 
that his or her marriage may be declared null and void.


</article>



<article><tid>1852078</tid>
<number> 19</number> Grounds of decree.- Such decree may be made on any of the 
following grounds:-
<section><tid>1222630</tid>
<number>1</number>that the respondent was impotent at the time of the marriage 
and at the time of the institution of the suit;

</section>

<section><tid>1522899</tid>
<number>2</number>that the parties are within the prohibited degrees of 
consanguinity (whether natural or legal) or affinity;

</section>

<section><tid>691529</tid>
<number>3</number>that either party was a lunatic or idiot at the time of the 
marriage;

</section>

<section><tid>438967</tid>
<number>4</number>that the former husband or wife of either party was living 
at the time of the marriage, and the marriage with such former husband 
or wife was then in force.
Nothing in this section shall affect the jurisdiction of the High 
Court to make decrees of nullity of marriage on the ground that the 
consent of either party was obtained by force or fraud.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1795630</tid>
<number>20</number>Confirmation of District Judge' s decree.- Every decree of 
nullity of marriage made by a District Judge shall be subject to 
confirmation by the High Court, and the provisions of section 
seventeen, clauses one, two, three and four, shall, mutatis mutandis 
apply to such decrees.


</article>



<article><tid>1232831</tid>
<number>21</number>Children of annulled marriage.- Where a marriage is annulled 
on the ground that a former husband or wife was living, and it is 
adjudged that the subsequent marriage was contracted in good faith and 
with the full belief of the parties that the former husband or wife 
was dead, or when a marriage is annulled on the ground of insanity, 
children begotten before the decree is made shall be specified in the 
decree, and shall be entitled to succeed, in the same manner as 
legitimate children, to the estate of the parent who at the time of 
the marriage was competent to contract.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>58</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by A. O. <year>1937</year>, for the original s. 17A.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for certain words.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Second paragraph omitted by s. 3., ibid.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

JUDICIAL SEPARATION

V.- JUDICIAL SEPARATION

V.- JUDICIAL SEPARATION



</article>



<article><tid>1591892</tid>
<number>22</number>Bar to decree for divorce a mensa et toro; but judicial 
separation obtainable by husband or wife.- No decree shall hereafter be 
made for a divorce a mensa et toro, but the husband or wife may obtain 
a decree of judicial separation, on the ground of adultery, or 
cruelty, or desertion without reasonable excuse for two years or 
upwards, and such decree shall have the effect of a divorce a mensa et 
toro under the existing law, and such other legal effect as 
hereinafter mentioned.


</article>



<article><tid>1131574</tid>
<number>23</number>Application for separation made by petition.-- Application 
for judicial separation on any one of the grounds aforesaid, may be 
made by either husband or wife by petition to the District Court or 
the High Court; and the Court, on being satisfied of the truth of the 
statements made in such petition, and that there is no legal ground 
why the application should not be granted, may decree judicial 
separation accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1700286</tid>
<number>24</number>Separated wife deemed spinster with respect to after- acquired 
property.- In every case of a judicial separation under this Act, the 
wife shall, from the date of the sentence, and whilst the separation 
continues, be considered as unmarried with respect to property of 
every description which she may acquire, or which may come to or 
devolve upon her.
Such property may be disposed of by her in all respects as an 
unmarried woman, and on her decease the same shall, in case she dies 
intestate, go as the same would have gone if her husband had been then 
dead:

Provided that, if any such wife again cohabits with her husband, 
all such property as she may be entitled to when such cohabitation 
takes place shall be held to her separate use, subject, however, to 
any agreement in writing made between herself and her husband whilst 
separate.



</article>



<article><tid>1905460</tid>
<number>25</number>Separated wife deemed spinster for purposes of contract and 
suing.- In every case of a judicial separation under this Act, the wife 
shall, whilst so separated, be considered as an unmarried woman for 
the purposes of contract, and wrongs and injuries, and suing and being 
sued in any civil proceeding; and her husband shall not be liable in 
respect of any contract, act or costs entered into, done, omitted or 
incurred by her during the separation:
Provided that where, upon any such judicial separation, alimony 
has been decreed or ordered to be paid to the wife, and the same is 
not duly paid by the husband, he shall be liable for necessaries 
supplied for her use:

Provided also that nothing shall prevent the wife from joining, 
at any time during such separation, in the exercise of any joint power 
given to herself and her husband.

Reversal of Decree of Separation



</article>



<article><tid>798597</tid>
<number>26</number>Decree of Separation obtained during absence of husband or 
wife may be reversed.- Any husband or wife, upon the application of 
whose wife or husband, as the case may be, a decree of judicial 
separation has been pronounced, may, at any time thereafter, present a 
petition to the Court by which the decree was pronounced, praying for 
a reversal of such decree, on the ground that it was obtained in his 
or her absence, and that there was reasonable excuse for the alleged 
desertion, where desertion was the ground of such decree.
The Court may, on being satisfied of the truth of the allegations 
of such petition, reverse the decree accordingly; but such reversal 
shall not prejudice or affect the rights or remedies which any other 
person would have had, in case it had not been decreed, in respect of 
any debts, contracts, or acts of the wife incurred, entered into, or 
done between the times of the sentence of separation and of the 
reversal thereof.

PROTECTION- ORDERS

VI.- PROTECTION- ORDERS

VI.- PROTECTION- ORDERS



</article>



<article><tid>885520</tid>
<number>27</number>Deserted wife may apply to Court for protection.- Any wife to 
whom section 4 of the Indian Succession Act, <footcitenum>18651</footcitenum> (10 of <year>1865</year>), does 
not apply, may, when deserted by her husband, present a petition to 
the District Court or the High Court, at any time after such 
desertion, for an order to protect any property which she may have 
acquired or may acquire, and any property of which she may have become 
possessed or may become possessed after such desertion, against her 
husband or his creditors, or any person claiming under him.


</article>



<article><tid>933351</tid>
<number>28</number>Court may grant protection- order.- The Court, if satisfied of 
the fact of such desertion. and that the same was without reasonable 
excuse, and that the wife is maintaining herself by her
<pagefootnote><pagenum>59</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year> (39 of <year>1925</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


own industry or property, may make and give to the wife an order 
protecting her earnings and other property from her husband and all 
creditors and persons claiming under him. Every such order shall 
state the time at which the desertion commenced, and shall, as regards 
all persons dealing with the wife in reliance thereon, be conclusive 
as to such time.



</article>



<article><tid>1560689</tid>
<number>29</number>Discharge of variation of orders.-- The husband or any creditor 
of, or person claiming under him, may apply to the Court by which such 
order was made for the discharge or variation thereof, and the Court, 
if the desertion has ceased, or if for any other reason it thinks fit 
so to do, may discharge or vary the order accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1934045</tid>
<number>30</number>Liability of husband seizing wife' s property after notice of 
order.- If the husband, or any creditor of, or person claiming under, 
the husband, seizes or continues to hold any property of the wife 
after notice of any such order, he shall be liable, at the suit of the 
wife (which she is hereby empowered to bring), to return or deliver to 
her the specific property, and also to pay her a sum equal to double 
its value.


</article>



<article><tid>1639312</tid>
<number>31</number>Wife' s legal position during continuance of order.- So long as 
any such order of protection remains in force, the wife shall be and 
be deemed to have been, during such desertion of her, in the like 
position in all respects, with regard to property and contracts and 
suing and being sued, as she would be under this Act if she obtained a 
decree of judicial separation.
VII.

RESTITUTION OF CONJUGAL RIGHTS

VII.- RESTITUTION OF CONJUGAL RIGHTS



</article>



<article><tid>806725</tid>
<number>32</number>Petition for restitution of conjugal rights.- When either the 
husband or the wife has without reasonable excuse, withdrawn from the 
society of the other, either wife or husband may apply, by petition to 
the District Court or the High Court, for restitution of conjugal 
rights, and the Court, on being satisfied of the truth of the 
statements made in such petition, Hand that there is no legal ground 
why the application should not be granted, may decree restitution of 
conjugal rights accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1560260</tid>
<number>33</number>Answer to petition.- Nothing shall be pleaded in answer to a 
petition for restitution of conjugal rights, which would not be ground 
for a suit for judicial separation or for a decree of nullity of 
marriage.
VIII.

DAMAGES AND COSTS

VIII.- DAMAGES AND COSTS



</article>



<article><tid>1613930</tid>
<number>34</number>Husband may claim damages from adulterer.- Any husband may, 
either in a petition for dissolution of marriage or for judicial 
separation, or in a petition to the District Court or the High Court 
limited to such object only, claim damages from any person on the 
ground of his having committed adultery with the wife of such 
petitioner.
Such petition shall be served on the alleged adulterer and the 
wife, unless the Court dispenses with such service, or directs some 
other service to be substituted.

The damages to be recovered on any such petition shall be 
ascertained by the said Court, although the respondents or either of 
them may not appear.

After the decision has been given, the Court may direct in what 
manner such damages shall be paid or applied.



</article>



<article><tid>1443327</tid>
<number> 35</number> Power to order adulterer to pay costs.- Whenever in any 
petition presented by a husband the alleged adulterer has been made a 
co- respondent, and the adultery his began established, the Court may 
order the co- respondent to pay the whole or any part of the costs of 
the proceedings:
Provided that the co- respondent shall not be ordered to pay the 
petitioner' s costs-

<section><tid>672209</tid>
<number>1</number>if the respondent was, at the time of the adultery, living 
apart from her husband and leading the life of a prostitute, or

</section>

<section><tid>1162069</tid>
<number>2</number>if the co- respondent had not, at the time of the adultery, 
reason to believe the respondent to be a married woman.
Power to order litiguous intervenor to pay costs.

Power to order litigious intervenor to pay costs.- Whenever any 
application is made under section 17, the Court, if it thinks that the 
applicant had no grounds or no sufficient grounds for intervening, may 
order him to pay the whole or any part of the costs occasioned by the 
application.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>60</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

IX.

ALIMONY

IX.- ALIMONY




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1628324</tid>
<number>36</number>Alimony pendente lite.-- In any suit under this Act, whether 
it be instituted by a husband of a wife, and whether or not she has 
obtained an order of protection, the wife may present a petition for 
alimony pending the suit.
Such petition shall be served on the husband; and the Court, on 
being satisfied of the truth of the statements therein contained, may 
make such order on the husband for payment to the wife of alimony 
pending the suit as it may deem just:

Provided that alimony pending the suit shall in no case exceed 
one- fifth of the husband' s average net income for the three years next 
preceding the date of the order, and shall continue, in case of a 
decree for dissolution of marriage or of nullity of marriage, until 
the decree is made absolute or is confirmed, as the case may be.



</article>



<article><tid>1799408</tid>
<number>37</number>Power to order permanent alimony.- The High Court may, if it 
think fit, on any decree absolute declaring a marriage to be 
dissolved, or on any decree of judicial separation obtained by the 
wife,
and the District Judge may, if he thinks fit, on the confirmation 
of any decree of his declaring a marriage to be dissolved, or on any 
decree of judicial separation obtained by the wife,

order that the husband shall, to the satisfaction of the Court, 
secure to the wife such gross sum of money, or such annual sum of 
money for any term not exceeding her own life, as, having regard to 
her fortune (if any), to the ability of the husband, and to the 
conduct of the parties, it thinks reasonable; and for that purpose may 
cause a proper instrument to be executed by all necessary parties.

Power to order monthly or weekly payments.

Power to order monthly or weekly payments.-- In every such case 
the Court may make an order on the husband for payment to the wife of 
such monthly or weekly sums for her maintenance and support as the 
Court may think reasonable:

Provided that if the husband afterwards from any cause becomes 
unable to make such payments, it shall be lawful for the Court to 
discharge or modify the order, or temporarily to suspend the same is 
to the whole or any part of the money so ordered to be paid, and again 
to revive the same order wholly or in part, as to the Court seems fit.



</article>



<article><tid>491233</tid>
<number>38</number>Court may direct payment of alimony to wife or to her 
trustee.- In all cases in which the Court makes any decree or order for 
alimony, it may direct the same to be paid either to the wife herself, 
or to any trustee on her behalf to be approved by the Court, and may 
impose any terms or restrictions which to the Court seem expedient, 
and may from time to time appoint a new trustee, if it appears to' the 
Court expedient so to do.
X.

SETTLEMENTS

X.- SETTLEMENTS



</article>



<article><tid>676854</tid>
<number>39</number>Power to order settlement of wife' s property for benefit of 
husband and children.- Whenever the Court pronounces a decree of 
dissolution of marriage or judicial separation for adultery of the 
wife, if it is made to appear to the Court that the wife is entitled 
to any property, the Court may, if it think fit, order such settlement 
as it thinks reasonable to be made of such property or any part 
thereof, for the benefit of the husband, or of the children of the 
marriage, or of both.
Any instrument executed pursuant to any order of the Court at the 
time of or after the pronouncing of a decree of dissolution of 
marriage or judicial separation, shall be deemed valid notwithstanding 
the existence of the disability of coverture it the time of the 
execution thereof.

Settlement of damages.

Settlement of damages.- The Court may direct that the whole or any 
part of the damages recovered under section 34 shall be settled for 
the benefit of the children of the marriage, or as a provision for the 
maintenance of the wife.



</article>



<article><tid>1916549</tid>
<number>40</number>Inquiry into existence of ante- nuptial or post- nuptial 
settlements.- The High Court, after a decree absolute for dissolution 
of marriage, or a decree of nullity of marriage,
and the District Court, after its decree for dissolution of 
marriage or of nullity of marriage has been confirmed,

may inquire into the existence of ante- nuptial or post- nuptial 
settlements made on the parties whose marriage is the subject of the 
decree, and may make such orders, with reference to the application of 
the whole or a portion of the property settled, whether for the 
benefit of the husband of the wife, or of the children (if any) of the 
marriage, or of both children and parents, as to the Court seems fit:

Provided that the Court shall not make any order for the benefit 
of the parents or either of them at the expense of the children.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>61</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

XI.

CUSTODY OF CHILDREN

XI.- CUSTODY OF CHILDREN



</article>



<article><tid>1265253</tid>
<number>41</number>Power to make orders as to custody of children in suit for 
separation.- In any suit for obtaining a judicial separation the Court 
may from time to time, before making its decree, make such interim 
orders, and may make such provision in the decree, as it deems proper 
with respect to the custody, maintenance and education of the minor 
children, the marriage of whose parents is the subject of such suit, 
and may, if it think fit, direct proceedings to be taken for placing 
such children under the protection of the said Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1994158</tid>
<number>42</number>Power to make such orders after decree.- The Court, after a 
decree of judicial separation, may upon application (by petition) for 
this purpose make, from time to time, all such orders and provision, 
with respect to the custody, maintenance and education of the minor 
children, the marriage of whose parents is the subject of the decree, 
or for placing such children under the protection of the said Court, 
as might have been made by such decree or by interim orders in case 
the proceedings for obtaining such decree were still pending.


</article>



<article><tid>1201741</tid>
<number>43</number>Power to make orders as to custody of children in suits for 
dissolution or nullity.- In any suit for obtaining a dissolution of 
marriage or a decree of nullity of marriage instituted in, or removed 
to, a High Court, the Court may from time to time, before making its 
decree absolute or its decree (as the case may be), make such interim 
orders, and may make such provision in the decree absolute or decree,
and in any such suit instituted in a District Court, the Court 
may from time to time, before its decree is confirmed, make such 
interim orders, and may make such provision on such confirmation,

as the High Court or District Court (as the case may be) deems 
proper with respect to the custody, maintenance and education of the 
minor children, the marriage of whose parents is the subject of the 
suit,

and may, if it think fit, direct proceedings to be taken for 
placing such children under the protection of the Court.



</article>



<article><tid>419199</tid>
<number>44</number>Power to make such orders after decree or confirmation.- The 
High Court after a decree absolute for dissolution of marriage or a 
decree of nullity of marriage,
and the District Court, after a decree for dissolution of 
marriage or of nullity of marriage has been confirmed,

may, upon application by petition for the purpose, make from time 
to time all such orders and provision, with respect to the custody, 
maintenance and education of the minor children, the in marriage of 
whose parents was the subject of the decree, or for placing such 
children under the protection of the said Court, as might have been 
made by such decree absolute or decree (as the case may be), or by 
such interim orders as aforesaid.

XII.

PROCEDURE

XII.- PROCEDURE



</article>



<article><tid>858803</tid>
<number>45</number>Code of Civil Procedure to apply.- Subject to the provisions 
herein contained, all proceedings under this Act between party and 
party shall be regulated by the Code of Civil Procedure <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.


</article>



<article><tid>141608</tid>
<number>46</number>Forms of petitions and statements.- The forms set forth in the 
schedule to this Act, with such variation as the circumstances of each 
case require, may be used for the respective purposes mentioned in 
such schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>267237</tid>
<number>47</number>Petition to state absence of collusion.- Every petition under 
this Act for a decree of dissolution of marriage, or of nullity of 
marriage, or of judicial separation <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> shall <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> state that 
there is not any collusion or connivance between the petitioner and 
the other patty to the marriage.
Statements to be verified.

Statements to be verified.- The statements contained in every 
petition under this Act shall be verified by the petitioner or some 
other competent person in manner required by law for the verification 
of plaints, and may at the hearing be referred to as evidence.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>62</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See now the Code of Civil Procedure, 1008 (Act 5 of <year>1908</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" or of reversal of judicial separation, or for 
restitution of conjugal rights, or for damages, shall bear a stamp of 
five rupees, and" rep. by Act 7 of <year>1870</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" in the first, second and third cases mentioned in 
this section," rep., ibid.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>81011</tid>
<number>48</number>Suits on behalf of lunatics.- When the husband or wife is a 
lunatic or idiot, any suit under this Act (other than a suit for  
  restitution of conjugal rights) may be brought on his or her behalf by 
the committee or other person entitled to his or her custody.


</article>



<article><tid>446280</tid>
<number>49</number>Suits by minors.- Where the petitioner is a minor, he or she 
shall sue by his or her next friend to be approved by the Court; and 
no petition presented by a minor under this Act shall be filed until 
the next friend has undertaken in writing to be answerable for costs.
Such undertaking <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> shall be filed in Court, and the next 
friend shall thereupon be liable in the same manner and to the same 
extent as if he were a plaintiff in an ordinary suit.



</article>



<article><tid>1675219</tid>
<number>50</number>Service of petition.- Every petition under this Act shall be 
served on the party to be affected thereby, either within or without 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India], in such manner is the High Court by general or special order 
from time to time directs:
Provide that the Court may dispense with such service altogether 
in case it seems necessary or expedient so to do.



</article>



<article><tid>199511</tid>
<number>51</number>Mode of taking evidence.- The witnesses in all proceedings 
before the Court, where their attendance can be had, shall be examined 
orally, and any party may offer himself or herself as a witness, and 
shall be examined, and may be cross- examined and re- examined, like any 
other witness:
Provided that the parties shall be at liberty to verify their 
respective cases in whole or in part by affidavit, but so that the 
deponent in every such affidavit shall, on the application of the 
opposite party, or by direction of the Court, be select to be cross- 
examined by or on behalf of the opposite party orally, and after such 
cross- examination may be re- examined orally as aforesaid by or on 
behalf of the party by whom such affidavit was filed.



</article>



<article><tid>723571</tid>
<number>52</number>Competence of husband and wife to give evidence as to cruelly 
or desertion.- On any petition presented by a wife, praying that her 
marriage may be dissolved by reason of her husband having been guilty 
of adultery coupled with cruelty, or of adultery coupled with 
desertion without reasonable excuse, the husband and wife respectively 
shall be competent and compellable to give evidence of or relating to 
such cruelty or desertion.


</article>



<article><tid>783500</tid>
<number>53</number>Power to close doors.- The whole or any part of any proceeding 
under this Act may be heard, if the Court thinks fit, with closed 
doors.


</article>



<article><tid>1618685</tid>
<number>54</number>Power to adjourn.- The Court may from time to time adjourn the 
hearing of any petition under this Act, and may require further 
evidence thereon if it sees fit so to do.


</article>



<article><tid>1036560</tid>
<number>55</number>Enforcement of, and appeal from, orders and decrees.-- All 
decrees and orders made by the Court in any suit or proceeding under 
this Act shall be enforced and may be appealed from, in the like 
manner as the decrees and orders of the Court made in the exercise of 
its original civil jurisdiction are enforced and may be appealed from, 
under the laws, rules and orders for the time bring in force:
Provided that there shall be no appeal from a decree of a 
District Judge for dissolution of marriage or of nullity of marriage; 
nor from the order of the High Court confirming or refusing to confirm 
such decree:

No appeal as to costs.

No appeal as to costs.- Provided also that there shall be no 
appeal on the subject of costs only.



</article>



<article><tid>683816</tid>
<number>56</number>Appeal to the Supreme Court.- Any person may appeal to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
Supreme Court] from any decree (other than a decree nisi) or order 
under this Act of a High Court made on' appeal or otherwise,
and from any decree (other than a decree nisi) or order made in 
the exercise of original jurisdiction by Judges of a High Court or of 
any Division Court from which an appeal shall not lie to the High 
Court,

when the High Court declares that the case is a fit one for 
appeal to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Supreme Court].

<pagefootnote><pagenum>63</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" shall bear a stamp of eight annas and" rep. by Act 7 
of <year>1870</year>, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>subs. by A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Provinces" which had been subs. by 
A. O. <year>1948</year>, for British India".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Her Majesty in Council".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


XIII.

RE- MARRIAGE

XIII.- RE- MARRIAGE



</article>



<article><tid>424920</tid>
<number>57</number>Liberty to parties to marry again.- When six months after the 
date of an order of a High Court confirming the decree for a 
dissolution of marriage made by a District Judge have expired,
or when six months after the date of' any decree of a high Court 
dissolving a marriage have expired, and no appeal has been presented 
against such decree to the High Court in its appellate jurisdiction,

or when any such appeal has been dismissed,

or when in the result of any such appeal any marriage is declared 
to be dissolved,

but not sooner, it shall be lawful for the respective parties to the 
marriage to marry again, as if the prior marriage had been dissolved 
by death:

Provided that no appeal to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Supreme Court] has been 
presented against any such order or decree.

When such appeal has been dismissed, or when in the result 
thereof the marriage is declared to be dissolved, but not sooner, it 
shall be lawful for the respective parties to the marriage to marry 
again as if the prior marriage had been dissolved by death.



</article>



<article><tid>698655</tid>
<number>58</number>English clergyman not compelled to solemnize marriages of 
persons divorced for adultery.-- No clergyman in Holy Orders of the 2' 
No Church of England <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> shall be compelled to solemnize the 
marriage of any person whose former marriage has been dissolved on the 
ground of his or her adultery, or shall be liable to any suit, penalty 
or censure for solemnizing or refusing to solemnize the marriage of 
any such person.


</article>



<article><tid>516672</tid>
<number>59</number>English Minister refusing to perform ceremony to permit use of 
his Church.- When any Minister of any Church or Chapel of the said <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
Church refuses to perform such marriage service between any persons 
who but for such refusal would be entitled to have the same service 
performed in such Church or Chapel, such Minister shall permit any 
other Minister in Holy Orders of the said Church, entitled to 
officiate within the diocese in which such Church or Chapel is 
situate, to perform such marriage- service in such Church or Chapel.
XIV.

MISCELLANEOUS

XIV.-- MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>360041</tid>
<number>60</number>Decree for separation or protection- order valid as to 
persons dealing with wife before reversal.- Every decree for judicial 
separation or order to protect property, obtained by a wife under this 
Act shall, until reversed or discharged, be deemed valid, so far as 
necessary, for the protection of any person dealing with the wife.
No reversal, discharge or variation of such decree or order shall 
affect any rights or remedies which any person would otherwise have 
had in respect of any contracts or acts of the wife entered into or 
done between the dates of such decree or order, and of the reversal, 
discharge or variation thereof.

Indemnity of persons making payment to wife without notice of reversal 
of decree or protection order.

Indemnity of persons making payment to wife without notice of 
reversal of decree or protection order.-- All persons who in reliance 
on any such decree or order make any payment to, or permit any 
transfer or act to be made or done by, the wife who has obtained the 
same shall, notwithstanding such decree or order may then have been 
reversed, discharged or varied, or the separation of the wife from her 
husband may have ceased, or at some Lime since the making of the 
decree or order been discontinued, be protected and indemnified as if, 
at the time of such payment, transfer or other act, such decree or 
order were valid and still subsisting without variation, and the 
separation had not ceased or been discontinued,

unless, at the time of the, payment, transfer or other act, such 
persons had notice of the reversal, discharge or variation of the 
decree or order or of the cessation or discontinuance of the 
separation.



</article>



<article><tid>818541</tid>
<number>61</number>Bar of suit for criminal conversation.- After this Act comes 
into operation, no person competent to present a petition under 
sections 2 and 10 shall maintain a suit for criminal conversation with 
his wife.


</article>



<article><tid>81990</tid>
<number>62</number>Power to make rules.- The High Court shall make such rules 
under this Act as it may from time to time consider expedient, and may 
from time to time alter and add to the same:
Provided that such rules, alterations and additions are 
consistent with the provisions of this Act and the Code of Civil 
Procedure <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.

All such rules, alterations and additions shall be published in 
the Official Gazette.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>71</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" Her Majesty in Council". 
2. The word" United" rep. by Act 12 of <year>1873</year>, s. 1 and Sch. 
3. The words" and Ireland" rep. by s. 1 and Sch. ibid. 
4. See now the Code of civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


STATEMENT OF OBJECTS AND REASONS

THE object of this Bill is to place the Matrimonial Law 
administered by the High Courts, in the exercise of their original 
jurisdiction, on the same footing as the Matrimonial Law administered 
by the Court for Divorce and Matrimonial Causes in England.

The 9th Section of the Act of Parliament for establishing High 
Courts of Judicature in India 24 and 25 Vic., Ch. 10 (4) provides that 
the High Courts shall exercise such Matrimonial Jurisdiction as Her 
Majesty by Letters Patent shall grant and direct. Under the authority 
thus conferred by Parliament, the 35th Section of the Letters Patent, 
constituting the High Courts of Judicature, provides as follows:-

" And we do further ordain that the said High Court of 
Judicature at Fort William in Bengal shall have 
Jurisdiction in matters matrimonial between our subjects 
professing the Christian religion, and that such 
Jurisdiction shall extend to the local limits within 
which the Supreme Court now has Ecclesiastical 
Jurisdiction. Provided always that nothing herein 
contained shall be held to interfere with the exercise 
of any Jurisdiction in matters Matrimonial by any Court 
not established by Royal Charter within the said 
Presidency lawfully possessed thereof."

Letter from Secretary of State, Judicial No. 24, dated 
 14th May, <year>1862</year>.

In the Despatch of the Secretary of State transmitting the 
Letters Patent, the 33rd and 34th paragraphs are to the following 
effect:-

</article>



<article><tid>1560260</tid>
<number>33</number>" Her Majesty' s Government are desirous of placing the 
Christian subjects of the Crown within the Presidency in the same 
position under the High Court, as to matters matrimonial in general, 
as they now are under the Supreme Court, and this they believe, to be 
effected by Clause 3 5 of the Charter. But they consider it expedient 
that the High Court should possess, in addition, the power of 
decreeing divorce which the Supreme Court does not possess, in other 
words, that the High Court should have the same Jurisdiction as the 
Court for Divorce and Matrimonial Causes in England, established in 
virtue of Act 20 and 21 Vic., C. 85 and in regard to which further 
provisions were made by 22 and 23 Vic., C. 61, and 23 and 24 Vic., C. 
144. The Act of Parliament for establishing the High Courts, however, 
does not purport to give to the Crown the power of importing into the 
Charter all the provisions of the Divorce Court Act, and some of them, 
the Crown clearly could not so import, such, for instance, as those 
which prescribe the period of re- marriage, and those which exempt from 
punishment clergymen refusing to re- marry adulterers. All these are, 
in truth, matters for Indian legislation, and I request that you will 
immediately take the subject into your consideration, and introduce 
into your Council a Bill for conferring upon the High Court, the 
Jurisdiction and Powers of the Divorce Court in England, one of the 
provisions of which should be to give an appeal to the Privy Council 
in those cases in which the Divorce Court Act gives an appeal to the 
House of Lords."
</article>



<article><tid>1613930</tid>
<number>34</number>" The object of the provision at the end of Clause 35 is to 
obviate any doubt that may possibly arise as to whether, by vesting 
the High Court with the powers of the Court for Divorce and 
Matrimonial Causes in England, it was intended to take away from the 
Courts within the division of the Presidency, not established by Royal 
Charter, any Jurisdiction which they might have in matters 
matrimonial, as for instance in a suit for alimony between Armenians 
or Native Christians. With any such Jurisdiction it is not intended 
to interfere."
In addition to the Act of Parliament mentioned by the Secretary 
of State as regulating the Jurisdiction of the English Divorce Court, 
the Statute 25 and 26 Vic., Ch. 81 has been passed in the year just 
expired (1862). The object of this Statute is to render perpetual 23 
and 24 Vic., Ch. 144, the duration of which had been originally 
limited to two years.

The Draft of a Bill has been prepared to give effect to the 
Secretary of State' s instructions but some variations from the English 
Statutes in respect of Procedure have been adopted.

With a view to uniformity in practice in the several branches of 
Jurisdiction, the Bill provides that the Procedure of the Code of 
Civil Procedure shall be followed, instead of the Rules of Her 
Majesty' s Court for Divorce and Matrimonial Causes in England, and it 
omits the provision in 20 and 21 Vic., Ch. 85 respecting the 
occasional trial of questions of fact by Juries.

In respect of fees, it has been considered that the Act XX of 
<year>1862</year>, (lately continued by the Governor- General in Council for another  
  year), renders special legislation unnecessary.

The power of intervening in suits, given by 23 and 24 Vic., Ch. 
144, to the Attorney General and the Queen' s Proctor is, in this Bill, 
given to the Advocate General and the Solicitor to Government.

There are also other variations of a minor and verbal character.



<pagefootnote><pagenum>72</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


The Draft Bill having been submitted to the Judges of the several 
High Courts, with a request that they would favour the Government with 
their opinions on it, communications have been received, and will be 
laid before the Council, from the Judges at Calcutta and Bombay. In 
these letters there are several important suggestions, and the 
Honorable the Chief Justice of the High Court at Calcutta has 
intimated that he considers it doubtful whether decrees by the High 
Court under the proposed Act, dissolving the marriages of persons who 
have been married in England, would have legal effect there. The 
question is one of considerable difficulty as well as of great 
importance, and has been stated to the Secretary of State, with the 
view of obtaining the opinion of Her Majesty' s Law officers, and, if 
necessary, some legislative measure to remove all doubt.

 1st January, <year>1863</year>. HENRY S. MAINE.



</article>



 </act>