<act><tid>1818248</tid>
<title>THE ELECTION LAWS (EXTENSION TO SIKKIM) ACT, <year>1976</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 26th January, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to provide for the extension of the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> and the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year>, to 
the State of Sikkim.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- sixth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Short title and commencement.



<article><tid>1195640</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1010661</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Election Laws (Extension to Sikkim) Act, <year>1976</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>61285</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 9th day of 
September, <year>1975</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Extension and amendment of election laws.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>382787</tid>
<number> 2</number> Extension and amendment of election laws.
<section><tid>1453679</tid>
<number>1</number>The Acts  
mentioned in the Schedule are hereby extended to, and shall be in 
force in, the State of Sikkim.

</section>

<section><tid>561623</tid>
<number>2</number>With effect from the commencement of this Act, the Acts men- 
tioned in the Schedule shall be amended as specified therein.

</section>

<section><tid>403254</tid>
<number>3</number>Any reference in the Acts mentioned in the Schedule to a law 
not in force, or to a functionary not in existence, in the State of 
Sikkim shall be construed as a reference to the corresponding law in 
force, or to the corresponding functionary in existence, in that 
State:
Provided that if any question arises as to who such corresponding 
functionary is, or if there is no such corresponding functionary, the 
Central Government shall decide as to who such functionary will be and 
the decision of the Central Government shall be final.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Repeal and saving.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1774121</tid>
<number> 3</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>131090</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Laws (Extension to   
  Sikkim) Ordinance, <year>1975</year>, (9 of <year>1975</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1366534</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under or by virtue of the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have 
been done or taken under or by virtue of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>