<act><title>THE CIGARETTES AND OTHER TOBACCO PRODUCTS (PROHIBITION OF ADVERTISEMENT AND REGULATION OF TRADE AND COMMERCE, PRODUCTION, SUPPLY AND DISTRIBUTION) RULES, 20041</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Cigarettes and other Tobacco Products (Prohibition of Advertisement and Regulation of Trade and Commerce, Production, Supply and Distribution) Rules, 2004. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the 1st day of May, 2004. 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.­In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    Act means the Cigarettes and other 
      Tobacco Products (Prohibition of Advertisement and Regulation of Trade and 
      Commerce, Production, Supply and Distribution Act, 2003;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    section means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    open space mentioned in section 
      3(1) of the Act shall not include any place visited by the public such as 
      open auditorium, stadium, railway station, bus stop and such other places; 
      and
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    words and expressions used herein and 
      not defined in these rules but defined in the Act, shall have the 
      meanings, respectively, assigned to them in the Act.
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>e</number>    indirect advertisement 
      mentioned in section 5(1) of the Act means
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the use of a name or brand of 
        tobacco products for marketing, promoting or advertising other goods, 
        services and events;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the marketing of tobacco products 
        with the aid of a brand name or trademark which is known as, or in use 
        as, a name or brand for other goods and service;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    the use of particular colours and 
        layout and/or presentation those are associated with particular tobacco 
        products; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    the use of tobacco products and 
        smoking situations when advertising other goods and services.]
</subsection>
</section>
 










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Prohibition of smoking in a public place.
<section><number>1</number> 
    The owner or the manager or in charge of the affairs of a public place shall 
    cause to be displayed prominently a board, of a minimum size of sixty 
    centimetre by thirty centimetre in the Indian language(s) as applicable, at 
    least one at the entrance of the public place and one at conspicuous place(s) 
    inside, containing the warning No Smoking Area­Smoking Here is an 
    Offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The owner 
    or the manager or in charge of the affairs of a hotel having thirty rooms or 
    restaurant having seating capacity of thirty persons or more and the manager 
    of the airport shall ensure that,­
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    the smoking and non-smoking areas are 
      physically segregated;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the smoking area shall be located in 
      such manner that the public is not required to pass through it in order to 
      reach the non-smoking area; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    each area shall contain boards 
      indicating thereon Smoking Area/Non-Smoking Area.
</subsection>
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>4</number> Prohibition of 
    advertisement of cigarettes and other tobacco products.
<section><number>1</number> The size of 
    the board used for the advertisement of cigarettes and any other tobacco 
    products displayed at the entrance of a warehouse or a shop where cigarettes 
    or any other tobacco products is offered for sale shall not exceed sixty 
    centimeters by forty-five centimeters.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each such 
    board shall contain in an Indian language as applicable, one of the 
    following warnings occupying the top edge of the board in a prominent manner 
    measuring twenty centimeters by fifteen centimeters, namely:
 <subsection>
    <number>i</number> Tobacco causes cancer, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>ii</number> Tobacco kills,
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The health 
    warning referred to in sub-rule (2) must be prominent, legible and in black 
    colour with a white background.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The display 
    board shall only list the type of tobacco products available and no brand 
    pack shot, brand name of the tobacco product or other promotional message 
    and picture shall be displayed on the board. The display board shall not be 
    backlit or illuminated in any manner.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The owner 
    or manager or in charge of the affairs of a place where cigarettes and other 
    tobacco products are sold shall not display tobacco products in such a way 
    that they are visible so as to prevent easy access of tobacco products to 
    persons below the age of eighteen years.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No 
    individual or a person or a character in films and television programmes 
    shall display tobacco products or their use:
 
Provided that 
    this sub-rule shall not apply to
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  old Indian films and old television 
    programmes, produced prior to coming into effect of this notification, being 
    screened in a cinema hall or theatre or aired on television;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  old foreign films and old television 
    programmes, including dubbed and sub-titled foreign films and television 
    programmes, being screened in cinema halls or theatres or aired on 
    television;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  Indian or foreign documentaries and 
    health spots displaying use of tobacco products made to clearly and 
    unambiguously reflect the dangers and dire consequences of tobacco use being 
    screened in cinema hall or theatre or aired on television;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  live coverage of news, current 
    affairs, interviews, public meetings, sports events, cultural events and the 
    like, being telecast on television whereby there is a purely incidental and 
    completely unintentional coverage of use of tobacco products:
 
Provided 
    further that the exemptions under clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) above shall 
    not extend to display of brands of tobacco products or tobacco product 
    placement in any form:
 
Provided also 
    that close ups of cigarette packages or tobacco products shall not be 
    permissible and such scenes shall be edited by the producer or distributor 
    or broadcaster prior to screening in cinemas or theatres or airing on 
    television.
 
Explanation 
    (1).For the purpose of this 
    sub-rule, all films that receive Central Board of Film Certification prior 
    to the effective date of this notification shall be categorized as old 
    films. 
 
Explanation 
    (2).For the purpose of this 
    sub-rule, foreign film implies Imported as defined in the Cinematograph 
    (Certification) Rules, 1983.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6A</number> In case of 
    old Indian and foreign films, the owner or manager of the cinema hall or 
    theatre where the film is being screened shall ensure that anti-tobacco 
    health spots of minimum thirty seconds duration each are screened at the 
    beginning, middle and end of the said film. The provisions of this sub-rule 
    shall not apply to clause (c) of sub-rule (6).
 </section><section>
<number>6B</number>(a) In case 
    of old television programmes, it shall be mandatory for the broadcaster to 
    ensure either placement of an anti-tobacco health warning as a prominent 
    scroll at the bottom of the television screen during the period of such 
    display or airing of anti-tobacco health spots for a period of minimum 
    thirty seconds during the telecast of each television programme of thirty 
    minute duration or less.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> In case the 
    television programme is more than thirty minutes further airtime of thirty 
    seconds shall be allocated for each incremental thirty minutes, for 
    telecasting anti-tobacco spots.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> The minimum 
    duration of each anti-tobacco spot shall be not less than fifteen seconds.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> The 
    provisions of this sub-rule shall not apply to clauses (c) and (d) of 
    sub-rule (6):
 
Provided that, 
    the anti-tobacco health warning scroll shall be legible and readable with 
    font in black colour on white background with the warnings Smoking causes 
    cancer or Smoking kills for smoking form of tobacco use and Tobacco 
    causes cancer or Tobacco kills for chewing and other form of tobacco or 
    such other warnings as may be specified by the Central Government from time 
    to time:
 
Provided 
    further that, the anti-tobacco health warning scrolls or health spots shall 
    be in the same language(s) as used in the film or television programme. In 
    case of dubbed or sub-titled films or television programmes, the scrolls or 
    spots shall be carried in the language of dubbing or sub-titlement.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> Sub-rule 
    (6) shall not apply to new Indian or foreign films and television programmes 
    displaying use of tobacco products necessary to represent the smoking or 
    tobacco usage of a real historical figure or for representation of a 
    historical era or classified well known character:
 
Provided that 
    in very rare cases where there is display or use of tobacco products due to 
    compulsions of the script, they shall be supported by a strong editorial 
    justification:
 
Provided 
    further that the display of usage of tobacco products in such movies and 
    television programmes under this sub-rule shall be subject to the following 
    safeguards:
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  Film and television programmes 
    depicting tobacco related scenes shall mandatorily be given A 
    Certification. Such films and television programmes may be permitted to be 
    telecast at such timings as are likely to have least viewership from persons 
    below the age of eighteen years.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  The films or television programmes, 
    which depict such scenes, would have a disclaimer by the concerned actor 
    regarding the ill effects of use of such products. The disclaimer would be 
    shown in the beginning, middle and end of the film.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  Whenever such scenes are shown in a 
    film or television programme, an anti-tobacco health warning scroll will be 
    continuously displayed on the screen starting a minute before the scene and 
    would be continuously displayed until one minute after the scene:
 
Provided also 
    that there shall not be any display of brands of tobacco products or tobacco 
    product placement in any form:
 
Provided also 
    that close-ups of cigarette packages or tobacco products shall not be 
    permissible and such scenes shall be edited by the producer or distributor 
    or broadcaster prior to screening in cinemas or theatres or airing on 
    television.
 
Explanation 
    (1).For the purpose of this 
    sub-rule, all films and television programmes that receive Central Board of 
    Film Certification after the effective date of this notification shall be 
    categorized as new.
 
Explanation 
    (2).For the purpose of this 
    sub-rule, representatives from Ministry of Health and Family Welfare shall 
    also be represented in the Central Board of Film Certification.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> Wherever 
    brand names or logos of tobacco products form a part of the pictures to be 
    printed in any form of print or outdoor media or footage to be aired through 
    any form of electronic media, it shall be mandatory for the media to crop or 
    mask the same to ensure that the brand names and logos of the tobacco 
    products are not visible, except in case of live or deferred live telecast 
    of sports, cultural and other events or activities held in other countries 
    being aired on television in India.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> A Steering 
    Committee shall be constituted under the chairmanship of the Union Health 
    Secretary with representation from among others, the Ministry of Information 
    and Broadcasting, Ministry of Law and Justice, Advertising Standards Council 
    of India, Press Council of India, Members of Parliament and voluntary 
    organisations. This Committee shall take cognizance suo motu or look 
    into specific violations under section 5 of the Act and shall also evaluate 
    cases related to indirect advertising and promotion and pass orders 
    thereof.]
 





























 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> Prohibition on sale of tobacco products to and by persons below the age of eighteen years. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The owner or the manager or the in-charge of the affairs of a place where cigarettes or other tobacco products are sold shall ensure that, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a board with a warning as specified in Annexure I is displayed at the entrance of the place where cigarettes or other tobacco products are sold and all the components of the board should appear in a manner exactly as in the soft copy provided in the compact disk [CD] accompanying these rules: 
</subsection>
 Provided that such board shall not have any advertisement or promotional messages or pictures or images of cigarettes or any other tobacco products. 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> no tobacco product is sold through a vending machine; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> no tobacco product is handled or sold by a person below the age of eighteen years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> tobacco products are not displayed in a manner that enables easy access of tobacco products to persons below the age of eighteen years. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The onus of proof, that the buyer of the tobacco product is not a person below the age of eighteen years lies with the seller of the tobacco products and the seller in case of doubts may request the buyer to provide appropriate evidence or age proof of having reached eighteen years of age.] 



 
  <title>5. Prohibition of sale to minors.­ </title>(1) The owner or the manager or the incharge of the affairs of a place where cigarettes and other tobacco products are sold shall display a board of minimum size of sixty centimetre by thirty centimetre at conspicuous place(s) containing the warning Sale of tobacco products to a person under the age of eighteen years is a punishable offence, in Indian language(s) as applicable. 
 
</section><section><number>2</number> The onus of proof that the buyer of the tobacco product is not a minor lies with the seller of the tobacco products. The seller, in case of doubt, may request tobacco purchaser to provide appropriate evidence of having reached eighteen years of age. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The owner or the manager or the in-charge of the affairs of a place where cigarettes or other tobacco products are sold shall ensure that no tobacco product is sold through a vending machine. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The owner or the manager or the in-charge of the affairs of a place where cigarettes or other tobacco products are sold shall ensure that no tobacco product is handled or sold by a person below the age of eighteen years.. 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>6</number> Recovery of Fine by authorised officers. </title>The authorised officers mentioned in Annexure II shall be competent to act under and compound the offences committed in violation of clause 
<section><number>a</number> and clause (b) of section 6 of the Act.] 



  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> Health Spots and Scroll in Old Films and Television Programmes. </title>The owner or manger of a cinema hall or theatre where on old Indian or foreign film displaying tobacco products or its use, is being screened, and the broadcaster telecasting old Indian or foreign television programme displaying tobacco products or its use, shall mandatorily screen the following namely: 
 
 <section><number>a</number> anti-tobacco health spots or messages, of minimum thirty seconds duration each at the beginning and middle of the film or the television programme; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> anti-tobacco health warning as a prominent scroll at the bottom of the screen during the period of such display: 
</section>
 Provided that, the anti-tabacco health warning scroll shall be legible and readable, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> (a) with font in black colour on white background; 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> with the warnings Smoking causes cancer or Smoking kills for smoking forms of tobacco use; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> with the warnings Tobacco causes cancer or Tobacco kills for chewing and other smokeless forms of tobacco; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>ii</number> or such other warnings as may be specified by the Central Government from time to time: 
</section>
 Provided further that, the anti-tobacco health warning scrolls or health spots shall be in the same language as used in the film or television programme and in case of dubbed or sub-titled films or television programmes, the scrolls or spots shall be carried in the language of dubbing or sub-title: 
 Provided also that such television programmes may be permitted to be telecast on television at such timings that are likely to have least viewership from persons below the age of eighteen years. 
 Explanation .For the purpose of this rule, 
 
 <section><number>i</number> all films that receive Central Board of film Certification prior to the effective date of this notification shall be categorized as old films; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> all television programmes produced prior to coming into effect of this notification shall be categorized as Old Television programme; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> the expression foreign film implies Imported as defined in the Cinematograph (Certification) Rules, 1983.] 
</section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> Health Spots, Scroll and Disclaimer in new Films and Television programmes. </title>
<section><number>1</number> All new Indian or foreign films and television programmes displaying tobacco products or its use shall have, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a strong editorial justification explaining the necessity of such display to the Central Board of Film Certification for films and the concerned authority under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting for television programmes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a U/A' Certification, from the Central Board of Film Certification for all films; and necessary approvals from the concerned authority under the Ministry of Information and Broadcasting for television programmes: 
</subsection>
 Provided that such television programmes may be permited to be telecast on television at such timings as are likely to have least viewership from persons below the age of eighteen years; 
 
 <subsection><number>c</number> a disclaimer, of minimum twenty seconds duration, by the concerned actor regarding the ill effects of the use of such products, in the beginning and middle of the film or television programme; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> anti-tobacco health spots or messages, of minimum thirty seconds duration each at the beginning and middle of the film or the television programme; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> anti-tobacco health warning as a prominent scroll at the bottom of the screen during the period of such display: 
</subsection>
 Provided that, the anti-tobacco health warning scroll shall be legible and readable, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> (a) with font in black colour on white background; 
 
 <subsubsection><number>b</number> with the warnings Smoking causes cancer or Smoking kills for smoking forms of tobacco use; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> with the warnings Tobacco causes cancer or Tobacco kills for chewing and other smokeless forms of tobacco; 
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> or such other warnings as may be specified by the Central Government from time to time: 
</subsection>
 Provided further that, the anti-tobacco health warning scrolls or health spots shall be in the same language as used in the film or television programme and in case of dubbed or sub-titled films or television programmes, the scrolls or spots shall be carried in the language of dubbing or sub-title. 
 Explanation .For the purpose of this rule, 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> representatives from Ministry of Health and Family welfare shall also be represented in the Central Board of Film Certification. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> all films that receive Central Board of Film Certification after the effective date of this notification shall be categorized as New Films 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> all television programmes produced after the effective date of this notification shall be categorized as New Television Programme;] 
</subsection>



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>9</number> Product Placement, promotional materials and posters. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The display of tobacco products or their use in films and television programmes shall not extend to the following, namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> display of the brands of cigarettes or other tobacco products or any form of tobacco product placement; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> close ups of tobacco products and tobacco products packages: 
</subsection>
 Provided that in a new film or television programme such scenes shall be edited by the producer or distributor or broadcaster prior to screening in cinema or theatre or airing on television, and in an old film or television programme such scenes shall be masked or blurred by the producer or distributor or broadcaster while screening 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Promotional materials and posters of films and television programmes shall not depict any tobacco products or their usage in any form.] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> Cropping or Masking of Brand names and Logos of Tobacco Products. </title>Wherever brand names or logos of tobacco products form a part of the pictures to be printed in any form of print or outdoor media or footage to be aired through any form of electronic media, it shall be mandatory for the media to crop or mask the same to ensure that the brand names and logos of the tobacco products are not visible, except in case of live or deferred live telecast of sports, cultural and other events or activities held in other countries being aired on television in India.] 



</article><form>
 

THE CIGARETTES AND OTHER TOBACCO PRODUCTS (PROHIBITION OF ADVERTISEMENT AND REGULATION OF TRADE AND COMMERCE, PRODUCTION, SUPPLY AND DISTRIBUTION) RULES, 20041
 

 
 

2[Annexure I 
 

[ See rule 5(1)(a)] 
 

1. The Board shall be of a minimum size of 60 cm by 30 cm of white background. 
 

2. The Board shall contain the warning sale of tobacco products to a person below the age of eighteen years is a punishable offence, in Indian language(s) as applicable and a pictorial depiction of the ill-effects of tobacco use on health.] 
 

----------
 

1. Vide  G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., 
  Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004. 
 

2. Ins. by G.S.R. 619(E), dated 11th August, 2011 (w.e.f. 11-8-2011).
  
</form><form>
 

THE CIGARETTES AND OTHER TOBACCO PRODUCTS (PROHIBITION OF ADVERTISEMENT AND REGULATION OF TRADE AND COMMERCE, PRODUCTION, SUPPLY AND DISTRIBUTION) RULES, 20041
 

 
 

2[Annexure II 
 

[ See rule 5(1)(a)] 
 
 
   

Sl. No.
  

Person authorised to take action

 
 1
 Vice Chancellor or Director or Proctor or Principal or Headmaster or In-Charge of an Educational Institution

 
 2
 Assistant Labour Commissioner from the Department of Labour

 
 3
 All officers of the rank of Sub-Inspector in State Food and Drug Administration from the Department of Food and Drugs

 
 4
 All officers of the rank of Inspectors from the Department of Education

 
 5
 All police officers of the rank of Sub-Inspector of Police and above

 
 6
 Municipal Health Officers

 
 7
 Representatives of Panchayati Raj Institutions (Chairpersons or Sarpanch or Panchayat Secretary)

 
 8
 District Programme Manager of Finance Manager—District Health Society (National Rural Health Mission)

 
 9
 Civil Surgeon or Chief Medical Officer at District Hospital or Medical Officer at Primary Health Centre (PHC)

 
 10
 Block Development Officer, Block Extension Educator (BEE)

 
 11
 Director or Joint Director Department of Health, and Department of Education in the State Government

 
 12
 Nodal Officers of State and District Tobacco Control Cell under National Tabacco Control Programme.]


 

 
 

----------
 

1. Vide  G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., 
  Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004. 
 

2. Ins. by G.S.R. 619(E), dated 11th August, 2011 (w.e.f. 11-8-2011).
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 656(E), 
    dated 20th October, 2006, for clause (e). Earlier clause (e) was inserted by 
    G.S.R. 345(E), dated 31st May, 2005 and as corrected by G.S.R. 190(E), dated 
    30th March, 2006 (w.e.f. 1-5-2006). Clause (e), before substitution by G.S.R. 
    656(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 656(E), 
    dated 20th October, 2006, for rule 4. Earlier rule 4 was substituted by 
    G.S.R. 345(E), dated 31st May, 2005 and as corrected by G.S.R. 496(E), dated 
    22nd July, 2005 and was amended by G.S.R. 698(E), dated 30th November, 2005, 
    and as corrected by G.S.R. 190(E), dated 30th March, 2006 (w.e.f. 1-5-2006). 
    Rule 4, before substitution by G.S.R. 656(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Vide   G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., 
  Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 619(E), dated 11th August, 2011, for rule 5 (w.e.f. 11-8-2011). Earlier 
  rule 5 was amended by G.S.R. 656(E), dated 20th October, 2006, G.S.R. 345(E), 
  dated 31st May, 2005, G.S.R. 190(E), dated 30th March, 2006 (w.e.f. 1-5-2006). Rule 5, before substitution by G.S.R. 619(E), dated 11th August, 2011, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Vide   G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., 
  Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 619(E), dated 11th August, 2011 (w.e.f. 11-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Vide   G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 619(E), dated 11th August, 2011 (w.e.f. 11-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Vide   G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 619(E), dated 11th August, 2011 (w.e.f. 11-8-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Vide   G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 786(E), dated 27th October, 2011 (w.e.f. 14-11-2011).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Vide   G.S.R. 137(E), dated 25th February, 2004, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 25th February, 2004.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 786(E), dated 27th October, 2011 (w.e.f. 14-11-2011).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>