<act><title>THE BORDER SECURITY FORCE ACT, 1968 
</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called 
the Border Security Force Act, 1968. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.
<section><number>1</number> 
    In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   active duty, in relation to 
    a person subject to this Act, means any duty as a member of the Force during 
    the period in which such person is attached to, or forms part of, a unit of 
    the Force
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   which is engaged in 
    operations against an enemy, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   which is operating at a 
    picket or engaged on patrol or other guard duty along the borders of India,
 
and includes duty by such 
    person during any period declared by the Central Government by notification 
    in the Official Gazette as a period of active duty with reference to any 
    area in which any person or class of persons subject to this Act may be 
    serving;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   battalion means a unit of the 
    Force constituted as a battalion by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   Chief Law Officer and Law 
    Officer mean, respectively, the Chief Law Officer and a Law Officer of the 
    Force appointed by the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   civil offence means an offence 
    which is triable by a criminal court;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   civil prison means any jail 
    or place used for the detention of any criminal prisoner under the Prisons 
    Act, 1894 (9 of 1894), or under any other law for the time being in force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   Commandant, when used in any 
    provision of this Act with reference to any unit of the Force, means the 
    officer whose duty it is under the rules to discharge with respect to that 
    unit, the functions of a Commandant in regard to matters of the description 
    referred to in that provision;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   criminal court means a court 
    of ordinary criminal justice in any part of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   Deputy Inspector-General 
    means a Deputy Inspector-General of the Force appointed under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   Director-General means the 
    Director-General of the Force appointed under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   enemy includes all armed 
    mutineers, armed rebels, armed rioters, pirates and any person in arms 
    against whom it is the duty of any person subject to this Act to take 
    action;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   enrolled person means an 
    under-officer or other person enrolled under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   Force means the Border 
    Security Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   Force custody means the 
    arrest or confinement of a member of the Force according to rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   Inspector-General means the 
    Inspector-General of the Force appointed under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   member of the Force means an 
    officer, a subordinate officer, an under-officer or other enrolled person;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>   notification means a 
    notification published in the Official Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>   offence means any act or 
    omission punishable under this Act and includes a civil offence;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>   officer means a person 
    appointed or in pay as an officer of the Force, but does not include a 
    subordinate officer or an under-officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>   prescribed means prescribed 
    by rules made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number>   rule means a rule made under 
    this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>   Security Force Court means a 
    court referred to in section 64; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   subordinate officer means a 
    person appointed or in pay as a Subedar-Major, a Subedar or a Sub-Inspector 
    of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>w</number>   superior officer, when used 
    in relation to a person subject to this Act, means,
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   any member of the force 
    to whose command such person is for the time being subject in accordance 
    with the rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   any officer of higher rank or 
    class or of a higher grade in the same class, and includes when such person 
    is not an officer, a subordinate officer or an under-officer of higher rank, 
    class or grade;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>x</number>   under-officer means a Head 
    Constable, Naik and Lance Naik of the Force;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>y</number>   all words and expressions used 
    and not defined in this Act but defined in the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
    1860) shall have the meanings assigned to them in that Code.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In this Act, references 
    to any law not in force in the State of Jammu and Kashmir shall be construed 
    as references to the corresponding law in force in that State.
 
 
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Persons subject to this 
    Act.
<section><number>1</number> The 
    following persons shall be subject to this Act, wherever they may be, 
    namely:
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   Officers and Subordinate 
    Officers; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   under-officers and other 
    persons enrolled under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person subject to 
    this Act shall remain so subject until retired, discharged, released, 
    removed or dismissed from the Force in accordance with the provisions of 
    this Act and the rules.
 
 
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Constitution of the 
    Force.
<section><number>1</number> There 
    shall be an armed force of the Union called the Border Security Force for 
    ensuring the security of the borders of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
    provisions of this Act, the Force shall be constituted in such manner as may 
    be prescribed and the conditions of service of the members of the Force 
    shall be such as may be prescribed.




 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Control, direction, 
    etc.
<section><number>1</number> The 
    general superintendence, direction and control of the Force shall vest in, 
    and be exercised by, the Central Government and subject thereto and to the 
    provisions of this Act and the rules, the command and supervision of the 
    Force shall vest in an officer to be appointed by the Central Government as 
    the Director-General of the Force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director-General 
    shall, in the discharge of his duties under this Act, be assisted by such 
    number of Inspectors-General, Deputy Inspectors-General, Commandants and 
    other officers as may be prescribed by the Central Government.





 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>6</number> Enrolment.
<section><number>1</number> 
    The persons to be enrolled to the Force, the mode of enrolment, and the 
    procedure for enrolment shall be such as may be prescribed by the Central 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act and the rules, every person who has, for a 
    continuous period of three months, been in receipt of pay as a person 
    enrolled under this Act and borne on the rolls of the Force shall be deemed 
    to have been duly enrolled.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>7</number> Liability for service 
    outside India.Every 
    member of the Force shall be liable to serve in any part of India as well as 
    outside India.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Resignation and 
    withdrawal from the post.No 
    member of the Force shall be at liberty,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   to resign his appointment 
    during the term of his engagement; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   to withdraw himself from all 
    or any of the duties of his appointment,
 
except with the previous permission in writing 
    of the prescribed authority.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Tenure of service under 
    the Act.Every 
    person subject to this Act shall hold office during the pleasure of the 
    President.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Termination of service 
    by Central Government.Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act and the rules, the Central Government may 
    dismiss or remove from the service any person subject to this Act.




 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>11</number> Dismissal, removal or 
      reduction by the Director-General and by other officers.
<section><number>1</number> The Director-General or 
      any Inspector-General may dismiss or remove from the service or reduce to 
      a lower grade or rank or the ranks any person subject to this Act other 
      than an officer.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An officer not below the 
      rank of Deputy Inspector-General or any prescribed officer may dismiss or 
      remove from the service any person under his command other than an officer 
      or a subordinate officer of such rank or ranks as may be 
      prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any such officer as is 
      mentioned in sub-section (2) may reduce to a lower grade or rank or the 
      ranks any person under his command except an officer or a subordinate 
      officer.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The exercise of any power 
      under this section shall be subject to the provisions of this Act and 
      rules.




 

 
 

 

 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Certificate of 
    termination of service.A 
    subordinate officer, or an under-officer or other enrolled person who is 
    retired, discharged, released, removed or dismissed from the service shall 
    be furnished by the officer, to whose command he is subject, with a 
    certificate in the language which is the mother tongue of such person and 
    also in Hindi or English language setting forth
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the authority terminating his 
    service;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the cause for such 
    termination; and
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the full period of his service 
    in the Force.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>13</number> Restrictions respecting 
      right to form association, freedom of speech, etc.
<section><number>1</number> No person subject to this 
      Act shall, without the previous sanction in writing of the Central 
      Government or of the prescribed authority,
 <subsection>         
      <number>a</number>   be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any 
      trade union, labour union, political association or with any class of 
      trade unions, labour unions or political associations; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>         
      <number>b</number>   be a member of, or be associated in any way with, any 
      society, institution, association or organisation that is not recognised 
      as part of the Force or is not of a purely social, recreational or 
      religious nature; or
 </subsection><subsection>         
      <number>c</number>   communicate with the press or publish or cause to be 
      published any book, letter or other document except where such 
      communication or publication is in the bona fide discharge of his 
      duties or is of a purely literary, artistic or scientific character or is 
      of a prescribed nature.
 Explanation.If any question arises as to 
      whether any society, institution, association or organisation is of a 
      purely social, recreational or religious nature under clause (b) of this 
      sub-section, the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be 
      final.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> No person subject to this 
      Act shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in any 
      demonstration organised by any body of persons for any political purposes 
      or for such other purposes as may be prescribed.
  
 
  
 
 
  
 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Offences in relation to 
    the enemy and punishable with death.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   shamefully abandons or 
    delivers up any post, place or guard, committed to his charge or which it is 
    his duty to defend; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   intentionally uses any means 
    to compel or induce any person subject to this Act or to military, naval or 
    air force law to abstain from acting against the enemy or to discourage such 
    person from acting against the enemy; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   in the presence of the enemy, 
    shamefully casts away his arms, ammunition, tools or equipment or misbehaves 
    in such manner as to show cowardice; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   treacherously holds 
    correspondence with , or communicates intelligence to, the enemy or any 
    person in arms against the Union; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   directly or indirectly assists 
    the enemy with money, arms, ammunition, stores or supplies or in any other 
    manner whatsoever; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   in time of active operation 
    against the enemy, intentionally occasions a false alarm in action, camp 
    quarters, or spreads or causes to be spread reports calculated to create 
    alarm or despondency; or
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   in time of action leaves his 
    Commandant or other superior officer or his post, guard, picket, patrol or 
    party without being regularly relieved or without leave; or
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   having been captured by the 
    enemy or made a prisoner of war, voluntarily serves with or aids the enemy; 
    or
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   knowingly harbours or protects 
    an enemy not being a prisoner; or
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   being a sentry in time of 
    active operation against the enemy or alarm, sleeps upon his post or is 
    intoxicated; or
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   knowingly does any act 
    calculated to imperil the success of the Force or the military, naval or air 
    force of India or any forces co-operating therewith or any part of such 
    forces,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer death or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Offences in relation to 
    the enemy and not punishable with death.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   is taken prisoner or captured 
    by the enemy, by want of due precaution or through disobedience of orders, 
    or wilful neglect of duty, or having been taken prisoner or so captured 
    fails to rejoin his service when able to do so; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   without due authority holds 
    correspondence with, or communicates intelligence to, the enemy or any 
    person in league with the enemy or having come by the knowledge of any such 
    correspondence or communication, wilfully omits to discover it immediately 
    to his Commandant or other superior officer,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Offences punishable 
    more severely on active duty than at other times.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   forces a safeguard, or forces 
    or uses criminal force to a sentry; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   breaks into any house or other 
    place in search of plunder; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   being a sentry sleeps upon his 
    post, or is intoxicated; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   without orders from his 
    superior officer leaves his guard, picket, patrol or post; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   intentionally or through 
    neglect occasions a false alarm in camp or quarters, or spreads or causes to 
    be spread reports calculated to create unnecessary alarm or despondency; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   makes known the parole, 
    watchword or countersign to any person not entitled to receive it; or 
    knowingly gives a parole, watchword or countersign different from what he 
    received,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court,
 <subsection>
<number>A</number>   if he commits any such offence 
    when on active duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>B</number>   if he commits any such offence 
    when not on active duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Mutiny.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   begins, incites, causes or 
    conspires with any other person to cause any mutiny in the Force or in the 
    military, naval or air forces of India or any forces co-operating therewith; 
    or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   joins in any such mutiny; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   being present at any such 
    mutiny, does not use his utmost endeavours to suppress the same; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   knowing or having reason to 
    believe in the existence of any such mutiny, or of any intention to mutiny 
    or of any such conspiracy, does not, without delay, give information thereof 
    to his Commandant or other superior officer; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   endeavours to seduce any person 
    in the Force or in the military, naval or air forces of India or any forces 
    co-operating therewith from his duty or allegiance to the Union,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer death or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Desertion and aiding 
    desertion.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person subject to this Act who deserts or attempts to desert the service 
    shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court,
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if he commits the offence when 
    on active duty or when under orders for active duty, be liable to suffer 
    death or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if he commits the offence 
    under any other circumstances, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person subject to 
    this Act who knowingly harbours any such deserter shall, on conviction by a 
    Security Force Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to seven years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person subject to 
    this Act who, being cognizant of any desertion or attempt at desertion of a 
    person subject to this Act, does not forthwith give notice to his own or 
    some other superior officer, or take any steps in his power to cause such 
    person to be apprehended, shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, be 
    liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years or 
    such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Absence without leave.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   absents himself without leave; 
    or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   without sufficient cause 
    overstays leave granted to him; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   being on leave of absence and 
    having received information from the appropriate authority that any 
    battalion or part thereof or any other unit of the Force, to which he 
    belongs, has been ordered on active duty, fails, without sufficient cause, 
    to rejoin without delay; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   without sufficient cause fails 
    to appear at the time fixed at the parade or place appointed for exercise or 
    duty; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   when on parade, or on the line 
    of march, without sufficient cause, or without leave from his superior 
    officer, quits the parade or line of march; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   when in camp or elsewhere, is 
    found beyond any limits fixed, or in any place prohibited, by any general, 
    local or other order, without a pass or written leave from his superior 
    officer; or
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   without leave from his 
    superior officer or without due cause, absents himself from any school when 
    duly ordered to attend there,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
    years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Striking or threatening 
    superior officers.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
         <number>a</number>   uses criminal force to or 
    assaults his superior officer; or
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>   uses threatening language to 
    such officer; or
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>   uses insubordinate language to 
    such officer;
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court,
 <subsection>
        <number>A</number>   if such officer is at the time 
    in the execution of his office or, if the offence is committed on active 
    duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
    fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>B</number>   in other cases, be liable to 
    suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten years or such less 
    punishment as is in this Act mentioned:
 
Provided that in the case 
    of an offence specified in clause (c), the imprisonment shall not exceed 
    five years.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Disobedience to 
    superior officer.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person subject to this Act who disobeys in such manner as to show a 
    wilful defiance of authority any lawful command given personally by his 
    superior officer in the execution of his office whether the same is given 
    orally, or in writing or by signal or otherwise, shall, on conviction by a 
    Security Force Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person subject to 
    this Act who disobeys any lawful command given by his superior officer 
    shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court,
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if he commits such offence 
    when on active duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if he commits such offence 
    when not on active duty, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to five years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Insubordination and 
    obstruction.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   being concerned in any 
    quarrel, affray or disorder, refuses to obey any officer, though of inferior 
    rank, who orders him into arrest, or uses criminal force to or assaults any 
    such officer; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   uses criminal force to, or 
    assaults any person, whether subject to this Act or not, in whose custody he 
    is lawfully placed, and whether he is or is not his superior officer; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   resists an escort whose duty 
    it is to apprehend him or to have him in charge; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   breaks out of barracks, camp 
    or quarters; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   neglects to obey any general, 
    local or other order; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   impedes the Force Police 
    referred to in section 63 or any person lawfully acting on his behalf, or 
    when called upon, refuses to assist in the execution of his duty a Force 
    Police or any person lawfully acting on his behalf,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend, in the 
    case of the offences specified in clauses (d) and (e), to two years, and in 
    the case of the offences specified in the other clauses, to ten years, or in 
    either case such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> False answers on 
    enrolment.Any 
    person having become subject to this Act who is discovered to have made at 
    the time of enrolment a wilfully false answer to any question set forth in 
    the prescribed form of enrolment which has been put to him by the enrolling 
    officer before whom he appears for the purpose of being enrolled, shall, on 
    conviction by a Security Force Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to five years or such less punishment as is in this 
    Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Certain forms of 
    disgraceful conduct.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   is guilty of any disgraceful 
    conduct of a cruel, indecent or unnatural kind; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   malingers, or feigns, or 
    produces disease or infirmity in himself or intentionally delays his cure or 
    aggravates his disease or infirmity; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   with intent to render himself 
    or any other person unfit for service, voluntarily causes hurt to himself or 
    that person,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven 
    years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Ill-treating a 
    subordinate.Any 
    officer, subordinate officer or under-officer, who uses criminal force to or 
    otherwise ill-treats any person subject to this Act, being his subordinate 
    in rank or position, shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, be 
    liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or 
    such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Intoxication.Any 
    person subject to this Act who is found in a state of intoxication, whether 
    on duty or not, shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, be liable to 
    suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or such less 
    punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Permitting escape of 
    person in custody.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   when in command of a guard, 
    picket, patrol or post, releases without proper authority, whether wilfully 
    or without reasonable excuse, any person committed to his charge, or refuses 
    to receive any prisoner or person so committed; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   wilfully or without reasonable 
    excuse allows to escape any person who is committed to his charge, or whom 
    it is his duty to keep or guard,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable, if he has acted wilfully, to suffer imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to ten years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned; and if he has not acted wilfully, to suffer imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to two years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Irregularity in 
    connection with arrest or confinement.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
         <number>a</number>   unnecessarily detains a person 
    in arrest or confinement without bringing him to trial, or fails to bring 
    his case before the proper authority for investigation; or
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>   having committed a person to 
    Force custody fails without reasonable cause to deliver at the time of such 
    committal, or as soon as practicable, and in any case within forty-eight 
    hours thereafter, to the officer or other person into whose custody the 
    person arrested is committed, an account in writing signed by himself of the 
    offence with which the person so committed is charged,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to one 
    year or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Escape from custody.Any 
    person subject to this Act, who, being in lawful custody, escapes or 
    attempts to escape, shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, be 
    liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or 
    such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Offences in respect of 
    property.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   commits theft of any property 
    belonging to the Government, or to any Force mess, band or institution, or 
    to any person subject to this Act; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    dishonestly misappropriates or converts to his own use any such property; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   commits 
    criminal breach of trust in respect of any such property; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   
    dishonestly receives or retains any such property in respect of which any of 
    the offences under clauses (a), (b) and (c) has been committed, knowing or 
    having reasons to believe the commission of such offences; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   wilfully 
    destroys or injures any property of the Government entrusted to him; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   does any 
    other thing with intent of defraud, or to cause wrongful gain to one person 
    or wrongful loss to another person,
 
shall, on conviction by a 
    Security Force Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to ten years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.




 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Extortion and corruption.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
         <number>a</number>   commits 
    extortion; or
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>   without 
    proper authority exacts from any person money, provisions or service,
 
shall, on conviction by a 
    Security Force Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may 
    extend to ten years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.



 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Making away with 
    equipment.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   makes away with, or is 
    concerned in making away with, any arms, ammunition equipment, instruments, 
    tools, clothing or any other thing being the property of the Government 
    issued to him for his use or entrusted to him; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   loses by neglect anything 
    mentioned in clause (a); or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   sells, pawns, destroys or 
    defaces any medal or decoration granted to him,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend, in the 
    case of the offences specified in clause (a), to ten years, and in the case 
    of the offences specified in the other clauses, to five years, or in either 
    case such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Injury to property.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   destroys or injures any 
    property mentioned in clause (a) of section 32, or any property belonging to 
    any Force mess, band or institution, or to any person subject to this Act; 
    or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   commits any act which causes 
    damage to, or destruction of, any property of the Government by fire; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   kills, injures, makes away 
    with, ill-treats or loses any, animal entrusted to him,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable, if he has acted wilfully, to suffer imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to ten years or such less punishment as is in Act 
    mentioned; and if he has acted without reasonable excuse, to suffer 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or such less 
    punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> False accusations.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   makes a false accusation 
    against any person subject to this Act, knowing or having reason to believe 
    such accusation to be false; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   in making a complaint against 
    any person subject to this Act makes any statement affecting the character 
    of such person, knowing or having reason to believe such statement to be 
    false, or knowingly and wilfully suppresses any material facts,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
    years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Falsifying official 
    documents and false declarations.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
         <number>a</number>   in any report, return, list, 
    certificate, book or other document made or signed by him, or of the 
    contents of which it is his duty to ascertain the accuracy, knowingly makes, 
    or is privy to the making of, any false or fraudulent statement; or
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>   in any document of the 
    description mentioned in clause (a) knowingly makes, or is privy to the 
    making of, any omission, with intent to defraud; or
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>   knowingly and with intent to 
    injure any person, or knowingly and with intent to defraud, suppresses, 
    defaces, alters or makes away with any document which it is his duty to 
    preserve or produce; or
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>   where it is his official duty to 
    make a declaration respecting any matter, knowingly makes a false 
    declaration; or
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>   obtains for himself, or for any 
    other person, any pension, allowance or other advantage or privilege by a 
    statement which is false, and which he either knows or believes to be false 
    or does not believe to be true, or by making or using a false entry in any 
    book or record, or by making any document containing a false statement, or 
    by omitting to make a true entry or document containing a true statement,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to ten 
    years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Signing in blank and 
    failure to report.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   when signing any document 
    relating to pay, arms, ammunition, equipment, clothing, supplies or stores, 
    or any property of the Government fraudulently leaves in blank any material 
    part for which his signature is a voucher; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   refuses or by culpable neglect 
    omits to make or send a report or return which it is his duty to make or 
    send,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
    years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Offences relating to 
    Security Force Court.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   being duly summoned or ordered 
    to attend as a witness before a Security Force Court, wilfully or without 
    reasonable excuse, makes default in attending; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   refuses to take an oath or 
    make an affirmation legally required by a Security Force Court to be taken 
    or made; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   refuses to produce or deliver 
    any document in his power or control legally required by a Security Force 
    Court to be produced or delivered by him; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   refuses, when a witness, to 
    answer any question which he is by law bound to answer; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   is guilty of contempt of the 
    Security Force Court by using insulting or threatening language, or by 
    causing any interruption or disturbance in the proceedings of such court,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
    years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> False evidence.Any 
    person subject to this Act who, having been duly sworn or affirmed before 
    any Security Force Court or other court competent under this Act to 
    administer an oath or affirmation, makes any statement which is false, and 
    which he either knows or believes to be false or does not believe to be 
    true, shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, be liable to suffer 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or such less 
    punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Unlawful detention of 
    pay.Any 
    officer, subordinate officer or an under-officer who, having received the 
    pay of a person subject to this Act unlawfully detains or refuses to pay the 
    same when due, shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, be liable to 
    suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or such less 
    punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Violation of good order 
    and discipline.Any 
    person subject to this Act who is guilty of any act or omission which, 
    though not specified in this Act, is prejudicial to good order and 
    discipline of the Force shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, be 
    liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years or 
    such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.



 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Miscellaneous offences.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any of the following offences, that 
    is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   being in command at any post 
    or on the march, and receiving a complaint that any one under his command 
    has beaten or otherwise maltreated or oppressed any person, or has disturbed 
    any fair or market, or committed any riot or trespass, fails to have due 
    reparation made to the injured person or to report the case to the proper 
    authority; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   by defiling any place of 
    worship, or otherwise, intentionally insults the religion, or wounds the 
    religious feelings of, any person; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   attempts to commit suicide, 
    and in such attempt does any act towards the commission of such offence; or
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   being below the rank of 
    subordinate officer, when off duty, appears without proper authority, in or 
    about camp, or in or about, or when going to, or returning from, any town or 
    bazaar, carrying a rifle, sword or other offensive weapon; or
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   directly or indirectly accepts 
    or obtains, or agrees to accept, or attempts to obtain, for himself or for 
    any other person, any gratification as a motive or reward for procuring the 
    enrolment of any person, or leave of absence, promotion or any other 
    advantage or indulgence for any person in the service; or
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   commits any offence against 
    the property or person of any inhabitant of, or resident in, the country in 
    which he is serving,
 
shall, on conviction by a Security Force 
    Court, be liable to suffer imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven 
    years or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Attempt.Any 
    person subject to this Act who attempts to commit any of the offences 
    specified in sections 14 to 41 (both inclusive) and in such attempt does any 
    act towards the commission of the offence shall, on conviction by a Security 
    Force Court, where no express provision is made by this Act for the 
    punishment of such attempt, be liable,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   if the offence attempted to be 
    committed is punishable with death, to suffer imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to fourteen years or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if the offence attempted to be 
    committed is punishable with imprisonment, to suffer imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to one half of the longest term provided for that offence 
    or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>43</number> Abetment of offences 
    that have been committed.Any 
    person subject to this Act who abets the commission of any of the offences 
    specified in sections 14 to 41 (both inclusive) shall, on conviction by a 
    Security Force Court, if the Act abetted is committed in consequence of the 
    abetment and no express provision is made by this Act for the punishment of 
    such abetment, be liable to suffer the punishment provided for that offence 
    or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Abetment of offences 
    punishable with death and not committed.Any 
    person subject to this Act who abets the commission of any of the offences 
    punishable with death under sections 14, 17 and sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
    18 shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, if that offence be not 
    committed in consequence of the abetment, and no express provision is made 
    by this Act for the punishment of such abetment, be liable to suffer 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to fourteen years or such less 
    punishment as is in this Act mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>45</number> Abetment of offences 
    punishable with imprisonment and not committed.Any 
    person subject to this Act who abets the commission of any of the offences 
    specified in sections 14 to 41 (both inclusive) and punishable with 
    imprisonment shall, on conviction by a Security Force Court, if that offence 
    be not committed in consequence of the abetment, and no express provision is 
    made by this Act for the punishment of such abetment, be liable to suffer 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to one-half of the longest term 
    provided for that offence or such less punishment as is in this Act 
    mentioned.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>46</number> Civil offences.Subject 
    to the provisions of section 47, any person subject to this Act who at any 
    place in, or beyond, India commits any civil offence shall be deemed to be 
    guilty of an offence against this Act and, if charged therewith under this 
    section shall be liable to be tried by a Security Force Court and, on 
    conviction, be punishable as follows, that is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   if the offence is one which 
    would be punishable under any law in force in India with death, he shall be 
    liable to suffer any punishment, assigned for the offence, by the aforesaid 
    law and such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   in any other case, he shall be 
    liable to suffer any punishment, assigned for the offence by the law in 
    force in India, or imprisonment for a term which may extend to seven years, 
    or such less punishment as is in this Act mentioned.





 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Civil offences not 
    triable by a Security Force Court.A 
    person subject to this Act who commits an offence of murder or of culpable 
    homicide not amounting to murder against, or of rape in relation to, a 
    person not subject to this Act shall not be deemed to be guilty of an 
    offence against this Act and shall not be tried by a Security Force Court, 
    unless he commits any of the said offences,
 <section>
         <number>a</number>   while on active duty; or
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>   at any place outside India; or
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>   at any place specified by the 
    Central Government by notification in this behalf.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>48</number> Punishments awardable 
    by Security Force Courts.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Punishments may be inflicted in respect of offences committed by persons 
    subject to this Act and convicted by Security Force Courts according to the 
    scale following, that is to say,
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   death;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   imprisonment which may be for 
    the term of life or any other lesser term but excluding imprisonment for a 
    term not exceeding three months in Force custody;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   dismissal from the service;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   imprisonment for a term not 
    exceeding three months in Force custody;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   reduction to the ranks or to a 
    lower rank or grade or place in the list of their rank in the case of an 
    under-officer;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   forfeiture of seniority of 
    rank and forfeiture of all or any part of the service for the purpose of 
    promotion
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   forfeiture of service for the 
    purpose of increased pay, pension or any other prescribed purpose;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   fine, in respect of civil 
    offences;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   severe reprimand or reprimand 
    except in the case of persons below the rank of an under-officer
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   forfeiture of pay and 
    allowances for a period not exceeding three months for an offence committed 
    on active duty;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   forfeiture in the case of 
    person sentenced to dismissal from the service of all arrears of pay and 
    allowances and other public money due to him at the time of such dismissal;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   stoppage of pay and allowances 
    until any proved loss or damage occasioned by the offence for which he is 
    convicted is made good.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Each of the punishments 
    specified in sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be inferior in degree to 
    every punishment preceding it in the above scale.



 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Alternative punishments 
    awardable by Security Force Courts.Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, a Security Force Court may, on convicting a 
    person subject to this Act of any of the offences specified in sections 14 
    to 45 (both inclusive) award either the particular punishment with which the 
    offence is stated in the said sections to be punishable or, in lieu thereof, 
    any one of the punishments lower in the scale set out in section 48 regard 
    being had to the nature and degree of the offence.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Combination of 
    punishments.A 
    sentence of a Security Force Court may award in addition to, or without any 
    one other punishment, the punishment specified in clause (c) of sub-section 
    
<section><number>1</number> of section 48, and any one or more of the punishments specified in 
    clauses (e) to (l) (both inclusive) of that sub-section.




 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Retention in the Force 
    of a person convicted on active duty.When 
    on active duty any enrolled person has been sentenced by a Security Force 
    Court to dismissal or to imprisonment whether combined with dismissal or 
    not, the prescribed officer may direct that such person may be retained to 
    serve in the ranks, and such service shall be reckoned as part of his term 
    of imprisonment if any.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Punishments otherwise 
    than by Security Force Courts.Punishments 
    may also be inflicted in respect of offences committed by persons subject to 
    this Act without the intervention of a Security Force Court in the manner 
    stated in sections 53 and 55.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>53</number> Minor punishments.Subject 
    to the provisions of section 54, a commandant or such other officer as is, 
    with the consent of Central Government, specified by the Director-General 
    may, in the prescribed manner, proceed against a person subject to this Act, 
    otherwise than as an officer or a subordinate officer, who is charged with 
    an offence under this Act and award such person, to the extent prescribed, 
    one or more of the following punishments, that is to say,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   imprisonment in Force custody upto twenty-eight days;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   detention upto twenty-eight 
    days;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   confinement to the lines upto 
    twenty-eight days;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   extra guards or duties;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   deprivation of any special 
    position or special emoluments or any acting rank or reduction to a lower 
    grade of pay;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   forfeiture of good service and 
    good conduct pay;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   severe reprimand or reprimand;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   fine upto fourteen days pay in 
    any one month;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   deductions from his pay of any 
    sum required to make good such compensation for any expenses, loss, damage 
    or destruction caused by him to the Central Government, or to any building 
    or property as may be awarded by his commandant.
  



 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>54</number> Limit of punishments 
    under section 53.
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the case of an award of two or more of the punishments specified in 
    clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number>, (b), (c) and (d) of section 53, the punishments specified in 
    clause (c) or clause (d) shall take effect only at the end of the punishment 
    specified in clause (a) or clause (b).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When two or more of the 
    punishments specified in the said clauses (a), (b) and (c) are awarded to a 
    person conjointly, or when already undergoing one or more of the said 
    punishments, the whole extent of the punishments shall not exceed in the 
    aggregate forty-two days.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The punishments 
    specified in the said clauses (a), (b) and (c) shall not be awarded to any 
    person who is of the rank of an under-officer or was, at the time of 
    committing the offence for which he is punished, of such rank.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The punishment 
    specified in clause (g) of section 53 shall not be awarded to any person 
    below the rank of an under-officer.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>55</number> Punishment of persons of and below the rank of subordinate officers by Deputy Inspectors-General and others. </title>
<section><number>1</number> An officer not below the rank of the Deputy Inspector-General or such other officer as is, with the consent of the Central Government, specified by the Director-General may, in the prescribed manner, proceed against a person of or below the rank of a subordinate officer who is charged with an offence under this Act and award one or more of the following punishments, that is to say, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> forfeiture of seniority, or in the case of any of them whose promotion depends upon the length of service forfeiture of service for the purpose of promotion for a period not exceeding twelve months, but subject to the right of the accused previous to the award to elect to be tried by a Security Force Court; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> severe reprimand or reprimand; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> stoppage of pay and allowances until any proved loss or damage occasioned by the offence of which he is convicted is made good. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> In every case in which punishment has been awarded under sub-section (1), certified true copies of the proceedings shall be forwarded, in the prescribed manner, by the officer awarding the punishment to the prescribed superior authority who may, if the punishment awarded appears to him to be illegal, unjust or excessive, cancel, vary or remit the punishment and make such other direction as may be appropriate in the circumstances of the case. 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>56</number> Collective fines.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever any weapon or part of a weapon, or ammunition, forming part of the 
    equipment of a unit of the Force, is lost or stolen, an officer not below 
    the rank of the Commandant of a battalion may, after making such enquiry as 
    he thinks fit and subject to the rules, impose a collective fine upon the 
    subordinate officers, under-officers and men of such unit, or upon so many 
    of them as, in his judgment, should be held responsible for such loss or 
    theft.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such fine shall be 
    assessed as a percentage on the pay of the individuals on whom it falls.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>57</number> Custody of offenders.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person subject to this Act who is charged with an offence may be taken 
    into Force custody, under the order of any superior officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub-section (1), an officer may order into Force 
    custody any other officer, though such other officer may be of a higher 
    rank, engaged in a quarrel, affray or disorder.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>58</number> Duty of commandant in 
    regard to detention.
<section><number>1</number> 
    It shall be the duty of every Commandant to take care that a person under 
    his command when charged with an offence is not detained in custody for more 
    than forty-eight hours after the committal of such person into custody is 
    reported to him, without the charge being investigated, unless investigation 
    within that period seems to him to be impracticable having regard to the 
    public service.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The case of every 
    person being detained in custody beyond a period of forty-eight hours, and 
    the reasons therefor, shall be reported by the Commandant to the Deputy 
    Inspector-General under whom he is serving or such other officer to whom an 
    application may be made to convene a Security Force Court for the trial of 
    the person charged.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In reckoning the period 
    of forty-eight hours specified in sub-section (1), Sundays and other public 
    holidays shall be excluded.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to the 
    provisions of this Act, the Central Government may make rules providing for 
    the manner in which and the period for which any person subject to this Act 
    may be taken into and detained in Force custody, pending the trial by any 
    competent authority for any offence committed by him.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>59</number> Interval between 
    committal and trial.In 
    every case where any such person as is mentioned in section 57 and as is not 
    on active duty, remains in such custody for a longer period than eight days 
    without a Security Force Court for his trial being convened, a special 
    report giving reasons for the delay shall be made by his Commandant in the 
    manner prescribed, and a similar report shall be forwarded at intervals of 
    every eight days until a Security Force Court is convened or such person is 
    released from custody.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>60</number> Arrest by civil 
    authorities.Whenever 
    any person subject to this Act, who is accused of an offence under this Act, 
    is within the jurisdiction of any magistrate or police officer, such 
    magistrate or police officer shall aid in the apprehension and delivery to 
    Force custody of such person upon receipt of a written application to that 
    effect signed by his Commandant or an officer authorised by the Commandant 
    in that behalf.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>61</number> Capture of deserters.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever any person subject to this Act deserts, the Commandant of the unit 
    to which he belongs, shall give information of the desertion to such civil 
    authorities as, in his opinion, may be able to afford assistance towards the 
    capture of the deserter; and such authorities shall thereupon take steps for 
    the apprehension of the said deserter in like manner as if he were a person 
    for whose apprehension a warrant had been issued by a magistrate, and shall 
    deliver the deserter, when apprehended, into Force custody.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any police officer may 
    arrest without warrant any person reasonably believed to be subject to this 
    Act, and to be a deserter or to be travelling without authority and shall 
    bring him without delay before the nearest magistrate, to be dealt with 
    according to law.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>62</number> Inquiry into absence 
    without leave.
<section><number>1</number> 
    When any person subject to this Act has been absent from duty without due 
    authority for a period of thirty days, a court of inquiry shall, as soon as 
    practicable, be appointed by such authority and in such manner as may be 
    prescribed; and such court shall, on oath or affirmation administered in the 
    prescribed manner, inquire respecting the absence of the person, and the 
    deficiency, if any, in the property of the Government entrusted to his care, 
    or in any arms, ammunition, equipment, instruments, clothing or necessaries; 
    and if satisfied of the fact of such absence without due authority or other 
    sufficient cause, the court shall declare such absence and the period 
    thereof and the said deficiency, if any, and the Commandant of the unit to 
    which the person belongs shall make a record thereof in the prescribed 
    manner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the person declared 
    absent does not afterwards surrender or is not apprehended, he shall for the 
    purposes of this Act, be deemed to be a deserter.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>63</number> Force police officers.
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Director-General or any prescribed officer may appoint persons (in this 
    Act referred to as Force police) for discharging the functions specified in 
    sub-sections (2) and (3).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The duties of a person 
    appointed under sub-section (1), are to take charge of persons confined for 
    any offence, to preserve good order and discipline and to prevent breaches 
    of the same by persons serving in, or attached to, the Force.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 57, a person appointed under sub-section (1) 
    may, at any time, arrest and detain for trial any person subject to this Act 
    who commits, or is charged with, an offence, and may also carry into effect 
    any punishment to be inflicted in pursuance of a sentence awarded by a 
    Security Force Court or by an officer exercising authority under section 53 
    but shall not inflict any punishment on his own authority:
 
Provided that no officer 
    shall be so arrested or detained otherwise than on the order of another 
    officer.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>64</number> Kinds of Security Force 
    Courts.For the 
    purposes of this Act there shall be three kinds of Security Force Courts, 
    that is to say,
 <section>
         <number>a</number>   General Security Force Courts;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>   Petty Security Force Courts; 
    and
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>   Summary Security Force Courts.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>65</number> Power to convene a 
    General Security Force Court.A 
    General Security Force Court may be convened by the Central Government or 
    the Director-General or by any officer empowered in this behalf by warrant 
    of the Director-General.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>66</number> Power to convene a 
    Petty Security Force Court.A 
    Petty Security Force Court may be convened by an officer having power to 
    convene a General Security Force Court or by an officer empowered in this 
    behalf by warrant of any such officer.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Contents of warrants 
    issued under sections 65 and 66.A 
    warrant, issued under section 65 or section 66 may contain such 
    restrictions, reservations or conditions as the officer issuing it may think 
    fit.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>68</number> Composition of General 
    Security Force Court.A 
    General Security Force Court shall consist of not less than five officers, 
    each of whom has held the post of Deputy Superintendent of Police for not 
    less than three whole years and of whom not less than four are of a rank not 
    below that of a confirmed Deputy Superintendent of Police.
 
Explanation.For 
    the purposes of this section and section 69 Deputy Superintendent of 
    Police includes any post of a higher rank and any post declared by Central 
    Government by notification to be an equivalent post as also any post higher 
    in rank than the post so declared.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Composition of a Petty 
    Security Force Court.A 
    Petty Security Force Court shall consist of not less than three officers 
    each of whom has held the post of Deputy Superintendent of Police for not 
    less than two whole years.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>70</number> Summary Security Force 
    Court.
<section><number>1</number> A 
    Summary Security Force Court may be held by the Commandant of any unit of 
    the Force and he alone shall constitute the Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The proceedings shall 
    be attended throughout by two other persons who shall be officers or 
    subordinate officers or one of either, and who shall not as such, be sworn 
    or affirmed.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>71</number> Dissolution of a 
    Security Force Court.
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a Security Force Court after the commencement of a trial is reduced below 
    the minimum number of officers required by this Act, it shall be dissolved.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, on account of the 
    illness of the Law Officer or of the accused before the finding, it is 
    impossible to continue the trial, a Security Force Court shall be dissolved.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The officer who 
    convened a Security Force Court may dissolve the same if it appears to him 
    that the exigencies of the service or necessities of discipline render it 
    impossible or inexpedient to continue the said Security Force Court.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a Security Force 
    Court is dissolved under this section, the accused may be tried again.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>72</number> Powers of a General 
    Security Force Court.A 
    General Security Force Court shall have the power to try any person subject 
    to this Act for any offence punishable thereunder and to any sentence 
    authorised thereby.



 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>73</number> Powers of a Petty 
    Security Force Court.A 
    Petty Security Force Court shall have power to try any person subject to 
    this Act other than an officer or a subordinate officer for any offence made 
    punishable thereunder and to pass any sentence authorised by this Act other 
    than a sentence of death, or imprisonment for a term exceeding two years.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> Powers of a Summary 
    Security Force Court.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), a Summary Security Force Court 
    may try any offence punishable under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When there is no grave 
    reason for immediate action and reference can without detriment to 
    discipline be made to the officer empowered to convene a Petty Security 
    Force Court for the trial of the alleged offender, an officer holding a 
    Summary Security Force Court shall not try without such reference any 
    offence punishable under any of the sections 14, 17 and 46 of this Act, or 
    any offence against the officer holding the court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A Summary Security 
    Force Court may try any person subject to this Act and under the command of 
    the officer holding the court, except an officer, or a subordinate officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A Summary Security 
    Force Court may pass any sentence which may be passed under this Act, except 
    the sentence of death or of imprisonment for a term exceeding the limit 
    specified in sub-section (5). 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The limit referred to 
    in sub-section (4) shall be,
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   one year, if the officer 
    holding the Security Force Court has held either the post of Superintendent 
    of Police or a post declared by the Central Government by notification to be 
    equivalent thereto, for a period of not less than three years or holds a 
    post of higher rank than either of the said posts; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   three months, in any other 
    case.



 


 
 

 

 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> Prohibition of second 
    trial.
<section><number>1</number> When 
    any person subject to this Act has been acquitted or convicted of an offence 
    by a Security Force Court or by a criminal court or has been dealt with 
    under section 53 or under section 55, he shall not be liable to be tried 
    again for the same offence by a Security Force Court or dealt with under the 
    said sections.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When any person, 
    subject to this Act, has been acquitted or convicted of any offence by a 
    Security Force Court or has been dealt with under section 53 or section 55, 
    he shall not be liable to be tried again by a criminal court for the same 
    offence or on the same facts.



 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> Period of limitation 
    for trial for an offence of desertion in certain cases.No 
    trial for an offence of desertion, other than desertion on active duty, 
    shall be commenced if the person in question, not being an officer, has 
    subsequently to the commission of the offence, served continuously in an 
    exemplary manner for not less than three years with any unit of the Force.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> Trial, etc., of 
    offender who ceases to be subject to this Act.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an offence under this Act had been committed by any person while 
    subject to this Act, and he has ceased to be so subject, he may be taken 
    into and kept in Force custody and tried and punished for such offence as if 
    he continued to be so subject.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No such person shall be 
    tried for an offence, unless his trial commences within six months after he 
    had ceased to be subject to this Act :
 
Provided that nothing 
    contained in this sub-section shall apply to the trial of any such person 
    for an offence of desertion or for any of the offences mentioned in section 
    17 or shall affect the jurisdiction of a criminal court to try any offence 
    triable by such court as well as by a Security Force Court.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> Application of Act 
    during term of sentence.
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a person subject to this Act is sentenced by a Security Force Court to 
    imprisonment, this Act shall apply to him during the term of his sentence, 
    though he is dismissed from the Force, or has otherwise ceased to be subject 
    to this Act, and he may be kept, removed, imprisoned and punished as if he 
    continued to be subject to this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a person subject 
    to this Act is sentenced by a Security Force Court to death, this Act shall 
    apply to him till the sentence is carried out.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> Place of trial.Any 
    person subject to this Act who commits any offence against it may be tried 
    and punished for such offence in any place whatever.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> Choice between criminal 
    court and Security Force Court.When 
    a Criminal Court and a Security Force Court have each jurisdiction in 
    respect of an offence, it shall be in the discretion of the 
    Director-General, or the Inspector-General or the Deputy Inspector-General 
    within whose command the accused person is serving or such other officer as 
    may be prescribed, to decide before which court the proceedings shall be 
    instituted, and, if that officer decides that they shall be instituted 
    before a Security Force Court, to direct that the accused person shall be 
    detained in Force custody.




 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>81</number> 
    Power of criminal court to require delivery of offender.
<section><number>1</number> 
    When a criminal court having jurisdiction is of opinion that proceedings 
    shall be instituted before itself in respect of any alleged offence, it may, 
    by written notice, require the officer referred to in section 80 at his 
    option, either to deliver over the offender to the nearest Magistrate to be 
    proceeded against according to law, or to postpone proceedings, pending a 
    reference to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    every such case the said officer shall either deliver over the offender in 
    compliance with the requisition, or shall forthwith refer the question as to 
    the court before which the proceedings are to be instituted, for the 
    determination of the Central Government whose order upon such reference 
    shall be final.



 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> Presiding Officer.At 
    every General Security Force Court or Petty Security Force Court, the senior 
    member shall be the Presiding Officer.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> Law Officer.Every 
    General Security Force Court shall, and every Petty Security Force Court 
    may, be attended by a Law Officer, or if no such officer is available, an 
    officer approved by the Chief Law Officer, or a Law Officer.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>84</number> Challenges.
<section><number>1</number> 
    At all trials by a General Security Force Court or by a Petty Security Force 
    Court, as soon as the court is assembled, the names of the presiding officer 
    and members shall be read over to the accused, who shall thereupon be asked 
    whether he objects to being tried by any officer sitting on the court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the accused objects 
    to such officer, his objection and also the reply thereto of the officer 
    objected to shall be heard and recorded, and the remaining officers of the 
    court shall in the absence of the challenged officer decide on the 
    objection.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the objection is 
    allowed by one-half or more of the votes of the officers entitled to vote, 
    the objection shall be allowed, and the member objected to shall retire, and 
    his vacancy may be filled in the prescribed manner, by another officer 
    subject to the same right of the accused to object.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When no challenge is 
    made, or when a challenge has been made and disallowed, or the place of 
    every officer successfully challenged has been filled by another officer to 
    whom no objection is made or allowed, the court shall proceed with the 
    trial.
  


 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> Oaths of member, Law 
    Officer and witness.
<section><number>1</number> 
    An oath or affirmation in the prescribed manner shall be administered to 
    every member of every Security Force Court and to the Law Officer or as the 
    case may be the officer approved under section 83, before the commencement 
    of the trial.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person giving 
    evidence before a Security Force Court shall be examined after being duly 
    sworn or affirmed in the prescribed form.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of 
    sub-section (2) shall not apply where the witness is a child under twelve 
    years of age and the Security Force Court is of opinion that though the 
    witness understands the duty of speaking the truth, he does not understand 
    the nature of an oath or affirmation.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>86</number> Voting by members.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3), every decision of a 
    Security Force Court shall be passed by an absolute majority of votes; and 
    where there is an equality of votes on either the finding or the sentence, 
    the decision shall be in favour of the accused.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No sentence of death 
    shall be passed by a General Security Force Court without the concurrence of 
    at least two-thirds of the members of the court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In matters, other than 
    a challenge or the finding or sentence, the presiding officer shall have a 
    casting vote.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>87</number> General rule as to 
    evidence.The 
    Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), shall, subject to the provisions of 
    this Act, apply to all proceedings before a Security Force Court.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>88</number> Judicial notice.A 
    Security Force Court may take judicial notice of any matter within the 
    general knowledge of the members as officers of the Force.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>89</number> Summoning witnesses.
<section><number>1</number> 
    The convening officer, the presiding officer of a Security Force Court, the 
    Law Officer or, as the case may be, the officer approved under section 83 or 
    the Commandant of the accused person may, by summons under his hand, require 
    the attendance at a time and place to be mentioned in the summons, of any 
    person either to give evidence or to produce any document or other thing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of a 
    witness who is subject to this Act, the summons shall be sent to his 
    Commandant and such officer shall serve it upon him accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the case of any 
    other witness, the summons shall be sent to the magistrate within whose 
    jurisdiction he may be, or resides, and such magistrate shall give effect to 
    the summons as if the witness were required in the court of such a 
    magistrate.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When a witness is 
    required to produce any particular document or other thing in his possession 
    or power, the summons shall describe it with reasonable precision.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>90</number> Documents exempted from 
    production.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nothing in section 89 shall be deemed to affect the operation of sections 
    123 and 124 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872) or to apply to any 
    letter, postcard, telegram or other document in the custody of the postal or 
    telegraph authorities.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any document in such 
    custody is, in the opinion of any District Magistrate, Chief Presidency 
    Magistrate, High Court or Court of Sessions, wanted for the purpose of any 
    Security Force Court, such magistrate, or court may require the postal or 
    telegraph authorities, as the case may be, to deliver such document to such 
    person as such magistrate, or court may direct.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If any such document 
    is, in the opinion of any other magistrate or of any Commissioner of Police 
    or District Superintendent of Police, wanted for any such purpose, he may 
    require the postal or telegraph authorities, as the case may be, to cause 
    such search to be made for, and to detain such document pending the orders 
    of any such District Magistrate, Chief Presidency Magistrate or High Court 
    or Court of Sessions.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>91</number> Commissions for 
    examination of witnesses.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever in the course of a trial by a Security Force Court, it appears to 
    the court that the examination of a witness is necessary for the ends of 
    justice, and that the attendance of such witness cannot be procured without 
    an amount of delay, expense or inconvenience which, in the circumstances of 
    the case, would be unreasonable, such court may address the Chief Law 
    Officer in order that a commission to take the evidence of such witness may 
    be issued.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Law Officer 
    may then, if he thinks necessary, issue a commission to any District 
    Magistrate or Magistrate of the first class, within the local limits of 
    whose jurisdiction such witness resides, to take the evidence of such 
    witness.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The magistrate or 
    officer to whom the commission is issued, or, if he is the District 
    Magistrate, he or such Magistrate of the first class as he appoints in this 
    behalf, shall proceed to the place where the witness is, or shall summon the 
    witness before him and shall take down his evidence in the same manner, and 
    may for this purpose exercise the same powers, as in the trial of warrant 
    cases under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When the witness 
    resides in a tribal area or in any place outside India, the commission may 
    be issued in the manner specified in Chapter XL of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>92</number> Examination of witness 
    on commission.
<section><number>1</number> 
    The prosecutor and the accused person in any case in which a commission is 
    issued under section 91 may respectively forward any interrogatories in 
    writing which the court may think relevant to the issue, and the Magistrate 
    or officer executing the commission shall examine the witness upon such 
    interrogatories.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The prosecutor and the 
    accused person may appear before such Magistrate or officer by counsel or, 
    except in the case of an accused person in custody, in person, and may 
    examine, cross-examine and re-examine, as the case may be, the said witness.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After a commission 
    issued under section 91 has been duly executed, it shall be returned, 
    together with the deposition of the witness examined thereunder to the Chief 
    Law Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of a 
    Commission, and deposition returned under sub-section (3), the Chief Law 
    Officer shall forward the same to the Court at whose instance the commission 
    was issued or, if such court has been dissolved, to any other court convened 
    for the trial of the accused person; and the commission, the return thereto 
    and the deposition shall be open to inspection by the prosecutor and the 
    accused person, and may, subject to all just exceptions, be read in evidence 
    in the case by either the prosecutor or the accused, and shall form part of 
    the proceedings of the court.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In every case in which 
    a commission is issued under section 91, the trial may be adjourned for 
    specified time reasonably sufficient for the execution and return of the 
    commission.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>93</number> Conviction of offence 
    not charged.
<section><number>1</number> 
    A person charged before a Security Force Court with desertion may be found 
    guilty of attempting to desert or of being absent without leave.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person charged before 
    a Security Force Court with attempting to desert may be found guilty of 
    being absent without leave.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person charged before 
    a Security Force Court with using criminal force may be found guilty of 
    assault.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A person charged before 
    a Security Force Court with using threatening language may be found guilty 
    of using insubordinate language.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A person charged before 
    a Security Force Court with any one of the offences specified in clauses 
    (a), (b), (c) and (d) of section 30 may be found guilty of any other of 
    these offences with which he might have been charged.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A person charged before 
    a Security Force Court with an offence punishable under section 46 may be 
    found guilty of any other offence of which he might have been found guilty, 
    if the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), were 
    applicable.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A person charged before 
    a Security Force Court with any offence under this Act may, on failure of 
    proof of an offence having been committed in circumstances involving a more 
    severe punishment, be found guilty of the same offence as having been 
    committed in circumstances involving a less severe punishment.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A person charged before 
    a Security Force Court with any offence under this Act may be found guilty 
    of having attempted or abetted the Commission of that offence, although the 
    attempt or abetment is not separately charged.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>94</number> Presumption as to 
    signatures.In 
    any proceeding under this Act, any application, certificate, warrant, reply 
    or other document purporting to be signed by an officer in the service of 
    the Government shall, on production, be presumed to have been duly signed by 
    the person by whom and in the character in which it purports to have been 
    signed, until the contrary is shown.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>95</number> Enrolment paper.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any enrolment paper purporting to be signed by an enrolling officer shall, 
    in proceedings under this Act, be evidence of the person enrolled having 
    given the answers to questions which he is therein represented as having 
    given.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The enrolment of such 
    person may be proved by the production of the original or a copy of his 
    enrolment paper purporting to be certified to be a true copy by the officer 
    having the custody of the enrolment paper.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>96</number> Presumption as to 
    certain documents.
<section><number>1</number> 
    A letter, return or other document respecting the service of any person in, 
    or the dismissal or discharge of any person from, any unit of the Force, or 
    respecting the circumstances of any person not having served in, or belonged 
    to, any unit of the Force, if purporting to be signed by or on behalf of the 
    Central Government or the Director-General, or by any prescribed officer, 
    shall be evidence of the facts stated in such letter, return or other 
    document.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Border Security Force 
    List or Gazette purporting to be published by authority shall be evidence of 
    the status and rank of the officers, subordinate officers therein mentioned, 
    and of any appointment held by them and of the battalion, unit, or branch of 
    the Force to which they belong.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a record is made 
    in any battalion book in pursuance of this Act or of any rules made 
    thereunder or otherwise in the discharge of official duties and purports to 
    be signed by the commandant or by the officer whose duty it is to make such 
    record, such record shall be evidence of the facts therein stated.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A copy of any record in 
    any battalion book purporting to be certified to be a true copy by the 
    officer having custody of such book shall be evidence of such record.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where any person 
    subject to this Act is being tried on a charge of desertion or of absence 
    without leave, and such person has surrendered himself into the custody of 
    any officer or other person subject to this Act, or any unit of the Force, 
    or has been apprehended by such officer or person, a certificate purporting 
    to be signed by such officer, or by the Commandant of the unit to which such 
    person belongs, as the case may be, and stating the fact, date and place of 
    such surrender or apprehension, and the manner in which he was dressed, 
    shall be evidence of the matters so stated.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where any person 
    subject to this Act is being tried on a charge of desertion or of absence 
    without leave and such person has surrendered himself into the custody of, 
    or has been apprehended by, a police officer not below the rank of an 
    officer in charge of a police station, a certificate purporting to be signed 
    by such police officer and stating the fact, date and place of such 
    surrender or apprehension and the manner in which he was dressed shall be 
    evidence of the matters so stated.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any document purporting 
    to be a report under the hand of any Chemical Examiner or Assistant Chemical 
    Examiner to Government upon any matter or thing duly submitted to him for 
    examination or analysis and report, may be used as evidence in any 
    proceeding under this Act.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>97</number> Reference by accused to 
    Government Officer.
<section><number>1</number> 
    If at any trial for desertion or absence without leave, overstaying leave or 
    not rejoining when warned for service, the accused person states in his 
    defence any sufficient or reasonable excuse for his unauthorised absence, 
    and refers in support thereof to any officer in the service of the 
    Government, or if it appears that any such officer is likely to prove or 
    disprove the said statement in the defence, the court shall address such 
    officer and adjourn the proceedings until his reply is received.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The written reply of 
    any officer so referred to shall, if signed by him, be received in evidence 
    and have the same effect as if made on oath before the court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If the court is 
    dissolved before the receipt of such reply, or if the court omits to comply 
    with the provisions of this section, the convening officer may, at his 
    discretion, annul the proceedings and order a fresh trial
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>98</number> Evidence of previous 
    convictions and general character.
<section><number>1</number> 
    When any person subject to this Act has been convicted by a Security Force 
    Court of any offence, such Security Force Court may inquire into, and 
    receive, and record evidence of any previous convictions of such person, 
    either by a Security Force Court or by a criminal court, or any previous 
    award of punishment under section 53 or 55, and may further inquire into and 
    record the general character of such person and such other matters as may be 
    prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Evidence received under 
    this section may be either oral, or in the shape of entries in, or certified 
    extracts from, books of Security Force Courts or other official records; and 
    it shall not be necessary to give notice before trial to the person tried 
    that evidence as to his previous convictions or character will be received.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At a Summary Security 
    Force Court, the officer holding the trial may, if he thinks fit, record any 
    previous convictions against the offender, his general character, and such 
    other matters as may be prescribed, as of his own knowledge instead of 
    requiring them to be proved under the foregoing provisions of this section.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>99</number> Lunacy of accused.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever, in the course of a trial by a Security Force Court, it appears to 
    the court that the person charged is by reason of unsoundness of mind 
    incapable of making his defence, or that he committed the act alleged but 
    was by reason of unsoundness of mind incapable to knowing the nature of the 
    act or knowing that it was wrong or contrary to law, the court shall record 
    a finding accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The presiding officer 
    of the court, or, in the case of a Summary Security Force Court, the officer 
    holding the trial, shall forthwith report the case to the confirming 
    officer, or to the authority empowered to deal with its finding under 
    section 115, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The confirming officer 
    to whom the case is reported under sub-section (2) may, if he does not 
    confirm the finding, take steps to have the accused person tried by the same 
    or another Security Force Court for the offence with which he was charged.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The authority to whom 
    the finding of a Summary Security Force Court is reported under sub-section 
    (2), and a confirming officer confirming the finding in any case so reported 
    to him shall order the accused person to be kept in custody in the 
    prescribed manner and shall report the case for the orders of the Central 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On receipt of a report 
    under sub-section (4), the Central Government may order the accused person 
    to be detained in a lunatic asylum or other suitable place of safe custody.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>100</number> Subsequent fitness of 
    lunatic accused for trial.Where 
    any accused person, having been found by reason of unsoundness of mind to be 
    incapable of making his defence, is in custody or under detention under 
    section 99, any officer prescribed in this behalf, may
 <section>
<number>a</number>   if such person is in custody 
    under sub-section (4) of section 99, on the report of a medical officer that 
    he is capable of making his defence, or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if such person is detained in a 
    jail under sub-section (5) of section 99, on a certificate of the Inspector 
    General of Prisons, and if such person is detained in a lunatic asylum under 
    the said sub-section, on a certificate of any two or more of the visitors of 
    such asylum and if he is detained in any other place under that sub-section, 
    on a certificate of the prescribed authority, that he is capable of making 
    his defence, take steps to have such person tried by the same or another 
    Security Force Court for the offence with which he was originally charged 
    or, if the offence is a civil offence, by a criminal court.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>101</number> Transmission to 
    Central Government of orders under section 100.A 
    copy of every order made by an officer under section 100 for the trial of 
    the accused shall forthwith be sent to the Central Government.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>102</number> Release of lunatic 
    accused.Where 
    any person is in custody under sub-section (4) of section 99 or under 
    detention under sub-section (5) of that section,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   if such person is in custody 
    under the said sub-section (4), on the report of a medical officer, or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if such person is detained 
    under the said sub-section (5), on a certificate from any of the authorities 
    mentioned in clause (b) of section 100 that in the judgment of such officer 
    or authority such person may be released without danger of his doing injury 
    to himself or to any other person,
 
the Central Government may order that such 
    person be released or detained in custody, or transferred to a public 
    lunatic asylum if he has not already been sent to such an asylum.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>103</number> Delivery of lunatic 
    accused to relatives.Where 
    any relative or friend of any person who is in custody under sub-section (4) 
    of section 99 or under detention under sub-section (5) of that section 
    desires that he should be delivered to his care and custody, the Central 
    Government may, upon application by such relative or friend and, on his 
    giving security to the satisfaction of that Government that the person 
    delivered shall be properly taken care of, and, prevented from doing injury 
    to himself or to any other person, and be produced for the inspection of 
    such officer, and at such times and places, as the Central Government may 
    direct, order such person to be delivered to such relative or friend.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>104</number> Order for custody and 
    disposal of property pending trial.When 
    any property regarding which any offence appears to have been committed, or 
    which appears to have been used for the commission of any offence, is 
    produced before a Security Force Court during a trial, the court may make 
    such order as it thinks fit for the proper custody of such property pending 
    the conclusion of the trial, and if the property is subject to speedy or 
    natural decay may, after recording such evidence as it thinks necessary, 
    order it to be sold or otherwise disposed of.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>105</number> Order for disposal of 
    property regarding which offence is committed.
<section><number>1</number> 
    After the conclusion of a trial before any Security Force Court, the court 
    or the officer confirming the finding or sentence of such Security Force 
    Court, or any authority superior to such officer, or, in the case of a 
    Summary Security Force Court whose finding or sentence does not require 
    confirmation, an officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General 
    within whose command the trial was held, may make such order as it or he 
    thinks fit for the disposal by destruction, confiscation, delivery to any 
    person claiming to be entitled to possession thereof, or otherwise, of any 
    property or document produced before the court or in its custody, or 
    regarding which any offence appears to have been committed or which has been 
    used for the commission of any offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any order has 
    been made under sub-section (1) in respect of property regarding which an 
    offence appears to have been committed, a copy of such order signed and 
    certified by the authority making the same may, whether the trial was held 
    within India or not, be sent to a magistrate within whose jurisdiction such 
    property for the time being is situated, and such magistrate shall thereupon 
    cause the order to be carried into effect as if it were an order passed by 
    him under the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 
    1898).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In this section, the 
    term property includes, in the case of property regarding which an offence 
    appears to have been committed, not only such property as has been 
    originally in the possession or under the control of any person, but also 
    any property into or for which the same may have been converted or 
    exchanged, and anything acquired by such conversion or exchange whether 
    immediately or otherwise.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>106</number> Powers of Security 
    Force Court in relation to proceedings under this Act.Any 
    trial by a Security Force Court under the provisions of this Act shall be 
    deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 
    228 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Security Force Court shall 
    be deemed to be a court within the meaning of sections 480 and 482 of the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>107</number> Finding and sentence 
    not valid, unless confirmed.No 
    finding or sentence of a General Security Force Court or a Petty Security 
    Force Court shall be valid except so far as it may be confirmed as provided 
    by this Act.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>108</number> Power to confirm 
    finding and, sentence of General Security Force Court.The 
    findings and sentences of General Security Force Courts may be confirmed by 
    the Central Government or by any officer empowered in this behalf by warrant 
    of the Central Government.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>109</number> Power to confirm 
    finding and sentence of Petty Security Force Court.The 
    findings and sentences of Petty Security Force Courts may be confirmed by an 
    officer having power to convene a General Security Force Court or by any 
    officer empowered in this behalf by warrant of such officer.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>110</number> Limitation of powers 
    of confirming authority.A 
    warrant issued under section 108 or section 109 may contain such 
    restrictions, reservations or conditions as the authority issuing it may 
    think fit.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>111</number> Power of confirming 
    authority to mitigate, remit or commute sentences.Subject 
    to such restrictions, reservations or conditions, as may be contained in any 
    warrant issued under section 108 or section 109, a confirming authority may, 
    when confirming the sentence of a Security Force Court, mitigate or remit 
    the punishment thereby awarded, or commute that punishment for any 
    punishment or punishments lower in the scale laid down in section 48.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>112</number> Confirming of findings 
    and sentences on board a ship.When 
    any person subject to this Act is tried and sentenced by a Security Force 
    Court while on board a ship, the finding and sentence so far as not 
    confirmed and executed on board the ship, may be confirmed and executed in 
    like manner as if such person had been tried at the port of disembarkation.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>113</number> Revision of finding or 
    sentence.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any finding or sentence of a Security Force Court which requires 
    confirmation may be once revised by order of the confirming authority and on 
    such revision, the court, if so directed by the confirming authority, may 
    take additional evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The court, on revision, 
    shall consist of the same officers as were present when the original 
    decision was passed, unless any of those officers are unavoidably absent.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In case of such 
    unavoidable absence the cause thereof shall be duly certified in the 
    proceedings, and the court shall proceed with the revision, provided that, 
    if a General Security Force Court, it still consists of five officers, or, 
    if a Petty Security Force Court, of three officers.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>114</number> Finding and sentence 
    of a Summary Security Force Court.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Save as otherwise provided in sub-section (2), the finding and sentence of a 
    Summary Security Force Court shall not require to be confirmed, but may be 
    carried out forthwith.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the officer holding 
    the trial is of the rank of Superintendent of Police or of a rank declared 
    under clause (a) of sub-section (5) of section 74 as equivalent thereto or 
    of a lower rank has held such rank for less than five years, he shall not, 
    except on active duty, carry into effect any sentence, until it has received 
    the approval of an officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>115</number> Transmission of 
    proceedings of Summary Security Force Courts.The 
    proceedings of every Summary Security Force Court shall, without delay, be 
    forwarded to the officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General 
    within whose command the trial was held, or to the prescribed officer, and 
    such officer, or the Director-General or any officer empowered by him in 
    this behalf may, for reasons based on the merits of the case, but not on 
    merely technical grounds, set aside the proceedings, or reduce the sentence 
    to any other sentence which the court might have passed.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>116</number> Alteration of finding 
    or sentence in certain cases.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a finding of guilty by a Security Force Court, which has been 
    confirmed or which does not require confirmation, is found for any reason to 
    be invalid or cannot be supported by the evidence, the authority which would 
    have had power under section 128 to commute the punishment awarded by the 
    sentence, if the finding had been valid may substitute a new finding and 
    pass a sentence for the offence specified or involved in such finding:
 
Provided that no such 
    substitution shall be made unless such finding could have been validly made 
    by the Security Force Court on the charge and unless it appears that the 
    Security Force Court must have been satisfied of the facts establishing the 
    said offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a sentence passed 
    by a Security Force Court which has been confirmed, or which does not 
    require confirmation, not being a sentence passed in pursuance of a new 
    finding substituted under sub-section (1), is found for any reason to be 
    invalid, the authority referred to in sub-section (1) may pass a valid 
    sentence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The punishment awarded 
    by a sentence passed under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall not be 
    higher in the scale of punishments than, or in excess of, the punishment 
    awarded by, the sentence for which a new sentence is substituted under this 
    section.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any finding 
    substituted, or any sentence passed, under this section shall, for the 
    purposes of this Act and the rules, have effect as if it were a finding or 
    sentence, as the case may be, of a Security Force Court.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>117</number> Remedy against order, 
    finding or sentence of Security Force Court.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person subject to this Act who considers himself aggrieved by any order 
    passed by any Security Force Court may present a petition to the officer or 
    authority empowered to confirm any finding or sentence of such Security 
    Force Court, and the confirming authority may take such steps as may be 
    considered necessary to satisfy itself as to the correctness, legality or 
    propriety of the order passed or as to the regularity of any proceeding to 
    which the order relates.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person subject to 
    this Act who considers himself aggrieved by a finding or sentence of any 
    Security Force Court which has been confirmed, may present a petition to the 
    Central Government, the Director-General, or any prescribed officer superior 
    in command to the one who confirmed such finding or sentence, and the 
    Central Government, the Director-General, or the prescribed officer, as the 
    case may be, may pass such order thereon as it or he thinks fit.
  




 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>118</number> Annulment of 
    proceedings.The 
    Central Government, the Director-General, or any prescribed officer may 
    annul the proceedings of any Security Force Court on the ground that they 
    are illegal or unjust.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>119</number> Form of sentence of 
    death.In 
    awarding a sentence of death, a Security Force Court shall, in its 
    discretion direct the offender shall suffer death by being hanged by the 
    neck until he be dead, or shall suffer death by being shot to death.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>120</number> Commencement of 
    sentence of imprisonment.Whenever 
    any person is sentenced by a Security Force Court under this Act to 
    imprisonment, the term of his sentence shall, whether it has been revised or 
    not, be reckoned to commence on the day on which the original proceedings 
    were signed by the presiding officer, or in the case of a Summary Security 
    Force Court, by the court.


 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>121</number> Execution of sentence 
    of imprisonment.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever any sentence of imprisonment is passed under this Act by a Security 
    Force Court or whenever any sentence of death is commuted to imprisonment, 
    the confirming officer or in case of a Summary Security Force Court the 
    officer holding the court or such other officer as may be prescribed shall, 
    save as otherwise provided in sub-sections (3) and (4) direct that the 
    sentence shall be carried out by confinement in a civil prison.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a direction has 
    been made under sub-section (1) the Commandant of the person under sentence 
    or such other officer as may be prescribed shall forward a warrant in the 
    prescribed form to the officer in charge of the prison in which such person 
    is to be confined and shall arrange for his despatch to such prison with the 
    warrant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the case of a 
    sentence of imprisonment for a period not exceeding three months and passed 
    under this Act by a Security Force Court, the appropriate officer under 
    sub-section (1) may direct that the sentence shall be carried out by 
    confinement in Force custody instead of in a civil prison.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On active duty, a 
    sentence of imprisonment may be carried out by confinement in such place as 
    the Deputy Inspector-General within whose command the person sentenced is 
    serving or any prescribed officer, may from time to time appoint.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>121A</number> Period of Custody 
      undergone by a person to be set-off against the 
      imprisonment.When any person subject to 
      this Act is sentenced by a Security Force Court to a term of imprisonment, 
      not being an imprisonment in default of payment of fine, the period spent 
      by him in civil or Force custody during investigation, inquiry or trial of 
      the same case, and before the date of order of such sentence, shall be set 
      off against the term of imprisonment imposed upon him, and the liability 
      of such person to undergo imprisonment on such order of sentence shall be 
      restricted to the remainder, if any, of the term of imprisonment imposed 
      upon him.]




 

 
 

 

 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>122</number> Temporary custody of 
    offender.Where 
    a sentence of imprisonment is directed to be under-gone in a civil prison, 
    the offender may be kept in Force custody or in any other fit place, till 
    such time as it is possible to send him to a civil prison.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>123</number> Execution of sentence 
    of imprisonment in special cases.Whenever, 
    in the opinion of an officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General 
    within whose command the trial is held, any sentence or portion of a 
    sentence of imprisonment cannot for special reasons, conveniently be carried 
    out in Force custody in accordance with the provisions of section 121, such 
    officer may direct that such sentence or portion of sentence shall be 
    carried out by confinement in any civil prison or other fit place.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>124</number> Conveyance of prisoner 
    from place to place.A 
    person under sentence of imprisonment may during his conveyance from place 
    to place, or when on board ship, aircraft, or otherwise, be subjected to 
    such restraint as is necessary for his safe conduct and removal.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>125</number> Communication of 
    certain orders to prison officers.Whenever 
    an order is duly made under this Act setting aside or varying any sentence, 
    order or warrant under which any person is confined in a civil prison, a 
    warrant in accordance with such order shall be forwarded by the officer 
    making the order or his staff officer or such other person as may be 
    prescribed, to the officer in charge of the prison in which such person is 
    confined.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>126</number> Execution of sentence 
    of fine.When a 
    sentence of fine is imposed by a Security Force Court under section 46, a 
    copy of such sentence signed and certified by the confirming officer, or 
    where no confirmation is required, by the officer holding the trial may be 
    sent to any magistrate in India, and such magistrate shall there upon cause 
    the fine to be recovered in accordance with the provisions of the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), as if it were a sentence of fine 
    imposed by such magistrate.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>127</number> Informality or error 
    in the order or warrant.Whenever 
    any person is sentenced to imprisonment under this Act, and is undergoing 
    the sentence in any place or manner in which he might be confined under a 
    lawful order or warrant in pursuance of this Act, the confinement of such 
    person shall not be deemed to be illegal only by reason of informality or 
    error in, or as respects, the order, warrant or other document, or the 
    authority by which, or in pursuance whereof such person was brought into, 
    or, is confined in any such place, and any such order, warrant or document 
    may be amended accordingly.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>128</number> Pardon and remission.When 
    any person subject to this Act has been convicted by a Security Force Court 
    of any offence, the Central Government or the Director-General or, in the 
    case of a sentence, which he could have confirmed or which did not require 
    confirmation, an officer not below the rank of Deputy Inspector-General 
    within whose command such person at the time of conviction was serving, or 
    the prescribed officer may,
 <section>
<number>a</number>   either with or without 
    conditions which the person sentenced accepts, pardon the person or remit 
    the whole or any part of the punishment awarded; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   mitigate the punishment 
    awarded; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   commute such punishment for 
    any less punishment or punishments mentioned in this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   either with or without 
    conditions which the person sentenced accepts, release the person on parole.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>129</number> 
      Cancellation of conditional pardon, release on parole or 
      remission.
<section><number>1</number> 
      If any condition on which a person has been pardoned or released on parole 
      or a punishment has been remitted is, in the opinion of the authority 
      which granted the pardon, release or remission, not fulfilled, such 
      authority may cancel the pardon, release or remission, and thereupon the 
      sentence of the court shall be carried into effect as if such pardon, 
      release or remission had not been granted.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person 
      whose sentence of imprisonment is carried into effect under the provisions 
      of sub-section (1) shall undergo only the unexpired portion of his 
      sentence.
  
 
  
 
 
  
 
  
 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>130</number> Suspension of sentence of 
imprisonment. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Where a person subject to this Act is sentenced by a 
Security Force Court to imprisonment, the Central Government, the 
Director-General or any officer empowered to convene a General Security Force 
Court may suspend the sentence whether or not the offender has already been 
committed to prison or to Force custody. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The authority or officer specified in sub-section (1) may, 
in the case of an offender so sentenced, direct that until the orders of such 
authority or officer have been obtained, the offender shall not be committed to 
prison or to Force custody. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The powers conferred by sub-sections (1) and (2) may be 
exercised in the case of any such sentence which has been confirmed, reduced or 
commuted. </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>131</number> Orders pending 
    suspension.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the sentence referred to in section 130 is imposed by a Security Force 
    Court other than a Summary Security Force Court, the confirming officer may, 
    when confirming the sentence, direct that the offender be not committed to 
    prison or to Force custody until the orders of the authority or officer 
    specified in section 130, have been obtained.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a sentence of 
    imprisonment is imposed by a Summary Security Force Court, the officer 
    holding the trial or the officer authorised to approve of the sentence under 
    sub-section (2) of section 114 may make the direction referred to in 
    sub-section (1).
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>132</number> Release on suspension.Where 
    a sentence is suspended under section 130, the offender shall forthwith be 
    released from custody.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>133</number> Computation of period 
    of suspension.Any 
    period during which the sentence is under suspension shall be reckoned as 
    part of the term of such sentence.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>134</number> Order after 
    suspension.The 
    authority or officer specified in section 130 may, at any time while a 
    sentence is suspended, order
 <section>
<number>a</number>   that the offender be committed 
    to undergo the unexpired portion of the sentence; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   that the sentence be remitted.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>135</number> Reconsideration of 
    case after suspension.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a sentence has been suspended, the case may at any time, and shall at 
    intervals of not more than four months, be reconsidered by the authority or 
    officer specified in section 130, or by any officer not below the rank of a 
    Deputy Inspector-General duly authorised by the authority or officer 
    specified in section 130.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where on such 
    reconsideration by the officer so authorised it appears to him that the 
    conduct of offender since his conviction has been such as to justify a 
    remission of the sentence, he shall refer the matter to the authority or 
    officer specified in section 130.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>136</number> Fresh sentence after 
    suspension.Where 
    an offender, while a sentence on him is suspended under this Act, is 
    sentenced for any other offence, then
 <section>
<number>a</number>   if the further sentence is 
    also suspended under this Act, the two sentences shall run concurrently;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if the further sentence is for 
    a period of three months or more and is not suspended under this Act, the 
    offender shall also be committed to prison or Force custody for the 
    unexpired portion of the previous sentence, but both sentences shall run 
    concurrently; and 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   if the further sentence is for 
    a period of less than three months and is not suspended under this Act, the 
    offender shall be so committed on that sentence only, and the previous 
    sentence shall, subject to any order which may be passed under section 134 
    or section 135 continue to be suspended.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>137</number> Scope of power of 
    suspension.The 
    powers conferred by sections 130 and 134 shall be in addition to, and not in 
    derogation of, the power of mitigation, remission and commutation.
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>138</number> Effect of suspension 
    and remission on dismissal.
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where in addition to any other sentence the punishment of dismissal has been 
    awarded by a Security Force Court, and such other sentence is suspended 
    under section 130, then, such dismissal shall not take effect until so 
    ordered by the authority or officer specified in section 130.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If such other sentence 
    is remitted under section 134, the punishment of dismissal shall also be 
    remitted.
  
  
 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>139</number> Powers and duties 
      conferable and imposable on members of the Force.
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government 
      may, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette direct 
      that, subject to such conditions and limitations, and within the local 
      limits of such area adjoining the borders of India, as may be specified in 
      the order, any member of the Force may,
 <subsection><number>i</number>   for the purpose of prevention of 
      any offence punishable under the Passport (Entry into India) Act, 1920 (34 
      of 1920), the Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939 (16 of 1939) the 
      Central Excises and Salt Act, 1944 (1 of 1944), the Foreigners Act, 1946 
      (31 of 1946), the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1947 (7 of 1947), the 
      Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962), or the Passports Act, 1967 (15 of 1967), 
      or of any cognizable offence punishable under any other Central Act; or 
      punishable under any other Central Act; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   
      for the purpose of apprehending any person who has committed any offence 
      referred to in clause (i),
 exercise or 
      discharged such of the powers or duties under that Act or any other 
      Central Act as may be specified in the said order, being the powers and 
      duties which, in the opinion of the Central Government, an officer of the 
      corresponding or lower rank is by that or such other Act empowered to 
      exercise or discharge for the said purposes.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government may, 
      by general or special order published in the Official Gazette, confer or 
      impose, with the concurrence of the State Government concerned, any of the 
      powers on duties which may be exercised or discharged under a State Act by 
      a police officer upon a member of the Force who, in the opinion of the 
      Central Government, holds a corresponding or higher 
rank.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every order made under this 
      section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
      House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty 
      days which may be comprised in one session or 1[in two or more successive 
      sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following 
      the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agreed in 
      making any modification in the order or both Houses agree that the order 
      should not be made, the order shall thereafter have effect only in such 
      modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that 
      any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
      validity of anything previously done under that order.




 

 
 

 

 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>140</number> Protection for acts of 
      members of the Force.
<section><number>1</number> In any suit or proceeding 
      against any member of the Force for any act done by him in pursuance of a 
      warrant or order of a competent authority, it shall be lawful for him to 
      plead that such act was done by him under the authority of such warrant or 
      order.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any such 
      plea may be proved by the production of the warrant or order directing the 
      act, and if it is so proved the member of the Force shall thereupon be 
      discharged from liability in respect of the act so done by him, 
      notwithstanding any defect in the jurisdiction of the authority which 
      issued such warrant or order.
 </section><section><number>3</number> 
      Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in 
      force, any legal proceeding (whether civil or criminal) which may lawfully 
      be brought against any member of the Force for anything done or intended 
      to be done under the powers conferred by, or in pursuance of any provision 
      of this Act or the rules, shall be commenced within three months after the 
      act complained of was committed and not otherwise and notice in writing of 
      such proceeding and of the cause thereof shall be given to the defendant 
      or his superior officer at least one month before the commencement of such 
      proceeding.
  
 
  
 
 
  
 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>141</number> Power to make 
      rules.
<section><number>1</number> The 
      Central Government may, by notification, make rules for the purpose of 
      carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular and without 
      prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide 
      for,
 <subsection><number>a</number>   the constitution, governance, 
      command and discipline of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   the enrolment of persons to the 
      Force and the recruitment of other members of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   the conditions of service 
      (including deduction from pay and allowances) of members of the 
      Force;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   the rank, precedence, powers of 
      command and authority of the officers, subordinate officers, 
      under-officers and other persons subject to this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>   the removal, retirement, release 
      or discharge from the service of persons subject to this 
      Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>   the purposes and other matters 
      required to be prescribed under section 13;
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>   the convening, constitution, 
      adjournment, dissolution and sittings of Security Force Courts, the 
      procedure to be observed in trials by such courts, the persons by whom an 
      accused may be defended in such trials and the appearance of such persons 
      thereat;
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>   the confirmation, revision and 
      annulment of, and petitions against, the findings and sentences of 
      Security Force Courts;
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>   the 1[forms of orders] to be made under the provisions 
      of this Act relating to Security Force Courts and the awards and 
      infliction of death, imprisonment and detention.
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>   the carrying into effect of 
      sentences of Security Force Courts;
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>   any matter necessary for the 
      purpose of carrying this Act into execution, as far as it relates to the 
      investigation, arrest, custody, trial and punishment of offences triable 
      or punishable under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number>   the ceremonials to be observed and 
      marks of respect to be paid in the Force;
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number>   the convening of, the 
      constitution, procedure and practice of, Courts of inquiry, the summoning 
      of witnesses before them and the administration of oaths by such 
      Courts;
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number>   the recruitment and conditions of 
      service of the Chief Law Officer and the Law Officers.
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number>   any other matter which is to be, 
      or may be prescribed or in respect of which this Act makes no provision or 
      makes insufficient provision and provision is, in the opinion of the 
      Central Government, necessary for the proper implementation of this 
      Act.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made under this 
      Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
      of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days 
      which may be comprised in one session or 2[in two or more successive 
      sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following 
      the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in 
      making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule 
      should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
      modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that 
      any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
      validity of anything previously done under that rule.
  







 

 
 

 

 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>142</number> Provisions as to existing 
      Border Security Force.
<section><number>1</number> The Border Security Force 
      in existence at the commencement of this Act shall be deemed to be the 
      Force constituted under this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Member of the Border 
      Security Force in existence at the commencement of this Act shall be 
      deemed to have been appointed or as the case may be, enrolled as such 
      under this Act.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Anything done or any action 
      taken before the commencement of this Act in relation to the constitution 
      of the Border Security Force referred to in sub-section (1), in relation 
      to any person appointed or enrolled, as the case may be, thereto, shall be 
      as valid and as effective in law as if such thing or action was done or 
      taken under this Act:
 Provided that nothing in this 
      sub-section shall render any person guilty of any offence in respect of 
      anything done or omitted to be done by him before the commencement of this 
      Act.
  



 

 
 

 

 
</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 1-3-1969, vide S.O. 732, dated 20th 
February, 1969, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), 
p. 235.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Ins. by Act 35 of 
      2000, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-9-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 Subs. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
      15-5-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
 Subs. Act 19 of 1988, sec. 3 and Second Sch. (w.e.f. 
      31-3-1988).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>