<act> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 20061
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—These rules may be 
called the National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006.
 <section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  



</section></article> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the National Rural Employment 
Guarantee Act, 2005 (42 of 2005);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “Central Government” means Central Government in 
the Ministry of Rural Development;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “National Fund” means the National Employment 
Guarantee Fund established under sub-section (1) of section 20;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  all other words and expressions used herein and 
not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in the Act.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>3</number> Account of the National 
Fund.—The National Fund shall be 
maintained by the Central Government in a Public Account.
  
</article> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>4</number> Usage of the National 
Fund.—The National Fund shall be used 
by the Central Government to meet the Central Government share of expenditure on 
implementation of the Act including the grants to the State Governments and 
Union territories and the expenses of the Central Employment Guarantee Council.
  
</article> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>5</number> Release of grants from the 
Fund to the State Governments and Union Territory Administrations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Before the beginning of each financial year on or before 31st January, all 
Secretaries of the State Governments and Union territories concerned with the 
implementation of the Act and the State Employment Guarantee Schemes shall 
present their annual work plan and labour budget to the Ministry of Rural 
Development.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The State Governments and 
Union territories may also in their annual work plan and labour budget submit 
proposals for any work other than those specified in Schedule I of the Act
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Ministry of Rural 
Development may examine the proposals received by it on or before the 31st of 
January of each financial year and review the performance of the States and 
Union territories with respect to the implementation of the Act and estimate the 
amount to be released to the State Governments and Union Territory 
Administrations from the National Fund.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Release of funds to the 
State Governments and Union Territory Administrations shall be made in 
accordance with the directions issued by the Ministry of Rural Development from 
time to time.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Ministry of Rural 
Development may, in order to meet emergent needs and to meet the temporary 
shortage of funds on account of non-completion of prescribed formalities, give 
advances as it may consider necessary to the districts, States and Union 
territories pending regular release of funds and such advances shall be adjusted 
against regular releases.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The sanctioned amount may be 
released directly from the National Employment Guarantee Fund to the State 
Employment Guarantee Fund under sub-section (1) of section 21.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The rules for State 
Employment Guarantee Fund and the fund-flow from State Employment Guarantee Fund 
to the Districts, Block and Gram Panchayat may be notified by the concerned 
State Government.
 </section><section><number>8</number> The State Employment 
Guarantee Fund shall be maintained in a separate bank account which shall be 
non-lapsable.
 </section><section><number>9</number> The State Employment or any 
other authority shall not create any encumbrance on the grants released by the 
Ministry either through the State Employment Guarantee Fund or directly to the 
districts or any other agency.
 </section><section><number>10</number> The sanctioned amount may 
also be released directly from the National Fund to a separate bank account at 
the district level for the implementation of the Act, which shall be 
non-lapsable.
 </section><section><number>11</number> The decision in regard to 
release of funds shall be taken by the Ministry of Rural Development in 
consultation with the concerned State Government and Union territory.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>6</number> Release of grants from the 
National Fund to the Central Employment Guarantee Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Employment Guarantee Council shall be given a grant every year with 
an initial corpus of five crores of rupees in order to meet the expenses in 
connection with the functions assigned to the Council.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Council shall maintain a 
bank account in a Scheduled Bank for the funds so given.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The grants shall be given to 
the Council after audit report for the previous year and the utilization 
certificate for at least sixty per cent. of the amount already released are 
furnished.
  
</section></article> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>7</number> Balance budgeted grant.—The 
balance budgeted grant of each financial year shall be transferred to the 
National Fund before the close of the financial year and shall constitute the 
reserve in the National Fund.
  
</article> 
 The National Employment Guarantee Fund Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>8</number> Audit.—The 
grants released from the National Fund to the State Governments and Union 
Territory Administrations shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General through respective Accountant-Generals. The internal audit shall 
be done on behalf of the Head of the Department (Secretary) to the Government of 
India and shall be supervised and monitored by the office of Chief Controller of 
Accounts.
  
  
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>