<act><title>


the multi-state co-operative societies rules, 20021</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Multi-State Co-operative Societies Rules, 2002.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These rules shall come 
into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  “Act“ means the Multi-State Co-operative Societies Act, 2002 (39 of 
2002);
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  “authorised officer” means an officer authorised by the Central 
Government for the purpose of section 103 of the Act;
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  “decree” means any decree of a civil court and includes any decision 
or order referred to in section 94 of the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  “decree holder” means any person holding a decree as defined in 
clause (iii);
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  “defaulter” means any multi-State co-operative society, any 
co-operative society, member or any other person committing default;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  “Form” means a Form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
       
<number>vii</number>  “general meeting” means a meeting of the general body including a 
representative general body referred to in the first proviso to sub-section (1) 
of section 38;
 </section><section>
      
<number>viii</number>  “judgement debtor” means any multi-State co-operative society 
against which or any person against whom a decree has been obtained;
 </section><section>
        
<number>ix</number>  “recovery officer” means any person authorised to execute the powers 
of the Central Registrar under section 94;
 </section><section>
        
<number>x</number>  “Sale Officer” means a person authorised by the Central Registrar by a 
general or special order, to attach and sale the property of judgement debtor or 
to execute any decree by attachment or sale of property;
 </section><section>
        
<number>xi</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 <subsection>
       
<number>xii</number>  “Schedule” means Schedule appended to these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>xiii</number>  words and expressions defined in the Act and used but not defined 
in these rules shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Application for 
registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application for registration of a multi-State co-operative society under 
sub-section (1) of section 6 shall be made in Form I and shall, subject to the 
provisions of sub-section (2) of section 6 and sub-rules (2), (3), (4) and (5) 
of these rules be signed by the applicants and be accompanied by—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  four copies of the proposed bye-laws of the multi-State co-operative 
society, duly signed by each of the persons who sign the application for 
registration;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  a list of persons who have contributed to the share capital, together 
with the amount contributed by each of them, and the admission fee paid by them;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  a certificate from the bank or banks stating the credit balance in 
favour of the proposed multi-State co-operative society;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  a scheme showing the details explaining how the working of the 
multi-State co-operative society will be economically sound and the registration 
of such multi-State co-operative society will be beneficial for social and 
economic betterment of its members through self-help and mutual aid in 
accordance with the co-operative principles;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  certified copy of the resolution of the promoters which shall specify 
the name and address of one of the applicants to whom the Central Registrar may 
address correspondence under the rules before registration and dispatch or hand 
over registration documents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any member of a 
multi-State co-operative society to be registered is a multi-State co-operative 
society or a co-operative society, the Chairperson or Chief Executive or a 
member duly authorised by board of directors or the governing body of such 
multi-State co-operative society or co-operative society, as the case may be, 
shall be authorised by that board by a resolution, to sign the application for 
registration and bye-laws on its behalf, and a copy of such resolution shall be 
appended to the application.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the members of a 
multi-State co-operative society to be registered are co-operative societies or 
multi-State co-operative societies and individuals, such application shall be 
signed by individuals and authorised representative of such co-operative society 
or multi-State co-operative society.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where any member of 
multi-State co-operative society to be registered is a Government company, a 
corporate body or a society registered under the Societies Registration Act, 
1860 (21 of 1860) such member shall duly authorise any person to sign the 
application for registration and the bye-laws on its behalf and a copy of such 
resolution giving such authority shall be appended to the application.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A copy of the 
resolution indicating the name of one or more applicants, who are authorised to 
make alterations or additions to the proposed bye-laws submitted with the 
application, as may be suggested by the Central Registrar, shall be submitted.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The application shall 
either be sent by registered post or delivered by hand to the Central Registrar 
in his Office.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of an application under rule 3, the Central Registrar shall enter the 
particulars of the application in the register of applications to be maintained 
in Form II, give a serial number to the application and issue a receipt in 
acknowledgement thereof.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Central 
Registrar is satisfied that the proposed multi-State co-operative society has 
complied with the requirements of the Act and the rules, he may register the 
society and its bye-laws.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Central 
Registrar registers a multi-State co-operative society, he shall issue to the 
said society a certificate of registration signed by him and bearing his 
official seal containing registration number and date of registration of the 
said society. The Central Registrar shall also issue, alongwith the certificate 
of registration, a certified copy of the bye-laws, as approved and registered by 
him, which shall be the registered bye-laws of the said society for the time 
being in force.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Refusal of 
registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The order of refusal to register a multi-State co-operative society referred to 
in sub-section (3) of section 7 shall be communicated through registered post to 
the person referred to in clause (e) of sub-rule (1) of rule 3, of the proposed 
society.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The manner of 
communication of orders refusing the registration under sub-rule (1) shall be 
the conclusive proof for refusal of the registration of the proposed society.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Bye-laws.—Every 
multi-State co-operative society applying for registration under this Act may 
make bye-laws consistent with the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
thereunder and model bye-laws, if any, framed by the Central Registrar. The 
subject matter of the bye-laws shall be as provided in section 10 and other 
relevant provisions of the Act and rules made thereunder. In addition, the 
bye-laws may also include,—
 <section>
         
<number>i</number>  Procedure and manner of redemption of shares.
 </section><section>
        
<number>ii</number>  The provisions of office bearers of the society, the terms and 
conditions, their functions and responsibilities other than those specified in 
the Act.
 </section><section>
        
<number>iii</number>  Constitution of various funds as required under the Act and Rules.
 </section><section>
       
<number>iv</number>  Rate of dividend subject to maximum of the rates specified in the 
bye-laws.
 </section><section>
        
<number>v</number>  The procedure for the association and representation of employees of 
the society.
 </section><section>
       
<number>vi</number>  Constitution of the committees of the board.
 </section><section>
       
<number>vii</number>  The procedure of election or selection for constitution of smaller 
body of delegates.
 </section><section>
      
<number>viii</number>  The method of recruitment, the condition of service and the 
authority competent to fix, revise or regulate the scales of pay and allowance 
to be paid to the officers and other employees of the society and the procedure 
to be followed in the disposal of disciplinary cases.
 </section><section>
        
<number>ix</number>  The constitution and powers of the representative general body and 
the restrictions subject to which this body may exercise its powers.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Refusal of amendment 
of bye-laws.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Central Registrar refuses to register an amendment of bye-laws of a 
multi-State co-operative society under sub-section (9) of section 11, he shall 
communicate the order of refusal together with the reasons therefor to the chief 
executive of a multi-State co-operative society, through registered post.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The manner of 
communication of the order of refusal under sub-rule (1) shall be conclusive 
proof that the amendments of bye-laws have been refused and communicated to the 
society.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Principal place of 
business and address.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every multi-State co-operative society shall have one principal place of 
business which shall be the registered office of the society and shall be 
specified in the bye-laws.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every change in 
principal place of business of a multi-State co-operative society shall be made 
by an amendment of its bye-laws after following the procedure laid down in 
section 11 of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any change in 
registered office of a multi-State co-operative society, the same shall be 
notified to the Central Registrar within a period of fifteen days of its change.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Maintenance of 
registration file by the society.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every multi-State co-operative society shall maintain at its registered address 
a registration file containing,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  the certificate of registration;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  the registered bye-laws;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  all registered amendments to the bye-laws alongwith the certificates 
of registration of amendments;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  a copy of the Act and the rules.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The registration file 
shall be kept open for inspection at all times during working hours to the 
Central Registrar or any other officer authorised by him or any member of the 
multi-State co-operative society.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Change in name of 
multi-State co-operative society.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The name of a multi-State co-operative society may be changed after following 
the procedure given in section 11, however, that it does not refer to any caste 
or religion denomination and is not inconsistent with the objects of the 
multi-State co-operative society.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every change in the 
name of the multi-State co-operative society shall be made by an amendment of 
its bye-laws.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> After the change in 
the name is approved by the Central Registrar the multi-State co-operative 
society shall send the original registration certificate for amendment to the 
Central Registrar who shall return the same to the multi-State co-operative 
society duly amended.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <title> </title>
 <article><title><number>11</number> Conditions to be complied with for membership. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> No 
person shall be admitted as a member of a multi-State co-operative society 
unless,— 
 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> he has applied in writing in the form, if any, laid down by the 
    multi-State co-operative society or in the form specified by the Central 
    Registrar, if any, for membership; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> his application is approved by the board of the multi-State 
     co-operative society; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> he has purchased the minimum number of shares and paid the value 
    thereof in full or in part in such calls as may be laid down in the bye-laws 
    of the multi-State co-operative society; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> he has fulfilled all other conditions laid down in the Act, the rules 
    and the bye-laws; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> in the case of a multi-State co-operative society or a co-operative 
    society or the national co-operative society or any other corporation owned 
    or controlled by the Government or any Government or any Government company 
    or body of persons whether incorporated or not, the application for 
    membership shall be accompanied by a resolution authorising it to apply for 
    such membership. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person shall be eligible for admission as a member of a multi-State 
co-operative society if he— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has not attained the age of 18 years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> has been adjudged by a competent court to be an insolvent or an 
  undischarged insolvent; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> has been sentenced for any offence, other than offence of a political 
  character or an offence not involving moral turpitude and dishonesty and a 
  period of five years has not elapsed from the date of expiry of the sentence. 
  </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in these rules or the bye-laws of the 
multi-State co-operative society, if a member becomes or has already become 
subject to any disqualifications specified in sub-rule (2), he shall be deemed 
to have ceased to be a member of the society from the date when the 
disqualification was incurred. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> No individual being a member of a primary level multi-State 
 co-operative society or a multi-State credit society, or a multi-State urban 
 co-operative bank, shall be the member of any other multi-State co-operative 
society or co-operative society of the same class without the general or special 
permission of the Central Registrar and where an individual has become a member 
of two such co-operative societies aforesaid, than either or both of the 
societies shall be bound to remove him from membership on written requisition 
from the Central Registrar to that effect: 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Provided that if on direction of the Central Registrar such a 
member has been removed from the membership of both the Multi-State Co-operative 
Societies, on application of such a member any of such primary Multi-State 
Co-operatve Society may consider to admit such a person as its member]. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> No multi-State co-operative society shall admit members within thirty 
days prior to the date of the meeting of its general body. 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Classification of 
federal co-operatives.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The federal co-operative societies may be classified with reference to the 
nature of their activities. Not more than one federal co-operative society shall 
be registered in similar and identical objects in same area of operation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The federal 
co-operatives for the sake of promotion of their constituent members will make 
suitable provisions in their bye-laws to avoid competition with the member 
societies.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Annual General 
Meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every multi-State co-operative society, shall hold the annual general meeting of 
its members not later than a period of six months after the close of 
co-operative year. All the general meetings shall be called at the principal 
place of the society.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
the provisions sub-section (3) of section 38 of the Act, a multi-State 
co-operative society with a membership exceeding one thousand may provide in its 
bye-laws for the constitution of a smaller body. The small body so constituted 
shall exercise all such powers of the general body as may be specified in the 
bye laws.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Interim board and 
general meeting for the first election.—The 
first general meeting of the society shall be held within six months of the 
registration of the society by the promoter members for the election of the 
board of directors. The interim board selected by the applicants for the 
registration of a multi-State co-operative society shall hold office till the 
regular board is elected.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Notice for general 
meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Annual general meeting of a multi-State co-operative society may be called by 
giving not less than fourteen days notice in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Special general 
meeting of a multi-State co-operative society may be called by giving not less 
than seven days notice in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When a general meeting 
is called by the Central Registrar or any person authorised by him under 
sub-section (2) of section 39 or a special general meeting under sub-section (2) 
of section 40, he may determine—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  the period of notice of such meeting which shall not be less than 
seven days;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  the time and place of such meeting; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  the subjects to be considered in such meeting.
 
The Central Registrar or 
any person authorised by him may preside over such meeting.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The notice of annual 
general meeting shall be accompanied by a copy each of the audited balance 
sheet, profit and loss account, together with the auditor’s report thereon 
relating to the preceding year and the report of the board, amendment of 
bye-laws, if any and election of members of the board, if any.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Quorum at a general 
meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Unless otherwise provided in the bye-laws, the quorum for a general meeting 
shall be one-fifth of the total number of members of the general body of a 
multi-State co-operative society.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No business shall be 
transacted at any general meeting unless there is a quorum at the time when the 
business of the meeting is due to commence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If within half an hour 
from the time appointed for the meeting a quorum is not present, the meeting 
shall stand adjourned:
 
Provided that a meeting 
which has been called on requisition of the members shall not be adjourned but 
dissolved.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If at any time during 
the meeting sufficient number of members are not present to form the quorum the 
Chairperson or the member presiding over the meeting on his own, or on his 
attention being drawn to this fact, shall adjourn the meeting and the business 
that remains to be transacted at this meeting, if any, shall be disposed of in 
the usual manner at the adjourned meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a meeting is 
adjourned under sub-rule (3) or sub-rule (4), the adjourned meeting shall be 
held either on the same day or on such date, time and place as may be decided by 
the Chairperson or the member presiding over the meeting, but within seven days 
from the date of adjourned meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No business shall be 
transacted at any adjourned meeting other than the business on the agenda of the 
adjourned meeting under sub-rule (3) or sub-rule (4).
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No quorum shall be 
necessary in respect of an adjourned general meeting.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Voting in general 
meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All resolutions which are put to vote at the general meeting shall be decided by 
a majority of the members present and voting unless otherwise required under the 
Act, these rules or the bye-laws of the multi-State co-operative society. Every 
society shall provide in its bye-laws the procedure and manner of voting and 
other matters connected therewith.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the event of an 
equality of votes, the Chairperson of the meeting, shall have a second or 
casting vote.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Minutes of the 
general meeting.—Minutes 
of the proceedings of the general meeting shall be entered in a minutes book 
kept for the purpose and shall be signed by the Chairperson and Chief Executive 
of the meeting. The minutes so signed, shall be an evidence of the correct 
proceedings of that meeting.
 
 
</article> 

  
 <title> </title>
 <article><title> </title><title><number>19</number> Procedure for conduct of elections. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> The election of members of the board shall be conducted by a 
returning officer appointed by the board in its meeting. The returning officer 
so appointed shall not be a member or an employee of the society: 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The election of the members of the board referred to in sub-rule (1) 
shall be conducted by secret ballot in the manner as specified in the Schedule 
attached with these rules. 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Election of the 
office bearers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The election of the office bearers of the board shall be conducted as per the 
programme given in the election schedule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The eligibility of the 
candidates for the election of office bearers shall be subject to the provisions 
contained in sections 43 and 44 of the Act.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Terms and 
conditions of the chief executive.—Where 
the Central Government or a State Government holds fifty one per cent. or more 
equity capital of a multi-State co-operative society, the qualifications and 
eligibility conditions for the post of Chief Executive, the salaries and 
allowances, other terms and conditions of service including suspension, removal, 
pension, gratuity, retirement benefits etc., shall be as approved by the Central 
Government.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Certification of 
copies of entries in books.—
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> A copy of any entry in a book of a multi-State co-operative society 
regularly kept in the course of its business shall be certified by the Chief 
Executive or officer authorised by the bye-laws of the society.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Where an order has 
been passed under section 123 superseding the board and appointing an 
administrator, by administrator or any other officer authorised by him.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Where an order has 
been passed under sub-section (1) of section 89 appointing a liquidator of the 
multi-State co-operative society, by the liquidator.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every certified copy 
shall bear the signature of the Chief Executive or any director or authorised 
officer and seal of the multi-State co-operative society.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The charges to be 
levied for the supply of such certified copies shall be as provided in the 
bye-laws of such a multi-State co-operative society. In absence of such a 
provision in the bye-laws of a multi-State co-operative society, a charge of 
rupees two per folio shall be levied.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Government aid to 
multi-State co-operative societies.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 61 of the Act, the Central Government or a State 
Government may provide aid to any multi-State co-operative society on the terms 
and conditions mutually agreed upon.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Distribution of 
profit to members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No part of the funds, other than net profits, of a multi-State co-operative 
society shall be distributed by way of bonus or dividend or otherwise among its 
members.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Payment of dividend to 
the members on their paid-up share capital shall be as specified in the 
bye-laws.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The bye-laws of a 
multi-State co-operative society may provide for distribution of patronage bonus 
to its members in consonance with the transactions of a member with the society.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every multi-State 
co-operative society may also provide for in their bye-laws the subjects and 
purposes for which the reserve fund will be utilized.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Contribution 
towards Co-operative Education Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every multi-State co-operative society shall credit a sum calculated at one per 
cent. of its net profits every year as contribution to the co-operative 
education fund maintained by the National Co-operative Union of India Limited, 
New Delhi. The co-operative education fund shall be administered by a committee 
constituted by the Central Government for this purpose consisting of the 
following members:—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  The President of the National Co-operative 
 
              
Union of India Ltd., New Delhi                                              
Chairperson
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  The Central Registrar                                                               
Member
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  The Financial adviser to the Department 
 
              
of Agriculture and Co-operation in the
 
              
Ministry of Agriculture                                                              
Member
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  Two representatives of the multi-State 
 
              
co-operative societies to be nominated by the 
 
              
Central Government for every two years                                    
Members
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>v</number>  The Director General, National Council for 
 
              
Co-operative Training, New Delhi                                               
Member
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  The Director Vaikunth Mehta National Institute 
 
              
of Co-operative Management, Pune                                           
Member.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No expenditure out of 
the co-operative education fund shall be incurred without approval of the 
committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The National 
Co-operative Union of India Limited, shall maintain this fund in a separate 
account and all income by way of interest or otherwise accruing from 
contribution towards this fund shall be credited to this fund.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The balance in the 
fund, constituted under rule 4 of the Multi-State Co-operative Societies 
(Privileges, Properties and Funds, Accounts, Audit, Winding up and Execution of 
Decrees, Orders and Decisions) Rules, 1985, at the commencement of these rules 
shall be construed the fund as if constituted under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The co-operative 
education fund shall be utilised for the purposes connected with the 
co-operative education and training and human resource development for 
co-operatives. The Committee may undertake the programmes of co-operative 
education and training and human resource development, through National 
Co-operative Union of India, National Council for Co-operative Training, 
contributing members or any other professionally qualified body as the Committee 
may, decide.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Contributory 
Provident Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every multi-State co-operative society which has in its service ten or more 
regular employees shall establish a Contributory Provident Fund referred to in 
sub-section (1) of section 69.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The multi-State 
co-operative society creating such a fund shall provide for the following in its 
bye-laws:—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  Authority to administer the fund.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  Amount of contribution to be deducted from the employee’s salary.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  Mode of nomination for payment of the amount of the contributory 
provident fund in case of employee’s death.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  Purpose for which, the extent to which, and the period after which, 
advances may be made against the security of such fund and the number of monthly 
instalments in which advance is to be repaid.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  Refund of employees’ contribution and contribution made by the 
society.
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>f</number>  Maintenance of accounts of such fund.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The amount of 
contribution that can be deducted from the salary of an employee of the 
multi-State co-operative society shall not be less than the ceiling provided in 
the Employees’ Provident Fund and Miscellaneous Provisions Act, 1952 (19 of 
1952).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The multi-State 
co-operative society may make such contribution every year to the employees’ 
contributory provident fund as may be approved by the board subject to the 
maximum ceiling as provided in the Employees’ Provident Fund and Miscellaneous 
Provisions Act, 1952 (19 of 1952).
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Audit and Accounts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every multi-State co-operative society shall keep books of account with respect 
to—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  all sums of money received and expended and the matters in respect of 
which the receipt and expenditure take place;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  all sales and purchase of goods;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  the assets and liabilities;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  in the case of a multi-State co-operative society engaged in 
production, processing and manufacturing, particulars relating to utilisation of 
materials or labour or other items of costs as may be specified in the bye-laws 
of such a society.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The audit of a 
multi-State co-operative society under sub-section (1) of section 73 shall 
include, in addition to the matters specified in sub-section (2) of that section 
the following particulars:—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  whether the auditor has obtained all the information and explanations 
which, to the best of his knowledge and belief are necessary for the purposes of 
his audit;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  whether in his opinion proper books of accounts as specified in these 
rules and bye-laws have been kept by the multi-State co-operative society so far 
as it appears from the examination of those books and proper returns adequate 
for the purposes of his audit have been received from the branches not visited 
by him;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  whether the balance-sheet and profit and loss account exhibit a true 
and fair view of the state of affairs of the multi-State co-operative society 
according to best of his information and explanation given to him and as shown 
by the books of the multi-State co-operative society; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  whether there has been any material impropriety or irregularity in the 
expenditure or in the realisation of money due to the multi-State co-operative 
society;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  whether in case of a co-operative bank, the guidelines issued by the 
Reserve Bank and National Agriculture and Rural Development Bank established 
under the National Agriculture and Rural Development Bank Act, 1981 (61 of 1981) 
have been adhered to.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The audit report shall 
also contain schedules with particulars of,—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  all transactions which appear to be contrary to the provisions of the 
Act, the rules or the bye-laws of the multi-State co-operative society;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  all transactions which appear to be contrary to the guidelines issued 
by the Reserve Bank and National Agriculture and Rural Development Bank;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  any money belonging to the multi-State co-operative society which 
appears to the auditor to be bad or doubtful of recovery;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  the loans given by the multi-State co-operative society to the members 
of the board;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  any violation of guidelines, conditions etc. issued by the Reserve 
Bank of India or National Agriculture and Rural Development Bank by any 
co-operative bank;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>f</number>  any other matter as may be specified by the Central Registrar in this 
regard.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Procedure to be 
adopted by liquidator.—When 
a liquidator has been appointed under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 89, the 
following procedure shall be adopted:—
 <subsection>
        
<number>a</number>  The appointment of the liquidator shall be notified by the Central 
Registrar in the Official Gazette.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>b</number>  The liquidator shall, as soon as the order of winding up of the 
multi-State co-operative society takes effect, publish by such means as he may 
think proper, a notice, requiring all claims against the multi-State 
co-operative society, the winding up of which has been ordered, to be submitted 
to him within two months of the publication of the notice. All liabilities 
recorded in the account books of a multi-State co-operative society shall be 
deemed ipso facto to have been duly submitted to him under this clause.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>c</number>  The liquidator shall investigate all the claims against the 
multi-State co-operative society and decide questions of priority arising 
between claimants.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>d</number>  The liquidator shall recover all sums and other properties to which 
the multi-State co-operative society is entitled and may institute such suits 
for that purpose or such suits incidental to liquidation proceedings as he may 
think proper.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>e</number>  The liquidator may empower any person, by general or special order in 
writing, to make collections and to grant valid receipts on his behalf.
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>f</number>  The liquidator shall, after setting the assets and liabilities of 
multi-State co-operative society as they stood on the date on which the order of 
winding up is made, proceed next to determine from time to time the contribution 
including debts due and costs of liquidation to be made or remaining to be made 
by each of its members, past members, or by the estates, or nominees, heirs or 
legal representatives of deceased members or by any officers or former officers, 
to the assets of the multi-State co-operative society, under clause (b) of 
sub-section (2) of section 90. Should necessity arise, he may also make a 
subsidiary order regarding such contributions and such order shall be 
enforceable in the same manner as the original order.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>g</number>  All funds in the charge of the liquidator shall be deposited in the 
Post Office Savings Banks or in a co-operative bank or with such other banks as 
may be approved by the Central Registrar and shall stand in his name.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>h</number>  The Central Registrar shall fix the amount of remuneration, if any, to 
be paid to the liquidator. The remuneration shall be included in the cost of 
liquidation, which shall be payable out of the assets of the multi-State 
co-operative society in priority of all other claims.
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  The liquidator may call for the meeting of the members of the 
multi-State co-operative society under liquidation.
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>j</number>  The liquidator shall submit to the Central Registrar a quarterly 
report in such form as the Central Registrar may, specify showing the progress 
made in liquidation of the multi-State co-operative society.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>k</number>  The liquidator shall keep such books and accounts as may from time to 
time be specified by the Central Registrar who may at any time cause such books 
and accounts to be audited.
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>l</number>  At the conclusion of the liquidation, the liquidator shall call for a 
general meeting of the members of the dissolved society at which the liquidator 
or any other person authorised by him, by special or general order in writing in 
this behalf, shall summarise, the result of his proceedings and shall take a 
vote as to the disposal of any surplus funds. The liquidator shall submit his 
final report to the Central Registrar with a copy of the proceedings of the 
general meeting referred to above and make over to the Central Registrar all 
books and registers and accounts etc., belonging to the multi-State co-operative 
society and all books and accounts relating to the liquidation proceedings kept 
by him.
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>m</number>  If any liability cannot be discharged by the liquidator owing to the 
whereabouts of the claimants not being known or for any other cause, the amount 
covered by such undischarged liability may be deposited in a Co-operative Bank 
and shall be available for meeting the claims of the person or persons 
concerned.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>n</number>  A liquidator may, at any time, be removed by the Central Registrar and 
he shall on such removal be bound to hand over all the property and documents 
relating to the society under liquidation to such persons as the Central 
Registrar may direct.
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>o</number>  All the books and records of a multi-State co-operative society whose 
registration has been cancelled and the proceedings of liquidation of a 
multi-State co-operative society ordered to be wound up may be destroyed by the 
Central Registrar after the expiry of three years from the date of the order 
cancelling the registration of the multi-State co-operative society.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Application of 
assets of the multi-State co-operative society.—The 
assets of the multi-State co-operative society shall be applied in order of 
priority as given below for payment of the liabilities:
 <section>
        
<number>1</number>  Pro-rata payment of all outside liabilities.
 </section><section>
        
<number>2</number>  Pro-rata repayment of loans and deposits of members.
 </section><section>
        
<number>3</number>  Pro-rata refund of share capital.
 </section><section>
        
<number>4</number>  Pro-rata payment of dividend on the share at the rate not exceeding 
6.25 per cent. per annum for the period of liquidation.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Disputes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purposes of sub-section (4) of section 84 of the Act, the Central 
Registrar may appoint and fix the fee of the arbitrators subject to the 
provisions of Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise 
provided under this Act, the provisions of the Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 
1996 shall apply to all arbitration under this Act as if the proceedings for 
arbitration were referred for settlement or decision under the provisions of the 
Arbitration and Conciliation Act, 1996.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Appeals.—For 
the purpose of sub-section (2) of section 99, an appeal against any decision or 
order shall be made, if the decision or order was made by—
 <section>
        
<number>a</number>  the Central Registrar appointed under sub-section (1) of section 4 of 
the Act, to the Officer not below the rank of Additional Secretary to the 
Government of India in the Department of Agriculture and Co-operation as may be 
decided by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
        
<number>b</number>  any officer of the Central Government or of a State Government of the 
rank of Registrar, on whom powers of the Central Registrar have been conferred 
under sub-section (2) of section 4 of the Act, to the Joint Secretary to the 
Government of India in the Department of Agriculture and Co-operation, Incharge 
of Co-operation.
 </section><section>
        
<number>c</number>  any other officer of the State Government on whom powers of Central 
Registrar have been conferred under sub-section (2) of section 4 of the Act, to 
the Chief Director (Co-operation) in the Ministry of Agriculture and 
Co-operation or any other Officer authorised by the Central Government in this 
behalf.
 
 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Procedure regarding appeals. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> An appeal under 
sub-section (2) of section 99 shall be either presented in person or sent by 
registered post to the appellate authority. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The appeal shall be in the form of a memorandum and shall be accompanied 
by the original or certified copy of the order appealed from. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal shall— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> specify the name and address of the appellant and also the name and 
  address of the respondent or respondents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> state by whom the order appealed against was made; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> set forth concisely and under distinct heads, the grounds of objection 
  to the order appealed against together with a memorandum of evidence; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> state preciselyt 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> give the date of order appealed against; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> the memorandum of the appeal inclusive of memorandum of evidence shall 
  be supported by an affidavit duly sworn by the appellant. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where, an appeal under sub-section (2) of section 99 is preferred after 
the expiry of sixty days specified in the said sub-section, it shall be 
accompanied by a petition supported by an affidavit setting forth the facts on 
which the appellant relies to satisfy the appellate authority that he had 
sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within the period mentioned in 
that sub-section. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> On receipt of the appeal, the appellate authority shall as soon as 
possible examine it and ensure that— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the person presenting the appeal has the locus standi to do 
  so; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> The appellate authority may call upon the appellant to remedy the defects 
if any, or he relief which the appellant sought for; and furnish such additional 
information as may be necessary, within a period of fifteen days of the receipt 
of the notice to do so. If the appellant fails to remedy the defects or furnish 
the additional information called for within the said period, the appeal 
petition may be dismissed. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The appellate authority may, before passing orders under section 99 
obtain from any subordinate officer such further information in regard to the 
enquiry or the proceedings for the purpose of verifying the regularity of such 
proceedings or the correctness, legality or propriety of any decision passed or 
order made therein. The appellate authority may also call for and obtain from 
the parties connected with such enquiry or proceedings such information as is 
necessary with reference to the examination of the records of enquiry or 
proceedings and the information obtained from the subordinate officer. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The appellate authority shall on the basis of the enquiry conducted and 
with reference to the records examined, pass such order on the appeal as may 
deem just and reasonable: 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[Provided that the Appellate Authority shall pass such order 
within a period of 180 days except in the cases where there is any order, stay 
or restraint or injunction from any competent court]. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> Every order of the appellate authority under sub-section (2) of section 
99 shall be in writing and it shall be communicated to the appellant and to such 
other parties as in the opinion of that authority are likely to be affected by 
the decision or order and to officer concerned against whose order was made. 

 
 <subsection><number>b</number> it is made within the prescribed time limit; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> it conforms to all the provisions of the Act and the rules. 
</subsection>




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>33</number> Application for review. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every application under 
section 101 shall be in the form of a memorandum setting forth concisely and 
under distinct heads the new and important facts which after the exercise of the 
due diligence, were not then within the knowledge of the applicant or could not 
be produced by him when the order was made or mistake or errors apparent on the 
face of the record or order reasons on the basis of which review is sought. It 
shall be accompanied by a memorandum of evidence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application shall be accompanied by the original or a certified copy 
of the order to which the application relates. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No application for review shall be entertained unless it is accompanied 
by such additional number of copies as there are parties to the original order. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> An application for review by any party shall be made within thirty days 
from the date of communication of the order of the appellate authority sought to 
be reviewed. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The application shall, so far as it may be necessary, be disposed of by 
the appellant authority in such manner as may be deemed fit: 
 Provided that no order in review application shall be made unless notice has 
been given to all interested parties and they have been afforded a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard: 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[Provided further that the Appellate Authority shall pass such 
order within a period of 180 days except in the cases where there is any order, 
stay or restraint or injunction from any competent court]. 

</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Preparation of a 
scheme for the reconstitution or reorganisation of multi-State co-operative 
societies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Registrar or the authorised officer, as the case may be, shall 
prepare a scheme referred to in sub-section (2) of section 103 for the 
reconstitution or reorganisation of any multi-State co-operative society 
rendered as such, consequent on the reorganisation of States referred to in 
sub-section (1) of section 103. The Central Registrar or the authorised officer 
with the previous approval of the Central Government forward a copy of the 
scheme to the President or the Chairperson of the multi-State co-operative 
society with the direction that the scheme be placed before a meeting of the 
general body of the multi-State co-operative society specially convened for the 
purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The meeting referred 
to in sub-rule (1) shall be convened not less than forty days after the date of 
issue of the notice to the members and the creditors of the multi-State 
co-operative society in the manner specified in sub-rule (3).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A written notice 
specifying the date, hour and place of meeting and the business to be transacted 
there at shall be given to every member and shall be accompanied by a copy of 
the scheme to be considered at the meeting. The notice to each member and 
creditor shall,—
 <subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  be delivered or tendered to him in person;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  be sent to him by registered post; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>iii</number>  be served on him in such other manner as may be specified in the 
bye-laws of the society.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in any rule or bye-law governing the 
multi-State co-operative society, where the Central Registrar or the authorised 
officer in this behalf is satisfied that the President or Chairperson of the 
society has failed to convene the meeting of the general body as required under 
sub-rule (1), the Central Registrar or the authorised officer, as the case may 
be, shall convene a meeting of the general body of the multi-State co-operative 
society by giving fourteen days notice to all the members and creditors of the 
multi-State co-operative society.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> Payment of fees for 
inspection of records.—The 
fees for payment of inspection of records by any other person, other than the 
member shall be rupee one per folio.
 
 
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>36</number> Mode of service of summon. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every summon issued 
under the Act or these rules shall be in writing, shall be authenticated by the 
seal, if any, of the officer by whom it is issued and shall be signed by such 
officer or by any person authorised by him 1 [not below the rank of Assistant 
Registrar of Co-operative Societies in a State or an officer of equivalent rank] 
in writing in that behalf. It shall require the person summoned to appear before 
the said officer at a stated time and place, and shall specify whether his 
attendance is required for the purpose of giving evidence, or to produce a 
document, or for both purposes, and any particular document the production of 
which is required, shall be described in the summons with reasonable accuracy. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person may be summoned to produce a document, without being summoned 
to give evidence, and any person summoned merely to produce a document shall be 
deemed to have complied with the summons if he causes such document to be 
produced, instead of attending personally to produce the same. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The service of summons under the Act or these rules on any person, may be 
effected in any of the following ways:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> by giving or tendering it to such person; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> if such person is not found, by delivering or transmitting at the place 
  where the person or his agent empowered to accept the summons on behalf of the 
  person, actually and voluntarily resides or carries on business or personally 
  works for gain; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> if the address of such person is known to the Central Registrar or 
  other authorised person by sending it to him by registered post 
  acknowledgement due; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> if none of the means aforesaid is available, by affixing it in some 
  conspicuous part of his last known place where actually or voluntarily resides 
  or carries on business or personally works for gain. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where the serving officer delivers or tenders a copy of the summons to 
the person personally or his agent in his behalf, he shall require the signature 
of the person to whom the copy is so delivered or tendered as an acknowledgement 
of service endorsed on the original summons. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The serving officer shall in all cases in which the summons have been 
served under sub-rule (4), endorse or annex, or cause to be endorsed or annexed, 
on or to the original summons a return stating the time when and the manner in 
which the summons was served and the name and address of the person, if any, 
identifying the person served and witnessing the delivery or tender of the 
summons. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where the person to be summoned is a public officer or is a servant of a 
company or a local authority, the officer issuing the summons may, if it appears 
that the summons may be conveniently so served, send it by registered post 
acknowledgement due for service on the party to be summoned, to the head of the 
office in which he is employed together with a copy to be retained by such 
person. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>37</number> Procedure in execution of decrees, orders and decisions. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any decree-holder requiring the provisions of clause (c) of 
section 94 to be applied, shall apply to the recovery officer in whose 
jurisdiction the cause of action arose and shall deposit the necessary costs as 
fixed by the Central Registrar. If the judgement debtor resides, or the property 
to be proceeded against is situated, outside the jurisdiction of such recovery 
officer, the recovery officer shall transfer the application to the recovery 
officer in whose jurisdiction the judgement debtor resides or the property is 
situated. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every such application shall be made in the form specified by the Central 
Registrar and shall be signed by the decree-holder. The decree-holder may 
indicate whether he wishes to proceed against the immovable property mortgaged 
to the decree-holder or other immovable property or to secure the attachment of 
movable property. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> On receipt of such application, the recovery officer shall verify the 
correctness and genuineness of the particulars set forth in the application with 
the records, if any, in the office of Central Registrar and prepare a demand 
notice in writing in duplicate in the form specified by the Central Registrar, 
setting forth the name of the judgment debtor and the amount due and forward it 
to the Sale Officer. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Unless the decree-holder has expressed a desire that proceedings should 
be taken in a particular order as laid down in sub-rule (2), execution shall 
ordinarily be taken in the following manner, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> movable property of the defaulter shall be first proceeded against, but 
  this shall not preclude the immovable property being proceeded against 
  simultaneously in case of necessity; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> if there is no movable property, or if the sale proceeds of the 
  movable property, or properties attached and sold are insufficient to meet in 
  full the demand of the decree-holder, the immovable property mortgaged to the 
  decree-holder, or other immovable property belonging to the judgment debtor 
  may be proceeded against. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>5</number> In the attachment and sale of movable property, the following rules shall 
be observed, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Sale Officer, shall after giving previous notice to the 
  decree-holder proceed to the village or place where the judgment debtor 
  resides or the property to be distrained is situated and serve a demand notice 
  upon the judgment debtor if he is present. If the amount due together with the 
  expenses be not at once paid, the Sale Officer shall make the distress and 
  shall immediately deliver to the judgment debtor a list or inventory of the 
  property distrained and an intimation of place and day and hour at which the 
  distrained property will be brought to sale if the amount due are not 
  previously discharged. If the judgment debtor is absent, the Sale Officer 
  shall serve the demand notice on some adult male member of his family, or on 
  his authorised agent, or when such service cannot be effected, shall affix a 
  copy of the demand notice on some conspicuous part of his residence. He shall 
  then proceed to make the distress and shall fix the list of property attached 
  on the usual place of residence of the judgment debtor, endorsing thereon the 
  place where the property may be lodged or kept and an intimation of the place, 
  day and hour of sale. 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>aa</number> The demand notice issued by the recovery officer under 
  sub-rule (3) shall contain the name of the judgment debtor, the amount due, 
  including the expenses, if any, and the batta to be paid to the person who 
  shall have the demand notice, the time allowed for payment and in case of 
  non-payment, the particulars of the properties to be attached and sold. After 
  receiving the demand notice, the time allowed for payment and in case of 
  non-payment, the particulars of the properties to be attached and sold. After 
  receiving the demand notice, the sale officer shall serve or cause to be 
  served demand notice upon the judgment debtor. If the judgment debtor fails to 
  pay the amount specified in the demand notice within the time allowed.] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> After the distress is made, the Sale Officer may arrange for the 
  custody of the property attached with the decree-holder or otherwise. If the 
  Sale Officer requires the decree-holder to undertake the custody of the 
  property he shall be bound to do so and any loss incurred owing to his 
  negligence shall be made good by the decree-holder. If the attached property 
  is live-stock, the decree-holder shall be responsible for providing the 
  necessary food therefor. The Sale Officer may, at the instance of the judgment 
  debtor or of any person claiming an interest in such property, leave it in the 
  village or place where it was attached, in the charge of such judgment debtor 
  or person, if he gives a bond in the form specified in the Central Registrar 
  with one or more sufficient sureties for the production of the property as and 
  when called for. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The distress shall be made after sunrise and before sunset and not at 
  any other time. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> The distress levied shall not be excessive, that is to say, the 
  property distrained shall be as nearly as possible proportionate to the sum 
  due by the defaulter together with interest and all expenses incidental to the 
  distraint, detention and sale. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> If crops or ungathered products of the land belonging to a judgment 
  debtor are attached, the Sale Officer may cause them to be sold when fit for 
  reaping or gathering, or at his option may cause them to be reaped or gathered 
  in due session and stored in proper place until sold. In the latter case, the 
  expense of reaping or gathering and storing such crops or products shall be 
  defrayed by the owner upon his redeeming the property or from the proceeds of 
  the sale in the event of its being sold. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> The Sale Officer shall not work the bullocks or cattle, or make use of 
  the goods or effect distrained, and he shall provide the necessary food for 
  the cattle or livestock, the expense attending which shall be defrayed by the 
  owner upon his redeeming the property or from the proceeds of the sale in the 
  event of its being sold. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> It shall be lawful for the Sale Officer to force open any stable, cow 
  house, granary, godown, out-house or other building and he may also enter any 
  dwelling house, the outer door of which may be open and may break open the 
  door of any room in such dwelling house for the purpose of attaching property 
  belonging to a defaulter and lodged therein, provided always that it shall not 
  be lawful for the officer to break open or enter apartment in such dwelling 
  house appropriate for the zenana or residence of women except as hereinafter 
  provided. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> Where the Sale Officer may have reason to suppose that the property of 
  a defaulter is lodged within a dwelling house the outer door of which may be 
  shut or within any apartments appropriated to women which by custom or usage 
  are considered private, the Sale Officer shall represent the fact to the 
  officer in charge of the nearest police station. On such representation, the 
  officer-in-charge of the said station shall send a police officer to the spot 
  in the presence of whom the Sale Officer may force open the other door of such 
  dwelling house, like manner as he may break open the door of any room within 
  the house except the zenana. The Sale Officer may also, in the presence of the 
  police officer, after due notice given for the removal of women within a 
  zenana and, after furnishing means for their removal in a suitable manner if 
  they be women of rank who according to the custom of usage cannot appear in 
  public, enter the zenana apartments for the purpose of distraining the 
  judgment debtor's property, if any, deposited therein, but such property, if 
  found, shall be immediately removed from such apartments after which they 
  shall be left free to the former occupants. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> The Sale Officer shall on the day previous to and on the day of sale 
  cause proclamation of the time and place of the intended sale to be made by 
  beat of drum in the village or place in which the judgment debtor resides on 
  two consecutive days previous to the date of sale and on the day of sale prior 
  to the commencement of the sale and in such other place or places as the 
  officer may consider necessary to give due publicity to the sale. No sale 
  shall take place until after the expiration of the period of fifteen days from 
  the date on which the sale notice has been served or affixed in the manner 
  prescribed in clause (a) of this sub-rule: 
 Provided that where the property seized is subject to speedy or natural 
  decay, or where the expense of keeping it in custody is likely to exceed its 
  value, the Sale Officer may sell it at any time before the expiry of the said 
  period of fifteen days, unless the amount due is sooner paid. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> At the appointed time the property shall be put up in one or more lots, 
  as the Sale Officer may consider advisable and shall be disposed of to the 
  highest bidder: 
 Provided further that the Sale Officer may, in his discretion, adjourn the 
  sale to a specified date and time recording his reasons for such adjournment. 
  Where a sale is so adjourned for a longer period than seven days, a fresh 
  proclamation under clause (i) shall be made unless the judgment debtor 
  consents to waive it. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> The property shall be paid for in cash at the time of sale, or as soon 
  thereafter as the officer holding the sale shall appoint, and the purchaser 
  shall not be permitted to carry away any part of the property until he has 
  paid for it in full. Where the purchaser may fail in payment of purchase 
  money, the property shall be resold. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> Where any property which has been attached under these rules has been 
  forcibly or clandestinely removed by any person, the Sale Officer may apply to 
  a civil court having jurisdiction for restoration of such property. Where the 
  court is satisfied about the truth of the facts, as alleged in the 
  application, it may order forthwith such property to be restored to the Sale 
  Officer. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> Where prior to the day fixed for sale, the defaulter or any person 
  acting on his behalf or any person claiming an interest in the property 
  attached, pays the full amount due including interest, batta and other costs 
  incurred in attaching the property, the Sale Officer shall cancel the order of 
  attachment and release the property forthwith. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> The movable property mentioned as exempt from attachment in the proviso 
  to section 60 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), shall not be 
  liable to attachment or sale under these rules. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>6</number> Where the movable property to be attached is the salary or allowance or 
wages of a public servant or a servant of a local authority or a firm or a 
company, the recovery officer may, on receiving a report from the Sale Officer, 
order that the amount shall, subject to the provisions of section 60 of the Code 
of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) be withheld from such salary or allowances 
or wages either in one payment or by monthly instalment as the recovery officer 
may direct and upon receipt of the order, the officer or other person whose duty 
it is to disburse such salary or allowance or wages shall withhold and remit to 
the Sale Officer, the amount due under the order or the monthly instalment, as 
the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> (i) Where the property to be attached consists of the share or interest 
of the defaulter in movable property belonging to him and another as co-owners, 
the attachment shall be made by a notice to the defaulter, prohibiting him from 
transferring the share or interest or charging it in any way. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Where the property to be attached is negotiable instrument not 
  deposited in a court, nor in the custody of a public officer, the attachment 
  shall be made by actual seizure and the instrument shall be brought to the 
  office of the recovery officer ordering the attachment and be held subject to 
  his further orders. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Where the property to be attached in the custody of any court or 
  public officer, the attachment shall be made by a notice to such court or 
  officer, requesting that such property and any interest or dividend becoming 
  payable thereon may be held subject to the further orders of the recovery 
  officer issuing the notice: </subsection>
 Provided that where such property is in the custody of a court or recovery 
officer of another district, any question of title or priority arising between 
the decree-holder and any other person not being the judgment debtor claiming to 
be interested in such property by virtue of any assignment, attachment or 
otherwise shall be determined by such court or recovery officer. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> (i) Where the property to be attached is a decree either for the payment 
of money or for sale in enforcement of a mortgage or charge, the attachment 
shall be made if the decree sought to be attached was passed by the Central 
Registrar or any other person authorised by him <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[not below the rank 
of Assistant Registrar of Co-operative Societies in a State or an officer of 
equivalent rank]. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Where the Central Registrar makes an order under clause (i) he shall 
  on the application of the decree-holder who has attached the decree, proceed 
  to execute the attached decree and apply the net proceeds in satisfaction of 
  the decree sought to be executed. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The holder of a decree sought to be executed by the attachment of 
  another decree of the nature specified in clause (i), shall be deemed to be 
  the representative of the holder of the attached decree and to be entitled to 
  execute such attached decree in any manner for the holder thereof. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Where the property to be attached in execution of a decree is a decree 
  other than a decree of the nature referred to in clause (i), the attachment 
  shall be made by the issue of a notice by the recovery officer to the holder 
  of such decree prohibiting him from transferring or charging the same in any 
  way. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> The holder of a decree attached under this sub-rule shall give the 
  recovery officer executing the decree such information and aid as may 
  reasonably be required. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> On the application of the holder of a decree sought to be executed by 
  the attachment of another decree, the recovery officer making an order of 
  attachment under this sub-rule shall give notice of such order to the 
  judgment-debtor bound by the decree attached; and no payment or adjustment of 
  the attached decree made by the judgment-debtor in contravention of such order 
  after receipt of notice thereof either through the said recovery officer or 
  otherwise, shall be recognised so long as the attachment remains in force. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>9</number> Where the movable property to be attached is,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a debt due to the judgment debtor in question, 
 
 
 A copy of such order shall be sent in the case of the debt to the debtor, in 
the case of the share or deposit, to the proper officer of the corporation and 
in the case of the other movable property to the person in possession of such 
property. As soon as the debt referred to in clause (a) or the deposit referred 
to in clause (b) matures, the recovery officer may direct the person concerned 
to pay the amount to him. Where the share is not withdrawable, the recovery 
officer shall arrange for its sale through a broker. Where the share is 
withdrawable, its value shall be paid to the recovery officer or to the party 
referred to in clause (c). In the case of other moveable property referred to in 
sub-clause (iii) of clause (c) the person concerned shall place it in the hands 
of the recovery officer when it becomes deliverable to the defaulter. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a share in the capital of a corporation or a deposit invested therein, 
  or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> other movable property not in the possession of the judgment debtor, 
  except property deposited in or in the custody of any civil court, the 
  attachment shall be made by a written order signed by the recovery officer 
  prohibiting— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> in the case of a debt, the creditor from recovering the debt and the 
    debtor from making payment thereof; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> in the case of a share or deposit, the person in whose name the 
    share or the deposit may be standing, from transferring the share or deposit 
    or receiving any dividend or interest thereon; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> in the case of any other movable property, the person in possession 
    of it from giving it over to the judgment debtor. </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>10</number> Immovable property shall not be sold in execution of a decree unless 
such property has been previously attached: 
 Provided that where the decree has been obtained on the basis of a mortgage 
of such property it shall not be necessary to attach it. 
 </section><section><number>11</number> In the attachment and sale, or sale without attachment of immovable 
property, the following rules shall be observed, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> The application presented under sub-rule (2) shall contain a 
  description of the immovable property to be proceeded against, sufficient for 
  its identification and in case such property can be identified by boundaries 
  or numbers in a record of settlement or survey, the specification of such 
  boundaries or numbers and the specification of the defaulter's share or 
  interest in such property to the best of the belief of the decree-holder and 
  so far as he has been able to ascertain it. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The demand notice issued by the recovery officer under sub-rule (3) 
  shall contain the name of the judgment debtor, the amount due, including the 
  expenses, if any, and the batta to be paid to the person who shall serve the 
  demand notice, the time allowed for payment and in case of non-payment, the 
  particulars of the properties to be attached and sold or to be sold without 
  attachment, as the case may be. After receiving the demand notice, the Sale 
  Officer shall serve or cause to be served a copy of the demand notice upon the 
  judgment debtor or upon some adult male member of his family at his usual 
  place of residence, or upon his authorised agent or if such personal service 
  is not possible, shall affix a copy thereof on some conspicuous part of such 
  immovable property to be attached and sold or sold without attachment, as the 
  case may be: </subsection>
 Provided that where the recovery officer is satisfied <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[for the 
reasons to be recorded in writing] that a judgment debtor with intent to defeat 
or delay the execution proceedings against him is about to dispose of whole or 
any part of his property, the demand notice issued by the recovery officer under 
sub-rule (3) shall not allow any time to the judgment debtor for payment of the 
amount due by him and the property of the judgment debtor shall be attached 
forthwith. 
 
 <subsection><number>c</number> If the judgment debtor fails to pay the amount specified in the demand 
  notice within the time allowed, the Sale Officer shall proceed to attach and 
  sell or sell without attachment, as the case may be, the immovable property 
  mentioned in the application for execution in the following manner. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Where attachment is required before sale, the Sale Officer shall, if 
  possible cause a notice of attachment to be served on the judgment debtor 
  personally. Where personal service is not possible, the notice shall be 
  affixed in some conspicuous part of the judgment debtor's last known 
  residence, if any. The fact of attachment shall also be proclaimed by beat of 
  drum or other custody mode at some place on, or adjacent to, such property and 
  at such other place or places as the recovery officer may consider necessary 
  to give due publicity to the sale. The attachment notice shall set forth that, 
  unless the amount due with interest and expenses be paid within the date 
  therein mentioned, the property will be brought to sale. A copy of attachment 
  notice shall be sent to the decree-holder. Where the Sale Officer so directs 
  the attachment shall also be notified by public proclamation in the Official 
  Gazette. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Proclamation of sale shall be published by affixing a notice in the 
  office of the recovery officer and the taluk office at least thirty days 
  before the date fixed for the sale and also by beat of drum in the village (on 
  two consecutive days previous to the date of sale and on the day of sale prior 
  to the commencement of the sale). Such proclamation shall, where attachment is 
  required before sale, be made after the attachment has been effected. Notice 
  shall also be given to the decree-holder and the judgment debtor. The 
  proclamation shall state the time and place of sale and specify as fairly and 
  accurately as possible, the following namely:— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> the property to be sold; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> any encumbrances to which the property is liable; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> the amount for the recovery of which sale is ordered; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> every other matter which the Sale Officer considers material for a 
    purchaser to know in order to judge the nature and value of the property. 
    </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> When any immovable property is sold under these rules, the sale shall 
  be subject to the prior encumbrances on the property, if any. The 
  decree-holder shall, when the amount for the realisation of which the sale is 
  held exceeds rupees one hundred, furnish to the Sale Officer within such time 
  as may be fixed by him or by the recovery officer, an encumbrance certificate 
  from the Registration Department for the period of not less than twelve years 
  prior to the date of attachment of the property sought to be sold, or in cases 
  falling under the proviso to sub-rule (10), prior to the date of the 
  application for execution. The time for production of the encumbrance 
  certificate may be extended at the discretion of the Sale Officer or the 
  recovery officer, as the case may be. The sale shall be by public auction to 
  the highest bidder: </subsection>
 Provided that it shall be open to the Sale Officer to decline to accept the 
highest bid where the price offered appears to be unduly low or for other 
adequate reasons: 
 Provided further that the recovery officer or the Sale Officer may in his 
discretion adjourn the sale to a specified day and hour recording his reason for 
such adjournment. Where a sale is so adjourned for a longer period than seven 
days, a fresh proclamation under clause (e) shall be made, unless the judgment 
debtor consents to waive it. The sale shall be held after the expiry of not less 
than thirty days calculated from the date on which notice of the proclamation 
was affixed in the office of the recovery officer. The time and place of sale 
shall be the village where the property to be sold is situated or such adjoining 
prominent place of public resort as may be fixed by the recovery officer: 
 Provided also that in cases where an encumbrance certificate is not 
obtainable owing to the destruction of the connected records, an affidavit from 
the village patwari or corresponding officer in regard to the encumbrances known 
to him supported by a certificate from the Registration Department that the 
encumbrance certificate cannot be granted owing to the destruction of the 
connected records, shall be accepted in place of an encumbrance certificate. 

 
 <subsection><number>g</number> A sum of money equal to fifteen per cent. of the price of the immovable 
  property shall be deposited by the purchaser in the hands of the Sale Officer 
  at the time of the purchase and in default of such deposit, the property shall 
  forthwith be resold: 
 Provided that where the decree-holder is the purchaser and is entitled to 
  set off the purchase money under clause (k), the Sale Officer shall dispense 
  with the requirement of this clause. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> The remainder of the purchase money and the amount required for the 
  general stamp for the sale certificate shall be paid within fifteen days from 
  the date of sale: 
 Provided that the time for payment of the cost of the stamps may, for good 
  and sufficient reasons, be extended at the discretion of the recovery officer 
  up to thirty days from the date of sale: 
 Provided further that in calculating the amounts to be paid under this 
  clause, the purchaser shall have the advantage of any set off to which he may 
  be entitled under clause (k). 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> In default of payment within the period mentioned in clause (h) the 
  deposit may, if the recovery officer thinks fit, after defraying the expenses 
  of sale, be forfeited to the Central Government and the defaulting purchaser 
  shall forfeit all claims to the property or to any part of the sum for which 
  it may subsequently be sold. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> Every resale of immovable property in default of payment of the amount 
  mentioned in clause (h) within the period allowed for such payment, shall be 
  made after the issue of a fresh proclamation in the manner and for the period 
  herein before prescribed for the sale. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> Where a decree-holder purchases the property, the purchase money and 
  the amount due on the decree shall be set off against one another, and the 
  Sale Officer shall enter satisfaction of the decree in whole or in part 
  accordingly. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>12</number> Where prior to the date fixed for a sale, the defaulter or any person 
acting on his behalf or any person claiming an interest in the property sought 
to be sold tenders payment of the full amount due together with interest, batta 
and other expenses incurred in bringing the property to sale including the 
expenses of attachment, if any, the Sale Officer shall forthwith release the 
property after cancelling, where the property has been attached, the order the 
attachment. 
 </section><section><number>13</number> (a) Where immovable property has been sold by the Sale Officer, any 
person either owning such property or holding an interest therein by virtue of a 
title acquired before such sale may apply to have the sale set aside on his 
depositing with the recovery officer— 
 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> for payment to the purchaser a sum equal to five per cent. of the 
    purchase money, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> for payment to the decree-holder, the amount of arrears specified in 
    the proclamation of sale as that for the recovery of which the sale was 
    ordered together with interest thereon and the expenses of attachment, if 
    any, and sale and other costs due in respect of such amount, less amount 
    which may since the date of such proclamation have been received by the 
    decree-holder. </subsection>
 <subsection><number>b</number> If such deposit and application are made within thirty days from the 
  date of sale, the recovery officer shall pass an order setting aside the sale 
  and shall repay to the purchaser, the purchase money so far as it has been 
  deposited, together with five per cent. deposited by the applicant: 
 Provided that if more than one person have made deposit and application 
  under this sub-rule, the application of the first depositor to the officer 
  authorised to set aside the sale, shall be accepted. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> If a person applies under sub-rule (14) to set aside the sale of 
  immovable property, he shall not be entitled to make an application under this 
  sub-rule. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>14</number> (i) At any time within thirty days from the date of sale of immovable 
property, the decree-holder or any person entitled to share in a ratable 
distribution of the assets or whose interests are effected by the sale, may 
apply to the recovery officer to set aside the sale on the ground of a material 
irregularity or mistake or fraud in publishing or conducting it: 
 Provided that no sale shall be set aside on the ground of irregularity or 
fraud unless the recovery officer is satisfied that the applicant has sustained 
substantial injury by reason of such irregularity, mistake or fraud. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> If the application is allowed, the recovery officer, shall set aside 
  the sale and may direct a fresh one. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> On the expiration of thirty days from the date of sale if no 
  application to have the sale set aside is made or if such application has been 
  made and rejected, the recovery officer shall make an order confirming the 
  sale: 
 Provided that if he shall have reason to believe that the sale ought to be 
  set aside notwithstanding that no such application has been made or on grounds 
  other than those alleged in any application which has been made and rejected, 
  he may, after recording his reasons in writing, set aside the sale. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Whenever the sale of any immovable property is not so confirmed or is 
  set aside, the deposit or the purchase money, as the case may be, shall be 
  returned to the purchaser. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> After the confirmation of any such sale, the recovery officer shall 
  grant a certificate of sale bearing his seal and signature to the purchaser, 
  and such certificate shall state the property sold and the name of the 
  purchaser and it shall be conclusive evidence of the fact of the purchase in 
  all courts and tribunals, where it may be necessary to prove it and no proof 
  of the seal or signature of the recovery officer shall be necessary unless the 
  authority before whom it is produced shall have reason to doubt its 
  genuineness. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> An order made under this sub-rule shall be final, and shall not be 
  liable to be questioned in any suit or other legal proceedings. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>15</number> Where any lawful purchaser of immovable property is resisted and 
prevented by any person other than a person (not being the judgment debtor) 
claiming in good faith to be in possession of the property on his own account 
from obtaining possession of the immovable property purchased any court of 
competent jurisdiction on application, and production of the certificate of sale 
provided for by sub-rule (14) shall cause the proper process to be issued for 
the purpose of putting such purchaser in possession, in the same manner as if 
the immovable property purchased had been decreed to the purchaser by a decision 
of the court. 
 </section><section><number>16</number> It shall be lawful for the Sale Officer to sell the whole or any portion 
of the immovable property of a judgment debtor in discharge of money due: 
 Provided that so far as may be practicable, no larger section or portion of 
immovable property shall be sold than may be sufficient to discharge the amount 
due with interest and expenses of attachment, if any, and sale. 
 </section><section><number>17</number> Persons employed in serving notice or in other process under these rules 
shall be entitled to batta at such rates as may from time to time be fixed by 
the recovery officer. 
 </section><section><number>18</number> Where the cost and charges incurred in connection with attachment and 
sale of movable property or the attachment and sale or sale without attachment 
of immovable property under this rule, exceeds the amount of the cost deposited 
from the sale proceeds of the property sold or the money paid by judgment 
debtor, as the case may be, and the balance shall be made available to the 
decree-holder. 
 </section><section><number>19</number> Every person making a payment towards any money due for the recovery of 
which application has been made under this rule shall be entitled to a receipt 
for the amount signed by the Sale Officer or other officer empowered by the 
recovery officer in that behalf; such receipt shall state the name of the person 
making the payment and the subject matter in respect of which the payment is 
made. 
 </section><section><number>20</number> (a) Where any claim is preferred to, or any objection is made to the 
property attached under this rule on the ground that such property is not liable 
to such attachment, the Sale Officer shall investigate the claim or objection 
and dispose it of on the merits: 
 Provided that no such investigation shall be made when the Sale Officer 
considers that the claim or objection is frivolous. 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> Where the property to which the claim or objection relates has been 
  advertised for sale, the Sale Officer may postpone the sale pending the 
  investigation of the claim or objection. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Where a claim or an objection is preferred, the party against whom an 
  order is made may institute a suit to establish the right which the claim to 
  the property in dispute, but, subject to the result of such suit, if any, the 
  order shall be conclusive. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>21</number> (i) Any deficiency of price which may arise on a resale held under 
clause (j) of sub-rule (11) by reason of the purchaser's default and all 
expenses attending such resale shall be certified by the Sale Officer to the 
recovery officer and shall, at the instance of either the decree-holder or the 
judgment debtor be recoverable from the defaulting purchaser under the 
provisions of this rule. The cost, if any, incidental to such recovery shall be 
borne by the defaulting purchaser. 
 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Where the property may on the second sale, sell for a higher price 
  than at the first sale, the defaulting purchaser at the first sale, shall have 
  no claim to the difference or increase. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>22</number> Where any property has been attached in execution of a decree, but by 
reason of the decree-holder's default the recovery officer is unable to proceed 
further with the application for execution, he shall either dismiss the 
application or for any sufficient reason adjourn the proceedings to a future 
date. Upon the dismissal of such application, the attachment shall cease. 
 </section><section><number>23</number> Where assets are held by the Sale Officer and before the receipt of such 
assets, demand notices in pursuance of application for execution of 
decree-against the same defaulter have been received from more than one 
decree-holder and the decree-holders have not obtained satisfaction, the assets 
after deducting the costs or realisation shall be rateably distributed by the 
Sale Officer among all such decree-holders in the manner provided in section 73 
of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908). 
 </section><section><number>24</number> Where a defaulter dies before the decree has been fully satisfied, an 
application under sub-rule (1) may be made against the legal representative of 
the deceased and thereupon all the provisions of this rule shall, save as 
otherwise provided in this sub-rule, apply as if such legal representative were 
the judgment debtor. Where the decree is executed against such legal 
representative, he shall be liable only to the extent of the property of the 
deceased which has come to his hands and has not been duly disposed of, and for 
the purpose of ascertaining such liability, the recovery officer executing the 
decree may, of his own motion or on the application of the decree-holder compel 
such legal representative to produce such accounts as he thinks fit. 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Multi-State Co-operative Societies (Registration, Membership, Direction and 
Management, Settlement of Disputes, Appeal and Revision) Rules, 1985 and the 
Multi-State Co-operative Societies (Privileges, Properties and Funds, Accounts, 
Audit, Winding up and Execution of Decrees, Orders and Decisions) Rules, 1985 
are hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
appeal, anything done or any action taken under any of the rules so repealed 
shall, unless such thing or action is inconsistent with the provisions of these 
rules, be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions 
of these rules.
</section></article><form>
 

THE MULTI-STATE CO-OPERATIVE SOCIETIES RULES, 2002 

 

 
 

SCHEDULE
 

1. Procedure for the conduct of election to the board of multi-State 
co-operative societies. —(a) The board of directors in office shall 
meet, at least, sixty clear days in advance of the date of expiration of its 
term and by resolution determine the date, time and place for convening a 
general body meeting for the conduct of elections of its successor board. This 
provision will also apply mutatis mutandis to such multi-State 
co-operative societies as are under charge of the administrator appointed under 
sub-section (1) of section 123. The board of directors in this meeting shall 
also appoint a returning officer. 
 

(b) A copy of the decision referred to in paragraph (a) shall forthwith be 
sent to the Central Registrar. 
 

(c) The returning officer appointed under paragraph (a) shall, send 
intimation by local delivery or under postal certificate, about the date, time 
and place of the general meeting to each of the members of the multi-State 
co-operative society. Where other co-operative societies or multi-State 
co-operative societies are members, the returning officer shall call on such 
societies to send the name of their Chairperson or President or the Chief 
Executive or a duly authorised member of the board of such co-operative society 
or other multi-State co-operative society as a representative (hereinafter 
referred to as the delegate) in accordance with the provisions contained in 
sub-section (3) of section 38 together with the resolution of the board of the 
society and the specimen signature of the Chairperson or President or the Chief 
Executive or duly authorised member of the board, duly attested and bearing the 
seal of the society so as to reach him at least twenty-one clear days prior to 
the date fixed for the general meeting. Where there is no board of such 
co-operative society or other multi-State  
co-operative society, the 
administrator, or duly authorised administrator if there are more than one 
administrators, by whatever name called, shall intimate the returning officer in 
writing under his signature at least twenty-one clear days prior to the date 
fixed for the general meeting that he or the Chief Executive shall represent 
such society in the general meeting. Where no such resolution or communication 
intimating the name of delegate is received by the date fixed or where any 
intimation changing the name of the delegate is received after such date, it 
shall not be accepted for inclusion in the list of members or delegates of 
member-societies. Fresh resolution shall be required for every general meeting 
at which election shall be held. 
 

(d) It shall be the duty of the board of directors in office, or the 
administrator, as the case may be, to bring up-to-date the register of members 
and such other registers, as the returning officer may require and hand over 
such records, register or registers to the returning officer thirty days prior 
to the date fixed for the general meeting for the purpose of election. 
 

(e) The election shall be held at a general meeting of the society convened 
for the purpose, of which not less than fourteen days notice shall be given to 
the members. Such elections shall take place after all other matters included in 
the agenda have been considered. For the conduct of elections, the returning 
officer shall preside over the meeting: 
 

1[Provided that where the membership of a multi-State co-operative 
society exceeds one thousand, the returning officer may arrange for polling 
booths in the area of operation of such a Multi-State Co-operative Society, as 
deemed appropriate. Ballots cast in these polling booths shall be counted at the 
place of the General body convened for the purpose of election and results to be 
declared in the general body meeting.] 
 

(f) The notice of the general meeting shall be sent to members by any of the 
following modes, namely:— 
 
 

(i) by local delivery; or 
 

(ii) under postal certificate; or 
 

(iii) by publication in the news paper having wide circulation. 

 

(g) Notice of the general meeting shall also be affixed on the notice board 
of the multi-State co-operative society and its branches, if any. The notice 
shall contain information regarding— 
 
 

(i) the number of vacancies to be filled by election; 
 

(ii) the area of the constituency (specified in the bye-laws) from which 
  the members are to be elected; 
 

(iii) the qualifications, if any, specified in the bye-laws for eligibility 
  for membership on the board; 
 

(iv) the name of the returning officer, date, place and hours between which 
  nomination paper shall be filed by the members, such date being not less than 
  one clear day before the date fixed for election or if that happens to be a 
  holiday the day preceding which is not a public holiday. 
 

Explanation. —For the purpose of the sub-paragraph the term 
  “public holiday” means any day which is declared as a public holiday under 
  section 25 of the Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (26 of 1881) or any day 
  which has been notified by the Central Government, or as the case may be, the 
  State Government to be a public holiday for the offices of the Central 
  Government or the State Government; 
 

(v) the date on which and the time and place at which the nomination papers 
  will be taken up for scrutiny; 
 

(vi) the date and time of which, the place at which and the time between 
  which polling will take place. 
 

2. Preparation of list of members/delegates. —(a) The 
returning officer shall prepare a list of members eligible to vote as it stood 
on the date, thirty days prior to the date fixed for the poll and publish copies 
of the list by affixing them on the notice board at the principal place of 
business of the society and all its branches, if any, not less than fifteen days 
prior to the date fixed for election. The list shall specify,— 
 
 

(i) the admission number and name of the member, the name of the father or 
  husband, and the address of such member in the case of an individual member; 
  and 
 

(ii) the admission number, the name of the society, name of the delegate 
  proposed to represent the society, in the case of a member society; 
 

(iii) the admission number, the name of the society, name of the delegate 
  and the name of the constituency proposed to represent in the case of a member 
  society and the admission number, the name of the delegate and the name of the 
  constituency where a smaller body has been constituted under proviso to 
  sub-section (1) of section 38. 
 

(b) A copy of the list shall be supplied by the society to any member on 
payment of such fee as may be specified by the board. Where no fees has been 
specified, the person authorised as per bye-laws of the society shall supply 
such list on payment of an amount of rupees ten. 
 

(c) The returning officer shall also prepare an election programme specifying 
the date and time of receipt of nominations, scrutiny of nominations, withdrawal 
of nominations, the poll, if required and declaration of results. The election 
programme shall be displayed on the notice board of the society and also publish 
in the local newspaper at least fifteen days prior to the date of election. 
 

3. Nomination of candidates. —(a) Nomination of the 
candidate for election shall be made in Form III, which on application shall be 
supplied by the returning officer or any other officer authorised by him in this 
behalf, to any member free of costs. 
 

(b) Every nomination paper shall be signed by two members whose names are 
included in the list of the members or delegates. One of the members shall sign 
the form as proposer and the other as seconder for the nomination. The 
nomination paper shall also contain a declaration signed by the candidate, 
expressing his willingness to stand for election. 
 

(c) Every nomination paper shall be presented in person or sent by registered 
post with acknowledgement due, by the candidate himself to the Returning Officer 
or any person authorised by him in this behalf, so as to reach him before the 
date and time specified for the election programme. The returning officer or any 
officer authorised by him who receives the nomination paper shall enter on the 
nomination paper its serial number and certify the date and time at which the 
nomination paper has been received by him and shall immediately give a written 
acknowledgement for the receipt of the nomination papers if presented in person, 
which shall also bear the seal of the society. The returning officer shall, at 
the close of the time fixed for the receipt of nomination papers, prepare and 
display on the notice board of the society, a list of nominations received by 
him. Any nomination paper which is not delivered or received on or before the 
date and time fixed for its receipt, shall be rejected. 
 

(d) No person shall be nominated as a candidate for election to fill a seat 
on the board if he,— 
 
 

(i) is ineligible to vote; 
 

(ii) is disqualified to be the member or delegate or a member of the board 
  under the provisions of the Act and these rules; and 
 

(iii) does not posses the necessary qualifications specified in the 
  bye-laws of the society for election as member of the board. 
 

4. Scrutiny of nomination papers. —(a) (i) On the day fixed 
for the scrutiny of nomination papers, the returning officer shall, at the 
appointed hours, take up the scrutiny of nomination papers. The candidate or the 
proposer or seconder of each of the candidate may be present at the time and 
place when nomination papers are scrutinised. 
 

(ii) The returning officer shall examine the nomination papers and shall 
decide all objections which may be made by any candidate or his proposer or 
seconder in respect of any nomination and may, either on such objection, or on 
his own motion and after such summary enquiry, if any, as he thinks necessary, 
either accept or reject any nomination: 
 

Provided that the nomination of a candidate shall not be rejected namely on 
the ground of an incorrect description of his name or the name of his proposer 
or seconder or of any other particulars relating to the candidate or his 
proposer or seconder, as entered in the list of members referred to in paragraph 
4 (a) if the identity of the candidate, proposer or seconder, as the case may 
be, is established beyond reasonable doubt. 
 

(iii) The returning officer shall endorse on each nomination paper his 
decision accepting or rejecting the same as the case may be, and if the 
nomination paper is rejected, he shall record in writing a brief statement of 
his reasons for such rejection. 
 

(iv) The returning officer shall not allow any adjournment of the proceedings 
except when proceedings are interrupted or obstructed by riot or affray or by 
causes beyond his control. 
 

(v) The list of valid nominations as decided by the returning officer shall 
be published on the notice board of the society containing the names in the 
alphabetical order in English and address of the candidate as given in the 
nomination paper on the same day on which the scrutiny of the nomination paper 
is completed. 
 

(b) Any candidate may withdraw his candidature by notice in writing signed by 
him and delivered in person or by the person duly authorised by him at any time 
after the presentation of the nomination papers but before the date and time 
specified in the election programme for such withdrawal. A notice of withdrawal 
of candidate once given shall be irrevocable. 
 

5. Voting. —(a) If for any area or constituency for which 
election is to be held, the number of candidates whose nomination papers have 
been declared valid, does not exceed the number of candidates to be elected for 
that area or constituency, the returning officer shall at the general meeting 
convened for the purpose of the election, declare them to have been duly elected 
to the board. If the number of candidate whose nominations are valid exceeds the 
number to be elected for any area or constituency, the returning officer shall 
arrange for conducting a poll on the date and time fixed for the purpose. The 
returning officer may appoint as many polling officers as may be necessary for 
conducting the poll. 
 

(b) A candidate contesting the election may, by a letter, in Form IV, to the 
returning officer, appoint an agent to represent him where polling is held, to 
identify the voters and to watch the recording of votes. Such letter shall 
contain the consent in writing of the agent concerned. 
 

(c) Canvassing of votes by any person at the place where election are to be 
conducted shall be prohibited. 
 

(d) Immediately before the commencement of the poll, the returning officer 
shall show the empty ballot box to such persons as may be present at the time 
and shall then lock it up and affix his seal in such manner as to prevent its 
being opened without breaking the seal. The candidate or his agent also affix 
his own seal, if he so desires. 
 

(e) Every member or delegate who desires to exercise his right of vote shall 
be supplied with a ballot paper containing the names of contesting candidates 
arranged in alphabetical order either printed, typewritten or cyclostyled, 
according to convenience, on the ballot paper. The ballot paper shall also bear 
the seal of the society and also the initials of the returning officer on 
reverse of the ballot paper and further contain a column, for the voter to 
inscribe mark ‘X' against the name or names of the persons to whom he wants to 
vote. 
 

(f) Each polling station and where there is more than one polling booth at a 
station, each such booth shall contain a separate compartment in which the 
members or delegates can record their votes in secrecy. 
 

(g) Every member who desires to exercise his votes shall enter the polling 
station with an identity card, given to him by the society. The polling officer 
shall identify the member by putting questions to him with reference to the list 
of members or delegates eligible to vote in the polling station, furnished to 
him. If the polling officer is satisfied about the identity of the member and if 
there is no objection from any candidate or his polling agent present at the 
polling station, he shall issue a ballot paper to him after obtaining signature 
or thumb impression of the member or delegate on counterfoil perforated with the 
ballot paper. The counterfoil shall bear the serial number and other details of 
the ballot paper. On receipt of such ballot paper, the member shall proceed to 
the polling compartment set apart for the purpose and indicate the person or 
persons in whose favour he exercises his vote by inscribing a mark ‘X' against 
the name of the candidate or candidates, as the case may be, and put the ballot 
paper in the ballot box kept for the purpose with utmost secrecy. If owing to 
blindness or other physical infirmity or illiteracy a member is unable to 
inscribe the mark on the ballot paper the polling officer, and where no such 
polling officer is appointed, the returning officer shall ascertain from him the 
candidate or candidates, in whose favour he desires to vote, inscribe the mark 
‘X' on his behalf and put the ballot paper in the ballot box. 
 

(h) (i) Every member whose name is entered in the list of members/delegates 
eligible to vote, furnished to the polling officer, is entitled to poll his 
vote, unless there is a challenge by the candidate or his agent against his 
identity. If there is such a challenge about the identity of a member or if the 
polling officer feels any reasonable doubt, he shall then refer the matter to 
the returning officer who shall make a summary inquiry and decide the question 
with reference to the books of the society. 
 

(ii) The returning officer shall not entertain any challenge by a candidate 
or his polling agent, of a member's identity until the person who challenges 
pays a fee of  
Rs. 5 (Rupees five only) for every such vote, in cash. The 
returning officer shall thereafter entertain the challenge and ask the member 
who has come to poll the vote to affix his thumb-impression or signature, as the 
case may be, on a declaration describing his identity. If he refuses to do so, 
the member shall not be allowed to vote. If, on the other hand, as a result of 
such summary enquiry the identity of the member is established to the 
satisfaction of the returning officer, the polling officer shall issue ballot 
paper, and the member shall then be allowed to vote. In such cases the challenge 
fees paid shall be forfeited. At the end of the poll, the returning officer, 
shall render an account of challenge fees collected, fees refunded to the 
persons who challenged and the fees forfeited to the society together with a 
brief note on the decision arrived at by him after the summary inquiry in each 
case. 
 

(i) (A) If, at any stage of the polling, the proceedings are interrupted or 
obstructed by any riot or affray or if at such election it is not possible to 
conduct poll for any sufficient cause, the returning officer shall have power to 
cancel the polling after recording his reasons for such action. 
 

(B) Where the poll is stopped under clause (A) or where counting of votes is 
rendered impossible on account of destruction or loss of ballot boxes or any 
other sufficient reason, the returning officer shall cancel the polling after 
recording the reasons for such action in the minutes book of the society. 
 

(j) No voter shall be admitted after the time fixed for the polling; but a 
voter who enters the premises where ballot papers are being issued before the 
close of the polling time shall be issued the ballot paper and allowed to vote. 

 

(k) The counting of votes shall take place immediately after close of the 
poll. If this is not possible for reasons beyond the control of the returning 
officer, the ballot box shall be sealed with the seal of the returning officer 
and of the contesting candidates or of their agents, if they so desire, and 
deposited with the society for safe custody. The returning officer shall then 
announce and also intimate in writing to the candidates or their agents present 
the time and place at which the counting shall commence next day. Votes shall be 
counted by or under the supervision of the returning officer. Each candidate and 
his authorised agent shall have a right to be present at the time of counting. 
But the absence of any candidate or his agent at the time of counting shall not 
vitiate counting or announcement of results by the returning officer. 
 

6. General. —(a) A ballot paper shall be rejected by the 
returning officer, if,— 
 
 

(i) it bears any mark or writing by which the member who voted can be 
  identified; or 
 

(ii) it does not bear the seal of the society or the initial of the 
  returning officer; or 
 

(iii) the mark indicating the vote thereon is placed in such manner as to 
  make it doubtful to which candidate the vote has been cast; or 
 

(iv) is so damaged or mutilated that its identity as a genuine ballot paper 
  cannot be established. 
 

(b) If after the counting of the votes is completed, an equality of votes is 
found to exist between any candidates and the addition of one vote will entail 
any of those candidates to be declared elected, the returning officer shall 
forthwith decide between these candidates by lot and proceed as if the candidate 
on whom the lot falls had received an additional vote and declare him elected. 

 

(c) After the returning officer has completed the counting of votes, he shall 
prepare a return of the results of the polling and shall forthwith declare the 
results. The returning officer shall immediately thereafter record the 
proceedings of the election in a comprehensive report which shall form part of 
the records of the society and shall be binding on all. The returning officer 
shall immediately also furnish a copy of such a report together with a copy of 
the return of the results of polling, to the society for onward transmission to 
the Central Registrar. The society shall immediately forward such report and 
return of the results furnished by the returning officer to the Central 
Registrar. 
 

7. Election of office bearers. —(1) As soon as the members 
of the board have been elected the returning officer shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in the bye-laws of the multi-State co-operative society, 
convene a meeting of the newly constituted board for the purpose of election of 
the President or Chairperson, Vice-President or Vice-Chairperson or other 
elected office bearers of the society, by whatever name they are called. Such a 
meeting of the board shall not be conducted unless a majority of the number of 
members of newly constituted board, as per bye-laws are present. 
 

(2) At the meeting so convened by the Returning Officer, he shall preside 
over the meeting for the purpose of election of the office bearers. The election 
of office bearers of the multi-State co-operative society shall be by secret 
ballot. 
 

(3) The returning officer shall announce the schedule of election of office 
bearers, stating the number of vacancies to be filled by election, date, place 
and time between which nomination papers shall be filled by the members; the 
date on which and the time and place at which the nomination papers will be 
taken up for scrutiny; the date and time of withdrawal; and the date on which, 
the place at which the polling, if required, will take place. The returning 
officer shall intimate the schedule of election to all the newly elected or 
nominated members of the board. The nomination, in Form V, shall be made to the 
returning officer at such a meeting. The returning officer shall decide the 
objections if any, which may be made at the time, to any nomination and after 
making such summary inquiry, as he thinks necessary, announce the name of valid 
nominations. 
 

(4) If for any office for which elections are to be held, the number of 
candidates in respect of whom valid nominations have been announced, does not 
exceed the number of candidates to be elected for that office, the candidates 
for whom valid nominations have been announced shall be deemed to have been 
elected for that office and the returning officer shall make a declaration to 
that effect. If the number of candidates in respect of whom valid nominations 
have been announced for any office exceeds the number of candidates to be 
elected a poll by secret ballot shall be taken by the returning officer. The 
returning officer shall, thereafter, announce the number of votes secured by 
each candidate and the result of the election. 
 

(5) The returning officer, shall immediately thereafter record the 
proceedings of the election in a comprehensive report which shall form part of 
the records of the society and shall be binding on all. The returning officer 
shall immediately also furnish a copy of such a report together with a copy of 
the return of the results of polling, to the society for onward transmission to 
the Central Registrar. The society shall immediately forward such report and 
return of the results furnished by the returning officer to the Central 
Registrar. 
 

8. Custody of record of elections conducted. —After 
declaration of the result of election, the returning officer shall hand over the 
ballot papers and records relating to the election of the members of the board 
of directors and the office bearers to the chief executive of the multi-State 
co-operative society in a sealed cover. These shall safely, be preserved by the 
chief executive of the society for a period of six months from the date of 
election or till such time a dispute regarding elections, if any, filed is 
disposed of, whichever is later, and shall thereafter be destroyed. 
 

----------
 

1. Ins. by G.S.R. 717(E), dated 12th November, 2007 (w.e.f. 
15-11-2007 ). </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 717(E), dated 12th November, 2007 (w.e.f. 
15-11-2007 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> The proviso omitted by G.S.R. 717(E), dated 12th November, 
2007 (w.e.f. 15-11-2007 ). The proviso, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 717(E), dated 12th November, 2007 (w.e.f. 
15-11-2007 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 717(E), dated 12th November, 2007 (w.e.f. 
15-11-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 717(E), dated 12th November, 2007 (w.e.f. 
15-11-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Vide G.S.R. 790(E), dated 2nd December, 2002, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 2nd 
December, 2002.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 717(E), dated 12th November, 2007 
(w.e.f. 15-11-2007).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>