<act><tid>1834371</tid>
<title>THE MEDICAL TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 64 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 18th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to amend the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act, <year>1971</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1668170</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1370527</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Medical Termination of Pregnancy (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1257576</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>105436</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Medical Termination of 
Pregnancy Act, <year>1971</year> (34 of <year>1971</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the  
  principal Act),-
<section><tid>1248987</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the word" lunatic", the words" mentally ill 
person" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>386517</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (b), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (b)" mentally ill person" means a person who is in need of treatment 
by reason of any mental disorder other than mental retardation;'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>540255</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (4), in clause (a), for the word" lunatic", the words 
" mentally ill person" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>40701</tid>
<number> 4</number> Substitution of new section for section 4.- For section 4 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 4. Place where pregnancy may be terminated.- No termination of 
pregnancy shall be made in accordance with this Act at any place other 
than-

<section><tid>688138</tid>
<number>a</number>a hospital established or maintained by Government, or

</section>

<section><tid>948046</tid>
<number>b</number>a place for the time being approved for the purpose of this Act by 
Government or a District Level Committee constituted by that 
Government with the Chief Medical Officer or District Health Officer 
as the Chairperson of the said Committee:
Provided that the District Level Committee shall consist of not less 
than three and not more than five members including the Chairperson, 
as the Government may specify from time to time.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>826536</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (2) and the Explanation thereto, the following shall be 
substituted, namely:-
' (2) Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Penal Code (45  
  of <year>1860</year>), the termination of pregnancy by a person who is not a 
registered medical practitioner shall be an offence punishable with 
rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be l ss than two 
years but which may extend to seven years under that Code, and that 
Code shall, to this extent, stand modified.

<section><tid>1010107</tid>
<number>3</number>Whoever terminates any pregnancy in a place other than that 
mentioned in section 4, shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than two years but which may extend 
to seven years.

</section>

<section><tid>487398</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person being owner of a place which is not approved under 
clause (b) of section 4 shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which shall not be less than two years but which may extend 
to seven years.
Explanation 1.- For the purposes of this section, the expression 
" owner" in relation to a place means any person who is the 
administrative head or otherwise responsible for the working or 
pregnancy may be terminated under this Act. maintenance of a hospital 
or place, by whatever name called, where he

Explanation 2.- For the purposes of this section, so much of the 
provisions of clause (d) of section 2 as relate to the possession, by 
registered medical practitioner, of experience or training in 
gynaecology and obstetrics shall not apply.'.

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</section>

</article>



 </act>