<act><title>

The
Muslim Women (Protection of Rights
on Divorce) Rules, 19861</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Divorce)
Rules, 1986.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force at once.
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Muslim Women (Protection
of Rights on Divorce) Act, 1986 (25 of 1986); 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Code” means the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974); and 
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Form” means form annexed to these rules. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Service of summons.—
<section><number>1</number> Every
summons issued by a Magistrate on an
application made under the Act, shall be in writing, in duplicate, signed by the
Magistrate or by such other officer as he may, from time to time, direct, and
shall bear the seal of the Court.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Every such summons shall be accompanied by a true copy of the application.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every such summons issued under sub-rule (1) shall specify the date of the first
hearing of the application which shall not be later than seven days from the
date on which the summons is issued.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every summons shall be served by a police officer or by an officer of the Court
issuing it.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
The summons shall, if practicable, be served personally on the respondent by
delivering or tendering to him one of the duplicates of the summons.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Every respondent on whom the summons is so served shall, if so required by the
serving officer, sign a receipt therefor on the back of other duplicate.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
Where the respondent cannot, by the exercise of due diligence, be found, the
summons may be served by leaving one of the duplicates for him with some adult
male member of his family residing with him, and the person with whom the
summons is so left shall, if so required by the serving officer, sign a receipt,
therefor on the back of the other duplicate.
 


 </section><section><number>8</number>
If the service cannot, by the exercise of due diligence, be effected as provided
in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[sub-rule
(5)] or sub-rule (7), the serving officer shall affix
one of the duplicates of the summons to some conspicuous part of the
house or homestead in which the respondent ordinarily resides; and thereupon the
court, after making such inquiries as it thinks fit, may either declare that the
summons has been duly served <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[or]
order fresh summons in such manner as it considers proper.
 </section><section><number>9</number>
When a court desires that a summons issued by it shall be served at any place
outside its local jurisdiction, it shall ordinarily send such summons in
duplicate to a Magistrate within whose local jurisdiction, the respondent
resides, or is, to be there served.
 


 </section><section><number>10</number>
When a summons issued by a court is served outside its local jurisdiction and in
any case when an officer who served the summons is not present at the hearing of
the case, an affidavit purporting to be made before a Magistrate that such
summons has been served and a duplicate of summons purporting to be enforced [in
the manner provided by sub-rule (6) or sub-rule (7)] by the person to whom it
was delivered or tendered or with whom it was left shall be admissible in
evidence and the statements made therein shall be deemed to be correct unless
and until the contrary is proved.
 </section><section><number>11</number>
The affidavit mentioned in sub-rule (10) may be attached to the duplicates of
the summons and returned to the court. 


   







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>4</number>
Evidence.—All
evidence in the proceedings under the Act shall be taken in the presence of the
respondent against whom an order for the payment of provision and maintenance, Mahr
or 1[dower]
or the delivery of property is proposed to be made or, when his personal
attendance is dispensed with, in the presence of his pleader, and shall be
recorded in the manner specified for summary trial under the Code:
 


 Provided
that if the Magistrate is satisfied that the respondent is wilfully avoiding
service or wilfully neglecting to attend the court, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[the]
Magistrate may proceed to hear and determine the case ex parte and any
order so made may be set aside for good cause shown on application made within
seven days from the date thereof subject to such terms as to payment of cost to
the opposite party as the Magistrate may think just and proper.
 


  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Power to postpone or adjourn proceedings.—In
every application under the Act, the proceedings shall be held as expeditiously
as possible and in particular, when the examination of witnesses has once begun,
the same shall be continued from day to day until all the witnesses in
attendance have been examined unless the court finds adjournment of the same
beyond the following day to be necessary for reasons to be recorded.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Costs.—The court in dealing with the
applications under the Act shall have power to make such order as to cost as may
be just.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Affidavit under section 5.—An
affidavit filed under section 5 of the Act shall be in Form A.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Declaration under section 5.—A
declaration in 1[writing]
filed under
section 5 shall be in Form B.
  
  

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The
Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Divorce) Rules, 1986
 



 



 


Form
A
 


Form
of Affidavit 


 

(See
rule 7)
 

 
 

I/we,..........................son/wife
of......................aged............years, resident of....................
and...........son/wife of..........aged......years, resident
of...................hereby state on oath as follows:—
 

1.
That I/we have informed myself/ourselves of the provisions of section 5 of the
Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Divorce) Act, 1986 and of the provisions
of sections 125 to 128 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.
 

2.
That I/we, ........................., desire to be governed by the provisions of
sections 125 to 128 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 in preference to the
provisions of the Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Divorce) Act, 1986.
 

3.
That the contents of the above affidavit are true.
 

Deponent/Deponents.
 

Signed
and verified at........................this the ..............day
of..............19......../20........
 

Deponent/Deponents.
 

  



 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The
Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Divorce) Rules, 1986
 



 



 


Form
B
 


Form
of Declaration   


 

(See
rule 8)
 

 
 

I/we..........................,
son/wife of............................aged............years, resident of
........................ and..................son/wife
of........................aged..........years, resident of............
.............hereby declare as follows:—
 

1.
That I/we have informed myself/ourselves of the provisions of section 5 of the
Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Divorce) Act, 1986 and the provisions of
sections 125 to 128 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.
 

2.
That I/we,..........................,deisre to be governed by the provisions of
sections 125 to 128 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 in preference to the
provisions of the Muslim Women (Protection of Rights on Divorce) Act, 1986.
 

3.
That the contents of the above declaration are true.
 

Deponent/Deponents.
 

Signed
and verified at...........................this the........day
of...............................20........
 

Deponent/Deponents.
 

 

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Vide Corrigenda G.S.R. 834 (E), dated 4th June, 1986.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Vide Corrigenda G.S.R. 834 (E), dated 4th June, 1986.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>