<act><tid>1849884</tid>
<title>THE CONSTITUTION (SCHEDULED CASTES) ORDERS (SECOND AMENDMENT) 
ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 61 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 17th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, 
<year>1950</year>, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes)  (Union Territories) Order, 
<year>1951</year>, the Constitution (Jammu and Kashmir) Scheduled Castes Order, 
<year>1956</year>, the Constitution (Dadra and Nagar Haveli) Sch duled Castes 
Order, <year>1962</year> and the Constitution (Pondicherry) Scheduled Castes Order, 
<year>1964</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>455717</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Constitution (Scheduled  
  Castes) Orders (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1499332</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of Scheduled Castes Orders.-
<section><tid>719369</tid>
<number>1</number>The Schedule to the  
Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year> is hereby amended in the 
manner and to the extent specified in Schedule I.

</section>

<section><tid>628047</tid>
<number>2</number>The Schedule to the Constitution (Scheduled Castes)  (Union  
  Territories) Order, <year>1951</year> is hereby amended in the manner and to the 
extent specified in Schedule II.

</section>

<section><tid>608836</tid>
<number>3</number>The Constitution (Jammu and Kashmir) Scheduled Castes Order, <year>1956</year> 
is hereby amended in the manner and to the extent specified in 
Schedule III.

</section>

<section><tid>1356875</tid>
<number>4</number>The Constitution (Dadra and Nagar Haveli) Scheduled Castes Order, 
 <year>1962</year> is hereby amended in the manner and to the extent specified in 
Schedule IV.

</section>

<section><tid>605832</tid>
<number>5</number>The Constitution (Pondicherry) Scheduled Castes Order, <year>1964</year> is 
hereby amended in the manner and to the extent specified in Schedule 
V.


</section>

</article>



 </act>