<act><tid>1849431</tid>
<title>THE BHOPAL AND VINDHYA PRADESH (COURTS), ACT, <year>1950</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>1950</year> AN ACT TO PROVIDE FOR THE ESTABLISHMENT OF <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> CO 
URTS INBHOPAL AND V
[ 10th May, <year>1950</year>.]

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1818773</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>445400</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Bhopal and Vindhya Pradesh (Courts) Act, <year>1950</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1521366</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Bhopal and Vindhya Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1088432</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1041781</tid>
<number>i</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>" Bhopal" means the territories which, immediately 
before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in the Part C 
State of Bhopal;

</section>

<section><tid>744064</tid>
<number>ii</number>" Division" means the Division of Bhopal or the 
Division of Vindhya Pradesh, as the case may be;]

</section>

<section><tid>1504193</tid>
<number>iii</number>" District Court" means the Court of the District 
Judge and includes the Court of an Additional District Judge 
;

</section>

<section><tid>1987595</tid>
<number>iv</number>" land suit" means a suit for the establishment of 
title to land or for possession of land or in which any right 
or interest in land is claimed;

</section>

<section><tid>1247496</tid>
<number>v</number>" small cause suit" means a suit of the nature 
cognizable by a Court of Small Causes under the Provincial 
Small Cause Courts Act, <year>1887</year>; (9 of <year>1887</year>)
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>764843</tid>
<number>vii</number>" unclassed suit" means a suit which is neither a land 
suit nor a small cause suit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>100</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" Judicial Commissioners' Courts and other" omitted by 
the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" the States of" omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for cls. (i) and (ii).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Cl. (vi) omitted, ibid.

Amn. in Madhya Pradesh by Madhya Pradesh Act 19 of <year>1958</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>130608</tid>
<number>viii</number>" Vindhya Pradesh" means the territories which., 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
the Part C State of Vindhya Pradesh.]
CHAP

Court of the Judicial Commissioner.

CHAPTER II.-[ Court of the Judicial Commissioner.] Rep. by the 
Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>.

CHAP

SUBORDINATE COURTS

CHAPTER III

SUBORDINATE COURTS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>34555</tid>
<number> 14</number> Classes of Courts. In addition to <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Courts of 
Small Causes established under the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, 
<year>1887</year>, (9 of <year>1887</year>) and the Courts established under any other law for 
the time being in force, there shall be the following classes of Civil 
Courts, namely:-
<section><tid>1860351</tid>
<number>i</number>the Court of the District Judge;

</section>

<section><tid>64937</tid>
<number>ii</number>the Court of a Subordinate Judge;

</section>

<section><tid>364847</tid>
<number>iii</number>the Court of a Munsiff:
Provided that in the case of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Vindhya Pradesh, Courts of 
Subordinate Judges shall be established only with effect from such 
date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, specify.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1116948</tid>
<number> 15</number> Civil districts and District Judges.
<section><tid>174436</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of  
this Chapter the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State Government] may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, divide <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Bhopal and Vindhya Pradesh] into civil 
districts and may alter the limits or the number of such districts and 
may determine the headquarters of each such district.

</section>

<section><tid>1630172</tid>
<number>2</number>The <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State Government] shall, after consultation with the 
 <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> High Court], appoint as many persons as it thinks necessary to be 
District Judges and shall post one such person to each district as 
District Judge of that district:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>103</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" the Court of the Judicial Commissioner and" 
omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" the State of" omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for" Chief Commissioner;

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs.. ibid., for" the State".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs., ibid., for" Judicial Commissioner".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided that the same person may, if the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] 
thinks fit, be appointed to be the District Judge of two or more 
districts.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1913386</tid>
<number> 16</number> Additional Districts Judges.
<section><tid>796604</tid>
<number>1</number>When the business pending  
before the Court of a District Judge requires the aid of an Additional 
Judge or Judges for its speedy disposal the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may, 
after consultation with the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court], appoint such Additional 
District Judges as may be necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>683927</tid>
<number>2</number>An Additional District Judge so appointed shall discharge any 
of the functions of a District Judge which the District Judge may 
assign to him, and in the discharge of his functions he shall exercise 
the same powers as the District Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1618015</tid>
<number> 17</number> Munsiffs and Subordinate Judges.
<section><tid>96569</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government]  
may, after consultation with the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court], fix the number of 
Subordinate Judges and Munsiffs to be appointed and, if there is a 
vacancy in that number, may, subject to the rules, if any, made under 
sub- section (2), appoint such person as is nominated by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High 
Court] to the vacancy.

</section>

<section><tid>1264434</tid>
<number>2</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may, after consultation with the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court], make rules as to the qualifications of persons to be 
appointed as Subordinate Judges and Munsiffs.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>313799</tid>
<number>18</number>District Court to be principal Civil court of original 
jurisdiction. The Court of the District Judge shall be the principal 
Civil Court of original jurisdiction in the district.


</article>



<article><tid>710656</tid>
<number>19</number>Original jurisdiction of District Courts. Save as otherwise 
provided by any other law for the time being in force, the Court of 
the District Judge shall have original jurisdiction in civil suits 
without limit as regards the value.


</article>



<article><tid>1347984</tid>
<number>20</number>Original jurisdiction of Subordinate Judges and Munsiffs. 
The jurisdiction to be exercised in original civil suits as regards 
the value by any person appointed to be a Subordinate Judge or a 
Munsiff shall be determined by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government], after 
consultation with the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court], in such manner as it thinks fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>104</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" 
Chief Commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" Judicial Commissioner".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>777720</tid>
<number> 21</number> Local limits of jurisdiction of Munsiffs and Subordinate 
Judges.
<section><tid>521048</tid>
<number>1</number>The local limits of the jurisdiction of a Subordinate  
Judge or a Munsiff shall be such as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, define.

</section>

<section><tid>179865</tid>
<number>2</number>When the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] posts a Subordinate Judge to a 
district, the local limits of the district shall, in the absence of 
any directions to the contrary, be the local limits of his 
jurisdiction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1825661</tid>
<number>22</number>Powers of the State Government to regulate the institution 
of particular class of suits. Notwithstanding anything contained in 
sections 18, 19, 20 and 21, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may, by order 
published in the Official Gazette, direct that any particular class or 
classes of suits shall only be instituted in any particular Court or 
Courts.


</article>



<article><tid>1438312</tid>
<number> 23</number> Honorary Subordinate Judges or Munsiffs.
<section><tid>931467</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State  
Government] may, after consultation with the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court], appoint 
any person to be an honorary Subordinate Judge or an honorary Munsiff 
and may confer on such Judge or Munsiff all or any of the powers 
conferrable under this Act on a Subordinate Judge or a Munsiff, as the 
case may be, with respect to any class of suits or withdraw or suspend 
the exercise of any powers so conferred.

</section>

<section><tid>92282</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person on whom powers are conferred under sub- section 
 (1) shall be deemed for the purposes of this Act to be a Subordinate 
Judge or a Munsiff, as the case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1913797</tid>
<number>24</number>Small Cause jurisdiction of Subordinate Judge or Munsiff. 
The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
confer within such local limits as it thinks fit on a Subordinate 
Judge or a Munsiff the jurisdiction of a Judge of the Court of Small 
Causes under the Provincial Small Cause Courts Act, <year>1887</year>, (9 of <year>1887</year>) 
for the trial of small cause suits up to such value, not exceed ing 
five hundred rupees in the case of a Subordinate Judge of one hundred 
rupees in the case of a Munsiff as the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] thinks fit, 
and may withdraw any jurisdiction so conferred.


</article>



<article><tid>136008</tid>
<number> 25</number> Exercise by Subordinate Judges of jurisdiction of District 
Court in certain proceedings.
<section><tid>617665</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court] may, by general or  
special order authorise any Subordinate Judge to take cognizance of, 
and any District Judge to transfer to a Subordinate Judge under his

<pagefootnote><pagenum>105</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" 
Chief Commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" Judicial Commissioner".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

control, any proceeding or any class of proceeding, specified in such 
order, under-


<subsection><tid>1654811</tid>
<number>a</number>the Indian Succession Act, <year>1925</year>; (39 of <year>1925</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>980436</tid>
<number>b</number>the Guardians and Wards Act, <year>1890</year>; (8 of <year>1890</year>); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1930808</tid>
<number>c</number>the Provincial Insolvency Act, <year>1920</year>. (5 of <year>1920</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1359352</tid>
<number>2</number>The District Judge may withdraw any such proceeding taken 
cognizance of by, or transferred to, a Subordinate Judge under his 
control, and may either dispose of it himself or transfer it to any 
other competent Court.

</section>

<section><tid>937833</tid>
<number>3</number>Proceedings taken cognizance of by, or transferred to, a 
Subordinate Judge under this section shall be disposed of by him, 
subject to the rules applicable to like proceedings in the Court of 
the District Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1378837</tid>
<number> 26</number> Place of sitting of Courts.
<section><tid>621583</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] may  
by order fix the place of places at which any Court constituted under 
this Chapter is to be held.

</section>

<section><tid>1063947</tid>
<number>2</number>The place or places so fixed may be beyond the local limits 
of the jurisdiction of the Court.

</section>

<section><tid>314277</tid>
<number>3</number>Save as otherwise provided by an order under this section, 
Court constituted under this Chapter may be held at any place within 
the local limits of its jurisdiction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>590125</tid>
<number>27</number>Control of Courts by District Judges. Subject to the general 
superintendence and control of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court], the District Judge 
shall have control over all the Civil Courts within the local limits 
of his jurisdiction.


</article>



<article><tid>1142674</tid>
<number> 28</number> Ministerial officers of Courts.
<section><tid>921011</tid>
<number>1</number>The ministerial officers  
of the District Court shall be appointed by the District Judge.

</section>

<section><tid>1634704</tid>
<number>2</number>The ministerial officers of Civil Courts under the control 
of the District Judge shall be appointed by the District Judge.

</section>

<section><tid>469994</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appointment under this section shall be subject to 
such rules as the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court], with the approval of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State 
Government], may make in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1663549</tid>
<number>29</number>Delegation of powers of District Judge and District Court. 
The District Judge may, with the previous sanction of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High 
Court], delegate to the Judge of any Court under his control all or 
any of the powers conferred on the District Judge by section 27

<pagefootnote><pagenum>106</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> for" Chief 
Commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" Judicial Commissioner".




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

of this Act and on a District Court by section 24 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>) to be exercised by such Judge in any 
specified portion of the district, subject to the control of the 
District Judge.

CHAP

APPELLATE AND REVISIONAL JURISDICTION IN CIVIL CASES

CHAPTER IV

APPELLATE AND REVISIONAL JURISDICTION IN CIVIL CASES



</article>



<article><tid>467404</tid>
<number> 30</number> Appeals from original decrees. Save as otherwise provided by 
any law for the time being in force, appeals from decrees of Courts 
exercising original jurisdiction shall lie as follows:-
<section><tid>1592262</tid>
<number>a</number>from a decree of a Munsiff in any suit and of a 
Subordinate Judge in a suit the value of which does not 
exceed five thousand rupees, to the Court of the District 
Judge, and

</section>

<section><tid>844140</tid>
<number>b</number>in all other cases, to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court]:
Provided that the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court] with the previous sanction of the 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> State Government] may, by notification in the Official Gazette 
direct that appeals lying to the Court of the District Judge from all 
or any of the decrees passed by a Munsiff in any unclassed suit the 
value of which does not exceed one hundred rupees shall be preferred 
to such Subordinate Judge as may be mentioned in the notification, and 
the appeals shall thereupon be preferred accordingly, and the Court of 
such Subordinate Judge shall be deemed to be the Court of the District 
Judge for the purposes of all appeals so preferred.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1706172</tid>
<number> 31</number> Appeals from appellate decrees.
<section><tid>185535</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise  
provided by any law for the time being in force a second appeal shall 
lie to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court] in any of the following cases from an 
appellate decree of a District Court on any ground which would be a 
good ground of appeal if the decree had been passed in an original 
suit, namely:-

<subsection><tid>216464</tid>
<number>a</number>in a small cause suit or unclassed suit-

<subsubsection><tid>157967</tid>
<number>i</number>if the value of the suit is one thousand rupees or 
upwards, or the decree involves directly some claim to, 
or question respecting property of like value and the 
decree of the District Court varies or reverses, 
otherwise than as to costs, the decree of the Court 
below, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>107</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> for" Court 
of the Judicial. Commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" Judicial Commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for" Chief Commissioner".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>736839</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the value of the suit is two thousand five hundred 
rupees or upwards, or the decree of the District Court 
involves directly some claim to, or question respecting, 
property of like value

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>992030</tid>
<number>b</number>in a land suit-

<subsubsection><tid>1805073</tid>
<number>i</number>if the value of the suit is two hundred and fifty 
rupees or upwards or the decree involves directly some claim 
to, or question respecting, property of like value, and the 
decree of the District Court varies or reverses, otherwise 
than as to costs, the decree of the Court below, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1080698</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the value of the suit is one thousand rupees or 
upwards, or the decree of the District Court involves 
directly some claim to, or question respecting, property of 
like value.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>886019</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of Order XLI of the Code of Civil Procedure, 
 <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>) other than rule 34 of the said Order, shall apply, so 
far as may be, to a second appeal under this section and to the 
execution of a decree passed on any such appeal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1764489</tid>
<number>32</number>Finality of appellate decree of District Court. Subject to 
the provisions of sections 31 and 34 an appellate decree of a District 
Court shall be final,


</article>



<article><tid>1712847</tid>
<number> 33</number> Period of limitation.
<section><tid>1773385</tid>
<number>1</number>The period of limitation for a  
second appeal under section. 31 shall be ninety days from the date of 
the decree appealed against.

</section>

<section><tid>874318</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing such period and in all other respects not herein 
specified the period of limitation of the appeal shall be governed by 
the provisions of the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year>. (9 of <year>1908</year>)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>244095</tid>
<number> 34</number> Revisional powers of the High Court.
<section><tid>316605</tid>
<number>1</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court]  
may call for the record of any case which has been decided by a Civil 
Court subordinate to it and in which no appeal lies to it, and

<subsection><tid>1345087</tid>
<number>a</number>if any Civil Court by which the case was decided 
appears to have exercised a jurisdiction not vested in it by 
law, or to have failed to exercise a jurisdiction so vested, 
or to have acted in the exercise of its jurisdiction with 
material irregularity, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>528764</tid>
<number>b</number>if on an application made to it the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court] is of 
opinion that there is an important question of law or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>108</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" 
Court of the Judicial Commissioner".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

custom involved and that such question requires further 
consideration,

the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court] may make such order in the case as it thinks fit:

Provided that-


<subsubsection><tid>1176</tid>
<number>i</number>no application under clause (b) shall be entertained 
after in respect of which the application is made unless the 
applicant satisfies the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court] that he had sufficient 
cause for not making the application within that period,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1344308</tid>
<number>ii</number>no such application shall be admitted in a small, cause 
suit under the value of one thousand rupees or in an 
unclassed suit under the value of two hundred rupees,

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1563427</tid>
<number>iii</number>on any such application the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court] shall not 
revise the decision of the Court below except in so far as 
such decision involves a question of law or custom in respect 
of which the application has been admitted, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>170795</tid>
<number>iv</number>when any such application has been admitted, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High 
Court] shall, subject to proviso (iii), treat the matter of 
the application, as if it were an appeal.
Explanation.- A question of procedure is not a question of law or 
custom within the meaning of clause (b).


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>577985</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the period of limitation mentioned in proviso 
 (i) to sub- section (1) and in all other respects not herein specified, 
the period of limitation of the application shall be governed by the 
provisions of the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year>. (9 of <year>1908</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>614283</tid>
<number>3</number>Section 115 of the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of  
  <year>1908</year>) shall not apply to the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Divisions] of Bhopal or Vindhya 
Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1485252</tid>
<number> 35</number> Court- fees payable on revision. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

<section><tid>893522</tid>
<number>2</number>If the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court], on an application in respect of which 
the fee payable <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> for the exercise of its jurisdiction under section 
34] has been paid, sets aside or modifies a decree or order of the 
Court below or remands the case for a fresh decision, the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High 
Court] may grant to the applicant a certificate authorizing him to 
receive back from the Collector of the district in which such Court

<pagefootnote><pagenum>109</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for 
" Court of the Judicial Commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" States".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Sub- section (1) omitted, ibid.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs., ibid., for" under sub- section (1)".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

is situated the full amount of such fee or such part thereof as the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> High Court], having regard to the circumstances of the case, may 
think fit.

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1557949</tid>
<number>36</number>Temporary vacancies in office of District Judge. In the 
event of the death of a District Judge or of his being prevented from 
performing his duties by illness or other cause or of his absence from 
the civil district on leave, the Additional District Judge, if any, in 
the district or if there are more than one the first in rank among 
them or where there is no Additional District Judge the first in rank 
of the Subordinate Judges, if any,- shall assume charge of the 
District Court, without interruption to his ordinary duties, and while 
so in charge, shall perform the duties of a District Judge with 
respect to the filing of suits and appeals, receiving pleadings, 
execution of processes, return of writs and the like, and shall be 
designated as the Additional District Judge, or the Subordinate Judge, 
as the case may be, in charge of the District and shall continue in 
such charge until the office of the District Judge has been resumed, 
or assumed by an officer duly appointed thereto.


</article>



<article><tid>1200512</tid>
<number>37</number>Delegation of powers of District Judge. Any District Judge 
leaving the headquarters and proceeding on duty to any place within 
his district may delegate to an Additional District Judge, or where 
there is no such Additional District Judge, to a Subordinate Judge at 
the headquarters, the power of performing such duties, specified in 
section 36 as may be emergent, and such officer shall be designated as 
the Additional District Judge or the Subordinate Judge, as the case 
may be, in charge of the headquarters.


</article>



<article><tid>295406</tid>
<number>38</number>Temporary vacancy in office of Subordinate Judge. In the 
event of the death, suspension or temporary absence of any Subordinate 
Judge or a Munsiff, the District Judge may empower the Judge of any 
subordinate Court or the Court of a Munsiff of the same civil district 
to perform the duties of the Judge of the vacated subordinate Court or 
the Court of the Munsiff, as the case may be, either at the place of 
such Court or of his own Court; but in every such case the registers 
and records of the two Courts shall be kept distinct.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>110</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" 
Court of the Judicial Commissioner".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1833372</tid>
<number>39</number>Continuance of powers of officers. Where any person holding 
an office in the service of the State Government who has been invested 
with any powers under this Act throughout any local area is 
transferred or posted to an equal or higher office of the same nature 
within a like local area, he shall, unless the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State Government] 
otherwise directs, or has otherwise directed, exercise the same powers 
in the local area to which he is so transferred or posted.


</article>



<article><tid>678236</tid>
<number> 40</number> Vacations.
<section><tid>898566</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the approval of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> State  
Government], the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> High Court] shall prepare a list of days to be 
observed in each year as closed holidays in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> High Court] and the 
Civil Courts subordinate to that Court.

</section>

<section><tid>542078</tid>
<number>2</number>The list shall be published in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1072237</tid>
<number>3</number>Any judicial act done by a Civil Court on a day specified in 
the list shall not be, invalid by reason only of its having been done 
on that day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1975988</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power to make rules. The <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> High Court] may, from time to 
time, make rules consistent with this Act and any other law for the 
time being in force-
<section><tid>986108</tid>
<number>a</number>for the supervision of all Courts subordinate to the 
 <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> High Court] and their inspection;

</section>

<section><tid>1969165</tid>
<number>b</number>for the translation of any papers filed in the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> High 
Court] and the preparation of paper books for the hearing of 
appeals and the copying, typing or printing of any such 
papers or translations and the recovery from the persons at 
whose instance or on whose behalf papers are filed, of the 
expenses thereby incurred;

</section>

<section><tid>289552</tid>
<number>c</number>the fees to be charged for processes issued by Civil 
courts, or by any officer of any such Court and the fee 
payable in any suit or proceeding in any such Court by any 
party to such suit or proceeding in respect of the fees of 
the pleader of any other party to such suit or proceedings;

</section>

<section><tid>165768</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which proceedings of Civil Courts shall 
be kept and recorded, the manner in which paper books for the 
hearing of appeals shall be prepared and the granting of 
copies;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>111</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" 
Chief Commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs., ibid., for" Judicial commissioner".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs., ibid., for" Court of the Judicial Commissioner".





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1066334</tid>
<number>e</number>all matters relating to officers of Court;

</section>

<section><tid>951906</tid>
<number>f</number>declaring what persons shall be permitted to act as 
petition writers in the Courts subordinate thereto;

</section>

<section><tid>1290676</tid>
<number>g</number>regulating the issue of licences to such persons, the 
conduct of business by them and the scale of fees to be 
charged by them; and

</section>

<section><tid>647004</tid>
<number>h</number>determining the authority by which breaches of such 
rules shall be investigated and the penalties which may be 
imposed.






</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1264341</tid>
<number> 43</number> Existing rights not affected.
<section><tid>683764</tid>
<number>1</number>The abolition of any  
existing Civil Court under section 42 shall not prejudicially affect. 
the continued operation of any notice served, injunction issued, 
direction made or proceeding taken before the commencement of this Act 
by such Civil Court under the powers then conferred upon it.

</section>

<section><tid>640751</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal, suit or other proceeding pending before any of 
the existing Civil Courts immediately before the commencement of this 
Act shall, on such commencement, stand transferred to the Court 
exercising the jurisdiction under this Act which corresponds, so far 
as may be, to the jurisdiction of the Court in which the proceeding 
was pending, and the Court to which the proceeding so stands 
transferred shall proceed to try, hear and determine the matter as if 
it had been pending in that Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1391892</tid>
<number>3</number>Every decree or order made or sentence passed by any of the 
existing Civil Courts shall be deemed for the purposes of execution to 
have been made or passed by the corresponding Court established under 
this Act.
Explanation.- In this sub- section, the expression" corresponding 
Court" means the Court in which the case or proceeding in which the 
decree or order was made or sentence was passed would have lain, if 
the case or proceeding had been instituted after the commencement of 
this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>341495</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any existing Civil Court has by reason of its 
abolition under section 42 ceased to have jurisdiction with respect to 
any suit or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>112</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Section 42 shall stand unmodified vide Adaptation of Laws (No.  
  2) Order, <year>1956</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

proceeding, any proceeding in relation to that suit or proceeding 
which if that Court had not ceased to have jurisdiction might have 
been had therein may be had in the Court to which the business of the 
former Court has been transferred under this section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1432512</tid>
<number> 44</number> Repeals and savings. The Vindhya Pradesh (Judicial  
  Commissioner' s Court) Ordinance, <year>1950</year> (10 of <year>1950</year>) and the Bhopal 
 (Courts) Ordinance, <year>1950</year> (11 of <year>1950</year>) are hereby repealed:
Provided that the repeal by this Act of any of the Ordinances 
aforesaid shall not affect-

<section><tid>1272219</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation thereof; or

</section>

<section><tid>1720100</tid>
<number>b</number>any penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in 
respect of any offence committed against any Ordinance so 
repealed; or

</section>

<section><tid>1477940</tid>
<number>c</number>any investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in 
respect of any such punishment,
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be insti- 
tuted, continued or enforced, and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
punishment may be imposed as if this Act had not been passed:

Provided further that, subject to the provisions of the preceding 
proviso, anything done or any action taken, including any appointment 
or delegation made, notification, instruction or direction issued, or 
any rule, regulation or form issued or framed under any Ordinance 
hereby repealed shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provisions of this Act.



</section>

</article>



 </act>