<act><title>


The National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005</title> 

 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date* as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint:
 
Provided that different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in 
any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a 
reference to the coming into force of that provision.
 
 


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Bench” means a Bench of the National Tax Tribunal;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “Board of Direct Taxes” means the Central Board of Direct Taxes 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963 (54 of 1963);
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Board of Excise and Customs” means the Central Board of Excise and 
Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, 1963 (54 of 1963);
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  “Central Excise Act” means the Central Excise Act, 1944 (1 of 1944);
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  “Central Excise Tariff Act” means the Central Excise Tariff Act, 1985 
(5 of 1986);
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the National Tax Tribunal;
 </section><section>
       
<number>g</number>  “Companies (Profits) Surtax Act” means the Companies (Profits) Surtax 
Act, 1964 (7 of 1964);
 </section><section>
       
<number>h</number>  “Customs Act” means the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962);
 </section><section>
        
<number>i</number>  “Customs, Excise and Service Tax Appellate Tribunal” means the 
Customs, Excise and Service Tax Appellate Tribunal constituted under section 129 
of the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962);
 </section><section>
        
<number>j</number>  “Customs Tariff Act” means the Customs Tariff Act, 1975 (51 of 1975);
 </section><section>
       
<number>k</number>  “Expenditure‑tax Act” means the Expenditure‑tax Act, 1987 (35 of 
1987);
 </section><section>
        
<number>l</number>  “Gift‑tax Act” means the Gift‑tax Act, 1958 (18 of 1958);
 </section><section>
       
<number>m</number>  “Income‑tax Act” means the Income‑tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961);
 </section><section>
       
<number>n</number>  “Income‑tax Appellate Tribunal” means the Income‑tax Appellate 
Tribunal constituted under section 252 of the Income‑tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961);
 </section><section>
       
<number>o</number>  “Interest‑tax Act” means the Interest‑tax Act, 1974 (45 of 1974);
 </section><section>
       
<number>p</number>  “law officer” means the Attorney‑General for India, the 
Solicitor-General of India or the Additional Solicitor-General of India;
 </section><section>
       
<number>q</number>  “Member” means a Member of the National Tax Tribunal and includes the 
Chairperson;
 </section><section>
        
<number>r</number>  “National Tax Tribunal” means the National Tax Tribunal established 
under section 3;
 </section><section>
       
<number>s</number>  “notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;
 </section><section>
        
<number>t</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>u</number>  “Supreme Court” means the Supreme Court of India;
 </section><section>
       
<number>v</number>  “Wealth‑tax Act” means the Wealth‑tax Act, 1957 (27 of 1957);
 </section><section>
       
<number>w</number>  words and expressions used in this Act but not defined herein and 
defined in the Central Excise Act, the Central Excise Tariff Act, the Customs 
Act, the Customs Tariff Act (hereinafter referred to as the indirect taxes) or 
the rules made thereunder or in Chapter V of the Finance Act, 1994 (32 of 1994) 
shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in the said Acts or the 
rules made thereunder;
 </section><section>
       
<number>x</number>  words and expressions used in this Act but not defined herein and 
defined in the Income‑tax Act, the Wealth‑tax Act, the Gift‑tax Act, the 
Expenditure‑tax Act, the Interest‑tax Act or the Companies (Profits) Surtax Act 
(hereinafter referred to as the direct taxes) or the rules made thereunder shall 
have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in the said Acts or the rules 
made thereunder.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Establishment of 
National Tax Tribunal.—The 
Central Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish 
with effect from such date as may be specified therein, a Tax Tribunal to be 
known as the National Tax Tribunal1 to 
exercise the jurisdiction, powers and authority conferred on such Tribunal by or 
under this Act.






</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Composition of 
National Tax Tribunal.—The 
National Tax Tribunal shall consist of a Chairperson and such number of Members 
as the Central Government deems fit, to be appointed by that Government, by 
notification in the Official Gazette.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Constitution and 
jurisdiction of Benches.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The jurisdiction of the National Tax Tribunal may be exercised by the Benches 
thereof to be constituted by the Chairperson.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Benches of the 
National Tax Tribunal shall ordinarily sit at any place in the National Capital 
Territory of Delhi or such other places as the Central Government may, in 
consultation with the Chairperson, notify:
 
Provided that the 
Chairperson may for adequate reasons permit a Bench to hold its temporary 
sitting for a period not exceeding fifteen days at a place other than its 
ordinary place of seat.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
shall notify the areas in relation to which each Bench of the National Tax 
Tribunal may exercise its jurisdiction.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
shall determine the number of Benches and each Bench shall consist of two 
members.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Central Government 
may 

1[***] transfer a 
Member from headquarters of one Bench in one State to the headquarters of 
another Bench in another State or to the headquarters of any other Bench within 
a State.
 

2[Provided that no 
Member shall be transferred without the concurrence of the Chairperson.]






</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Qualifications for 
appointment of Chairperson and other Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson of the National Tax Tribunal shall be a person who has been a 
Judge of the Supreme Court or the Chief Justice of a High Court.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment as Member unless he—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  is, or has been, or is eligible to be, a Judge of a High Court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  is, or has been, a Member of the Income‑tax Appellate Tribunal or of 
the Customs, Excise and Service Tax Appellate Tribunal for at least 

1[five years].
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Appointment of 
Chairperson and other Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub‑section (2), the Chairperson and every other 
Member shall be appointed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson and 
the other Members shall be appointed by the Central Government on the 
recommendations of a Selection Committee consisting of—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the Chief Justice of India or a Judge of the Supreme Court nominated 
by him;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the Secretary in the Ministry of Law and Justice (Department of Legal 
Affairs);
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  the Secretary in the Ministry of Finance (Department of Revenue).
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No appointment of the 
Chairperson or of any other Member shall be invalidated merely by reason of any 
vacancy or any defect in the constitution of the Selection Committee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Terms of office of 
Chairperson and other Members.—The 
Chairperson and every other Member shall hold office as such for a term of five 
years from the date on which he enters upon his office but shall be eligible for 
re‑appointment:
 
Provided that no 
Chairperson or other Member shall hold office as such after he has attained,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  in the case of Chairperson, the age of sixty‑eight years; and
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  in the case of any other Member, the age of sixty‑five years.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Resignation of 
Chairperson and other Members.—The 
Chairperson or any other Member may, by notice in writing under his hand 
addressed to the Central Government, resign his office.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Salary and 
allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this Act, the salary and allowances and other terms 
and conditions of the Chairperson shall be the same as applicable to a sitting 
Judge of the Supreme Court, but no vacation shall be allowed:
 
Provided that if a person 
who, immediately before the date of assuming the office as the Chairperson was 
in receipt of or being eligible so to do, had elected to draw, a pension in 
respect of any previous service or office held by such person under the 
Government of the Union or of a State, his salary in respect of service as 
Chairperson shall be reduced by the amount of that pension.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this sub‑section, “vacation” shall have the meaning assigned to 
it in the Supreme Court Judges (Conditions of Service) Act, 1958 (41 of 1958).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member shall draw 
salary of a High Court Judge and other allowances and the terms and conditions 
of his service shall be the same as applicable to a Secretary to the Government 
of India:
 
Provided that if a person 
who, immediately before the date of assuming the office as Member was in receipt 
of, or being eligible so to do, had elected to draw, a pension in respect of any 
previous service held by such person in connection with the affairs of the Union 
or of a State, his salary in respect of service as Member shall be reduced to 
the extent of that pension.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The salary and 
allowances and other terms and conditions of service of Chairperson or a Member 
of the Tribunal shall not be varied to his disadvantage after appointment.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Removal and 
suspension of Chairperson and other Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, in consultation with the Chief Justice of India, 
remove from office the Chairperson or any Member who—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  has been adjudged an insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  has been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, involves moral turpitude; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  has become physically or mentally incapable of acting as such 
Chairperson or Member of the National Tax Tribunal; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  has acquired such financial or other interest as is likely to affect 
prejudicially his functions as the Chairperson or a Member of the National Tax 
Tribunal; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  has so abused his position as to render his continuance in office 
prejudicial to the public interest.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson or any 
other Member shall not be removed from his office except by an order made by the 
Central Government on the ground of proved misbehaviour or incapacity after an 
inquiry made by a Judge of the Supreme Court in which such Chairperson or Member 
had been informed of the charges against him and given a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard in respect of those charges.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
may suspend from office the Chairperson or any other Member in respect of whom a 
reference of conducting an inquiry has been made to the Judge of the Supreme 
Court under sub‑section (2) until the Central Government has passed orders on 
receipt of the report of the Judge of the Supreme Court on such reference.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
may, by rules, regulate the procedure for the investigation of misbehaviour or 
incapacity of the Chairperson or a Member referred to in sub‑section (2).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Officers and 
employees of National Tax Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall provide the National Tax Tribunal with such 
officers and employees as it may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The salaries and 
allowances and other conditions of service of officers and employees of the 
National Tax Tribunal shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The officers and 
employees of the National Tax Tribunal shall discharge their functions under the 
general superintendence of the Chairperson.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The officers and the 
other employees shall be appointed on the recommendations of a Selection 
Committee constituted by the Central Government.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Appearance before 
National Tax Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A party to an appeal other than Government may either appear in person or 
authorise one or more chartered accountants or legal practitioners 

1[***] to present 
his or its case before the National Tax Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Government may 
authorise one or more legal practitioners or any of its officers to present its 
case before the National Tax Tribunal.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  “chartered accountant” means a chartered accountant as defined in 
clause (b) of sub‑section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 
1949 (38 of 1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under 
sub‑section (1) of section 6 of that Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  “legal practitioner” means an advocate, a vakil or any attorney 
of any High Court, and includes a pleader in practice.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Member to act as 
Chairperson or to discharge his functions in certain circumstances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In the event of any vacancy in the office of the Chairperson by reason of his 
death, resignation or otherwise, the Central Government may designate the 
senior-­most Member to act as the Chairperson until the day on which a 
Chairperson, appointed in accordance with the provisions of this Act to fill 
such vacancy, enters upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When the Chairperson 
is unable to discharge his functions owing to absence, illness or any other 
cause, the Central Government may authorise the senior‑most Member to discharge 
the functions of the Chairperson until the date on which the Chairperson resumes 
his duties.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The senior‑most member 
designated to act under sub‑section (1) or to discharge functions of the 
Chairperson under sub‑section (2), of the Chairperson shall continue to draw 
salary and allowances of a Member.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Appeal to National 
Tax Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall lie to the National Tax Tribunal from every order passed in 
appeal by the Income‑tax Appellate Tribunal and the Customs, Excise and Service 
Tax Appellate Tribunal, if the National Tax Tribunal is satisfied that the case 
involves a substantial question of law.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Commissioner 
or the Commissioner of Income‑tax or the Chief Commissioner or Commissioner of 
Customs and Central Excise, as the case may be, or an assessee aggrieved by any 
order passed by the Income‑tax Appellate Tribunal or any person aggrieved by any 
order passed by the Customs, Excise and Service Tax Appellate Tribunal 
(hereinafter referred to as aggrieved person), may file an appeal to the 
National Tax Tribunal and such appeal under this sub‑section shall—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  be filed within one hundred and twenty days from the date on which the 
order appealed against is received by the assessee or the aggrieved person or 
the Chief Commissioner or Commissioner, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  be in the form of a memorandum of appeal precisely stating therein the 
substantial question of law involved; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  be accompanied by such fees as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that separate 
form of memorandum of appeal shall be filed for matters involving direct and 
indirect taxes:
 
Provided further that the 
National Tax Tribunal may entertain the appeal within sixty days after the 
expiry of the said period of one hundred and twenty days, if it is satisfied 
that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring an appeal 
in time.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where an appeal is 
admitted under sub‑section (1), the National Tax Tribunal—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  shall formulate the question of law for hearing the appeal; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  may also determine any relevant issue in connection with the question 
so formulated—
 <subsubsection>
             
<number>i</number>  which has not been so determined by the Income‑tax Appellate Tribunal 
or by the Customs, Excise and Service Tax Appellate Tribunal; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>ii</number>  which has been wrongly determined by the Income‑tax Appellate 
Tribunal or by the Customs, Excise and Service Tax Appellate Tribunal,
 
and shall decide the 
question of law so formulated and the other relevant issue so determined and 
deliver such judgment thereon containing the grounds on which such decision is 
founded and may award such cost as it deems fit.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where in any appeal 
under this section, the decision of the Income‑tax Appellate Tribunal or the 
Customs, Excise and Service Tax Appellate Tribunal involves the payment of any 
tax or duties, the assessee or the aggrieved person, as the case may be, shall 
not be allowed to prefer such appeal unless he deposits at least twenty‑five per 
cent. of such tax or duty payable on the basis of the order appealed against:
 
Provided that where in a 
particular case the National Tax Tribunal is of the opinion that the deposit of 
tax or duty under this sub‑section would cause undue hardship to such person, it 
may dispense with such deposit subject to such conditions as it may deem fit to 
impose so as to safeguard the interest of revenue.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Procedure and 
powers of National Tax Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The National Tax Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by the 
Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) but shall be guided by the principles 
of natural justice.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the other 
provisions of this Act, the National Tax Tribunal shall have powers to regulate 
its own procedure.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The National Tax 
Tribunal shall have, for the purposes of discharging its functions under this 
Act, the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) while trying a suit, in respect of the following 
matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  requiring the discovery and production of books of account and other 
documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  subject to the provisions of sections 123 and 124 of the Indian 
Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), requisitioning any public record or document or 
a copy of such record or document, from any office;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  dismissing an appeal for default or deciding it, ex parte;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  setting aside any order of dismissal of any appeal for default or any 
order passed by it, ex parte;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  rectifying any mistake or error apparent on the face of record; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>f</number>  any other matter which may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> All proceedings before 
the National Tax Tribunal shall be deemed to be judicial proceedings within the 
meaning of sections 193 and 228 and for the purposes of section 196 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the National Tax Tribunal shall be deemed to 
be a civil court for the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Finality of orders 
of National Tax Tribunal.—Any 
order passed by the National Tax Tribunal shall be final and shall be given 
effect to accordingly and no civil court shall have or be entitled to exercise 
any jurisdiction, power or authority with respect to any of the matters falling 
within the jurisdiction of the National Tax Tribunal.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Decision by 
majority.—If 
the Members of a Bench consisting of two Members differ in opinion on any point, 
they shall state the point or points on which they differ, and make a reference 
to the Chairperson, who shall hear the point or points himself or nominate any 
other Member for such hearing and such point or points shall be decided 
according to the opinion of the majority, who have heard the case including 
those who first heard it.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Special Bench.—Where 
a judgment pronounced on a question of law by a Bench subsequently comes up for 
hearing before any Bench, and the latter Bench is of the opinion that the 
question of law requires reconsideration, then the latter Bench shall make a 
reference to the Chairperson to constitute a Special Bench consisting of five 
Members to hear and decide such question of law.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Interim Order.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other provisions of this Act or any other law for the 
time being in force, no interim order (whether by way of injunction or stay or 
otherwise) shall be made in relation to any appeal under this Act, unless—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  copies of such appeal and all documents in support of the plea for 
such interim order are furnished to the party against whom the appeal is 
preferred; and
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  opportunity is given to such party to be heard in the matter.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Power to punish for 
contempt.—The 
National Tax Tribunal shall have and exercise the same jurisdiction, powers and 
authority in respect of contempt of itself as the High Court has and may 
exercise such power or authority, for this purpose under the provisions of the 
Contempt of Courts Act, 1971 (70 of 1971), which shall have effect subject to 
the modification that—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  any reference therein to a High Court shall be construed as including 
a reference to the National Tax Tribunal;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  any reference to the Advocate-General in section 15 of the said Act 
shall be construed as a reference to such law officer as the Central Government 
may specify in this behalf:
 
Provided that such matters 
shall be heard by a Special Bench consisting of five Members constituted by the 
Chairperson.


</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Order of National 
Tax Tribunal.—The 
National Tax Tribunal may, after giving the parties to any proceedings before 
it, an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Transfer of pending 
cases from High Court.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On and from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, specify, 
all matters and proceedings including appeals and references under the direct 
taxes and indirect taxes pending before any High Court immediately before that 
date shall stand transferred to the National Tax Tribunal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any matter or 
proceeding including appeals and references stand transferred from the High 
Court to the National Tax Tribunal under sub‑section (1),—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the High Court shall, as soon as may be after such transfer, forward 
the records pertaining to such matter or proceeding to the National Tax 
Tribunal;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the National Tax Tribunal shall, on receipt of such records, proceed 
to deal with such matter or proceeding from the stage at which it is transferred 
or from an earlier stage or de novo as it may deem fit;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  the Chairperson shall constitute a Bench consisting of such number of 
Members as he deems fit for hearing cases transferred under this section.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Appeal to Supreme 
Court.—Any 
person including any department of the Government aggrieved by any decision or 
order of the National Tax Tribunal may file an appeal to the Supreme Court 
within sixty days from the date of communication of the decision or order of the 
National Tax Tribunal to him:
 
Provided that the Supreme 
Court may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient 
cause from filing the appeal within the said period, allow it to be filed within 
such time as it may deem fit.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Members, etc., to 
be public servants.—The 
Chairperson, Members and other officers and employees of the National Tax 
Tribunal shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 
of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Protection of 
action taken in good faith.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the National Tax 
Tribunal or its Chairperson, Member, officer or other employee in the discharge 
of any function for any loss or damage caused or likely to be caused by any act 
which is, in good faith, done or intended to be done in the discharge of any 
function under this Act.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no such 
order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the 
commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall, as soon as may be, after it is made, be laid before each 
House of Parliament.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Power to make 
rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the provisions 
of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of 
the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the procedure under sub‑section (4) of section 11 for the 
investigation of charges of misbehaviour or incapacity against the Chairperson 
or other Members;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the salaries and allowances and other conditions of service of 
officers and other employees of the National Tax Tribunal under sub‑section (2) 
of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  the amount of fees payable under clause (c) of sub‑section (2) of 
section 15;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  the other matters in respect of which the National Tax Tribunal may 
exercise the powers of a civil court under clause (f) of sub‑section (3) of 
section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>e</number>  any other matter which may be prescribed or in respect of which rules 
are required to be made by the Central Government.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Laying of rules 
before Parliament.—Every 
rule made under this Act by the Central Government shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for 
a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
more successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Consequential 
amendments.—On 
and from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, specify, the 
enactments mentioned in the Schedule shall stand amended in the manner specified 
therein.
 
 
</article><form>
 




The National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005
 


 
 




The Schedule
 


(See section 30)
 




Amendment of Certain Enactments
 



Part I
 




Amendments to the Income‑Tax Act, 1961
 


(43 of 1961)
 


1. In section 2, after 
clause (29C), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:—
 


                  
‘(29D) “National Tax Tribunal” means the National Tax Tribunal established under 
section 3 of the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005;’.
 


2. In Chapter XX,—
 


         
(i)  in section 254, in sub‑section (4), for the words, figures and letter 
“Save as provided in section 256 or section 260A”, the words and figures “Save 
as provided in the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005” shall be substituted;
 


        
(ii)  sub‑heading “C.—Reference to High Court” and sections 256, 258 
and 259 shall be omitted;
 


        
(iii)  for section 260, the following section shall be substituted, 
namely:—
 


                      
“260. Effect to the decisions of Supreme Court and of the National Tax 
Tribunal.—(1) The Supreme Court upon hearing any reference made to it by the 
Appellate Tribunal under section 257 shall decide the question of law raised 
therein, and shall deliver its judgment thereon containing the grounds on which 
such decision is founded, and a copy of the judgment shall be sent under the 
seal of the Court and the signature of the Registrar to the Appellate Tribunal 
which shall pass such orders as are necessary to dispose of the case conforming 
to such judgment.
 


                      
(2) Where the National Tax Tribunal delivers a judgment in an appeal filed 
before it or in any matter transferred to it under the National Tax Tribunal 
Act, 2005, effect shall be given to the order of that Tribunal by the assessing 
officer on the basis of certified copy of the judgment.
 


                      
(3) The cost of any reference to the Supreme Court which shall not include the 
fee for making the reference shall be at the discretion of the Court.”;
 


       
(iv)  in section 260A, in sub‑section (1), after the words “order passed in 
appeal by the Appellate Tribunal”, the words “before the date of establishment 
of the National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted;
 


        
(v)  in section 261, after the words “any judgment of the High Court 
delivered”, the words “before the establishment of the National Tax Tribunal” 
shall be inserted;
 


       
(vi)  in section 263, in sub‑section (3), after the words “the Appellate 
Tribunal,”, the words “National Tax Tribunal,” shall be inserted;
 


       
(vii)  in section 264, in sub‑section (7), after the words “the Appellate 
Tribunal,”, the words “National Tax Tribunal,” shall be inserted.
 



Part II
 




Amendments to the wealth‑tax act, 1957
 


(27 of 1957)
 


1. In section 2, after 
clause (lc), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:—
 


                  
‘(ld) “National Tax Tribunal” means the National Tax Tribunal established 
under section 3 of the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005;’.
 


2. In section 25, in 
sub‑section (4), after the words “Appellate Tribunal,” the words “National Tax 
Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


3. In section 27A,—
 


         
(i)  in sub‑section (1), after the words and figures, “file on or after the 
1st day of October, 1998”, the words “but before the date of establishment of 
the National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted;
 


        
(ii)  in sub‑section (2), after the words “An appeal shall lie to the High 
Court”, the words “before the date of establishment of the National Tax 
Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


4. In section 29, in 
sub‑section (1), after the words, “any judgment of the High Court delivered”, 
the words “before the date of establishment of the National Tax Tribunal” shall 
be inserted.
 


5. In section 29A, after 
the words “preferred to the Supreme Court”, the words and figures “under this 
Act before the commencement of the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005” shall be 
inserted.
 



Part III
 




Amendments to the Expenditure‑Tax Act, 1987
 


(35 of 1987)
 


1. In section 13, in 
sub‑section (4), for the words “or any order of a High Court”, the words “or any 
order of the National Tax Tribunal or of a High Court” shall be substituted.
 


2. In section 21, in 
sub‑section (7), after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words “the National 
Tax Tribunal,” shall be inserted.
 



Part IV
 




Amendments To The Interest‑Tax Act, 1974
 


(45 of 1974)
 


1. In section 19, in 
sub‑section (3), after the words “the Appellate Tribunal”, the words “the 
National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


2. In section 20, in 
sub‑section (7), for the words “Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the 
Supreme Court”, the words “Appellate Tribunal, the National Tax Tribunal, the 
High Court or the Supreme Court” shall be substituted.
 



Part V
 




Amendment to the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1998
 


(21 of 1998)
 


In section 76, in 
sub‑section (1), the words, figures, letter and brackets “sections 23, 23A, 24, 
25, 28 and 29 of the Wealth‑tax Act as amended and section 27A as inserted by 
the Finance (No. 2) Act, 1998”, the words, figures and letter “sections 23, 23A, 
24 and 25 of the Wealth‑tax Act” shall be substituted.
 



Part VI
 




Amendments To The Customs Act, 1962
 


(52 of 1962)
 


1. In section 2, after 
clause (30), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:—
 


                  
‘(30A) “National Tax Tribunal” means the National Tax Tribunal 
established under section 3 of the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005;”.
 


2. In section 27, in 
sub‑section (3), after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, “the National 
Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


3. In section 27A, in the
Explanation, after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, “National 
Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


4. In section 28AA, in 
Explanations 1 and 2, after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, 
“National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


5. In section 28AB, in 
Explanations 1 and 2, after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, 
“National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


6. In section 28B, in 
sub‑section (1), after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, “National Tax 
Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


7. Sections 130, 130A, 
130B, 130C and 130D shall be omitted.
 


8. In section 130E, in 
clause (b), after the words “any order passed”, the words “before the 
establishment of the National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


9. In section 131, after 
the words “an appeal has been preferred to the Supreme Court”, the words and 
figure “under this Act before the commencement of the National Tax Tribunal Act, 
2005” shall be inserted.
 


10. In section 131C, clause 
(b) shall be omitted.
 



Part VII
 




Amendments To The Central Excise Act, 1944
 


(1 of 1944)
 


1. In section 2, after 
clause (f), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:—
 


                  
‘(ff) “National Tax Tribunal” means the National Tax Tribunal established under 
section 3 of the National Tax Tribunal Act, 2005;’.
 


2. In section 11AA, in 
Explanations 1 and 2, after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, 
“National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


3. In section 11AB, in 
Explanations 1 and 2, after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, 
“National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


4. In section 11BB, in the
Explanation, after the words “Appellate Tribunal”, the words, “National 
Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


5. In section 35C, in 
sub‑section (4), for the words, figures and letters “Save as provided in section 
35G or section 35L”, the words and figures “Save as provided in the National Tax 
Tribunal Act, 2005” shall be substituted.
 


6. Sections 35G, 35H, 35-I 
and 35J shall be omitted.
 


7. In section 35K,—
 


         
(i)  in sub-section (1), the words “High Court or the” shall be omitted;
 


        
(ii)  in sub-section (2),—
 


             
(a) the words “the High Court or” occurring at both the places shall be omitted;
 


             
(b) the words “as the case may be,” shall be omitted.
 


8. In section 35L, in 
clause (b), after the words “any order passed”, the words “before the 
establishment of the National Tax Tribunal” shall be inserted.
 


9. In section 35N, after 
the words “an appeal has been preferred to the Supreme Court”, the words and 
figures “under this Act before the commencement of the National Tax Tribunal 
Act, 2005” shall be inserted.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>