<act><title>THE ENERGY CONSERVATION (THE FORM AND MANNER FOR 
SUBMISSION OF REPORT ON THE STATUS OF ENERGY CONSUMPTION BY THE DESIGNATED 
CONSUMERS) RULES, 20071</title> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Energy Conservation (the Form and Manner for Submission of Report on 
the Status of Energy Consumption by the Designated Consumers) Rules, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 




 
 
  </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these rules unless the 
context otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Energy Conservation Act, 2001 (52 of 2001); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Financial Year means the year beginning on the 1st day of April and 
  ending on the 31st March following. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expression used herein but not defined shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
 
  </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Submission of Report on the status of energy consumption by 
Designated Consumer. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every designated consumer shall: 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> submit in electronic form as well as hard copy to the designated 
  agency, within three months, the first report on the status of energy 
  consumption at the end of the previous financial year in Form 1 of the 
  Annexure; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> submit to the designated agency subsequent reports for each financial 
  year in the same manner on the status of energy conservation in Form 1 of the 
  Annexure within three months of the close of that financial year. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Bureau may prescribe different forms for different sections from time 
to time. 
  </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Authentication of Data. </title>Every designated consumer shall 
ensure that all the data furnished under rule 3 are duly authenticated by the 
energy manager appointed or designated by the designated consumer, the Chief 
Executive or his nominee authorized for the purpose before it is sent to the 
designated agency under rule 3 of these rules. </article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Supply of Data to the Bureau.</title>
<section><number>1</number> Every designated 
consumer shall also furnish the data in electronic form as well as hard copy, 
referred to in clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number> and (b) of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 of these rules, 
duly authenticated, in the manner prescribed in rule 4 of these rules, to the 
Bureau of Energy Efficiency.</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Vide  G.S.R. 174(E), dated 2nd March, 2007, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 5th March, 2007.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>