<act><title>THE BORDER SECURITY FORCE LEAVE RULES, 1971 1</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Border Security Force Leave Rules, 1971. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
  



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> [<number>2</number> Application of the Central Civil Service (Leave) Rules, 1972, to Border Security Force. </title>Subject to the provisions of rules 3 and 4, all members of the Force shall be governed by the provisions of the Central Civil Service (Leave) Rules, 1972 as amended from time to time.] 


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Special earned leave in certain cases. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 2, any member of the Force or enrolled person so long as he is serving in any Battalion, Unit or Training Institution of the Border Security Force, shall be entitled to 60 days earned leave in a calendar year. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The leave account of such member shall be credited with earned leave in advance in two instalments of 30 days each on the 1st of January and the 1st of July every year subject to the following conditions, namely: 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the leave at the credit of such member at the close of the previous half year shall be carried forward to the next half year, subject to the condition that the leave so carried forward plus the credit for the half year do not exceed the maximum limit of 120 days; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> no such earned leave shall be granted for more than 90 days at a time; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> no second Saturday shall be availed of as a holiday; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***]] 
  



</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> [ <title><number>4</number> Calculation of earned leave. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Earned leave shall be credited to the leave account of a member of the Force or enrolled person at the rate of 5 days for each completed calendar month of service which he is likely to render in a half-year of the calendar year in which he is appointed or is transferred from the office at the Force Headquarters, Inspector General or Deputy Inspector General in Border Security Force. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> (a) The credit of the half-year in which such member is due to retire or resigns from the service or is transferred from any Battalion, Unit or Training Institution to Force Headquarters, Inspector General or Deputy Inspector General's Office shall be afforded only at the rate of 5 days per completed calendar month upto the date of retirement, resignation or transfer, as the case may be. 
 <subsection><number>b</number> When such member is removed or dismissed from service or dies while in service, credit of earned leave shall be allowed at the rate of 5 days per completed calendar month upto the end of calendar month preceding the calendar month in which he is removed or dismissed from the service or dies while in service. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> If such member or enrolled person has taken any leave other than earned leave in a half-year, the credit to be afforded to his leave account at the commencement of the next half-year shall be reduced by 1/6th of such leave, subject to the condition that the reduction so made is limited to the maximum period of earned leave that would be credited at the commencement of the next half-year. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> While affording credit of earned leave, fraction of a day shall be rounded off to the nearest day. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The leave account of such member shall be maintained in the Forms annexed to these rules. 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Border Security Force Leave
    Rules, 1971
 



 



 




    Schedule
 



Form 1
 


[See rule 4(5)]
 


             1.  Name of Officer, Subordinate 
    Officer or enrolled person.
 


             2.  Date of birth.
 


             3.  Date of commencement of 
    continuous service.
 


             4.  Date of 
    quasi-permanent/permanent employment.
 


             5.  Date of 
    retirement/resignation.
 


 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Border Security Force Leave
    Rules, 1971
 



 



 



Form 2
 


(See rule 15)
 



    Form of Leave Account
 


             1.  Name of Government Servant.
 


             2.  Date of birth.
 


             3.  Date of commencement of 
    continuous service.
 


             4.  Date of 
    retirement/resignation.
 


             5.  Date of 
    quasi-permanent/permanent employment.
 

  




 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, sec. 3(i) dated 11th September, 1971.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 849, dated 2nd June, 1979 and published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, sec. 3(i), dated 16th June, 1979.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 1302, dated 30th August, 1976 and published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, sec. 3(i), dated 11th November, 1976.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>Omitted by G.S.R. 236, dated 18th February, 1980 and published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, sec. 3(i), dated 1st March, 1980.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>Added by G.S.R. 849, dated 2nd June, 1979 along with the Schedule and published in the Gazette of India, Pt. II, sec. 3(i), dated 16th June, 1979.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>