<act><title>THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY 
  (ASSETS, LIABILITIES, AND 
  SOLVENCY MARGIN OF INSURERS) REGULATIONS, 20001</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These regulations may be called the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Assets, Liabilities, and Solvency Margin of Insurers) Regulations, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force from the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>
<section><number>1</number> In these regulations, unless the context otherwise requires 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Act means the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Authority means the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999). 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> All words and expressions used herein and not defined but defined in the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938), or in the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999), or in any Rules or Regulations made thereunder, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts or Rules or Regulations. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>3</number> Valuation of Assets. </title>Every insurer shall prepare a statement of the value of assets in Form IRDA-Assets-AA in accordance with Schedule I. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>4</number> Determination of Amount of Liabilities. </title>Every insurer shall prepare a statement of the amount of liabilities in accordance with Schedule IIA, in respect of life insurance business, and in Form HG in accordance with Schedule IIB, in respect of general insurance Business, as the case may be. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>5</number> Determination of Solvency Margin. </title>Every insurer shall prepare a statement of solvency margin in accordance with Schedule IIIA, in respect of life insurance business, and in Form KG in accordance with Schedule IIIB, in respect of general insurance business, as the case may be. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>6</number> Health Insurance Business. </title>Where the insurer transacts health insurance business, providing health covers, the amount of liabilities shall be determined in accordance with the principles specified under these Regulations. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>7</number> Business outside India. </title>Where the insurer transacts insurance business in a country outside India, and submits statements or returns or any such particulars to public authority of that country, he shall enclose the same along with the Forms specified in accordance with these Regulations and the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Actuarial Report and Abstract) Regulations, 2000: 
 Provided that if the appointed actuary is of the opinion that it is necessary to set additional reserves over and above the reserves shown in the statements or returns or any such particulars submitted to the public authority of a country outside India, he may set such additional reserves. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>8</number> Furnishing of Forms. </title>The Forms, namely, Form IRDA-Assets-AA, Form HG, and Form KG, shall be furnished separately for Business within India and Total Business transacted by the insurer. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>9</number> Personal visit of appointed actuary to the Authority. </title>The Authority may, if considered necessary and expedient, ask the appointed actuary to make a personal visit to the office of the Authority to elicit from him any further information. 


</article><form>
 

THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY 
  (ASSETS, LIABILITIES, AND  

  SOLVENCY MARGIN OF INSURERS) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

SCHEDULE IIB 
 

( See Regulation 4) 
 

Valuation of Liabilities (General Insurance) 
 

1. Interpretation. In this schedule, 
 
 

(a) Reserve for claims incurred but not reported (IBNR)) means the reserve for claims incurred but not reported on the balance sheet date, and includes reserve for claims which may be inadequately reserved; 
 

(b) Reserve for outstanding claims means the reserve for outstanding claims as mentioned in para 2(1)(b)(iii) of this Schedule. 

 

2. Determination of Liabilities. (1) An insurer shall 
 
 

(i) place a proper value in respect of the following items, namely: 
 
 

(I) provision for bad and doubtful debts, 
 

(II) reserve for dividends declared or recommended, and outstanding dividends in full, 
 

(III) amount due to insurance companies carrying on insurance business, in full, 
 

(IV) amount due to sundry creditors, in full, 
 

(V) provision for taxation, in full, and 
 

(VI) foreign exchange reserve; 

 

(ii) determine the amount of following reserves, in the manner specified herein below for each reserve: 
 
 

(a) reserve for unexpired risks, shall be, in respect of, 
 
 

(I) Fire business, 50 per cent., 
 

(II) Miscellaneous business, 50 per cent., 
 

(III) Marine business other than marine hull business, 50 per cent., and 
 

(IV) Marine hull business, 100 per cent., of the premium, net of ore-insurances, received or receivable during the preceding twelve months; 

 

(b) reserve for outstanding claims shall be determined in the following manner: 
 
 

(I) where the amounts of outstanding claims of the insurers are known, the amount is to be provided in full; 
 

(II) where the amounts of outstanding claims can be reasonably estimated according to the insurer, he may follow the case by case method, after taking into account the explicit allowance for changes in the settlement pattern or average claim amounts, expenses and inflation; 

 

(c) reserve for claims incurred but not reported (IBNR) shall be determined using actuarial principles. In such determination, the appointed actuary shall follow the Guidance Notes issued by the Actuarial Society of India, with the concurrence of the Authority, and any directions issued by the Authority, in this behalf. 


 

3. Statement of Liability. Every general insurer shall prepare a statement of liabilities in Form HG, certified by an auditor approved by the Authority in accordance with section 64V of the Act, and also certified by its appointed actuary in respect of IBNR reserves. The statement shall be furnished to the Authority along with the returns mentioned in section 15 of the Act. 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. IRDA/Reg/7/2000, dated 14th July, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 19th July, 2000. 
</form><form>
 

THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY 
  (ASSETS, LIABILITIES, AND  

  SOLVENCY MARGIN OF INSURERS) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

SCHEDULE IIIA 
 

( See Regulation 5) 
 

DETERMINATION OF SOLVENCY MARGINSLIFE INSURERS 
 

1. Interpretation. In this schedule, 
 
 

(a) Available Solvency Margin means the excess of value of assets (furnished in IRDA-Form-AA) over the value of life insurance liabilities (furnished in Form H as specified in Regulation 4 of Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Actuarial Report and Abstract) Regulations, 2000) and other liabilities of policy-holders' fund and share-holders' funds; 
 

(b) Solvency Ratio means the ratio of the amount of Available Solvency Margin to the amount of Required Solvency margin. 

 

2. Determination of Solvency Margin. Every insurer shall determine the required solvency margin, the available solvency margin, and the solvency ratio in Form K as specified under Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority (Actuarial Report and Abstract), Regulations, 2000. 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. IRDA/Reg/7/2000, dated 14th July, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 19th July, 2000. 
</form><form>
 

THE INSURANCE REGULATORY AND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY 
  (ASSETS, LIABILITIES, AND  

  SOLVENCY MARGIN OF INSURERS) REGULATIONS, 20001
 

 
 

SCHEDULE IIIB 
 

( See section 5) 
 

DETERMINATION OF SOLVENCY MARGINSGENERAL INSURERS 
 

1. Interpretation. In this schedule, 
 

(a) Available Solvency Margin means the excess of value of assets (furnished in Form IRDA-Assets-AA) over the value of liabilities (furnished in Form HG),with further adjustments as shown in Table III of Form KG. 
 

(b) Solvency Ratio means the ratio of the amount of Available Solvency Margin to the amount of Required Solvency margin. 
 

2. Determination of Solvency Margin. Every insurer shall determine the required solvency margin, the available solvency margin, and the solvency ratio in Form KG. 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide Notification No. IRDA/Reg/7/2000, dated 14th July, 2000, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, dated 19th July, 2000. 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>