<act><title>

    THE ESSENTIAL COMMODITIES (SPECIAL PROVISIONS) ACT, 1981</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, commencement and duration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Essential Commodities (Special Provisions) Act, 
    1981.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
    and different dates may be appointed for different States.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall cease to have effect on the expiry of 

    2[fifteen years] from 
    the date of commencement of this Act except as respects things done or 
    omitted to be done before such cesser of operation of this Act, and section 
    6 of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall apply upon such 
    cesser of operation of this Act as if it had then been repealed by a Central 
    Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> References 
    in this Act of the commencement of this Act and to the continuance in force 
    of this Act shall be construed in relation to each State as references, 
    respectively, to the coming into force of this Act in that State and to the 
    continuance in force of this Act in that State. 
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> Act 10 of 1955 to have effect subject to 
      certain special provisions for a temporary period.—During the continuance in force of this Act, 
      the Essential Commodities Act, 1955 (hereinafter referred to as the 
      principal Act) shall have effect subject to the amendments specified in 
      sections 3 to 11: 
 Provided that the amendments specified in 
      sections 7 to 11 shall not apply to, or in relation to, any offence under 
      the principal Act committed before the commencement of this Act and the 
      provisions of the principal Act shall apply to, and in relation to, such 
      offence as if those amendments had not been made. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Amendment of section 2.—In 
    section 2 of the principal Act,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    clause (ia) shall be renumbered as 
    clause (iia), and before clause (iia) as so re-numbered, the following 
    clause shall be inserted namely:— 
 
‘(ia) “Code” means the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974); and’; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    after clause (e), the following clause 
    shall be inserted, namely:— 
 
“(f) words and expressions used but not 
    defined in this Act and defined in the Code shall have the meanings 
    respectively assigned to them in that Code.”. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Amendment of section 6A.—In 
    section 6A of the principal Act, for the proviso to sub-section (2), the 
    following proviso shall be substituted, namely:— 
 
“Provided that 
    in the case of any such essential commodity the retail sale price whereof 
    has been fixed by the Central Government or a State Government under this 
    Act or under any other law for the time being in force, the Collector may, 
    for its equitable distribution and availability at fair prices, order the 
    same to be sold through fair price shops at the price so fixed.” 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Amendment of section 6C.—In 
    section 6C of the principal Act,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in sub-section (1), for the words “any 
    judicial authority appointed by the State Government concerned and the 
    judicial authority”, the words “the State Government concerned and the State 
    Government” shall be substituted. 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    in sub-section (2), for the words “such 
    judicial authority”, the words “the State Government” shall be substituted. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Amendment of section 6E.—In 
    section 6E of the principal Act,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    for the words, figure and letter “the 
    judicial authority appointed under section 6C” the words, figure and letter 
    “the State Government concerned under section 6C” shall be substituted; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    for the words “any other court, 
    tribunal or authority”, the words “any court, tribunal or other authority” 
    shall be substituted. 
 
 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Amendment of section 7.—In 
    section 7 of the principal Act,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    in sub-section (1), the proviso to 
    sub-clause (ii) of clause (a) shall be omitted; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    the proviso to sub-section (2) shall be 
    omitted; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    the proviso to sub-section (2A) shall 
    be omitted; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    sub-section (2B) shall be omitted. 
 
 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Amendment of section 8.—To 
    section 8 of the principal Act, the following proviso shall be added, 
    namely:— 
 
“Provided that 
    where a person has abetted the contravention of any order for the purpose of 
    procuring any essential commodity of the nature mentioned in sub-clause (iva) 
    or sub-clause (v) of clause 
<section><number>a</number> of section 2 for his own use or for the use 
    of any member of his family or for the use of any person dependent on him, 
    and not for the purpose of carrying on any business or trade in such 
    essential commodity, the court may, notwithstanding anything contained in 
    section 7 and for reasons to be mentioned in the judgment, impose a sentence 
    of fine only.”. 
 
 
  
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Amendment of section 10A.—In 
    section 10A of the principal Act, after the word “cognizable” the words “and 
    non-bailable” shall be inserted. 
 
 
  
  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>9A</number> Insertion of new section 10AA in Act 10 of 1955</title>.—In the Essential Commodities Act, 1955 (10 of 1955), after section 10A, the following section shall be inserted, namely:—



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Omission of section 12.—Section 
    12 of the principal Act shall be omitted. 
 
 
  
  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Substitution of new sections for section 12A. 
</title>—For section 12A of the principal Act, the following sections shall be 
substituted, namely:— 
 
 


</article><article>‘<number>12A</number> Constitution of Special Courts .—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
  Government may, for the purpose of providing speedy trial of the offences 
  under this Act, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute as many 
  Special Courts as may be necessary for such area or areas as may be specified 
  in the notification. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A Special Court shall consist of a single judge who shall 
  be appointed by the High Court upon a request made by the State Government. 
  
 Explanation. —In this sub-section, the word “appoint” 
  shall have the meaning given to it in the explanation to section 9 of the 
  Code. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A person shall not be qualified for appointment as a judge 
  of a Special Court unless— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> he is qualified for appointment as a judge of a High 
    Court, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> he has, for a period of not less than one year, been a 
    Sessions Judge or an Additional Sessions Judge. </subsection>
 </section></article><article><number>12AA</number> Offences triable by Special Courts .—
<section><number>1</number> 
  Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> all offences under this Act shall be triable only by the 
    Special Court constituted for the area in which the offence has been 
    committed or where there are more Special Courts than one for such area, by 
    such one of them as may be specified in this behalf by the High Court; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> where a person accused of or suspected of the commission 
    of an offence under this Act is forwarded to a Magistrate under sub-section 
    (2) or sub-section (2A) of section 167 of the Code, such Magistrate may 
    authorise the detention of such person in such custody as he thinks fit for 
    a period not exceeding fifteen days in the whole where such Magistrate is a 
    Judicial Magistrate and seven days in the whole where such Magistrate is an 
    Executive Magistrate: </subsection>
 Provided that where such Magistrate considers— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> when such person is forwarded to him as aforesaid; or 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> upon or at any time before the expiry of the period of 
    detention authorised by him, </subsection>
 that the detention of such person is unnecessary, he may, if 
  he is satisfied that the case falls under the proviso to section 8, order the 
  release of such person on bail and if he is not so satisfied, he shall order 
  such person to be forwarded to the Special Court having jurisdiction; 
 
 <subsection><number>c</number> the Special Court may, subject to the provisions of 
    clause (d) of this sub-section, exercise, in relation to the person 
    forwarded to it under clause (b), the same power which is Magistrate having 
    jurisdiction to try a case may exercise under section 167 of the Code in 
    relation to an accused person in such case who has been forwarded to him 
    under that section; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> save as aforesaid no person accused of or suspected of 
    the commission of an offence under this Act shall be released on bail by any 
    court other than a Special Court or the High Court: </subsection>
 Provided that a Special Court shall not release any such 
  person on bail— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> without giving the prosecution an opportunity to oppose 
    the application for such release unless the Special Court, for reasons to be 
    recorded in writing, is of opinion that it is not practicable to give such 
    opportunity; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> where the prosecution opposes the application, if the 
    Special Court is satisfied that there appear reasonable grounds for 
    believing that he has been guilty of the offence concerned: </subsection>
 Provided further that the Special Court may direct that any 
  such person may be released on bail if he is under the age of sixteen years or 
  is a woman or is a sick or infirm person, or if the Special Court is satisfied 
  that it is just and proper so to do for any other special reason to be 
  recorded in writing; 
 
 <subsection><number>e</number> a Special Court may, upon a perusal of police report of 
    the facts constituting an offence under this Act <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[or upon a 
    complaint made by an Officer of the Central Government or a State Government 
    authorised in this behalf by the Government concerned] <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[or any 
    person aggrieved or any recognised consumer association, whether such person 
    is a member of that association or not,] take cognizance of that offence 
    without the accused being committed to it for trial; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> all offences under this Act shall be tried in a summary 
    way and the provisions of sections 262 to 265 (both inclusive) of the Code 
    shall, as far as may be, apply to such trial: </subsection>
 Provided that in the case of any conviction in a summary trial 
  under this section, it shall be lawful for the Special Court to pass a 
  sentence of imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When trying an offence under this Act, a Special Court may 
  also try an offence other than an offence under this Act, with which the 
  accused may, under the Code, be charged at the same trial: 
 Provided that such other offence is, under any other law for 
  the time being in force, triable in a summary way: 
 Provided further that in the case of any conviction for such 
  other offence in such trial, it shall not be lawful for the Special Court to 
  pass a sentence of imprisonment for a term exceeding the term provided for 
  conviction in a summary trial under such other law. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A Special Court may, with a view to obtaining the evidence 
  of any person suspected to have been directly or indirectly concerned in, or 
  privy to, an offence under this Act, tender a pardon to such person on 
  condition of his making a full and true disclosure of the whole circumstances 
  within his knowledge relating to the offence and to every other person 
  concerned whether as principal or abettor in the commission thereof and any 
  pardon so tendered shall, for the purposes of section 308 of the Code, be 
  deemed to have been tendered under section 307 thereof. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to 
  affect the special powers of the High Court regarding bail under section 439 
  of the Code and the High Court may exercise such powers including the power 
  under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of that section as if the reference to 
  “Magistrate” in that section included also a reference to a “Special Court” 
  constituted under section 12A. 
 </section></article><article><number>12AB</number> Appeal and revision .—The High Court may 
  exercise, so far as may be applicable, all the persons conferred by Chapters 
  XXIX and XXX of the Code on a High Court, as if a Special Court within the 
  local limits of the jurisdiction of the High Court were a Court of Sessions 
  trying cases within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the High Court. 
  
 </article><article><number>12AC</number> Application of Code to proceedings before a Special 
  Court .—Save as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of the 
  Code (including the provisions as to bail and bonds) shall apply to the 
  proceedings before a Special Court and for the purposes of the said 
  provisions, the Special Court shall be deemed to be a Court of Sessions and 
  the person conducting a prosecution before a Special Court, shall be deemed to 
  be a Public Prosecutor'. </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
‘<number>12A</number> 
    Constitution of Special Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, for the purpose of providing speedy trial of the 
    offences under this Act, by notification in the Official Gazette, constitute 
    as many Special Courts as may be necessary for such area or areas as may be 
    specified in the notification. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Special 
    Court shall consist of a single judge who shall be appointed by the High 
    Court upon a request made by the State Government. 
 

    Explanation.—In this sub-section, 
    the word “appoint” shall have the meaning given to it in the explanation to 
    section 9 of the Code. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person 
    shall not be qualified for appointment as a judge of a Special Court unless— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    he is qualified for appointment as a 
    judge of a High Court, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    he has, for a period of not less than 
    one year, been a Sessions Judge or an Additional Sessions Judge. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12AA</number> 
    Offences triable by Special Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all offences under this Act shall be 
    triable only by the Special Court constituted for the area in which the 
    offence has been committed or where there are more Special Courts than one 
    for such area, by such one of them as may be specified in this behalf by the 
    High Court; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where a person accused of or suspected 
    of the commission of an offence under this Act is forwarded to a Magistrate 
    under sub-section (2) or sub-section (2A) of section 167 of the Code, such 
    Magistrate may authorise the detention of such person in such custody as he 
    thinks fit for a period not exceeding fifteen days in the whole where such 
    Magistrate is a Judicial Magistrate and seven days in the whole where such 
    Magistrate is an Executive Magistrate: 
 
Provided that 
    where such Magistrate considers— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    when such person is forwarded to him as 
    aforesaid; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    upon or at any time before the expiry 
    of the period of detention authorised by him, 
 
that the detention of such person is 
    unnecessary, he may, if he is satisfied that the case falls under the 
    proviso to section 8, order the release of such person on bail and if he is 
    not so satisfied, he shall order such person to be forwarded to the Special 
    Court having jurisdiction;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Special Court may, subject to the 
    provisions of clause (d) of this sub-section, exercise, in relation to the 
    person forwarded to it under clause (b), the same power which is Magistrate 
    having jurisdiction to try a case may exercise under section 167 of the Code 
    in relation to an accused person in such case who has been forwarded to him 
    under that section; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    save as aforesaid no person accused of 
    or suspected of the commission of an offence under this Act shall be 
    released on bail by any court other than a Special Court or the High Court: 
 
Provided that 
    a Special Court shall not release any such person on bail— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    without giving the prosecution an 
    opportunity to oppose the application for such release unless the Special 
    Court, for reasons to be recorded in writing, is of opinion that it is not 
    practicable to give such opportunity; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    where the prosecution opposes the 
    application, if the Special Court is satisfied that there appear reasonable 
    grounds for believing that he has been guilty of the offence concerned: 
 
Provided 
    further that the Special Court may direct that any such person may be 
    released on bail if he is under the age of sixteen years or is a woman or is 
    a sick or infirm person, or if the Special Court is satisfied that it is 
    just and proper so to do for any other special reason to be recorded in 
    writing; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    a Special Court may, upon a perusal of 
    police report of the facts constituting an offence under this Act take 
    cognizance of that offence without the accused being committed to it for 
    trial; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    all offences under this Act shall be 
    tried in a summary way and the provisions of sections 262 to 265 (both 
    inclusive) of the Code shall, as far as may be, apply to such trial: 
 
Provided that 
    in the case of any conviction in a summary trial under this section, it 
    shall be lawful for the Special Court to pass a sentence of imprisonment for 
    a term not exceeding two years. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When 
    trying an offence under this Act, a Special Court may also try an offence 
    other than an offence under this Act, with which the accused may, under the 
    Code, be charged at the same trial: 
 
Provided that 
    such other offence is, under any other law for the time being in force, 
    triable in a summary way: 
 
Provided 
    further that in the case of any conviction for such other offence in such 
    trial, it shall not be lawful for the Special Court to pass a sentence of 
    imprisonment for a term exceeding the term provided for conviction in a 
    summary trial under such other law. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A Special 
    Court may, with a view to obtaining the evidence of any person suspected to 
    have been directly or indirectly concerned in, or privy to, an offence under 
    this Act, tender a pardon to such person on condition of his making a full 
    and true disclosure of the whole circumstances within his knowledge relating 
    to the offence and to every other person concerned whether as principal or 
    abettor in the commission thereof and any pardon so tendered shall, for the 
    purposes of section 308 of the Code, be deemed to have been tendered under 
    section 307 thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing 
    contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the special powers of 
    the High Court regarding bail under section 439 of the Code and the High 
    Court may exercise such powers including the power under clause (b) of 
    sub-section (1) of that section as if the reference to “Magistrate” in that 
    section included also a reference to a “Special Court” constituted under 
    section 12A. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12AB</number> 
    Appeal and revision.—The High 
    Court may exercise, so far as may be applicable, all the persons conferred 
    by Chapters XXIX and XXX of the Code on a High Court, as if a Special Court 
    within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the High Court were a Court 
    of Sessions trying cases within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the 
    High Court. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12AC</number> 
    Application of Code to proceedings before a Special Court.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of the Code (including the 
    provisions as to bail and bonds) shall apply to the proceedings before a 
    Special Court and for the purposes of the said provisions, the Special Court 
    shall be deemed to be a Court of Sessions and the person conducting a 
    prosecution before a Special Court, shall be deemed to be a Public 
    Prosecutor’. 
 
 
  
  
  
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by Act 34 of 1993, sec. 4 (w.r.e.f. 27-8-1992).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 42 of 1986, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 
9-9-1986).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 73 of 1986, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
1-5-1987).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>