<act><tid>1865332</tid>
<title>THE LIFE INSURANCE (EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>1956</year>
[ 21st March, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the taking over, in the public interest, of the 
management of life insurance business pending nationalisation thereof.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--





<article><tid>1466832</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Life Insurance 
 (Emergency Provisions) Act, <year>1956</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>907315</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1692284</tid>
<number>1</number>" appointed day" means the 19th day of January, <year>1956</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>315461</tid>
<number>2</number>" controlled business" means--

<subsection><tid>1801332</tid>
<number>i</number>in the case of an insurer specified in sub- 
clause (a)  (ii) or sub- clause (b) of clause (9) of 
section 2 of the Insurance Act and carrying on life 
insurance business--

<subsubsection><tid>1470142</tid>
<number>a</number>all his business, if he carries on no 
other class of insurance business;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1975907</tid>
<number>b</number>all the business appertaining to his life 
insurance business, if he carries on some other 
class of insurance business also;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>111991</tid>
<number>c</number>all his business, if his certificate of 
registration under the Insurance Act in respect of 
general insurance business stands wholly cancelled 
for a period of more than six months on the 
appointed day;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>706928</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the case of any other insurer specified in 
clause (9) of section 2 of the Insurance Act and 
carrying on life insurance business--

<subsubsection><tid>1178313</tid>
<number>a</number>all his business in India, if he carries 
on no other class of insurance business in India;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1060972</tid>
<number>b</number>all the business appertaining to his life 
insurance business in India, if he carries on some 
other class of insurance business also in India;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>685147</tid>
<number>c</number>all his business in India, if his 
certificate of registration under the Insurance 
Act in respect of

<pagefootnote><pagenum>234</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

general insurance business in India stands wholly 
cancelled for a period of more than six months on 
the appointed day;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1453974</tid>
<number>iii</number>in the case of a provident society, as 
defined in section 65 of the Insurance Act, all its 
business;
Explanation.-- An insurer is said to carry on no 
class of insurance business other than life insurance 
business if, in addition to life insurance business, he 
carries on only capital redemption business or annuity 
certain business or both; and the expression" business 
appertaining to his life insurance business" shall be 
construed accordingly;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1334584</tid>
<number>3</number>" Custodian" means the person appointed under section 4 
to take over the management of any controlled business;

</section>

<section><tid>1998872</tid>
<number>4</number>" Insurance Act" means the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of  
  <year>1938</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>232285</tid>
<number>5</number>" insurer" means an insurer as defined in the Insurance 
Act who carries on life insurance business in India, 
and includes a provident society as defined in section 
 65 of the Insurance Act;

</section>

<section><tid>539757</tid>
<number>6</number>" notified order" means an order notified in the Official 
Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1911840</tid>
<number>7</number>all other words and expressions used herein but not 
defined, and defined in the Insurance Act, shall have 
the meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>736983</tid>
<number> 3</number> Management of controlled business to vest in Government on 
commencement of Act.
<section><tid>1189391</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day, the management  
of the controlled business of all insurers shall vest in the Central 
Government, and, pending the appointment of a Custodian for the 
controlled business of any insurer, the persons in charge of the 
management of such business immediately before the appointed day 
shall, on and from the appointed day, be in charge of the management 
of the business for and on behalf of the Central Government; and the 
controlled business of the insurer shall be carried on by them subject 
to the provisions contained in sub- sections (3) and (5) and to such 
further directions, if any, as the Central Government may give to them 
by notice addressed and sent to the principal officer of the insurer.

</section>

<section><tid>452000</tid>
<number>2</number>Any contract, whether express or implied, providing for the 
management of the controlled business of an insurer made before the 
appointed day between the insurer and any person in charge of the 
management of such business immediately before the appointed day shall 
be deemed to have terminated on the appointed day.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>235</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1461292</tid>
<number>3</number>No insurer shall, without the previous approval of the person 
specified by the Central Government in this behalf in respect of that 
insurer (hereinafter referred to as the authorized person),--

<subsection><tid>1052788</tid>
<number>a</number>make any payment or grant any loan in respect of a 
policy of life insurance otherwise than in accordance 
with the normal practice observed by him in respect of 
such matters immediately before the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1302791</tid>
<number>b</number>incur any expenditure from the assets appertaining to 
the controlled business otherwise than for the purpose 
of making routine payments of salaries or commissions 
to employees, insurance agents, special agents or chief 
agents or for the purpose of meeting the routine day to 
day expenditure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1552214</tid>
<number>c</number>transfer or otherwise dispose of any such assets or 
create any charge, hypothecation, lien or other 
encumbrance thereon;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1245768</tid>
<number>d</number>invest in any manner any moneys forming part of such 
assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1268357</tid>
<number>e</number>acquire any immovable property out of any moneys forming 
part of such assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1920970</tid>
<number>f</number>enter into any contract of service or agency, whether 
expressly or by implication, for purposes connected 
wholly or partly with the controlled business or vary 
the terms and conditions of any such contract 
subsisting on the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>89849</tid>
<number>g</number>enter into any other transaction relating to controlled 
business other than a contract relating to the issue of 
a new policy of life insurance or vary the terms and 
conditions of any agreement relating to any such 
transaction subsisting at the commencement of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>804164</tid>
<number>4</number>The approval of the authorized person may be given either 
generally in relation to certain classes of transactions of the 
insurer or specially in relation to any of his transactions.

</section>

<section><tid>470965</tid>
<number>5</number>Every insurer shall deposit all securities and documents of 
title to any assets appertaining to the controlled business in any 
Scheduled Bank in which the insurer had an account immediately before 
the appointed day or in any branch of the State Bank in the place 
where the head office or the principal office of the insurer is 
situated or, where there is no branch of the State Bank in such place, 
the nearest branch of the State Bank; and no such security or document 
shall be withdrawn from the Scheduled Bank or the State Bank, as the 
case may be, except with the permission of the authorized person:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>236</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply 
to any security or document of title kept with approved trustees by 
reason of the provisions contained in sub- section (6) of section 27 of 
the Insurance Act, or kept in trust with an Official Trustee in 
pursuance of the articles of association of an insurer unless the 
Central Government, by notified order, otherwise directs.

Explanation.-- In this sub- section,--


<subsection><tid>244109</tid>
<number>a</number>" Scheduled Bank" means a bank included for the time 
being in the Second Schedule to the Reserve Bank of 
India Act, <year>1934</year> (2 of <year>1934</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370561</tid>
<number>b</number>" State Bank" means the State Bank of India constituted 
under the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of <year>1955</year>).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1227453</tid>
<number>6</number>Every insurer shall deliver forthwith at the place and to the 
person specified in this behalf by the Central Government in respect 
of that insurer the following documents, namely:--

<subsection><tid>439677</tid>
<number>i</number>the minutes book or any other book in India containing 
all resolutions up to the appointed day of the persons 
in charge of the management of the controlled business 
before the appointed day;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1869126</tid>
<number>ii</number>the current cheque books relating to the controlled 
business which are at the head office or the principal 
office of the insurer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1324516</tid>
<number>iii</number>all registers or other books containing particulars 
relating to the investment of any moneys appertaining 
to the controlled business including investments on 
mortgaged properties and all loans granted and advances 
made otherwise than on policies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>688949</tid>
<number>iv</number>all brokers' notes or certificates in the possession of 
the insurer in respect of any orders for the investment 
of any moneys appertaining to the controlled business:
Provided that if any document specified in this sub- section is 
relevant for the purpose of any business other than the controlled 
business carried on by the insurer, the person specified in the 
notified order shall be bound to return it to the persons in charge of 
the management of such other business with the least possible delay, 
but shall have power to place identification marks on such document or 
to take extracts or copies therefrom.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1398655</tid>
<number>7</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the powers conferred 
by sub- section (1) and to the provisions contained in sub- sections 
 (3), (5) and (6), any directions issued under sub- section (1) may 
require the persons in charge of the management of the controlled 
business

<pagefootnote><pagenum>237</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of an insurer under this Act to furnish to the Central Government or 
to the authorized person such returns, statements and other 
information relating to the controlled business as may be mentioned in 
the direction.


</section>

<section><tid>684147</tid>
<number>8</number>The persons in charge of the management of the controlled 
business of an insurer under this Act shall be entitled to such 
remuneration, whether by way of allowance or salary as the Central 
Government may fix; and any such person may, by giving a month' s 
notice in writing to the Central Government of his intention so to do, 
relinquish charge of the management of the controlled business.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1993677</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power of Central Government to appoint Custodians to take over 
management of controlled business.
<section><tid>1908443</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, as  
soon as it is convenient administratively so to do, appoint any person 
as Custodian for the purpose of taking over the management of the 
controlled business of an insurer.

</section>

<section><tid>1696120</tid>
<number>2</number>On the appointment of a Custodian under sub- section (1), all 
persons in charge of the management of the controlled business of the 
insurer for and on behalf of the Central Government immediately before 
such appointment shall cease to be in charge of such management and 
shall be bound to deliver to the Custodian all books of account, 
registers or other documents in their custody relating to the 
controlled business of the insurer.

</section>

<section><tid>782927</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing contained in sub- section (3), (5) and (6) of section 
 3 shall apply to any insurer the management of whose controlled 
business has been taken over by the Custodian, but the Central 
Government may issue such directions to the Custodian as to his powers 
and duties as it deems desirable in the circumstances of the case, and 
the Custodian may apply to the Central Government at any time for 
instructions as to the manner in which he shall conduct the management 
of the controlled business of the insurer or in relation to any matter 
arising in the course of such management.

</section>

<section><tid>1107967</tid>
<number>4</number>The Custodian shall receive such remuneration as the Central 
Government may fix; and the Central Government may at any time cancel 
the appointment of any person as Custodian and appoint some other 
person in his stead.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>576819</tid>
<number>5</number>Refund of deposits made under Insurance Act. The Central 
Government may, by order, direct that the whole or any part of the 
deposit appertaining to his controlled business made by an insurer 
under section 7, section 73 or section 98 of the Insurance Act, as the 
case may be, shall be returned to the Custodian who has been appointed 
to take over the management of the controlled business of the insurer, 
and every such order shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Insurance Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>238</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1711920</tid>
<number>6</number>Powers of Custodian to institute proceedings, etc. The 
Custodian may, in relation to the controlled business of any insurer 
the management of which has been taken over by him, exercise all or 
any of the powers which the Controller of Insurance or an 
Administrator appointed under section 52A of the Insurance Act may 
exercise under section 52BB, section 106 or section 107 of that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1139493</tid>
<number>7</number>Compensation for management of controlled business vesting in 
Central Government. The amount of compensation payable in respect of 
the vesting in the Central Government of the management of the 
controlled business of an insurer shall, for every month during which 
the management thereof remains vested in the Central Government, be a 
sum which is equivalent to one- twelfth of the annual average of the 
share of the surplus allocated to shareholders as disclosed in the 
abstracts prepared in accordance with Part II of the Fourth Schedule 
to the Insurance Act in respect of the last two actuarial 
investigations relating to the controlled business as at dates earlier 
than the first day of January, <year>1956</year>:
Provided that, if in respect of the controlled business of an 
insurer no such surplus as is referred to in this sub- section has been 
allocated to shareholders either because there are no shareholders or 
for any other reason, the compensation shall be payable at the rate of 
one rupee per month for every two thousand rupees or part thereof of 
the premium income of the insurer relating to his controlled business 
during the year <year>1954</year>.



</article>



<article><tid>1594400</tid>
<number> 8</number> Compensation, how to be paid and distributed.
<section><tid>1257251</tid>
<number>1</number>The amount  
of compensation payable under section 7 shall in the first instance be 
payable out of the seven and a half per cent. of the surplus referred 
to in sub- section (1) of section 49 of the Insurance Act earned by the 
insurer during the period the management of the controlled business of 
the insurer vests in the Central Government, and where such 
compensation or any part thereof cannot be so paid out the Central 
Government shall make due provision for the payment of such 
compensation or part thereof as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>852714</tid>
<number>2</number>The compensation payable under section 7 shall be distributed 
among the persons entitled thereto by the Central Government in such 
manner as may be prescribed by rules made in this behalf:
Provided that in the case of an insurer who is a company the 
Central Government shall have due regard to the wishes of the members 
expressed by them at any general meeting convened for the purpose.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1406545</tid>
<number> 9</number> Penalties. If any person--
<section><tid>1362383</tid>
<number>a</number>fails to deliver to the Custodian any books of account, 
registers or any other documents in his custody 
relating

<pagefootnote><pagenum>239</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to the controlled business of an insurer in respect of 
the management of which the Custodian has been 
appointed; or


</section>

<section><tid>580557</tid>
<number>b</number>retains any property of such insurer appertaining to the 
controlled business of the insurer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1566509</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to comply with the provisions contained in sub- 
section (3) or sub- section (5) or sub- section (6) of 
section 3; or

</section>

<section><tid>931369</tid>
<number>d</number>fails to comply with any directions issued under sub- 
section (1) or sub- section (7) of section 3;
he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1273220</tid>
<number>10</number>Insurer not to be wound up by Court. No proceeding for the 
winding up of an insurer the management of whose controlled business 
has vested in the Central Government under this Act or for the 
appointment of a Receiver in respect of such business shall lie in any 
Court.


</article>



<article><tid>83264</tid>
<number>11</number>Exclusion of time of Act for computing period of limitation. 
In computing the period of limitation prescribed by any law for the 
time being in force for any suit or application against any person by 
an insurer in respect of any matter arising out of his controlled 
business, the time during which the Life Insurance (Emergency  
  Provisions) Ordinance, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), and this Act have been in 
force shall be excluded.


</article>



<article><tid>1718442</tid>
<number>12</number>Effect of Act on other laws. The provisions of this Act shall 
have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith in any 
other law or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any other 
law.


</article>



<article><tid>620093</tid>
<number>13</number>Delegation of powers. The Central Government may, by notified 
order, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it under 
this Act may also be exercised by any such person as may be specified 
in the order.


</article>



<article><tid>92260</tid>
<number> 14</number> Protection of action taken under Act.
<section><tid>1800079</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit, prosection  
or other legal proceeding shall lie against any Custodian or 
authorized person in respect of anything which is in good faith done 
or intended to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1030915</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or any Custodian or authorized person for any 
damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in good 
faith done or intended to be done under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>501677</tid>
<number>15</number>Prevention of disqualification for membership of Parliament. 
It is hereby declared that no person who holds any office of profit 
under an insurer the management of whose controlled business.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>240</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

has vested in the Central Government under this Act shall be 
disqualified, or ever to have been disqualified for being chosen as, 
or for being, a member of either House of Parliament.



</article>



<article><tid>1434998</tid>
<number> 16</number> Exemptions. Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to--
<section><tid>168371</tid>
<number>a</number>any insurer in respect of the management of whose 
affairs an Administrator has been appointed under 
section 52A of the Insurance Act;

</section>

<section><tid>505367</tid>
<number>b</number>any insurer whose business is being voluntarily wound up 
or is being wound up under the orders of a Court;

</section>

<section><tid>327581</tid>
<number>c</number>any insurer to whom the Insurance Act does not apply by 
reason of the provisions contained in section 2E 
thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1313892</tid>
<number>d</number>any approved superannuation fund as defined in clause 
 (a) of section 58N of the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> 
 (11 of <year>1922</year>); or

</section>

<section><tid>1917074</tid>
<number>e</number>any insurance business carried on by the Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1934882</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1087360</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notified order, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>169865</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, rules made under sub- section (1) may provide for-

<subsection><tid>620437</tid>
<number>a</number>the form and manner in which books of accounts 
appertaining to controlled business shall be maintained 
by insurers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>442673</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which any compensation payable under this 
Act may be paid to the persons entitled thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1612203</tid>
<number>c</number>the circumstances in which the remuneration payable to 
persons in charge of the management of the controlled 
business of an insurer under this Act or to Custodians 
shall be met by the Central Government, whether wholly 
or in part.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>403068</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
from or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>5614</tid>
<number>18</number>[ Repeal of Ordinance 1 of <year>1956</year> and savings.] Rep. by the 
Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. 1.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>241</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>