<act><title>The 
      Marriage Validation Act, 1892</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>1</number> Commencement.—Repealed by Act X of 1914, sec. 3 and 
      Sch. II.
    
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act the
expression 1[Indian
Christian] has the same meaning as in the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872.
  
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number>
Validation of irregular marriages.—All
marriages which have already been solemnized under Part VI of the Indian
Christian Marriage Act, 1872, between persons of whom one only was <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[an
Indian Christian], shall be as good and valid in law as if such marriages had
been solemnized between persons of whom both were <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Indian
Christians]:
 Provided
that nothing in this section shall apply to any mar­riage which has been
judicially declared to be null and void, or to any case where either of the
parties has, since the solemniza­tion of such marriage and prior to the
commencement of this Act, contracted a valid marriage.
   


  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number>
Validation of records of irregular marriages.—Certificates
of marriages which are declared by the last foregoing section to be good and
valid in law, and register-books, and certified copies of true and duly
authenticated extracts therefrom, deposited in compliance with the law for the
time being in force, in so far as the register-books and extracts relate to such
marriages are aforesaid, shall be received as evidence of such marriages as if
such marriages had been solemnized between persons of whom both were <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Indian
Christians].
   







 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Application of Act to marriages under Act V 
      of 1865.—Refer­ences in 
      this Act to the Indian Christian Marriage Act, 1872, shall, so far as may 
      be requisite, be construed as applying also to the corresponding portions 
      of the Indian Marriage Act, 1865.
    
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number>
Penalty for solemnizing irregular marriages.—If
any person licensed under section 9 of the said Act, to grant certificates of
marriage between 1[Indian
Christians] shall at any time after the commencement of this Act solemnized or
affect to solemnize any marriage under Part VI of the said Act or grant any such
certificate as therein mentioned, knowing that one of the parties to such
marriage or affected marriage was at the date of such solemnization not a
Christian, he shall be liable to have his license cancelled, and in addition
thereto he shall be deemed to have been guilty of an offence prohibited by
section 73 of the said Act, and shall be punishable accordingly.
  
  





 



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Subs. by A.L.O. 1950, for “Native Christians”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>
Subs. by ALO 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
Subs. by ALO 1950.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>