<act><title>

The
Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and Placement of
Seafarers) Rules, 2005. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette. 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules,
unless the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Merchant Shipping Act, 1958 (44 of 1958); 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
“advisory board” means the advisory board or other authority
constituted by the Central Government under clause (a) of sub-section (3) of
section 95 of the Act;  
 

 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Director” means the Director of the seamen’s employment office
concerned or any other officer authorised by the Director-General in this
behalf;  
 

 </section><section><number>d</number>
“Director-General” means the “Director-General of Shipping”
appointed under section 7 of the Act; 
 

 </section><section><number>e</number>
“employer” means any person, who has assumed the responsibility of
employing seafarers for himself or for any other person in respect of a ship and
who has agreed to take over all such duties and responsibilities; 
 

 </section><section><number>f</number>
“Form” means a Form appended to these rules; 
 

 </section><section><number>g</number>
“inspecting authority” means any officer subordinate to the
Director-General or any other person or body of persons professionally competent
to carry out inspection under rule 3 and authorised by the Director-General in
this behalf; 
 

 </section><section><number>h</number>
“licence” means the recruitment and placement service licence issued
under rule 4; 
 

 </section><section><number>i</number>
“ship owner” means the owner of a ship or any organisation or any
person such as manager, agent or bareboat charterer, who or which has assumed
the responsibility for operation of the ship from such owner and who or which on
assuming such responsibilities had agreed to take over all the duties and
responsibilities as such owner. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>3</number>
Inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> The inspecting
authority shall carry out the inspection of recruitment and placement service so
as to ensure that—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
no fees or other charges for recruitment or for providing employment to
seafarers are borne directly or indirectly, in whole or in part, by the
seafarer: 
 

 Provided
that the cost of the requisite medical examination or requisite certificates or
passport or visa or continuous discharge certificate shall be borne by the
seafarer; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the seafarers’ personal data is collected, stored, processed, combined
and communicated to third parties:  
 

 Provided
that the right to privacy of the seafarer and the need to protect
confidentiality as per general employment practices shall be maintained;  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the management and staff are adequately trained persons having relevant
knowledge of the maritime industry to the extent of the duties assigned; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
no means, mechanism or list is used with the intention to prevent or deter
seafarers from gaining employment; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> the employment contract or agreement contains a provision to repatriate
the seafarer in the event of his being stranded at any place or transportation
of the mortal remains of an expired seafarer: 
 

 Provided
that the employment contract or agreement shall be in accordance with any law
for the time being in force and collective agreements, if any: 
 

 Provided
further that the seafarer is informed of his rights and duties under the
employment contract or agreement prior to placement: 
 

 Provided
also that the seafarer shall be supplied with a copy of employment contract or
agreement and the terms of such contract or agreement shall be explained to him
before he signs the same; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> The provisions relating to prohibition against discrimination contained
in section 97A of the Act are not violated; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
records of all seafarers recruited are maintained;  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
a seafarer recruited or placed is qualified and holds the requisite
documents for the job concerned; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number>
a proper grievance redressal mechanism is adopted in regard to any
complaint made against the recruitment and placement service or against the ship
owner: 
 

 Provided
that any unresolved grievance against the recruitment and placement service or
the ship owner shall be brought to the notice of the Director-General or the
country to which the ship belongs, as the case may be: 
 

 Provided
further that any complaint against a recruitment and placement service or a ship
owner may be directly referred by the seafarer to the Director-General or the
country to which the ship belongs; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number>
the seamen’s employment office concerned and next of kin of the
seafarer is informed of each death or disability of the seafarer within
forty-eight hours of such death or disability in Form V; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number>
the details of the employer and the ship owner are maintained in respect
of each ship; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> an acknowledgement containing the name, address, licence number and its
validity is issued to the seafarer on filing an application for placement; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> the responsibility, authority and inter-relation of all the personnel in
the recruitment and placement service who manage, perform and verify the work
are defined and adequate resources and infrastructure are available to carry out
their functions. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
On completion of an inspection under sub-rule (1), the inspecting authority
shall submit a report to the Director within a period of fifteen days:
 


 Provided
that the Director-General may permit such inspection authority to submit a
report within a further period not exceeding fifteen days.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (4), the
Director-General may require any inspecting authority to submit a report to him
directly or cause any other inspections to be done as he deems fit.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The Director shall ensure that annual inspections or inspections otherwise
required by these rules are carried out by the inspecting authority.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
The recruitment and placement service shall pay a fee of ten thousand rupees for
every inspection under these rules.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Where the inspecting authority is an officer subordinate to the
Director-General, the recruitment and placement service shall remit the fee
referred to in sub-rule (5) by way of crossed demand draft drawn on a scheduled
bank and payable at the seamen’s employment office concerned: 
 


 Provided
that where an inspecting authority is an authority other than an officer
subordinate to the Director-General, the fees shall be directly paid to such
authority.
 



 
  


</section></article> 

 <title></title>
  
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>4</number> Recruitment and placement service licence. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A recruitment and placement service registered in India may apply for a recruitment and placement licence to the seamen's employment office concerned in Form I: 
 Provided that the Director shall examine the report of the inspecting authority and issue the licence on authorisation by the Director-General: 
 Provided further that the Director-General may authorise the Director to issue a licence after any inspection carried out under sub-rule (3) of rule 3. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A recruitment and placement service licence and such number of attested copies thereof equal to the number of branch offices of the recruitment and placement service shall be issued in Form II. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> An application for licence shall be accompanied by— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a declaration in Form III; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a fee for twenty thousand rupees drawn in favour of the Director concerned by way of crossed demand draft; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a copy of the employment contract entered into between the employer and the seafarer; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> a statement of qualification and experience of the management personnel in Form VIII; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>e</number> a copy of the agreement between the recruitment and placement service and the employer or the ship owner as the case may be, in Form IX;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> such number of bank guarantees as required under sub-rule (12). 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> The contract and the agreement referred to in clause (c) and clause (e) of sub-rule (3) shall make provision for the repatriation of a stranded seafarer, his maintenance and the transportation of the mortal remains of an expired seafarer. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> A licence shall be issued for a period not exceeding five years. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> An application for renewal of licence shall be in Form VI and shall be accompanied by— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> declaration in Form III; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a fee of ten thousand rupees in favour of the Director concerned by way of crossed demand draft; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a copy of the employment contract entered into between the employer and the seafarer; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> a statement of qualification and experience of the management personnel in Form VIII; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>e</number> a copy of the agreement between the recruitment and placement service and the employer or the ship owner as the case may be, in Form IX;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> such number of bank guarantees as required under sub-rule (12). 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>7</number> The contract and the agreement referred to in clause (c) and clause (e) of sub-rule (6) shall make provision for the repatriation of a stranded seafarer, his maintenance and the transportation of the mortal remains of an expired seafarer. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> An application for renewal of licence shall be submitted by a recruitment and placement service before three months of the date of expiry of such licence. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The licence issued under these rules shall not be transferable. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> The recruitment and placement service shall, from time to time, intimate the Director any change in the place of business within seven days of such change and apply for a fresh licence on payment of a fee of five thousand rupees in the manner specified in sub-rule (3). 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The licence shall be prominently displayed at the premises of the recruitment and placement service at a place accessible to public. 
 </section><section><number>12</number> The bank guarantee referred to in clause (f) of sub-rule (3) or in clause (f) of sub-rule (6) shall be in accordance with the Table below:— 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[TABLE 
 
 
  Sl. No.
  Number of jobs
  Amount of bank guarantee in Indian Rupees

 
  1  2  3  4  5  6
  upto 50  51 to 250  251 to 500  501 to 750  751 to 1000  1001 and above
  5.00 lakhs  7.50 lakhs  10.00 lakhs  12.50 lakhs  15.00 lakhs  20.00 lakhs


  
 </section><section><number>13</number> The bank guarantee shall be drawn in favour of the seamen's employment office, which shall be drawn on a scheduled bank in India. 
 </section><section><number>14</number> A bank guarantee shall be in the denomination commensurate with the number of jobs and shall be valid at all times. 
 </section><section><number>15</number> In the event of any change in the number of jobs, the recruitment and placement service may furnish the requisite bank guarantee within a period of one month from the date of such change. 
 </section><section><number>16</number> Without prejudice to the foregoing sub-rules, the recruitment and placement service shall ensure that a seafarer with whom an employment agreement is entered into is placed on board a ship. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>17</number> In the event of any change in the agreement between the recruitment and placement service and the employer or the ship owner, as the case may be, or in the event of any new agreement with any other employer or ship owner, the recruitment and placement service shall, within seven days thereof, intimate the same of the Director along with the copy of the amended agreement, or new agreement, as the case may be.] 





 
 
  Sl. no. 
   Number of jobs 
  Amount of bank guarantee in Indian Rupees 

 
  1
 2
 3
 4
 5
 6
 7
 8
 9
 10
 11
  upto 50 
 51 to 100 
 101 to 150 
 151 to 200 
 201 to 250 
 251 to 300 
 301 to 350 
 351 to 400 
 401 to 450 
 451 to 500 
 501 and above 
  5 lakhs 
 10 lakhs  
        15 lakhs 
      
 20 lakhs 
 25 lakhs 
 30 lakhs 
 35 lakhs 
 40 lakhs 
 45 lakhs 
 50 lakhs 
 60 lakhs” 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Functions of seamen’s employment office.—
<section><number>1</number>
The seamen’s employment office shall— 
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
issue or renew a licence referred to in rule 4 on receipt of
authorisation from the Director-General; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
maintain a register of licence and to assign distinct licence numbers and
to display the details of licence on the website; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
maintain a register of recruitment and placement service to whom licence
is rejected, or suspended or cancelled and the details thereof and display it on
website;  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
maintain the details of complaints received from seafarers concerning
working or living conditions on board a ship; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
refer, where required, the complaints concerning the activities of the
recruitment and placement service from seafarers to the advisory board; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
maintain details of information received in cases of death or disability
of seafarers; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
maintain registers of seafarers in respect of various categories of
seafarers;  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
maintain a register for <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[quarterly
reports] received from the recruitment and placement service in Form IV; 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where the recruitment and placement service fails to repatriate the seafarer in
the event of his being stranded or fails to transport the mortal remains of an
expired seafarer, the bank guarantee may be utilised by the seamen’s
employment office for the aforesaid purposes and also for the maintenance of the
stranded seafarer.
 


   






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>5</number>
Functions of seamen’s employment office.—
<section><number>1</number>
The seamen’s employment office shall— 
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
issue or renew a licence referred to in rule 4 on receipt of
authorisation from the Director-General; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
maintain a register of licence and to assign distinct licence numbers and
to display the details of licence on the website; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
maintain a register of recruitment and placement service to whom licence
is rejected, or suspended or cancelled and the details thereof and display it on
website;  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
maintain the details of complaints received from seafarers concerning
working or living conditions on board a ship; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number>
refer, where required, the complaints concerning the activities of the
recruitment and placement service from seafarers to the advisory board; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number>
maintain details of information received in cases of death or disability
of seafarers; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>
maintain registers of seafarers in respect of various categories of
seafarers;  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number>
maintain a register for <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[quarterly
reports] received from the recruitment and placement service in Form IV; 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Where the recruitment and placement service fails to repatriate the seafarer in
the event of his being stranded or fails to transport the mortal remains of an
expired seafarer, the bank guarantee may be utilised by the seamen’s
employment office for the aforesaid purposes and also for the maintenance of the
stranded seafarer.
 


   






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>6</number>
Suspension or withdrawal of recruitment and placement service licence.—
<section><number>1</number>
On a report by the inspecting authority or a complaint by a seafarer or
otherwise, the Director-General may authorise the Director to issue a notice in
Form VII to the recruitment and placement service requiring it to show cause
within a period of thirty days from the date of issue of such notice as to why
the licence shall not be suspended or withdrawn.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Director-General, after considering the reply to the show-cause notice,
shall as soon as possible but not later than thirty days from the date of
receipt of reply, if any, authorise the Director to pass such order of
suspension or withdrawal as he deems fit and communicate the same to the
recruitment and placement service and forward a copy thereof alongwith a
detailed report to the Central Government forthwith. 
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Every order passed under sub-rule (2) shall be self-contained and give reasons
for the conclusions stated therein for suspension or withdrawal of licence. 
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>7</number>
Appeal.—Any person aggrieved of an
order under rule 6 may within thirty days of the date of receipt of such order
appeal to the Central Government, which shall pass an order thereon within
thirty days from the date of receipt of such appeal.
 



 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article><number>8</number>
Transitional provision.—Notwithstanding
anything contained in the foregoing rules, a person, company, institution,
agency or other organization in the public or private sector which is engaged in
recruiting seafarers on behalf of employers or placing seafarers with employers
may obtain a licence within <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[one
year] from the date of commencement of these rules: 
 


 Provided
that a person, company, institution, agency or other organisation in the public
or private sector may continue to function as such till such person, company,
institution, agency or other organization obtains a licence under these rules. 
 


  
  




 



</article><form>
 

The Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005
 

 
 

FORM I
 

APPLICATION FOR 
RECRUITMENT AND PLACEMENT SERVICE LICENCE
 


[See rule 4(1)]
 


1.   Name       
 


2.   Status (person/company/institution/agency or other organisation)
 


3.   Date of incorporation                   
 


4.   Name, designation and address of
 


      the authorised signatories 
 


5.   Telephone Number 
 


6.   Fax Number 
 


7.   Website and e-mail id. 
 


8.   (a) Registered Office Address 
 


      (b) Address of all branches
 


9.   Whether the office is owned/leased/hired 
 


10. Residential address of the authorized signatories 
 


11.     Name and address of all the Bankers
 


12. Permanent income-tax number and GIR No., if applicable (enclose a copy of 
the previous  years’ income-tax returns)
 


13. Details of Business during the last five years—enclose Profit and Loss 
Account and Balance sheet 
 


14. Experience, if any, in recruitment of seafarer, number of years 
 


15. Whether any authorised signatory has been associated with any recruiting 
agency in the past if so, give details
 


 16.    If previously in the business of recruitment of seafarers total number 
of seafarers deployed year-wise, country-wise and category-wise during the last 
five years
 


17. Whether there are any complaints pending in respect of seafarers recruited, 
if so, details thereof
 


18. Whether there is any criminal or civil case pending in any court. If so, 
details thereof
 


19. Whether any authorised signatory has been convicted. If so, details thereof
 


20. Total number of agreements/contracts with employer with details thereof
 


21. Number of seafarers proposed to be recruited
 


22. Other Shipping related activities carried out, if any
 

Undertaking
 

      I/we undertake that all 
that are stated above are true and correct to the best of my/our knowledge, 
information and belief and in the event of any of the information furnished 
above is found false or incorrect in any respect, I/we shall abide by any 
decision of the Director, seamen’s employment office.
 

 
 


Date........................     Name and designation of the applicant 
 


                                                            Seal 
 

 
 

List of enclosures— 
 

         (i)  Prescribed fee

 

        (ii)  Agreement with 
the ship owner/ employer
 

        (iii)  Copy of 
certificate of incorporation 
 

       (iv)  Profit and Loss 
Account &amp; Balance sheet for last five years
 

        (v)  Certificate of 
the assets and liabilities by a chartered accountant 
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005
 

 
 

FORM II
 


RECRUITMENT AND PLACEMENT SERVICE LICENCE
 

 [see
rule 4(2)]
 


1.   Name of the Recruitment and Placement Service 
..............................................
 


2.   Address of the registered office   
..............................................
 


3.   Address of branch(s)       ..............................................
 


4.   Status (person/company/institution/agency  

or other organization.)                                        
..............................................
 


5.   Licence number    ..............................................
 



 

This is to certify that the 
....................................................has presented the requisite 
documents and has complied with the procedures prescribed under rules 3 and 4 of 
the Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005. 
 

 Subject to the conditions 
referred to in the rules, and unless the licence is suspended or withdrawn in 
writing, this licence is valid from 
.........................to.........................
 

 
 

Date.........................
 



 


Signature of the Director, 
 


    Seamen’s Employment Office
 


Stamp &amp; Seal
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005
 

 
 

FORM V
 


REPORT OF DEATH OR DISABILITY OF A SEAFARER 

 

[See rule 3(1)(j)]
 


1.   Name of seafarer                                       : 
 


2.   Sex                                                             : 
 


3.   Age                                                             :
 


4.   Date of Birth                                               :
 


5.   CDC No.                                                      :
 


6.   COC details, where applicable                   :
 


7.   Next-of-kin details                                      :
 

        (a)  
Name                                                   :
 

        (b)  
Relationship                                         :
 


        (c)  Address, Tel. No. and E-mail/Fax  

address                                                : 
 


8.   Nature of accident/incident including  

damages/casualties suffered (use  

additional sheet if required)                       : 
 


9.   Details of ship involved in marine  

casualty/incident                                        :
 

        (a)  Name of Ship and 
IMO No.                   :
 

        (b)  
Tonnage                                               :
 

        (c)  Location of 
ship                                    :
 

        (d)  
Flag                                                      :
 

        (e)  Coastal state(s) 
involved                     :
 

         (f)  Name of P&amp;I 
club                                  :
 

        (g)  Name of 
Captain                                  :
 

        (h)  Details of 
owners                                 :
 


10. Details of recruitment and placement  

service in India                                           :
 

        (a)  
Name                                                   :
 


        (b)  Address, Tel. No. and E-mail/Fax  

address                                                :
 

        (c)  Licence 
No.                                           : 
 


11. Details of Assistance given to the  

seafarer                                                     : 
 


12. Insurance Coverage of the seafarer          : 
 



 


Place......................                                         Name and 
Designation of  

                                                                        
Authorised Signatory  

Date......................                                           Signature 
and Seal
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005
 

 
 

FORM VI
 


FORM OF APPLICATION FOR RENEWAL OF LICENCE
 

[See rule 4(6)]
 

1.   Name
 


2.   Status [person/company/institution/agency or other organisation]
 


3.   Licence number and date of issue
 


4.   Validity period of licence
 


5.   Total number of seafarers employed during the period of licence – category 
wise Pending complaints of seafarers recruited and if so, details thereof
 


6.   Whether there is any criminal or civil case pending in any court. If so, 
details thereof.
 


7.   Whether any authorised signatory has been convicted
 


      If so, details thereof
 


8.   Details of change of registered office/branch
 


9.   Total number of agreement/contracts signed with employers. Please give the 
details Flag-wise and ownership wise
 

 
 

Undertaking
 

I/We undertake that all that are stated above are true and 
correct to the best of my/our knowledge, information and belief and in the event 
of any of the information furnished above is found false or incorrect in any 
respect, I/We shall abide by any decision of the Director, seamen’s employment 
office.
 

 
 


Date.........................  Name and designation of the applicant 
 


                                                     Seal 
 

List of 
enclosures— 
 

         (i)  Prescribed fee 
 

        (ii)  Agreement with the ship owner/ employer
 

        (iii)  Copy of certificate of incorporation 
 

       (iv)  Profit and Loss Account &amp; Balance sheet for 
last five years
 

        (v)  Certificate of the assets and liabilities by a 
chartered accountant 
</form><form>
 

The Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005
 

 
 

FORM VII
 


SHOW CAUSE NOTICE TO RECRUITMENT AND  

PLACEMENT SERVICE
 

[See 
rule 6(1)]
 

To
 

..........................................
 

..........................................
 

Sir,
 

Whereas ................................................. a 
Recruitment and Placement Service has been issued a licence bearing 
number..................for the period................to.......... by the 
Director, Seamen’s Employment Office under Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005.
 

2. Whereas ................................................. 
has failed to comply with the following provisions for the following reasons:—
 

      (a)
 

      (b)
 

      (c)
 

      (d)
 

Now, therefore, the Director 
Seamen’s Employment Office under rule 6 of the Merchant Shipping (Recruitment 
and Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005 directs............... 
.....................to show cause as to why the Recruitment and Placement 
Service Licence bearing No. .............................. should not be 
suspended/withdrawn.
 



 

Yours faithfully,
 


Director SEO
 

Place......................
 

Date......................
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005
 

 
 

FORM VIII
 


QUALIFICATION AND EXPERIENCE OF MANAGEMENT 
PERSONNEL
 

[See rule 
4(3)(d) and 4(6)(d)]
 

Name of the Recruitment and Placement Service 
.................................................................
 

Address.................................................................................................................................
 

1.   
Designation........................................Name........................................................................
 

      
Responsibilities....................................................................................................................
 

      
Educational 
Qualification......................................................................................................
 

      
Professional 
Qualification.....................................................................................................
 

      
Experience............................................................................................................................
 


2.   
Designation........................................Name.........................................................................
 


      
Responsibilities....................................................................................................................
 


      Educational 
Qualification......................................................................................................
 


      Professional 
Qualification......................................................................................................
 


      
Experience............................................................................................................................
 


3.   
Designation........................................Name.........................................................................
 


      
Responsibilities....................................................................................................................
 


      Educational 
Qualification......................................................................................................
 


      Professional 
Qualification.....................................................................................................
 


      
Experience............................................................................................................................
 


4.   
Designation........................................Name........................................................................
 


      
Responsibilities....................................................................................................................
 


      Educational 
Qualification.....................................................................................................
 


      Professional 
Qualification.....................................................................................................
 


      
Experience............................................................................................................................
 


5.   Designation: Medical Officer 
Name.......................................................................................
 


      
Qualification.........................................................................................................................
 


      
Experience...........................................................................................................................
 

      DGS 
Approval 
No..................................................................................................................
 

 
</form><form>
 

The Merchant Shipping (Recruitment and 
Placement of Seafarers) Rules, 2005
 

 
 


1[FORM IX
 

Agreement between 
recruitment and placement service  

and the Employer/ship owner
 

Name, Address and full style of 
the employer/Ship owner:
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 

Name, address and full style of 
the recruitment and placement service:
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 


....................................................................................................................................................
 

Whereas the above-named 
recruitment and placement service has entered into an agreement with the 
above-named employer/ship owner for the recruitment and placement of seafarers 
on board for and on behalf of the employer as agent only.
 

The employer/ship owner undertakes to repatriate the seafarers 
so employed if stranded at any place as well as to look after his reasonable 
maintenance and to transport the mortal remains of the seafarer, if permissible 
under local laws, in case of death.
 

Signed, stamped and delivered:
 

(For and on behalf of the employer/ship owner)
 

Signed, stamped and delivered:
 

(For and on behalf of the 
recruitment and placement service)]
 


 
 


—————
 


      1.   Ins. by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 14th September, 2005 (w.e.f. 14-9-2005).
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 14th September, 2005, for clause (e) (w.e.f. 14-9-2005). Clause (e), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 14th September, 2005, for Table (w.e.f. 14-9-2005). Table , before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. By G.S.R. 318(E), dated 30 th April, 2007 (w.e.f. 30-4-2007).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 14th September, 2005, for “monthly
reports” (w.e.f. 14-9-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 14th September, 2005, for “monthly
reports” (w.e.f. 14-9-2005).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 14th September, 2005, for “six
months” (w.e.f. 14-9-2005).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>