<act> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 20031
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
  


</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>        <number>a</number>   “Act” means the Wild Life (Protection) Act, 
1972 (53 of 1972);
 </section><section>        <number>b</number>   “National Board” means the National Board for 
Wild Life constituted under section 5A of the Act;
 </section><section>        <number>c</number>   “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the 
National Board;
 </section><section>        <number>d</number>   all other words and expressions used in these 
rules shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>3</number> National Board for Wild 
Life.—
<section><number>1</number> The National Board shall be 
constituted in accordance with the provisions contained in sub‑section (1) of 
section 5A of the Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The term of office of the 
members other than those who are members ex‑officio shall be for a period 
of three years.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Member of Parliament 
nominated to the National Board shall cease to be the Member of the National 
Board on his having ceased to the Member of Parliament.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The vacancies referred to in 
clauses (e), (f) and (v) of sub‑section (1) of section 5A of the Act shall be 
filled by nomination by the Central Government with the approval of Chairperson.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>4</number> Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The National Board shall ordinarily meet once in a year at a place to be decided 
with the approval of the Chairperson.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Member‑Secretary shall 
prepare agenda items for the meetings, obtain approval of the Chairperson and 
circulate it to all members at least fifteen days prior to the date of such 
meeting.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Member‑Secretary shall 
prepare the minutes of the meeting and circulate it to all members within thirty 
days of the meeting after obtaining approval of the Chairperson.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Member‑Secretary shall 
also initiate follow up action on the decisions of the National Board.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>5</number> Removal from the National 
Board.—The Central Government may, 
with the prior approval of the Chairperson, remove any member of the National 
Board appointed under clauses (e), (f) and (v) of sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 5A 
of the Act, if—
 <subsection>        <number>a</number>   he is of unsound mind and stands so declared 
by a competent court; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>b</number>   he is an undischarged insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>c</number>   he is convicted of any offence including moral 
turpitude; or
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>d</number>   his conduct is found to be unbecoming of a 
member.
</subsection></section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>6</number> Disclosure of interest by 
members.—If any member of the 
National Board or his family member has any interest in a proposal submitted for 
consideration of the National Board, the member shall disclose the extent of his 
interest in the proposal.
</article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>7</number> Presiding over the 
meetings of the National Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson in the absence the Vice‑Chairperson shall preside at every 
meeting of the National Board.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the absence of both the 
Chairperson and the Vice‑Chairperson, such other member present as is decided by 
the National Board shall preside over the meeting.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>8</number> Quorum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The quorum necessary for the transaction of business at a meeting of the 
National Board shall be one‑half of the total number of members.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If at any time there is no 
quorum, the Chairperson or the person presiding over a meeting shall adjourn the 
meeting until there is a quorum.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>9</number> Invitees to the National 
Board meetings.—The Chairperson of 
the National Board may invite any person or persons having experience in the 
wild life conservation to attend any meeting of the National Board.
</article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>10</number> Record of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The record of business transaction at every meeting of the National Board shall 
be prepared by the Member‑Secretary for approval by the Chairperson or the 
Member presiding at such meeting.
 </section><section><number>2</number> When any business is 
transacted by circulation of papers, the Member- Secretary shall prepare a 
record of the business so transacted for approval by the Chairperson of the 
National Board permitting the circulation.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The record of business 
transacted at every meeting of the National Board shall be approved and signed 
by the Chairperson or the Vice-Chairperson or the member presiding at such 
meeting, and the approved record of business shall be circulated to all the 
members.
 </section><section><number>4</number> All records shall be 
maintained by the Member‑Secretary of items of business transacted by the 
National Board or the committees, sub­-committees or sub‑groups thereof.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>11</number> Appointment of 
Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> The National Board 
may, constitute a Standing Committee and such other committees or study groups, 
as may be necessary, in accordance with the provisions contained in section 5B 
of the Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The National Board shall 
determine the terms of reference, tenure, membership and other related aspects 
as may be necessary in respect of the committees constituted under sub‑rule (1) 
of this rule.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>12</number> Travelling and other 
allowances to members of the National Board and its committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A member of the National Board or any committee other than members ex‑officio, 
shall be entitled to receive, in respect of any journey performed by him for the 
purpose of attending a meeting of the National Board or of a duly constituted 
committee thereof or for the purpose of discharging any duty assigned to him by 
the National Board or the committee concerned, travelling allowances and daily 
allowances at the rates as are admissible to the Group ‘A’ officers of the 
Central Government for the time being in force.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No travelling allowance or 
daily allowance shall be allowed to a member of the National Board or of any 
committee unless he certifies that he has not drawn any travelling or daily 
allowance from, any other source in respect of the journey and halt for which 
the claim is made.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The travelling allowance 
shall be payable from the usual place of residence of a member of the National 
Board or any of the committee to the place of the meeting or the place where he 
has gone to attend to any business of the National Board and back to his place 
of residence.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In special circumstances, 
the Chairperson may grant travelling allowance from the places other than usual 
place of residence of a member.
</section></article> 
 The National Board for Wild Life Rules, 2003
  
 <article><number>13</number> Interpretation of 
rules.—Where any doubt arises as to 
the interpretation of these rules, interpretation shall be referred to the 
Central Government for its decision.</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>