<act><tid>1902628</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN RAILWAY COMPANIES ACT, <year>1895</year></title>

ACT NO. 10 OF <year>1895</year>
[ 7th March, <year>1895</year>.] WH

An Act to provide for the payment by Railway Companies registered 
under the Indian Companies Act, <year>1882</year>, of interest out of capital 
during construction.





<article><tid>1626049</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title and extent.
<section><tid>776795</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Indian  
Railway Companies Act, <year>1895</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>586599</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States]. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1158394</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is something repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>327804</tid>
<number>1</number>" railway" means a railway as defined in section 3, 
clause (4), of the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of  
  <year>1890</year>.):

</section>

<section><tid>966509</tid>
<number>2</number>" the railway" means the railway in relation to the 
construction of which interest out of capital is 
permitted to be paid as hereinafter provided: and

</section>

<section><tid>920207</tid>
<number>3</number>" Railway Company" means a Company registered under the 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Indian Companies Act, <year>1882</year> (6 of <year>1882</year>.), and formed 
for the purpose of making and working, or making or 
working, a railway in India, whether alone or in 
conjunction with other purposes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1072731</tid>
<number> 3</number> Payment of interest out of capital. A Railway Company may pay 
interest on its paid- up share capital out of capital, for the period, 
and subject to the conditions and restrictions, in this section 
mentioned, and may charge the same to capital as part of the cost of 
construction of the railway:--
<section><tid>65338</tid>
<number>1</number>Such interest shall be paid only for such period as 
shall be determined by the Central Government; and such 
period
The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

Extonded to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli (w. e. f.  
  1- 7- 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>116</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been rep. by the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> (7 of  
  <year>1913</year>), which has also been rep. by the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>). 
2 Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
3 The word" and" at the end of sub- section (2) and sub- section (3) 
rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II. 
4 See now the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


shall in no case extend beyond the close of the half- 
year next after the half- year during which the railway 
shall be actually completed and opened for traffic.


</section>

<section><tid>1046404</tid>
<number>2</number>No such payment shall be made unless the same is 
authorised by the Company' s memorandum of association 
or by a special resolution of the Company.

</section>

<section><tid>841987</tid>
<number>3</number>No such payment, whether authorised by the Company' s 
memorandum of association or by special resolution as 
aforesaid, shall be made without the previous sanction 
of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>827910</tid>
<number>4</number>The amount so paid out of capital by way of interest, in 
respect of any period, shall in no case exceed a sum 
which shall, together with the net earnings of the 
railway during such period, make up the rate of four 
per cent. per annum.

</section>

<section><tid>829739</tid>
<number>5</number>No such payment of interest shall be made until such 
Railway Company has satisfied the Central Government 
that two- thirds at least of its share capital, in 
respect whereof interest is to be so paid, has been 
actually issued and accepted, and is held by 
shareholders who, or whose representatives, are legally 
liable for the same.

</section>

<section><tid>118208</tid>
<number>6</number>No such interest shall accrue in favour of any 
shareholder for any time during which any call on any 
of his shares is in arrear.

</section>

<section><tid>5341</tid>
<number>7</number>The payment of such interest shall not operate as a 
reduction of the amount paid up on the shares in 
respect of which it is paid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>918583</tid>
<number>4</number>Provisions of section 3 applicable to additional share capital 
for extensions. A railway in course of construction and intended to be 
made or worked by a Railway Company in addition to or way of extentsion 
of any railway owned or worked by such Company shall be deemed to be 
the railway of such Company for the purposes of this Act, and all the 
provisions of the last preceding section shall apply to such railway 
and to the share capital issued for the purpose of its construction.


</article>



<article><tid>489208</tid>
<number>5</number>Notice in prospectus and other documents. When a Railway 
Company has power to pay interest under this Act, notice to that 
effect shall be given in every prospectus, advertisement or other 
document inviting subscriptions for shares therein, and in every 
certificate of such shares.


</article>



<article><tid>541977</tid>
<number>6</number>Accounts. When any interest has been paid by a Railway Company 
under this Act, the annual or other accounts of such company shall 
show the amount on which, and the rate at which, interest has been so 
paid.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>117</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>226423</tid>
<number>7</number>Construction of borrowing powers. If by any memorandum of 
association, articles of association or other document any power of 
borrowing money is conferred on a Railway Company, or on its 
Directors, with or without the sanction of any meeting, and if such 
power of borrowing is limited to an amount bearing any proportion to 
the capital of such Company, the amount of capital applied or to be 
applied in payment of interest under this Act shall, for the purpose 
of ascertaining the extent of such power of borrowing, be deducted 
from the capital of such Company.
</article>



 </act>