<act><tid>19033</tid>
<title>THE PRE- NATAL DIAGNOSTIC TECHNIQUES (REGULATION AND PREVENTION  
  OF MISUSE) AMENDMENT ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 14 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 17th January, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques 
 (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) Act, <year>1994</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>330603</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1852221</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) 
Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1540765</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1021849</tid>
<number>2</number>Substitution of long title.- In the Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques 
 (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) Act, <year>1994</year> (57 of <year>1994</year>) 
 (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), for the long title, 
the following long title shall be substituted, namely:-
" An Act to provide for the prohibition of sex selection, before or 
after conception, and for regulation of pre- natal diagnostic 
techniques for the purposes of detecting genetic abnormalities or 
metabolic disorders or chromosomal abnormalities or cert in congenital 
malformations or sex- linked disorders and for the prevention of their 
misuse for sex determination leading to female foeticide and for 
matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.".



</article>



<article><tid>1995216</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 1.- In section 1 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the words and brackets" the Pre- natal Diagnostic 
Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse)", the words and 
brackets" the Pre- conception and Pre- natal Diagno tic Techniques 
 (Prohibition of Sex Selection)" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1760395</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>710451</tid>
<number>i</number>after clause (b), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (ba)" conceptus" means any product of conception at any stage of 
development from fertilisation until birth including extra embryonic 
membranes as well as the embryo or foetus;


<subsection><tid>360893</tid>
<number>bb</number>" embryo" means a developing human organism after fertilisation 
till the end of eight weeks (fifty- six days);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1840904</tid>
<number>bc</number>" foetus" means a human organism during the period of its 
development beginning on the fifty- seventh day following fertilisation 
or creation (excluding any time in which its development has been  
  suspended) and ending at the birth;';

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1691257</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (d), the following Explanation shall be added, namely:-
' Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause," Genetic Clinic" 
includes a vehicle, where ultrasound machine or imaging machine or 
scanner or other equipment capable of determining sex of the foetus or 
a portable equipment which has the potential for det ction of sex 
during pregnancy or selection of sex before conception, is used;';


</section>

<section><tid>475098</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (e), the following Explanation shall be added, 
namely:-
' Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause," Genetic Laboratory" 
includes a place where ultrasound machine or imaging machine or 
scanner or other equipment capable of determining sex of the foetus or 
a portable equipment which has the potential for de ection of sex 
during pregnancy or selection of sex before conception, is used;';


</section>

<section><tid>286790</tid>
<number>iv</number>for clause (g), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (g)" medical geneticist" includes a person who possesses a degree or 
diploma in genetic science in the fields of sex selection and 
pre- natal diagnostic techniques or has experience of not less than two 
years in any of these fields after obtaining-


</section>

<section><tid>710451</tid>
<number>i</number>any one of the medical qualifications recognised under the Indian 
Medical Council Act, <year>1956</year> (102 of <year>1956</year>); or

</section>

<section><tid>1691257</tid>
<number>ii</number>a post- graduate degree in biological sciences;';

</section>

<section><tid>651588</tid>
<number>v</number>for clause (i), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (i)" pre- natal diagnostic procedures" means all gynaecological or 
obstetrical or medical procedures such as ultrasonography, foetoscopy, 
taking or removing samples of amniotic fluid, chorionic villi, embryo, 
blood or any other tissue or fluid of a man, or of a woman before or 
after conception, for being sent to a Genetic Laboratory or Genetic 
Clinic for conducting any type of analysis or pre- natal diagnostic 
tests for selection of sex before or after conception;';


</section>

<section><tid>30593</tid>
<number>vi</number>for clause (k), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (k)" pre- natal diagnostic test" means ultrasonography or any test or 
analysis of amniotic fluid, chorionic villi, blood or any tissue or 
fluid of a pregnant woman or conceptus conducted to detect genetic or 
metabolic disorders or chromosomal abnormaliti s or congenital 
anomalies or haemoglobinopathies or sex- linked diseases;';


</section>

<section><tid>731445</tid>
<number>vii</number>after clause (n), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (o)" sex selection" includes any procedure, technique, test or 
administration or prescription or provision of anything for the 
purpose of ensuring or increasing the probability that an embryo will 
be of a particular sex;


<subsection><tid>439179</tid>
<number>p</number>" sonologist or imaging specialist" means a person who possesses 
any one of the medical qualifications recognised under the Indian 
Medical Council Act, <year>1956</year> (102 of <year>1956</year>) or who possesses a 
post- graduate qualification in ultrasonography or imaging tec niques 
or radiology;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>595607</tid>
<number>q</number>" State Board" means a State Supervisory Board or a Union territory 
Supervisory Board constituted under section 16A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776956</tid>
<number>r</number>" State Government" in relation to Union territory with Legislature 
means the Administrator of that Union territory appointed by the 
President under article 239 of the Constitution.'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1064512</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act, for 
clause (2), the following clause shall be substituted, namely:-
" (2) no Genetic Counselling Centre or Genetic Laboratory or Genetic 
Clinic shall employ or cause to be employed or take services of any 
person, whether on honorary basis or on payment who does not possess 
the qualifications as may be prescribed.".



</article>



<article><tid>835478</tid>
<number>6</number>Insertion of new sections 3A and 3B.- After section 3 of the 
principal Act, the following sections shall be inserted, namely:-
" 3A. Prohibition of sex selection.- No person, including a specialist 
or a team of specialists in the field of infertility, shall conduct or 
cause to be conducted or aid in conducting by himself or by any other 
person, sex selection on a woman or a man or on both or on any tissue, 
embryo, conceptus, fluid or gametes derived from either or both of 
them.

</article>



<article><tid>743011</tid>
<number>3B</number>Prohibition of ultrasound machine, etc., to persons, 
laboratories, clinics, etc., not registered under the Act.- No person 
shall sell any ultrasound machine or imaging machine or scanner or any 
other equipment capable of detecting sex of the foetus t any Genetic 
Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic or any other 
person not registered under the Act.".


</article>



<article><tid>136242</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act, for 
clauses (3) and (4), the following clauses shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (3) no pre- natal diagnostic techniques shall be used or conducted 
unless the person qualified to do so is satisfied for reasons to be 
recorded in writing that any of the following conditions are 
fulfilled, namely:-

<section><tid>1613945</tid>
<number>i</number>age of the pregnant woman is above thirty- five years;

</section>

<section><tid>753871</tid>
<number>ii</number>the pregnant woman has undergone two or more spontaneous 
abortions or foetal loss;

</section>

<section><tid>1891776</tid>
<number>iii</number>the pregnant woman had been exposed to potentially teratogenic 
agents such as drugs, radiation, infection or chemicals;

</section>

<section><tid>1596832</tid>
<number>iv</number>the pregnant woman or her spouse has a family history of mental 
retardation or physical deformities such as, spasticity or any other 
genetic disease;

</section>

<section><tid>1894388</tid>
<number>v</number>any other condition as may be specified by the Board:
Provided that the person conducting ultrasonography on a pregnant 
woman shall keep complete record thereof in the clinic in such manner, 
as may be prescribed, and any deficiency or inaccuracy found therein 
shall amount to contravention of the provisions f section 5 or section 
 6 unless contrary is proved by the person conducting such 
ultrasonography;


<subsection><tid>513423</tid>
<number>4</number>no person including a relative or husband of the pregnant woman 
shall seek or encourage the conduct of any pre- natal diagnostic 
techniques on her except for the purposes specified in clause (2);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>956378</tid>
<number>5</number>no person including a relative or husband of a woman shall seek or 
encourage the conduct of any sex selection technique on her or him or 
both.".



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>733472</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (2) No person including the person conducting pre- natal diagnostic 
procedures shall communicate to the pregnant woman concerned or her 
relatives or any other person the sex of the foetus by words, signs, 
or in any other manner.".



</article>



<article><tid>1269777</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of section 6.- In section 6 of the principal Act, after 
clause (b), the following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (c) no person shall, by whatever means, cause or allow to be caused 
selection of sex before or after conception.".



</article>



<article><tid>784289</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of section 7.- In section 7 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1208772</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (2), for clause (c), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (c) three members to be appointed by the Central Government to 
represent the Ministries of Central Government in charge of Women and 
Child Development, Department of Legal Affairs or Legislative 
Department in the Ministry of Law and Justice, and Indian ystem of 
Medicine and Homoeopathy, ex officio;";


</section>

<section><tid>1270073</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (e), for sub- clause (ii), the following sub- clause 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" (ii) eminent gynaecologist and obstetrician or expert of stri- roga or 
prasuti- tantra.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1158727</tid>
<number>11</number>Amendment of section 14.- In section 14 of the principal Act, for 
clause (f), the following clause shall be substituted, namely:-
" (f) has, in the opinion of the Central Government, been associated 
with the use or promotion of pre- natal diagnostic technique for 
determination of sex or with any sex selection technique.".



</article>



<article><tid>223219</tid>
<number>12</number>Amendment of section 15.- In section 15 of the principal Act, the 
following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that no member other than an ex officio member shall be 
appointed for more than two consecutive terms.".



</article>



<article><tid>626993</tid>
<number> 13</number> Substitution of new section for section 16.- For section 16 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 16. Functions of the Board.- The Board shall have the following 
functions, namely:-

<section><tid>180676</tid>
<number>i</number>to advise the Central Government on policy matters relating to use 
of pre- natal diagnostic techniques, sex selection techniques and 
against their misuse;

</section>

<section><tid>585962</tid>
<number>ii</number>to review and monitor implementation of the Act and rules made 
thereunder and recommend to the Central Government changes in the said 
Act and rules;

</section>

<section><tid>483668</tid>
<number>iii</number>to create public awareness against the practice of 
pre- conception sex selection and pre- natal determination of sex of 
foetus leading to female foeticide;

</section>

<section><tid>1059457</tid>
<number>iv</number>to lay down code of conduct to be observed by persons working at 
Genetic Counselling Centres, Genetic Laboratories and Genetic Clinics;

</section>

<section><tid>1674893</tid>
<number>v</number>to oversee the performance of various bodies constituted under the 
Act and take appropriate steps to ensure its proper and effective 
implementation;

</section>

<section><tid>1808798</tid>
<number>vi</number>any other functions as may be prescribed under the Act.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>827840</tid>
<number> 14</number> Insertion of new section 16A.- After section 16 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 16A. Constitution of State Supervisory Board and Union territory 
Supervisory Board.- (1) Each State and Union territory having 
Legislature shall constitute a Board to be known as the State 
Supervisory Board or the Union territory Supervisory Board, as th case 
may be, which shall have the following functions:-

<section><tid>1045660</tid>
<number>i</number>to create public awareness against the practice of pre- conception 
sex selection and pre- natal determination of sex of the foetus leading 
to female foeticide in the State;

</section>

<section><tid>1349563</tid>
<number>ii</number>to review the activities of the Appropriate Authorities 
functioning in the State and recommend appropriate action against 
them;

</section>

<section><tid>1948704</tid>
<number>iii</number>to monitor the implementation of provisions of the Act and the 
rules and make suitable recommendations relating thereto, to the 
Board;

</section>

<section><tid>1694258</tid>
<number>iv</number>to send such consolidated reports as may be prescribed in respect 
of the various activities undertaken in the State under the Act to the 
Board and the Central Government; and

</section>

<section><tid>301315</tid>
<number>v</number>any other functions as may be prescribed under the Act.

<subsection><tid>1088716</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Board shall consist of,-

<subsubsection><tid>317818</tid>
<number>a</number>the Minister in charge of Health and Family Welfare in the State, 
who shall be the Chairperson, ex officio;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1235215</tid>
<number>b</number>Secretary in charge of the Department of Health and Family Welfare 
who shall be the Vice- Chairperson, ex officio;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1771151</tid>
<number>c</number>Secretaries or Commissioners in charge of Departments of Women and 
Child Development, Social Welfare, Law and Indian System of Medicines 
and Homoeopathy, ex officio, or their representatives;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1259746</tid>
<number>d</number>Director of Health and Family Welfare or Indian System of 
Medicines and Homoeopathy of the State Government, ex officio;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1551491</tid>
<number>e</number>three women members of Legislative Assembly or Legislative 
Council;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>820482</tid>
<number>f</number>ten members to be appointed by the State Government out of which 
two each shall be from the following categories,-

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1045660</tid>
<number>i</number>eminent social scientists and legal experts;

</section>

<section><tid>1349563</tid>
<number>ii</number>eminent women activists from non- governmental organisations or 
otherwise;

</section>

<section><tid>1948704</tid>
<number>iii</number>eminent gynaecologists and obstetricians or experts of stri- 
roga or prasuti- tantra;

</section>

<section><tid>1694258</tid>
<number>iv</number>eminent paediatricians or medical geneticists;

</section>

<section><tid>301315</tid>
<number>v</number>eminent radiologists or sonologists;

<subsection><tid>1205902</tid>
<number>g</number>an officer not below the rank of Joint Director in charge of 
Family Welfare, who shall be the Member Secretary, ex officio.

<subsubsection><tid>1591593</tid>
<number>3</number>The State Board shall meet at least once in four months.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1894635</tid>
<number>4</number>The term of office of a member, other than an ex officio member, 
shall be three years.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1578224</tid>
<number>5</number>If a vacancy occurs in the office of any member other than an ex 
officio member, it shall be filled by making fresh appointment.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>474046</tid>
<number>6</number>If a member of the Legislative Assembly or member of the 
Legislative Council who is a member of the State Board, becomes 
Minister or Speaker or Deputy Speaker of the Legislative Assembly or 
Chairperson or Deputy Chairperson of the Legislative Council she shall 
cease to be a member of the State Board.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1966126</tid>
<number>7</number>One- third of the total number of members of the State Board shall 
constitute the quorum.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1179846</tid>
<number>8</number>The State Board may co- opt a member as and when required, provided 
that the number of co- opted members does not exceed one- third of the 
total strength of the State Board.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>723177</tid>
<number>9</number>The co- opted members shall have the same powers and functions as 
other members, except the right to vote and shall abide by the rules 
and regulations.

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1580277</tid>
<number>10</number>In respect of matters not specified in this section, the State 
Board shall follow procedures and conditions as are applicable to the 
Board.".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>330649</tid>
<number> 15</number> Amendment of section 17.- In section 17 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1013089</tid>
<number>i</number>in sub- section (3), for clause (a), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (a) when appointed for the whole of the State or the Union territory, 
consisting of the following three members-


</section>

<section><tid>1013089</tid>
<number>i</number>an officer of or above the rank of the Joint Director of Health 
and Family Welfare- Chairperson;

</section>

<section><tid>626677</tid>
<number>ii</number>an eminent woman representing women' s organisation; and

</section>

<section><tid>293424</tid>
<number>iii</number>an officer of Law Department of the State or the Union territory 
concerned:
Provided that it shall be the duty of the State or the Union territory 
concerned to constitute multi- member State or Union territory level 
Appropriate Authority within three months of the coming into force of 
the Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulati n and Prevention of  
  Misuse) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>:

Provided further that any vacancy occurring therein shall be filled 
within three months of the occurrence.";


</section>

<section><tid>626677</tid>
<number>ii</number>in sub- section (4), after clause (d), the following clauses shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (e) to take appropriate legal action against the use of any sex 
selection technique by any person at any place, suo motu or brought to 
its notice and also to initiate independent investigations in such 
matter;


<subsection><tid>1427693</tid>
<number>f</number>to create public awareness against the practice of sex selection 
or pre- natal determination of sex;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1216501</tid>
<number>g</number>to supervise the implementation of the provisions of the Act and 
rules;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1585633</tid>
<number>h</number>to recommend to the Board and State Boards modifications required 
in the rules in accordance with changes in technology or social 
conditions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1744675</tid>
<number>i</number>to take action on the recommendations of the Advisory Committee 
made after investigation of complaint for suspension or cancellation 
of registration.";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>293424</tid>
<number>iii</number>for sub- section (7), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (7) No person who has been associated with the use or promotion of 
pre- natal diagnostic techniques for determination of sex or sex 
selection shall be appointed as a member of the Advisory Committee.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>737525</tid>
<number> 16</number> Insertion of new section 17A.- After section 17 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 17A. Powers of Appropriate Authorities.- The Appropriate Authority 
shall have the powers in respect of the following matters, namely:-

<section><tid>974457</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning of any person who is in possession of any information 
relating to violation of the provisions of this Act or the rules made 
thereunder;

</section>

<section><tid>1477463</tid>
<number>b</number>production of any document or material object relating to clause 
 (a);

</section>

<section><tid>62671</tid>
<number>c</number>issuing search warrant for any place suspected to be indulging in 
sex selection techniques or pre- natal sex determination; and

</section>

<section><tid>1121973</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1293796</tid>
<number>17</number>Amendment of section 18.- In section 18 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) No person shall open any Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic 
Laboratory or Genetic Clinic, including clinic, laboratory or centre 
having ultrasound or imaging machine or scanner or any other 
technology capable of undertaking determination of sex o foetus and 
sex selection, or render services to any of them, after the 
commencement of the Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and  
  Prevention of Misuse) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year> unless such Centre, 
Laboratory or Clinic is duly registered under the Ac.".



</article>



<article><tid>634190</tid>
<number> 18</number> Substitution of new section for section 22.- For section 22 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
' 22. Prohibition of advertisement relating to pre- conception and 
pre- natal determination of sex and punishment for contravention.- (1) 
No person, organisation, Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic 
Laboratory or Genetic Clinic including clinic, laboratory r centre 
having ultrasound machine or imaging machine or scanner or any other 
technology capable of undertaking determination of sex of the foetus 
or sex selection shall issue, publish, distribute, communicate or 
cause to be issued, published, distribu ed or communicated any 
advertisement, in any form, including internet, regarding facilities 
of pre- natal determination of sex or sex selection before conception 
available at such Centre, Laboratory, Clinic or at any other place.

<section><tid>1998510</tid>
<number>2</number>No person or organisation including Genetic Counselling Centre, 
Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic shall issue, publish, distribute, 
communicate or cause to be issued, published, distributed or 
communicated any advertisement in any manner regarding pre- natal 
determination or pre- conception selection of sex by any means 
whatsoever, scientific or otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>674243</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person who contravenes the provisions of sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to three years and with fine which may extend to ten 
thousand rupees.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,'' advertisement'' 
includes any notice, circular, label, wrapper or any other document 
including advertisement through internet or any other media in 
electronic or print form and also includes any visible rep esentation 
made by means of any hoarding, wall- painting, signal, light, sound, 
smoke or gas.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>889549</tid>
<number> 19</number> Amendment of section 23.- In section 23 of the principal Act, for 
sub- sections (2) and (3), the following sub- sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2) The name of the registered medical practitioner shall be reported 
by the Appropriate Authority to the State Medical Council concerned 
for taking necessary action including suspension of the registration 
if the charges are framed by the court and ti l the case is disposed 
of and on conviction for removal of his name from the register of the 
Council for a period of five years for the first offence and 
permanently for the subsequent offence.

<section><tid>876406</tid>
<number>3</number>Any person who seeks the aid of any Genetic Counselling Centre, 
Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic or ultrasound clinic or imaging 
clinic or of a medical geneticist, gynaecologist, sonologist or 
imaging specialist or registered medical practitioner o any other 
person for sex selection or for conducting pre- natal diagnostic 
techniques on any pregnant women for the purposes other than those 
specified in sub- section (2) of section 4, he shall, be punishable 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and with 
fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees for the first offence 
and for any subsequent offence with imprisonment which may extend to 
five years and with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1850126</tid>
<number>4</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby provided that the 
provisions of sub- section (3) shall not apply to the woman who was 
compelled to undergo such diagnostic techniques or such selection.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>231248</tid>
<number>20</number>Substitution of new section for section 24.- For section 24 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 24. Presumption in the case of conduct of pre- natal diagnostic 
techniques.- Notwithstanding anything contained in the Indian Evidence 
Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of <year>1872</year>), the court shall presume unless the contrary is 
proved that the pregnant woman was compelled by he husband or any 
other relative, as the case may be, to undergo pre- natal diagnostic 
technique for the purposes other than those specified in sub- section 
 (2) of section 4 and such person shall be liable for abetment of 
offence under sub- section (3) of sec ion 23 and shall be punishable 
for the offence specified under that section.".



</article>



<article><tid>144220</tid>
<number>21</number>Amendment of section 28.- In section 28 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, in clause (b), for the words" thirty days", the words 
" fifteen days" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>156796</tid>
<number>22</number>Amendment of section 30.- In section 30 of the principal Act, for 
sub- section 1, the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1) If the Appropriate Authority has reason to believe that an 
offence under this Act has been or is being committed at any Genetic 
Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic or any other 
place, such Authority or any officer authorised in t is behalf may, 
subject to such rules as may be prescribed, enter and search at all 
reasonable times with such assistance, if any, as such Authority or 
officer considers necessary, such Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic 
Laboratory, Genetic Clinic or any other place and examine any record, 
register, document, book, pamphlet, advertisement or any other 
material object found therein and seize and seal the same if such 
Authority or officer has reason to believe that it may furnish 
evidence of the commissio of an offence punishable under this Act.".



</article>



<article><tid>387699</tid>
<number> 23</number> Insertion of new section 31A.- After section 31 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 31A. Removal of difficulties.- (1) If any difficulty arises in giving 
effect to the provisions of the Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques 
 (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>, the Central 
Government may, by order published in the Offici l Gazette, make such 
provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of the said Act as 
appear to it to be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:

Provided that no order shall be made under this section after the 
expiry of a period of three years from the date of commencement of the 
Pre- natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) 
Amendment Act, <year>2002</year>.

<section><tid>1231786</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>742438</tid>
<number> 24</number> Amendment of section 32.- In section 32 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>1775810</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (i), the following clauses shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (i) the minimum qualifications for persons employed at a registered 
Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic under 
clause (2) of section 3;


<subsection><tid>417467</tid>
<number>ia</number>the manner in which the person conducting ultrasonography on a 
pregnant woman shall keep record thereof in the clinic under the 
proviso to sub- section (3) of section 4;";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>657626</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (iv), the following clauses shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (iva) code of conduct to be observed by persons working at Genetic 
Counselling Centres, Genetic Laboratories and Genetic Clinics to be 
laid down by the Central Supervisory Board under clause (iv) of 
section 16;


<subsection><tid>1971536</tid>
<number>ivb</number>the manner in which reports shall be furnished by the State and 
Union territory Supervisory Boards to the Board and the Central 
Government in respect of various activities undertaken in the State 
under the Act under clause (iv) of sub- section (1) o section 16A;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1083325</tid>
<number>ivc</number>empowering the Appropriate Authority in any other matter under 
clause (d) of section 17A;".
----

K. N. CHATURVEDI,

Additional Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>