<act><title>The
Payment of Wages (Procedure) Rules, 19371


</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title.—<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>]
These rules may be called the Payment of Wages (Procedure) Rules, 1937.
 


 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number>
They extend to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.] 


    






</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
these rules, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number> ‘the Act’ means the Payment
of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936); 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number> ‘Appeal’
means an appeal under section 17; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>c</number> ‘the
Authority’ means the authority appointed under sub-section (1) of section 15; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>d</number> ‘the
Court’ means the court mentioned in sub-section (1) of section 17; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>e</number> ‘employer’
includes the persons responsible for the payment of wages under section 3; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>f</number> ‘section’
means a section of the Act; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>g</number>
‘form’ means a form appended to these rules; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>gg</number>
‘record of order or direction’ means the record of an order
dismissing either wholly or in part an application made under sub-section (2) of
section 15 or of a direction made under sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) of
that section kept in Form F;] 
 
 


 </section><section><number>h</number>words
and expressions defined in the Act shall be deemed to have the same meaning as
in the Act.


</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>3</number>
Form of application.—Applications
under sub-section (2) of section 15 by or on behalf of an employed person or
group of employed persons shall be made in duplicate in Form A, Form B or Form
C, as the case may be, one copy of which shall bear such court-fee as may be
prescribed.
 


</article> 

   


 <article><number>4</number>
Authorisation.—The
authorisation to act on behalf of an employed person or persons, under section
15, shall be given by a certificate in Form D, shall be presented to the
authority hearing the application and shall form part of the record.
.
 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Permission to appear.—Any
person desiring the permission of the Authority to act on behalf of any employed
person or persons shall present to the Authority a brief written statement
explaining his interest in the matter, and the Authority shall record an order
on the statement which in the case of refusal shall include reasons for the
order, and shall incorporate it in the record.
 


</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>6</number>
Presentation of documents.—
<section><number>1</number>
Applications or other documents relevant to an application may be presented in
person to the Authority at any time during hours to be fixed by the Authority,
or may be sent to him by registered post.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Authority shall at once endorse, or cause to be endorsed, on each document
the date of the presentation or receipt, as the case may be.
 


</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>7</number>
Refusal to entertain application.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Authority may refuse to entertain an application presented under rule 6, if
after giving the applicant an opportunity of being heard, the Authority is
satisfied, for reason to be recorded in writing that—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the applicant is not entitled to present an application; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the application is barred by reason of the provisions in the provisos to
sub-section (2) of section 15; or 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the applicant shows no sufficient cause for making a direction under
section 15. 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
The Authority may refuse to entertain an application which is insufficiently
stamped or otherwise incomplete and, if he so refuses, shall return it at once
with an indication of the defects. If the application is presented again, after
the defects have been made good, the date of representation shall be deemed to
be the date of presentation for the purpose of the proviso to sub-section (2) of
section 15.
 


</section></article> 

   


   




 <article><number>8</number>
Appearance of parties.—
<section><number>1</number>
If the application is entertained, the Authority shall call upon the employer by
a notice in Form E to appear before him on a specified date together with all
relevant documents and witnesses, if any, and shall inform the applicant of the
date so specified.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
If the employer or his representative fails to appear on the specified date, the
Authority may proceed to hear and determine the application ex parte.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
If the applicant fails to appear on the specified date, the Authority may
dismiss the application:
 


 Provided
that an order passed under sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (3) may be set aside and the
application re-heard on good cause being shown within one month of the date of
the said order, notice being served on opposite party of the date fixed for
rehearing.
 


</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Record of 
proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall in all cases enter the particulars indicated in Form F and 
at the time of passing orders shall sign and date the form.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In a case where no 
appeal lies, no further record shall be necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In a case where an 
appeal lies, the Authority shall record the substance of the evidence and shall 
append it under his signature to 

1[the record of 
order or direction].
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Signature on forms.—Any 
form, other than 

1[the record of 
order or direction], which is required by these rules to be signed by the 
Authority, may be signed under his direction and on his behalf by any officer 
subordinate to him, appointed by him, in writing for this purpose.
 
 



</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Exercise of powers.—In 
exercising the powers of a Civil Court conferred by section 18, the Authority 
shall be guided in respect of procedure by relevant orders of the First Schedule 
of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908, with such alterations as the Authority may 
find necessary, not affecting their substance, for adapting them to the matter 
before him, and save where they conflict with the express provisions of the Act 
or these rules.
 


</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Appeals.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
An appeal shall be preferred in duplicate in the form of a memorandum, one copy 
of which shall bear the prescribed court-fee, setting forth concisely the 
grounds of objection to the order dismissing either wholly or in part an 
application made under sub-section (2) of section 15 or a direction made under 
sub-section (3) or sub-section (4) of that section, as the case may be, and 
shall be accompanied by a certified copy of the said order or direction.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When an appeal is 
lodged a notice shall be issued to the respondent in Form G.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court after 
hearing the parties and after such further inquiry, if any, as it may deem 
necessary, may confirm, vary, or set aside the 

1[order or 
direction] from which the appeal is preferred, and shall make an order 
accordingly.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>12A</number> Order or 
direction when to be made.—The Authority or the Court, as the case may be, 
after the case has been heard, shall make the order or direction either at once 
or, as soon thereafter as may be practicable, on some future day; and when the 
order or direction is to be made on some future day, it shall fix date for the 
purpose of which due notice shall be given to the parties or their pleaders.]
 
 



</article> 
 
The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Inspection of 
documents.—Any 
employed person, or any employer or his representative, or any person permitted 
under sub-section (2) of section 15 to apply for a direction, shall be entitled 
to inspect any application, memorandum of appeal, or any other document filed 
with the Authority or the Court, as the case may be, in a case to which he is a 
party and may obtain copies thereof on the payment of such fees as may be 
prescribed.
 


</article><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 


 
 


Form A
 


Form of Individual Application
 


[See sub-section (2) of section 15 of 
the Payment of Wages Act]
 


In the Court of the Authority appointed under 
the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936) for 
................................... area.
 


Application No..................... of 
20.....
 


Between 
A.B.C.................................................................................Applicant 
(through a legal practitioner/an official 
of.............................................................. which is a 
registered Trade Union.)
 


And 
X.Y.Z........................................................................................opposite 
party:
 


The applicant states as follows:—
 


1. A.B.C. is a person employed in the/on the 
factory/railway/industrial establishment entitled and resides at......................................................................................
 


The address of the applicant for the service 
of all notices and processes is:
 



........................................................................................................................................
 


2. X.Y.Z., the opposite party, is the person 
responsible for the payment of his wages under section 3 of the Act, and his 
address for the service of all notices and processes is 
................................................................................................................................
 


3. (1) The applicant’s wages have not been 
paid for the following wage-period(s) ................[give (dates)]
 


Or 
 


A sum of Rs..........................has been 
unlawfully deducted from his wages of ............... amount for the wage-period(s) 
which ended on...............[(give date(s)].
 


 (2) [Here give any further claim or 
explanation].
 


4. The applicant estimates the value of the 
relief sought by him at the sum of Rs..........................
 


5. The applicant prays that a direction may 
be issued under sub-section (3) of section 15 for—
 


        (a)  Payment of delayed wages as 
estimated or such greater or lesser amount as the Authority may find to be due;
 


              Or 
Refund of the amount illegally deducted;
 


        (b)  Compensation amounting to 
...................................
 


The applicant certifies that the statement of 
facts contained in this application is to the best of his knowledge and belief 
accurate.
 



                                                  
...................................................................
 



                                                  Signature or thumb impression 
of the employed 
 



                                                  person, or legal practitioner, 
or official of a 
 



                                                  registered trade union duly 
authorised.
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 


 
 


FORM B
 


Form of Group Application 
 


[See sub-section (2) of sections 15 
and 16 of Payment of Wages Act]
 


In the Court of the Authority appointed under 
the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936) for 
....................................area.
 


Application No............... of 20.....
 


Between 
A.B.C................................................................ Applicants 
a legal practitioner (through a legal practitioner/an official 
of....................................................................... which 
is a registered trade union).
 


And 
X.Y.Z....................................................................................................Opposite 
Party.
 


The applicants state as follows:—
 


1.1[The 
applicants whose names and permanent addresses] appear in the attached schedule 
are persons employed in /on the/factory/railway/industrial establishment 
entitled and resides at.........................
 


 The address of the applicants for service of 
all notices and processes is:
 



........................................................................................................................................................
 


2. X.Y.Z, the opposite party, is the person 
responsible for the payment of wages under section 3 of the Act, and his address 
for the service of all notices and processes is.................................................................................................................................
 


3. The applicants’ wages have not been paid 
for the following wage-period(s):
 


 ........................................................................................................................................
 


4. The applicants estimate the value of the 
relief sought by them at the sum of Rs................
 


5. The applicants pray that a direction may 
be issued under sub-section (3) of section 15 for:—
 


        (a)  Payment of the applicants’ 
delayed wages as estimated.........................or such greater or lesser 
amount as the Authority may find to be due.
 


        (b)  Compensation amounting 
to.........................
 


The applicants certify that the statement of 
facts contained in this application is to the best of their knowledge and belief 
accurate.
 



...........................................................................
 



Signature or thumb 
impression of two of the 
 



                                                    applicants, or legal 
practitioner, or an official 
 



                                                    of a registered trade union 
duly authorised.
 




 



2[Schedule
 


 


    S.No.                      Name of 
  Applicant                  Permanent address
 


 


       
  1                                     
  2                                             3
 


 
 


 
 


 


 
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1960.
 


   2.  Subs. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1960.
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 


 
 


Form C
 


Form of Application by an Inspector or 
Person Permitted by the Authority or Authorised to Act
 


[See sub-section (2) of sections 15 
and 16 of the Payment of Wages Act]
 


In the Court of Authority appointed under the 
Payment of Wages Act, for.........................area.
 


Application No..............of 20.....
 


Between
 


A.B.C.[(designation)....................................................................an 
Inspector under the 
 


Payment of Wages Act] or a person/permitted 
by the authority/authorised 
................................................................................to 
act under sub-section (2) of section 15] 
........................................................................................... 
authorised applicant.
 


And
 


X.Y.Z.................................................................................................the 
opposite party.
 


The applicant states as follows:—
 


1. X.Y.Z., the opposite party is the person 
responsible under the Act for the payment of wages to the following 

1[persons whose names and permanent 
addresses are given below]:
 


(1)
 


(2)
 


(3)
 


2. His address for the service of all notices 
and processes is:
 


3. The wages of the said person(s) due in 
respect of the following wage-period(s) have not been paid/have been subjected 
to the following illegal deductions:
 


4. The applicant estimates the value of the 
relief sought for the person(s) employed at the sum of Rs..........................
 


5. The applicant prays that a direction may 
be issued under sub-section (3) of section 15 for:—
 


        (a)  Payment of the delayed wages as 
estimated or such greater or lesser amount as the Authority may find to be due.
 


 Or Refund of the amount 
illegally deducted.
 


        (b)  Compensation amounting to Rs..........................
 


The applicant certifies that the statement of 
facts contained in this application is to the best of his knowledge and belief 
accurate.
 


...............................
 


Signature
</form><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 


 
 


Form D
 


Certificate of Authorisation
 


I/We employed person(s) hereby authorise a 
legal practitioner/an official of................................ which is a 
registered trade union to act on my/our behalf under section 15 and section 17 
of the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936), in respect of the claim 
against.........................on account of the delay in payment/illegal 
deduction from my/our wages for.........................
 


Witnesses 
(1)                                            Signatures       (1)
 


                  
(2)                                                                    (2)
 


                  
(3)                                                                    (3)
 


                  
(4)                                                                    (4)
 


I accept the authorisation.
 



                                                            
.............................................
 



                                                            Signature
 



                                                            Legal practitioner/
 



                                                            Official of a 
registered trade union
 


 
</form><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 


 
 


Form E 
 


Notice for the Disposal of Application
 


To
 


Whereas under the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 
(4 of 1936) a claim against you has been presented to me in the application of 
which a copy is enclosed, you are hereby called upon to appear before me either 
in person or by any person duly instructed, and able to answer all material 
questions relating to the application, or who shall be accompanied by some 
person able to answer all material questions relating to the application, or who 
shall be accompanied by some person able to answer all such questions, on the 
........................day 
of.........................20.........at............o’clock in the 
forenoon/afternoon to answer the claim; and as the day fixed for your appearance 
is appointed for the final disposal of the application, you must be prepared to 
produce on that day all the witnesses upon whose evidence, and the documents 
upon which you intend to rely in support of your defence.
 


Take notice that, in default of your 
appearance on the day before mentioned, the application will be heard and 
determined in your absence.
 


Given under my hand and seal, this day 
of..............20......
 


.........................
 


Authority
 


Seal
</form><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 


 
 


Form F 
 




1[Record of Order or Direction]
 


        (1)  Serial 
number.........................
 


        (2)  Date of the 
application.........................
 


        (3)  Name or names, parentage, 
address or addresses of the applicants, or some, or all of the applicants 
belonging to the same unpaid group:
 


        (4)  Name and address of the 
employer:
 


        (5)  Amount claimed:
 


           (a)  as delayed wages: Rs 
..........................
 


           (b)  as deducted from wages: Rs.........................
 


        (6)  Plea of the employer and his 
examination (if any):
 



       1[(7)  Finding, and a brief 
statement of the reasons therefor]:
 


        (8)  Amounts awarded:
 


           (a)  Delayed wages Rs.........................
 


           (b)  Deducted 
wages.........................
 


        (9)  Compensation 
awarded.........................
 


      (10)  Penalty 
imposed.........................
 


      (11)  Costs awarded to:
 


           (a)  Court-fee 
charges.........................
 


           (b)  Pleader’s 
fee.........................
 


            (c)  Witnesses’ 
expenses.........................
 



        2[(12) Date by which the 
amounts awarded shall be paid.]
 


      Signed.........................
 


      Dated..........................
 


Note:—In 
case where an appeal lies, attach on a separate sheet the substance of the 
evidence.
 

 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1959.
 


   2.  Ins. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1970.
 

 
</form><form>
 


The Payment of Wages (Procedure) 
Rules, 1937
 


 
 


Form G
 


Notice to Respondent of the Day Fixed for the 
Hearing of the Appeal Under Section 17 of The Payment of Wages Act, 1936
 


Appeal from the decision of the Authority for 
the................................... area dated the..............day 
of..................20......
 


To
 



............................................................................Respondent
 


Take notice that an appeal of which a copy is 
enclosed, from the decision of the Authority 
for...................................area has been presented by X.Y.Z. (and 
others), and registered in this Court, and that the ..............day 
of..............20....., has been fixed by this Court for the hearing of the 
appeal.
 


If no appearance is made on your behalf by 
yourself, or by some one by law authorised to act for you in this appeal, it 
will be heard and decided in your absence.
 


Given under my hand and the seal of the 
Court, this...............day of...............20......
 


.........................
 


Seal of the Court   Judge
 


 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Rule 1 renumbered as sub-rule (1) thereof by the Payment of Wages
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1951.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by the Payment of Wages (Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1951.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins.
by the Payment of Wages (Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Subs. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1959.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Ins. by the Payment of Wages 
(Procedure) (Amendment) Rules, 1970.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>