<act><tid>1905130</tid>
<title>THE COMPANIES (DONATIONS TO NATIONAL FUNDS) ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 54 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 17th October, <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to enable companies to make donations to National funds.





<article><tid>1617397</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1747752</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Companies (Donations to National Funds) Act, <year>1951</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>145792</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>569118</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act,--
<section><tid>416655</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means a company as defined in section 2 of the 
Companies Act, and includes a company deemed to be 
incorporated and registered under that Act by virtue of 
section 2B thereof;

</section>

<section><tid>1165194</tid>
<number>b</number>" the Companies Act" means the Indian Companies Act, <year>1913</year> 
 (7 of <year>1913</year>)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1160779</tid>
<number>3</number>Power of companies to make donations to certain National 
Funds. Any company may, notwithstanding anything contained in the 
Companies Act or in any other law for the time being in force 
regulating the affairs thereof, and notwithstanding that the 
memorandum or articles of association of the company do not enable it 
so to do, by an extraordinary resolution passed in accordance with the 
provisions contained in section 81 of the Companies Act, authorise the 
making of donations to the Gandhi National Memorial Fund or the Sardar 
Vallabhbhai National Memorial Fund, or to any other Fund established 
for a charitable purpose which by reason of its national importance 
has been approved by the Central Government for the purposes of this 
section.


</article>



<article><tid>1671624</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Repeal of Act 35 of <year>1948</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending 
Act, <year>1957</year> (36 of <year>1957</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.
Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, S. 3 
and Schedule.


</article>



 </act>