<act><tid>1909015</tid>
<title>THE JUTE MANUFACTURES CESS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 13 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 27th March, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act to amend the Jute Manufactures Cess Act, <year>1983</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>727624</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>914658</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Jute  
Manufactures Cess (Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>461143</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>281561</tid>
<number>2</number>Substitution of a new Schedule for Schedule to Act 28 of <year>1983</year>.- 
For the Schedule to the Jute Manufactures Cess Act, <year>1983</year>, the 
following Schedule shall be substituted, namely:- 
" THE SCHEDULE 
[ See sections 2 (a) and 3. 1] 
Sl. Articles of jute The maximum rate at Actual rate at which 
No. manufacture which duty of excise duty of excise is to 
may be collected be collected until a 
different rate is 
specified by the 
Central Government 
1. Carpet Backing Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
valorem Valorem 
2. Hessian Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
valorem Valorem 
3. Sacking Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
valorem Valorem 
4. Yarn and Twine Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
valorem Valorem 
5. D. W. Tarpaulin Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
valorem Valoremorem 
6. Decorative Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
Fabrics valorem Valoremd valorem 
7. Cotton Bagging Two per cent ad One per cent adorem 
valorem Valorem 
8. Soil saver Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
valorem Valorem ad valorem 
9. Japanese Rice Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
Bags valorem Valorem ad valorem 
10. Any other article Two per cent ad One per cent ad 
of Jute valorem Valorem ad valorem 
Manufacture
K. N. CHATURVEDI, 
Addl. Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>