<act><title>


The Information Technology (Use of Electronic 
    Records and Digital Signatures) Rules, 20041</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Information Technology (Use of Electronic Records 
    and Digital Signatures) Rules, 2004.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Information Technology 
    Act, 2000 (21 of 2000);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “electronic record” means data, record 
    or data generated, image or sound stored, received or sent in an electronic 
    form or micro film or computer generated micro fiche;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    words and expressions used herein and 
    not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meaning respectively 
    assigned to them in the Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Filing 
    of form, application or any other document.—Any 
    form, application or any other document referred to in clause 
<section><number>a</number> of 
    sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act may be filed with any office, 
    authority, body or agency owned or controlled by the appropriate Government 
    using the software specified by it and such office, authority, body or 
    agency shall, while generating such software, take into account the 
    following features of the electronic record, namely:—
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>    life time;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    preservability;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    accessibility;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    readability;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    comprehensibility in respect of linked 
    information;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    evidentiary value in terms of 
    authenticity and integrity;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    controlled destructibility; and  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    augmentability.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Issue or 
    grant of any licence, permit, sanction or approval.—Any 
    licence, permit, sanction or approval whatever name called referred to in 
    clause (b) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 6 of the Act may be issued or 
    granted by using the software specified under rule 3. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Payment 
    and receipt of fee or charges.—The 
    payment of receipt of any fee or charges for filing, creation or issue of 
    any electronic record under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) of section 6 of 
    the Act may be made in a cheque in the electronic form. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this rule, “a cheque in the electronic form” has the meaning assigned to it 
    in clause (a) of Explanation 1 to section 6 of the Negotiable 
    Instruments Act, 1881 (26 of 1881).  
 


 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>