<act><tid>191123</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL SALES TAX (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2001</year></title>

ACT NO. 41 OF <year>2001</year>
[ 11th September, <year>2001</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Central Sales Tax Act, <year>1956</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- second Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1901270</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>947432</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Central Sales Tax (Amendment) Act, <year>2001</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>849771</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>407363</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 13.- In the Central Sales Tax Act, <year>1956</year> (74 of  
  <year>1956</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in section 13, 
in sub- section 1, after clause (g), the following clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (h) the proper functioning of the Authority constituted under section 
19;

<section><tid>1760366</tid>
<number>i</number>the salaries and allowances payable to, and the terms and 
conditions of service of, the Chairman and Members under sub- section 
 (3) of section 19;

</section>

<section><tid>12303</tid>
<number>j</number>any other matter as may be prescribed.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1423875</tid>
<number>3</number>Insertion of new Chapter after Chapter V.- After Chapter V of the 
principal Act, the following Chapter shall be inserted, namely:-
' CHAPTER VI

AUTHORITY TO SETTLE DISPUTES IN COURSE OF INTER- STATE TRADE OR 
COMMERCE

</article>



<article><tid>1384853</tid>
<number> 19</number> Central Sales Tax Appellate Authority.-
<section><tid>524777</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
shall constitute, by notification in the Official Gazette, an 
Authority to settle inter- State disputes falling under section 6A or 
section 9 of this Act, to be known as" the Central S les Tax Appellate 
Authority (hereinafter referred to as the Authority)".

</section>

<section><tid>1908912</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall consist of the following Members appointed by 
the Central Government, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1986838</tid>
<number>a</number>a Chairman, who is a retired Judge of the Supreme Court, or a 
retired Chief Justice of a High Court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1775392</tid>
<number>b</number>an officer of the Indian Legal Service who is, or is qualified to 
be, an Additional Secretary to the Government of India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1781407</tid>
<number>c</number>an officer of a State Government not below the rank of Secretary 
or an officer of the Central Government not below the rank of 
Additional Secretary, who is an expert in sales tax matters.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1176344</tid>
<number>3</number>The salaries and allowances payable to, and the terms and 
conditions of service of, the Chairman and Members shall be such as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>41592</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall provide the Authority with such 
officers and staff as may be necessary for the efficient exercise of 
the powers of the Authority under this Act.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1795778</tid>
<number> 20</number> Appeals.-
<section><tid>601173</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of this Chapter shall apply to  
appeals filed by the aggrieved dealer against any order of the 
assessing authority made under section 6A or section 9 of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>637907</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the general sales tax laws, 
the Authority shall adjudicate an appeal filed by a dealer aggrieved 
against any order of the assessing authority rejecting his claim under 
section 6A or section 9 of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>303401</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal against the order of the assessing authority rejecting 
the claim of the dealer under section 6A or section 9 of this Act may 
be filed by the aggrieved dealer within forty- five days from the date 
on which the order is served on him:
Provided that the Authority may entertain any appeal after the expiry 
of the said period of forty- five days, but not later than sixty days, 
from the date aforesaid if it is satisfied that the appellant was 
prevented by sufficient cause from filing the ap eal in time.


</section>

<section><tid>139190</tid>
<number>4</number>The application shall be made in quadruplicate and be accompanied 
by a fee of five thousand rupees.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1269828</tid>
<number> 21</number> Procedure on receipt of application.-
<section><tid>1506433</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of an appeal,  
the Authority shall cause a copy thereof to be forwarded to the 
assessing authority concerned and to call upon it to furnish the 
relevant records:
Provided that such records shall, as soon as possible, be returned to 
the assessing authority.


</section>

<section><tid>476405</tid>
<number>2</number>The Authority shall adjudicate and decide upon the appeal filed 
against an order of the assessing authority.

</section>

<section><tid>612143</tid>
<number>3</number>The Authority, after examining the appeal and the records called 
for, by order, either allow or reject the appeal:
Provided that no appeal shall be rejected unless an opportunity has 
been given to the appellant of being heard in person or through a duly 
authorised representative:

Provided further that whether an appeal is rejected or accepted, 
reasons for such rejection or acceptance shall be given in the order. 
 (4) The Authority shall make an endeavour to pronounce its order in 
writing within six months of the receipt of the appeal.


</section>

<section><tid>1957041</tid>
<number>5</number>A copy of every order made under sub- section (3) shall be sent to 
the appellant and to the assessing authority.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>319838</tid>
<number> 22</number> Powers of the Authority.-
<section><tid>1676421</tid>
<number>1</number>The Authority shall have the same  
powers as are vested in a court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
 <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit in respect of the following 
matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1591147</tid>
<number>a</number>enforcing the attendance of any person, examining him on oath or 
affirmation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>963481</tid>
<number>b</number>compelling the production of accounts and documents;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1262811</tid>
<number>c</number>issuing commission for the examination of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>169633</tid>
<number>d</number>the reception of evidence on affidavits;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1824923</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1817687</tid>
<number>2</number>Every proceeding before the Authority shall be deemed to be a 
judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) and the Authority shall be deemed to be 
Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year> (2 of <year>1974</year>). a civil court for the 
purposes of section 195 a d Chapter XXVI of the

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1890505</tid>
<number>23</number>Procedure of Authority.- The Authority shall, subject to the 
provisions of this Chapter, have power to regulate its own procedure 
in all matters arising out of the exercise of powers under this Act.
</article>



<article><tid>262358</tid>
<number> 24</number> Authority for Advance Rulings to function as Authority under this 
Act.-
<section><tid>448935</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the  
time being in force and in section 19 of this Act, the Authority for 
Advance Rulings constituted under section 245 O of the Income- tax Act, 
 <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>) shall be notified by the Central Government in the 
Official Gazette, with such modifications as may be necessary, to make 
its composition in conformity with section 19 of this Act, as the 
Authority under this ct till such time an Authority is constituted 
under that section.

</section>

<section><tid>457483</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the date of the constitution of the Authority in 
accordance with the provisions of section 19 of this Act, the 
proceedings pending with the Authority for Advance Rulings shall stand 
transferred to the Authority constituted under that sect on from the 
stage at which such proceedings stood before the date of constitution 
of the said Authority.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1773102</tid>
<number> 25</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.- On and from the date when the 
Authority is constituted under section 19, every appeal arising out of 
the provisions contained in this Chapter-
<section><tid>1183505</tid>
<number>i</number>which is pending immediately before the constitution of such 
Authority before the appellate authority constituted under the general 
sales tax law of a State or of the Union territory, as the case may 
be; or

</section>

<section><tid>448268</tid>
<number>ii</number>which would have been required to be taken before such appellate 
Authority, shall stand transferred to such Authority on the date on 
which it is established.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>480796</tid>
<number>26</number>Applicability of order passed.- An order passed by the Authority 
under this Chapter shall be binding on the assessing authorities and 
other authorities created by or under any law relating to general 
sales tax, in force for the time being in any State or Union 
territory.'.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>