<act><tid>1914427</tid>
<title>THE GOLD BONDS (IMMUNITIES AND EXEMPTIONS) ACT, <year>1993</year></title>

NO. 25 OF <year>1993</year> 
[ 2nd April, <year>1993</year>.
An Act to provide for certain immunities to the subscribers of 
the Gold Bonds and for certain exemptions from direct taxes in rela- 
tion to such Bonds and for matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto.

WHEREAS with a view to mobilising the idle gold resources of resi- 
dents in India, it is expedient to provide for certain immunities and 
exemptions to render it possible for such residents to subscribe to 
Gold Bonds;

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the 
Republic 
of India as follows:-




<article><tid>1653429</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1054958</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Gold Bonds (Immunities and Exemptions) Act, <year>1993</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>131392</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 31st day 
of January, <year>1993</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1171752</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>534887</tid>
<number>a</number>" Gold Bonds" means the Gold Bonds, <year>1998</year>, issued by the 
Central Government in accordance with the scheme framed by 
that Government under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1256356</tid>
<number>b</number>" subscriber" means an individual, a Hindu undivided 
family, trustees of a trust, a firm or a company, being a 
resident or residents in India, who has or have initially 
subscribed to the Gold Bonds.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, the expression 
" individual" shall also include,-


<subsection><tid>325171</tid>
<number>i</number>his legal heirs; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>61172</tid>
<number>ii</number>where a partition has taken place among the members of 
the Hindu undivided family, every member of such family 
having a share in the Gold Bonds;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>191155</tid>
<number>c</number>all other words and expressions used in this Act but 
not defined and defined in the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>) shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them 
in that Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>321924</tid>
<number> 3</number> Gold Bonds Scheme.
<section><tid>517137</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, frame a scheme for subscription 
to the Gold Bonds, <year>1998</year>, on or after the date of commencement of this 
Act, but before the specified date.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section," specified 
date" means the 31st day of March, <year>1993</year> or such other later date as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify in this behalf


</section>

<section><tid>894641</tid>
<number>2</number>The scheme framed under sub- section (1) shall be laid, as 
soon as may be after it is framed, before each House of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1036248</tid>
<number> 4</number> Immunities.
<section><tid>1081426</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the  
Wealth- tax Act, <year>1957</year>, (27 of <year>1957</year>) the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year> (18 of <year>1953</year>), 
the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>) the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of  
  <year>1962</year>), the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, <year>1973</year> (46 of <year>1973</year>) and the 
Foreign Contribution (Regulation) Act, <year>1976</year> (49 of <year>1976</year>),-

<subsection><tid>1849963</tid>
<number>a</number>no subscriber shall be required to disclose, for any 
purpose whatsoever, the nature and source of acquisition of 
the gold subscribed for the Gold Bonds, including the source 
of money with which the gold was acquired;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>951008</tid>
<number>b</number>no inquiry or investigation shall be commenced against 
any subscriber under any of the said Acts on the ground that 
such subscriber owns the Gold Bonds; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>396204</tid>
<number>c</number>the fact that any subscriber owns the Gold Bonds shall 
not be taken into account for the purposes of, and shall be 
inadmissible as evidence in, any proceedings under any of the 
said Acts:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall apply 
where any proceedings In respect of the gold subscribed by the 
subscriber have already been initiated before the commencement of this 
Act in accordance with the provisions of any of the aforesaid Acts.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1782340</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply in relation to 
prosecution for any offence punishable under Chapter IX or Chapter 
XVII of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), the Narcotic Drugs and 
Psychotropic Substances Act, <year>1985</year> (61 of <year>1985</year>), the Terrorist and 
Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act, <year>1987</year> (28 of <year>1987</year>), the Pre- 
vention of Corruption Act, <year>1988</year> (49 of <year>1988</year>) or for the purposes of 
enforcement of any civil liability.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1212234</tid>
<number> 5</number> Gold Bonds not to be taken into account in certain cases. 
Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions of section 4,-
<section><tid>840952</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>) 
shall not apply to-

<subsection><tid>193883</tid>
<number>i</number>any interest accruing to the subscriber from the Gold 
Bonds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>124802</tid>
<number>ii</number>any long- term capital gains arising to the subscriber;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>803552</tid>
<number>b</number>the provisions of the Gift- tax Act, <year>1958</year> (18 of <year>1958</year>) 
shall not apply where the gift of the Gold Bonds is made by a 
subscriber, being an individual, to his spouse, child or 
parent.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1807720</tid>
<number> 6</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>1045065</tid>
<number>1</number>The Gold Bonds (Immunities and   
  Exemptions) Ordinance <year>1993</year> (Ord. 22 of <year>1993</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>376400</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>