<act><tid>1917867</tid>
<title>THE SUGAR (SPECIAL EXCISE DUTY) ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 58 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 24th December, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to provide for the imposition of a special duty of excise on 
certain sugar.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>962766</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1513694</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Sugar (Special Excise Duty) Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1813112</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 25th day 
of October, <year>1959</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>54340</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>87301</tid>
<number>a</number>" Central Excises Act" means the Central Excises and 
Salt Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of <year>1944</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>990863</tid>
<number>b</number>" factory" means any premises, including the precincts 
thereof, wherein or in any part of which sugar is being 
manufactured, or, wherein or in any part of which, any 
manufacturing process connected with the production of sugar 
is being carried on or is ordinarily carried on, and includes 
any premises wherein sugar in respect of which the duty of 
excise payable under the Central Excises Act or the 
Additional Duties of Excise (Goods of Special Importance) 
Act, <year>1957</year>, (58 of <year>1957</year>.) has not been paid, is stored;

</section>

<section><tid>1295318</tid>
<number>c</number>" sugar" means any form of sugar, whether wholly or 
partially manufactured, but does not include-

<subsection><tid>1525134</tid>
<number>i</number>khandsari sugar, that is to say sugar in the manu- 
facture of which neither a vacuum pan nor a vacuum 
evaporator is employed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1605452</tid>
<number>ii</number>palmyra sugar, that is to say sugar manufactured 
from jaggery obtained by boiling the juice of the 
palmyra palm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>880313</tid>
<number> 3</number> Imposition of special additional excise duty on certain sugar.

<section><tid>765306</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and collected in respect of that quantity  
of sugar removed from any factory on or after the commencement of this 
Act as is equivalent to the quantity of sugar lying in stock on such 
commencement within the precincts of the factory,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>892</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

a special duty of excise at the rate of rupees two and fifty- two naye 
paise per cwt.


</section>

<section><tid>1380187</tid>
<number>2</number>The duty of excise referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
in addition to the duties of excise chargeable on sugar under the 
Central Excises Act or any other law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>276248</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of the Central Excises Act and the rules 
thereunder, including those relating to refunds and exemptions from 
duty shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to the levy and 
collection of the special duty of excise referred to in sub- section 
 (1) as they apply in relation to the levy and collection of the duties 
of excise on sugar under the Central Excises Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1222430</tid>
<number>4</number>Effect of levy of duty on certain transactions. Where, in 
compliance with an order made with reference to clause (f) of sub- 
section (2) of section 3 of the Essential Commodities Act, <year>1955</year>, a 
person is required to sell any sugar, the price of the sugar so 
required to be sold shall, if he has paid the special duty of excise 
leviable under section 3 on such sugar, include an amount equivalent 
to the duty so paid, and he shall be entitled to be paid such amount 
by the buyer.


</article>



<article><tid>850462</tid>
<number>5</number>Repeal. The Sugar (Special Excise Duty) Ordinance, <year>1959</year>, is 
hereby repealed.

</article>



 </act>