<act><tid>1926537</tid>
<title>THE TRIPURA LAND REVENUE AND LAND REFORMS ACT, <year>1960</year> 
NO. 43 OF <year>1960</year></title>

[ 21st September, <year>1960</year>]
An Act to consolidate and amend the law relating to land revenue in 
the Union territory of Tripura and to provide for the acquisition. of 
estates and for certain other measures of land reform.

be IT Enacted by Parliament in the Eleventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I.

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>24360</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1194350</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Tripura Land Revenue and Land Reforms Act, <year>1960</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>754475</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Tripura.

</section>

<section><tid>1451030</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Administrator 
may, by notification' in the Official Gazette, appoint; and different 
dates may be appointed for different areas and for different provi- 
sions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1338590</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1211962</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the Administrator of the Union 
territory of Tripura;

</section>

<section><tid>1638160</tid>
<number>b</number>" agriculture" includes horticulture, the raising of 
annual or periodical crops or garden produce, dairy farming, 
poultry farming, stock breeding, grazing and pisciculture;

</section>

<section><tid>929288</tid>
<number>c</number>" basic holding" means land used for agricultural pur- 
poses which is equal to two standard acres In area;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>544</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1380248</tid>
<number>d</number>" Collector" means the Collector of the district and 
includes any officer appointed by the Administrator to 
exercise and perform all or any of the powers and functions 
of a Collector under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>596780</tid>
<number>e</number>" commencement of this Act", in relation to any provi- 
sion., means the date specified in respect of that provision 
in a notification under sub- section (3) of section 1;

</section>

<section><tid>406757</tid>
<number>f</number>" competent authority", in relation to any provision, 
means any officer appointed by the Administrator to be the 
competent authority for the purpose of that provision;

</section>

<section><tid>283367</tid>
<number>g</number>" family" except in Chapter XIII means, in relation to a 
person, the wife or husband of such person, his children, 
grandchildren, parents and brothers, and in the case of a 
Joint Hindu family, any member of such family;

</section>

<section><tid>1424439</tid>
<number>h</number>" family holding" means land used for agricultural pur- 
poses which is equal to 6. 4 standard acres in area;

</section>

<section><tid>915382</tid>
<number>i</number>" Government" means the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>784595</tid>
<number>j</number>" holding" means a parcel of land separately assessed to 
land revenue;

</section>

<section><tid>843017</tid>
<number>k</number>" improvement", in relation to any land, means any work 
which materially adds to the value of the land and which is 
suitable to the land and consistent with the character 
thereof and includes-

<subsection><tid>273679</tid>
<number>i</number>the construction of tanks, wells, water channels 
and other works for the storage, supply and distribution 
of water for agricultural purposes or for the use of man 
and cattle employed in agriculture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1100841</tid>
<number>ii</number>the construction of works for the drainage of land 
or for the protection of land from floods or from 
erosion or from other damage by water;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1033575</tid>
<number>iii</number>the preparation of land for irrigation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>462516</tid>
<number>iv</number>the conversion of one- crop into two- crop land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>502197</tid>
<number>v</number>the reclaiming, clearing, enclosing, levelling or 
terracing of land used for agricultural purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1710992</tid>
<number>vi</number>the erection on land or in the immediate vicinity 
thereof otherwise than on the village site, of a 
building or house for the occupation of the under- 
raiyat, his family and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>545</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

servants or of a cattle shed, a store- house or other 
construction for agricultural purposes or of any 
building required for the convenient or profitable use 
or occupation of the land; and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>142148</tid>
<number>vii</number>the renewal or reconstruction of any of the fore- 
going works or such alterations therein or additions 
thereto as are not of the nature of ordinary repairs;.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>283699</tid>
<number>l</number>" minor" means a person who is deemed not to have 
attained majority under the Indian Majority Act, <year>1875</year>; (9 of  
  <year>1875</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>39942</tid>
<number>m</number>" Official Gazette" means the Tripura Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>54557</tid>
<number>n</number>" pay"," payable" and" payment", used with reference to 
rent, include' deliver"," deliverable" and" delivery";

</section>

<section><tid>1158746</tid>
<number>o</number>" person under disability" means-

<subsection><tid>653287</tid>
<number>i</number>a widow;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>963485</tid>
<number>ii</number>a minor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1150005</tid>
<number>iii</number>a woman who is unmarried or who, if married, Is 
divorced or judicially separated from her husband or 
whose husband is a person falling under item (iv) or 
 (v);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1822318</tid>
<number>iv</number>a member of the Armed Forces of the Union:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518554</tid>
<number>v</number>a person incapable of cultivating land by reason of 
some physical or mental disability;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1024960</tid>
<number>p</number>" personal cultivation", with its grammatical variations 
and cognate expressions, means cultivation by a person on his 
own account-

<subsection><tid>442297</tid>
<number>i</number>by his own labour, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1150326</tid>
<number>ii</number>by the labour of any member of his family, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>904137</tid>
<number>iii</number>by servants or by hired labour on wages, payable 
in cash or in kind but not as a share of produce, under 
his personal supervision or the personal supervision of 
any member of his family;
Explanation I.- Land shall not be deemed to be cultivated 
under the personal supervision of a person or a member of his 
family unless such person or member resides in the village in 
which the land is situated or in a nearby village situated 
within a distance to be prescribed, during the major part of 
the agricultural season;

Explanation II.- In the case of a person under disability, 
supervision by a paid employee on behalf of such person shall 
be deemed to be personal supervision;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>546</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1774361</tid>
<number>q</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1153241</tid>
<number>r</number>" public purpose" includes a purpose connected with 
allotment of land' co cultivators, under- raiyats ejected as a 
result of resumption, land- less agricultural workers or co- 
operative farming societies;

</section>

<section><tid>1861449</tid>
<number>s</number>" raiyat" means a person who owns land for purposes of 
agriculture paying land revenue to the Government and in- 
cludes the successors- in- interest of such person;

</section>

<section><tid>694712</tid>
<number>t</number>" rent" means whatever is lawfully payable, in money or 
in kind, or partly in money and partly in kind, whether as a 
fixed quantity of produce or as a share of the produce, on 
account of the use or occupation of land or on account of any 
right in land but shall not include. land revenue;

</section>

<section><tid>1309307</tid>
<number>u</number>" standard acre" means one acre of' lunga' or' nal' or 
three acres of' tilla' land;

</section>

<section><tid>1969222</tid>
<number>v</number>" under- raiyat" means a person who cultivates or holds 
the land of a raiyat under an agreement, express or implied, 
on condition of paying therefor rent in cash or in kind or 
delivering a share of the produce and includes a person who 
cultivates or holds land of a raiyat under the system 
generally known as' bhag',' adhi or' barga';

</section>

<section><tid>1556406</tid>
<number>w</number>" village" means any tract of land which, before the 
commencement of this Act, was recognised as or was declared 
to be a village under any law for the time being in force or 
which may after such commencement be recognised as a village 
at any settlement or which the Administrator may, by 
notification, in the Official Gazette, declare to be a 
village;

</section>

<section><tid>1936403</tid>
<number>x</number>" year" means the agricultural year commencing on such 
date as the Administrator may, in the case of any specified 
area, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
PART II

CHAP 
REVENUE DIVISIONS, REVENUE OFFICERS AND THEIR APPOINTMENT

CHAPTER II- REVENUE DIVISIONS, REVENUE OFFICERS AND THEIR

APPOINTMENT



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1086817</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to create, alter or abolish districts, sub- divisions, 
etc.
<section><tid>122207</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, with the previous concurrence of the  
Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, divide the Union 
territory of Tripura into one or more districts, and may similarly 
divide any district into sub- divisions, circles and tehsils, and may 
alter the limits of, or abolish, any district, sub- division, circle or 
tehsil,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>547</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1957083</tid>
<number>2</number>The districts, sub- divisions, circles and tehsils existing 
at the commencement of this Act shall continue respectively to be the 
districts, sub- divisions, circles and tehsils under this Act unless 
otherwise provided under sub- section (1).


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>494914</tid>
<number> 4</number> Appointment of revenue officers. The Government or such 
other officer as may be authorised by the Government in this behalf 
may appoint the following classes of revenue officers, namely:-
<section><tid>1434487</tid>
<number>a</number>Collector,

</section>

<section><tid>563591</tid>
<number>b</number>director of settlement and land records,

</section>

<section><tid>448476</tid>
<number>c</number>- sub- divisional officers,

</section>

<section><tid>580920</tid>
<number>d</number>survey and settlement officers,

</section>

<section><tid>431818</tid>
<number>e</number>assistant, survey and settlement officers,

</section>

<section><tid>57979</tid>
<number>f</number>circle officers,

</section>

<section><tid>1564124</tid>
<number>g</number>revenue' inspectors,

</section>

<section><tid>1480809</tid>
<number>h</number>tehsildars,

</section>

<section><tid>10043</tid>
<number>i</number>village accountants and such other village officers and 
servants as may be specified by rules made under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1097092</tid>
<number> 5</number> Collector and certain other revenue officers.
<section><tid>384340</tid>
<number>1</number>Each  
district shall be placed under the charge of a Collector who shall be 
in charge of the revenue administration of the district and exercise 
the powers and discharge the duties of the Collector under this Act or 
any other law for the time being in force and- shall exercise so far as 
is consistent therewith such other powers of superintendence and 
control within the district and over the officers subordinate to him 
as may from time to time be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>437431</tid>
<number>2</number>Each sub- division shall be placed under the charge of a sub- 
divisional officer.

</section>

<section><tid>970334</tid>
<number>3</number>Each circle or tehsil shall be placed under the charge of a 
circle officer or a tehsildar, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>812078</tid>
<number>4</number>The duties and powers of the sub- divisional officers, the 
circle officers and other revenue officers shall be such as may be 
imposed or conferred on them by or under this Act or any other law in 
force for the time being or any general or special order of the 
Administrator published in the Official Gazette.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1688285</tid>
<number>6</number>Settlement officers. The officers specified in items (b), (d) 
and (e) of section shall have power to take cognizance of all matters 
connected wit the survey of land and the settlement of the revenue- 
rates and the preparation. and maintenance of land records and other 
register and shall exercise all such powers and, perform all such 
duties as

<pagefootnote><pagenum>548</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

may be prescribed by or under this Act or by any general or special 
order of the Administrator published in the Official Gazette.


</article>



<article><tid>434397</tid>
<number>7</number>Subordination of revenue officers. All revenue officers shall 
be subordinate to the Administrator and all revenue officers in the 
district or a sub- division shall be subordinate to the Collector or 
the sub- divisional officer, as the case may be.

</article>



<article><tid>1740869</tid>
<number>8</number>Combination of offices. It shall be lawful for the 
Administrator to appoint one and the same person to any two or more of 
the offices provided for in this Chapter, to make any appointment by 
virtue of office and also to confer on any officer of the Government 
all or any of the powers and duties of any of the revenue officers 
including the Collector.

</article>



<article><tid>395681</tid>
<number>9</number>Notification of appointments. All appointments made under this 
Chapter except appointments of revenue inspectors, tehsildars and 
village accountants and other village officers land servants shall be 
notified in the Official Gazette.

</article>



<article><tid>1496949</tid>
<number>10</number>Seals. The Administrator shall, from time to time, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify the revenue officers who 
shall use a seal and also the size and description of the seal which 
each such officer shall use.
CHAP 
LAND AND LAND REVENUE

CHAPTER III.- LAND AND LAND REVENUE


</article>



<article><tid>628159</tid>
<number> 11</number> Title of Government to lands, etc.
<section><tid>1194274</tid>
<number>1</number>All lands, public  
roads, lanes and paths and bridges, ditches, dikes, and fences on or 
beside the same, the beds of rivers, streams, nallas, lakes and tanks, 
and all canals and water courses, and all standing and flowing water, 
and all rights in or over the same or appertaining thereto, which are 
not the property of any person, are and are hereby declared to be the 
property of the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>92324</tid>
<number>2</number>Unless it is- otherwise expressly provided in the terms of a 
grant made by the Government, the right to mines, quarries, minerals 
and mineral products including mineral oil, natural gas and petroleum 
shall vest in the Government, and it shall have all the powers neces- 
sary for the proper enjoyment of such rights.

</section>

<section><tid>1271167</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any property or any right in or over any property is 
claimed by or on behalf of the Government, or by any person as against 
the Government and the claim is disputed, such dispute shall be 
decided by the Collector whose order shall, subject to the provisions 
of this Act, be final.

</section>

<section><tid>153427</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person aggrieved by an order made under sub- section (3) 
or in appeal or revision therefrom may institute a civil suit to 
contest the order within a period of six months from the date of such 
order and the decision of the civil court shall be binding on the 
parties.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>549</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1062208</tid>
<number> 12</number> Right to trees, forests, etc.
<section><tid>1526350</tid>
<number>1</number>The right to all trees,  
jungles or other natural products growing on land set apart for forest 
reserves and to all trees, brush wood, jungle or other natural 
product, wherever growing, except in so far as the same may be the 
property of any person, vests in the Government, and such trees, brush 
wood, jungle or other natural product shall be preserved or disposed 
of in such manner as may be prescribed, keeping in view the interests 
of the people in the area with regard to the user of the natural 
products.

</section>

<section><tid>561233</tid>
<number>2</number>All road side trees which have been planted and reared by or 
under the orders or at the expense of the Government and all trees 
which have been planted and reared at the expense of local authorities 
by the side of any road belonging to the Government vest in the 
Government.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>120781</tid>
<number>13</number>Assignment of land for special purposes. Subject to rules made 
in this behalf under this Act, the Collector may set apart land 
belonging to the Government for pasturage for the village cattle, for 
forest reserves or for any other purpose.

</article>



<article><tid>1081665</tid>
<number> 14</number> Allotment of land.
<section><tid>1255523</tid>
<number>1</number>The Collector may allot land belonging  
to the Government for agricultural purposes or for construction of 
dwelling houses, in accordance with such rules as may be made in this 
behalf under this Act; and such rules may provide for allotment of 
land to persons evicted under section 15.

</section>

<section><tid>1184883</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator shall have power-

<subsection><tid>763608</tid>
<number>a</number>to allot any such land for the purpose of an industry 
or for any purpose of public utility on such conditions as 
may be prescribed, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>878617</tid>
<number>b</number>to entrust the management of any such land or any 
rights therein to the gram panchayat of the village 
established under any law for the time being in force.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1565437</tid>
<number> 15</number> Unauthorised occupation of land.
<section><tid>1042950</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person who occupies  
or continues to occupy any land belonging to Government without lawful 
authority shall be regarded as a trespasser and may be summarily 
evicted therefrom by the competent authority and any building or other 
construction erected or anything deposited on such land, if not 
removed within such reasonable time as such authority may from time to 
time fix for the purpose, shall be liable to be forfeited to the 
Government and to be disposed of in such manner as the competent 
authority may direct:
Provided that the competent authority may, in lieu of ordering 
the forfeiture of any such building or other construction, order the 
demolition of the whole or any part thereof.


</section>

<section><tid>1949494</tid>
<number>2</number>Such trespasser shall also be liable by way of penalty to 
pay a sum which may extend to six times the annual assessment on such

<pagefootnote><pagenum>550</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

land as may be specified by the competent authority and such sum shall 
be recoverable in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.


</section>

<section><tid>537169</tid>
<number>3</number>Upon payment of the penalty referred to in sub- section (2), 
the trespasser shall have the right of tending, gathering and removing 
any ungathered crops.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1471077</tid>
<number> 16</number> Liability of land to land revenue.
<section><tid>136688</tid>
<number>1</number>All lands, to whatever  
purpose applied, are liable to payment of land revenue to the 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1626429</tid>
<number>2</number>The Administrator may exempt any land from the liability to 
such payment by means of a special grant or contract or in accordance 
with any law for the time being in force or the rules made under this 
Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>932544</tid>
<number>17</number>Alluvial lands. All alluvial lands, newly formed islands, or 
abandoned river beds, which vest under any law for the time being in 
force in any holder of land shall be subject in respect of liability 
to land revenue to the same privileges, conditions and restrictions as 
are applicable to the original holding by virtue of which such lands, 
islands or river beds vest in the said holder, but no revenue shall be 
leviable in respect of any such lands, islands or river beds unless 
the area of the same exceeds one acre.

</article>



<article><tid>172891</tid>
<number>18</number>Land revenue in case of diluvion. Every holder of land 
paying land revenue in respect thereof shall be entitled, subject to 
such rules as may be made in this behalf, to a decrease of assessment 
if any portion thereof, not being less than one acre in extent, is 
lost by diluvion.

</article>



<article><tid>1402780</tid>
<number> 19</number> Assessment of land revenue.
<section><tid>574430</tid>
<number>1</number>The assessment of land  
revenue on any land shall be made, or shall be deemed to have been 
made, with respect to the use of the land-

<subsection><tid>643385</tid>
<number>a</number>for purposes of agriculture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>993663</tid>
<number>b</number>for industrial or commercial purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1721629</tid>
<number>c</number>as sites for dwelling houses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>903675</tid>
<number>d</number>for any other purpose.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>350267</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, land assessed for use for any one purpose is diverted 
to any other purpose, the land revenue payable upon such land shall, 
notwithstanding that the term for which the assessment may have been 
fixed has not expired, be liable to be altered and assessed, at a 
different rate in accordance with the rules made under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1436731</tid>
<number> 20</number> Diversion of land.
<section><tid>1819127</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person holding land for any  
purpose wishes to divert such land or any part thereof to any other 
purpose except agriculture, he shall apply for permission to the 
competent authority who may, subject to the provisions of this 
section and to the rules made under this Act, refuse permission or 
grant it on such conditions as it may think fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>551</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>913598</tid>
<number>2</number>Permission to divert may be refused by the competent autho- 
rity only on the ground that the diversion is likely to cause a public 
nuisance or that it is not in the interest of the general public or 
that the holder is unable or unwilling to comply with the conditions 
that may be imposed under sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>88046</tid>
<number>3</number>Conditions may be imposed on diversion for the following 
objects and no others, namely, in order to secure the public health, 
safety and convenience, and in the case of land which is to be used as 
building sites, in order to secure in addition that the dimensions, 
arrangement and accessibility of the sites are adequate for the health 
and convenience of occupiers or are suitable to the locality.

</section>

<section><tid>613576</tid>
<number>4</number>If any land has been diverted without permission by the 
holder or by any other person with or without the consent of the 
holder, the competent authority, on receiving information thereof, may 
impose on the person responsible for the diversion a penalty not ex- 
ceeding one hundred rupees, and may proceed in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- section (1) as if an application for permission to 
divert has been made.

</section>

<section><tid>1304936</tid>
<number>5</number>If any land has been diverted in contravention of an order 
passed or of a condition imposed under any of the foregoing sub 
- sections, the competent authority may serve a notice on the person 
responsible for such contravention, directing him, within a reasonable 
period to be stated in the notice, to use the land for its original 
purpose or to observe the condition; and such notice may require such 
person to remove any structure, to fill up any excavation, or to take 
such other steps as may be required in order that the land may be used 
for its original purpose, or that the condition may be satisfied. The 
competent authority may also impose on such person a penalty not 
exceeding one hundred rupees for such contravention, and a further 
penalty not exceeding four rupees for each day during which such 
contravention continues.

</section>

<section><tid>1534816</tid>
<number>6</number>If any person served with a notice under sub- section (5), 
fails within the period stated in the notice to take the steps ordered 
by the competent authority under that sub- section, the competent 
authority may itself take such steps or cause them to be taken; and 
any cost incurred in so doing shall be recoverable from such person in 
the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.
Explanation.-" Diversion" in this section means using land assess- 
ed to one purpose for any other purpose, but using land for the pur- 
pose of agriculture where it is assessed with reference to any other 
purpose shall not be deemed to be diversion.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>552</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1219574</tid>
<number>21</number>Remission or suspension of revenue on failure of crops. The 
Administrator may, in accordance with the rules made in this behalf 
under this Act, grant a remission or suspension of land revenue in 
years in which crops have failed in any area.

</article>



<article><tid>1515588</tid>
<number> 22</number> Responsibility for payment of land revenue.
<section><tid>89951</tid>
<number>1</number>The following  
persons shall be primarily liable for the payment of land revenue 
assessed on land, namely:-

<subsection><tid>559603</tid>
<number>a</number>the person to whom the land belongs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1542415</tid>
<number>b</number>the under- raiyat or any other person in possession of 
the land, provided that such under- raiyat or other person 
shall be entitled to credit from the owner of the land for 
the amount paid by him.:

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1084452</tid>
<number>2</number>Where there are two or more persons liable to pay land reve- 
nue under sub- section (1), all of them shall be jointly and severally 
liable for its payment.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>645993</tid>
<number>23</number>Receipt for land revenue. Every revenue officer receiving 
payment of land revenue shall, at the time when such payment is 
received by him, give a written receipt for the same.
CHAP 
SURVEY AND SETTLEMENT OF LAND REVENUE

CHAPTER IV.- SURVEY AND SETTLEMENT OF LAND

REVENUE


</article>



<article><tid>1253096</tid>
<number>24</number>Definitions of" revenue survey"," settlement" and" term of 
settlement". The operations carried out in accordance with the 
provisions of this Chapter in order to determine or revise the land 
revenue payable on lands in any local area are called a" revenue 
survey", the results of the operations are called a" Settlement" and 
the period during which such results are to be in force is called the 
" term of settlement".

</article>



<article><tid>1302097</tid>
<number> 25</number> Inquiry into profits of agriculture.
<section><tid>133149</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as may be  
after the commencement of this Act, the Administrator shall take steps 
to institute and shall cause to be constantly maintained, in 
accordance with the rules made under this Act, an inquiry into the 
profits of agriculture and into the value of land used for 
agricultural and non- agricultural purposes.

</section>

<section><tid>1078722</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of determining the profits of agriculture 
the following matters shall be taken into account in estimating the 
cost of cultivation, namely:-

<subsection><tid>635132</tid>
<number>a</number>the depreciation of stock and buildings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>20838</tid>
<number>b</number>the money equivalent of the labour and supervision by 
the cultivator and his family;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>743719</tid>
<number>c</number>all other expenses usually incurred in the cultivation 
of the land which is under inquiry; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>553</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1114663</tid>
<number>d</number>interest on the cost of buildings and stock, on all 
expenditure for seed and manure and on the cost of 
agricultural operations paid for in cash.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1387752</tid>
<number>26</number>Revenue surrey. Whenever the Administrator thinks it expedient 
so to do, he may, with the approval of the Government, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, direct the revenue survey of any local area 
with a view to the settlement of the land revenue and to the 
preparation of a record of rights connected therewith or the revision 
of any existing settlement or record of rights.

</article>



<article><tid>329365</tid>
<number>27</number>Power to require assistance from landholders. A survey officer 
deputed to conduct or take part in any revenue survey may, by special 
order or by general notice to be published in the prescribed manner, 
require the attendance of holders of lands to assist in the 
measurement or classification of the lands to which the revenue survey 
extends and, when hired labour is employed for purposes incidental to 
the revenue survey, may assess and apportion the cost thereof on the 
lands surveyed, for collection as land revenue due on such lands.

</article>



<article><tid>1567973</tid>
<number> 28</number> Survey numbers and villages. Subject to the rules made in this 
behalf under this Act, the survey officer may-
<section><tid>256127</tid>
<number>a</number>divide the lands to which the revenue survey extends into 
villages and the villages into plots and survey numbers: and

</section>

<section><tid>1197655</tid>
<number>b</number>recognise the existing villages and survey numbers, 
reconstitute them or form new survey numbers.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>544116</tid>
<number>29</number>Division of survey numbers into sub- divisions. The survey 
officer may sub- divide survey numbers into as many sub- divisions as 
may be required in the manner prescribed,

</article>



<article><tid>559204</tid>
<number>30</number>Determination of revenue- rates. The Administrator may at any 
time direct the determination or the revision of the revenue- rates for 
all lands in any area, of which a revenue survey has been made.

</article>



<article><tid>304450</tid>
<number>31</number>Preparation of statistical and fiscal records. It shall be the 
duty of the survey officer or the settlement officer on the occasion 
of making or revising a settlement of land revenue to prepare a 
register to be called the" settlement register", showing the area and 
assessment of each survey number, with any other particulars that may 
be prescribed, and other records in accordance with such orders as may 
from time to time be made in this behalf by the Administrator.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>554</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>533243</tid>
<number>32</number>Revenuerates how determined. For the purpose of determining 
the revenue- rates, the settlement officer may divide any area into 
units and in forming such units, he shall have regard to the physical 
features, agricultural and economic conditions and trade facilities 
and communications; and shall then determine the revenue- rates for 
different classes of lands in each such unit in the manner and 
according to the principles prescribed and in particular, in the case 
of agricultural land, to the profits of agriculture, to the 
consideration paid for leases, to the sale prices of land and to the 
principal monies on mortgages and in the case of non- agricultural 
land, to the value of the land for the. purpose for which it is held.

</article>



<article><tid>1926599</tid>
<number> 33</number> Publication of table of revenuerates.
<section><tid>867118</tid>
<number>1</number>The settlement  
officer shall prepare a table of revenuerates in the prescribed form 
and publish it in the prescribed manner for' the prescribed period.

</section>

<section><tid>1835738</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person objecting to any entry in the table of revenue- 
rates may present a petition in writing to the settlement officer 
within the prescribed period and the settlement officer shall consider 
such objections after giving a hearing to the objector.

</section>

<section><tid>665358</tid>
<number>3</number>The settlement officer shall submit the table of revenue- 
rates to the Administrator together with a summary of objections, if 
any, his decisions on such objections and a statement of the grounds 
in support of his proposals.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1560347</tid>
<number> 34</number> Confirmation of the table of revenuerates.
<section><tid>1744523</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Administrator may confirm the table of revenuerates submitted to him 
by the settlement officer with such modifications, if any, as be may 
consider necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1428043</tid>
<number>2</number>The table of revenue- rates confirmed under sub- section (1) 
shall be finally published in the Official Gazette.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>686085</tid>
<number>35</number>Rates of revenue to form part settlement register. The table 
of revenue- rates published under section 34 shall be incorporated in 
and form part of the settlement register of the village.

</article>



<article><tid>799449</tid>
<number>36</number>Introduction of revenuerates. When the revenue- rates are 
determined under this Chapter in respect of any area, such rates shall 
take effect from the beginning of the year next after the date of 
final publication of the table of revenue- rates under section 34.

</article>



<article><tid>1333061</tid>
<number> 37</number> Duration of revenuerates.
<section><tid>97529</tid>
<number>1</number>When the table of revenue- rates  
for any area has been finallay published, the rates specified therein 
shall remain in force for a period of thirty years.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>555</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>148800</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in subsection (1)

<subsection><tid>822109</tid>
<number>a</number>revenue- rates may be altered or revised in any year 
after the expiry of every ten years from the date on which 
the table of revenue- rates was introduced, in such manner and 
to such extent as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1315935</tid>
<number>b</number>when the circumstances of a local area are such that a 
fresh determination of the revenue- rates is in the opinion of 
the Administrator inexpedient, he may extend the term of 
settlement by such further period as he may think necessary.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>171021</tid>
<number> 38</number> Assessment on holdings.
<section><tid>788833</tid>
<number>1</number>The settlement. officer shall  
calculate the assessment on each holding in accordance with the 
revenue- rates confirmed and finally published under section 34 and 
such assessment shall be the fair assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>1277556</tid>
<number>2</number>The settlement officer shall have the power to make fair 
assessment on all lands whatsoever to which the revenue survey 
extends, whether such lands are held with liability to pay full land 
revenue or land revenue at concessional rates or are held revenue 
free.

</section>

<section><tid>1956561</tid>
<number>3</number>The fair assessment of all lands shall be calculated in 
accordance with rules made in this behalf and having' regard to the 
following principles, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1414762</tid>
<number>a</number>no regard shall be had to any claim to hold land on 
privileged terms;'

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1353772</tid>
<number>b</number>regard shall be had in the case of agricultural land to 
the profits of agriculture, to the consideration paid for 
leases, to the sale prices of land and to the principal 
monies on mortgages, and in the case of non- agricultural 
land, to the value of the land for the purpose for which it 
is held;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1231773</tid>
<number>c</number>where any improvement has been effected at any time in 
any holding held for the purpose of agriculture by or at the 
expense of the holder thereof, the fair assessment of such 
holding shall be fixed as if the improvement had not been 
made.'


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>2994</tid>
<number>39</number>Additional assessment for water advantages. Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Chapter, the Administrator may direct that 
any land in respect of which the rate of revenue has been determined 
shall be liable to be assessed to additional land revenue during, the 
term of the settlement for additional advantages accruing to it from 
water received on account of irrigation works or improvements in 
existing irrigation works' completed after the table of revenue- rates 
dame into force and not effected by or at the expense of the holder of 
the land.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>356</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>330835</tid>
<number>40</number>Continuance of survey operations and rates in force at 
commencement of Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in this 
Chapter, all survey operations commenced under any law for the time 
being in force and continuing at the commencement of this Act shall be 
deemed to have been commenced and to be continuing under the 
provisions of this Chapter, and all revenue- rates in force at such 
commencement shall be deemed to have been determined and introduced in 
accordance with the provisions of this Chapter and shall remain in 
force until the introduction of revised revenue- rates; and such 
revised revenue- rates may be introduced at any time, notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 37.

</article>



<article><tid>147577</tid>
<number> 41</number> Power of Collector to correct errors, etc.
<section><tid>579878</tid>
<number>1</number>The powers and  
duties exercisable by the officers referred to in section 6 may also 
be exercised', during the term of settlement, by the Collector or such 
other revenue officer as may be specified by the Administrator for the 
purpose by notification in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1565765</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector may at any time during the term of settlement 
correct any error in the area or the assessment of any survey number 
or sub- division due to a mistake of survey or arithmetical miscalcu- 
lation:
Provided that no arrears of land revenue shall become payable by 
reason of such correction

CHAP 
LAND RECORDS

CHAPTER V.- LAND RECORDS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>668193</tid>
<number>42</number>Preparation of record of rights. It shall be the duty of the 
survey officer to prepare a record of rights for each village showing 
the area of each survey number and other particulars and any other 
record or register, in accordance with the rules made under this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>125502</tid>
<number> 43</number> Publication of the record of rights.
<section><tid>136643</tid>
<number>1</number>When a record of  
rights has been prepared, the survey officer shall publish a draft of 
the record in such manner and for such period as may be prescribed and 
shall receive and consider any objections which may be made during the 
period of such publication, to any entry therein or to any omission 
therefrom.

</section>

<section><tid>1393305</tid>
<number>2</number>When all objections have been considered and disposed of in 
accordance with the rules made in this behalf, the survey officer 
shall cause the record to be finally published in the prescribed 
manner.

</section>

<section><tid>81697</tid>
<number>3</number>Every entry in the record of rights as finally published 
shall, until, the contrary is proved, be presumed to be correct.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1656705</tid>
<number>44</number>Jurisdiction of civil courts to decide disputes. The civil 
courts shall have jurisdiction to decide any dispute to which the 
Government is not a party relating to any right or entry which is 
recorded in the record of rights.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>557</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1562493</tid>
<number>45</number>Correction of bona fide mistake in register. The survey 
officer may, on application made to him in this behalf or on his own 
motion, within one year from the date of final publication of the 
record of, rights, correct any entry in such record which he is 
satisfied has been made owing to a bona fide mistake.

</article>



<article><tid>438701</tid>
<number> 46</number> Register of mutations.
<section><tid>169948</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be maintained for every  
village a register of mutations in such form as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1640620</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person acquiring by succession, survivorship, 
inheritance, partition, purchase, gift, mortgage, lease or otherwise 
any right in land or, where such person acquiring the right is a minor 
or otherwise disqualified, his guardian or other person having charge 
of his property, shall report his acquisition of such right to the 
village accountant within three months from the date of such 
acquisition and the village accountant shall give at once a written 
acknowledgement in the prescribed form for such report to the person 
making it.

</section>

<section><tid>155474</tid>
<number>3</number>The village accountant shall enter the substance of every 
report made to him under sub- section (2) in the register of mutation 
and also make an entry therein respecting the acquisition of any right 
of the kind mentioned in sub- section (2) which he has reason to 
believe to have taken place and of which a, report has not bee made 
under the said sub- section and, at the same time, shall post up a 
complete copy of the entry in a conspicuous place in the village and 
shall give written intimation to all persons appearing from the record 
of rights or the register of mutations to be interested in the 
mutations and to any other person whom he has reason to believe to be 
interested therein.

</section>

<section><tid>94116</tid>
<number>4</number>Should any objection to an entry made under sub- section (3) 
in the register of mutations be made either orally or in writing to 
the village accountant, he shall enter the particulars of the 
objection in the register of disputed cases and shall at once give a 
written acknowledgement in the prescribed form for the objection to 
the person making it.

</section>

<section><tid>1745607</tid>
<number>5</number>The objections made under sub- section (4) shall be decide on 
the basis of possession by the competent authority and orders dis- 
posing of objections entered in the register of disputed cases 
shall be recorded in the register of mutations by the competent 
authority

</section>

<section><tid>1175202</tid>
<number>6</number>After the entries in the register of mutations have been 
tested and found correct,. the entries shall be transferred to the 
record of rights and shall be certified by such officer as may be 
prescribed in this behalf.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>558</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>779446</tid>
<number>47</number>Penalty for neglect to afford information. The Collector may, 
if he is of opinion that any person has wilfully neglected to make the 
report required by section 46 within the prescribed period, impose on 
such person a penalty not exceeding twenty- five rupees.

</article>



<article><tid>1724897</tid>
<number> 48</number> Assistance in preparation of maps. Subject to rules made under 
this Act,-
<section><tid>846460</tid>
<number>a</number>any revenue officer may, for the purpose of preparing or 
revising any map or plan required for or in connection with 
any record or register under this Chapter, exercise any of 
the powers of the survey officer under section 27 except the 
power of assessing the cost of hired labour; and

</section>

<section><tid>1893650</tid>
<number>b</number>any revenue officer not below the rank of sub- divisional 
officer may assess the cost of the preparation or revision of 
such maps or plans and all expenses incidental thereto, and 
such costs and expense' shall be recoverable in the same 
manner as an arrear of land revenue.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>443046</tid>
<number>49</number>Certified copies. Certified copies of entries in the record of 
rights may be granted by such officers and on payment of such fees as 
may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>348157</tid>
<number>50</number>Maps and other records open to inspection. Subject to such 
rules and on payment of such fees, if any as may be prescribed, all 
maps and land records shall be open to inspection by the public during 
office hours, and' Certified extracts therefrom or Certified copies 
thereof may be given to all persons applying for the same.

</article>



<article><tid>1848304</tid>
<number>51</number>Power to transfer duty of maintaining maps and records to 
settlement officer. When a local area is under settlement, the duty of 
maintaining the maps and records may, under the orders of the 
Administrator, be transferred from the Collector to the settlement 
officer.
CHAP 
BOUNDARIES AND BOUNDARY MARKS

CHAPTER VI.- BOUNDARIES AND BOUNDARY MARKS


</article>



<article><tid>1878543</tid>
<number>52</number>Determination of village boundaries. The boundaries of 
villages, survey numbers, sub- divisions and fields shall be fix 4d, and 
all disputes relating thereto shall be determined, by survey officers 
or by such other officers as may be appointed by the Administrator for 
the purpose, in accordance with the rules made in this behalf.

</article>



<article><tid>937500</tid>
<number> 53</number> Effect of settlement of boundary.
<section><tid>515536</tid>
<number>1</number>The settlement of a  
boundary under this Chapter shall be determinative-

<subsection><tid>1183663</tid>
<number>a</number>of the proper position of the boundary line or boundary 
marks; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>559</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1188819</tid>
<number>b</number>of the rights of the landholders on either side of the 
boundary fixed in respect of the land adjudged to appertain, 
or not to appertain, to their respective holdings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1013124</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a boundary has been so fixed, the Collector may at any 
time summarily evict any landholder who is wrongfully in possession of 
any land which has been adjudged in the settlement of a boundary not 
to appertain to his holding or to the holding of any person through or 
under whom he claims.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1289778</tid>
<number>54</number>Construction and repair of boundary marks. It shall be lawful 
for any survey officer authorised in this behalf to specify, or' pause 
to be constructed, laid out, maintained or repaired, boundary marks of 
villages or survey numbers or subdivisions and to assess all charges 
incurred thereby on the holders or others having an interest therein.

</article>



<article><tid>1589416</tid>
<number>55</number>Description of boundary marks. The boundary marks shall be of 
such description and shall be constructed, laid out, maintained or 
repaired in such manner and shall be of such dimensions and materials 
as may, subject to the rules made under this Act, be determined by the 
Collector or other officer appointed for the purpose.

</article>



<article><tid>1180049</tid>
<number>56</number>Responsibilities for maintaining boundary marks. Every 
landholder shall be responsible for the maintenance an good repair of 
the boundary marks of his holding and for any charge, reasonably 
incurred on account of the same by the revenue officers in case of 
alteration, removal or disrepair. It shall be the duty of the village 
officers and servants to prevent the destruction or unauthorised 
alteration of the village boundary marks.

</article>



<article><tid>575290</tid>
<number>57</number>Collector to have charge of boundary marks. After the 
introduction of survey and settlement in a district, the charge of the 
boundary marks shall devolve on the Collector and it shall be his duty 
to take measures for their construction, laying out, maintenance and 
repair.

</article>



<article><tid>209200</tid>
<number>58</number>Penalty for injuring boundary marks. Any person wilfully 
erasing, removing or injuring a boundary mark shall be liable to 
such penalty not exceeding fifty rupees 
as the competent authority may impose.
CHAP 
REALISATION OF LAND REVENUE MO OTHER PUBLIC DEMANDS

CHAPTER VII.- REALISATION OF LAND REVENUE MO OTHER PUBLIC

DEMANDS


</article>



<article><tid>888615</tid>
<number>59</number>Land revenue to be first charge. Land revenue assessed on any 
land shall be the first charge on that land and on the crops, rents 
and profits thereof.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>560</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1706488</tid>
<number>60</number>Payment of land revenue. Land revenue shall be payable at such 
times, in such instalments, to such persons, and at such places, as 
may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>1564764</tid>
<number> 61</number> Arrear of land revenue.
<section><tid>1967526</tid>
<number>1</number>Any instalment of land revenue or  
part thereof which is not paid on the due date shall become an arrear 
of land revenue and the person responsible for the payment shall 
become a defaulter.

</section>

<section><tid>829687</tid>
<number>2</number>A statement of account certified by the circle officer 
shall, for the purpose of this Chapter, be conclusive evidence of the 
existence of the arrear, of its amount and of the person who is the 
defaulter:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall prejudice the 
right of such person to make payment under protest and to question the 
correctness of the account in separate proceedings before the com- 
petent authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>741007</tid>
<number> 62</number> Recovery of arrears. An arrear of land revenue may be 
recovered by any one or more of the following processes, namely:-
<section><tid>364381</tid>
<number>a</number>by serving a written notice of demand on the defaulter-,

</section>

<section><tid>1580956</tid>
<number>b</number>by distraint and sale of the defaulter' s movable 
property, including the produce of the land;

</section>

<section><tid>980545</tid>
<number>c</number>by the attachment and sale of the defaulter' s immovable 
property.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>315915</tid>
<number>63</number>Notice of demand. The form and contents of the notice of 
demand and the officers by whom such notices shall be. issued shall be 
such as may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>232898</tid>
<number> 64</number> Distraint and sale of movable property.
<section><tid>1119683</tid>
<number>1</number>The distraint and  
sale of the movable property of a Defaulter shall be made by such 
officers or class of officers, in such manner and in accordance with 
such procedure, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>878634</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be deemed to authorise the 
distraint or sale of any property which, under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>), is exempt from attachment or sale in 
execution of a decree or of any article set aside exclusively for 
religious use.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>755466</tid>
<number> 65</number> Sale of immovable property.
<section><tid>987030</tid>
<number>1</number>When the Collector is of  
opinion that the processes referred to in clauses (a) and (b) of 
section 62 are not sufficient for the recovery of an arrear, be may, 
in addition to or instead of any of those processes, cause the land in 
respect of which such arrear is due to be attached and sold in the 
prescribed manner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>561</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>958924</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector may also cause the right, title and interest of 
the defaulter in any other immovable property to be similarly attached 
and sold.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1976412</tid>
<number> 66</number> Notice of sale.
<section><tid>1839430</tid>
<number>1</number>Before effecting the sale of any land or  
other immovable property under the provisions of this Chapter, the 
Collector or other officer empowered in this behalf shall issue such 
notices and proclamations, in such form, in such manner and containing 
such particulars, as may be prescribed; the notices and proclamations 
shall also be published in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>251366</tid>
<number>2</number>A copy of every notice or proclamation issued under sub- section 
 (1) shall be served on the defaulter.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1463715</tid>
<number>67</number>Sale to be by auction. All sales of property, movable or 
immovable, under this Chapter shall be by public auction held in 
accordance with such rules as may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>1367352</tid>
<number>68</number>Prohibition to bid at auction. No officer having any duty to 
perform in connection with any such sale and no person employed by or 
subordinate to such officer shall, either directly or indirectly, bid 
for or acquire any property except on behalf of the Government.

</article>



<article><tid>1430080</tid>
<number>69</number>Sale of perishables. Perishable articles shall be sold by 
auction with the least possible delay and such sale shall be finally 
concluded by the officer conducting the sale.

</article>



<article><tid>1829821</tid>
<number>70</number>Sales not to be excessive. Every sale of property, movable or 
immovable, under the provisions of this Chapter shall, as far as may 
be practicable, be proportionate to the amount of the arrear of land 
revenue to be recovered together with the interest thereon and the 
expenses of attachment and sale.

</article>



<article><tid>1740404</tid>
<number>71</number>Deposit by purchaser of immovable property. In all cases of 
sale of immovable property, the party who is declared to be the 
purchaser shall be required to deposit immediately 25 per cent. of the 
amount of his bid, and the balance within fifteen days of the date of 
sale.

</article>



<article><tid>436955</tid>
<number> 72</number> Failure to make deposit.
<section><tid>222862</tid>
<number>1</number>In default of the payment of  
deposit referred to in section 71, the property shall be put up for 
re- sale and the expenses incurred in connection with the first sale 
shall be borne by the defaulting bidder.

</section>

<section><tid>1864119</tid>
<number>2</number>In default of payment of the balance of the bid amount within 
the period prescribed in section 71, the deposit after defraying 
therefrom the expenses of the sale shall be forfeited to the Govern- 
ment and the property shall be re- sold.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>562</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>226150</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the proceeds of the re- sale are less than the price bid 
by such defaulting purchaser, the difference shall also be recoverable 
from him in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>720157</tid>
<number> 73</number> Setting aside sale. Where immovable property has been sold 
under this Chapter, the defaulter, or any person owning such property 
or holding an interest therein, may, at any time, within thirty days 
of the date of sale or within such further period not exceeding thirty 
days as the Collector may for sufficient cause allow, apply in the 
prescribed manner to the Collector to have the sale set aside-
<section><tid>118664</tid>
<number>a</number>on the ground of some material irregularity or mistake or 
fraud resulting in substantial loss or injury to him, or

</section>

<section><tid>1409136</tid>
<number>b</number>on his depositing in the Collector' s office the amount of 
the arrear specified in the proclamation of sale, the, cost 
of the sale and for payment to the purchaser, a sum equal to 
 5 per cent. of the purchase money.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1283869</tid>
<number>74</number>Confirmation of sale. If, on the expiration of thirty days 
from the date of sale of any immovable property or of the further 
period, if any, allowed under section 73, no application has been made 
for setting aside the sale, or if any such application has been made 
and rejected, the Collector shall make an order confirming the sale 
unless, for reasons to be recorded, the Collector sets aside the sale 
notwithstanding that no application therefor has been made.

</article>



<article><tid>1989505</tid>
<number> 75</number> Refunds.
<section><tid>1920797</tid>
<number>1</number>The Collector shall order the refund and payment  
to me purchaser, of-

<subsection><tid>1801525</tid>
<number>a</number>the amounts deposited by him under section 71; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1499993</tid>
<number>b</number>the sum equal to 5 per cent. of the purchase money 
deposited under clause (b) of section 73;
if the sale is not confirmed or is set aside.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1458363</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector shall order the refund and payment of all the 
moneys deposited under clause (b) of section 73 to the person who made 
the deposit, if the sale is confirmed:
Provided that the Collector may set off the whole or any part of 
any such moneys against any arrears of land revenue or any other 
arrear recoverable as an arrear of land revenue, which may be out- 
santanding against the person who made the deposit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1981928</tid>
<number>76</number>Certificate of purchase. When a, sale held under this Chapter 
is confirmed, he Collector shall put, the person declared to, be the 
purchaser in possession of the property and shall grant him a 
certificate in the prescribed



</article>



<article><tid>350933</tid>
<number>77</number>Application of proceeds of sale. The proceeds of the sale of 
any property- under this Chapter shall be applied in defraying the 
expenses of the sale which shall be determined, in the prescribed 
manner and the balance shall be applied to the payment of the arrears 
on account of which the sale was held and the surplus, if any, shall 
be paid to the person whose property has been sold.

</article>



<article><tid>76155</tid>
<number>78</number>Liability of certified purchaser. The person who has 
purchased any land and to whom a certificate of purchase has been 
granted shall not be liable for the land revenue in respect of the 
land for any period prior to the date of the sale.

</article>



<article><tid>1315584</tid>
<number>79</number>Precautionary measures in certain cases. When the crop of any 
land or any portion of the same is sold, mortgaged or otherwise 
disposed of, the Collector may, if he thinks it necessary, prevent its 
being removed from the land until the demand for the current year in 
respect of the said land is paid. whether the date fixed for the 
payment of the same has arrived or not.

</article>



<article><tid>1519121</tid>
<number> 80</number> Recovery of other public demands. The following moneys may be 
recovered under this Act in the same manner as an arrear of land 
revenue, namely:-
<section><tid>1703882</tid>
<number>a</number>rent, fees and royalties due to the Government for use or 
occupation of land or water or any product of land;

</section>

<section><tid>97267</tid>
<number>b</number>all moneys falling due to the Government under any grant, 
lease or contract which provides that they shall be re- 
coverable as arrears of land revenue;

</section>

<section><tid>652671</tid>
<number>c</number>all sums declared by this Act or any other law for the 
time being in force to be recoverable as an arrear of land 
revenue.
CHAP 
PROCEDURE OF REVENUE OFFICERS: APPEALS AND REVISIONS

CHAPTER VIII.- PROCEDURE OF REVENUE OFFICERS: APPEALS AND

REVISIONS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>953873</tid>
<number> 81</number> Revenue officers to be courts.
<section><tid>1156352</tid>
<number>1</number>A revenue officer, while  
exercising power under this Act or any other law for the time being in 
force to inquire into or to decide any question arising for 
determination between the Government and any person or between parties 
to any proceedings, shall be a revenue court.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>564</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>809773</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to limit or otherwise 
affect the inherent power of the revenue court to make such orders as 
may be necessary for the ends of justice or to prevent the abuse of 
the process of the revenue court.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1852517</tid>
<number>82</number>Place of hearing. Except for reasons to be recorded in 
writing, no revenue officer shall inquire into or hear any case at any 
place outside the local limits of his jurisdiction:
Provided that a sub- divisional officer may inquire into or hear 
any case at the headquarters of the district to which he is appointed.


</article>



<article><tid>564415</tid>
<number>83</number>Power to enter upon and survey land. All revenue officers and 
persons acting under their orders may enter upon and survey any land 
and demarcate boundaries and do all other acts necessary for the 
purpose of discharging their duties under this Act or any other law 
for the time being in force and in so doing, shall cause no more 
damage than the circumstances of the case may require.

</article>



<article><tid>1005297</tid>
<number> 84</number> Power to transfer cases.
<section><tid>863807</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may transfer  
any case or class of cases arising under this Act or any other law for 
the time being in force from any revenue. officer to any other revenue 
officer competent to deal with it.

</section>

<section><tid>767016</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector or a sub- divisional officer may transfer any 
case or class of cases arising under this Act or any other law for the 
time being in force for inquiry or decision from his own Me or from 
the Me of any revenue officer subordinate to him to the file of any 
other revenue officer subordinate to him competent to deal with such 
case or class of cases.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>723743</tid>
<number> 85</number> Power to take evidence, summon witnesses, etc.
<section><tid>1737077</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
revenue officer not lower in rank than a circle officer acting as a 
revenue court shall have power to take evidence and to summon any 
person whose attendance he considers necessary, either as a party or 
as a witness or to produce any document, for the purpose of any 
inquiry which such officer is legally empowered to make; and all 
persons so summoned shall be bound to attend either in person or by an 
authorised agent as such officer. may direct, and to produce such 
documents as may be, required.

</section>

<section><tid>1200022</tid>
<number>2</number>Every summons shall be in writing, signed and sealed by the 
officer issuing it and shall be in such form and be served in such 
manner as may be prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1774573</tid>
<number> 86</number> Compelling attendance of witnesses. If any person on whom a 
summons to attend as witness or to produce any document has been 
served fails to comply with the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>565</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

summons, the officer by whom the summons has been issued under section 
 85 may-

<section><tid>1522457</tid>
<number>a</number>issue a bailable warrant of arrest;

</section>

<section><tid>1552356</tid>
<number>b</number>order him to furnish security for appearance; or

</section>

<section><tid>1183625</tid>
<number>c</number>impose upon him a fine not exceeding rupees twenty.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1073320</tid>
<number> 87</number> Hearing in absence of party.
<section><tid>1024520</tid>
<number>1</number>If, on the date fixed for  
hearing a case or proceeding, a revenue officer finds that a summons 
or notice was not served on any party due to the failure of the 
opposite party to pay the requisite process fees for such service, the 
case or proceeding may be dismissed for default of payment of such 
process fees.

</section>

<section><tid>1618938</tid>
<number>2</number>If any party to a case or proceeding before a revenue officer 
does not appear on the date fixed for hearing, the case may be heard 
and determined in his absence or may be dismissed for default.

</section>

<section><tid>222920</tid>
<number>3</number>The party against whom any order is passed under sub- section 
 (1) or (2) may apply, within thirty days from the date of such order, 
to have it set aside on the ground that he was prevented by sufficient 
cause from paying the requisite process fees or from appearing at the 
hearing; and the revenue officer may, after notice to the opposite 
party and after making such inquiry as he considers necessary, set 
aside the order passed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1159134</tid>
<number> 88</number> Adjournment of hearing.
<section><tid>584975</tid>
<number>1</number>A revenue officer may, from time  
to time, for reasons to be recorded, adjourn the hearing of a case or 
proceeding before him.

</section>

<section><tid>1666461</tid>
<number>2</number>The date and place of an adjourned hearing shall be intimated 
at the time of the adjournment to such of the parties and witnesses as 
are present.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1747855</tid>
<number>89</number>Power to order payment of costs. A revenue officer may direct 
the parties to pay the cost incurred in any case before him and also 
apportion the cost among the parties in such manner and to such extent 
as he may think fit.

</article>



<article><tid>585179</tid>
<number>90</number>Use of force. Where any order is passed under this Act 
directing any person to deliver possession of land or directing the 
eviction of any person from land, such order shall be executed by the 
competent authority in such manner as may be prescribed and it shall 
be lawful for such authority, in accordance with rules to be 
prescribed, to take such steps and use or cause to be used such force 
as may be reasonably necessary for securing compliance with the order.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>566</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>401805</tid>
<number>91</number>Appearances before and applications to revenue officers. All 
appearances before, applications to, and acts to be done before, any 
revenue officer under this Act or any other law for the time being in 
force may be made or done by the parties themselves or by their 
authorised agents or by any legal practitioner:
Provided that any such appearance shall, if the revenue officer 
so directs, be made by the party in person.


</article>



<article><tid>1345946</tid>
<number>92</number>Correction of error or omission. Any revenue officer by whom 
an order was passed in a case or proceeding may, either on his own 
motion or on the application of a party, correct any error or omission 
not affecting a material part of the case or proceeding, after such 
notice to the parties as he may consider necessary.

</article>



<article><tid>887342</tid>
<number> 93</number> Appeals.
<section><tid>1559353</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise expressly provided, an appeal  
shall lie from every original order passed under this Act,--

<subsection><tid>696468</tid>
<number>a</number>if such an order is passed by an officer- subordinate to 
the sub- divisional officer, to the sub- divisional officer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>92138</tid>
<number>b</number>if such an order is passed by the sub- divisional officer, 
to the Collector;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>455871</tid>
<number>c</number>if such an order is passed by the Collector, to the Admi- 
nistrator;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>604359</tid>
<number>d</number>if such an order is passed by an assistant survey and 
settlement officer, to the survey and settlement officer or 
to a revenue officer notified by the Administrator in the 
Official Gazette to be the appellate authority; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1632104</tid>
<number>e</number>if such an order is passed by a survey and settlement 
officer, to the director of settlement and land records or to 
a revenue officer notified by the Administrator in the 
Official Gazette to be the appellate authority.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1119271</tid>
<number>2</number>A second' appeal shall lie against any order passed In first 
appeal,-

<subsection><tid>387333</tid>
<number>a</number>if such an order is passed under clause (a) of subsection 
 (1) to the Collector;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1892748</tid>
<number>b</number>if such an order is passed under clause (b) of subsection 
 (1), to the Administrator;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1690684</tid>
<number>c</number>if such an order is passed under clause (d) of subsection 
 (1), to the director of settlement and land records or to a 
revenue officer notified by the Administrator in the Official 
Gazette to be the second appellate authority; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>567</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>467697</tid>
<number>d</number>If such an order is passed under clause (e) of sub., 
section (1), to the Administrator.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1081928</tid>
<number> 94</number> Limitation of appeals.
<section><tid>1674704</tid>
<number>1</number>No appeal shall lie,- 

<subsection><tid>45649</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a first appeal, after the expiry of thirty 
days from the date of the order appealed against; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1873283</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a second appeal, after the expiry of sixty 
days from the date of the order appealed against.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1508897</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the above periods, the time required to obtain 
copies of the order appealed against shall be excluded.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1110518</tid>
<number>95</number>Revision. The Administrator or the Collector may, at any time, 
either on his own motion, or on the application of any party, can for 
the records of any proceedings before any revenue officer subordinate 
to him for the purpose of satisfying himself as to the legality or the 
propriety of any order passed by such revenue officer, and may pass 
such order in reference thereto as he thinks fit
Provided that he shall not vary or reverse any order affecting 
any right between private persons without having given to the parties 
interested notice to appear and be heard.


</article>



<article><tid>139933</tid>
<number> 96</number> Review of orders.
<section><tid>273267</tid>
<number>1</number>A revenue officer may, either on his,  
own motion or on the application of any party interested, review any 
order passed by himself or by any of his predecessors- in- office and 
pass such order in reference thereto as he thinks fit:
Provided that a revenue officer subordinate to the Collector 
shall, before reviewing any order under this section, obtain the 
permission of the Collector and the Collector shall, before reviewing 
an order passed by any of his predecessors- in- office obtain the 
permission of the Administrator.


</section>

<section><tid>1098830</tid>
<number>2</number>No order affecting any question of right between private 
persons shall be reviewed except on the application of a party to the 
proceedings or except after notice to the other party and no 
application for the review of such order shall be entertained unless 
it is made within ninety days from the date of the order.

</section>

<section><tid>712811</tid>
<number>3</number>No order shall be reviewed except on the following grounds, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>854647</tid>
<number>i</number>discovery of new and important matter of evidence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>400166</tid>
<number>ii</number>some mistake or error apparent on the face of the 
record; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1492867</tid>
<number>iii</number>any other sufficient reason.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>568</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>678760</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of this section, the Collector shall be 
deemed to be the successor- in- office of any revenue officer who has 
left the district or who has ceased to exercise powers as a revenue 
officer and to whom there is no successor in the district.

</section>

<section><tid>1483288</tid>
<number>5</number>An order which has been dealt with in appeal or on revision 
shall not be reviewed by any officer subordinate to the appellate or 
revisional authority.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>985403</tid>
<number> 97</number> Stay of execution of orders.
<section><tid>1985014</tid>
<number>1</number>A revenue officer who has  
passed any order or his successor- in- office may, at any time before 
the expiry of the period prescribed for appeal, direct the stay of 
execution of such order for such period as he thinks fit provided that 
no appeal has been filed.

</section>

<section><tid>639018</tid>
<number>2</number>Any authority before whom a case is pending in appeal or 
revision may direct the stay of execution of the order appealed from 
or under revision for such period as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1081296</tid>
<number>3</number>The revenue officer or other authority directing such stay 
of execution of any order may impose such conditions, or order such 
security to be furnished as he or it may think fit.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1970149</tid>
<number> 98</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>748454</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Part.

</section>

<section><tid>1703680</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for-

<subsection><tid>511398</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of appointment of revenue officers, survey 
officers and settlement officers, and other village officers 
and servants, their powers and duties, the official seals, if 
any, to be used by them and the size and description of the 
seals;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>977097</tid>
<number>b</number>the Collector' s powers of superintendence and control 
over other officers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>336381</tid>
<number>c</number>the officers who should hear and decide disputes regard- 
ing rights in or over any property claimed by or against the 
Government and the procedure to be followed by them;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518400</tid>
<number>d</number>the disposal of Government lands by assignment or grant 
to individuals or to public purposes and the terms and 
conditions subject to which such assignments or grants may be 
made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>157847</tid>
<number>e</number>the preservation and disposal of trees, brush, wood, 
jungle and other natural products on Government land and the 
recovery of the value of trees or other natural product 
unauthorisedly appropriated by persons;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>569</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1908085</tid>
<number>f</number>the procedure for summary eviction of trespassers on 
Government land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>433943</tid>
<number>g</number>the alteration and revision of the land revenue in cams. 
of alluvion or diluvion or of diversion of land for purposes 
other than agriculture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1054903</tid>
<number>h</number>the grant of permission to use agricultural land for non- 
agricultural purposes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>276081</tid>
<number>i</number>the determination of additional rates for use of water;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>427893</tid>
<number>j</number>the circumstances in which remission or suspension of 
revenue may be made and the rate of such remission or suspen- 
sion;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1773952</tid>
<number>k</number>the form of receipt for payment of land revenue;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>932090</tid>
<number>l</number>the conduct of surveys and settlements of land revenue;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1709754</tid>
<number>m</number>the manner of estimating the cost of cultivation and 
other expenses in relation to the inquiry into profits of 
agriculture;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1539007</tid>
<number>n</number>the division of survey numbers into sub- divisions and the 
assessment of sub- divisions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>250111</tid>
<number>o</number>the statistical, fiscal and other records and registers 
to be prepared and maintained under this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1391872</tid>
<number>p</number>the manner in which the costs and expenses incidental to 
revenue survey or the construction, repair and maintenance of 
boundary marks shall be determined and apportioned between 
persons who are liable to bear the same;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1073638</tid>
<number>q</number>the fixing, construction, laying out, maintenance and 
repair of boundary marks, and the settlement of disputes 
relating thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1736149</tid>
<number>r</number>the division of areas into units for determining the 
revenue- rates and the preparation of the table of revenue- 
rates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1287556</tid>
<number>s</number>the preparation and the preliminary and final publication 
of the record of rights and the table of revenue- rates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>214783</tid>
<number>t</number>the hearing and disposal of objections to any entry or 
omission in the table of revenue- rates, the record of rights, 
and the register of mutations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>590161</tid>
<number>u</number>the manner and extent of alteration or revision of reve- 
nue- rates during the term of settlement;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>570</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1568438</tid>
<number>v</number>the correction of bona fide errors and mistakes in the 
revenue records, registers and maps prepared under this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1031842</tid>
<number>w</number>the manner in which the average yield of crops of land 
shall be ascertained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1139557</tid>
<number>x</number>the manner of holding inquiries by revenue officers under 
this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1854210</tid>
<number>y</number>the application of the provisions of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5 of <year>1908</year>), to cases and proceedings before 
a revenue court;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>810346</tid>
<number>z</number>the form of summons and other processes, notices, orders 
and proclamations to be issued or made by revenue officers 
and the Manner of their service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1310214</tid>
<number>aa</number>the procedure for the attachment and sale of property 
and the confirmation and the setting aside of sales of 
immovable property under Chapter VII;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1118993</tid>
<number>bb</number>the manner of publication of notices and proclamations 
of attachment and sale of property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1043784</tid>
<number>cc</number>the manner In which the cost and expenses incidental to 
the attachment and sale of property shall be determined;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1522927</tid>
<number>dd</number>the manner of payment of deposit and of the purchase 
Money of property sold for arrears of land revenue;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1444845</tid>
<number>ee</number>the circumstances in which precautionary measures for 
securing the land revenue under section 79 may be taken;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>292639</tid>
<number>ff</number>the procedure for the transfer of cases from one revenue 
Officer to another;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1854072</tid>
<number>gg</number>the manner of preferring appeals or applications for 
revision or review, the documents to accompany the memorandum 
of appeal or such application and the fee, if any, leviable 
therefor',

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>708733</tid>
<number>hh</number>the grant of certified copies and the payment of fees 
for inspection and grant of certified copies of revenue 
records and registers;

<subsubsection><tid>1256712</tid>
<number>ii</number>the mode of execution of any orders directing any per- 
son to deliver possession of land or to be evicted from land, 
including the use of force for securing compliance with such 
order;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>66610</tid>
<number>jj</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.






</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1350557</tid>
<number> 99</number> Rights of raiyats.
<section><tid>1965214</tid>
<number>1</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby  
declared that subject to the other provisions of this Act,-

<subsection><tid>95420</tid>
<number>a</number>the rights of a raiyat in his land shall be permanent, 
heritable and transferable;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>914944</tid>
<number>b</number>the raiyat shall be entitled by himself, his servants, 
under- raiyats, agents or other representatives to erect farm 
buildings, construct wells or tanks or make other 
improvements thereon for the better cultivation of the land 
or its convenient or profitable use;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1461304</tid>
<number>c</number>the raiyat is entitled to plant trees on his land, to 
enjoy the products thereof and to fell, utilise or dispose of 
the timber of any trees on his land.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>772711</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall entitle a raiyat to use his 
land to the detriment of any adjoining land which is not his or In 
contravention of the provisions of any other law for the time being in 
force applicable to such lands.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1301772</tid>
<number> 100</number> Reservation of land for personal cultivation.
<section><tid>1887439</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
raiyat who, at the commencement of this Act, owns land. in excess of a 
basic holding shall be entitled to apply to the, competent authority 
for the reservation for his personal cultivation., of any parcel or 
parcels of his land leased to under- raiyats.

</section>

<section><tid>1403526</tid>
<number>2</number>Every application under sub- section (1) shall be in the pres- 
cribed form and shall be made in the prescribed manner within a period 
of one year from the commencement of this Act.
Explanation.- In, the case of a person under disability, the 
application shall be, made by his guardian or his authorised agent, as 
the case may be.'



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1677747</tid>
<number> 101</number> Procedure for reservation of lands.
<section><tid>1182491</tid>
<number>1</number>The competent  
authority shall, on an application made under section 100, issue 
notice together with a copy of the application to each of the under- 
raiyats holding land from the applicant requiring the. under- raiyat to 
submit his objections, if any, within a period of ninety days from the 
date of service of such notice or within such further period as the 
competent authority may allow.

</section>

<section><tid>1940719</tid>
<number>2</number>An under- raiyat on whom a notice has been served under sub- 
Section (1), shall furnish to the competent authority within, the 
period aforesaid details of lands owned by him or held as under- 
raiyat of any other raiyat and of lands which he selects for retention 
by him.

</section>

<section><tid>1019594</tid>
<number>3</number>The competent authority shall, after considering the objec- 
tions and the details, if any, furnished by the under- raiyats and 
after making such inquiry as it may consider necessary, determine the 
land or lands, not exceeding the permissible limit, which in its 
opinion having regard to all the circumstances of the case may be 
reserved for personal cultivation of the raiyat and the lands which 
each of his under- raiyats may be allowed, to retain.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1913269</tid>
<number> 102</number> " Permissible limit" defined.
<section><tid>1487322</tid>
<number>1</number>In section 101," permissible  
limit" means an area of land which a raiyat may resume from under- 
raiyats for personal cultivation, that is to say,-

<subsection><tid>1810835</tid>
<number>a</number>In the case of a person under disability, 25 standard 
acres;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1917068</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of any other person who-

<subsubsection><tid>565080</tid>
<number>i</number>owns a basic holding or less, the entire area own by 
him;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1993269</tid>
<number>ii</number>owns more than a basic holding but not exceeding a 
family holding, one- half of the area leased to under- raiyats 
or the area by which the land under his personal cultivation 
falls, short of a basic holding, whichever it greater;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1191981</tid>
<number>iii</number>owns more than a family- holding,-

<subsubsubsection><tid>276619</tid>
<number>1</number>if he has no land, or any land which' is less th family 
holding under his personal cultivation, half of the area 
leased to under- raiyats but not exceeding the area by which 
land under his personal cultivation falls short of a family 
holding, provided that the under- raiyat is left with not less 
than a basic holding a provided further that a raiyat shall 
in any case be en titled to resume an area by which land 
under his persona cultivation falls short of a basic holding; 
and,

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1980287</tid>
<number>2</number>if he has a family holding or more under his personal 
cultivation,' the area leased to under- raiyat rats but no 
exceeding the area by which land in' his personal cultivation 
falls short of 25 standard acres, provided that the under- 
raiyat is left with riot less than a holding.
Explanation.-- For the purpose of determining the permissible limit of 
a raiyat under this sub- section, any non- resumable Ian which he may 
hold as an under- raiyat, shall also be taken into account.


</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1980287</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section under- 
raiyat who under any law, custom or usage is it liable to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>573</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

eviction at the commencement of this Act on the ground that the land 
is required for personal cultivation, shall in all cases be left with 
a basic holding or the land actually held by him, whichever is less.


</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1765836</tid>
<number>3</number>Any transfer of land made on or after the 10th August, <year>1957</year> 
shall be disregarded in computing the permissible limit.


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>401768</tid>
<number>103</number>Land deemed to be reserved for personal cultivation in 
certain cases. In the case of a raiyat who at the commencement of this 
Act does not own land in excess of a basic holding, all lands owned by 
him and held by under- raiyats at such commencement shall, subject to 
the provisions of sub- section (2) of section 102, be deemed to have 
been reserved for his personal cultivation.
Explanation.- Any transfer of land made on or after the 10th 
August, <year>1957</year> shall be disregarded in determining the extent of land 
owned by a raiyat at the commencement of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1041528</tid>
<number>104</number>Non- resumable land. The competent authority shall declare 
every land which, under sub- section (3) of section 101, an under- 
raiyat is allowed to retain to be the non- resumable land of the under- 
raiyat.

</article>



<article><tid>1731645</tid>
<number> 105</number> Right to lease.
<section><tid>1342869</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, a  
raiyat may lease out his land to another person on such rent not 
exceeding the maximum rent referred to in section 111 as may be agreed 
upon between him and such person.

</section>

<section><tid>1375992</tid>
<number>2</number>Every lease of land made after the commencement of this Act 
shall be for a period of five years and at the end of the said period, 
and thereafter at the end of every such period of five years, the 
tenancy shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), be deemed 
to be renewed for a further period of five years on the same terms and 
conditions except to the extent that a modification thereof consistent 
with this Act is agreed to by both parties.

</section>

<section><tid>150367</tid>
<number>3</number>In respect of, any lease made after the commencement of this 
Act, a raiyat who is a member of the Armed Forces of the Union, on his 
discharge from service or posting to the reserve, may by giving the 
under- raiyat three months' notice in writing before the expiry of any 
year, and any other raiyat may by giving the under- raiyat one year' s 
notice in writing before the expiry of any term of five years, 
terminate the tenancy if the raiyat requires the land bona fide for 
personal cultivation by him.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1001177</tid>
<number> 106</number> Land left uncultivated.
<section><tid>917220</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Collector is satisfied  
that any land has remained uncultivated for a period of not less than 
two consecutive years. otherwise than in accordance with rules made in 
this behalf under this Act, and that it is necessary for the purpose 
of ensuring

<pagefootnote><pagenum>574</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the full and efficient use of the land for agriculture to do so, he 
may after making such inquiry as may be prescribed lease out the land 
in accordance with the rules made under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>1046563</tid>
<number>2</number>Any lease made under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to be a 
lease made by the raiyat under sub- section (1) of section 105.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1279633</tid>
<number> 107</number> Relinquishment.
<section><tid>950662</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to any rules that may be made  
under this Act, a raiyat may relinquish his rights in respect of any 
land in his possession in favour of Government by giving a notice in 
writing to the competent authority in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed, not less than three months before the close of any year 
and thereupon he shall cease to be a raiyat in respect of that land 
from the year next following the date of notice:
Provided that relinquishment of only a part of a holding or of a 
holding which, or part of which, is subject to an encumbrance or a 
charge, shall not be valid.


</section>

<section><tid>907911</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person relinquishes his rights to a land under sub- 
section (1), the way to which lies through other land retained by him, 
any future holder of the land relinquished shall be entitled to a 
right of way through the land retained.
CHAP 
RIGHTS OF UNDER- RAIYATS

CHAPTER X.- RIGHTS OF UNDER- RAIYATS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1141714</tid>
<number> 108</number> Interest of under- raiyats.
<section><tid>1515798</tid>
<number>1</number>The interest of an under-  
raiyat in any land held by him as such shall be heritable but, save as 
otherwise provided in this Act, shall not be transferable.

</section>

<section><tid>1181651</tid>
<number>2</number>No under- raiyat shall be evicted from his land except as pro- 
vided in this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1436533</tid>
<number>109</number>Right to create a mortgage or charge. It shall be lawful for 
an under- raiyat to create a simple mortgage or a charge on his 
interest in the land leased to him, in favour of the Government or a 
co- operative society in consideration of any loan advanced to him by 
the Government or such society; and in the event of his making default 
in the repayment of such loan in accordance with its terms, it shall 
be lawful for the Government or the society, as the case may be, to 
cause his interest in the land to be attached and sold and the 
proceeds applied in payment of such loan.

</article>



<article><tid>1535861</tid>
<number>110</number>Right to make improvements. An under- raiyat may, with the 
permission in writing of the raiyat, or if permission is refused 
without sufficient reason or is not given within two months, after 
obtaining the orders of the competent authority in the prescribed 
manner, make at his own expense any improvement to the land held by 
him, but shall not become liable to

<pagefootnote><pagenum>575</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

pay a higher rate of rent on account of any increase of production or 
of any change in the nature of the crop raised, as a consequence of 
such improvement.


</article>



<article><tid>1840061</tid>
<number> 111</number> Maximum rent. The rent payable by an under- raiyat in respect 
of any land held by him shall not exceed,--
<section><tid>1926362</tid>
<number>a</number>where the rent is payable in kind as a share of the 
produce, one- fourth of the produce of such land or its value 
estimated in the prescribed manner if plough cattle for the 
cultivation of such land is supplied by the raiyat and one- 
fifth of such produce or its value as so estimated if plough 
cattle is not supplied by the raiyat;

</section>

<section><tid>704056</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, four times the land revenue payable in 
respect of the land.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>57653</tid>
<number> 112</number> Payment of rent.
<section><tid>1945615</tid>
<number>1</number>The rent payable by an under- raiyat  
shall, subject to the provisions of section 111, be the rent agreed 
upon between him and the raiyat, or where there is no such agreement, 
the reasonable rent.

</section>

<section><tid>1614889</tid>
<number>2</number>The rent shall be paid at such times and in such manner as 
may have been agreed upon, or in the absence of such agreement, as may 
be prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>91936</tid>
<number> 113</number> Reasonable rent.
<section><tid>415086</tid>
<number>1</number>The competent authority may, on  
application made to it in this behalf by the raiyat or the under- 
raiyat, determine the reasonable rent for any land.

</section>

<section><tid>494058</tid>
<number>2</number>The form of application under sub- section (1) and the 
procedure to be followed by the competent authority shall be such as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1303495</tid>
<number>3</number>In determining the reasonable rent, the competent authority 
shall have regard to-

<subsection><tid>1462628</tid>
<number>a</number>the rental value of lands used for similar purposes in 
the locality;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>872696</tid>
<number>b</number>the profits of agriculture of similar lands in the 
locality;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>186661</tid>
<number>c</number>the price of crops and commodities in the locality;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>612945</tid>
<number>d</number>the improvements, if any, made to the land by the 
raiyat or the under- raiyat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1507663</tid>
<number>e</number>the land revenue payable in respect of the land; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>445691</tid>
<number>f</number>any other factor which. may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>576</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>802847</tid>
<number>4</number>Where the reasonable rent for any land has been determined under 
this section, it shall not be altered for a period of five years 
except on any of the following grounds, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1038736</tid>
<number>a</number>that the quality of the land has deteriorated by flood or 
other natural causes;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1973715</tid>
<number>b</number>that there has been an increase in the produce of the 
land on account of improvements made to it at the expense of 
the raiyat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>646598</tid>
<number>c</number>that the extent of land has been altered by more than one acre 
by alluvion or diluvion.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>807961</tid>
<number>d</number>that the land has been partially or wholly rendered unfit 
for cultivation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>649369</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in sub- sections (1) to (4) shall affect the right of 
the Government to make an order directing the determination of the 
reasonable rent of lands in any specified area.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>417327</tid>
<number> 114</number> Commutation of rent payable in kind.
<section><tid>258333</tid>
<number>1</number>In any case in which  
rent is payable in kind, the raiyat or the under- raiyat may apply in 
writing to the competent authority in the prescribed form and manner, 
for commuting the rent into money rent.

</section>

<section><tid>1074960</tid>
<number>2</number>On receipt of such application, the competent authority 
shall, after giving notice to the other party, determine the money 
rent payable for the land in accordance with the following provisions 
but not exceeding the maximum rent specified in section 111.

</section>

<section><tid>497084</tid>
<number>3</number>In determining the money rent, regard shall be had to-

<subsection><tid>606525</tid>
<number>a</number>the average money rent payable by under- raiyats for land 
of similar description and with similar advantages in the 
vicinity;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>687967</tid>
<number>b</number>the average value of the rent for the land actually 
received by the raiyat during the three years preceding the 
date of application;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1369206</tid>
<number>c</number>the average prices of crops and commodities in the 
locality during the three years preceding the date of 
application;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>317433</tid>
<number>d</number>the improvements, if any, made to the land by the raiyat 
or the under- raiyat; and
 (e) any other factor which may be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>841256</tid>
<number>115</number>Receipt for payment of rent. Every raiyat shall give or cause 
to be given a receipt for the rent received by him or on his behalf in 
such from as may be prescribed duly signed by him or his authorised 
agent.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>577</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1881885</tid>
<number>116</number>Refund of rent recovered in excess. If any raiyat recovers 
from an- under- raiyat rent in excess of the amount due under this Act, 
he shall forthwith refund the excess amount so recovered and shall 
also be liable to punishment as provided in this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>1056918</tid>
<number> 117</number> Suspension or remission of rent.
<section><tid>1306807</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a raiyat has  
obtained from or been granted by the Government any relief by way of 
suspension or remission, whether in whole or in part, of the land 
revenue payable in respect of his land, he shall be bound to give, and 
the under- raiyat concerned shall be entitled to receive from the 
raiyat, a corresponding or proportionate relief by way of suspension 
or remission of rent payable in respect of such land.

</section>

<section><tid>1835604</tid>
<number>2</number>The nature and extent of the relief which a raiyat is bound 
to give and which the under- raiyat is entitled to receive under sub- 
section (1) shall be determined in accordance with the rules made 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1591337</tid>
<number>3</number>No suit shall lie and no decree of a civil court shall be 
executed for the recovery by a raiyat of any rent the payment of which 
has been remitted, or during the period for which the payment of such 
rent has been suspended, under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>218650</tid>
<number>4</number>The period during which the payment of rent is suspended 
under this section shall be excluded in computing the period of 
limitation for any suit or proceeding for the recovery of such rent.

</section>

<section><tid>1037276</tid>
<number>5</number>If any raiyat fails to suspend or remit the payment of rent 
as provided in sub- section (1), he shall be liable to refund to the 
under- raiyat the amount recovered by him in contravention of the 
provisions of this section and shall also be liable to punishment as 
provided in this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1433109</tid>
<number> 118</number> Eviction of under- raiyat.
<section><tid>502338</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall be evicted  
from any land held by him as under- raiyat except under the order of 
the competent authority made on any of the following grounds, namely:-

<subsection><tid>189898</tid>
<number>a</number>that the land has been reserved for personal cultivation 
of the raiyat under section 101, or is deemed to have been 
reserved for personal cultivation of the raiyat under section 
103;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1237620</tid>
<number>b</number>that a notice has been given to the under- raiyat under 
sub- section (3) of section 105;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1311343</tid>
<number>c</number>that the under- raiyat has intentionally and wilfully 
committed such acts of waste as are calculated to impair 
materially or permanently the value or utility of the land 
for agricultural purposes;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>578</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1370818</tid>
<number>d</number>that the under- raiyat has failed to pay rent within a 
period of three months after it falls due:
Provided that the competent authority may, if it thinks fit, 
grant further time not exceeding six months for payment of the rent;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>712205</tid>
<number>e</number>that the under- raiyat, not being a person under 
disability, has, after the commencement of this Act, sublet 
the land without the consent in writing of the raiyat.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>326216</tid>
<number>2</number>No order for eviction of an under- raiyat shall be executed 
till the standing crops, if any, on the land are harvested.

</section>

<section><tid>509401</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any land has been reserved for the personal cultivation 
of a raiyat by an order made under sub- section (3) of section 101, no 
suit or application for the eviction of the under- raiyat in respect of 
such land under clause (a) of sub- section (1) shall lie after the 
expiry of five years from the commencement of this Act or one year 
from the date of the said order, whichever is later:
Provided that where any such raiyat is a person under disability, 
such suit or application may be instituted or made within a period of 
five years from the date when the disability ceases.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, the disability of a 
person shall cease,-


<subsection><tid>825692</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case, of a widow, if she remarries, on the date of 
her remarriage or if any person succeeds to the widow on her 
death, on the date of her death;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>672352</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a minor, on the date of his attaining 
majority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>80346</tid>
<number>c</number>in the case of a woman who is unmarried or who is 
divorced or judicially separated from her husband. on the 
date of her marriage or, remarriage, as the case may be, or 
in the case of a woman whose husband is a person falling 
under clause (d) or (e), on the date', on which the 
disability of the husband ceases;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>189512</tid>
<number>d</number>in the case of a person who is a member of the Armed 
Forces of the Union, on the date of his discharge from 
service or of his posting to the reserve;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>290914</tid>
<number>e</number>in the case of a person suffering from a physical or 
mental disability, on the date on which the disability ceases 
to exist.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1939478</tid>
<number>119</number>Restoration of possession of land to under- raiyat. Where a 
person who has taken possession of any land by evicting an under- 
raiyat therefrom on the ground that the land had been reserved for 
personal cultivation by him, fails to cultivate such land personally 
within one year from the date on which he took

<pagefootnote><pagenum>579</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

possession thereof or ceases to cultivate such land personally in any 
year during a period of four years next following, the under- raiyat 
shall be entitled to be restored to possession of the land from which 
he was evicted.

Explanation.- For the purpose of this section, land shall not be 
deemed to be under the personal cultivation of a person (not being a  
  person under disability) unless such person or a member of his family 
engages himself in the principal agricultural operations.


</article>



<article><tid>1804666</tid>
<number> 120</number> Certain lands to be non- resumable land of under- raiyat. If a 
raiyat fails to--
<section><tid>1845669</tid>
<number>a</number>apply for reservation of any land within the period 
prescribed in section 100, and the land is not deemed to have 
been reserved under section 103, or

</section>

<section><tid>666008</tid>
<number>b</number>File a suit or application for the eviction of the under- 
raiyat from any land reserved under section 101 within the 
period prescribed in sub- section (3) of section 118, or

</section>

<section><tid>1985680</tid>
<number>c</number>cultivate or ceases to cultivate the land and the under- 
raiyat is restored to possession of the land under section 
119,
the competent authority may suo motu and shall, on application, after 
making such inquiry as may be prescribed, declare the land to be the 
non- resumable land of the under- raiyat.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1175198</tid>
<number> 121</number> Compensation for improvements.
<section><tid>346192</tid>
<number>1</number>An under- raiyat who has  
made any improvement at his own expense on the' land leased to him 
shall, if he is to be evicted under the provisions' of this Chapter, 
be entitled to receive compensation, before he is so evicted, for such 
improvement as, in the opinion of the competent authority, is 
reasonable.

</section>

<section><tid>1559183</tid>
<number>2</number>The compensation payable to an under- raiyat under sub- section 
 (1) shall be determined in accordance with the value of such 
improvements on the date of eviction, and in determining such 
compensation, regard shall be had to the following matters, namely:

<subsection><tid>280810</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount by which the value of the land has increased 
by reason of the improvement;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>400590</tid>
<number>b</number>the condition of the improvement at the date of the 
determination of the value thereof and the probable duration 
of its effect;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1196194</tid>
<number>c</number>the labour and capital involved in the making of the 
improvement; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1829797</tid>
<number>d</number>the advantages secured by the under- raiyat in consi- 
deration of the improvement made by him.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>580</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>388393</tid>
<number>3</number>In any case in which compensation is payable to an under- 
raiyat under this section, the competent authority may direct that-

<subsection><tid>1045026</tid>
<number>a</number>the whole or any part of any loan which the underraiyat 
has taken on the security of his interest in the land under 
section 109 and which is outstanding shall be deducted from 
such compensation and paid to the Government or the co- 
operative society, as the case may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1987041</tid>
<number>b</number>any arrear of rent due by the under- raiyat to the raiyat 
and the costs, if any, awarded to the raiyat shall be 
adjusted against the compensation.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>75489</tid>
<number>122</number>Underraiyat may remove building, works, etc., not deemed 
improvements. An under- raiyat against whom an order of eviction has 
been passed, shall be. entitled to remove within such time as is 
deemed reasonable by the competent authority any work of improvement 
which can be severed from the land and which the under- raiyat desires 
to remove, or any building or construction or work (which is not an  
  improvement) in respect of which the raiyat is not willing to pay the 
compensation.

</article>



<article><tid>1121826</tid>
<number> 123</number> Restoration of possession of land in certain other cases.

<section><tid>454837</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an under- raiyat of any land has, on or after the 10th  
August, <year>1957</year>, surrendered, or been evicted from, such land and the 
surrender or eviction could not have taken place if this Act had been 
in force on the date of such surrender or eviction, the competent 
authority may, suo motu or on application made by the underraiyat, 
restore him to possession of the land which he surrendered or from 
which he was evicted unless some other under- raiyat, not being a 
member of the raiyat' s family, had bona fide been admitted to 
possession of such land.

</section>

<section><tid>1299302</tid>
<number>2</number>The competent authority shall, before making an order under 
sub- section (1), make such inquiry as may be prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1407463</tid>
<number>124</number>Relief against termination of tenancy for act of waste. Where 
a tenancy is sought to be terminated on the ground that the 
underraiyat has materially impaired the value or utility of the land 
for agricultural purposes, if the damage to the land admits of being 
repaired or if pecuniary compensation would afford adequate relief, no 
proceeding for eviction shall lie against the under- raiyat unless and 
until the raiyat has served on the under- raiyat a notice in writing 
specifying the damage complained of and the under- raiyat has failed 
within a period of one year from the service of such notice to repair 
the damage or to pay compensation therefor.

</article>



<article><tid>37898</tid>
<number> 125</number> Surrender of land by underraiyat.
<section><tid>1612733</tid>
<number>1</number>After the commencement  
of this Act, no under- raiyat shall surrender any land held by him as 
such, and no raiyat shall enter upon the land surrendered by the 
underraiyat, without the previous permission in writing of the 
competent authority.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>581</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1191844</tid>
<number>2</number>Such permission shall be granted if, after making such 
Inquiry as may be prescribed, the competent authority is satisfied 
that the proposed surrender is bona fide and in case the surrender is 
by a person who was holding the land as under- raiyat immediately 
before the commencement of this Act, the permissible limit of the 
raiyat concerned is not exceeded by such surrender; in other cases, 
, the permission shall be refused.

</section>

<section><tid>1306635</tid>
<number>3</number>Where permission is refused in any case, and the underraiyat 
gives a declaration in writing relinquishing his rights in the land, 
the competent authority shall, in accordance with the rules made in 
this behalf, lease out the land to any other person who shall acquire 
all the rights of the under- raiyat who relinquished his rights.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1352959</tid>
<number>126</number>Transfer of ownership of land to under- raiyats. Subject to 
the other provisions of this Act, the ownership of any land which is 
declared to be the non- resumable land of an underraiyat tinder section 
 104 or section 120 shall stand transferred from the raiyat thereof to 
the under- raiyat with effect from the date of such declaration, and 
the under- raiyat shall become the owner of such land and be liable to 
pay land revenue therefor.

</article>



<article><tid>94810</tid>
<number> 127</number> Compensation to raiyat.
<section><tid>826350</tid>
<number>1</number>In respect of every land the  
ownership of which stands transferred to the under- raiyat under 
section 126, the raiyat shall be entitled to compensation which shall 
consist of the aggregate of the following amounts, that is to say,-

<subsection><tid>171882</tid>
<number>a</number>an amount equal to thirty times the full land revenue 
payable for the land or, if the land is held revenue- free or 
at a concessional rate, thirty times the amount of land 
revenue payable for similar lands in the locality;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1552999</tid>
<number>b</number>the value of trees, if any, planted by the raiyat.
Explanation.- Where any improvement has been made on the land at 
the expense of the raiyat at any time subsequent to the last 
settlement, the land revenue for the purpose of this section shall be 
the' land revenue payable for similar lands in the locality.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1709290</tid>
<number>2</number>The land revenue payable for similar lands in the locality 
and the value of trees referred to in sub- section (1) shall be 
determined in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>411766</tid>
<number>3</number>Every raiyat entitled to compensation under this section 
shall, within a period of six months from the date of the declaration 
referred to in section 126, apply to the competent authority In the 
prescribed manner for determining the compensation.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>582</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1921779</tid>
<number> 128</number> Payment of compensation to raiyat.
<section><tid>1881464</tid>
<number>1</number>The compensation to  
which a raiyat is entitled under section 127 shall be paid to him by 
the Government in the first instance, and it may be paid in cash, in 
lump sum or in annual instalments not exceeding twenty or in the form 
of bonds which may be negotiable or non- negotiable but transferable.

</section>

<section><tid>1817670</tid>
<number>2</number>From the date of the declaration referred to in section 126, 
the raiyat shall be entitled to interest at the rate of 2 12 per cent. 
per annum. on the compensation or such portion thereof as remains un- 
paid.

</section>

<section><tid>335756</tid>
<number>3</number>Any mortgage of, or encumbrance on, the land of which the 
ownership is transferred to the under- raiyat under section 126 shall 
be a valid charge on the amount of compensation payable to the raiyat.

</section>

<section><tid>637132</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) to 
 (3), where the person entitled to compensation under section 127 Is a 
charitable or religious institution, the compensation shall, instead 
of being assessed under that section, be assessed as a perpetual 
annuity equal to the reasonable rent for the land, less the land re- 
venue payable on such land. The amount so assessed shall be paid to 
such institution in the prescribed manner.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1206646</tid>
<number> 129</number> Under- raiyat to pay compensation amount.
<section><tid>182182</tid>
<number>1</number>Every under-  
raiyat to whom ownership of any land has been transferred under 
section 126 shall be liable to pay to the Government in respect of 
that land compensation as determined under section 127.

</section>

<section><tid>244324</tid>
<number>2</number>The compensation shall be payable in cash, in lump sum or in 
such number of annual instalments, not exceeding twenty as may 
prescribed. Interest at the rate of 2 12 per cent. per annum shall be 
payable on the compensation or such portion thereof as remains unpaid.

</section>

<section><tid>1900828</tid>
<number>3</number>The compensation payable under this section shall be a 
charge on the land.

</section>

<section><tid>891676</tid>
<number>4</number>The compensation or any instalment thereof shall be re- 
coverable in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>443697</tid>
<number>130</number>Issue of certificate to under- raiyats. When the compensation 
or the first instalment of the compensation, as the case may be, has 
been paid by the under- raiyat, the competent authority may suo motu 
and shall, on application made to it in this behalf, issue to the 
under- raiyat a certificate in the prescribed form declaring him to be 
the owner of the land specified therein.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>583</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>915644</tid>
<number> 131</number> First option to purchase.
<section><tid>1089663</tid>
<number>1</number>If a raiyat at any time intends  
to sell his land held an under- raiyat, he shall give notice in writing 
of his intention such under- raiyat and offer to sell the land to him. 
In case th latter intends to purchase the land, he shall intimate in 
writing hi readiness to. do so within two months from the date of 
receipt of such notice.

</section>

<section><tid>708155</tid>
<number>2</number>If there is any dispute about the reasonable price payable 
for the land, either the raiyat or the under- raiyat may apply in 
writing to the competent authority for determining the reasonable 
price; and the competent authority, after giving notice to the other 
party and to all other persons interested in the land and after making 
such inquiry as it thinks fit, shall fix the reasonable price of the 
land which shall be- the average of the prices obtaining for similar 
lands in the locality during the ten years immediately preceding the 
date on which the application is made.

</section>

<section><tid>84773</tid>
<number>3</number>The under- raiyat shall deposit with the competent authority 
the amount of the price determined under sub- section (2) within such 
period as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>477413</tid>
<number>4</number>On deposit of the entire amount of the reasonable price, the 
competent authority shall issue a certificate in the prescribed form 
to the under- raiyat declaring him to be the purchaser of the land; the 
competent authority shall also direct that the reasonable price 
deposited shall be paid to the raiyat.

</section>

<section><tid>904211</tid>
<number>5</number>If an under- raiyat does not exercise the right of purchase in 
response to the notice given to him by the raiyat under sub- section 
 (1) or fails to deposit the amount of the price as required by sub- 
section (3), such under- raiyat shall forfeit his right of purchase, 
and the raiyat shall be entitled to sell such land to any other 
person.

</section>

<section><tid>191309</tid>
<number>6</number>The forfeiture of the right to purchase any land under this 
section shall not affect the other rights of the under- raiyat in such 
land.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>828836</tid>
<number> 132</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>285016</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Part.

</section>

<section><tid>225682</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for-

<subsection><tid>310653</tid>
<number>a</number>the form of notices to be issued under this Part and the 
manner of their service;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1392806</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner of holding inquiries under this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>180714</tid>
<number>c</number>the circumstances in which and the period for which land 
used for agricultural purposes may be left uncultivated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1254154</tid>
<number>d</number>the conditions subject to which lands may be leased by 
the Collector under section 106;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>584</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>283481</tid>
<number>e</number>the form of applications to be made under this Part, the 
authorities to whom they may be made and the procedure to be 
followed by such authorities in disposing of the applica- 
tions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>725529</tid>
<number>f</number>the determination of the value of the produce of land, 
the profits of agriculture, and the rental values of land, 
for the purposes of this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>222947</tid>
<number>g</number>the time and manner of payment of rent by the under-- 
raiyat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1508078</tid>
<number>h</number>the form of receipt for rent to be given by the raiyat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>920228</tid>
<number>i</number>the factors to be taken into account in determining 
reasonable rent for land and in commuting rent in kind into 
money rent;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>505111</tid>
<number>j</number>the nature and the extent of relief to the under- raiyat 
in cases of suspension or remission of land revenue by the 
Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373070</tid>
<number>k</number>the determination of compensation for improvements to 
under- raiyats who are evicted from land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1023698</tid>
<number>l</number>the grant of permission to surrender land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>36694</tid>
<number>m</number>the determination of the amount of compensation payable 
to the raiyat in respect of the non- resumable lands of under- 
raiyats;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1341265</tid>
<number>n</number>the form of certificates to be granted to under- 
raiyats;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>60656</tid>
<number>o</number>the determination of the price to be paid by under- raiyat 
for land in respect of which the first option to purchase is 
exercised;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>977991</tid>
<number>p</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.
PART IV

CHAP 
ACQUISITION OF ESTATES AND OF RIGHTS OF INTERMEDIARIES THEREIN

CHAPTER XI.- ACQUISITION OF ESTATES AND OF RIGHTS OF INTERMEDIARIES

THEREIN



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1252772</tid>
<number> 133</number> Definitions. In this Part,-
<section><tid>882292</tid>
<number>a</number>" estate" means lands included under one entry in any of 
the general registers of revenue- paying and revenue- free 
lands and includes-

<subsection><tid>1740261</tid>
<number>i</number>revenue- free lands not entered in any register, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>819053</tid>
<number>ii</number>a part of, or a share in, an estate;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>390297</tid>
<number>b</number>" homestead" means a dwelling house together with any 
courtyard, compound, garden, or outhouse and includes any 
outbuildings used for purposes connected with agriculture and 
any family graveyard, library, office, guest house, grain 
store,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>585</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

latrines, boundary walls, tanks, wells or places of worship 
appertaining to such dwelling house;


</section>

<section><tid>1473068</tid>
<number>c</number>" intermediary" means a person who holds in an estate the 
right, title or interest of a talukdar and includes-

<subsection><tid>1345868</tid>
<number>i</number>a person who holds land either revenue- free or at a 
concessional rate, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1655435</tid>
<number>ii</number>a tenure holder;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>529386</tid>
<number>d</number>" tenant" means a person who cultivates or holds the land 
of an intermediary under an agreement, express or implied, on 
condition of paying therefor rent in cash or in kind or de- 
livering a share of the produce and includes a person who 
cultivates or holds land of an intermediary under the system 
generally known' as" bhag"," adhi or" barga"; and the term 
" sub- tenant" shall be construed accordingly;

</section>

<section><tid>1119744</tid>
<number>e</number>" tenure holder" means a person who has acquired from an 
intermediary the right to hold lands for the purpose of col- 
lecting rents or bringing them under cultivation by 
establishIng tenants thereon.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>104486</tid>
<number> 134</number> Notification vesting estates in the State.
<section><tid>1607077</tid>
<number>1</number>As soon as  
may be after the commencement of this Act, the Administrator may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare that, with effect from 
the date specified in the notification (hereinafter referred to as the  
  vesting date), all estates situated in any area or areas and all 
rights, title and interest of every intermediary in such estates shall 
vest in the Government free from all encumbrances.

</section>

<section><tid>844553</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification under sub- section (1) shall also be 
published in such other as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1994052</tid>
<number>3</number>The publication of a notification in the manner provided in 
sub- sections (1) and (2) shall' be conclusive evidence of the notice of 
declaration to the intermediaries whose interests are affected by 
such notification.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>420070</tid>
<number> 135</number> Consequences of notification under section 134. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in 
force or in any agreement or contract, express or implied, with effect 
from the vesting date,-
<section><tid>605545</tid>
<number>a</number>each estate to which the notification relates and all 
rights, title and interest of intermediaries in such estate 
shall vest in the Government free from all encumbrances, 
Including-

<subsection><tid>1901726</tid>
<number>i</number>rights in hats. bazars, ferries, forests, wastelands, 
abadi sites, fisheries, tolls and other interests;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1760059</tid>
<number>ii</number>rights in any building other than a dwelling house or in 
any part of such building, used primarily as office cutcherry 
for collection of rent;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>586</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1760759</tid>
<number>b</number>all, grants and confirmation of title to the estate and 
rights therein made in favour of an intermediary shall cease 
and determine;

</section>

<section><tid>896195</tid>
<number>c</number>any building used for educational or charitable purposes 
and held by the intermediary shall vest in the Government for 
those educational or charitable purposes;

</section>

<section><tid>737058</tid>
<number>d</number>subject to the other provisions of this Act, every tenant 
holding any land under an intermediary shall hold the same 
directly under the Government as a raiyat thereof and shall 
be liable to pay to the Government land revenue equal to the 
rent payable by him to the intermediary on the vesting date, 
subject to a maximum of the value of one- eighth of the gross 
produce which. value shall be determined in the manner 
prescribed:
Provided that the tenant shall become the owner of any 
building or structure constructed on such land at the expense 
of the intermediary on payment of such compensation to the 
intermediary as is equivalent to its market value on the 
vesting date, which value shall be determined in accordance 
with the rules made in this behalf;


</section>

<section><tid>1087252</tid>
<number>e</number>all arrears of land revenue, local rates, cesses and 
other dues lawfully payable to the Government by the 
intermediary on the vesting date in respect of the estate 
shall, without prejudice to any other mode of recovery, be 
recoverable by deduction from the compensation payable to the 
intermediary;

</section>

<section><tid>27603</tid>
<number>f</number>all rents and other dues in respect of the estate for any 
period after the vesting date which, but for this Act, would 
be payable to an intermediary shall be payable to the 
Government and any payment Made in contravention of this 
clause shall not be valid discharge of the person liable to 
pay the same;

</section>

<section><tid>1038009</tid>
<number>g</number>where under any agreement or contract made b the vesting 
date, any rent" cess,' local rate or other dues for an period 
after the said. date has been paid to or compounded of 
released by an intermediary, the same shall, notwithstanding 
such agreement or contract, be recoverable by the Government 
from the intermediary, and may, without prejudice to any 
other mode of recovery, be realised by deduction from the 
compensation payable to the intermediary.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1145547</tid>
<number> 136</number> Rihgts of intermediary to certain lands.
<section><tid>1686494</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in sections 134 and 135, an intermediary shall, 
subject to the provisions of sub- section, (2), be entitled to retain 
with effect from the vesting date,-

<subsection><tid>1763711</tid>
<number>a</number>homesteads," buildings and structures together with the 
lands appurtenant thereto in the occupation of the inter-'

<pagefootnote><pagenum>587</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

mediary other than buildings vested in the Government under 
section 135;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>437959</tid>
<number>b</number>lands under the personal cultivation of the intermediary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>643113</tid>
<number>c</number>lands in which permanent rights have not already accrued 
to a tenant under any custom, agreement or law and which have 
been leased by an intermediary who, both at the commencement 
of the lease and on the vesting date, was a person Under 
disability;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>275031</tid>
<number>d</number>lands held by the intermediary as mortgagor Which are 
subject to usufructuary mortgage and are under the personal 
cultivation of the mortgagee-,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1798895</tid>
<number>e</number>lands comprised in orchards or used for the purpose of 
live- stock breeding, poultry farming, or dairy farming Which 
are in the occupation of the intermediary;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>45888</tid>
<number>f</number>so much of the lands comprised in a tea garden, mill, 
factory or workshop as in the opinion of the Administrator is 
required for such tea garden, mill, factory or workshop.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1025720</tid>
<number>2</number>An intermediary who is entitled to retain possession of any 
land under sub- section (1) shall hold such land directly under the 
Government from the vesting date as a raiyat thereof and be liable to 
pay therefor land revenue at full rate applicable to similar lands in 
the locality.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>21797</tid>
<number> 137</number> Collector to take charge of estates, etc., vested in the 
Government.
<section><tid>1797149</tid>
<number>1</number>The Collector shall take charge of estates and  
interests of intermediaries vest in the Government under section 
135.

</section>

<section><tid>286319</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose aforesaid, the Collector may, by written 
order served in the prescribed manner, require any intermediary other 
person in possession, of any such estate or interest to give up such 
possession by a date to be specified in the order (which shall not be  
  earlier than sixty days from the date of service of the order) or to 
deliver by that date any documents, registers, or records, connected 
with the management of such estate or interest which are in his 
custody or to furnish a statement in the prescribed form in respect of 
such estate or interest.

</section>

<section><tid>1536765</tid>
<number>3</number>The Collector' or any other officer authorised by him in this 
behalf may take such steps or use such force as may be necessary to 
enforce compliance With the order and may also enter any building or 
place for the purpose of taking possession of the documents, registers 
or records referred to in sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>682877</tid>
<number>4</number>An intermediary shall be entitled to make inspection of any 
documents, registers or records which have been delivered. to or taken 
possession of by the Collector, to make notes therefrom or to have 
certified copies thereof granted to him. No fees shall be charg-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>588</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

ed for making inspection or for making notes, but fees may' be 
charged, according to the prescribed scale, for the grant of certified 
copies.


</section>

<section><tid>1298917</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorise the 
collector to take possession of-

<subsection><tid>1929316</tid>
<number>a</number>any land or of any right of an intermediary therein, 
which may be retained by the intermediary under section 136, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1784631</tid>
<number>b</number>any religious institution or any building connected 
therewith.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1154483</tid>
<number> 138</number> Decision of disputes. If there, is any dispute as to the 
possession of any homestead or land or building referred to in sub- 
section
<section><tid>173108</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 136, the Collector shall, on application made  
to him in this behalf, make such inquiry as he deems fit and pass such 
orders thereon as may appear to him just and proper.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>471939</tid>
<number>139</number>Appeal. An appeal against an order of the Collector passed 
under section 138, if preferred within sixty. days, of such order, 
shall lie to the District Judge having jurisdiction.
CHAP 
ASSESSMENT AND PAYMENT OF COMPENSATION

CHAPTER XII.- ASSESSMENT AND PAYMENT OF COMPENSATION


</article>



<article><tid>764655</tid>
<number>140</number>Intermediaries entitled to receive compensation. Every 
intermediary, whose right, title and interest in any estate vest in 
the Government under Chapter XI shall be entitled to receive and be 
paid therefor compensation as hereinafter provided.

</article>



<article><tid>690483</tid>
<number>141</number>Date from which compensation shall be due. The compensation 
referred to in section 140 shall be due as from the vesting date and 
the portion remaining unpaid shall carry interest at the rate of 21 2 
per cent. per annum.

</article>



<article><tid>718081</tid>
<number> 142</number> Every intermediary to be treated as a separate unit.
<section><tid>34154</tid>
<number>1</number>For  
the purpose of assessing compensation under this Chapter,-

<subsection><tid>895769</tid>
<number>a</number>every intermediary shall be treated as a separate unit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1687102</tid>
<number>b</number>if two or more intermediaries hold an estate or any 
interest therein jointly, the share of each intermediary in 
such estate or interest hall be treated as a separate unit:
Provided that where any such estate or interest is held by a 
Hindu joint family consisting of a common ancestor in the 
male line and his descendants, the family shall' If the 
common ancestor was alive on the vesting date, be treated as 
one unit;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1944768</tid>
<number>c</number>if an intermediary holds shares or interest in two or 
more estates, the aggregate of his shares or interest in all 
such estates shall be treated as a single unit.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>448403</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any 
other law, no partition or transfer by way of sale or gift of an 
estate or part thereof made on or after the 10th August, <year>1957</year>, shall 
be recognised for the purpose of assessing the compensation.

</section>

<section><tid>1198942</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall apply to-

<subsection><tid>676233</tid>
<number>a</number>any sale made under an order of court in execution of any 
decree or order for payment of money, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1244151</tid>
<number>b</number>any sale or gift made in favour of a wakf, a trust, an 
endowment or a society registered under the Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>), and established wholly 
for charitable purposes, unless the Government in any 
particular case directs otherwise.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>42845</tid>
<number>143</number>Appointment of compensation officers. The Administrator 
shall, as soon as possible after the publication of a notification 
under section 134, appoint one or more officers to be compensation 
officers to prepare compensation assessment rolls and to perform such 
other duties as may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>662535</tid>
<number> 144</number> Compensation assessment roll.
<section><tid>1857089</tid>
<number>1</number>The compensation officer  
shall prepare a compensation assessment roll in respect of every 
estate vested in the Government under Chapter XI.

</section>

<section><tid>1835433</tid>
<number>2</number>The compensation assessment roll shall contain particulars of 
the gross income and the net income from the estate, the share of the 
net income of the intermediary or each of the intermediaries, the 
amount of compensation payable to him or them and such other par- 
ticulars as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1829729</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an intermediary has shares or interest in two or more 
estates all of which have vested in the Government, the particulars of 
the shares or interest of such intermediary in the net income from all 
such estates and the compensation payable to him in respect of his 
shares or interest in all such estates shall be shown in the com- 
pensation assessment roll relating to any one of such estates.

</section>

<section><tid>1587138</tid>
<number>4</number>Where an intermediary has shares or interest in two or more 
esates either or any of which has not vested in the Government, the 
compensation payable to the intermediary shall be determined after all 
such estates have vested in the Government, on the basis of the 
aggregate of his shares or interest in the net income from All such 
estates.

</section>

<section><tid>988628</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in sub- section (4) shall be construed as authorising 
the postponement of payment of ad interim compensation to any such 
intermediary as is referred to in that sub- section in respect of the 
estate or estates which have vested in the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1158832</tid>
<number>6</number>For the purpose of preparing the compensation assessment 
roll, the compensation officer may require an intermediary to submit 
such statements and furnish such particulars as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>590</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>635759</tid>
<number> 145</number> Determination of gross income and net income.
<section><tid>507687</tid>
<number>1</number>For the  
purpose of assessment of compensation payable in respect of an 
estate,-

<subsection><tid>267887</tid>
<number>a</number>the gross income from the estate shall be taken to consist of-

<subsubsection><tid>1532028</tid>
<number>i</number>in respect of lands other than those referred to in 
section 136, the rents, cesses, local rates and other amounts 
payable or deemed to be payable to the intermediary or 
intermediaries by the tenants and tenure- holders for the pre- 
vious year, including the commuted value of rents payable in 
kind which value shall be determined in the prescribed 
manner.;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1849323</tid>
<number>ii</number>the gross income from abadi sites, fisheries, hats, 
bazars, ferries, forests, tolls, waste lands and other 
interests in the estate for the previous year;-

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1500385</tid>
<number>iii</number>the aggregate of the annual rents for the previous year 
from buildings used as offices or cutcherries and any other 
building which vest' in the Government;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1276957</tid>
<number>iv</number>any other income during the previous year appertaining 
to the estate vesting in the Government not expressly 
mentioned in the foregoing sub- clauses;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1597413</tid>
<number>b</number>the net income from the estate shall be computed by 
deducting from the gross income the following, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>1874104</tid>
<number>i</number>any sum which was payable by the intermediary or 
intermediaries during the previous year as land revenue, 
ceases, local rates or rent to the Government in respect of 
the interests to which the gross income relates;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1899231</tid>
<number>ii</number>any sum payable under the Bengal Agricultural Income- 
tax Act <year>1944</year>, (Ben. IV of <year>1944</year>), as extended to Tripura or 
the Indian Income- tax Act <year>1922</year>, (11 of <year>1922</year>), during the 
previous year as defined in those Acts, in respect of the 
interests to which the gross 
income relates;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>920214</tid>
<number>iii</number>charge count of management and collection at the 
following namely:-
Amount of gross income Rate


<subsubsubsection><tid>32131</tid>
<number>a</number>Where the gross income exceeds 15 per centum of 
Rs. 30, 000. such gross income.

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1893140</tid>
<number>b</number>Where the gross income exceeds 12 1 2 per centum of 
Rs. 10, 000 but does not exceed such gross income.

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>784015</tid>
<number>c</number>Where the gross income exceeds 10 per centum of 
Rs. 5, 000 but does not exceed such gross income.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>591</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Amount of gross income Rate


</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>163513</tid>
<number>d</number>Where the gross income exceeds 7 2 1 per centum of such 
Rs. 25, 000 but does not exceed gross income. 
Rs. 5, 000.
Provided that the net income (after deducting the charges on  
  account of management and collection) from an estate which falls under 
item (a), (b), (c) or (d) shall in no case be less than the maximum 
net income from an estate which falls under the item immediately, 
following.

Illustration.- The net income after deducting the charges on 
account of management and collection at 12 1 per cent. under item (b) 
from an estate the gross income of which is Rs. 10, 100 will be Rs. 
8, 837- 50 while the net income after deducting the charges on account 
of management at 10 per cent. under item (c) from an estate the gross 
income of which is Rs. 10, 000 will be Rs. 9, 000; under the proviso, 
the net income from the first mentioned estate shall be taken to be 
Rs. 9, 000 and not Rs. 8, 837- 50.


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>541337</tid>
<number>2</number>The net income from the estate as determined under sub- 
section (1) shall be apportioned among all the intermediaries having a 
share or interest in the estate in the proportion of their shares or 
interest, and if in doing so, any dispute involving a question of 
title arises, the compensation officer shall refer the parties to a 
civil court.
Explanation.- For the purpose of this section except clause (b) 
 (ii) of sub- section (1)," previous year" means the year immediately 
preceding the year in which the vesting date falls.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1945662</tid>
<number> 146</number> Compensation payable to intermediary.
<section><tid>463829</tid>
<number>1</number>The compensation  
payable to an intermediary shall multiple of his net income from the 
estate or where the intermediary has shares or interests in two or 
more estates, of the aggregate of his net incomes from all such 
estates, in accordance with the following table, namely:-
Amount of- net income Total compensation payable


<subsection><tid>35625</tid>
<number>a</number>Where the net income Fifteen times such net income. 
does not exceed Rs. 1, 000.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1750818</tid>
<number>b</number>Where the net income Twelve times such net income 
exceeds Rs. 1, 000 but does or the maximum amount 
not exceed Rs. 2, 500. under (a) above, whichever is 
greater.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>592</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Amount of net income Total compensation payable


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>735126</tid>
<number>c</number>Where the net income Eleven times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 2, 500 but does the maximum amount under 
not exceed Rs. 5, 000. (b) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>859933</tid>
<number>d</number>Where the net income Ten times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 5, 000 but does the maximum amount under 
not exceed Rs. 7, 500. (c) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1720930</tid>
<number>e</number>Where the net income Nine times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 7, 500 but does the maximum amount under 
not exceed Rs. 10, 000. (d) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1748099</tid>
<number>f</number>Where the net income Eight times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 10, 000 but does the maximum amount under 
not exceed Rs. 15, 000. (e) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1294138</tid>
<number>g</number>Where the net income Seven times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 15, 000 but does the maximum' amount under 
not exceed Rs. 30, 000. (f) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>815487</tid>
<number>h</number>Where the net income Six times such net Income or 
exceeds Rs. 30, 000 but does the maximum amount under 
not exceed Rs. 50, 000, (g) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1274577</tid>
<number>i</number>Where the net income Five times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 50, 000 but does the maximum amount under 
not exceed Rs. 1, 00, 000. (h) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>961834</tid>
<number>j</number>Where the net income Three times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 1, 00, 000 but does the maximum amount under 
not exceed Rs. 3, 00, 000, (i) above, whichever is greater.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>691523</tid>
<number>k</number>Where the net income Two times such net income or 
exceeds Rs. 3, 00, 000. the maximum amount Under 
 (j) above, whichever, is greater.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>305957</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the net income or any portion of the net income from 
an estate is dedicated exclusively to charitable or religious 
purposes, the compensation payable in respect of such net income or 
portion shall, instead of being assessed under sub- section (1), be 
assessed as a perpetual annuity equal to such net income or portion, 
as the case may be, payable in the prescribed manner for those 
purposes.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>593</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purpose of this sub- section, if the salary, 
remuneration or any allowance payable to the Mutawalli of a wakf or 
the shebait of a Hindu temple or a trustee of any other charitable or 
religious trust does not exceed 15 per cent. of the net income, then 
such net income shall be deemed to be dedicated exclusively to 
charitable or religious purposes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>38701</tid>
<number> 147</number> Disposal of claims of creditors.
<section><tid>133194</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator shall  
appoint a claims officer not below the rank of sub- judge to dispose of 
the claims of creditors whose debts are secured by a mortgage of or 
charge on any estate or part thereof vested in the Government under 
section 134 and to discharge any other duties assigned to him by this 
Act or the rules made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>279456</tid>
<number>2</number>Every creditor referred to in sub- section (1) shall prefer 
his claim in writing before the claims officer In the manner and with- 
in the time prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1463176</tid>
<number>3</number>The claims officer shall inquire Into the claims in accord- 
ance with such rules as may be prescribed and determine the amount to 
which each of the creditors is entitled.

</section>

<section><tid>29328</tid>
<number>4</number>Where there are two or more creditors, the claims officer 
shall determine, in accordance with the provisions of the Transfer of 
Property Act, <year>1882</year>, the order in which each such 
creditor is entitled to receive the amount due to him.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>702710</tid>
<number> 148</number> Appeal against the decision of claims officer.
<section><tid>522011</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person  
aggrieved by an order of the claims officer may, within sixty days of 
the date of the order, prefer an appeal to the District Judge having 
jurisdiction.

</section>

<section><tid>1382173</tid>
<number>2</number>The decision of the District Judge on appeal, or of the 
claims officer where no appeal is preferred, shall be final.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1153209</tid>
<number> 149</number> Preliminary publication of compensation assessment roll and 
disposal of objections.
<section><tid>1234878</tid>
<number>1</number>After the amount of compensation has been  
determined in accordance with the provision' s of section 146 and 
entered In the compensation assessment roll, the compensation Officer 
shall cause a draft of such roll to be published in the prescribed 
manner and for the prescribed period. The compensation officer shall 
send copies of the relevant portions of the draft roll to the 
intermediaries concerned and shall receive and consider any objections 
which may be made within three months of the receipt of such copy to 
any entry therein or to any omission therefrom. The compensation 
officer shall dispose of such objections in the. prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>372135</tid>
<number>2</number>Separate draft compensation assessment rolls may be prepared 
and published under sub- section (1) for different villages or groups 
of villages.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1340130</tid>
<number> 150</number> Contents of the order of compensation officer. Every order of 
the compensation officer deciding an objection under sub- section
<section><tid>1423636</tid>
<number>1</number> 
of section 149 shall contain a concise statement of the case, the 
points for determination, the decision thereon and the reasons for 
such decision.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1360544</tid>
<number> 151</number> Appeals against order of compensation officer.
<section><tid>1634559</tid>
<number>1</number>From every  
order passed by a compensation officer under section 150, an appeal 
shall lie to a Special Judge appointed for, the purpose, within ninety 
days of the date of the order.

</section>

<section><tid>697811</tid>
<number>2</number>An appeal shall lie to the court of the Judicial 
Commissioner, from every order passed on appeal by a Special Judge 
under 
sub- section (1), within sixty days of the passing of such order, on 
any of the grounds specified in section 100 of the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year>. (5 of <year>1908</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1433942</tid>
<number>3</number>The decision of the Judicial Commissioner, or of the Special 
Judge where no second appeal is preferred, or of the compensation 
officer where no appeal to the Special Judge is preferred, shall be 
final.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>752859</tid>
<number> 152</number> Final publication of the compensation assessment roll.
<section><tid>959969</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where no objection or appeal has been filed or all the objections and 
appeals filed have been finally disposed of the compensation officer 
shall clause the draft compensation assessment roll to be finally 
published, or make such alterations in the draft compensation 
assessment roll as may be necessary to give effect to any order passed 
on objection made under sub- section (1) of section 149-or on, appeal 
under section 151 and cause the roll as so altered to be finally 
published, in the prescribed manner together with a certificate 
stating the fact of such final publication and the date thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>514130</tid>
<number>2</number>The publication of the compensation assessment roll under 
sub- section (1) shall be conclusive evidence that the said roll has 
been duly made under this Chapter and every entry in such roll shall, 
save as otherwise provided in, this Act, be conclusive evidence of 
the matters referred to in such entry.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>775938</tid>
<number> 153</number> Correction of bona fide mistakes.
<section><tid>913221</tid>
<number>1</number>No Correction of the  
compensation assessment roll after it has been finally published under 
section 152 shall be made except as provided in this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1882374</tid>
<number>2</number>Correction of bona fide mistakes or corrections necessitated 
by Succession to or Inheritance of any interest in the estate can be 
made by the compensation officer at any time before the payment of 
compensation either of his own motion or on the application of the 
person interested, but no such correction shall be made while any 
legal proceeding affecting such entry is pending.

</section>

<section><tid>67421</tid>
<number>3</number>Every time a, correction is made under- sub- section, (2) the 
compensation officer shall cause a draft of, the correction to be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>595</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Published in the same manner as the draft compensation, assessment 
roll, and after considering and disposing of any objections that may 
be made, shall cause the correction to be finally published.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1088862</tid>
<number> 154</number> Ad interim payment of compensation. After the vesting date 
and before the final publication of the compensation assessment roll, 
ad interim payment to the outgoing intermediary may be made as 
follows:-
<section><tid>1909170</tid>
<number>a</number>the compensation officer shall calculate the probable 
amount of compensation payable to him

</section>

<section><tid>1534790</tid>
<number>b</number>two and a half per cent. of such probable amount shall be 
paid ad interim to each intermediary in cash, every year 
until such time as the compensation assessment roll is 
finally published;

</section>

<section><tid>1559180</tid>
<number>c</number>if there is any dispute as to the title of any person to 
receive the amount or as to- the apportionment of it, the 
amount shall bet kept in deposit in the manner prescribed 
until the dispute is finally determined; and on such determi- 
nation, the compensation officer shall pay the amount or the 
portion thereof to the person or persons entitled to receive 
the same.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1771677</tid>
<number> 155</number> Mode of payment of compensation.
<section><tid>165530</tid>
<number>1</number>After the compensation  
assessment roll has been, final published, the compensation officer 
' shall deduct from the amount shown in such roll as payable to an 
intermediary or any other person having interest in the estate the 
following amounts namely;--

<subsection><tid>458332</tid>
<number>a</number>ad interim payments made under section 154;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1861707</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount, if any, the deduction of which has been 
ordered under section 135;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1330057</tid>
<number>c</number>the amounts payable to creditors as determined by the 
claims officer.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1922635</tid>
<number>2</number>The balance remaining after the deductions referred to in 
sub- section (1) are made shall be given in cash, in one lump sum or in 
annual instalments not exceeding twenty, or in bonds, or not exceeding 
twenty, or in partly in cash and partly in bonds, in accordance with 
such rules as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>119926</tid>
<number>3</number>The bonds referred to in sub- section (2) may be either 
negotiable, or, non- negotiable, and. transferable in such circumstances 
and in such manner as may be prescribed, and shall carry interest at 
the rate of two and a half per cent. per annum on the amount 
outstanding thereon, with effect from the date of issue.

</section>

<section><tid>468414</tid>
<number>4</number>If any dispute, arises as to the, title of any person to 
receive the, amount or, as to the apportionment of it, the 
compensation

<pagefootnote><pagenum>596</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

officer may, if he thinks fit, keep the amount of compensation or the 
bonds referred to above in deposit in the manner prescribed, until the 
dispute is finally determined; and on such determination, the 
compensation officer shall pay the amount or the portions thereof to 
the person or persons entitled to receive the same.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1729902</tid>
<number> 156</number> Compensation due to maintenance holder.
<section><tid>1864038</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person  
claiming as maintenance holder to be entitled to any portion of the 
compensation awarded to any intermediary under this Chapter applies to 
the compensation officer for payment of the same to him, the 
compensation officer may, with the consent of the intermediary, direct 
the payment to the applicant out of the compensation of such amount 
as the intermediary nay, have agreed to be paid to the applicant, and 
any such payment shall be a valid discharge of the liability of the 
Government in respect of the amount so paid.

</section>

<section><tid>1631672</tid>
<number>2</number>If the intermediary does not give his consent, the com- 
pensation officer shall direct the applicant to file, within three 
months, a suit or other proceeding in the court having jurisdiction to 
establish his claim and order that the amount claimed shall, not in 
the meantime be paid to the intermediary.

</section>

<section><tid>1338482</tid>
<number>3</number>The Government shall not be made a, party to any, suit or 
proceeding instituted or commenced in pursuance of any direction given 
under sub- section (2).

</section>

<section><tid>884213</tid>
<number>4</number>If the suit or proceeding referred to in sub- section (2) is 
instituted or commenced within the period aforesaid, the compensation 
officer shall place the amount claimed at the disposal of the court 
before which such suit or proceeding is instituted.

</section>

<section><tid>905617</tid>
<number>5</number>If the suit or proceeding is not instituted or commenced 
within the period of three months aforesaid, the compensation officer 
shall order the amount to be paid to the intermediary.
Explanation.-- For the purpose of this section, a maintenance 
holder Means a person entitled to, receive maintenance under a 
registered deed, decree or order of court.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1094458</tid>
<number>157</number>Compensation due to person incompetent to alienate. If any 
intermediary entitled to receive compensation in respect of any 
interest is a person incompetent to alienate such interest, the 
compensation officer shall keep the amount of compensation payable, in 
respect of such interest, whether in cash or in bonds, in deposit with 
the Collector who shall arrange to Invest the cash or the income from 
the bonds in the purchase of such Government or other approved 
securities as the Collector thinks fit and shall direct the payment of 
the income from such investment to the intermediary who would for the 
time being have been entitled to hold and enjoy such interest if it 
had not vested in the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>597</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Government; and such cash, bonds and securities shall remain so 
deposited until they are made over to any person or persons becoming 
absolutely entitled thereto:

Provided that nothing herein contained shall affect the liability 
of any person who may receive the whole or any part of any 
compensation under this section to pay the same to the person lawfully 
entitled thereto.


</article>



<article><tid>1904141</tid>
<number> 158</number> Inquiries to be judicial proceedings. The Collector, the 
compensation officer and the claims officer, for the purposes of any 
inquiries or proceedings under this Part, shall have the same powers 
as are vested in a court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year>, (5  
  of <year>1908</year>.) in respect of-
<section><tid>1087375</tid>
<number>a</number>enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him 
on oath or affirmation;

</section>

<section><tid>1491111</tid>
<number>b</number>compelling the production of documents; and

</section>

<section><tid>1533656</tid>
<number>c</number>issuing commission for the examination of witnesses;
and such inquiries or proceedings shall be deemed to be judicial pro- 
ceedings within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian 
Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>.)



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1374499</tid>
<number> 159</number> Penalties. Whoever---
<section><tid>1773517</tid>
<number>a</number>wilfully fails or neglects' to comply with any require- 
ments made of him under this Part, or

</section>

<section><tid>1592874</tid>
<number>b</number>contravenes any lawful order passed under this Part, or

</section>

<section><tid>586035</tid>
<number>c</number>obstructs or resists the taking by the Collector or any 
other officer authorized by him in writing of charge any 
property which is vested in the Government under this Part or

</section>

<section><tid>241358</tid>
<number>d</number>furnishes information which he knows or believes to be 
false or does not believe to be true,
shall, on conviction before a Magistrate, be punishable with fine 
which may extend to five hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1997553</tid>
<number>160</number>Application of Part III to persons becoming raiyats or 
under- raiyats under Part IV. Where, as a result of the operation of 
this Part, any person acquires the right to hold land either as a 
raiyat or an under- raiyat, the provisions of Part III shall as far as 
may be, apply to the determination of such right and in such 
application, any reference in the said Part to the commencement of 
this Act shall be construed, as a reference to the vesting date.

</article>



<article><tid>1342325</tid>
<number> 161</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1481984</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of 
carrying out the purposes of this Part.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>598</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>267084</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power' such rules may provide for-

<subsection><tid>1190875</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner of publication of a notification under 
section 134;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1477510</tid>
<number>b</number>the procedure to be followed and the forms to be 
adopted in inquiries and proceedings under this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1247065</tid>
<number>c</number>the mode of service of any order, notice or other 
documents under this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1323356</tid>
<number>d</number>the form of the statements to be furnished by Inter- 
mediaries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>726195</tid>
<number>e</number>the inspection of and making notes from documents, 
registers and records under section 137, the grant of 
certified copies thereof and the fee to be charged for such 
grant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>355237</tid>
<number>f</number>the form and the manner in which compensation assess- 
ment rolls shall be prepared and the particulars to be 
mentioned therein;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1775606</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner of apportionment of net income among 
intermediaries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>850989</tid>
<number>h</number>the procedure to be followed in the case of inter- 
mediaries having shares or interest in different estates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1594525</tid>
<number>i</number>the manner in which the preliminary and the final 
publication of the compensation assessment roll shall be 
made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1887679</tid>
<number>j</number>the manner of determining the amount of annuities 
payable to religious and charitable institutions and the pro- 
cedure for making payments;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1880607</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner in which the income of the previous year 
shall be determined;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1259429</tid>
<number>l</number>the determination of the amount of ad interim com- 
pensation

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30956</tid>
<number>m</number>The manner in which and the period within which 
creditors may prefer their claims before the claims officer 
and the procedure to be followed in the disposal of such 
claims;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1902606</tid>
<number>n</number>the manner in. which objections shall be submitted to the 
compensation officer and the procedure to be followed In the 
disposal of such objections;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>135920</tid>
<number>o</number>the manner of determining the commuted value of rents 
under section 145;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>864796</tid>
<number>p</number>the manner of preferring appeals under Chapters XI and 
XII;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1656811</tid>
<number>q</number>the manner of keeping In deposit the amount of com- 
pensation under sections 155 and 157;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>599</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>290753</tid>
<number>r</number>the form and contents of bonds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>50873</tid>
<number>s</number>the manner in which and the circumstances under which, 
bonds shall be transferable, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1403536</tid>
<number>t</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.
PART V

CHAP 
CEILING ON LAND HOLDINGS

CHAPTER XIII.- CEILING ON LAND HOLDINGS



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1525836</tid>
<number>162</number>Exemptions. The provisions of this Chapter shall not apply 
to land owned by the Government or a local authority.

</article>



<article><tid>248641</tid>
<number> 163</number> Definitions. For the purposes of this Chapter,-
<section><tid>260491</tid>
<number>a</number>" ceiling limit", in relation to land, means the limit 
fixed under section 164;

</section>

<section><tid>1159381</tid>
<number>b</number>" family" relation to a person, means the person, the 
wife or husband, as the ease may be, and, the dependent 
children and grand- children, of such person;

</section>

<section><tid>542333</tid>
<number>c</number>" land" does not Include land used for non- agricultural 
purposes.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1020657</tid>
<number>164</number>Cellings on holdings. No person dither by himself or, If he 
has a family, together with any other member of his family 
 (hereinafter referred to as the, person representing the family) 
shall, whether as a raiyat or an under- raiyat or as a mortgagee with 
possession or otherwise, or partly in one capacity and partly in 
another, hold land in excess of twenty- five standard acres in the 
aggregate:
Provided that where the number of members of the family of such 
person- exceed five, he may hold five additional standard acres for 
each member in excess of five, so however as not to, exceed fifty 
standard acres in the aggregate.

Explanation.- In the case of a company, an association or any 
other body of individuals, the ceiling limit shall be twenty- five 
standard acres.


</article>



<article><tid>117131</tid>
<number>165</number>Submission of returns. Every person representing a family 
who at the commencement of this Act holds, or has at any time during 
the period between the 10th day of August, <year>1957</year> and such commencement 
held, land In excess of the ceiling limit shall submit to the 
competent authority, in such form and within such time as may be 
prescribed, a return giving the particulars of all land held by him 
and indicating therein the parcels of land, not exceeding the ceiling 
limit, which he desires to retain;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>600</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that in the case of a joint holding, all co- sharers may 
submit the return jointly indicating the parcels of land, not exceed- 
ing the aggregate of their individual ceiling limits, which they 
desire to retain.

Explanation.- In the case of a person under disability, the return 
shall be furnished by his guardian or authorised agent, as the case 
may be.


</article>



<article><tid>247867</tid>
<number>166</number>Collection of information through other agency. If any 
person, who under section 165 is required to submit a return, fails to 
do so, the competent authority may collect the necessary information 
through such agency as may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>1870381</tid>
<number> 167</number> Procedure for determination of excess land.
<section><tid>195669</tid>
<number>1</number>On- receipt of  
any return under section 165 or Information under section 166 or 
otherwise, the competent authority shall, after giving the persons 
affected an opportunity of being heard, hold an inquiry in such manner 
as may be prescribed, and having regard to the provisions of section 
 168 and section 169 or of any rules that may be made in this behalf, 
it shall determine---

<subsection><tid>1819175</tid>
<number>a</number>the total area of land held by each person representing 
the family;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1797092</tid>
<number>b</number>the specific parcels of land which he may retain;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1584813</tid>
<number>c</number>the land held by him in excess of the ceiling limit;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>57363</tid>
<number>d</number>whether such excess land is held by him as a raiyat or 
as an under- raiyat or as a mortgagee with possession;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>571835</tid>
<number>e</number>the excess land in respect of which the under- raiyat or 
the mortgagee with possession may acquire the rights of the 
raiyat or the mortgagor, as the case may be;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1514915</tid>
<number>f</number>the excess land which may be restored to a raiyat or a 
mortgagor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1097671</tid>
<number>g</number>the excess land which shall vest in the Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>4807</tid>
<number>h</number>such other matters as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>880264</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of determining the excess land under this 
section, any land transferred at any time during the period between 
the 10th day of August, <year>1957</year> and the commencement of this Act shall, 
notwithstanding such transfer, be deemed to be held by the transferor.

</section>

<section><tid>24348</tid>
<number>3</number>The competent authority shall prepare a list in the 
prescribed form containing the particulars determined by him under 
subsection (1) and shall cause every such list to be published in the 
Official Gazette and also in such other manner as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>601</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>909377</tid>
<number> 168</number> Selection of excess land in cases of certain transfers.
<section><tid>1471067</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any person holding land in excess of the ceiling limit at any 
time during the period between the 10th day of August, <year>1957</year> and the 
 2nd day of December, <year>1959</year>, has transferred during such period any part 
of his land to any other person under a registered deed for valuable 
consideration, the excess land to be determined under section 167 
shall, to the extent possible, be selected out of the land held at the 
commencement of this Act by the transferor in excess of a family 
holding and no land shall be selected out of the land transferred.

</section>

<section><tid>1971805</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any person holding land in excess of the ceiling limit 
at any time-

<subsection><tid>1451799</tid>
<number>a</number>during the period between the 10th day of August, <year>1957</year> 
and the 2nd day of December, <year>1959</year>, has transferred during 
such period any part of his land to any other person in any 
manner other than under a registered deed for valuable consi- 
deration, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>661599</tid>
<number>b</number>during the period between the 2nd day of December, <year>1959</year> 
and the commencement of this Act has transferred during such 
period any part of his land to any other person in any manner 
whatsoever,
the excess land to be determined under section 167 shall be selected 
out of the lands held at the commencement of this Act by the trans- 
feror and the transferee in the same proportion as the land held by 
the transferor bears to the land transferred and where no land is hed 
by the transferor, out of the land transferred.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>816984</tid>
<number>3</number>Where excess land is to be selected out of the lands of more 
than one transferee, such land shall be selected out of the lands held 
by each of the transferees in the same proportion as the area of the 
land transferred to him bears to the total area of the lands 
transferred to all the transferees.

</section>

<section><tid>108438</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any excess land is selected out of the land 
transferred, the transfer of such land shall be void.

</section>

<section><tid>1748503</tid>
<number>5</number>Notwithstanding anything hereinbefore contained, the excess 
land to be selected shall in no case include the homestead land of a 
person.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section,' homestead 
land" means the land on which the homestead (whether used by the owner  
  or let out on rent) stands together with any courtyard, compound and 
attached garden, not exceeding one acre in the aggregate.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1428645</tid>
<number> 169</number> Excess land to vest in Government.
<section><tid>1454844</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any excess  
land of a raiyat is in his actual possession, the excess land shall 
vest in the Government.
 346 M of Law- 76.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>602</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>291242</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any excess land of a raiyat is in the possession of a 
person holding the same as an under- raiyat or as a mortgagee and the 
excess land together with any other land held by such person exceeds 
his ceiling limit, the land in excess of the ceiling limit shall vest 
in the Government.

</section>

<section><tid>709761</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any excess land of, a raiyat is in the possession of a 
person holding the same as an under- raiyat or as a mortgagee and such 
person is allowed to retain the excess land or a part thereof as being 
within his ceiling limit, that person shall acquire the rights of the 
raiyat or of the mortgagor, as the case may be, in respect of such 
excess land or part thereof on payment of compensation, if any, as 
hereinafter provided, but if that person refuses to pay such com- 
pensation, the excess land or part thereof shall vest in the Govern- 
ment.

</section>

<section><tid>544627</tid>
<number>4</number>Where there is any excess land of an under- raiyat or of a 
mortgagee with possession, the excess land shall vest in the Govern- 
ment:
Provided that in any case where the excess land or any part 
thereof held by the raiyat or the mortgagor together with any other 
land held by such person does not exceed the ceiling limit, the excess 
land or such part thereof as does not exceed the ceiling limit shall 
be restored to the possession of that person on an application made by 
him in this behalf to the competent authority within such time as may 
be prescribed and in the case where the possession of such land is 
restored to the mortgagor, the mortgage in respect of such land shall 
be deemed to be a simple mortgage.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>350033</tid>
<number> 170</number> Publication of the final list and consequences thereof.

<section><tid>964457</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by an entry in the list published under sub-  
section (3) of section 167 may, within thirty days from the date of 
publication thereof in the Official Gazette, file objections thereto 
before the Collector.

</section>

<section><tid>1454167</tid>
<number>2</number>The Collector or any other officer authorised in this behalf 
by the Administrator may, after considering the objections and after 
giving the objector or his representatives an opportunity of being 
heard in the matter', approve or modify the list.

</section>

<section><tid>155159</tid>
<number>3</number>The list as approved or modified under sub- section (2) shall 
then be published in the Official Gazette and also in such other 
manner as may be prescribed and subject to the provisions of this Act, 
the list shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>381418</tid>
<number>4</number>With effect from the date of the publication of the list In 
the Official Gazette under sub- section (3),--

<subsection><tid>1414278</tid>
<number>a</number>the excess land shall stand transferred to and vest in 
the. Government free of all encumbrances; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>603</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985125</tid>
<number>b</number>the possession of the excess land shall stand restored to 
the raiyat or the mortgagor, as the case may be; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1583307</tid>
<number>c</number>the rights of the raiyat or the mortgagor in respect of 
the excess land shall stand transferred to the under- raiyat 
or the mortgagee, as the case may be.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>916988</tid>
<number> 171</number> Compensation.
<section><tid>47035</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any excess land of a raiyat vests in  
the Government there shall be paid by the Government to the raiyat 
compensation, subject to the provisions of sub- section (2), of an 
amount equal to twenty times the net annual income from such land.
Explanation.--- For the purposes of sub- section (1), the net 
annual income from any land shall be deemed to be one- fifth of the 
value of the average yearly gross produce of the land, calculated in 
such manner as may be prescribed.


</section>

<section><tid>18329</tid>
<number>2</number>Where such excess land or any part thereof is in the 
possession of an under- raiyat, the compensation payable under sub- 
section (1) in respect of the land shall be apportioned between the 
raiyat and the under- raiyat in such proportion as may be 
determined by the competent authority in the prescribed manner, having 
regard to their respective shares in the net income from such land.

</section>

<section><tid>1460709</tid>
<number>3</number>In addition to the compensation payable in respect of any 
excess land under sub- section (1), there shall also be paid compensa- 
tion in respect of any structure or building constructed on such land 
and any trees planted thereon and such compensation shall be deter- 
mined by the competent authority in the prescribed manner, having 
regard to the market value of such structure or building or the value 
of such trees, and such compensation shall be paid to the person who 
has constructed the structure or building or planted the trees.

</section>

<section><tid>1479975</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any excess land in respect of which compensation is 
payable is subject to any mortgage or other encumbrance, the amount 
due under the mortgage or other encumbrance in respect of such excess 
land, or where a transfer in respect of any excess land is void by 
virtue of sub- section (4) of section 168, the consideration money paid 
by the transferee in respect of such excess land, shall be a charge on 
the compensation payable in respect of the excess land to the person 
who has created the mortgage or encumbrance or, as the case may be, to 
the transferor.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>604</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>531581</tid>
<number>5</number>Where an under- raiyat acquires the rights of a raiyat In 
respect of any excess land, the compensation payable by him in respect 
of that land shall be equal to the amount which the raiyat would nave 
been paid as compensation under sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) if 
the land had vested in the Government; and the amount shall, in the 
first instance, be paid to the raiyat by the Government and shall be 
recovered from the under- raiyat in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>534697</tid>
<number>6</number>Where a mortgagee in possession acquires the rights of the 
mortgagor in respect of any excess land under sub- section (3) of 
section 169, the compensation payable by the mortgagee in respect of 
that land shall be such sum of money, if any, as may be due to the 
mortgagor after setting off the mortgage debt against the market value 
of such excess land.

</section>

<section><tid>339735</tid>
<number>7</number>Where any excess land of a religious or charitable 
institution vests in the Government, such institution shall, in 
lieu of compensation payable under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), 
or sub- section (3), be paid an annuity equal to the net annual income 
of the excess land and such net annual income shall be determined by 
the competent authority in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1945153</tid>
<number>8</number>The competent authority shall, after holding an inquiry in 
the prescribed manner, make an order determining the amount of com- 
pensation payable to any person under this section.,


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1244617</tid>
<number> 172</number> Manner of payment of compensation.
<section><tid>885365</tid>
<number>1</number>The compensation  
payable under section 171 shall be due from the date of the 
publication of the list under sub- section (3) of section 170 and may 
be paid in cash, in a lump sum or in instalments, or in bonds.

</section>

<section><tid>50553</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the compensation is payable in bonds, the bonds may be 
made not transferable or transferable by endorsement or in any other 
manner but all such bonds shall be redeemed within such period, not 
exceeding twenty years from the date of issue, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1138114</tid>
<number>3</number>Where there is any delay In the payment of compensation or 
where the compensation is paid either in instalments or in bonds, it 
shall carry interest at the rate of two and a half per cent. per annum 
from the date on which it falls due.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>605</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>343902</tid>
<number>173</number>Limit of future acquisition of land. No person representing 
a family shall acquire in any manner whatsoever, whether by transfer, 
exchange, lease, agreement or succession, any land where such 
acquisition has the effect of making the total area of the land held 
by him exceed the ceiling limit; and any such land in excess of the 
ceiling limit shall be treated as excess land of the transferee and 
the provisions of sections 167 to 172 shall, as far as may be, apply 
to such excess land.

</article>



<article><tid>599457</tid>
<number>174</number>Excess land not to be surrendered in certain cases. Where a 
person representing a family holds land not exceeding the ceiling 
limit, but subsequently the land held exceeds the ceiling limit, then, 
notwithstanding anything contained in this Chapter, such person shall 
not be required to surrender any part of the land on the ground that 
it is excess land, if such excess is due to any improvements effected' 
in the land by the efforts of the family or to a decrease in the 
number of its members.

</article>



<article><tid>961079</tid>
<number>175</number>Power of Collector to take possession of excess land. 
After the publication of the list of excess land under sub- section (3) 
of section 170, and after demarcation' in the prescribed manner of 
such land where necessary, the Collector may take possession of any 
excess land and may use or cause to be used such force as may be 
necessary for the purpose.

</article>



<article><tid>276356</tid>
<number> 176</number> Offences and penalties.
<section><tid>618263</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever being bound to submit a  
return under section 165 fails to do so, without reasonable cause, 
within the prescribed time, or submits a return which he knows or has 
reason to believe to be false, shall be punishable with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1185830</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever contravenes any lawful order made under this Chapter 
or otherwise obstructs any person from lawfully taking possession of 
any land shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>782498</tid>
<number>177</number>Finality of orders. Subject to the revisions of this Act, 
every order made under this Chapter shall be final.

</article>



<article><tid>1706450</tid>
<number> 178</number> Power to exempt, etc.
<section><tid>1015106</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, on an  
application made to him in this behalf within three months from the 
commencement of this Act, exempt from the operation of section 164-

<subsection><tid>56070</tid>
<number>a</number>any land which is being used for growing tea, coffee or 
rubber including lands used or required for use for purposes 
ancillary to, or for the extension of, the cultivation of 
tea, coffee or rubber to be determined in the prescribed 
manner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1597528</tid>
<number>b</number>any sugarcane farm operated by a sugar factory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1158688</tid>
<number>c</number>any specialised farm which is being used for cattle 
breeding, dairy or wool raising;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>606</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1032103</tid>
<number>d</number>any person who holds a compact block of land exceeding 
the ceiling limit which-

<subsubsection><tid>1674504</tid>
<number>i</number>is being used as an orchard from before the 1st 
January, <year>1958</year>; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>242459</tid>
<number>ii</number>is being used as a farm in which heavy investment
or permanent structural improvements have been made and 
which, in the opinion of the Administrator, is being so effi- 
ciently managed that its break up is likely to bring a fall 
in production:

Provided that where such person holds the compact block of 
land together with any other land, he shall be permitted to 
elect to retain either the compact block of land, 
notwithstanding that it exceeds the ceiling limit or the 
other land not exceeding the ceiling limit;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1250250</tid>
<number>e</number>any land which is being held by a co- operative society, 
provided that where a member of any such society holds a 
share in such land, his share shall be taken into account in 
determining his ceiling limit:
Provided that the Administrator may entertain the application 
after the expiry of the said period of three months, if he is 
satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from 
making the application in time.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>719951</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any land in respect of which exemption has beer. 
granted to a person under clause (d) of sub- section (1) is transferred 
to another person, the Administrator may, on an application made to 
him within three months from the date of the transfer, exempt the 
transferee from the operation of section 164 and section 173 and the 
provisions of the said clause shall, as far as may be, apply to the 
grant of such exemption.

</section>

<section><tid>351615</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the Administrator is of opinion that the use of land 
for any specified purpose is expedient or necessary in the public 
interest, he may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make a dec- 
laration to that effect and on the issue of such notification, any 
person may, notwithstanding anything contained in section 173, acquire 
land in excess of the ceiling limit for being used for such specified 
purpose and such person shall, within one month from the date of such 
acquisition, send intimation thereof to the competent authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1023124</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any land, in respect of which exemption has been 
granted under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) or sub- section (3),

<pagefootnote><pagenum>607</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

ceases to be used, or is not within the prescribed time used, for the 
purpose for which exemption had been granted, the Administrator may, 
after giving the persons affected an opportunity of being heard 
withdraw such exemption.

CHAP 
PREVENTION OF FRAGMENTATION

CHAPTER XIV.- PREVENTION OF FRAGMENTATION



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1674527</tid>
<number> 179</number> Definitions. For the purposes of this Chapter,-
<section><tid>1279820</tid>
<number>a</number>" holding" means the aggregate area of land held by 
person as a raiyat;

</section>

<section><tid>1483499</tid>
<number>b</number>" fragment" means a holding of less than two standard 
acres in area;

</section>

<section><tid>1913884</tid>
<number>c</number>" land" has the same meaning as in Chapter XIII.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>673806</tid>
<number> 180</number> Restrictions on transfer, etc.
<section><tid>916865</tid>
<number>1</number>No portion of a holding  
shall be transferred by way of sale, exchange, gift, bequest or 
mortgage with possession, so as to create a fragment:
Provided that the provisions of this sub- section shall not apply to a 
gift made in favour of the Bhoodan movement initiated by Acharya 
Vinoba Bhave.


</section>

<section><tid>84775</tid>
<number>2</number>No portion of a holding shall be transferred by way of 
lease, where as a result of such lease,-

<subsection><tid>763839</tid>
<number>i</number>the lessor shall be left with less than two standard 
acres, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1995397</tid>
<number>ii</number>the total area held by the lessee exceeds the limit of 
a family holding.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1272703</tid>
<number>3</number>No fragment shall be transferred to a person who does not 
have some land under personal cultivation or to a person who holds, or 
by reason of such transfer shall hold, land in excess of the limit of 
a family holding.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>96738</tid>
<number> 181</number> Partition of holding.
<section><tid>1896113</tid>
<number>1</number>No holding shall be partitioned in  
such manner as to create a fragment.

</section>

<section><tid>422421</tid>
<number>2</number>A fragment shall not be partitioned unless as a result of 
such partition its portions get merged in holdings of two standard 
acres or more or in fragments so as to create holdings of two standard 
acres or more.

</section>

<section><tid>965926</tid>
<number>3</number>Whenever, in a suit for partition, the court finds that the 
partition of a holding will result in the creation of a fragment, the 
court shall, instead of proceeding to divide the holding, direct the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>608</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

sale of the same and distribute the proceeds thereof among the co- 
sharers.


</section>

<section><tid>1309652</tid>
<number>4</number>Wherever a holding is put up for sale under sub- section (3), 
a co- sharer shall have the first option to purchase the holding at the 
highest bid; if there are two or more co- sharers claiming the first 
option, that co- sharer who offers the highest consideration shall be 
preferred.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1769451</tid>
<number> 182</number> Transfers in contravention of this Chapter.
<section><tid>1190994</tid>
<number>1</number>Any  
transfer, partition or lease of land made in contravention of the 
provisions of this Chapter shall be void.

</section>

<section><tid>1889430</tid>
<number>2</number>No document of transfer, partition or lease of land shall be 
registered unless declarations in writing are made, in such form and 
manner as may be prescribed, by the parties thereto before the 
competent registering authority under the Indian Registration Act, 
<year>1908</year>, (16 of <year>1908</year>.) regarding lands held by each prior to the 
transaction and the land which each shall come to hold thereafter.

</section>

<section><tid>611190</tid>
<number>3</number>No registering authority shall register under the Indian 
Registration Act, <year>1908</year>, (16 of <year>1908</year>.) any document of transfer, 
partition or lease of land if, from the declarations made under sub- 
section (2), it appears that the transaction has been effected in 
contravention of the provisions of this Chapter.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>333202</tid>
<number>183</number>Penalty. The parties to any transfer, partition or lease 
made or entered into in contravention of any of the provisions of this 
Chapter shall be punishable with fine which may extend to one hundred 
rupees.

</article>



<article><tid>1399342</tid>
<number> 184</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1423521</tid>
<number>1</number>The Administrator may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Part.

</section>

<section><tid>1223798</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1202916</tid>
<number>a</number>the form in which, and the period within which, a 
return under section 165 may be submitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>848553</tid>
<number>b</number>the agency through which information may be collected 
under section 166;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>986545</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner of holding enquiries under this Part; id 
the matters which may be determined under sub- section (1) of 
section 167 and the manner of determination of excess lands 
under this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1791949</tid>
<number>d</number>the matters which may be determined under sub- section (1) 
of section 167 and the manner of determination of excess 
lands under this Part;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>399301</tid>
<number>e</number>the form in which a list under sub- section (3) of section 
AT or sub- section' (3) of section 170 may be prepared and the 
manner of publication of such list;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1769175</tid>
<number>f</number>the period within which an application for restoration of 
excess land may be made under the proviso to sub- section (4)' 
of section 169;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>430298</tid>
<number>g</number>the manner of apportionment of compensation between the 
raiyat and the under- raiyat under sub- section (2) of section 
171;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>534715</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner of assessment of the market value of any 
structure or. building or trees under sub- section (3) of 
section 171;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1676782</tid>
<number>i</number>the manner of recovery of the compensation payable by the 
under- raiyat under sub- section (5) of section 171;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>993084</tid>
<number>j</number>the manner of determining under sub- section (6) of 
section 171 the market value of any excess land in respect of 
which a mortgagee, in Possession acquires the rights of the 
mortgagor;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>803073</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner of determination of the net annual Income of 
any excess land for the purpose of payment of compensation 
under section 171;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>584191</tid>
<number>l</number>The manner of, payment of compensation, including the 
number of instalments in which the compensation may be paid 
or recovered and the period within which bonds may be 
redeemed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30914</tid>
<number>m</number>the manner of demarcation of any excess land under 
section 175;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1037414</tid>
<number>n</number>the matters which may be determined by the Administrator 
in granting an exemption under section 178 including the form 
in which applications and intimations may be made or given, 
under section 178;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1220058</tid>
<number>o</number>the form of declarations under section 182;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>930926</tid>
<number>p</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.
PART VI

CHAP 
GENERAL AND MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER XV.-- GENERAL AND MISCELLANEOUS



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>891426</tid>
<number>185</number>Recovery of amount due as arrear of land revenue. Without 
prejudice to any, other provision of this Act, any amount due to the 
Government, whether by way of costs, penalty

<pagefootnote><pagenum>610</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

or otherwise, and any other amount which is ordered to be paid to or 
recovered by the Government, under this Act shall be recoverable in 
the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.


</article>



<article><tid>651843</tid>
<number> 186</number> Protection against eviction or surrender in certain cases.

<section><tid>846873</tid>
<number>1</number>After the commencement of this Act and before the vesting date  
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 134,--

<subsection><tid>1975336</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of sections Ill to 117 shall, so Far as 
may be, apply to tenants and sub- tenants as defined in clause 
 (d) of section 133;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1572232</tid>
<number>b</number>no such tenant or sub- tenant shall surrender any land 
held by him as such and no person shall enter upon any such 
land unless such surrender is bona fide and is made with the 
previous permission in writing of the competent authority, 
and the provisions, of sub- section (3) of section 125 shall 
apply to any case where such permission is refused;'

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1632561</tid>
<number>c</number>no such tenant or sub- tenant shall whether in execution of 
a decree or order of court or otherwise, be evicted from any 
such land on any ground other than those specified In clauses 
 (c) and (d) a sub- section (1) of section 118, and any 
proceeding for eviction of such tenant or sub- tenant on any 
ground other than those specified in the said clauses (c) and 
 (d) pending at such commencement shall abate without 
prejudice to any action that may be taken under the 
provisions of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1975544</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, on or after the 10th day of August, <year>1957</year> and before 
the commencement of this Act, any such tenant or sub- tenant has 
surrendered any land held by him as such or been evicted from such 
land and the surrender or eviction could not have taken place if this 
Act had been in force on the date of such surrender or eviction, 
the competent authority may, either on his own motion or on 
application made by the tenor sub- tenant in this behalf, restore him 
to possession of the land 
which has been surrendered or from which he has been evicted.,


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>481917</tid>
<number> 187</number> Special provision regarding Scheduled Tribes. No transfer of 
land by a person who is a member the Scheduled Tribes shall be valid 
unless-
<section><tid>520541</tid>
<number>a</number>the transfer is to another member of the Scheduled 
Tribes; or

</section>

<section><tid>1419952</tid>
<number>b</number>where the transfer is to a person who is not a member of 
any such tribe, it is made with the previous permission in 
writing of the Collector; or

</section>

<section><tid>1309325</tid>
<number>c</number>the transfer is by way of, mortgages to a co- operative 
society.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>611</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1712735</tid>
<number>188</number>Jurisdiction of civil courts excluded. No suit or other 
proceeding shall, unless otherwise expressly provided in this Act, lie 
or be instituted in any civil court with respect to Any matter arising 
under and provided for by this Act:
Provided that if in a dispute between parties a question of title 
is involved, a civil suit may be brought for the adjudication of such 
question.


</article>



<article><tid>1199097</tid>
<number>189</number>Act to over- ride contracts and other laws. Save as otherwise 
provided, the provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in any other law, custom or usage 
or agreement or decree or order of court.

</article>



<article><tid>1529122</tid>
<number>190</number>Court- fees. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Court- 
fees Act, <year>1870</year>, (7 of <year>1870</year>) every application, appeal or other 
proceeding under this Act shall bear a court- fee stamp of such value 
as may be prescribed.

</article>



<article><tid>489087</tid>
<number>191</number>Village officers to be public servants. Every village 
accountant and every other village officer appointed under this Act 
shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 
 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of <year>1860</year>)

</article>



<article><tid>801690</tid>
<number>192</number>Power to exempt. With the previous approval of the 
Government, the Administrator may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, exempt any class of lands from all or any of the provisions 
of this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>256202</tid>
<number>193</number>General provision as to penalties. Whoever contravenes any 
provision of this Act for which no penalty has been otherwise provided 
for therein shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees.

</article>



<article><tid>795938</tid>
<number> 194</number> Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit, 
prosecution or other proceedings shall lie-
<section><tid>370842</tid>
<number>a</number>against any officer of the Government for anything in 
good faith done or intended to be done under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1083009</tid>
<number>b</number>against the Government for any damage caused or likely 
to be caused or any injury suffered or likely to be suffered 
by anything in good faith done or intended to be done under 
this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1397452</tid>
<number>195</number>Delegation of powers. The Administrator may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette delegate to any officer or authority 
subordinate to him any of the powers conferred on him or on any 
officer subordinate to him by this Act, other than the power to make 
rules, to be exercised subject to such restrictions and conditions as 
may be specified in the said notification.

</article>



<article><tid>1693474</tid>
<number>196</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to any provision of this Act, the Government may, as 
occasion requires, take any action not inconsistent with the 
provisions of this Act which may appear to it necessary for the 
purpose of removing the difficulty,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>612</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>1525705</tid>
<number>197</number>General power to make rules. Without prejudice to any power 
to make rules contained elsewhere In this Act, the Administrator may, 
by notification in the official Gazette, make rules, generally to carry 
out the purposes of this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>1943804</tid>
<number>198</number>Laying of rules before Parliament. Repeal and savings. 
Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as way be after 
it, is made before each House of Parliament while it is In session for 
a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
In two successive sessions, and If before the expiry of the session In 
which it is so laid or the session immediately following, both Houses 
agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that 
the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect 
only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so 
however that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.

</article>



<article><tid>994101</tid>
<number> 199</number> Repeal and savings.
<section><tid>819739</tid>
<number>1</number>On, and from the date on which any  
of the. provisions of this Act are' brought into force in any area in 
the Union territory of Tripura, the enactments specified In the 
Schedule, or so much thereof as relate to the matters, covered by the 
provisions so brought into force repealed In such area.

</section>

<section><tid>564757</tid>
<number>2</number>The repeal of any enactment or part thereof by sub- section

</section>

<section><tid>819739</tid>
<number>1</number>shall not effect,--

<subsection><tid>1210934</tid>
<number>a</number>the previous operation of such enactment of anything 
duly done or suffered thereunder;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1459741</tid>
<number>b</number>any right privilege, obligation or liability acquired, 
accrued or incurred under such enactment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>384262</tid>
<number>c</number>any penalty for forfeiture or punishment incurred in res- 
pect of any offence committed against such enactment;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>526296</tid>
<number>d</number>any investigation legal proceeding or remedy may pect of 
any such right, privilege, obligation, liability, Penalty 
forfeiture orpunishment as aforesaid;
and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
Instituted or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or of had not 
been punishment may be imposed as if such enactment or part there- 
repealed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1243317</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions contained; In, sub- section (2), any 
appointment, rulu order, notification or proclamation made or issued, 
any lease, rent, right or liability granted, fixed, acquired or 
Incurred and any other thing done or action taken under any of the 
enactments or parts thereof repealed, under sub- section (1) shall, in 
so far as it Is not inconsistent with the provision of this Act 
brought Into force, be deemed to have been made, issued, granted, 
fixed

<pagefootnote><pagenum>613</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

acquired, incurred, done or taken under this Act and shall continue to 
be in force until, superseded by anything done or any action taken 
under this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>505161</tid>
<number>4</number>Any custom or usage prevailing At the time any of the pro- 
visions of this Act are brought into force in any area in the Union 
territory of Tripura and having the force of law therein shall if such 
custom or usage is repugnant to or inconsistent with such provision, 
cease to be operative to the extent of such repugnancy, or 
inconsistency.


</section>

</article>



 </act>