<act><title>


THE DRUGS AND MAGIC REMEDIES 
    (OBJECTIONABLE ADVERTISEMENTS) ACT, 1954</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Drugs and Magic Remedies (Objectionable 
    Advertisements) Act, 1954. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir, 
    and applies also to persons domiciled in the territories to which this Act 
    extends who are outside the said territories. 
 </section><section>

    <number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint. 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   ‘advertisement’ includes any notice, circular, label, wrapper, or 
    other document, and any announcement made orally or by any means of 
    producing or transmitting light, sound or smoke; 
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   ‘drug’ includes— 
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   a medicine for the internal or external use of human beings or 
    animals; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   any substance intended to be used for or in the diagnosis, cure, 
    mitigation, treatment or prevention of disease in human beings or animals; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>iii</number>   any article, other than food, intended to affect or influence in any 
    way the structure or any organic function of the body of human beings or 
    animals; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>iv</number>   any article intended for use as a component of any medicine, 
    substance or article, referred to in sub-clauses (i), (ii) and (iii); 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>c</number>   ‘magic remedy’ includes a talisman, mantra, kavacha, 
    and any other charm of any kind which is alleged to possess miraculous 
    powers for or in the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment or prevention of 
    any disease in human beings or animals or for affecting or influencing in 
    any way the structure or any organic function of the body of human beings or 
    animals; 
 

    1[(cc)   
    ‘registered medical practitioner’ means any person,— 
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   who holds a qualification granted by an authority specified in, or 
    notified under, section 3 of the Indian Medical Degrees Act, 1916 (7 of 
    1916) or specified in the Schedules to the Indian Medical Council Act, 1956 
    (102 of 1956); or 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   who is entitled to be registered as a medical practitioner under any 
    law for the time being in force in any State to which this Act extends 
    relating to the registration of medical practitioners;] 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>d</number>   ‘taking any part in the publication of any advertisement’ includes— 
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   the printing of the advertisement; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   the publication of any advertisement outside the territories to which 
    this Act extends by or at the instance of a person residing within the said 
    territories. 
 

    2[***]
 







 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> Prohibition of advertisement of certain drugs for treatment of certain 
    diseases and disorders.—Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, no person shall take any part in the 
    publication of any advertisement referring to any drug in terms which 
    suggest or are calculated to lead to the use of that drug for— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   the procurement of miscarriage in women or prevention of conception in 
    women; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   the maintenance or improvement of the capacity of human beings for 
    sexual pleasure; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>   the correction of menstrual disorder in women; or 
 

    1[(d)   
    the diagnosis, cure, mitigation, treatment or prevention of any disease, 
    disorder or condition specified in the Schedule, or any other disease, 
    disorder or condition (by whatsoever name called) which may be specified in 
    the rules made under this Act: 
 

    Provided that no such rule shall be made except— 
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   in respect of any disease, disorder or condition which requires timely 
    treatment in consultation with a registered medical practitioner or for 
    which there are normally no accepted remedies, and 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   after consultation with the Drugs Technical Advisory Board 
    constituted under the Drugs and Cosmetics Act, 1940 (23 of 1940) and, if the 
    Central Government considers necessary, with such other persons having 
    special knowledge or practical experience in respect of Ayurvedic or Unani 
    systems of medicines as that Government deems fit.] 
 
 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Prohibition of misleading advertisements relating to drugs.—Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, no person shall take any part in the 
    publication of any advertisement relating to a drug if the advertisement 
    contains any matter which— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   directly or indirectly gives a false impression regarding the true 
    character of the drug; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   makes a false claim for the drug; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>   is otherwise false or misleading in any material particular. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Prohibition of advertisement of magic remedies for treatment of certain 
    diseases and disorders.—No 
    person carrying on or purporting to carry on the profession of administering 
    magic remedies shall take any part in the publication of any advertisement 
    referring to any magic remedy which directly or indirectly claims to be 
    efficacious for any of the purposes specified in section 3.
 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>6</number> Prohibition of import into, and export from, India of certain advertise-ments.—No 
    person shall import into, or export from, the territories to which this Act 
    extends any document containing an advertisement of the nature referred to 
    in section 3, or section 4, or section 5, and any documents containing any 
    such advertisement shall be deemed to be goods of which the import or export 
    has been prohibited under section 19 of the Sea Customs Act, 1878 (8 of 
    1878) and all the provisions of that Act shall have effect accordingly, 
    except that section 183 thereof shall have effect as if for the word ‘shall’ 
    therein the word ‘may’ were substituted. 
 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>7</number> Penalty.—Whoever 
    contravenes any of the provisions of this Act 

    1[or 
    the rules made thereunder] shall, on conviction, be punishable— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   in the case of a first conviction, with imprisonment which may extend 
    to six months, or with fine, or with both; 
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   in the case of a subsequent conviction, with imprisonment which may 
    extend to one year, or with fine, or with both. 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>

    1[<number>8</number> 
    Powers of entry, search, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of any rules made in this behalf, any Gazetted 
    Officer authorised by the State Government may, within the local limits of 
    the area for which he is so authorised,— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   enter and search at all reasonable times, with such assistants, if 
    any, as he considers necessary, any place in which he has reason to believe 
    that an offence under this Act has been or is being committed; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   seize any advertisement which he has reason to believe contravenes any 
    of the provisions of this Act: 
 

    Provided that the power of seizure under this clause may be exercised in 
    respect of any document, article or thing which contains any such 
    advertisement, including the contents, if any, of such document, article or 
    thing, if the advertisement cannot be separated by reason of its being 
    embossed or otherwise, from such document, article or thing without 
    affecting the integrity, utility or saleable value thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   examine any record, register, document or any other material object 
    found in any place mentioned in clause (a) and seize the same if he has 
    reason to believe that it may furnish evidence of the commission of an 
    offence punishable under this Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>2</number> The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898) 
    shall, so far as may be, apply to any search or seizure under this Act as 
    they apply to any search or seizure made under the authority of a warrant 
    issued under section 98 of the said Code.
 </section><section>

    <number>3</number> Where any person seizes anything under clause (b) or clause (c) of 
    sub-section (1), he shall, as soon as may be, inform a Magistrate and take 
    his orders as to the custody thereof.] 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>9</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the person contravening any of the provisions of this Act is a company, 
    every person who, at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, 
    and was responsible to, the company for the conduct of the business of the 
    company as well as the company shall be deemed to be guilty of the 
    contravention and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
    accordingly: 
 

    Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such 
    person liable to any punishment provided in this Act if he proves that the 
    offence was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due 
    diligence to prevent the commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence was committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable 
    to any neglect on the part of, any director or manager, secretary or the 
    officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer 
    of the company shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall 
    be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly. 
 


    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   ‘company’ means any body corporate and includes a firm or other 
    association of individuals, and
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   ‘director’ in relation to a firm means a partner in the firm. 
  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>9A</number> 
    Offences to be cognizable.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898), an 
    offence punishable under this Act shall be cognizable.] 
 

 








 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>10</number> Jurisdiction to try offences.—No 
    court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the 
    first class shall try any offence punishable under this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>10A</number> 
    Forfeiture.—Where 
    a person has been convicted by any court for contravening any provision of 
    this Act or any rule made thereunder, the court may direct that any document 
    (including all copies thereof), article or thing, in respect of which the 
    contravention is made, including the contents thereof where such contents 
    are seized under clause (b) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 8, shall be 
    forfeited to the Government.]
  
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>11</number> Officers to be deemed to be public servants.—Every 
    person authorised under section 8 shall be deemed to be a public servant 
    within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 

 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>12</number> Indemnity.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person for 
    anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>13</number> Other laws not affected.—The 
    provisions of this Act are in addition to, and not in derogation of the 
    provisions of any other law for the time being in force.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>14</number> 
    Savings.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall apply to—
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   any signboard or notice displayed by a registered medical practitioner 
    on his premises indicating that treatment for any disease, disorder or 
    condition specified in section 3, the Schedule or the rules made under this 
    Act is undertaken in those premises; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   any treatise or book dealing with any of the matters specified in 
    section 3 from a bona fide scientific or social standpoint; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>   any advertisement relating to any drug sent confidentially in the 
    manner prescribed under section 16 only to a registered medical 
    practitioner; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>d</number>   any advertisement relating to a drug printed or published by the 
    Government; or 
 </section><section>

    <number>e</number>   any advertisement relating to a drug printed or published by any 
    person with the previous sanction of the Government granted prior to the 
    commencement of the Drugs and Magic Remedies (Objectionable Advertisements) 
    Amendment Act, 1963 (42 of 1963): 
 

    Provided that the Government may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, 
    withdraw the sanction after giving the person an opportunity of showing 
    cause against such withdrawal.]
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> 
      Power to exempt from application of Act.—If 
      in the opinion of the Central Government public interest requires that the 
      advertisement of any specified drug or class of drugs 1[or 
      any specified class of advertisements relating to drugs] should be 
      permitted, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that 
      the provisions of sections 3, 4, 5 and 6 or any one of such provisions 
      shall not apply or shall apply subject to such conditions as may be 
      specified in the notification to or in relation to the advertisement of 
      any such drug or class of drugs 2[or 
      any such class of advertisements relating to drugs].
  
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    <number>16</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>

    <number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
    power, such rules may— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   specify any 

    1[disease, 
    disorder or condition] to which the provisions of section 3 shall apply;
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   prescribe the manner in which advertisements of articles or things 
    referred to in clause (c) of 

    2[***] 
    section 14 may be sent confidentially. 
 

    3[(3) 
    Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each of House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
    more successive sessions and if before the expiry of the session in which it 
    is so laid or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making 
    any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
    be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
    be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any such modification 
    or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
    previously done under that rule.]
 

 
 












 



</subsection></section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




THE DRUGS AND MAGIC REMEDIES  

    (OBJECTIONABLE ADVERTISEMENTS) ACT, 1954
 

 
 

 
 



    1[THE 
    SCHEDULE
 



    [See sections 3(d) and 14]
 

 
 
 
 S. No.
 Name of the 
        disease, disorder or condition
  
 S. No.
 Name of the 
        disease, disorder or condition

 
 
 



        1.   Appendicitis tc 
        " 
        1. Appendicitis" 
 



        2.   Arteriosclerosis tc 
        " 
        2. Arteriosclerosis" 
 



        3.   Blindness tc 
        " 
        3. Blindness" 
 



        4.   Blood poisoning tc 
        " 
        4. Blood poisoning" 
 



        5.   Bright’s disease tc 
        " 
        5. Bright’s disease" 
 



        6.   Cancer tc 
        " 
        6. Cancer" 
 



        7.   Cataract tc 
        " 
        7. Cataract" 
 



        8.   Deafness tc 
        " 
        8. Deafness" 
 



        9.   Diabetes
 



        10. Diseases and disorders of the brain
 



        11. Diseases and disorders of the optical system
 



        12. Diseases and disorders of the uterus
 



        13.   Disorders of menstrual flow
 



        14.   Disorders of the nervous system
 



        15.   Disorders of the prostatic gland
 



        16.   Dropsy tc 
        " 
        16. Dropsy" 
 



        17.   Epilepsy tc 
        " 
        17. Epilepsy" 
 



        18.   Female diseases (in general)
 



        19.   Fevers (in general)
 



        20.   Fits tc 
        " 
        20. Fits" 
 



        21.   Form and structure of the female bust
 



        22. Gall stones, kidney stones and bladder stones
 



        23.   Gangrene tc 
        " 
        23. Gangrene" 
 



        24.   Glaucoma tc 
        " 
        24. Glaucoma" 
 



        25.   Goitre tc 
        " 
        25. Goitre" 
 



        26.   Heart diseases tc 
        " 
        26. Heart diseases" 
 



        27.   High or low blood pressure
  
 
 



        28.   Hydrocele tc 
        " 
        28. Hydrocele" 
 



        29.   Hysteria tc 
        " 
        29. Hysteria" 
 



        30.   Infantile paralysis tc 
        " 
        30. Infantile paralysis" 
 



        31.   Insanity tc 
        " 
        31. Insanity" 
 



        32.   Leprosy tc 
        " 
        32. Leprosy" 
 



        33.   Leucoderma tc 
        " 
        33. Leucoderma" 
 



        34.   Lockjaw tc 
        " 
        34. Lockjaw" 
 



        35.   Locomotor ataxia tc 
        " 
        35. Locomotor ataxia" 
 



        36.   Lupus tc 
        " 
        36. Lupus" 
 



        37.   Nervous debility tc 
        " 
        37. Nervous debility" 
 



        38.   Obesity tc 
        " 
        38. Obesity" 
 



        39.   Paralysis tc 
        " 
        39. Paralysis" 
 



        40.   Plague tc 
        " 
        40. Plague" 
 



        41.   Pleurisy tc 
        " 
        41. Pleurisy" 
 



        42.   Pneumonia tc 
        " 
        42. Pneumonia" 
 



        43.   Rheumatism tc 
        " 
        43. Rheumatism" 
 



        44.   Ruptures tc 
        " 
        44. Ruptures" 
 



        45.   Sexual impotence
 



        46.   Smallpox tc 
        " 
        46. Smallpox" 
 



        47.   Stature of persons
 



        48.   Sterility in women tc 
        " 
        48. Sterility in women" 
 



        49.   Trachoma tc 
        " 
        49. Trachoma" 
 



        50.   Tuberculosis tc 
        " 
        50. Tuberculosis" 
 



        51.   Tumours tc 
        " 
        51. Tumours" 
 



        52.   Typhoid fever tc 
        " 
        52. Typhoid fever" 
 



        53.   Ulcers of the gastro-intestinal tract
 



        54.   Venereal diseases, including syphilis,  

  gonorrhoea, soft chancre, venereal  

  granuloma and lympho granuloma.]


 

 
 




    -----------------------
 


          1.       Added 
    by Act 42 of 1963, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 7-12-1963). tc 
    " 2. Added by Act 42 of 1963, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 
    7-12-1963)."
 




    -----------------------
 





 



 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>