<act><tid>1930625</tid>
<title>THE OBSTRUCTIONS IN FAIRWAYS ACT, <year>1881</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1881</year>
[ 15th March, <year>1881</year>.] Preamb

An Act to empower the Government to remove or destroy obstructions in 
fairways, and to prevent the creation of such obstructions.





<article><tid>1837172</tid>
<number>1</number>short title. This Act may be called the Obstructions in 
Fairways Act, <year>1881</year>; <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
But nothing herein contained shall apply to vessels <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> belonging 
to, or hired by a contract made on behalf of, the Government].



</article>



<article><tid>563393</tid>
<number> 2</number> Central Government empowered to remove or destroy obstruction 
in fairway. Whenever, in any fairway leading to any port in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
territories which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were 
comprised in Part A States and Part C States], any vessel in sunk, 
stranded or abandoned, or any fishing- stake, timber or other thing is 
placed or left, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Central Government] may, if in its opinion such 
thing is, or is likely to become, an obstruction or danger to 
navigation,
<section><tid>593940</tid>
<number>a</number>cause such thing or any part thereof to be removed; or

</section>

<section><tid>49716</tid>
<number>b</number>if such thing is of such a description or so situate 
that, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> in the opinion of the Central Government], it 
is not worth removing, cause the same or any part 
thereof to be destroyed.
Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch.

Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f.  
  1. 10. <year>1967</year>): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>56</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> for" a Part A 
State or a Part C State". 
2. The words" and it shall come into force at once" rep. by Act 10 
to <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II. 
3. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" belonging to Her Majesty or hired by 
Her Majesty or by the Secretary of State for India in Council". 
4. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the L. G. of the part of British 
India in which such port is situate". 
5. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" in the opinion of the L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>595424</tid>
<number>3</number>Central Government entitled to expenses incurred in removing 
obstruction. Whenever anything is removed under section 2, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 
Central Government] shall be entitled to receive a reasonable sum, 
having regard to all the circumstances of the case, for the expenses 
incurred in respect of such removal.
Dispute concerning such expenses.

Any dispute arising concerning the amount due under this section, 
in respect of anything so removed, shall be decided by the District 
Magistrate or Presidency Magistrate having jurisdiction at the place 
where such thing is, upon application to him for that purpose by 
either of the disputing parties; and such decision shall be final.



</article>



<article><tid>504913</tid>
<number>4</number>Notice of removal to be given by Central Government. The 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] shall, whenever anything is removed under 
section 2, publish in the Official Gazette a notification containing a 
description of such thing, and the time at which and the place from 
which the same was so removed.


</article>



<article><tid>305889</tid>
<number>5</number>Things removed may, in certain cases, be sold. If after 
publishing such notification, such thing is unclaimed, or
if the person claiming the same fails to pay the amount due 
for the said expenses and any customs- duties or other 
charges properly incurred by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] 
in respect thereof,

the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] may sell such thing by public 
auction, if it is of a perishable nature, forthwith, 
and if it is not of a perishable nature, at any time 
not less than six months after publishing such 
notification as aforesaid.



</article>



<article><tid>904876</tid>
<number>6</number>Proceeds how applied. On realizing the proceeds of such sale, 
the amount due for expenses and charges as aforesaid, together with 
the expenses of the sale, shall be deducted therefrom, and the surplus 
 (if any) shall be paid to the owner of the thing sold, or, if no such 
person appear and claim such surplus, shall be held in deposit for 
payment, without interest, to any person thereafter establishing his 
right to the same:
Provided that he makes the claim within one year from the date of 
the sale.



</article>



<article><tid>1064769</tid>
<number>7</number>" Vessel" to include tackle, cargo, etc. For the purposes of 
this Act, the term" vessel" shall be deemed to include also every 
article or thing or collection of things being or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>57</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the Govt.". 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" L. G.".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


forming part of the tackle, equipment, cargo, stores or ballast of a 
vessel; and any proceeds arising from the sale of a vessel, and of the 
cargo thereof, or of any other property recovered therefrom, shall be 
regarded as a common fund.



</article>



<article><tid>1198201</tid>
<number>8</number>Power to make rules to regulate and prohibit the placing of 
obstructions in fairways. The Central Government may, from time to 
time, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to regulate 
or prohibit, in any fairway leading to a port in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part A States and Part C States] the placing of fishing- stakes, the 
casting or throwing of ballast, rubbish, or any other thing likely to 
give rise to a bank or shoal, or the doing of any other act which 
will, in its opinion, cause, or be likely to cause, obstruction or 
danger to navigation.


</article>



<article><tid>264431</tid>
<number>9</number>Penalty for breach of such rules. Whoever is guilty of any act 
or omission in contravention of the rules made under section 8, may be 
tried for such offence in any district or presidency- town in which he 
is found, and shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to six months, or with fine which may extend to five hundred 
rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1389055</tid>
<number>10</number>Compensation payable in certain cases for damage caused under 
this Act. Whenever the maintenance or creation of an obstruction in 
any fairway has become lawful by long usage or otherwise, and such 
obstruction is removed or destroyed under section 2, or its creation 
is regulated or prohibited under section 8, any person having a right 
to maintain or create such obstruction shall be entitled to receive 
from the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] reasonable compensation for any damage 
caused to him by such removal, destruction, regulation or prohibition.
Every dispute arising concerning the right to such compensation, 
or the amount thereof, shall be determined according to the law for 
the time being in force relating to like disputes in the case of land 
needed for public purposes <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and not otherwise; and for the purposes 
of such law the fairway from or in which such obstruction was removed 
or destroyed, or in which its creation was regulated or prohibited, 
shall be deemed to be a part of the presidency- town or district in 
which the port to which such fairway leads is situate.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>58</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" a Part A 
State or a Part C State". 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" Secretary of State for India in 
Council". 
3. See the Land Acquisition Act, <year>1894</year> (1 of <year>1894</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>589622</tid>
<number>11</number>Certain action of the Government previous to passing of this 
Act to be deemed to have been taken hereunder. Whenever any 
obstruction in a fairway leading to a port in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part A States and Part C States] has been removed or destroyed, or 
whenever the creation of any such obstruction has been regulated or 
prohibited, by an order of the Central Government or a State 
Government, previous to the passing of this Act, such removal, 
destruction, regulation or prohibition shall be deemed to have been 
effected under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>806385</tid>
<number>12</number>Saving of other powers possessed by Central Government. 
Nothing herein contained shall be deemed to prevent the exercise by 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Central Government] of any other powers possessed by it in this 
behalf.


</article>



<article><tid>763131</tid>
<number>13</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Application to fairways in inland waterways. All 
references in this Act to the Central Government shall, in relation to 
fairways in inland waterways, be construed as references to <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> State 
Government]].
<pagefootnote><pagenum>59</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> for" a Part A 
State or a Part C State". 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the Govt". 
3. Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
4. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year> for" the 
Government of a Part A State or a Part C State".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>