<act><tid>1934209</tid>
<title>THE SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF OFFICERS OF PARLIAMENT 
 (SECOND AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 31 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 27th May, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Salaries and Allowances of Officers of 
Parliament Act, <year>1953</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>158342</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>317073</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Salaries and Allowances of Officers of Parliament (Second Amendment) 
Act, <year>2002</year>. (2) It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 3rd 
day of March, <year>2002</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>668472</tid>
<number> 2</number> Insertion of new section 7A.- After section 7 of the Salaries and 
Allowances of Officers of Parliament Act, <year>1953</year> (20 of <year>1953</year>), the 
following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 7A. Family pension, etc., to spouse of Speaker dying in office.- (1) 
With effect from the commencement of the Salaries and Allowances of 
Officers of Parliament (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, there shall be 
paid a family pension, to the spouse of the Spe ker of the House of 
the People who dies while holding such office at the rate of fifty per 
cent. of the salary last drawn by him for the remainder of life of 
such spouse from the date of death of the Speaker:

Provided that the spouse of such Speaker shall not be entitled to 
receive pension available to the spouse of any member of Parliament 
who dies during his term of office as such member for a period of five 
years from the date of death of the member under ub- section (1A) of 
section 8A of the Salary, Allowances and Pension of Members of 
Parliament Act, <year>1954</year> (30 of <year>1954</year>).

<section><tid>871855</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of clause (a) of sub- section 
 (2) of section 4 and subject to any rules made in this behalf under 
section 11, such spouse shall be entitled to the use of unfurnished 
life. residence without payment of licence fee for the remainder of 
her

</section>

<section><tid>894070</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to any rules made in this behalf under section 11,-

<subsection><tid>1654422</tid>
<number>a</number>such spouse, for the remainder of her life; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>918714</tid>
<number>b</number>the minor children of such Speaker, shall be entitled to medical 
attendance and treatment, free of charge.".
-----

SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>