<act><title>THE WAREHOUSING (DEVELOPMENT AND REGULATION) REGISTRATION OF ACCREDITATION AGENCIES RULES, 20101 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Warehousing (Development and Regulation) Registration of Accreditation Agencies Rules, 2010. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "Act" means the Warehousing (Development and Regulation)  
    Act, 2007 (37 of 2007); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "applicant" means a person making an application to the Authority seeking registration as an accreditation agency under rule 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> "certificate" means certificate of registration granted under rule 6; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> "Form" means the form appended to these rules. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The words and expressions used in these rules and not defined but defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Qualifications and other requirements for functioning as an accreditation agency. </title>-Every person desirous of functioning as an accreditation agency shall fulfil the following qualifications and other requirements, namely:- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> such person shall be- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a body corporate either public or private, and incorporated under the Companies Act, 1956 or any other law in force; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> government body or government affiliated body; 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>ii</number> such person should possess necessary infrastructure including adequate office space, equipment, trained and experienced staff, expertise in the field of warehousing, financial capability and credibility to the satisfaction of the Authority; and 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> such person is not directly engaged in warehousing business. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Application for registration of an accreditation agency. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Any person possessing qualifications and other requirements specified under rule 3 and desirous of being registered as an accreditation agency may make an application to the Authority in duplicate, in Form A. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every application under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> proof of identity as a legal entity including certificate of incorporation, Memorandum of Association and Articles of Association; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> list of names of owners, shareholders, proprietor and authorized signatory of applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> list of key management personnel and technical experts engaged by the applicant and their qualifications and experience in various fields relating to warehousing; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> statement of financial credibility in the form of audited reports or budget statement with supporting documents; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> declaration that the applicant shall not accredit any warehouse in which it may have a direct conflict of interest; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> declaration that the applicant shall comply with the terms and conditions of certificate of registration; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> a non-refundable registration fee of rupees twenty-five thousand through bank draft/banker's cheque of any nationalized bank in favour of Drawing and Disbursing Officer, Warehousing Development and Regulatory Authority, payable in New Delhi; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> a security deposit of rupees one lakh through bank draft/banker's cheque of any nationalized bank in favour of Drawing and Disbursing Officer, Warehousing Development and Regulatory Authority payable in New Delhi : 
</subsection>
 Provided that the Government controlled institution or body may be exempted from payment of security deposit. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Power to make enquiry and call for information at the time of registration. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Before granting registration to an accreditation agency under  
rule 6, the Authority may make such inquiry and require such further information, as it deems necessary, other than the information furnished by the accreditation agency in the application. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Authority may call for any information at any time and the applicant shall furnish such information to the Authority within the time stipulated by it. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>6</number> Certificate of Registration. </title>-The Authority shall, after being satisfied that the applicant fulfils the qualifications and other requirements, grant the certificate of registration to the applicant within a period of one month from the date of receipt of application in Form B and subject to such terms and conditions as it may deem fit. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>7</number> Refusal of Registration. </title>-The Authority may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, refuse to grant the certificate of registration to any applicant and shall furnish him with a copy of the order so passed: 
 Provided that before rejecting such application, the Authority shall give a reasonable opportunity of hearing to the applicant. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>8</number> Validity and Renewal. </title>-The certificate of registration granted under rule 6 shall be valid for a period of three years and shall be renewable for a like period in the manner provided under rules 4, 5, 6 and 7. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>9</number> Duties of accreditation agency </title>.-Every accreditation agency shall- <title></title>
 
 <section><number>a</number> upon receipt of certificate of registration, display such certificate, in a conspicuous place in the principal place of its business; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> make an assessment report in relation to each warehouse that it assesses and shall maintain a copy thereof for a minimum period of three years; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> maintain accounts, books, records and documents relating to accredited warehouses; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> not transfer the certificate of registration granted to it; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> allow and assist the Authority or its authorized representative to inspect its office, books, records, papers, accounts, etc., at any time; and 
 </section><section><number>f</number> maintain a Register of accredited warehouses in Form C and shall publish the list on its website. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>10</number> Issue of duplicate registration certificate. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Where a certificate of registration is lost, damaged or mutilated, the Authority shall issue a duplicate certificate of registration on receipt of a request in Form D. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A certificate of registration, which is torn or defaced shall be surrendered by the accreditation agency to the Authority on issue of duplicate certificate. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The application for issue of a duplicate certificate of registration shall be accompanied by a fee of rupees five thousand through bank draft/banker's cheque of any nationalized bank in favour of Drawing and Disbursing Officer, Warehousing Development and Regulatory Authority, payable in New Delhi. 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>11</number> Publication of grant of registrations and list of accreditation agencies. </title>-The names and addresses of accreditation agencies to whom certificate of registration is granted under rule 6 shall be duly displayed on website of the Authority from time-to-time. 


</article> 

  
 <article> <title><number>12</number> Suspension or cancellation of certificate of Registration. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The Authority may suspend or cancel the certificate of registration granted to a accreditation agency if- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> it has furnished wrong information in the application; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> it has failed to comply with the terms and conditions of certificate of registration specified by the Authority; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> it has failed to perform duties specified under rule 9. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the certificate of registration is suspended or cancelled under  
  sub-rule (1), the security deposit paid under clause (h) of sub-rule (2) of rule 4 shall stand forfeited to the Authority. 


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 8-11-2010.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>