<act><title>The Central Information Commission (Appeal 
      Procedure) Rules, 20051</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Central 
      Information Commission (Appeal Procedure) Rules, 2005.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of 
      their publication in the Official Gazette.
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Right to Information 
    Act, 2005;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “section” means section of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Commission” means the Central 
    Information Commission;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    words and expressions used herein and 
    not defined but defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively 
    assigned to them in that Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Contents 
    of appeal.—An appeal to the 
    Commission shall contain the following information, namely:—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    name and address of the appellant;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    name and address of the Central Public 
    Information Officer against the decision of whom the appeal is preferred;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    particulars of the order including 
    number, if any, against which the appeal is preferred;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    brief facts leading to the appeal;  
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    if the appeal is preferred against 
    deemed refusal, the particulars of the application, including number and 
    date and name and address of the Central Public Information Officer to whom 
    the application was made;
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    prayer or relief sought;   
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>    grounds for the prayer or relief;   
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>    verification by the appellant; and  
 </section><section>
<number>ix</number>    any other information which the 
    Commission may deem necessary for deciding the appeal.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Documents to accompany appeal.—Every 
    appeal made to the Commission shall be accompanied by the following 
    documents, namely:—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    self-attested copies of the Orders or 
    documents against which the appeal is being preferred;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    copies of documents relied upon by the 
    appellant and referred to in the appeal; and  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    an index of the documents referred to 
    in the appeal.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Procedure in deciding appeal.—In 
    deciding the appeal the Commission may,—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>    hear oral or written evidence on oath 
    or on affidavit from concerned or interested person;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    peruse or inspect documents, public 
    records or copies thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    inquire through authorised officer 
    further details or facts;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    hear Central Public Information 
    Officer, Central Assistant Public Information Officer or such Senior Officer 
    who decide the first appeal, or such person against whom the complaint is 
    made, as the case may be;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    hear third party; and
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    receive evidence on affidavits from 
    Central Public Information Officer, Central Assistant Public Information 
    Officer, such Senior Officer who decided the first appeal, such person 
    against whom the complaint lies or the third party.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Service 
    of notice by Commission.—Notice 
    to be issued by the Commission may be served in any of the following modes, 
    namely:—
 <section>
<number>i</number>    service by the party itself;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    by hand delivery (dasti) through 
    Process Server;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    by registered post with 
    acknowledgement due; or 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    through Head of Office or Department.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Personal 
    presence of the appellant or complainant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The appellant or the complainant, as the case may be, shall in every case be 
    informed of the date of hearing at least seven clear days before that date.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    appellant or the complainant, as the case may be, may at his discretion at 
    the time of hearing of the appeal or complaint by the Commission be present 
    in person or through his duly authorised representative or may opt not to be 
    present.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    Commission is satisfied that the circumstances exist due to which the 
    appellant or the complainant, as the case may be, is being prevented from 
    attending the hearing of the Commission, then, the Commission may afford the 
    appellant or the complainant, as the case may be, another opportunity of 
    being heard before a final decision is taken or 
    take any other appropriate action as it may deem fit.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    appellant or the complainant, as the case may be, may seek the assistance of 
    any person in the process of the appeal while presenting his points and the 
    person representing him may not be a legal practitioner.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Order of 
    the Commission.—Order of the 
    Commission shall be pronounced in open proceedings and be in writing duly 
    authenticated by the Registrar or any other officer authorised by the 
    Commission for this purpose.  
  
 
 
 


 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>