<act><tid>1940532</tid>
<title>THE RECIPROCITY ACT, <year>1943</year></title>

ACT NO. 9 OF <year>1943</year>
[ 31st March, <year>1943</year>.]

An Act to make provisions on a basis of reciprocity in regard to entry 
into, travel, residence, the acquisition, holding or disposal of 
property, the enjoyment of educational facilities, the holding of 
public office, or the carrying on of any occupation, trade, business 
or profession in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India by, and the franchise in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India of, 
persons domiciled in British possessions.

Preamble. WHEREAS it is expedient to make provisions on a basis 
of reciprocity in regard to entry into, travel, residence, the 
acquisition, holding or disposal of property, the enjoyment of 
educational facilities, the holding of public office, or the carrying 
on of any occupation, trade, business or profession in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India by, 
and the franchise in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India of, persons domiciled in British 
possessions;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1668290</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>30923</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Reciprocity Act, <year>1943</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1490066</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>1980558</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It shall come into force on the 1st day of September, 
<year>1943</year>.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1084235</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context--
<section><tid>1455067</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" British possession" means any part of His Majesty' s 
dominions <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and includes a protectorate or other 
territory administered by a British possession as a 
mandatory on behalf of the League of Nations; and where 
parts of those dominions are under both a central and a 
local legislature, the expression shall mean either 
each part under a local legislature or all parts under 
the central legislature];
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, S. 3 
and Schedule.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" certain parts of" omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. 
2. The words" except Part B States" omitted by s. 3 and Sch., ibid. 
3. Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1943</year>, s. 2, for the original sub- section. 
4. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for the original definition. 
5. The words" exclusive of India" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1339684</tid>
<number>b</number>" entry" includes landing at any port in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] 
during the stay in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] of a ship or aircraft on 
its way to a destination outside <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India];
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1796596</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power of Central Government to impose reciprocal 
disabilities on persons domiciled in British possessions. Where by the 
law or practice of any British possession persons of Indian origin are 
subject in that British possession to disabilities in respect of entry 
into, or travel, residence, the acquisition, holding or disposal of 
property, the enjoyment of educational facilities, the holding of 
public office, the carrying on of any occupation, trade, business or 
profession, or the exercise of the franchise in, that British 
possession, to which in respect of the like matters in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] 
persons domiciled in that British possession are not subject in 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], the Central Government may, by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct that the same disabilities or disabilities as 
similar thereto as may be, shall, notwithstanding anything contained 
in any other law for the time being in force, be imposed in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] 
on persons not being of Indian origin who are domiciled in that 
British possession.]


</article>



<article><tid>120603</tid>
<number>4</number>Burden of proof on person claiming exemption. If any person 
alleged to be domiciled in any British possession and to be subject to 
the provisions of this Act pleads that he is not so domiciled, or that 
the provisions of this Act do not apply to him, the onus of proving 
the truth of such a plea shall be on him.


</article>



<article><tid>342793</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Direction imposing disabilities in respect of entry, travel 
and residence not to apply to armed forces. Any direction made by the 
Central Government under section 3 imposing disabilities in respect of 
entry into or travel or residence in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] upon persons domiciled 
in a British possession shall not, until the expiry of six months 
after the termination of the present hostilities, apply to any person 
domiciled in that British possession who is a member of its armed 
forces.]


</article>



<article><tid>1264413</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1678940</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> rules for carrying out 
the purposes of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States". 
2. Cl. (c) ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, omitted by s. 3 and Sch., ibid. 
3. Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1943</year>, s. 4, for the original section. 
4. For such notifications, see Gazette of India, <year>1944</year>, 
Extraordinary, pp. 1487 and 1488. 
5. Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1943</year>, s. 5, for the original section. 
6. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for the original section. 
7. For the Reciprocity (South Africa) Rules, <year>1944</year>, the Reciprocity 
 (Natal and the Transvaal) Rules, <year>1944</year> and the Reciprocity 
 (South Africa)  (Locai Franchise) Rules, <year>1944</year>, see Gazette of India, 
<year>1944</year>, Extraordinary, pp. 1527- 1529.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>480874</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, rules made under this section may provide-

<subsection><tid>1748637</tid>
<number>a</number>for the setting up of machinery to ascertain the 
disabilities in respect of any of the matters specified 
in section 3 to which persons of Indian origin are 
subject in any British possession;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>920355</tid>
<number>b</number>for the establishment of a suitable agency to 
administer the rules and for defining its functions and 
powers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1063785</tid>
<number>c</number>for specifying the disabilities that shall, when a 
direction has been made under section 3, be imposed in 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] on persons not being of Indian origin who are 
domiciled in any British possession and for the 
imposition on them of the disabilities so specified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>900664</tid>
<number>d</number>for the enforcement, by the prescription of a penalty 
by way of imprisonment or fine or both, of any rule 
made under clause (c);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>976725</tid>
<number>e</number>for authorizing the arrest of any person contravening 
or reasonably suspected of contravening any rule made 
under clause (c), and for prescribing the duties of 
public servants and others in regard to such arrests.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>599923</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1663357</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Repeal of Act 3 of <year>1924</year>. The Immigration into India Act, 
 <year>1924</year> (3 of <year>1924</year>), is hereby repealed.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States". 
2. Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 22 of <year>1943</year>, s. 7.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>