<act><tid>1945893</tid>
<title>THE DISPLACED PERSONS (COMPENSATION AND REHABILITATION) ACT, <year>1954</year></title>

ACT NO. 44 OF <year>1954</year>
[ 9th October, <year>1954</year>.]

An Act to provide for the payment of compensation and rehabilitation 
grants to displaced persons and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>762627</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Displaced Persons 
 (Compensation and Rehabilitation) Act, <year>1954</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>878934</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1375681</tid>
<number>a</number>" compensation pool" means the compensation pool 
constituted under section 14;

</section>

<section><tid>40284</tid>
<number>b</number>" displaced person" means any person who, on account of 
the setting up of the Dominions of India and Pakistan, 
or on account of civil disturbances or the fear of such 
disturbances in any area now forming part of West 
Pakistan, has, after the first day of March, <year>1947</year>, 
left, or been displaced from, his place of residence in 
such area and who has been subsequently residing in 
India, and includes any person who is resident in any 
place now forming part of India and who for that reason 
is unable or has been rendered unable to manage, 
supervise or control any immovable property belonging 
to him in West Pakistan, and also includes the 
successors- in- interest of any such person;

</section>

<section><tid>1610628</tid>
<number>c</number>" evacuee property" means any property which has been 
declared or is deemed to have been declared as evacuee 
property under the Administration of Evacuee Property 
Act, <year>1950</year>; (31 of <year>1950</year>)

</section>

<section><tid>409848</tid>
<number>d</number>" public dues" in relation to a displaced person, 
includes--

<subsection><tid>1554472</tid>
<number>i</number>arrears of rent in respect of any 
property allotted or leased to the displaced 
person by the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>112</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Central government or a State Government or the 
Custodian;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>477023</tid>
<number>ii</number>any amount recoverable, whether in one 
lump sum or in instalments, from the displaced 
person on account of loans granted to him by the 
Central Government or a State Government or the 
Rehabilitation Finance Administration constituted 
under the Rehabilitation Finance Administration 
Act, <year>1948</year> (12 of <year>1948</year>), and any interest on such 
loans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1272314</tid>
<number>iii</number>the amount of purchase money or any 
part thereof and any interest on such amount or 
part remaining unpaid and recoverable from the 
displaced person on account of transfer to him 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of any property or interest therein by-- 
 (a) the Central Government; or 
 (b) any State Government; or 
 (c) any body corporate or other authority or 
person financed by the Central Government or a 
State Government for the purpose of the 
acquisition, development or construction of any 
immovable property for the rehabilitation of 
displaced persons;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1638606</tid>
<number>iiia</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any dues payable, whether in one 
lump sum or in instalments, to a co- operative 
society, registered as such under any law for the 
time being in force, by the displaced person on 
account of loans granted to him by the co- 
operative society, where such loans have been 
granted out of funds placed at the disposal of the 
co- operative society by the Central Government or 
a State Government and such dues have been 
declared by the Central Government, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, to be public 
dues;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>720386</tid>
<number>iv</number>any other dues payable to the Central 
Government, a State Government or the Custodian 
which may be declared by the Central Government, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, to be 
public dues recoverable from the displaced person;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>212690</tid>
<number>e</number>" verified claim" means any claim registered under the 
Displaced Persons (Claims) Act, <year>1950</year>, (44 of <year>1950</year>) in 
respect of which
<pagefootnote><pagenum>113</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 86 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2, for certain words (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


a final order has been passed under that Act or under 
the Displaced Persons (Claims) Supplementary Act, <year>1954</year>, 
 (12 of <year>1954</year>) <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and includes any claim registered on or 
before the 31st day of May, <year>1953</year>, under the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> East 
Punjab Refugees (Registration of Land Claims) Act, 
 <year>1948</year> (East Punjab Act 12 of <year>1948</year>)], or under the 
Patiala Refugees (Registration of Land Claims) 
Ordinance, <year>2004</year> (Ord 10 of <year>2004</year> BK.), and verified 
by any authority appointed for the purpose by the 
Government of Punjab, the Government of patiala or the 
Government of patiala and East Punjab States Union, 
as the case may be, which has not been satisfied 
wholly or partially by the allotment of any evacuee 
land under the relevant notification specified in 
section 10 of this Act, but does not include--]


<subsection><tid>1387322</tid>
<number>i</number>any such claim registered in respect of 
property held in trust for a public purpose of a 
religious or charitable nature;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>94978</tid>
<number>ii</number>except in the case of a banking company 
for the purpose of sub- clause (i) of clause (b) of 
sub- section (3) of section 6, only-- 
 (a) any such claim made by or on behalf 
of any company or association, whether 
incorporated or not; 
 (b) any such claim made by a mortgagee 
or other person holding a charge or lien on 
immovable property belonging to a displaced 
person in West Pakistan;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1685892</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>378605</tid>
<number>g</number>" West Pakistan" means the territories of Pakistan 
excluding the Province of East Bengal and includes the 
tribal areas of Tochi and Kurram and such other tribal 
areas adjoining the North- West Frontier Province as may 
be specified in this behalf by order of the Central 
Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1655858</tid>
<number>h</number>all other words and expressions used but not defined in 
this Act and defined in the Administration of Evacuee 
Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of <year>1950</year>) have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in that Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>114</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 86 of <year>1956</year> s. 2, for certain words (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>). 
2. Subs, by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2, for" East Punjab Refugees 
 (Registration of Claims) Act, <year>1948</year>" (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP

PAYMENT OF COMPENSATION AND REHABILITATION GRANTS TO DISPLACED PERSONS

CHAPTER II

PAYMENT OF COMPENSATION AND REHABILITATION GRANTS TO 
DISPLACED PERSONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1218069</tid>
<number> 3</number> Appointment of Chief Settlement Commissioner, etc.
<section><tid>975368</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
appoint a Chief Settlement Commissioner, a Joint Chief Settlement 
Commissioner, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> and as many Deputy Chief Settlement Commissioners, 
Settlement Commissioners], Additional Settlement Commissioners, 
Assistant Settlement Commissioners, Settlement Officers, Assistant 
Settlement Officers and managing officers as may be necessary for the 
purpose of performing the functions assigned to them by or under this 
Act and may, by general or special order, provide for the distribution 
or allocation of work to be performed by them under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>907539</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Joint Chief 
Settlement Commissioner, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> all Deputy Chief Settlement Commissioners, 
Settlement Commissioners], Additional Settlement Commissioners, 
Settlement Officers and managing officers shall perform the functions 
assigned to them by or under this Act under the general 
superintendence and control of the Chief Settlement Commissioner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>848845</tid>
<number> 4</number> Application for payment of compensation.
<section><tid>701637</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, from time to time, but not later than the thirtieth 
day of June, <year>1955</year>, by notification in the Official Gazette, require 
all displaced persons having a verified claim to make applications for 
the payment of compensation and any such notification may be issued 
with reference to displaced persons residing in any State or in any 
one of a group of States.

</section>

<section><tid>297997</tid>
<number>2</number>Every displaced person who, by a notification issued under 
sub- section (1), is required to make an application for the payment of 
compensation shall make such application in the prescribed form to the 
Settlement Officer having jurisdiction, within three months of the 
date of the notification:
Provided that the Settlement Officer may entertain any such 
application after the expiry of the said period of three months, if he 
is satisfied that the applicant was prevented by sufficient cause from 
filing the application in time.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>114A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs, by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3, for" a Deputy Chief Settlement 
Commissioner and as many Settlement Commissioners". 
2. Subs. by s. 3, ibid., for" the Deputy Chief Settlement 
Commissioner and all Settlement Commissioners".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1736483</tid>
<number>3</number>An application for the payment of compensation under this 
section shall contain the following particulars, namely:-

<subsection><tid>534625</tid>
<number>a</number>the name and address of the applicant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1324393</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount of the verified claim;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>342999</tid>
<number>c</number>the encumbrances, if any, on the property to which the 
verified claim relates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1492417</tid>
<number>d</number>the form in which the applicant desires to receive 
compensation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>342983</tid>
<number>e</number>the amount if any, of the public dues recoverable from 
the applicant;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1732598</tid>
<number>f</number>the property, if any, allotted or leased to the 
applicant by the Central Government or a State 
Government or by the Custodian;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>543497</tid>
<number>g</number>such other particulars as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>251158</tid>
<number>4</number>Any notification issued by the Central Government before the 
commencement of this Act requiring displaced persons of any class or 
description to make applications for the payment of compensation, 
shall be deemed to have been issued under this section and all 
applications for compensation made in pursuance of any such 
notification shall be deemed to have been made under this section and 
any proceeding in relation to any such application pending at the 
commencement of this Act shall be disposed of in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act;
Provided that a displaced person who has made an application for 
payment of compensation before the commencement of this Act, may 
within one month of such commencement intimate in writing to the 
officer or authority to whom the application was made or to the 
successor- in- office of any such officer or authority, the form in 
which he desires to receive the compensation.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>115</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>957313</tid>
<number>5</number>Determination of public dues by Settlement Officers. On 
receipt of an application under section 4, the Settlement Officer 
shall, after making an inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed, 
pass an order determining the amount of public dues, if any, 
recoverable from the applicant and shall forward the application and 
the record of the case to the Settlement Commissioner.


</article>



<article><tid>1471417</tid>
<number> 6</number> Relief to certain banking companies.
<section><tid>23354</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a debt due to a  
banking company is secured by a mortgage, charge or lien on any 
immovable property belonging to a displaced person in West Pakistan in 
respect to which compensation is payable under this Act and such 
mortgage, charge or lien was subsisting at the date when the claim of 
the banking company was registered under the Displaced Persons 
 (Claims) Act, <year>1950</year> (44 of <year>1950</year>), the banking company shall be entitled 
to relief in accordance with the provisions of this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1360215</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the displaced person is entitled to receive 
compensation in respect of any such property as is referred to in sub- 
section (1), the banking company shall be entitled,--

<subsection><tid>458194</tid>
<number>a</number>if the compensation to the displaced person in respect 
of such property is payable in cash, to receive such 
amount as bears to the total debt, the same proportion 
as the compensation payable to the displaced person 
bears to the value of the verified claim of the 
displaced person in respect of such property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>909532</tid>
<number>b</number>if the compensation to the displaced person is payable 
in the form of transfer of any property from the 
compensation pool, then subject to a prior charge under 
sub- section (3) of section 20, to a second charge on 
such property for the amount which would have been 
payable to the banking company under clause (a) if the 
displaced person had been paid compensation in cash;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1708052</tid>
<number>c</number>if the compensation to the displaced person is payable 
in any other form to such relief as the Settlement 
Officer, having regard to the principle specified in 
clause (a) or clause (b), may determine.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>74745</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>974483</tid>
<number>a</number>the expression" banking company" means any of the 
displaced banks specified in the Schedule and includes 
any other banking company which, before the fifteenth

<pagefootnote><pagenum>116</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

day of August, <year>1947</year> carried on the business of banking, 
whether wholly or partially in any area now forming 
part of West Pakistan, and which the Central Government 
may, having regard to the dislocation of such business 
on account of the partition of the country, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this 
behalf;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1229029</tid>
<number>b</number>the expression" total debt" means,--

<subsubsection><tid>1070090</tid>
<number>i</number>where the banking company has preferred a 
claim under the Displaced Persons (Claims) Act, 
 <year>1950</year> (44 of <year>1950</year>) and the claim has been verified, 
the amount of the verified claim, subject to such 
adjustment as the Settlement Officer, having 
regard to the provisions of the Displaced Persons 
 (Debts Adjustment) Act, <year>1951</year> (70 of <year>1951</year>) 
applicable to secured debts, may make;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1146324</tid>
<number>ii</number>where the banking company has preferred 
such claim but the claim has not been verified, 
such amount as the Settlement Officer, having 
regard to the provisions of the Displaced Persons 
 (Debts Adjustment) Act, <year>1951</year> (70 of <year>1951</year>) 
applicable to secured debts, may determine.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>962841</tid>
<number> 7</number> Determination of the amount of compensation.
<section><tid>914014</tid>
<number>1</number>On receipt of  
an application for payment of compensation together with the record of 
the case forwarded under section 5, the Settlement Commissioner shall 
make an inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed and having due 
regard to the prescribed scales of compensation, the nature of the 
verified claim and other circumstances of the case, shall ascertain 
the amount of compensation to which the applicant is entitled.

</section>

<section><tid>274356</tid>
<number>2</number>On ascertaining the amount of compensation to which an 
applicant is entitled under sub- section (1), the Settlement 
Commissioner shall deduct therefrom the following dues recoverable 
from the applicant, in the order of priority mentioned below:--

<subsection><tid>1079618</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount, if any, of the public dues recoverable from 
the applicant under section 5;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>514824</tid>
<number>b</number>the amount, if any, payable to a banking company under 
section 6, and the amount, if any, of the prior charge 
declared under sub- section (3) of section 16 of the 
Displaced Persons (Debts Adjustment) Act, <year>1951</year> (70 of  
  <year>1951</year>) in respect of which any communication is received 
from any tribunal under section 52 of that Act;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>117</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753126</tid>
<number>c</number>where any communication is received from any tribunal 
under section 52 of the Displaced Persons (Debts  
  Adjustment) Act, <year>1951</year> (70 of <year>1951</year>) in respect of any 
unsecured debts, the amount of such debts payable by 
the applicant in accordance with the provisions of that 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>221503</tid>
<number>3</number>After deducting the dues referred to in sub- section (2), the 
Settlement Commissioner shall make an order determining the net amount 
of compensation, if any, payable to the applicant.

</section>

<section><tid>292284</tid>
<number>4</number>The amount, if any, deducted under sub- section (2) shall be 
paid to the person entitled to it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1993271</tid>
<number> 8</number> Form and manner of payment of compensation.
<section><tid>293838</tid>
<number>1</number>A displaced  
person shall be paid out of the compensation pool the amount of net 
compensation determined under sub- section (3) of section 7 as being 
payable to him, and subject to any rules that may be made under this 
Act, the Settlement Commissioner or any other officer or authority 
authorized by the Chief Settlement Commissioner in this behalf may 
make such payment in any one of the following forms or partly in one 
and partly in any other form, namely:-

<subsection><tid>894806</tid>
<number>a</number>in cash;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1482595</tid>
<number>b</number>in Government bonds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>373898</tid>
<number>c</number>by sale to the displaced person of any property from 
the compensation pool and setting off the purchase 
money against the compensation payable to him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>745736</tid>
<number>d</number>by any other mode of transfer to the displaced person 
of any property from the compensation pool and setting 
off the valuation of the property against the 
compensation payable to him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>513683</tid>
<number>e</number>by transfer of shares or debentures in any company or 
corporation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>776710</tid>
<number>f</number>in such other form as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>587771</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of payment of compensation under this Act, 
the Central Government may, by rules, provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1714157</tid>
<number>a</number>the classes of displaced persons to whom compensation 
may be paid;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>118</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>549222</tid>
<number>b</number>the scales according to which, the form and manner in 
which, and the instalments by which compensation may be 
paid to different classes of displaced persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1035744</tid>
<number>c</number>the valuation of all property, shares and debentures to 
be transferred to displaced persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>643703</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which is to be, or may be, prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1724915</tid>
<number> 8A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Payment of compensation in cases of mortgaged properties.

<section><tid>158259</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any compensation is payable to any displaced person in lieu  
of property abandoned by him in West Pakistan which on the date of his 
migration from West Pakistan was subject to a mortgage in favour of a 
person who is not resident in India, the Settlement Commissioner 
shall, after giving a reasonable notice to the displaced person, 
determine the principal sum for which the property was so mortgaged 
and such portion of the principal sum so determined as bears the same 
proportion as the Compensation payable to the displaced person bears 
to the value of the verified claim of the displaced person in respect 
of that mortgaged property shall be deductible from the compensation 
payable in respect of the mortgaged property:
Provided that where compensation has been paid to any displaced 
person without such deduction having been made, the displaced person 
shall pay to the Central Government the amount of such deduction 
within three months of the determination thereof or such longer period 
as may be prescribed:

Provided further that where compensation has been paid to any 
displaced person by sale or any other mode of transfer to him of any 
property from the compensation pool, the displaced person may, within 
the aforesaid period of three months or, as the case may be, within 
the aforesaid prescribed period,--


<subsection><tid>413551</tid>
<number>a</number>either retain the property on his paying in cash the 
aforesaid amount, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>551115</tid>
<number>b</number>surrender a portion of that property of a value 
equivalent to the amount of such deduction, such value 
being determined by the Settlement Commissioner in the 
prescribed manner.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>108039</tid>
<number>2</number>If any displaced person fails to pay any amount which is 
liable to be deducted from his compensation under sub- section (1), or 
fails to surrender the property of the value equivalent to such 
amount,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>118A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 17 of <year>1968</year>, s. 2 (retrospectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


such amount may be recovered in the same manner as an arrear of land 
revenue.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>200346</tid>
<number> 9</number> Payment of compensation in cases of disputes. Where there is 
any dispute as to the person or persons who are entitled to the 
compensation (including any dispute as to who are the successors- in-  
  interest of any deceased claimant to compensation) or as to the 
apportionment of compensation among persons entitled thereto, such 
dispute shall, after such enquiry as may be prescribed, be decided,--
<section><tid>609520</tid>
<number>a</number>where the value of the verified claim does not exceed 
twenty thousand rupees, by the Settlement Officer;

</section>

<section><tid>378627</tid>
<number>b</number>where the value of the verified claim exceeds twenty 
thousand rupees, by the Settlement Commissioner:
Provided that the Settlement Officer or the Settlement 
Commissioner, as the case may be, may refer any such dispute to the 
District Judge nominated in this behalf by the State Government, whose 
decision thereon shall be final.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1386056</tid>
<number> 10</number> Special procedure for payment of compensation in certain 
cases. Where any immovable property has been leased or allotted to a 
displaced person by the Custodian under the conditions published--
<section><tid>914532</tid>
<number>a</number>by the notification of the Government of Punjab in the 
Department of Rehabilitation No. 4891-S or 1892-S, 
dated the 8th July, <year>1949</year>; or

</section>

<section><tid>923320</tid>
<number>b</number>by the notification of the Government of Patiala and 
East Punjab States Union in the Department of 
Rehabilitation No. 8R or 9R, dated the 23rd July, <year>1949</year>, 
and published in the Official Gazette of that State, 
dated the 7th August, <year>1949</year>,
and such property is acquired under the provisions of this Act and 
forms part of the compensation pool, the displaced person shall, so 
long as the property remains vested in the Central Government, 
continue in possession of such property on the same conditions on 
which he held the property immediately before the date of the 
acquisition, and the Central Government may, for the purpose of 
payment of


<pagefootnote><pagenum>119</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

compensation to such displaced person, transfer to him such property 
on such terms and conditions as may be prescribed.

Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that the notifications of the Government of Patiala and East Punjab 
States Union Nos. 7R, 8R and 9R, dated the 23rd July, <year>1949</year>, and 
published in the Official Gazette on the 7th August, <year>1949</year>, purporting 
to have been made under the provisions of the Patiala and East Punjab 
States Union Evacuees (Administration of Property) Ordinance, <year>2006</year> 
 (P. E. P. S. U. Ord. 13 of <year>2006</year>), shall be deemed to have been 
issued under the provisions of the Patiala and East Punjab States 
Union Administration of Evacuee Property Ordinance, <year>2006</year> (P. E. P. S.  
  U. Ord. 17 of <year>2006</year>) and the said notifications shall not be invalid 
and shall be deemed never to have been invalid merely by reason of the 
fact that they were expressed to have been issued under the provisions 
of the said Ordinance No. 13 of <year>2006</year>, and anything done or any action 
taken (including any lease or allotment granted or made) under the 
provisions of the said notifications shall, notwithstanding any defect 
in, or invalidity of, the said notifications, be deemed for all 
purposes to have been validly done or taken as if the said 
notifications were issued under the provisions of the aforesaid 
Ordinance No 17 of <year>2006</year> and this section were in force on the day on 
which such thing was done or action was taken.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>856252</tid>
<number> 11</number> Rehabilitation and other grants to displaced persons.
<section><tid>598995</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government may, for the relief and rehabilitation of displaced 
persons, direct payment of any rehabilitation grant or other grant out 
of the compensation pool to a displaced person under such conditions 
and to such extent and in such form and manner as may be prescribed.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


CHAP

COMPENSATION POOL FOR PURPOSES OF PAYMENT OF COMPENSATION 
ANDREHABILITATION GRANTS TO DISPLACED PERSONS

CHAPTER III

COMPENSATION POOL FOR PURPOSES OF PAYMENT OF COMPENSATION AND 
REHABILITATION GRANTS TO DISPLACED PERSONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>956937</tid>
<number> 12</number> Power to acquire evacuee property for rehabilitation of 
displaced person.
<section><tid>691377</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is of opinion that it  
is necessary to acquire any evacuee property for a public purpose, 
being
<pagefootnote><pagenum>120</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (2) omitted by Act 86 of <year>1956</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


purpose connected with the relief and rehabilitation of displaced 
persons, including payment of compensation to such persons, the 
Central Government may at any time acquire such evacuee property by 
publishing in the Official Gazette a notification to the effect that 
the Central Government has decided to acquire such evacuee property in 
pursuance of this section.


</section>

<section><tid>1748425</tid>
<number>2</number>On the publication of a notification under sub- section (1), 
the right, title and interest of any evacuee in the evacuee property 
specified in the notification shall, on and from the beginning of the 
date on which the notification is so published, be extinguished and 
the evacuee property shall vest absolutely in the Central Government 
free from all encumbrances.

</section>

<section><tid>1154643</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be lawful for the Central Government, if it so 
considers necessary, to issue from time to time the notification 
referred to in sub- section (1) in respect of--

<subsection><tid>729633</tid>
<number>a</number>all evacuee property generally; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>320128</tid>
<number>b</number>any class of evacuee property; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1056570</tid>
<number>c</number>all evacuee property situated in a specified area; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1014925</tid>
<number>d</number>any particular evacuee property.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1740909</tid>
<number>4</number>All evacuee property acquired under this section shall form 
part of the compensation pool.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1874233</tid>
<number>13</number>Compensation for evacuee property acquired under this Act. 
There shall be paid to an evacuee compensation in respect of his 
property acquired under section 12 in accordance with such principles 
and in such manner as may be agreed upon between the Governments of 
India and Pakistan.


</article>



<article><tid>440115</tid>
<number> 14</number> Compensation pool.
<section><tid>1144381</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of payment of  
compensation and rehabilitation grants to displaced persons, there 
shall be constituted a compensation pool which shall consist of--

<subsection><tid>1307411</tid>
<number>a</number>all evacuee property acquired under section 12, 
including the sale proceeds of any such property and 
all profits and income accruing from such property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>147598</tid>
<number>b</number>such cash balances lying with the Custodian as may, by 
order of the Central Government, be transferred to the 
compensation pool;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>121</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1270194</tid>
<number>c</number>such contributions, in any form whatsoever, as may be 
made to the compensation pool by the Central Government 
or any State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>499736</tid>
<number>d</number>such other assets as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1907775</tid>
<number>2</number>The compensation pool shall vest in the Central Government 
free from all encumbrances and shall be utilised in accordance with 
the provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>708171</tid>
<number>15</number>Exemption of property in compensation pool from processes of 
Courts. No property which forms part of the compensation pool and 
which is vested in the Central Government under the provisions of this 
Act shall be liable to be proceeded against for any claim in any 
manner whatsoever in execution of any decree or order or by any other 
process of any Court or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>292054</tid>
<number> 16</number> Management of compensation pool.
<section><tid>942736</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may take such measures as it considers necessary or expedient for the 
custody, management and disposal of the compensation pool in order 
that it may be effectively utilised in accordance with the provisions 
of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1853551</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, the Central Government may, for the purposes referred 
to in sub- section (1), by notification in the Official Gazette,--

<subsection><tid>1173818</tid>
<number>a</number>appoint such officers as it may deem fit (hereinafter  
  referred to as managing officers); or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>811470</tid>
<number>b</number>constitute such authority or corporation, as it may 
deem fit (hereinafter referred to as managing  
  corporation).

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>979782</tid>
<number>3</number>Every managing corporation shall be constituted under such 
name and shall consist of such number of persons as may be specified 
in the notification, and every such corporation shall be a body 
corporate having perpetual succession and a common seal and shall by 
the said name sue and be sued:
Provided that one- third of the members of every managing 
corporation shall be non- officials.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1853435</tid>
<number> 17</number> Functions and duties of managing officers and managing 
corporations.
<section><tid>13365</tid>
<number>1</number>All managing officers or managing corporations shall  
perform such functions as may be assigned to them by or under this Act 
under the general superintendence and control of the Chief Settlement 
Commissioner.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>887274</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
thereunder, a managing officer or managing corporation may take such 
measures as he or it considers necessary or expedient for the purpose 
of securing, administering, preserving, managing or disposing of any 
property in the compensation pool entrusted to him or it and generally 
for the purpose of satisfactorily discharging any of the duties 
imposed on him or it by or under this Act and may, for any such 
purpose as aforesaid, do all acts and incur all expenses necessary or 
incidental thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>932345</tid>
<number>3</number>Any amount due to the Custodian in respect of any evacuee 
property acquired under this Act for any period prior to the date of 
the acquisition shall vest in, and be payable to, the Central 
Government and shall be recoverable by the managing officer or 
managing corporation from the person liable to pay the same.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1497545</tid>
<number> 18</number> Dissolution of managing corporation.
<section><tid>1978027</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central  
Government is satisfied that the property entrusted to a managing 
corporation for custody, management and disposal has been transferred 
to any person or persons under this Act or that for any other reason 
it is no longer necessary to continue the managing corporation, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
dissolve the managing corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>88953</tid>
<number>2</number>Upon the publication of a notification under sub- section (1) 
dissolving a managing corporation--

<subsection><tid>183974</tid>
<number>a</number>all the members of the managing corporation shall 
vacate their office as such members;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1730255</tid>
<number>b</number>all the powers and duties which may, by or under the 
provisions of this Act, be exercised or performed by or 
on behalf of the managing corporation shall be 
exercised and performed by such person or persons as 
the Central Government may direct;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1297929</tid>
<number>c</number>all property vested in the managing corporation at the 
date of dissolution shall vest in the Central 
Government.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1331324</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to vary or cancel leases or allotment of any property 
acquired under this Act.
<section><tid>1722687</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any  
contract or any other law for the time being in force but subject to 
any rules that may be made under this Act, the managing officer or 
managing corporation may cancel any allotment or terminate any lease 
or amend the terms of any lease or allotment under which any evacuee 
property acquired under this Act is held or occupied by a person,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>123</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Whether such allotment or lease was granted before or after the 
commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>155400</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Where any person,--

<subsection><tid>603499</tid>
<number>a</number>has ceased to be entitled to the possession of any 
evacuee property by reason of any action taken under 
sub- section (1), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1987607</tid>
<number>b</number>is otherwise in unauthorized possession of any evacuee 
property or any other immovable property forming part 
of the compensation pool;
he shall, after he has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing 
cause against his eviction from such property, surrender possession of 
the property on demand being made in this behalf by the managing 
officer or managing corporation or by any other person duly authorized 
by such officer or corporation.]


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>206288</tid>
<number>3</number>If any person fails to surrender possession of any property 
on demand made under sub- section (2), the managing officer or managing 
corporation may, notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in 
any other law for the time being in force, eject such person and take 
possession of such property and may, for such purpose, use or cause to 
be used such force as may be necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>687891</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Where a managing officer or a managing corporation is 
satisfied that any person, whether by way of allotment or lease, is, 
or has at any time been, in possession of any evacuee property 
acquired under this Act to which he was not entitled, or which was in 
excess of that to which he was entitled, under the law under which 
such allotment or lease was made or granted, then, without prejudice 
to any other action which may be taken against that person, the 
managing officer or the managing corporation may, having regard to 
such principles of assessment of rent as may be specified in this 
behalf by the Central Government, by order, assess the rent payable in 
respect of such property and that person shall be liable to pay the 
rent so assessed for the period for which the property remains or has 
remained in his possession:
Provided that no such order shall be made without giving to the 
person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>1138157</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any person is, or has at any time been, in unauthorised 
possession of any evacuee property acquired under this Act the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>124</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 86 of <year>1956</year>, s. 4, for sub- section (2)  (w. e. f. 22- 10-  
  <year>1956</year>). 
2. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


managing officer or the managing corporation may, having regard to 
such principles of assessment of damages as may be specified in this 
behalf by the Central Government, assess the damages on account of the 
use and occupation of such property and may, by order, require that 
person to pay the damages within such time and in such instalments as 
may be specified in the order:

Provided that no such order shall be made without giving to the 
person concerned a reasonable opportunity of being heard.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>113931</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to transfer property out of the compensation pool.
<section><tid>113116</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Subject to any rules that may be made under this Act, the managing 
officer or managing corporation may transfer any property out of the 
compensation pool--

<subsection><tid>187382</tid>
<number>a</number>by sale of such property to a displaced person or any 
association of displaced persons, whether incorporated 
or not, or to any other person, whether the property is 
sold by public auction or otherwise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1892991</tid>
<number>b</number>by lease of any such property to a displaced person or 
an association of displaced persons, whether 
incorporated or not, or to any other person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>534601</tid>
<number>c</number>by allotment of any such property to a displaced person 
or an association of displaced persons whether 
incorporated or not, or to any other person, on such 
valuation as the Settlement Commissioner may determine;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>489075</tid>
<number>d</number>in the case of a share of an evacuee in a company, by 
transfer of such share to a displaced person <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or any 
association of displaced persons, whether incorporated 
or not, or to any other person], notwithstanding 
anything to the contrary contained in the Indian 
Companies Act, <footcitenum>19132</footcitenum> (7 of <year>1913</year>.) or in the memorandum 
or articles of association of such company;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1894490</tid>
<number>e</number>in such other manner as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1172896</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> For the purpose of transferring any property out of the 
compensation pool under sub- section (1), it shall be lawful for the 
managing officer or the managing corporation to transfer the same to a 
displaced person jointly with any other person or an association of 
displaced persons or otherwise.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>125</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 86 of <year>1956</year>, s. 5. 
2. See now the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 5.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>906306</tid>
<number>2</number>Every managing officer or managing corporation selling any 
immovable property by public auction under sub- section (1) shall be 
deemed to be a Revenue Officer within the meaning of sub- section (4) 
of section 89 of the Indian Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16 of <year>1908</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>995072</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the ownership of any property has passed to the buyer 
before the payment of the whole of the purchase money, the amount of 
the purchase money or any part thereof remaining unpaid and any 
interest on such amount or part shall, notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in any other law, be a first charge upon the 
property in the hands of the buyer or any transferee from such buyer 
and may, on a certificate issued by the Chief Settlement Commissioner, 
be recovered in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>263058</tid>
<number> 20A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Utilisation of compensation pool in connection with 
restoration of evacuee property in certain cases.
<section><tid>241456</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any  
evacuee or his heir is entitled to the restoration of any evacuee 
property on an application made by him in this behalf under section 16 
of the Administration of Evacuee Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of <year>1950</year>) 
 (hereinafter in this section referred to as the Evacuee Property Act), 
and the Central Government is of opinion that it is not expedient or 
practicable to restore the whole or any part of such property to the 
applicant by reason of the property or part thereof being in 
occupation of a displaced person or otherwise, then, notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Evacuee Property Act and this Act, it shall 
be lawful for the Central Government--

<subsection><tid>417508</tid>
<number>a</number>to transfer to the applicant in lieu of the evacuee 
property or any part thereof, any immovable property in 
the compensation pool or any part thereof, being in the 
opinion of the Central Government as nearly as may be 
of the same value as the evacuee property or, as the 
case may be, any part thereof, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1488112</tid>
<number>b</number>to pay to the applicant such amount in cash from the 
compensation pool in lieu of the evacuee property or 
part thereof, as the Central Government having regard 
to the value of the evacuee property or part thereof, 
may, in the circumstances deem fit.
Explanation.-- The provisions of this sub- section shall apply, 
whether or not, a certificate for the restoration of the evacuee 
property has been issued to the applicant under sub- section (1) of 
section 16 of the Evacuee Property Act, as in force immediately before 
the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>126</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 86 of <year>1956</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 22- 10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


commencement of the Administration of Evacuee Property (Amendent) Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (91 of <year>1956</year>), if the evacuee property has not in fact been 
restored to the applicant.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1023577</tid>
<number>2</number>Where in pursuance of sub- section (1) any evacuee or his heir 
has been granted any immovable property from the compensation pool or 
has been paid any amount in cash from the compensation pool or has 
been paid any amount in cash from the compensation pool, his 
application under section 16 of the Evacuee Property Act for the 
restoration of the evacuee property shall be deemed to have been 
disposed of, and his right, title and interest in such evacuee 
property shall be deemed to have been extinguished but such 
extinguishment shall not affect the power of the Central Government to 
acquire the evacuee property under section 12 of this Act.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>441697</tid>
<number> 20B</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Restrictions on restoration of certain property.
<section><tid>86605</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any person is entitled to the restoration of any property by 
virtue of an order made by the Custodian- General under section 27 of 
the Administration of Evacuee Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of <year>1950</year>), or by 
the competent officer or the appellate officer under the Evacuee 
Interest (Separation) Act, <year>1951</year> (64 of <year>1951</year>), and the Central 
Government is of opinion that it is not expedient or practicable to 
restore the whole or any part of such property to that person by 
reason of the property or part thereof being in occupation of a 
displaced person or otherwise, then, notwithstanding anything 
contained in the said Acts or this Act, it shall be lawful for the 
Central Government--

<subsection><tid>989251</tid>
<number>a</number>to transfer to that person in lieu of the property to 
be restored or any part thereof, any immovable property 
in the compensation pool or any part thereof, being in 
the opinion of the Central Government as nearly as may 
be of the same value as the property to be restored or, 
as the case may be, any part thereof, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>876057</tid>
<number>b</number>to pay to that person such amount in cash from the 
compensation pool in lieu of the property to be 
restored or part thereof, as the Central Government 
having regard to the value of the property to be 
restored or part thereof, may in the circumstances deem 
fit.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>343276</tid>
<number>2</number>Where in pursuance of sub- section (1) any person has been 
granted any immovable property from the compensation pool or has been 
paid any amount in cash from the compensation pool, his right, title 
and interest in the property to be restored shall be deemed to have 
been extinguished.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>127</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 6.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>592433</tid>
<number> 21</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Recovery of certain sums as arrears of land revenue.
<section><tid>968547</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Any sum payable to the Government or to the Custodian in respect of 
any evacuee property, under any agreement, express or implied, lease 
or other document or otherwise howsoever, for any period prior to the 
date of acquisition of such property under this Act, which has not 
been recovered under section 48 of the Administration of Evacuee 
Property Act, <year>1950</year> (31 of <year>1950</year>), and any sum payable to the Government 
in respect of any property in the compensation pool, may be recovered 
in the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>1599282</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises whether a sum is payable to the 
Government or the Custodian within the meaning of sub- section (1) in 
respect of any property referred to therein, it shall be referred to 
the Settlement Commissioner within whose jurisdiction the property is 
situated, and the Settlement Commissioner shall, after making such 
inquiry as he may deem fit and giving to the person by whom the sum is 
alleged to be payable an opportunity of being heard, decide the 
question; and the decision of the Settlement Commissioner shall, 
subject to any appeal or revision under this Act, be final, and shall 
not be called in question by any Court or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1335151</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section, a sum shall be deemed to be 
payable to the Custodian, notwithstanding that its recovery is barred 
by the Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year> (9 of <year>1908</year>), or any other law for 
the time being in force, relating to limitation of actions.]
CHAP

APPEAL, REVISION AND POWERS OF OFFICERS UNDER THE ACT

CHAPTER IV

APPEAL, REVISION AND POWERS OF OFFICERS UNDER THE ACT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1162522</tid>
<number> 22</number> Appeals to the Settlement Commissioner.
<section><tid>1800926</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2), any person aggrieved by an order of the 
Settlement Officer or a managing officer under this Act may, within 
thirty days from the date of the order, prefer an appeal to the 
Settlement Commissioner in such form and manner as may be prescribed:
Provided that the Settlement Commissioner may entertain the 
appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days, if he is 
satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from 
filing the appeal in time.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>128</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 86 of <year>1956</year>, s. 7, for the former section (w. e. f. 22-  
  10- <year>1956</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1423285</tid>
<number>2</number>No appeal shall lie from an order of the Settlement Officer 
under section 5 if the difference between the amount of public dues as 
determined by the Settlement Officer and that as admitted by the 
applicant is less than one thousand rupees or such other amount not 
exceeding one thousand rupees as may be specified by the Central 
Government in this behalf, by notification in the Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>362114</tid>
<number>3</number>The Settlement Commissioner may, after hearing the appeal, 
confirm, vary or reverse the order appealed from and pass such order 
in relation thereto as he deems fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1587011</tid>
<number> 23</number> Appeals to the Chief Settlement Commissioner.
<section><tid>1844446</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to  
the provisions of sub- section (2), any person aggrieved by an order of 
the Settlement Commissioner or the Additional Settlement Commissioner 
or an Assistant Settlement Commissioner or a managing corporation 
under this Act may, within thirty days from the date of the order, 
prefer an appeal to the Chief Settlement Commissioner in such form and 
manner as may be prescribed:
Provided that the Chief Settlement Commissioner may entertain the 
appeal after the expiry of the said period of thirty days, if he is 
satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from 
filing the appeal in time.


</section>

<section><tid>1477244</tid>
<number>2</number>No appeal shall lie from any order passed in appeal under 
section 22.

</section>

<section><tid>1585304</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chief Settlement Commissioner may, after hearing the 
appeal, confirm, vary or reverse the order appealed from and pass such 
order in relation thereto as he deems fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>686900</tid>
<number> 24</number> Power of revision of the Chief Settlement Commissioner.
<section><tid>1900972</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Chief Settlement Commissioner may at any time call for the record 
of any proceeding under this Act in which a Settlement Officer, an 
Assistant Settlement Officer an Assistant Settlement Commissioner, a 
managing officer or a managing corporation has passed an order for the 
purpose of satisfying himself as to the legality or propriety of any 
such order and may pass such order in relation thereto as he thinks 
fit.

</section>

<section><tid>565385</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power 
under sub- section (1), if the Chief Settlement Commissioner is 
satisfied that any order for payment of compensation to a displaced 
person or any lease or allotment granted to such a person has been 
obtained by him by means of fraud, false representation or concealment 
of any material fact, then notwithstanding anything contained in this 
Act,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>129</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the Chief Settlement Commissioner may pass an order directing that no 
compensation shall be paid to such a person or reducing the amount of 
compensation to be paid to him, or as the case may be, cancelling the 
lease or allotment granted to him; and if it is found that a displaced 
person has been paid compensation which is not payable to him, or 
which is in excess of the amount payable to him, such amount or 
excess, as the case may be, may, on a certificate issued by the Chief 
Settlement Commissioner, be recovered in the same manner as an arrear 
of land revenue.


</section>

<section><tid>1472339</tid>
<number>3</number>No order which prejudicially affects any person shall be 
passed under this section without giving him a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard.

</section>

<section><tid>1738513</tid>
<number>4</number>Any person aggrieved by any order made under sub- section (2), 
may, within thirty days of the date of the order, make an application 
for the revision of the order in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed to the Central Government and the Central Government may 
pass such order thereon as it thinks fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>755009</tid>
<number> 25</number> Review and amendment of orders.
<section><tid>1154645</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person aggrieved by  
an order of the Settlement Officer under section 5, from which no 
appeal is allowed under section 22, may, within thirty days from the 
date of the order, make an application in such form and manner as may 
be prescribed, to the Settlement Officer for review of his order and 
the decision of the Settlement Officer on such application shall, 
subject to the provisions of section 24 and section 33, be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1007976</tid>
<number>2</number>Clerical or arithmetical mistakes in any order passed by an 
officer or authority under this Act or errors arising therein from any 
accidental slip or omission may, at any time, be corrected by such 
officer or authority or the successor- in- office of such officer or 
authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>113372</tid>
<number> 26</number> Powers of officers appointed under this Act, etc.
<section><tid>199439</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
officer appointed under this Act shall, for the purpose of making any 
inquiry or hearing any appeal under this Act, have the same powers as 
are vested in a Civil Court under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5  
  of <year>1908</year>) when trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1292096</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person 
and examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>924345</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of any document;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>547007</tid>
<number>c</number>requisitioning any public record from any Court or 
office;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>130</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>428626</tid>
<number>d</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1452063</tid>
<number>e</number>appointing guardians or next friends of persons who are 
minors or of unsound mind;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>757711</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which may be prescribed;
and any proceeding before any such officer shall be deemed to be a 
judicial proceeding within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>) and every such officer shall be deemed 
to be a Civil Court within the meaning of sections 480 and 482 of the 
Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>314533</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every officer appointed under this Act may, for the 
purpose of making an inquiry under this Act and generally for the 
purpose of enabling him satisfactorily to discharge any of the duties 
imposed on him by or under this Act, require any person to submit to 
him such accounts, books or other documents or to furnish to him such 
information relating to any evacuee property acquired under this Act 
as he may reasonably think necessary.]

</section>

<section><tid>889195</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Settlement Commissioner or any other officer 
hearing an appeal under this Act shall, subject to the provisions of 
this Act, have such further powers as are vested in a Civil Court 
under the Code of Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), when hearing an 
appeal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1341660</tid>
<number>27</number>Finality of orders. Save as otherwise expressly provided in 
this Act, every order made by any officer or authority under this Act, 
including a managing corporation, shall be final and shall not be 
called in question in any Court by way of an appeal or revision or in 
any original suit, application or execution proceeding.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>1829330</tid>
<number>28</number>Power to transfer cases. The Central Government or the Chief 
Settlement Commissioner may, by order in writing at any time, transfer 
any case pending before an officer appointed under this Act to another 
officer and the officer to whom the case is so transferred may, 
subject to any special direction in the order of transfer, proceed 
from the stage at which it was so transferred.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>131</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 7.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>103714</tid>
<number> 29</number> Special protection from ejectment to certain classes of 
persons.
<section><tid>1649082</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any person to whom the provisions of this section  
apply, is in lawful possession of any immovable property of the class 
notified under sub- section (2), which is transferred to another person 
under the provisions of this Act, then, notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law, such person shall, without prejudice to 
any other right which he may have in the property, be deemed to be a 
tenant of the transferee on the same terms and conditions as to 
payment of rent or otherwise on which he held the property immediately 
before the transfer:
Provided that notwithstanding anything contained in any such 
terms and conditions, no such person shall be liable to be ejected 
from the property during such period not exceeding two years as may be 
prescribed in respect of that class of property, except on any of the 
following grounds, namely:--


<subsection><tid>1723792</tid>
<number>a</number>that he has neither paid nor tendered the whole amount 
of arrears of rent due after the date of the transfer 
within one month of the date on which a notice of 
demand has been served on him by the transferee in the 
manner provided in section 106 of the Transfer of 
Property Act, <year>1882</year> (4 of <year>1882</year>);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985776</tid>
<number>b</number>that he has, without obtaining the consent of the 
transferee in writing--

<subsubsection><tid>1217423</tid>
<number>i</number>sublet or otherwise parted with the 
possession of the whole or any part of the 
property, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>635843</tid>
<number>ii</number>used the property for a purpose other 
than the purpose for which he was using it 
immediately before the transfer;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1096037</tid>
<number>c</number>that he has committed any act which is destructive of, 
or permanently injurious to, the property.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1327023</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, from time to time by notification 
in the Official Gazette, specify the class of persons to whom, and the 
class of immovable property in the compensation pool, other than 
Agricultural land, in respect of which, the provisions of this section 
shall apply and in issuing any such notification the Central 
Government shall have regard to the following matters, that is to 
say,--

<subsection><tid>1011721</tid>
<number>a</number>the length of the period for which any such persons may 
have been in lawful possession of the property;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>536885</tid>
<number>b</number>the difficulty of obtaining alternative accommodation;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>132</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>180008</tid>
<number>c</number>the availability of any other suitable residential 
accommodation for the use of the transferee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1687704</tid>
<number>d</number>such other matters as may be prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1047218</tid>
<number> 30</number> 
<section><tid>612814</tid>
<number>1</number>Exemption from arrest. No person shall be liable to  
arrest or imprisonment in pursuance of any process issued for the 
recovery of any sum due under this Act which is recoverable as an 
arrear of land revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>1700575</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) if 
the Chief Settlement Commissioner is of opinion that a person is 
refusing or neglecting, or has refused or neglected, to pay any sum 
due under this Act, he may, after giving such person an opportunity of 
being heard by order in writing stating the grounds therefor, direct 
that the provisions of sub- section (1) shall not apply to him, and 
thereupon such person shall cease to be entitled to the exemption 
conferred by that sub- section.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>265010</tid>
<number> 31</number> Advisory Board.
<section><tid>629519</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall, as soon as  
may be, constitute a Board to advise the Central Government on matters 
of policy arising out of the administration of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1256924</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall consist of a Chairman and such number of 
other members not exceeding six as the Central Government may think 
fit to appoint and the members (including the Chairman) shall hold 
office for a period of two years and shall be eligible for 
reappointment:
Provided that the Chairman or any other member of the Board may 
resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Central 
Government and shall, on such resignation being accepted by that 
Government, be deemed to have vacated his office.


</section>

<section><tid>1806337</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board may, subject to the previous approval of the 
Central Government, make by- laws fixing a quorum and regulating its 
own procedure and the conduct of all business to be transacted by it.

</section>

<section><tid>720251</tid>
<number>4</number>No act done or proceeding taken by the Board shall be 
questioned on the ground merely of the existence of any vacancy in, or 
a defect in the constitution of, Board.

</section>

<section><tid>449567</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> If at any time the Central Government is of opinion that 
the continued existence of the Board is unnecessary, it may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, declare that the Board shall be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>133</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Re- numbered as sub- section (1) by Act 21 of <year>1959</year>, s. 2. 
2. Ins. by s. 2, ibid. 
3. Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 8.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

dissolved with effect from such date as may be specified in the 
notification and the Board shall be deemed to be dissolved 
accordingly.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>75652</tid>
<number>32</number>Power to give directions. The Central Government may give 
directions to any State Government as to the carrying into execution 
in the State of any of the provisions contained in this Act or of any 
rules or orders made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1493413</tid>
<number>33</number>Certain residuary powers of Central Government. The Central 
Government may at any time call for the record of any proceeding under 
this Act and may pass such order in relation thereto as in its opinion 
the circumstances of the case require and as is not inconsistent with 
any of the provisions contained in this Act or the rules made 
thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>1290488</tid>
<number> 34</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>253070</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any power 
exercisable by it under this Act shall, in such circumstances and 
under such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the direction, 
be exercisable also by such officer or authority subordinate to the 
Central Government or by the State Government or by such officer or 
authority subordinate to the State Government as may be specified in 
the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1041505</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and the rules and 
orders made thereunder, the Chief Settlement Commissioner may, by 
general or special order, delegate all or any of his powers under this 
Act to the Joint Chief Settlement Commissioner, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a Deputy Chief 
Settlement Commissioner], a Settlement Commissioner, an Additional 
Settlement Commissioner or an Assistant Settlement Commissioner, 
subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1483161</tid>
<number>3</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act and of the rules and 
orders made thereunder, a Settlement Commissioner may, by general or 
special order, delegate all or any of his powers under this Act to an 
Additional Settlement Commissioner, an Assistant Settlement 
Commissioner, a Settlement Officer or an Assistant Settlement Officer, 
subject to such conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1960694</tid>
<number> 35</number> Penalty.
<section><tid>589070</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person who furnishes in his application for  
payment of compensation any information which he knows, or has reason 
to believe, to be false or which he does not believe to be true, shall 
be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to one year, or with 
fine, or with both.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>134</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 9, for" the Deputy Chief Settlement 
Commissioner".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1300069</tid>
<number>2</number>No Court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable 
under this Act save upon complaint in writing made by an officer 
authorized by the Chief Settlement Commissioner by general or special 
order in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>879263</tid>
<number>36</number>Bar of jurisdiction. Save as otherwise expressly provided in 
this Act, no Civil Court shall have jurisdiction to entertain any suit 
or proceeding in respect of any matter which the Central Government or 
any officer or authority appointed under this Act is empowered by or 
under this Act to determine, and no injunction shall be granted by any 
Court or other authority in respect of any action taken or to be taken 
in pursuance of any power conferred by or under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1003419</tid>
<number>37</number>Officers appointed under the Act to be public servants. Every 
officer appointed under this Act and every member of a managing 
corporation shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning 
of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>566303</tid>
<number>38</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No suit or other 
legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government or any 
person appointed under this Act in respect of anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or of 
any rules or orders made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>718369</tid>
<number>39</number>Validation of certain action taken before the commencement of 
the Act. Anything done or any action taken (including any order made) 
by the Chief Settlement Commissioner, Settlement Commissioners, 
Additional Settlement Commissioners or Settlement Officers for the 
purposes of payment of compensation or rehabilitation grants or other 
grants to displaced persons shall, in so far as it is not inconsistent 
with the provisions of this Act, be deemed to have been done or taken 
in the exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if 
this Act were in force on the date on which such thing was done or 
action was taken.


</article>



<article><tid>1048004</tid>
<number> 40</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1665973</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1871935</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1406071</tid>
<number>a</number>the form and manner in which and the time within which, 
an application for payment of compensation may be made 
and the particulars which it may contain;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>135</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See Displaced Persons (Compensation and Rehabilitation) Rules, 
<year>1955</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. II, Sec. 3, p. 1317.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>424161</tid>
<number>b</number>the circumstances in which and the conditions subject 
to which evacuee property may be acquired under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1606604</tid>
<number>c</number>the scales according to which, the form and manner in 
which, and the instalments by which, compensation may 
be paid to displaced persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1236716</tid>
<number>d</number>the dues which may be deducted from the amount of 
compensation to which a displaced person is entitled;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1423023</tid>
<number>e</number>the form and manner in which Government bonds may be 
issued to displaced persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>563062</tid>
<number>f</number>the valuation of property, shares and debentures which 
may be transferred to displaced persons;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>589580</tid>
<number>g</number>the terms and conditions subject to which property may 
be transferred to a displaced person under section 10;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1731911</tid>
<number>h</number>the circumstances under which, the extent to which and 
the manner in which, rehabilitation grants and other 
grants may be paid to a displaced person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1886047</tid>
<number>hh</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manner in which any dispute as to who are the 
successors- in- interest of any deceased claimant to a 
rehabilitation grant or other grant, and as to the 
apportionment of such grant among persons entitled 
thereto, may be determined;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>644253</tid>
<number>i</number>the powers, functions and duties of managing officers 
and managing corporations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1169332</tid>
<number>j</number>the procedure for the transfer of property out of the 
compensation pool and the manner of realisation of the 
sale proceeds or the adjustment of the value of the 
property transferred against the amount of 
compensation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>145069</tid>
<number>k</number>the procedure to be followed by officers appointed 
under this Act for making enquiries under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1890244</tid>
<number>l</number>the form and manner in which appeals and applications 
for review or revision may be preferred or made under 
this Act and the procedure for hearing such appeals or 
applications for review or revision;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1830857</tid>
<number>m</number>the powers vested in a Civil Court which may be 
exercised by an officer appointed under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1676854</tid>
<number>n</number>the form and manner in which records and books of 
accounts may be maintained under this Act;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>136</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 2 of <year>1960</year>, s. 10.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1818382</tid>
<number>nn</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the fees payable in respect of appeals, revisions or 
other applications made under this Act;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>245840</tid>
<number>o</number>any other matter which is to be or may be prescribed 
under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>375254</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon 
as may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
session or in two successive sessions and it, before the expiry of the 
session in which it is so laid or the session immediately following, 
both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule, or both 
Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]


</section>

</article>



 </act>