<act><tid>1951730</tid>
<title>THE UTTAR PRADESH REORGANISATION ACT, <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 29 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 25th August, <year>2000</year>.]

An Act to provide for the reorganisation of the existing State of 
Uttar Pradesh and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

PART

PRELIMINARY

PART I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>64406</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Uttar Pradesh 
Reorganisation Act, <year>2000</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>140811</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
<section><tid>1956269</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the day which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint;

</section>

<section><tid>247338</tid>
<number>b</number>" article" means an article of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>1188732</tid>
<number>c</number>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and" parliamentary 
constituency" have the same meanings as in the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1545947</tid>
<number>d</number>" Election Commission" means the Election Commission appointed by 
the President under article 324;

</section>

<section><tid>1956560</tid>
<number>e</number>" existing State of Uttar Pradesh" means the State of Uttar Pradesh 
as existing immediately before the appointed day;

</section>

<section><tid>1715905</tid>
<number>f</number>" law" includes any enactment, ordinance, regulation, order, 
bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or other instrument having, 
immediately before the appointed day, the force of law in the whole or 
in any part of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh;

</section>

<section><tid>1125148</tid>
<number>g</number>" notified order" means an order published in the Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>224699</tid>
<number>h</number>" population ratio", in relation to the States of Uttar Pradesh and 
Uttaranchal, means the ratio of 1321: 70;

</section>

<section><tid>1166604</tid>
<number>i</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of Parliament or of 
the Legislature of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh, means a person 
who immediately before the appointed day, is a member of that House;

</section>

<section><tid>253065</tid>
<number>j</number>" successor State", in relation to the existing State of Uttar 
Pradesh, means the State of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal;

</section>

<section><tid>1879854</tid>
<number>k</number>" transferred territory" means the territory which on the appointed 
day is transferred from the existing State of Uttar Pradesh to the 
State of Uttaranchal;

</section>

<section><tid>96097</tid>
<number>l</number>" treasury" includes a sub- treasury; and

</section>

<section><tid>813812</tid>
<number>m</number>any reference to a district, tehsil or other territorial division 
of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall be construed as a 
reference to the area comprised within that territorial division on 
the appointed day.
PART

REORGANISATION OF THE STATE OF UTTAR PRADESH

PART II

REORGANISATION OF THE STATE OF UTTAR PRADESH




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1885049</tid>
<number>3</number>Formation of Uttaranchal State.- On and from the appointed day, 
there shall be formed a new State to be known as the State of 
Uttaranchal comprising the following territories of the existing State 
of Uttar Pradesh, namely:-
Pauri Garhwal, Tehri Garhwal, Uttar Kashi, Chamoli, Dehradun, 
Nainital, Almora, Pithoragarh, Udham Singh Nagar, Bageshwar, 
Champawat, Rudraprayag and Hardwar districts, and thereupon the said 
territories shall cease to form part of the existing State of Uttar 
Pradesh.



</article>



<article><tid>321928</tid>
<number>4</number>State of Uttar Pradesh and territorial divisions thereof.- On and 
from the appointed day, the State of Uttar Pradesh shall comprise the 
territories of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh other than those 
specified in section 3.


</article>



<article><tid>201679</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of the First Schedule to the Constitution.- On and from 
the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under 
the heading" I. THE STATES",-
<section><tid>1760529</tid>
<number>a</number>in the paragraph relating to the territories of the State of Uttar 
Pradesh, after the words, brackets and figures" clause (a) of 
sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Bihar and Uttar Pradesh 
 (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, <year>1968</year> (24 of <year>1968</year>)", the foll wing 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" and the territories specified in section 3 of the Uttar Pradesh 
Reorganisation Act, <year>2000</year>";


</section>

<section><tid>559287</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 26, the following entry shall be inserted, namely:-
" 27. Uttaranchal: The territories specified in section 3 of the 
Uttar Pradesh Reorganisation Act, <year>2000</year>.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1567791</tid>
<number>6</number>Saving powers of State Governments.- Nothing in the foregoing 
provisions of this Part shall be deemed to affect the power of the 
Government of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal to alter, after the 
appointed day, the name, area or boundaries of any district r other 
territorial division in the State.
PART

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

PART III

REPRESENTATION IN THE LEGISLATURES

The Council of States



</article>



<article><tid>1431180</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution.- On and from 
the appointed day, in the Fourth Schedule to the Constitution, in the 
Table,-
<section><tid>1898814</tid>
<number>a</number>entries 17 to 28 shall be renumbered as entries 18 to 29 
respectively;

</section>

<section><tid>176132</tid>
<number>b</number>in entry 16, for the figures" 34", the figures" 31" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>577654</tid>
<number>c</number>after entry 16, the following entry shall be inserted, namely:-
" 17. Uttaranchal 
................................................................................ 
... 3".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>170578</tid>
<number> 8</number> Allocation of sitting members.-
<section><tid>970049</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day,  
thirty- four sitting members of the Council of States representing the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall be deemed to have been elected 
to fill the seats allotted to the States of U tar Pradesh and 
Uttaranchal, as specified in the First Schedule to this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1535805</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of such sitting members shall remain unaltered.
The House of the People




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>164594</tid>
<number>9</number>Representation in the House of the People.- On and from the 
appointed day, there shall be allocated 80 seats to the successor 
State of Uttar Pradesh, and 5 to the successor State of Uttaranchal, 
in the House of the People, and the First Schedule to the 
Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>) shall be deemed to 
be amended accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1536102</tid>
<number>10</number>Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies.- On and 
from the appointed day, the Delimitation of Parliamentary and Assembly 
Constituencies Order, <year>1976</year>, shall stand amended as directed in the 
Second Schedule to this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1680813</tid>
<number> 11</number> Provision as to sitting members.-
<section><tid>1059637</tid>
<number>1</number>Every sitting member of the  
House of the People representing a constituency which, on the 
appointed day by virtue of the provisions of section 10, stands 
allotted, with or without alteration of boundaries, to the uccessor 
State of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal, shall be deemed to have been 
elected to the House of the People by that constituency as so 
allotted.

</section>

<section><tid>1787347</tid>
<number>2</number>The term of office of such sitting members shall remain unaltered.
The Legislative Assembly




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>520100</tid>
<number> 12</number> Provisions as to Legislative Assemblies.-
<section><tid>1488362</tid>
<number>1</number>The number of seats  
as on the appointed day in the Legislative Assemblies of the States of 
Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal shall be four hundred and three and 
seventy respectively.

</section>

<section><tid>1517851</tid>
<number>2</number>In the Second Schedule to the Representation of the People Act, 
 <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), under heading" I. States"-

<subsection><tid>1057870</tid>
<number>a</number>entries 25 and 26 shall be renumbered as entries 26 and 27 
respectively;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>518479</tid>
<number>b</number>after entry 24, the following entry shall be inserted, namely:- 
25. 
Uttaranchal

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>547621</tid>
<number>c</number>in entry 26 as so renumbered, for the figures" 425", the figures 
" 403" shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1091347</tid>
<number> 13</number> Allocation of sitting members.-
<section><tid>964409</tid>
<number>1</number>Every sitting member of the  
Legislative Assembly of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh elected to 
fill a seat in that Assembly from a constituency which on the 
appointed day by virtue of the provisions of section 1 stands 
allotted, with or without alteration of boundaries, to the State of 
Uttaranchal shall, on and from that day, cease to be a member of the 
Legislative Assembly of Uttar Pradesh and shall be deemed to have been 
elected to fill a seat in the provisio al Legislative Assembly of 
Uttaranchal from that constituency as so allotted.

</section>

<section><tid>161431</tid>
<number>2</number>All other sitting members of the Legislative Assembly of the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall continue to be members of the 
Legislative Assembly of that State and any such sitting member 
representing a constituency the extent or the name and ext nt of which 
are altered by virtue of the provisions of section 10 shall be deemed 
to have been elected to the Legislative Assembly of Uttar Pradesh by 
that constituency as so altered.

</section>

<section><tid>1282243</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time 
being in force, the Legislative Assemblies of Uttar Pradesh and 
Uttaranchal shall be deemed to be duly constituted on the appointed 
day.

</section>

<section><tid>703700</tid>
<number>4</number>The sitting member of the Legislative Assembly of the existing 
State of Uttar Pradesh nominated to that Assembly under article 333 to 
represent the Anglo- Indian community shall be deemed to have been 
nominated to represent the said community in the L gislative Assembly 
of Uttar Pradesh under that article.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1646349</tid>
<number> 14</number> Composition of provisional Legislative Assembly of 
Uttaranchal.-
<section><tid>1706517</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day and until the  
Legislative Assembly of the successor State of Uttaranchal has been 
duly constituted and summoned to meet for the first session under the 
rovisions of the Constitution, a provisional Legislative Assembly of 
the State of Uttaranchal, consisting of the twenty- two sitting members 
of the Legislative Assembly and nine members of the Legislative 
Council of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh rep esenting the 
Assembly constituencies or Council constituencies of the territories 
transferred by virtue of the provisions of section 3 shall be 
constituted.

</section>

<section><tid>736342</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisional Legislative Assembly of the State of Uttaranchal 
shall exercise all the powers and perform all the duties conferred by 
the provisions of the Constitution on the Legislative Assembly of that 
State.

</section>

<section><tid>18070</tid>
<number>3</number>The term of office of the members of the provisional Legislative 
Assembly of the State of Uttaranchal shall, unless the said 
Legislative Assembly is sooner dissolved, expire immediately before 
the first meeting of the Legislative Assembly of the Stat of 
Uttaranchal.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1052155</tid>
<number> 15</number> Duration of Legislative Assemblies.- The period of five years 
referred to in clause
<section><tid>1573398</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 172 shall, in the case of the  
Legislative Assembly of the State of Uttar Pradesh, be deemed to have 
commenced on the date on which it actually commenced in the case of 
the Legislative Assembly of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1062808</tid>
<number> 16</number> Speaker and Deputy Speaker.-
<section><tid>1801374</tid>
<number>1</number>The persons who immediately  
before the appointed day are the Speaker and Deputy Speaker of the 
Legislative Assembly of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall 
continue to be the Speaker and Deputy Speaker respectivel of that 
Assembly on and from that day.

</section>

<section><tid>1328546</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the provisional 
Legislative Assembly of the successor State of Uttaranchal shall 
choose two members of that Assembly to be respectively Speaker and 
Deputy Speaker thereof and until they are so chosen, the du ies of the 
office of Speaker shall be performed by such member of the Assembly as 
the Governor may appoint for the purpose.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>881995</tid>
<number> 17</number> Rules of procedure.- The rules of procedure and conduct of 
business of the Legislative Assembly of Uttar Pradesh as in force 
immediately before the appointed day shall, until rules are made under 
clause
<section><tid>1390569</tid>
<number>1</number>of article 208, be the rules of procedure an conduct of  
business of the Legislative Assembly of Uttaranchal, subject to such 
modifications and adaptations as may be made therein by the Speaker 
thereof.
The Legislative Council of Uttar Pradesh




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>383850</tid>
<number>18</number>Legislative Council of Uttar Pradesh.- On and from the appointed 
day, there shall be ninety- nine seats in the Legislative Council of 
Uttar Pradesh, and in the Third Schedule to the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>), for the existing ntry 8, the following 
entry shall be substituted, namely:-
" 8. Uttar Pradesh 
..................................................... 99 36 8 8 37 10".



</article>



<article><tid>615082</tid>
<number>19</number>Amendment of the Delimitation of Council Constituencies.- On and 
from the appointed day, the Delimitation of the Council Constituencies 
 (Uttar Pradesh) Order, <year>1951</year> shall stand amended as directed in the 
Third Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>932958</tid>
<number> 20</number> Provision as to certain sitting members.-
<section><tid>1087119</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
appointed day, the sitting members of the Legislative Council of the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh specified in the Fourth Schedule to 
this Act shall cease to be members of that Council a d shall be deemed 
to be the members of the provisional Legislative Assembly.

</section>

<section><tid>708075</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the appointed day, all sitting members of the 
Legislative Council of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh other than 
those referred to in sub- section (1) shall continue to be members of 
that Council.

</section>

<section><tid>49807</tid>
<number>3</number>The term of office of the members referred to in sub- section (2) 
shall remain unaltered.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>364099</tid>
<number>21</number>Deputy Chairman.- The person who immediately before the appointed 
day is the Deputy Chairman of the Legislative Council of the existing 
State of Uttar Pradesh shall continue to be the Deputy Chairman, on 
and from that day of that Council.
Delimitation of constituencies



</article>



<article><tid>825520</tid>
<number> 22</number> Delimitation of constituencies.-
<section><tid>1649420</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of giving  
effect to the provisions of section 12, the Election Commission shall 
determine in the manner hereinafter provided-

<subsection><tid>110725</tid>
<number>a</number>the number of seats to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and 
the Scheduled Tribes in the Legislative Assemblies of the States of 
Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal, respectively, having regard to the 
relevant provisions of the Constitution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>532043</tid>
<number>b</number>the assembly constituencies into which each State referred to in 
clause (a) shall be divided, the extent of each of such constituencies 
and in which of them seats shall be reserved for the Scheduled Castes 
or for the Scheduled Tribes; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>928683</tid>
<number>c</number>the adjustments in the boundaries and description of the extent of 
the parliamentary constituencies in each State referred to in clause 
 (a) that may be necessary or expedient.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1967673</tid>
<number>2</number>In determining the matters referred to in clauses (b) and (c) of 
sub- section (1), the Election Commission shall have regard to the 
following provisions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1952534</tid>
<number>a</number>all the constituencies shall be single- member constituencies;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1864653</tid>
<number>b</number>all constituencies shall, as far as practicable, be geographically 
compact areas, and in delimiting them, regard shall be had to physical 
features, existing boundaries of administrative units, facilities of 
communication and conveniences to the publi; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>200534</tid>
<number>c</number>constituencies in which seats are reserved for the Scheduled 
Castes and the Scheduled Tribes shall, as far as practicable, be 
located in areas where the proportion of their population to the total 
population is the largest.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1584970</tid>
<number>3</number>The Election Commission shall, for the purpose of assisting it in 
the performance of its functions under sub- section (1), associate with 
itself as associate members, five persons as the Central Government 
may by order specify, being persons who are t e members of the 
Legislative Assembly of the State or of the House of the People 
representing the State: Provided that none of the associate members 
shall have a right to vote or to sign any decision of the Election 
Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>1686733</tid>
<number>4</number>If, owing to death or resignation, the office of an associate 
member falls vacant, it shall be filled as far as practicable, in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>755667</tid>
<number>5</number>The Election Commission shall-

<subsection><tid>1735974</tid>
<number>a</number>publish its proposals for the delimitation of constituencies 
together with the dissenting proposals, if any, of any associate 
member who desires publication thereof in the Official Gazette and in 
such other manner as the Commission may consider fit, ogether with a 
notice inviting objections and suggestions in relation to the 
proposals and specifying a date on or after which the proposals will 
be further considered by it;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>894507</tid>
<number>b</number>consider all objections and suggestions which may have been 
received by it before the date so specified; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>682809</tid>
<number>c</number>after considering all objections and suggestions which may have 
been received by it before the date so specified, determine by one or 
more orders the delimitation of constituencies and cause such order or 
orders to be published in the Official Gazett; and upon such 
publication, the order or orders shall have the full force of law and 
shall not be called in question in any court.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1458757</tid>
<number>6</number>As soon as may be after such publication, every such order 
relating to assembly constituencies shall be laid before the 
Legislative Assembly of the concerned State.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1077684</tid>
<number> 23</number> Power of Election Commission to maintain Delimitation Orders 
up- to- date.-
<section><tid>1028414</tid>
<number>1</number>The Election Commission may, from time to time, by  
notification in the Official Gazette,-

<subsection><tid>97258</tid>
<number>a</number>correct any printing mistakes in any order made under section 22 
or any error arising therein from inadvertent slip or omission; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>16956</tid>
<number>b</number>where the boundaries or name of any territorial division mentioned 
in any such order or orders is or are altered, make such amendments as 
appear to it to be necessary or expedient for bringing such order 
up- to- date.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1792664</tid>
<number>2</number>Every notification under this section relating to an assembly 
constituency shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is issued, 
before the concerned Legislative Assembly.
Scheduled Castes and Scheduled Tribes




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>786657</tid>
<number>24</number>Amendment of the Scheduled Castes Order.- On and from the 
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Castes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Fifth Schedule to this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1578460</tid>
<number>25</number>Amendment to the Scheduled Tribes Order.- On and from the 
appointed day, the Constitution (Scheduled Tribes) Order, <year>1950</year>, shall 
stand amended as directed in the Sixth Schedule to this Act.
PART

HIGH COURT

PART IV

HIGH COURT



</article>



<article><tid>1429230</tid>
<number> 26</number> High Court of Uttaranchal.-
<section><tid>228211</tid>
<number>1</number>As from the appointed day, there  
shall be a separate High Court for the State of Uttaranchal 
 (hereinafter referred to as" the High Court of Uttaranchal") and the 
High Court of Judicature at Allahabad shall become the H gh Court for 
the State of Uttar Pradesh (hereinafter referred to as the High Court  
  at Allahabad).

</section>

<section><tid>726330</tid>
<number>2</number>The principal seat of the High Court of Uttaranchal shall be at 
such place as the President may, by notified order, appoint.

</section>

<section><tid>1694828</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), the Judges 
and division courts of the High Court of Uttaranchal may sit at such 
other place or places in the State of Uttaranchal other than its 
principal seat as the Chief Justice may, with the pproval of the 
Governor of Uttaranchal, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1106939</tid>
<number> 27</number> Judges of Uttaranchal High Court.-
<section><tid>1250979</tid>
<number>1</number>Such of the Judges of the  
High Court at Allahabad holding office immediately before the 
appointed day as may be determined by the President shall on that day 
cease to be Judges of the High Court at Allahabad and ecome, Judges of 
the High Court of Uttaranchal.

</section>

<section><tid>1165185</tid>
<number>2</number>The persons who by virtue of sub- section (1) become Judges of the 
High Court of Uttaranchal shall, except in the case where any such 
person is appointed to be the Chief Justice of that High Court, rank 
in that Court according to the priority of their respective 
appointments as Judges of the High Court at Allahabad.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1364370</tid>
<number>28</number>Jurisdiction of Uttaranchal High Court.- The High Court of 
Uttaranchal shall have, in respect of any part of the territories 
included in the State of Uttaranchal, all such jurisdiction, powers 
and authority as, under the law in force immediately befor the 
appointed day, are exercisable in respect of that part of the said 
territories by the High Court at Allahabad.


</article>



<article><tid>289727</tid>
<number> 29</number> Special provision relating to Bar Council and advocates.-
<section><tid>1035241</tid>
<number>1</number>On  
and from the appointed day, in the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25 of <year>1961</year>), 
in section 3, in sub- section (1), in clause (a), for the words" and 
Uttar Pradesh", the words" Uttar Pradesh and Utt ranchal" shall be 
substituted.

</section>

<section><tid>1248651</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person who immediately before the appointed day is an advocate 
on the roll of the Bar Council of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh 
may give his option in writing, within one year from the appointed day 
to the Bar Council of such existing State, to transfer his name on the 
roll of the Bar Council of Uttaranchal and notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25 of <year>1961</year>) and the rules made 
thereunder, on such option so given his name shall be deemed to have 
been transferred on he roll of the Bar Council of Uttaranchal with 
effect from the date of the option so given for the purposes of the 
said Act and the rules made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>65519</tid>
<number>3</number>The persons other than the advocates who are entitled immediately 
before the appointed day, to practise in the High Court at Allahabad 
or any subordinate court thereof shall, on and after the appointed 
day, be recognised as such persons entitled also to practise in the 
High Court of Uttaranchal or any subordinate court thereof, as the 
case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1216639</tid>
<number>4</number>The right of audience in the High Court of Uttaranchal shall be 
regulated in accordance with the like principles as immediately before 
the appointed day are in force with respect to the right of audience 
in the High Court at Allahabad.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>534501</tid>
<number>30</number>Practice and procedure in Uttaranchal High Court.- Subject to the 
provisions of this Part, the law in force immediately before the 
appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the High Court 
at Allahabad shall, with the necessary modificati ns, apply in 
relation to the High Court of Uttaranchal, and accordingly, the High 
Court of Uttaranchal shall have all such powers to make rules and 
orders with respect to practice and procedure as are immediately 
before the appointed day exercisable by t e High Court at Allahabad:
Provided that any rules or orders which are in force immediately 
before the appointed day with respect to practice and procedure in the 
High Court at Allahabad shall, until varied or revoked by rules or 
orders made by the High Court of Uttaranchal, apply with the necessary 
modifications in relation to practice and procedure in the High Court 
of Uttaranchal as if made by that Court.



</article>



<article><tid>1555241</tid>
<number>31</number>Custody of seal of Uttaranchal High Court.- The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day with respect to the custody of 
the seal of the High Court at Allahabad shall, with the necessary 
modifications, apply with respect to the custody of the eal of the 
High Court of Uttaranchal.


</article>



<article><tid>1555645</tid>
<number>32</number>Form of writs and other processes.- The law in force immediately 
before the appointed day with respect to the form of writs and other 
processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court at Allahabad 
shall, with the necessary modifications, apply with espect to the form 
of writs and other processes used, issued or awarded by the High Court 
of Uttaranchal.


</article>



<article><tid>747727</tid>
<number>33</number>Powers of Judges.- The law in force immediately before the 
appointed day relating to the powers of the Chief Justice, single 
Judges and division courts of the High Court at Allahabad and with 
respect to all matters ancillary to the exercise of those p wers 
shall, with the necessary modifications, apply in relation to the High 
Court of Uttaranchal.


</article>



<article><tid>1575660</tid>
<number>34</number>Procedure as to appeals to Supreme Court.- The law in force 
immediately before the appointed day relating to appeals to the 
Supreme Court from the High Court at Allahabad and the Judges and 
division courts thereof shall, with the necessary modificatio s, apply 
in relation to the High Court of Uttaranchal.


</article>



<article><tid>637601</tid>
<number> 35</number> Transfer of proceedings from Allahabad High Court to Uttaranchal 
High Court.-
<section><tid>1089957</tid>
<number>1</number>Except as hereinafter provided, the High Court at  
Allahabad shall, as from the appointed day, have no jurisdiction in 
respect of the transferred territory.

</section>

<section><tid>701727</tid>
<number>2</number>Such proceedings pending in the High Court at Allahabad 
immediately before the appointed day as are certified, whether before 
or after that day, by the Chief Justice of that High Court, having 
regard to the place of accrual of the cause of action and other 
circumstances, to be proceedings which ought to be heard and decided 
by the High Court of Uttaranchal shall, as soon as may be after such 
certification, be transferred to the High Court of Uttaranchal.

</section>

<section><tid>183343</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and (2) of 
this section or in section 28, but save as hereinafter provided, the 
High Court at Allahabad shall have, and the High Court of Uttaranchal 
shall not have, jurisdiction to entertain, he r or dispose of appeals, 
applications for leave to the Supreme Court, applications for review 
and other proceedings where any such proceedings seek any relief in 
respect of any order passed by the High Court at Allahabad before the 
appointed day:
Provided that if after any such proceedings have been entertained by 
the High Court at Allahabad, it appears to the Chief Justice of that 
High Court that they ought to be transferred to the High Court of 
Uttaranchal, he shall order that they shall be so ransferred, and such 
proceedings shall thereupon be transferred accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>827367</tid>
<number>4</number>Any order made by the High Court at Allahabad-

<subsection><tid>840692</tid>
<number>a</number>before the appointed day, in any proceedings transferred to the 
High Court of Uttaranchal by virtue of sub- section (2), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1977561</tid>
<number>b</number>in any proceedings with respect to which the High Court at 
Allahabad retains jurisdiction by virtue of sub- section (3), shall for 
all purposes have effect, not only as an order of the High Court at 
Allahabad, but also as an order made by the High Court of Uttaranchal.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1764383</tid>
<number>36</number>Right to appear or to act in proceedings transferred to 
Uttaranchal High Court.- Any person who, immediately before the 
appointed day, is an advocate entitled to practise or any other 
persons entitled to practise in the High Court at Allahabad and was 
authorised to appear in any proceedings transferred from that High 
Court to the High Court of Uttaranchal under section 35, shall have 
the right to appear in the High Court of Uttaranchal in relation to 
those proceedings.


</article>



<article><tid>436005</tid>
<number> 37</number> Interpretation.- For the purposes of section 35-
<section><tid>716643</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in a court until that 
court has disposed of all issues between the parties, including any 
issues with respect to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings 
and shall include appeals, applications for leave o appeal to the 
Supreme Court, applications for review, petitions for revision and 
petitions for writs; and

</section>

<section><tid>1561197</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as including 
references to a Judge or division court thereof, and references to an 
order made by a court or a Judge shall be construed as including 
references to a sentence, judgment or decree passed or m de by that 
court or Judge.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>292371</tid>
<number>38</number>Savings.- Nothing in this Part shall affect the application to the 
High Court of Uttaranchal of any provisions of the Constitution, and 
this Part shall have effect subject to any provision that may be made 
on or after the appointed day with respect t that High Court by any 
Legislature or other authority having power to make such provision.
PART

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES

PART V

AUTHORISATION OF EXPENDITURE AND DISTRIBUTION OF REVENUES



</article>



<article><tid>1749755</tid>
<number>39</number>Authorisation of expenditure of Uttaranchal State.- The Governor 
of Uttar Pradesh may, at any time before the appointed day, authorise 
such expenditure from the Consolidated Fund of the State of 
Uttaranchal as he deems necessary for any period not mor than six 
months beginning with the appointed day pending the sanction of such 
expenditure by the Legislative Assembly of the State of Uttaranchal: 
Provided that the Governor of Uttaranchal may, after the appointed 
day, authorise such further expenditure as he deems necessary from the 
Consolidated Fund of the State of Uttaranchal for any period not 
extending beyond the said period of six months.


</article>



<article><tid>256607</tid>
<number> 40</number> Reports relating to accounts of Uttar Pradesh State.-
<section><tid>870526</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
reports of the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India referred to in 
clause (2) of article 151 relating to the accounts of the existing 
State of Uttar Pradesh in respect of any period pr or to the appointed 
day shall be submitted to the Governor of each of the successor States 
of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal who shall cause them to be laid 
before the Legislature of that State.

</section>

<section><tid>983463</tid>
<number>2</number>The President may by order-

<subsection><tid>1381810</tid>
<number>a</number>declare any expenditure incurred out of the Consolidated Fund of 
Uttar Pradesh on any service in respect of any period prior to the 
appointed day during the financial year or in respect of any earlier 
financial year in excess of the amount granted fo that service and for 
that year as disclosed in the reports referred to in sub- section (1) 
to have been duly authorised; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>447231</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for any action to be taken on any matter arising out of 
the said reports.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>990770</tid>
<number>41</number>Distribution of revenue.- The President shall, by order, determine 
the share of the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal in its total 
amount payable to the existing State of Uttar Pradesh on the 
recommendation of the Finance Commission constituted nder article 280 
in such manner as he thinks fit.
PART

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES

PART VI

APPORTIONMENT OF ASSETS AND LIABILITIES



</article>



<article><tid>1146138</tid>
<number> 42</number> Application of Part.-
<section><tid>1500650</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of this Part shall apply  
in relation to the apportionment of the assets and liabilities of the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh immediately before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>480700</tid>
<number>2</number>The successor States shall be entitled to receive benefits arising 
out of the decisions taken by the predecessor State and the successor 
States shall be liable to bear the financial liabilities arising out 
of the decisions taken by the existing State of Uttar Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>1752790</tid>
<number>3</number>The apportionment of assets and liabilities would be subject to 
such financial adjustment as may be necessary to secure just, 
reasonable and equitable apportionment of the assets and liabilities 
amongst the successor States.

</section>

<section><tid>1557823</tid>
<number>4</number>Any dispute regarding the amount of financial assets and 
liabilities shall be settled through mutual agreement, failing which 
by order by the Central Government on the advice of the Comptroller 
and Auditor- General of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1696349</tid>
<number> 43</number> Land and goods.-
<section><tid>1237835</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Part,  
all land and all stores, articles and other goods belonging to the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall,-

<subsection><tid>1147556</tid>
<number>a</number>if within the transferred territory, pass to the State of 
Uttaranchal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>305560</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, remain the property of the State of Uttar 
Pradesh:
Provided that where the Central Government is of opinion that any 
goods or class of goods should be distributed among the States of 
Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal, otherwise than according to the 
situation of the goods, the Central Government may issue su h 
directions as it thinks fit for a just and equitable distribution of 
the goods and the goods shall pass to the successor States 
accordingly:

Provided further that in case of any dispute relating to the 
distribution of any goods or class of goods under this sub- section, 
the Central Government shall endeavour to settle such dispute through 
mutual agreement arrived at between the Governments of he successor 
States for that purpose, failing which the Central Government may, on 
request by any of the Governments of the successor States, after 
consulting both the Governments of the successor States, issue such 
direction as it may deem fit for the d stribution of such goods or 
class of goods, as the case may be, under this sub- section.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1880402</tid>
<number>2</number>Stores held for specific purposes, such as use or utilisation in 
particular institutions, workshops or undertakings or on particular 
works under construction, shall pass to the successor States in whose 
territories such institutions, workshops, under akings or works are 
located.

</section>

<section><tid>1313953</tid>
<number>3</number>Stores relating to the Secretariat and offices of Heads of 
Departments having jurisdiction over the whole of the existing State 
of Uttar Pradesh shall be divided between the successor States in 
accordance with such directions as the Central Governmen may, after 
consultation with the Government of each successor States, think fit 
to issue for a just and equitable distribution of such stores.

</section>

<section><tid>1112823</tid>
<number>4</number>Any other unissued stores of any class in the existing State of 
Uttar Pradesh shall be divided between the successor States in 
proportion to the total stores of that class purchased in the period 
of three years prior to the appointed day, for the ter itories of the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh included respectively in each of the 
successor States:
Provided that where such proportion cannot be ascertained in respect 
of any class of stores or where the value of any class of such stores 
does not exceed rupees ten thousand, that class of stores shall be 
divided between the successor States according t the population ratio.


</section>

<section><tid>1502818</tid>
<number>5</number>In this section, the expression" land'' includes immovable 
property of every kind and any rights in or over such property, and 
the expression" goods'' does not include coins, bank notes and 
currency notes.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1136200</tid>
<number>44</number>Treasury and bank balances.- The total of the cash balances in all 
treasuries of the State of Uttar Pradesh and the credit balances of 
the State with the Reserve Bank of India, the State Bank of India or 
any other bank immediately before the appointed day shall be divided 
between the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal according to the 
population ratio:
Provided that for the purposes of such division, there shall be no 
transfer of cash balances from any treasury to any other treasury and 
the apportionment shall be effected by adjusting the credit balances 
of the two States in the books of the Reserve Ba k of India on the 
appointed day:

Provided further that if the State of Uttaranchal has no account on 
the appointed day with the Reserve Bank of India, the adjustment shall 
be made in such manner as the Central Government may, by order, 
direct.



</article>



<article><tid>436794</tid>
<number>45</number>Arrears of taxes.- The right to recover arrears of the tax or duty 
on property, including arrears of land revenue, shall belong to the 
successor State in which the property is situated, and the right to 
recover arrears of any other tax or duty shall b long to the successor 
State in whose territories the place of assessment of that tax or duty 
is included on the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>680553</tid>
<number> 46</number> Right to recover loans and advances.-
<section><tid>154445</tid>
<number>1</number>The right of the  
existing State of Uttar Pradesh to recover any loans or advances made 
before the appointed day to any local body, society, agriculturist or 
other person in an area within that State shall belo g to the 
successor State in which that area is included on that day.

</section>

<section><tid>181943</tid>
<number>2</number>The right of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh to recover any 
loans or advances made before the appointed day to any person or 
institution outside that State shall belong to the State of Uttar 
Pradesh:
Provided that any sum recovered in respect of any such loan or advance 
shall be divided between the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal 
according to the population ratio.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>968223</tid>
<number> 47</number> Investments and credits in certain funds.-
<section><tid>916934</tid>
<number>1</number>The securities held  
in respect of the investments made from Cash Balances Investment 
Account or from any Fund in the Public Account of the existing State 
of Uttar Pradesh as specified in the Seventh Sched le shall be 
apportioned in the ratio of population of the successor States:
Provided that the securities held in investments made from the 
Calamity Relief Fund of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall be 
divided in the ratio of the area of the territories occupied by the 
successor States:

Provided further that the balance in the Reserve Funds in the Public 
Account of Uttar Pradesh created wholly out of appropriations from the 
Consolidated Fund of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh, to the 
extent the balances have not been invested outsid Government account, 
shall not be carried forward to similar Reserve Funds in the Public 
Account of the successor States.


</section>

<section><tid>401360</tid>
<number>2</number>The investments of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh immediately 
before the appointed day in any special fund, the objects of which are 
confined to a local area, shall belong to the State in which that area 
is included on the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>1666017</tid>
<number>3</number>The investments of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh immediately 
before the appointed day in any private, commercial or industrial 
undertaking, in so far as such investments have not been made or are 
deemed not to have been made from the Cash Balan es Investment 
Account, shall pass to the State in which the principal seat of 
business of the undertaking is located.

</section>

<section><tid>582047</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any body corporate constituted under a Central Act, State 
Act or Provincial Act for the existing State of Uttar Pradesh or any 
part thereof has, by virtue of the provisions of Part II, become an 
inter- State body corporate, the investments in, o loans or advances 
to, any such body corporate by the existing State of Uttar Pradesh 
made before the appointed day shall, save as otherwise expressly 
provided by or under this Act, be divided between the States of Uttar 
Pradesh and Uttaranchal in the sa e proportion in which the assets of 
the body corporate are divided under the provisions of this Part.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>269379</tid>
<number> 48</number> Assets and liabilities of State undertakings.-
<section><tid>185443</tid>
<number>1</number>The assets and  
liabilities relating to any commercial or industrial undertaking of 
the State of Uttar Pradesh shall pass to the State in which the 
undertaking is located.

</section>

<section><tid>839906</tid>
<number>2</number>Where a depreciation reserve fund is maintained by the State of 
Uttar Pradesh for any such commercial or industrial undertaking, the 
securities held in respect of investments made from that fund shall 
pass to the State in which the undertaking is loc ted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1428530</tid>
<number> 49</number> Public Debt.-
<section><tid>346757</tid>
<number>1</number>All liabilities on account of Public Debt and  
Public Account of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh outstanding 
immediately before the appointed day shall be apportioned in the ratio 
of population of the successor States unless a dif erent mode of 
apportionment is provided under the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>34818</tid>
<number>2</number>The individual items of liabilities to be allocated to the 
successor States and the amount of contribution required to be made by 
one successor State to another shall be such as may be ordered by the 
Central Government in consultation with the Compt oller and 
Auditor- General of India:
Provided that till such orders are issued, the liabilities on account 
of Public Debt and Public Account of the existing State of Uttar 
Pradesh shall continue to be the liabilities of the successor State of 
Uttar Pradesh.


</section>

<section><tid>999130</tid>
<number>3</number>The liability on account of loan raised from any source and 
re- lent by the existing State of Uttar Pradesh to such entities as may 
be specified by the Central Government and whose area of operation is 
confined to either of the successor States shall devolve on the 
respective States as specified in sub- section (4).

</section>

<section><tid>1080160</tid>
<number>4</number>The public debt of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh 
attributable to loan taken from any source for the express purpose of 
re- lending the same to a specific institution and outstanding 
immediately before the appointed day shall,-

<subsection><tid>1299038</tid>
<number>a</number>if re- lent to any local body, body corporate or other institution 
in any local area, be the debt of the State in which the local area is 
included on the appointed day; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1341799</tid>
<number>b</number>if re- lent to the Uttar Pradesh Power Corporation Limited, the 
Uttar Pradesh Jal Vidyut Nigam Limited, the Uttar Pradesh Rajya Vidyut 
Utpadan Nigam Limited, the Uttar Pradesh State Road Transport 
Corporation, or the Uttar Pradesh Housing Board or a y other 
institution which becomes an inter- State institution on the appointed 
day, be divided between the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal in 
the same proportion in which the assets of such body corporate or 
institution are divided under the provi ions of Part VII.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1362247</tid>
<number>5</number>Where a sinking fund or a depreciation fund is maintained by the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh for repayment of any loan raised by 
it, the securities held in respect of investments made from that fund 
shall be divided between the successor States f Uttar Pradesh and 
Uttaranchal in the same proportion in which the total public debt is 
divided between the two States under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>11684</tid>
<number>6</number>In this section, the expression" Government security" means a 
security created and issued by a State Government for the purpose of 
raising a public loan and having any of the forms specified in, or 
prescribed under, clause (2) of section 2 of the Pu lic Debt Act, <year>1944</year> 
 (18 of <year>1944</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>140948</tid>
<number>50</number>Floating Debt.- The liability of the State of Uttar Pradesh in 
respect of any floating loan to provide short- term finance to any 
commercial undertaking shall be the liability of the State in whose 
territories the undertaking is located.


</article>



<article><tid>1011600</tid>
<number>51</number>Refund of taxes collected in excess.- The liability of the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh to refund any tax or duty on property, 
including land revenue, collected in excess shall be the liability of 
the successor State in whose territories the prope ty is situated, and 
the liability of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh to refund any 
other tax or duty collected in excess shall be the liability of the 
successor State in whose territories the place of assessment of that 
tax or duty is included.


</article>



<article><tid>1706563</tid>
<number> 52</number> Deposits, etc.-
<section><tid>1808517</tid>
<number>1</number>The liability of the existing State of Uttar  
Pradesh in respect of any civil deposit or local fund deposit shall, 
as from the appointed day, be the liability of the State in whose area 
the deposit has been made.

</section>

<section><tid>190100</tid>
<number>2</number>The liability of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh in respect of 
any charitable or other endowment shall, as from the appointed day, be 
the liability of the State in whose area the institution entitled to 
the benefit of the endowment is located or of the State to which the 
objects of the endowment, under the terms thereof, are confined.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1966326</tid>
<number>53</number>Provident Fund.- The liability of the existing State of Uttar 
Pradesh in respect of the provident fund account of a Government 
servant in service on the appointed day shall, as from that day, be 
the liability of the State to which that Government ser ant is 
permanently allotted.


</article>



<article><tid>708380</tid>
<number>54</number>Pensions.- The liability of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh in 
respect of pensions shall pass to, or be apportioned between, the 
successor States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal in accordance with 
the provisions contained in the Eighth Schedule o this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1454039</tid>
<number> 55</number> Contracts.-
<section><tid>1346460</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, before the appointed day, the existing  
State of Uttar Pradesh has made any contract in the exercise of its 
executive power for any purposes of the State, that contract shall be 
deemed to have been made in the exercise of the ex cutive power-

<subsection><tid>1267473</tid>
<number>a</number>if the purposes of the contract are, on and from the appointed 
day, exclusive purposes of either of the successor States of Uttar 
Pradesh and Uttaranchal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1803763</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, of the State of Uttar Pradesh, and all rights 
and liabilities which have accrued, or may accrue under any such 
contract shall, to the extent to which they would have been rights or 
liabilities of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh, be rights or 
liabilities of the State of Uttaranchal or the State of Uttar Pradesh, 
as the case may be:
Provided that in any such case as is referred to in clause (b), the 
initial allocation of rights and liabilities made by this sub- section 
shall be subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed upon 
between the successor States of Uttar Pradesh a d Uttaranchal or in 
default of such agreement, as the Central Government may, by order, 
direct.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>955002</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of this section, there shall be deemed to be 
included in the liabilities which have accrued or may accrue under any 
contract-

<subsection><tid>447489</tid>
<number>a</number>any liability to satisfy an order or award made by any court or 
other tribunal in proceedings relating to the contract; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1545168</tid>
<number>b</number>any liability in respect of expenses incurred in or in connection 
with any such proceedings.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>523928</tid>
<number>3</number>This section shall have effect subject to the other provisions of 
this Part relating to the apportionment of liabilities in respect of 
loans, guarantees and other financial obligation; and bank balances 
and securities shall, notwithstanding that the partake of the nature 
of contractual rights, be dealt with under those provisions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>362974</tid>
<number> 56</number> Liability in respect of actionable wrong.- Where, immediately 
before the appointed day, the existing State of Uttar Pradesh is 
subject to any liability in respect of any actionable wrong other than 
breach of contract, that liability shall,-
<section><tid>470613</tid>
<number>a</number>if the cause of action arose wholly within the territories which, 
as from that day, are the territories of either of the successor 
States of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal, be a liability of that 
successor State; and

</section>

<section><tid>818080</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, be initially a liability of the State of Uttar 
Pradesh, but subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed 
upon between the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal or, in 
default of such agreement, as the Central Government ay, by order, 
direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>862425</tid>
<number> 57</number> Liability as guarantor.- Where, immediately before the appointed 
day, the existing State of Uttar Pradesh is liable as guarantor in 
respect of any liability of a registered co- operative society or other 
person, that liability of the existing State of ttar Pradesh shall,-
<section><tid>212093</tid>
<number>a</number>if the area of operations of such society or persons is limited to 
the territories which, as from that day, are the territories of either 
of the States of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal, be a liability of that 
successor State; and

</section>

<section><tid>157173</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, be initially a liability of the State of Uttar 
Pradesh, subject to such financial adjustment as may be agreed upon 
between the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal or, in default of 
such agreements, as the Central Government may by order, direct.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1994770</tid>
<number>58</number>Items in suspense.- If any item in suspense is ultimately found to 
affect an asset or liability of the nature referred to in any of the 
foregoing provisions of this Part, it shall be dealt with in 
accordance with that provision.


</article>



<article><tid>395815</tid>
<number>59</number>Residuary provision.- The benefit or burden of any asset or 
liability of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh not dealt with in the 
foregoing provisions of this Part shall pass to the State of Uttar 
Pradesh in the first instance, subject to such financ al adjustment as 
may be agreed upon between the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal 
or, in default of such agreement, as the Central Government may, by 
order, direct.


</article>



<article><tid>373894</tid>
<number>60</number>Apportionment of assets or liabilities by agreement.- Where the 
successor States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal agree that the 
benefit or burden of any particular asset or liability should be 
apportioned between them in a manner other than that prov ded for in 
the foregoing provisions of this Part, notwithstanding anything 
contained therein, the benefit or burden of that asset or liability 
shall be apportioned in the manner agreed upon.


</article>



<article><tid>1802661</tid>
<number>61</number>Power of Central Government to order allocation or adjustment in 
certain cases.- Where, by virtue of any of the provisions of this Part, 
any of the successor States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal becomes 
entitled to any property or obtains any bene its or becomes subject to 
any liability, and the Central Government is of opinion, on a 
reference made within a period of three years from the appointed day 
by either of the States, that it is just and equitable that property 
or those benefits should be ransferred to, or shared with, the other 
successor State, or that a contribution towards that liability should 
be made by the other successor State, the said property or benefits 
shall be allocated in such manner between the two States, or the other 
Stat shall make to the State subject to the liability such 
contribution in respect thereof, as the Central Government may, after 
consultation with the two State Governments, by order, determine.


</article>



<article><tid>80931</tid>
<number>62</number>Certain expenditure to be charged on Consolidated Fund.- All sums 
payable either by the State of Uttar Pradesh or by the State of 
Uttaranchal to the other States or by the Central Government to either 
of those States, by virtue of the provisions of th s Act, shall be 
charged on the Consolidated Fund of the State by which such sums are 
payable or, as the case may be, the Consolidated Fund of India.
PART

PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS

PART VII

PROVISIONS AS TO CERTAIN CORPORATIONS



</article>



<article><tid>1630304</tid>
<number> 63</number> Provisions for Power Corporation Limited, etc.-
<section><tid>625159</tid>
<number>1</number>The following  
bodies Corporate constituted for the existing State of Uttar Pradesh, 
namely:-

<subsection><tid>98312</tid>
<number>a</number>the Uttar Pradesh Power Corporation Limited, the Uttar Pradesh Jal 
Vidyut Nigam Limited and the Uttar Pradesh Rajya Vidyut Utpadan Nigam 
Limited;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1909283</tid>
<number>b</number>the Uttar Pradesh Electricity Regulatory Commission; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>633974</tid>
<number>c</number>the State Warehousing Corporation established under the 
Warehousing Corporations Act, <year>1962</year> (58 of <year>1962</year>), shall, on and from 
the appointed day, continue to function in those areas in respect of 
which they were functioning immediately before that day, subject to 
the provisions of this section and to such directions as may, from 
time to time, be issued by the entral Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1931723</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- section 
 (1) in respect of the Power Corporation, Commission or Warehousing 
Corporation shall include a direction that the Act under which the 
Power Corporation, Commission or Warehousing Corpo ation was 
constituted shall, in its application to that Power Corporation, 
Commission or Warehousing Corporation, have effect subject to such 
exceptions and modifications as the Central Government thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1519618</tid>
<number>3</number>The Power Corporation, Commission or Warehousing Corporation 
referred to in sub- section (1) shall cease to function as from, and 
shall be deemed to be dissolved on such date as the Central Government 
may, by order, appoint; and upon such dissolution, its assets, rights 
and liabilities shall be apportioned between the successor States of 
Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal in such manner as may be agreed upon 
between them within one year of the dissolution of the Power 
Corporation, Commission or Warehousing Corporation, as the case may 
be, or if no agreement is reached, in such manner as the Central 
Government may, by order, determine:
Provided that any liabilities of any of the said Power Corporations 
referred to in clause (a) of sub- section (1) relating to the unpaid 
dues of the coal supplied to the Power Corporation by any public 
sector coal company shall be provisionally apportione between the 
corresponding Power Corporations constituted respectively in the 
successor States of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh or after the 
date appointed for the dissolution of the Power Corporation under this 
sub- section in such manner as may b agreed upon between the 
Governments of the successor States within one month of such 
dissolution or if no agreement is reached, in such manner as the 
Central Government may by order determine subject to reconciliation 
and finalisation of the liabilities which shall be completed within 
three months from the date of such dissolution by the mutual agreement 
between the successor States or failing such agreement by the 
direction of the Central Government:

Provided further that an interest at the rate of two per cent. higher 
than the cash credit interest shall be paid on outstanding unpaid dues 
of the coal supplied to the Electricity Corporation by the public 
sector coal company till the liquidation of suc dues by the concerned 
State Power Corporation constituted in the successor States on or 
after the date appointed for the dissolution of the Power Corporation 
under this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>711915</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of the State of Uttar Pradesh 
or, as the case may be, the Government of the State of Uttaranchal 
Power Corporation, an Electricity Regulatory Commission or a State 
Warehousing Corporation for the State under the provisions of this Act 
relating to such Power Corporation, Commission or Warehousing 
Corporation; and if such a Power Corp from constituting, at any time 
on or after the appoin ed day, a State ration, Commission or 
Warehousing Corporation is so constituted in either of the States 
before the dissolution of the Power Corporation, Commission or 
Warehousing Corporation referred to in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1610404</tid>
<number>a</number>provision may be made by order of the Central Government enabling 
the new Power Corporation, new Commission or the new Warehousing 
Corporation to take over from the existing Power Corporation, 
Commission or Warehousing Corporation all or any of its u dertakings, 
assets, rights and liabilities in that State, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1376694</tid>
<number>b</number>upon the dissolution of the existing Power Corporation, Commission 
or Warehousing Corporation,-

<subsubsection><tid>356634</tid>
<number>i</number>any assets, rights and liabilities which would otherwise have 
passed to that State by or under the provisions of sub- section (3) 
shall pass to the new Board, new Commission or the new Warehousing 
Corporation instead of to that State;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1498675</tid>
<number>ii</number>any employee who would otherwise have been transferred to or 
re- employed by that State under sub- section (3), read with clause (i) 
of sub- section (5), shall be transferred to or re- employed by the new 
Power Corporation, new Commission or the new War housing Corporation 
instead of to or by that State.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>981185</tid>
<number>5</number>An agreement entered into between the successor States under 
sub- section (3) and an order made by the Central Government under that 
sub- section or under clause (a) of sub- section (4) may provide for the 
transfer or re- employment of any employee of th Power Corporation, 
Commission or Warehousing Corporation referred to in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>954665</tid>
<number>i</number>to or by the successor States, in the case of an agreement under 
sub- section (2) or an order made under that sub- section;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>486393</tid>
<number>ii</number>to or by the new Power Corporation, new Commission or the new 
Warehousing Corporation constituted under sub- section (4), in the case 
of an order made under clause (a) of that sub- section, and, subject to 
the provisions of section 68, also for the terms and conditions of 
service applicable to such employees after such transfer or 
re- employment.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1139115</tid>
<number>64</number>Continuance of arrangements in regard to generation and supply of 
electric power and supply of water.- If it appears to the Central 
Government that the arrangement in regard to the generation of supply 
or electric power or the supply of water for any rea or in regard to 
the execution of any project for such generation or supply has been or 
is likely to be modified to the disadvantage of that area by reason of 
the fact that it is, by virtue of the provisions of Part II, outside 
the State in which the ower stations and other installations for the 
generation and supply of such power, or the catchment area, reservoirs 
and other works for the supply of water, as the case may be, are 
located, the Central Government may, after consultation with the 
Governm nt of each successor States wherever necessary, give such 
directions as it deems proper to the State Government or other 
authority concerned for the maintenance, so far as practicable, of the 
previous arrangement.


</article>



<article><tid>820133</tid>
<number> 65</number> Provisions as to Uttar Pradesh State Financial Corporation.-
<section><tid>1188975</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Uttar Pradesh State Financial Corporation established under the 
State Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>) shall, on and from 
the appointed day, continue to function in thos areas in respect of 
which it was functioning immediately before that day, subject to the 
provisions of this section and to such directions as may, from time to 
time, be issued by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>850095</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- section 
 (1) in respect of the Corporation may include a direction that the 
said Act, in its application to the Corporation, shall have effect 
subject to such exceptions and modifications as ma be specified in the 
direction.

</section>

<section><tid>885291</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2), the Board of Directors of the Corporation may, with 
the previous approval of the Central Government and shall, if so 
required by the Central Government, convene at any time aft r the 
appointed day a meeting for the consideration of a scheme for the 
reconstitution or reorganisation or dissolution, as the case may be, 
of the Corporation, including proposals regarding the formation of new 
Corporations, and the transfer thereto of he assets, rights and 
liabilities of the existing Corporation, and if such a scheme is 
approved at the general meeting by a resolution passed by a majority 
of the shareholders present and voting, the scheme shall be submitted 
to the Central Government fo its sanction.

</section>

<section><tid>1685520</tid>
<number>4</number>If the scheme is sanctioned by the Central Government either 
without modifications or with modifications which are approved at a 
general meeting, the Central Government shall certify the scheme, and 
upon such certification, the scheme shall, notwiths anding anything to 
the contrary contained in any other law for the time being in force, 
be binding on the Corporations affected by the scheme as well as the 
shareholders and creditors thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>454888</tid>
<number>5</number>If the scheme is not so approved or sanctioned, the Central 
Government may refer the scheme to such Judge of the High Court of 
Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal as may be nominated in this behalf by 
the Chief Justice thereof, and the decision of the Judg in regard to 
the scheme shall be final and shall be binding on the Corporations 
affected by the scheme as well as the shareholders and creditors 
thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>431015</tid>
<number>6</number>Nothing in the preceding provisions of this section shall be 
construed as preventing the Government of the States of Uttar Pradesh 
and Uttaranchal from constituting, at any time on or after the 
appointed day, a State Financial Corporation for that St te under the 
State Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>581382</tid>
<number> 66</number> Provisions as to certain companies.-
<section><tid>1783283</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything  
contained in the foregoing provisions of this Part, each of the 
companies specified in the Ninth Schedule to this Act shall, on and 
from the appointed day and until otherwise provided f r in any law, or 
in any agreement among the successor States, or in any direction 
issued by the Central Government, continue to function in the areas in 
which it was functioning immediately before that day; and the Central 
Government may from time to tim issue such directions in relation to 
such functioning as it may deem fit, notwithstanding anything to the 
contrary contained in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>), or in any 
other law.

</section>

<section><tid>509513</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued under sub- section (1) in respect of a 
company referred to in that sub- section, may include directions-

<subsection><tid>531738</tid>
<number>a</number>regarding the division of the interests and shares of existing 
State of Uttar Pradesh in the Company among the successor States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1042869</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the reconstitution of the Board of Directors of the 
Company so as to give adequate representation to all the successor 
States.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1502257</tid>
<number> 67</number> General provision as to statutory Corporations.-
<section><tid>849172</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise expressly provided by the foregoing provisions of this Part, 
where any body corporate constituted under a Central Act, State Act or 
Provincial Act for the existing State of Uttar P adesh or any part 
thereof has, by virtue of the provisions of Part II, become an 
inter- State body corporate, then, the body corporate shall, on and 
from the appointed day, continue to function and operate in those 
areas in respect of which it was functio ing and operating immediately 
before that day, subject to such directions as may from time to time 
be issued by the Central Government, until other provision is made by 
law in respect of the said body corporate.

</section>

<section><tid>1801040</tid>
<number>2</number>Any directions issued by the Central Government under sub- section 
 (1) in respect of any such body corporate shall include a direction 
that any law by which the said body corporate is governed shall, in 
its application to that body corporate, have eff ct subject to such 
exceptions and modifications as may be specified in the direction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1594687</tid>
<number> 68</number> Temporary provisions as to continuance of certain existing road 
transport permits.-
<section><tid>1018308</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in section  
 89 of the Motor Vehicles Act, <year>1988</year> (59 of <year>1988</year>), a permit granted by 
the State Transport Authority of the existing St te of Uttar Pradesh 
or any Regional Transport Authority in that State shall, if such 
permit was, immediately before the appointed day, valid and effective 
in any area in the transferred territory, be deemed to continue to be 
valid and effective in that a ea after that day subject to the 
provisions of that Act as for the time being in force in that area; 
and it shall not be necessary for any such permit to be countersigned 
by the State Transport Authority of Uttaranchal or any Regional 
Transport Authority therein for the purpose of validating it for use 
in such area:
Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with the 
successor State Government or Governments concerned add to amend or 
vary the conditions attached to the permit by the Authority by which 
the permit was granted.


</section>

<section><tid>1641251</tid>
<number>2</number>No tolls, entrance fees or other charges of a like nature shall be 
levied after the appointed day in respect of any transport vehicle for 
its operations in any of the successor States under any such permit, 
if such vehicle was, immediately before tha day, exempt from the 
payment of any such toll, entrance fees or other charges for its 
operations in the transferred territory:
Provided that the Central Government may, after consultation with the 
State Government or Governments concerned, authorise the levy of any 
such toll, entrance fees or other charges, as the case may be:

Provided further that the provisions of this sub- section shall not be 
applicable where any such tolls, entrance fees or other charges of a 
like nature is leviable for the use of any road or bridge which is 
constructed or developed for commercial purpose y the State 
Government, an undertaking of the State Government, a joint 
undertaking in which the State Government is a shareholder or a 
private sector.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>17222</tid>
<number> 69</number> Special provisions relating to retrenchment compansation in 
certain cases.- Where on account of the reorganisation of the existing 
State of Uttar Pradesh under this Act, any body corporate constituted 
under a Central Act, State Act or Provincial Act, ny co- operative 
society registered under any law relating to co- operative societies or 
any commercial or industrial undertaking of that State is 
reconstituted or reorganised in any manner whatsoever or is 
amalgamated with any other body corporate, co- ope ative society or 
undertaking, or is dissolved, and in consequence of such 
reconstitution, reorganisation, amalgamation or dissolution, any 
workman employed by such body corporate or in any such co- operative 
other body corporate, or in any other co- operative society or 
undertaking, then, notwithstanding anything contained in section 25F 
or section 25FF or section 25FFF of the Industrial Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> 
 (14 of <year>1947</year>), such transfer or re- e society or undertaking, is 
transferred to, or r- employed by, any ployment shall not entitle him 
to any compensation under that section:
Provided that-

<section><tid>616005</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of service applicable to the workman 
after such transfer or re- employment are not less favourable to the 
workman than those applicable to him immediately before the transfer 
or re- employment;

</section>

<section><tid>1773673</tid>
<number>b</number>the employer in relation to the body corporate, the co- operative 
society or the undertaking where the workman transferred or 
re- employed is, by agreement or otherwise, legally liable to pay to 
the workman, in the event of his retrenchment, compensati n under 
section 25F or section 25FF or section 25FFF of the Industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) on the basis that his service has been 
continuous and has not been interrupted by the transfer or 
re- employment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>495924</tid>
<number>70</number>Special provision as to income- tax.- Where the assets, rights and 
liabilities of any body corporate carrying on business are, under the 
provisions of this Part, transferred to any other bodies corporate 
which after the transfer carry on the same busin ss, the losses or 
profits or gains sustained by the body corporate first- mentioned 
which, but for such transfer, would have been allowed to be carried 
forward and set off in accordance with the provisions of Chapter VI of 
the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of 961), shall be apportioned amongst the 
transferee bodies corporate in accordance with the rules to be made by 
the Central Government in this behalf and, upon such apportionment, 
the share of loss allotted to each transferee body corporate shall be 
dealt ith in accordance with the provisions of Chapter VI of the said 
Act, as if the transferee body corporate had itself sustained such 
loss in a business carried on by it in the years in which these losses 
were sustained.


</article>



<article><tid>1503359</tid>
<number> 71</number> Continuance of facilities in certain State institutions.-
<section><tid>224473</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Government of State of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal, as the case may 
be, shall, in respect of the institutions specified in the Tenth 
Schedule to this Act, located in that State, contin e to provide 
facilities to the people of the other State which shall not, in any 
respect, be less favourable to such people than what were being 
provided to them before the appointed day, for such period and upon 
such terms and conditions as may be agree upon between the two State 
Governments before the 1st day of December, <year>2001</year> or if no agreement is 
reached by the said date as may be fixed by order of the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>359495</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, at any time before the 1st day of 
December, <year>2001</year>, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in 
the Tenth Schedule referred to in sub- section (1) any other 
institution existing on the appointed day in the States of U tar 
Pradesh and Uttaranchal and on the issue of such notification, such 
Schedule shall be deemed to be amended by the inclusion of the said 
institution therein.
PART

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES

PART VIII

PROVISIONS AS TO SERVICES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378178</tid>
<number> 72</number> Provisions relating to All- India Services.-
<section><tid>610312</tid>
<number>1</number>In this section,  
the expression" State cadre''-

<subsection><tid>231545</tid>
<number>a</number>in relation to the Indian Administrative Service, has the meaning 
assigned to it in the Indian Administrative Service (Cadre) Rules, 
<year>1954</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1026780</tid>
<number>b</number>in relation to the Indian Police Service, has the meaning assigned 
to it in the Indian Police Service (Cadre) Rules, <year>1954</year>; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1186595</tid>
<number>c</number>in relation to the Indian Forest Service, has the meaning assigned 
to it in the Indian Forest Service (Cadre) Rules, <year>1966</year>.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>382067</tid>
<number>2</number>In place of the cadres of the Indian Administrative Service, 
Indian Police Service and Indian Forest Service for the existing State 
of Uttar Pradesh, there shall, on and from the appointed day, be two 
separate cadres, one for the State of Uttar Prade h and the other for 
the State of Uttaranchal in respect of each of these services.

</section>

<section><tid>349639</tid>
<number>3</number>The initial strength and composition of the State cadres referred 
to in sub- section (2) shall be such as the Central Government may, by 
order, determine before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>631394</tid>
<number>4</number>The members of each of the said services borne on the Uttar 
Pradesh cadre thereof immediately before the appointed day shall be 
allocated to the State cadres of the same service constituted under 
sub- section (2) in such manner and with effect from su h date or dates 
as the Central Government may, by order, specify.

</section>

<section><tid>969381</tid>
<number>5</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to affect the operation, 
on or after the appointed day, of the All- India Services Act, <year>1951</year> (61  
  of <year>1951</year>), or the rules made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1926018</tid>
<number> 73</number> Provisions relating to other services.-
<section><tid>1926243</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person who  
immediately before the appointed day is serving in connection with the 
affairs of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall, on and from that 
day provisionally continue to serve in connecti n with the affairs of 
the State of Uttar Pradesh unless he is required, by general or 
special order of the Central Government to serve provisionally in 
connection with the affairs of the State of Uttaranchal:
Provided that every direction under this sub- section issued after the 
expiry of a period of one year from the appointed day shall be issued 
with the consultation of the Governments of the successor States.


</section>

<section><tid>934537</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be after the appointed day, the Central Government 
shall, by general or special order, determine the successor State to 
which every person referred to in sub- section (1) shall be finally 
allotted for service and the date with effect fr m which such 
allotment shall take effect or be deemed to have taken effect.

</section>

<section><tid>1095896</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person who is finally allotted under the provisions of 
sub- section (2) to a successor State shall, if he is not already 
serving therein be made available for serving in the successor State 
from such date as may be agreed upon between the Govern ents concerned 
or in default of such agreement, as may be determined by the Central 
Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>650446</tid>
<number> 74</number> Other provisions relating to services.-
<section><tid>1228926</tid>
<number>1</number>Nothing in this  
section or in section 73 shall be deemed to affect on or after the 
appointed day, the operation of the provisions of Chapter I of Part 
XIV of the Constitution in relation to determination of he conditions 
of service of persons serving in connection with the affairs of the 
Union or any State:
Provided that the conditions of service applicable immediately before 
the appointed day in the case of any person deemed to have been 
allocated to the State of Uttar Pradesh or to the State of Uttaranchal 
the previous approval of the Central Government. under section 73 
shall not be varied to his disad antage except with


</section>

<section><tid>1631538</tid>
<number>2</number>All services prior to the appointed day rendered by a person,-

<subsection><tid>1256134</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is deemed to have been allocated to any State under section 
73, shall be deemed to have been rendered in connection with the 
affairs of that State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>968049</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is deemed to have been allocated to the Union in connection 
with the administration of the Uttaranchal, shall be deemed to have 
been rendered in connection with the affairs of the Union, for the 
purposes of the rules regulating his conditions of service.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>248655</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of section 73, shall not apply in relation to 
members of any All- India Service.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1556814</tid>
<number> 75</number> Provisions as to continuance of officers in same post.-
<section><tid>145528</tid>
<number>1</number>Every  
person who, immediately before the appointed day, is holding or 
discharging the duties of any post or office in connection with the 
affairs of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh in any area which on 
that day falls within any of the successor States shall continue to 
hold the same post or office in that successor State, and shall be 
deemed, on and from that day, to have been duly appointed to the post 
or office by the Government of, or ny other appropriate authority in 
that successor State:
Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent a 
competent authority, on and from the appointed day, from passing in 
relation to such person any order affecting the continuance in such 
post or office.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>975901</tid>
<number> 76</number> Advisory Committees.- The Central Government may, by order, 
establish one or more Advisory Committees for the purpose of assisting 
it in regard to-
<section><tid>1707054</tid>
<number>a</number>the discharge of any of its functions under this Part; and

</section>

<section><tid>1770590</tid>
<number>b</number>the ensuring of fair and equitable treatment to all persons 
affected by the provisions of this Part and the proper consideration 
of any representations made by such persons.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1041606</tid>
<number>77</number>Power of Central Government to give directions.- The Central 
Government may give such directions to the State Government of Uttar 
Pradesh and the State Government of Uttaranchal as may appear to it to 
be necessary for the purpose of giving effect to t e foregoing 
provisions of this Part and the State Government shall comply with 
such directions.


</article>



<article><tid>172196</tid>
<number> 78</number> Provisions as to State Public Service Commission.-
<section><tid>1638493</tid>
<number>1</number>The Public  
Service Commission for the existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall, on 
and from the appointed day, be the Public Service Commission for the 
State of Uttar Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>375343</tid>
<number>2</number>The persons holding office immediately before the appointed day as 
the Chairman or other member of the Public Service Commission for the 
existing State of Uttar Pradesh shall, as from the appointed day, be 
the Chairman or, as the case may be, the oth r member of the Public 
Service Commission for the State of Uttar Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>1207022</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person who becomes the Chairman or other member of the 
Public Service Commission for the State of Uttar Pradesh on the 
appointed day under sub- section (2), shall-

<subsection><tid>1342334</tid>
<number>a</number>be entitled to receive from the Government of the State of Uttar 
Pradesh conditions of service not less favourable than those to which 
he was entitled under the provisions applicable to him;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1663146</tid>
<number>b</number>subject to the proviso to clause (2) of article 316, hold office 
or continue to hold office until the expiration of his term of office 
as determined under the provisions applicable to him immediately 
before the appointed day.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>81291</tid>
<number>4</number>The report of the Uttar Pradesh Public Service Commission as to 
the work done by the Commission in respect of any period prior to the 
appointed day shall be presented under clause (2) of article 323 to 
the Governors of the States of Uttar Pradesh and Uttaranchal, and the 
Governor of the State of Uttar Pradesh shall, on receipt of such 
report, cause a copy thereof together with a memorandum explaining as 
far as possible, as respects the cases, if any, where the advice of 
the Commission was not accepte, the reasons for such non- acceptance 
to be laid before the Legislature of the State of Uttar Pradesh and it 
shall not be necessary to cause such report or any such memorandum to 
be laid before the Legislative Assembly of the State of Uttaranchal.
PART

MANAGEMENT AND DEVELOPMENT OF WATER RESOURCES

PART IX

MANAGEMENT AND DEVELOPMENT OF WATER RESOURCES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1041092</tid>
<number> 79</number> Water Resources Development and its Management.-
<section><tid>798331</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act but subject to the 
provisions of section 80, all rights and liabilities of the existing 
State of Uttar Pradesh in respect of water resource projects n 
relation to-

<subsection><tid>1260800</tid>
<number>i</number>Ganga and its tributaries traversing the successor States 
excluding the Upper Yamuna River up to Okhla; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1265990</tid>
<number>ii</number>Upper Yumuna River and its tributaries up to Okhla, shall, on the 
appointed day, be the rights and liabilities of the successor States 
in such proportion as may be fixed, and subject to such adjustments as 
may be made, by agreement entered into by the said States after 
consultation with the Central Govern ent, or, if no such agreement is 
entered into within two years of the appointed day, then, the Central 
Government may, by order, determine within one year having regard to 
the purposes of the project:
Provided that the order so made by the Central Government may be 
varied by any subsequent agreement entered into by the successor 
States after consultation with the Central Government.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>968064</tid>
<number>2</number>An agreement or order referred to in sub- section (1) shall, where 
an extension or further development of any of the projects referred to 
in that sub- section after the appointed day is undertaken, be the 
rights and liabilities of the successor States in relation to such 
extension or further development.

</section>

<section><tid>101550</tid>
<number>3</number>The rights and liabilities referred to in sub- sections (1) and (2) 
shall include-

<subsection><tid>1633283</tid>
<number>a</number>the right to receive and utilise the water available for 
distribution as a result of the projects; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1873124</tid>
<number>b</number>the right to receive and utilise the power generated as a result 
of the projects, but shall not include the rights and liabilities 
under any contract entered into before the appointed day by the 
Government of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh with any person or 
authority other than Government.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>156415</tid>
<number> 80</number> Constitution and functions of the Ganga Management Board.-
<section><tid>1838454</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Central Government shall constitute a Board to be called the Ganga 
Management Board (hereinafter referred to as the Board) for 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 79 for any or for a 
combination of the following purposes, namely:- administration, 
construction, maintenance and operation of projects

<subsection><tid>644045</tid>
<number>i</number>irrigation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1884121</tid>
<number>ii</number>rural and urban water supply;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>147943</tid>
<number>iii</number>hydro power generation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1182457</tid>
<number>iv</number>navigation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>344681</tid>
<number>v</number>industries; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>41540</tid>
<number>vi</number>for any other purpose which the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>394924</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall consist of-

<subsection><tid>651721</tid>
<number>a</number>a whole- time Chairman to be appointed by the Central Government in 
consultation with the successor States;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1755666</tid>
<number>b</number>two full time members, one from each of the successor States, to 
be nominated by the respective State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>466446</tid>
<number>c</number>four part- time members, two from each of the successor States, to 
be nominated by the respective State Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>299965</tid>
<number>d</number>two representatives of the Central Government to be nominated by 
that Government.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1866344</tid>
<number>3</number>The functions of the Board shall include-

<subsection><tid>1124385</tid>
<number>a</number>the regulation of supply of water from the projects referred to in 
clause (i) of sub- section (1) of section 79 to the successor States 
having regard to-

<subsubsection><tid>1065463</tid>
<number>i</number>any agreement entered into or arrangement made covering the 
Government of existing State of Uttar Pradesh and any other State or 
Union territory, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1167726</tid>
<number>ii</number>the agreement or the order referred to in sub- section (2) of 
section 79;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>881965</tid>
<number>b</number>the regulation of supply of power generated at the projects 
referred to in clause (i) of sub- section (1) of section 79, to any 
Electricity Board or other authority in- charge of the distribution of 
power having regard to-

<subsubsection><tid>1852256</tid>
<number>i</number>any agreement entered into, or arrangement made covering the 
Government of the existing State of Uttar Pradesh and any other State 
or Union territory, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1541200</tid>
<number>ii</number>the agreement or the order referred to in sub- section (2) of 
section 79;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>332596</tid>
<number>c</number>the construction of such of the remaining on- going or new works 
connected with the development of the water resources projects 
relating to the rivers or their tributaries as the Central Government 
may specify by notification in the Official Gazette

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1903308</tid>
<number>d</number>such other functions as the Central Government may, after 
consultation with the successor States entrust to it.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>779365</tid>
<number> 81</number> Staff of the Management Board.-
<section><tid>813627</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may employ such  
staff, as it may consider necessary for the efficient discharge of its 
functions under this Act. Such staff shall at the first instance, be 
any other method: appointed on deputation from the successor State 
ailing which through
Provided that every person who, immediately before the constitution of 
the said Board, was engaged in the construction, maintenance or 
operation of the works relating to the projects referred to in clause 
 (i) of sub- section (1) of section 79 shall contin e to be so employed 
under the Board in connection with the said works on the same terms 
and conditions of service as were applicable to him before such 
constitution until the Central Government, by order, directs 
otherwise:

Provided further that the said Board may, in consultation with the 
Government of the successor State or the Electricity Board concerned 
and with the prior approval of the Central Government, retain any such 
person for service under that State Government r Board.


</section>

<section><tid>139666</tid>
<number>2</number>The Government of the successor States shall at all times provide 
the necessary funds to the Board to meet all expenses (including the  
  salaries and allowances of the staff) required for the discharge of 
its functions and such amounts shall be apporti ned between the States 
concerned in such proportion as the Central Government may, having 
regard to the benefits to each of the said States specify.

</section>

<section><tid>24285</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall be under the control of the Central Government and 
shall comply with such directions, as may, from time to time, be given 
to it by that Government.

</section>

<section><tid>279580</tid>
<number>4</number>The Board may delegate such of its powers, functions and duties as 
it may deem fit to the Chairman of the said Board or to any officer 
subordinate to the Board.

</section>

<section><tid>1311464</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may, for the purpose of enabling the Board 
to function efficiently, issue such directions to the State 
Governments concerned, or any other authority, and the State 
Governments, or the other authority shall comply with such dire tions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1625558</tid>
<number> 82</number> Jurisdiction of the Board.-
<section><tid>1518944</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board shall, ordinarily  
exercise jurisdiction in regard to any of the projects referred to in 
clause (i) of sub- section (1) of section 79 over headworks (barrages,  
  dams, reservoirs, regulating structures), part of c nal network and 
transmission lines necessary to deliver water or power to the States 
concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1056591</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether the Board has jurisdiction 
under sub- section (1) over any project referred thereto, the same 
shall be referred to the Central Government for decision thereon.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>197438</tid>
<number> 83</number> Power of Board to make regulations.- The Board may make 
regulations consistent with the Act and the rules made thereunder, to 
provide for-
<section><tid>1872411</tid>
<number>a</number>regulating the time and place of meetings of the Board and the 
procedure to be followed for the transaction of business at such 
meetings;

</section>

<section><tid>1569974</tid>
<number>b</number>delegation of powers and duties of the Chairman or any officer of 
the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>554349</tid>
<number>c</number>the appointment and regulation of the conditions of service of the 
officers and other staff of the Board;

</section>

<section><tid>933069</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter for which regulations are considered necessary by 
the Board.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>346294</tid>
<number> 84</number> Allocation of the water resources of the River Yamuna.-
<section><tid>1608528</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
utilisable water resources of the Yamuna River up to Okhla, as 
allocated, before the appointed day, to the existing State of Uttar 
Pradesh under the Memorandum of Undertakings, dated the 2th May, <year>1994</year> 
shall be further allocated between the successor States by mutual 
agreement within a period of two years, failing which, the Central 
Government shall, by order, determine the allocation of such water 
resource between the successor States wi hin a further period of one 
year.

</section>

<section><tid>316078</tid>
<number>2</number>The State of Uttaranchal shall, on the appointed day, be inducted 
as a member of the Upper Yamuna Board constituted for the 
implementation of the Memorandum of Undertaking referred to in 
sub- section (1).
PART

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS

PART X

LEGAL AND MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>10578</tid>
<number>85</number>Amendment of section 15 of Act 37 of <year>1956</year>.- On and from the 
appointed day, in section 15 of the States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (U. P. Act 1 of <year>1961</year>), in clause (b), for the words" Uttar Pradesh and 
Madhya Pradesh", the words" Uttar Pradesh, Uttarancha and Madhya 
Pradesh" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1852261</tid>
<number>86</number>Territorial extent of laws.- The provisions of Part II shall not 
be deemed to have affected any change in the territories to which the 
Uttar Pradesh Imposition of Ceiling of Land Holding Act, <year>1961</year> and any 
other law in force immediately before the appo nted day, extends or 
applies, and territorial references in any such law to the State of 
Uttar Pradesh shall, until otherwise provided by a competent 
Legislature or other competent authority be construed as meaning the 
territories within the existing Sta e of Uttar Pradesh before the 
appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>380928</tid>
<number>87</number>Power to adapt laws.- For the purpose of facilitating the 
application in relation to the State of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal 
of any law made before the appointed day, the appropriate Government 
may, before the expiration of two years from that day, y order, make 
such adaptations and modifications of the law, whether by way of 
repeal or amendment, as may be necessary or expedient, and thereupon 
every such law shall have effect subject to the adaptations and 
modifications so made until altered, repea ed or amended by a 
competent Legislature or other competent authority.
Explanation.- In this section, the expression" appropriate Government" 
means as respects any law relating to a matter enumerated in the Union 
List, the Central Government, and as respects any other law in its 
application to a State, the State Government.



</article>



<article><tid>1709802</tid>
<number>88</number>Power to construe laws.- Notwithstanding that no provision or 
insufficient provision has been made under section 87 for the 
adaptation of a law made before the appointed day, any court, tribunal 
or authority, required or empowered to enforce such law ay, for the 
purpose of facilitating its application in relation to the State of 
Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal, construe the law in such manner, without 
affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper in regard to 
the matter before the court, tribu al or authority.


</article>



<article><tid>812316</tid>
<number>89</number>Power to name authorities, etc., for exercising statutory 
functions.- The Government of the State of Uttaranchal, as respects the 
transferred territory may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify the authority, officer or person who, on or a ter the 
appointed day, shall be competent to exercise such functions 
exercisable under any law in force on that day as may be mentioned in 
that notification and such law shall have effect accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>269186</tid>
<number>90</number>Legal proceedings.- Where, immediately before the appointed day, 
the existing State of Uttar Pradesh is a party to any legal 
proceedings with respect to any property, rights or liabilities 
subject to apportionment between the States of Uttar Pradesh a d 
Uttaranchal under this Act, the State of Uttar Pradesh or Uttaranchal 
which succeeds to, or acquires a share in, that property or those 
rights or liabilities by virtue of any provision of this Act shall be 
deemed to be substituted for the existing Stat of Uttar Pradesh or 
added as a party to those proceedings, and the proceedings may 
continue accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1332587</tid>
<number> 91</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.-
<section><tid>1711899</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before a court (other than High  
  Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that day 
falls within the State of Uttar Pradesh shall, if t is a proceeding 
relating exclusively to the territory, which as from that day are the 
territories of Uttaranchal State, stand transferred to the 
corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer of that State.

</section>

<section><tid>1481235</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should stand 
transferred under sub- section (1) it shall be referred to the High 
Court at Allahabad and the decision of that High Court shall be final.

</section>

<section><tid>1268753</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section-

<subsection><tid>364010</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding'' includes any suit, case or appeal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>819440</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer'' in the 
State of Uttaranchal means-

<subsubsection><tid>425391</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer in which, or before 
whom, the proceeding would have laid if it had been instituted after 
the appointed day; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1933835</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, authority, or officer in 
that State, as may be determined after the appointed day by the 
Government of that State or the Central Government, as the case may 
be, or before the appointed day by the Government of the existing 
State of Uttar Pradesh to be the corresponding court, tribunal, 
authority or officer.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1395694</tid>
<number>92</number>Right of pleaders to practise in certain cases.- Any person who, 
immediately before the appointed day, is enrolled as a pleader 
entitled to practise in any subordinate courts in the existing State 
of Uttar Pradesh shall, for a period of one year from hat day, 
continue to be entitled to practise in those courts, notwithstanding 
that the whole or any part of the territories within the jurisdiction 
of those courts has been transferred to the State of Uttaranchal.


</article>



<article><tid>235456</tid>
<number>93</number>Effect of provisions of the Act inconsistent with other laws.- The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.


</article>



<article><tid>1487910</tid>
<number> 94</number> Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><tid>766202</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the President may, by 
order, do anything not inconsistent with such provisions which appears 
to him to be necessary or expedient for the purpos of removing the 
difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a period 
of three years from the appointed day.


</section>

<section><tid>1896699</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid before each 
House of Parliament.


</section>

</article>



 </act>