<act><title>

    THE INDIAN EVIDENCE ACT, 1872</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—This 
    Act may be called the Indian Evidence Act, 1872. 
 
It 
    extends to the whole of India 

    1[except the State of 
    Jammu and Kashmir] and applies to all judicial proceedings in or before any 
    Court, including Courts-martial, 

    2[other than 
    Courts-martial convened under the Army Act] (44 &amp; 45 Vict., c. 58) 


    3[the Naval Discipline 
    Act (29 &amp; 30 Vict., c. 109) or 

    4[***] the Indian Navy 
    (Discipline) Act, 1934 (34 of 1934)5 6[or 
    the Air Force Act] (7 Geo. 5, c. 51) but not to affidavits 

    7presented to any 
    Court or Officer, nor to proceedings before an arbitrator; 

 
and it shall 
    come into force on the first day of September, 1872. 
 
 











 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Repeal 
    of enactments.—[Rep. by the 
    Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938), sec. 2 and Sch.] 
 
 
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Interpretation clause. </title>—In this Act the following words 
and expressions are used in the following senses, unless a contrary intention 
appears from the context:— 
 <title>“Court”. </title>—“Court” includes all Judges <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>and 
Magistrates, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and all persons, except arbitrators, legally 
authorized to take evidence. 
 <title>“Fact”. </title>—“Fact” means and includes— 
 <section><number>1</number> any thing, state of things, or relation of things, capable of being 
perceived by the senses; 
 </section><section><number>2</number> any mental condition of which any person is conscious. 
 <title> Illustrations </title>
 <subsection><number>a</number> That there are certain objects arranged in a certain order in a certain 
place, is a fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> That a man heard or saw something, is a fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> That a man said certain words, is a fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> That a man holds a certain opinion, has a certain intention, acts in good 
faith, or fraudulently, or uses a particular word in a particular sense, or is 
or was at a specified time conscious of a particular sensation, is a 
fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> That a man has a certain reputation, is a fact. 
 <title>“Relevant”. </title>—One fact is said to be relevant to another when 
the one is connected with the other in any of the ways referred to in the 
provisions of this Act relating to the relevancy of facts. 
 <title>“Facts in issue”. </title>—The expression “facts in issue” means and 
includes— 
 any fact from which, either by itself or in connection with other facts, the 
existence, non-existence, nature, or extent of any right, liability, or 
disability, asserted or denied in any suit or proceeding, necessarily follows. 

 Explanation.— Whenever, under the provisions of the law for the time 
being in force relating to Civil Procedure, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>any Court records an 
issue of fact, the fact to be asserted or denied in the answer to such issue, is 
a fact in issue. 
 <title>Illustrations </title>
 A is accused of the murder of B . 
 At his trial the following facts may be in issue:— 
 That A caused B's death; 
 That A intended to cause B's death; 
 That A had received grave and sudden provocation from B ; 

 That A at the time of doing the act which caused B's death, 
was, by reason of unsoundness of mind, incapable of knowing its nature. 
 <title>“Document”. </title>—“Document” <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>means any matter 
expressed or described upon any substance by means of letters, figures or marks, 
or by more than one of those means, intended to be used, or which may be used, 
for the purpose of recording that matter. 
 <title>Illustrations </title>
 A writing<footcitenum>5</footcitenum> is a document; 
 Words printed, lithographed or photographed are documents; 
 A map or plan is a document; 
 An inscription on a metal plate or stone is a document; 
 A caricature is a document. 
 <title>“Evidence” </title>.— <title>“ </title>Evidence” means 
and includes— 
 <subsubsection><number>1</number> all statements which the Court permits or requires to be made before it 
by witnesses, in relation to matters of fact under inquiry, such statements are 
called oral evidence; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>2</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[all documents including electronic records produced for the 
inspection of the Court], 
 such documents are called documentary evidence. 
 <title>“Proved” </title>.—A fact is said to be proved when, after 
considering the matters before it, the Court either believes it to exist, or 
considers its existence so probable that a prudent man ought, under the 
circumstances of the particular case, to act upon the supposition that it 
exists. <title></title>
 <title>“Disproved”. </title>— A fact is said to be disproved when, 
after considering the matters before it, the Court either believes that it does 
not exist, or considers its non-existence so probable that a prudent man ought, 
under the circumstances of the particular case, to act upon the supposition that 
it does not exist. <title></title>
 <title>“ </title><title>Not proved”. </title>— A fact 
is said not to be proved when it is neither proved  nor  disproved. 
<title></title>
 <footcitenum>7</footcitenum><title>[“ India ”. </title>—“ India ” means the territory of 
India excluding the State of Jammu and Kashmir .] 
 <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[the expressions <title>“Certifying Authority”, 
</title><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[electronic signature], 
</title><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Electronic Signature Certificate], “electronic 
form”, “electronic records”, “information”, “secure electronic record”, “secure 
digital signature” </title>and <title>“subscriber” </title>shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Information Technology Act, 2000 
(21 of 2000).] 





































</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> “May 
    presume”.—Whenever it is provided 
    by this Act that the Court may presume a fact, it may either regard such 
    fact as proved, unless and until it is disproved, or may call for proof
of it. 
 
“Shall 
    presume”.—Whenever it is directed 
    by this Act that the Court shall presume a fact, it shall regard such fact 
    as proved, unless and until it is disproved. 
 
“Conclusive 
    proof”.—When one fact is declared 
    by this Act to be conclusive proof of another, the Court shall, on proof of 
    the one fact, regard the other as proved, and shall not allow evidence to be 
    given for the purpose of disproving it. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Evidence may be given of facts in issue and 
      relevant facts.—Evidence may be 
      given in any suit or proceedings of the existence or non-existence of 
      every fact in issue and of such other facts as are hereinafter declared to 
      be relevant, and of no others. 
 Explanation.—This section shall not enable any person to give evidence of a 
      fact which he is disentitled to prove by any provision of the law for the 
      time being in force relating to Civil Procedure1..—This 
    section shall not enable any person to give evidence of a fact which he is 
    disentitled to prove by any provision of the law for the time being in force 
    relating to Civil Procedure1." 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> A is 
        tried for the murder of B by beating him with a club with the 
        intention of causing his death.
 At A’s 
        trial the following facts are in issue:—
                    
        A’s beating B with the club;
                    
        A’s causing B’s death by such beating;
                    
        A’s intention to cause B’s death.
 </section><section><number>b</number> A 
        suitor does not bring with him, and have in readiness for production at 
        the first hearing of the case, a bond on which he relies. This section 
        does not enable him to produce the bond or prove its contents at a 
        subsequent stage of the proceedings, otherwise than in accordance with 
        the conditions prescribed by the Code of Civil 
      Procedure.</section>
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> Relevancy of facts forming part of same 
      transaction.—Facts which, 
      though not in issue, are so connected with a fact in issue as to form part 
      of the same transaction, are relevant, whether they occurred at the same 
      time and place or at different times and places. 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> A is 
        accused of the murder of B by beating him. Whatever was said or 
        done by A or B or the by-standers at the beating, or so 
        shortly before or after it as to form part of the transaction, is a 
        relevant fact.
 </section><section><number>b</number> 
        A is accused of waging war against the 1[Government of India] by taking part in an armed 
        insurrection in which property is destroyed, troops are attacked, and 
        goals are broken open. The occurrence of these facts is relevant, as 
        forming part of the general transaction, though A may not have 
        been present at all of them.
 </section><section><number>c</number> A 
        sues B for a libel contained in a letter forming part of a 
        correspondence. Letters between the parties relating to the subject out 
        of which the libel arose, and forming part of the correspondence in 
        which it is contained, are relevant facts, though they do not contain 
        the libel itself.
 </section><section><number>d</number> The question 
        is, whether certain goods ordered from B were delivered to 
        A. The goods were delivered to several intermediate persons 
        successively. Each delivery is a relevant fact.</section>
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Facts which are the occasion, cause or effect 
      of facts in issue.—Facts which 
      are the occasion, cause, or effect, immediate or otherwise, of relevant 
      facts, or facts in issue, or which constitute the state of things under 
      which they happened, or which afforded an opportunity for their occurrence 
      or transaction, are relevant. 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> The question 
        is, whether A robbed B.
 The facts that, 
        shortly before the robbery, B went to a fair with money in his 
        possession, and that he showed it, or mentioned the fact that he had it, 
        to third persons, are relevant.
 </section><section><number>b</number> The question 
        is, whether A murdered B.
 Marks on the 
        ground, produced by a struggle at or near the place where the murder was 
        committed, are relevant facts.
 </section><section><number>c</number> The question 
        is, whether A poisoned B.
 The state of 
        B’s health before the symptoms ascribed to poison, and habits of 
        B, known to A, which afforded an opportunity for the 
        administration of poison, are relevant facts.</section>
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Motive, 
    preparation and previous or subsequent conduct.—Any 
    fact is relevant which shows or constitutes a motive or preparation for any 
    fact in issue or relevant fact. 
 
The conduct of 
    any party, or of any agent to any party, to any suit or proceeding, in 
    reference to such suit or proceeding, or in reference to any fact in issue 
    therein or relevant thereto, and the conduct of any person an offence 
    against whom is the subject of any proceeding, is relevant, if such conduct 
    influences or is influenced by any fact in issue or relevant fact, and 
    whether it was previous or subsequent thereto. 
 
Explanation 
    1.—The word “conduct” in this section does not include statements, unless 
    those statements accompany and explain acts other than statements; but this 
    explanation is not to affect the relevancy of statements under any other 
    section of this Act. 
 
Explanation 
    2.—When the conduct of any person is relevant, any statement made to him or 
    in his presence and hearing, which affects such conduct, is relevant. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A is tried for the 
      murder of B.
 
The facts that A 
      murdered C, that B knew that A had murdered C, 
      and that B had tried to extort money from A by threatening 
      to make his knowledge public, are relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A sues B 
      upon a bond for the payment of money. B denies the making of the 
      bond.
 
The fact that, at the time 
      when the bond was alleged to be made, B required money for
a particular purpose is relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A is tried for the 
      murder of B by poison.
 
The fact that, before the 
      death of B, A procured poison similar to that which was 
      administered to B, is relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> The question is, whether a 
      certain document is the Will of A.
 
The facts that, not long 
      before the date of the alleged Will, A made inquiry into matters to 
      which the provisions of the alleged Will relate, that he consulted 
      vakils in reference to making the Will, and that he caused drafts or 
      other Wills to be prepared of which he did not approve, are relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>e</number> A is accused of a 
      crime.
 
The facts that, either before 
      or at the time of, or after the alleged crime, A provided evidence 
      which would tend to give to the facts of the case an appearance favourable 
      to himself, or that he destroyed or concealed evidence, or prevented the 
      presence or procured the absence of persons who might have been witnesses, 
      or suborned persons to give false evidence respecting it, are relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> The question is, whether
      A robbed B.
 
The facts that, after B 
      was robbed, C said in A’s presence—"the police are coming to 
      look for the man who robbed B”, and that immediately afterwards 
      A ran away, are relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>g</number> The question is, whether
      A owes B rupees 10,000.
 
The facts that A asked
      C to lend him money, and that D said to C in A’s 
      presence and hearing—“I advise you not to trust A, for he owes B
      10,000 Rupees”, and that A went away without making any answer, 
      are relevant facts.
 </section><section>
<number>h</number> The question is, whether
      A committed a crime.
 
The fact that A 
      absconded after receiving a letter warning him that inquiry was being made 
      for the criminal and the contents of the letter, are relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>i</number> A is accused of a 
      crime.
 
The facts that, after the 
      commission of the alleged crime, he absconded, or was in possession of 
      property or the proceeds of property acquired by the crime, or attempted 
      to conceal things which were or might have been used in committing it, are 
      relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>j</number> The question is, whether
A was ravished.
 
The facts that, shortly after 
      the alleged rape, she made a complaint relating to the crime, the 
      circumstances under which, and the terms in which, the complaint was made, 
      are relevant.
 
The fact that, without making 
      a complaint, she said that she had been ravished is not relevant as 
      conduct under this section, though it may be relevant as a dying 
      declaration under section 32, clause (1), or as corroborative evidence 
      under section 157.
 </section><section>

<number>k</number> The question is, whether A was 
      robbed. 
 
The fact that, soon after the 
      alleged robbery, he made a complaint relating to the offence, the 
      circumstances under which, and the terms in which, the complaint was made, 
      are relevant.
 
The fact that he said he had 
      been robbed, without making any complaint, is not relevant, as conduct 
      under this section, though it may be relevant as a dying declaration under 
      section 32, clause (1), or as corroborative evidence under section 157.
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Ground for 
      rejection of testimony of eye witness
 
The conduct of an eye witness 
      in non-disclosing the incident to anybody for a number of days, is highly 
      unnatural one and is sufficient to reject his testimony; Ganpat Kondiba 
      Chavan v. State of Maharashtra, (1997) 2 Crimes 38 (Bom). 
 
It is well settled that the 
      conduct of a witness in not disclosing the incident to person(s) whom he 
      must have met after the incident is indicative of the fact that he had not 
      seen the accident; Ganpat Kondiba Chavan v. State of 
      Maharashtra, (1997) 2 Crimes 38 (Bom). 
 
Role of 
      motive in an offence
 
If motive is proved, the case 
      of prosecution becomes more easier to connect accused to the alleged 
      incident; P.V. Narayana v. State of Andhra Pradesh, (1997) 2 
      Crimes 307 (AP). 
 
Normally there is a motive 
      behind every criminal act; Barikanoo v. State of Uttar Pradesh,
      (1997) 1 Crimes 500 (All).  
 
When motive 
      is not sine qua non
 
Where the ocular evidence is 
      very clear and convincing and the role of the accused person in the crime 
      stands clearly established, establishment of motive is not a sine qua 
      non for proving the prosecution case; Yunis alias Kariya v. 
      State of Madhya Pradesh, AIR 2003 SC 539. 
 
It is well settled that where 
      the direct evidence regarding the assault is worthy of the credence and 
      can be believed, the question of motive becomes more or less academic. 
      Sometimes the motive is clear and can be proved and sometimes the motive 
      is shrouded in the mystery and it is very difficult to locate the same. 
      If, however, the evidence of eye witnesses is credit-worthy and is 
      believed by the court which has placed implicit reliance on them, the 
      question whether there is any motive or not becomes wholly irrelevant; 
      Raja v. State, (1972) 2 Crimes 175. 
 
Motive is a thing primarily 
      known to the accused himself and it may not the possible for the 
      prosecution in each and every case to find out the real motive behind the 
      crime; Barikanoo v. State of Uttar Pradesh, (1997)1 Crimes 
      500 (All). 
 
It is well established that 
      where there is an eyewitness account regarding the incident, the motive 
      loses all its importance; Barikanoo v. State of Uttar Pradesh, 
      (1997) 1 Crimes 500 (All). 
</section>

 
  


</article> 

  
 <title></title>
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>9</number> Facts necessary to explain 
or introduce relevant facts. </title>—Facts necessary to explain or introduce a 
fact in issue or relevant fact, or which support or rebut an inference suggested 
by a fact in issue or relevant fact, or which establish the identity of anything 
or person whose identity is relevant, or fix the time or place at which any fact 
in issue or relevant fact happened, or which show the relation of parties by 
whom any such fact was transacted, are relevant in so far as they are necessary 
for that purpose. 
 <title>Illustrations </title>
 <section><number>a</number> The question is, whether a given document is the Will of 
A. 
 The state of A's property and of his family at the date 
of the alleged Will may be relevant facts. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> A sues B for a libel imputing disgraceful 
conduct to A; B affirms that the matter alleged to be libellous is 
true. 
 The position and relations of the parties at the time when the 
libel was published may be relevant facts as introductory to the facts in issue. 

 The particulars of a dispute between A and B 
about a matter unconnected with the alleged libel are irrelevant, though 
the fact that there was a dispute may be relevant if it affected the relations 
between A and B . 
 </section><section><number>c</number> A is accused of a crime. 
 The fact that, soon after the commission of the crime, A 
absconded from his house, is relevant, under section 8, as conduct 
subsequent to and affected by facts in issue. 
 The fact that, at the time when he left home, he had sudden and 
urgent business at the place to which he went, is relevant, as tending to 
explain the fact that he left home suddenly. 
 The details of the business on which he left are not relevant, 
except in so far as they are necessary to show that the business was sudden and 
urgent. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> A sues B for inducing C to break 
a contract of service made by him with A.C ., on leaving A's 
service, says to A— "I am leaving you because B has made 
me a better offer”. This statement is a relevant fact as explanatory of C's 
conduct, which is relevant as a fact in issue. 
 </section><section><number>e</number> A , accused of theft, is seen to give the stolen 
property to B, who is seen to give it to A's wife. B 
says, as he delivers it—" A says you are to hide this”. B's 
statement is relevant as explanatory of a fact which is part of the 
transaction. 
 </section><section><number>f</number> A is tried for a riot and is proved to have marched 
at the head of a mob. The cries of the mob are relevant as explanatory of the 
nature of the transaction. 








</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Things 
    said or done by conspirator in reference to common design.—Where 
    there is reasonable ground to believe that two or more persons have 
    conspired together to commit an offence or an actionable wrong, anything 
    said, done or written by any one of such persons in reference to their 
    common intention, after the time when such intention was first entertained 
    by any one of them, is a relevant fact as against each of the persons 
    believed to so conspiring, as well for the purpose of proving the existence 
    of the conspiracy as for the purpose of showing that any such person was a 
    party to it. 
 
 
Illustration
 
Reasonable ground 
      exists for believing that A has joined in a conspiracy to wage war 
      against the 
1[Government 
      of India].
 
The facts that B 
      procured arms in Europe for the purpose of the conspiracy, C 
      collected money in Calcutta for a like object, D persuaded 
      persons to join the conspiracy in Bombay, E published writings 
      advocating the object in view at Agra, and F transmitted from Delhi 
      to G at Kabul the money which C had collected at Calcutta, 
      and the contents of a letter written by H giving an account of the 
      conspiracy, are each relevant, both to prove the existence of the 
      conspiracy, and to prove A’s complicity in it, although he may have 
      been ignorant of all of them, and although the persons by whom they were 
      done were strangers to him, and although they may have taken place before 
      he joined the conspiracy or after he left it.
  
 

Comments  
 
Existence of 
      conspiracy
 
If prima facie evidence 
      of existence of a conspiracy is given and accepted, the evidence of acts 
      and statements made by anyone of the conspirators in furtherance of the 
      common object is admissible against all; Jayendra Saraswati Swamigal 
      v. State of Tamil Nadu, AIR 2005 SC 716.
 
Object
 
Section 10 has been 
      deliberately enacted in order to make acts and statements of a 
      co-conspirator admissible against the whole body of conspirators, because 
      of the nature of crime; Badri Rai v. State of Bihar, AIR 
      1958 SC 953.
 
Significance 
      of “common intention”
 
The words “common intention” 
      signify a common intention existing at the time when the thing was said, 
      done or written by the one of them. It had noting to do with carrying the 
      conspiracy into effect; Mirza Akbar v. Emperor, AIR 1940 PC 
      176.
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> When facts not otherwise relevant become 
      relevant.—Facts not otherwise 
      relevant are relevant— 
 <section><number>1</number>   if they are inconsistent with any 
      fact in issue or relevant fact; 
 </section><section><number>2</number>   if by themselves or in connection 
      with other facts they make the existence or non-existence of any fact in 
      issue or relevant fact highly probable or improbable. 
 
 Illustrations
 <subsection><number>a</number> The question 
        is, whether A committed a crime at Calcutta on a certain 
        day.
 The fact that, 
        on that day, A was at Lahore is relevant.
 The fact that, 
        near the time when the crime was committed, A was at a distance 
        from the place where it was committed, which would render it highly 
        improbable, though not impossible, that he committed it, is 
        relevant.
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The question 
        is, whether A committed a crime.
 The 
        circumstances are such that the crime must have been committed either by 
        A, B, C or D, every fact which shows that the crime could 
        have been committed by no one else and that it was not committed by 
        either B, C or D, is 
    relevant.</subsection>
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number> In suits for damages, facts tending to 
      enable Court to determine amount are relevant.—In suits in which damages are claimed, any fact 
      which will enable the Court to determine the amount of damages which ought 
      to be awarded, is relevant. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number> Facts relevant when right or custom is in 
      question.—Where the question is 
      as to the existence of any right or custom, the following facts are 
      relevant:— 
 <section><number>a</number>    any 
      transaction by which the right or custom in question was created, claimed, 
      modified, recognized, asserted, or denied, or which was inconsistent with 
      its existence; 
 </section><section><number>b</number>    particular 
      instances in which the right or custom was claimed, recognized, or 
      exercised or in which its exercise was disputed, asserted or departed 
from. 
 
 Illustration
 The question is, 
        whether A has a right to a fishery. A deed conferring the 
        fishery on A’s ancestors, a mortgage of the fishery by A’s 
        father, a subsequent grant of the fishery by A’s father, 
        irreconcilable with the mortgage, particular instances in which 
        A’s father exercised the right, or in which the exercise of the 
        right was stopped by A’s neighbours, are relevant 
        facts.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Facts showing existence of state of mind, or 
      of body or bodily feeling.—Facts showing the existence of any state of 
      mind, such as intention, knowledge, good faith, negligence, rashness, 
      ill-will or good-will towards any particular person, or showing the 
      existence of any state of body or bodily feeling, are relevant, when the 
      existence of any such state of mind or body or bodily feeling, is in issue 
      or relevant. 
 1[Explanation 
      1.—A fact 
      relevant as showing the existence of a relevant state of mind must show 
      that the state of mind exists, not generally, but in reference to the 
      particular matter in question.1[Explanation
    1.—A fact 
    relevant as showing the existence of a relevant state of mind must show that 
    the state of mind exists, not generally, but in reference to the particular 
    matter in question." 
 Explanation 2.—But where, upon the trial of a person accused 
      of an offence, the previous commission by the accused of an offence is 
      relevant within the meaning of this section, the previous conviction of 
      such person shall also be a relevant fact.] 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> A is 
        accused of receiving stolen goods knowing them to be stolen. It is 
        proved that he was in possession of a particular stolen 
        article.
 The fact that, 
        at the same time, he was in possession of many other stolen articles is 
        relevant, as tending to show that he knew each and all of the articles 
        of which he was in possession, to be stolen.
 2[(b) A is accused of fraudulently 
        delivering to another person a counterfeit coin which, at the time when 
        he delivered it, he knew to be counterfeit. 
 The fact that, 
        at the time of its delivery, A was possessed of a number of other 
        pieces of counterfeit coin is relevant.
 The fact that 
        A had been previously convicted of delivering to another person 
        as genuine a counterfeit coin knowing it to be counterfeit is 
        relevant.]
 </section><section><number>c</number> A 
        sues B for damage done by a dog of B’s, which 
        B knew to be ferocious.
 The facts that 
        the dog had previously bitten X, Y, and Z, and that they 
        had made complaints to B, are relevant.
 </section><section><number>d</number> The question 
        is, whether A, the acceptor of a bill of exchange, knew that the 
        name of the payee was fictitious.
 The fact that 
        A had accepted other bills drawn in the same manner before they 
        could have been transmitted to him by the payee if the payee had been a 
        real person, is relevant, as showing that A knew that the payee 
        was a fictitious person.
 </section><section><number>e</number> A is 
        accused of defaming B by publishing an imputation intended to 
        harm the reputation of B.
 The fact of 
        previous publications by A respecting B, showing ill-will 
        on the part of A towards B, is relevant, as proving A’s 
        intention to harm B’s reputation by the particular 
        publication in question.
 The facts that 
        there was no previous quarrel between A and B, and that 
        A repeated the matter complained of as he heard it, are relevant, 
        as showing that A did not intend to harm the reputation of 
        B. 
 </section><section><number>f</number> A is 
        sued by B for fraudulently representing to B that C 
        was solvent, whereby B, being induced to trust C, who was 
        insolvent, suffered loss.
 The fact that, 
        at the time when A represented C to be solvent, C 
        was supposed to be solvent by his neighbours and by persons dealing with 
        him, is relevant, as showing that A made the representation in 
        good faith.
 </section><section><number>g</number> A is 
        sued by B for the price of work done by B, upon a house of 
        which A is owner, by the order of C, a contractor. 
        
 A’s 
        defence is that B’s contract was with C.
 The fact that 
        A paid C for the work in question is relevant, as proving 
        that A did, in good faith, make over to C the management 
        of the work in question, so that C was in a position to contract 
        with B on C’s own account, and not as agent for 
        A.
 </section><section><number>h</number> A is 
        accused of the dishonest misappropriation of property which he had 
        found, and the question is whether, when he appropriated it, he believed 
        in good faith that the real owner could not be found.
 The fact that 
        public notice of the loss of the property had been given in the place 
        where A was, is relevant, as showing that A did not in 
        good faith believe that the real owner of the property could not be 
        found.
 The fact that 
        A knew, or had reason to believe, that the notice was given 
        fraudulently by C, who had heard of the loss of the property and 
        wished to set up a false claim to it, is relevant, as showing that the 
        fact that A knew of the notice did not disprove A’s good 
        faith.
 </section><section><number>i</number> A is 
        charged with shooting at B with intent to kill him. In order to 
        show A’s intent, the fact of A’s having previously shot at 
        B may be proved.
 </section><section><number>j</number> A is 
        charged with sending threatening letters to B. Threatening 
        letters previously sent by A to B may be proved, as 
        showing intention of the letters.
 </section><section><number>k</number> The question 
        is, whether A has been guilty of cruelty towards B, his 
        wife.
 Expressions of 
        their feeling towards each other shortly before or after the alleged 
        cruelty, are relevant facts.
 </section><section><number>l</number> The question 
        is, whether A’s death was caused by poison.
 Statements made 
        by A during his illness as to his symptoms, are relevant 
        facts.
 </section><section><number>m</number> The question 
        is, what was the state of A’s health at the time when an 
        assurance on his life was effected.
 Statements made 
        by A as to the state of his health at or near the time in 
        question are relevant facts.
 </section><section><number>n</number> A 
        sues B for negligence in providing him with a carriage for hire 
        not reasonably fit for use, whereby A was injured.
 The fact that 
        B’s attention was drawn on other occasions to the defect of that 
        particular carriage, is relevant.
 The fact that 
        B was habitually negligent about the carriages which he let to hire, 
        is irrelevant.
 </section><section><number>o</number> A is 
        tried for the murder of B by intentionally shooting him 
        dead.
 The fact that 
        A, on other occasions shot at B is relevant, as showing his 
        intention to shoot B.
 The fact that 
        A was in the habit of shooting at people with intent to murder 
        them, is irrelevant.
 </section><section><number>p</number> A is 
        tried for a crime.
 The fact that he 
        said something indicating an intention to commit that particular crime 
        is relevant.
 The fact that he 
        said something indicating a general disposition to commit crimes of that 
        class is irrelevant.</section>
  






 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number> Facts bearing on question whether act was accidental or 
      intentional.—When there is a question whether an act was accidental or 
      intentional, 1[or done with a particular 
      knowledge or intention,] the fact that such act formed part of a series of 
      similar occurrences, in each of which the person doing the act was 
      concerned, is relevant.—When 
    there is a question whether an act was accidental or intentional, 


    1[or done with a 
    particular knowledge or intention,] the fact that such act formed part of a 
    series of similar occurrences, in each of which the person doing the act was 
    concerned, is relevant." 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> A is 
        accused of burning down his house in order to obtain money for which it 
        is insured.
 The facts that 
        A lived in several houses successively, each of which he insured, 
        in each of which a fire occurred, and after each of which fires A 
        received payment from a different insurance office, are relevant, as 
        tending to show that the fires were not accidental.
 </section><section><number>b</number> A is 
        employed to receive money from the debtors of B. It is A’s 
        duty to make entries in a book showing the amounts received by him. He 
        makes an entry showing that on a particular occasion he received less 
        than he really did receive.
 The question is, 
        whether this false entry was accidental or intentional. 
 The facts that 
        other entries made by A in the same book are false, and that the 
        false entry is in each case in favour of A, are 
        relevant.
 </section><section><number>c</number> A is 
        accused of fraudulently delivering to B a counterfeit 
        rupee.
 The question is, 
        whether the delivery of the rupee was accidental.
 The facts that, 
        soon before or soon after the delivery to B, A delivered 
        counterfeit rupees to C, D and E are relevant, as showing 
        that the delivery to B, was not accidental.</section>
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Existence of course of business when relevant.—When 
    there is a question whether a particular act was done, the existence of any 
    course of business, according to which it naturally would have been done, is 
    a relevant fact. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> The question is, whether a 
      particular letter was despatched.
 
The facts that it was the 
      ordinary course of business for all letters put in a certain place to be 
      carried to the post, and that particular letter was put in that place, are 
      relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The question is, whether a 
      particular letter reached A. The facts that it was posted in due 
      course, and was not returned through the Dead Letter Office, are relevant.
</section>
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Admission defined.—An 
    admission is a statement, 

    1[oral or documentary 
    or contained in electronic form], which suggests any inference as to any 
    fact in issue or relevant fact, and which is made by any of the persons, and 
    under the circumstances, hereinafter mentioned.
 
 

Comment s
 

      Admissibility is substantive evidence of the fact
 
Admissibility is substantive 
      evidence of the fact admitted while a previous statement used to 
      contradict a witness does not become substantive evidence and merely 
      serves the purpose of throwing doubt on the veracity of the witness; 
      Bishwanath Prasad v. Dwarka Prasad, AIR 1974 SC 117.
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Admission by party to proceeding or his agent.—Statements 
    made by a party to the proceeding, or by an agent to any such party, whom 
    the Court regards, under the circumstances of the case, as expressly or 
    impliedly authorized by him to make them, are admissions. 
 
by suitor in 
    representative character.—Statements 
    made by parties to suits, suing or sued in a representative character, are 
    not admissions, unless they were made while the party making them held that 
    character. 
 
Statements made 
    by— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    party interested in subject-matter.—persons 
    who have any proprietary or pecuniary interest in the subject-matter of the 
    proceeding, and who make the statement in their character of persons so 
    interested, or 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    person from whom interest derived.—persons 
    from whom the parties to the suit have derived their interest in the 
    subject-matter of the suit,  
 
are admissions, if they are made during the 
    continuance of the interest of the persons making the statements. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Admissions by persons whose position must be proved as against party to 
    suit.—Statements made by persons 
    whose position or liability, it is necessary to prove as against any party 
    to the suit, are admissions, if such statements would be relevant as against 
    such persons in relation to such position or liability in a suit brought by 
    or against them, and if they are made whilst the person making them occupies 
    such position or is subject to such liability. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A undertakes to collect 
      rents for B.
 
B sues A for not 
      collecting rent due from C to B. 
 
A denies that rent was 
      due from C to B.
 
A statement by C 
      that he owed B rent is an admission, and is a relevant fact as 
      against A, if A denies that C did owe rent to B.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Admissions by persons expressly referred to by party to suit.—Statements 
    made by persons to whom a party to the suit has expressly referred for 
    information in reference to a matter in dispute are admissions. 
 
 
Illustration
 
The question is, whether a 
      horse sold by A to B is sound.
 
 A says to B—"Go 
      and ask C. C knows all about it”. C’s statement is an 
      admission.
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
In eviction suit where person 
      having power of attorney for tenant admits arrears of rent tenant 
      subsequently cannot resile from such admission; Ram Sahai v. Jai 
      Prakash, AIR 1993 MP 147. 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Proof of 
    admissions against persons making them, and by or on their behalf.—Admissions 
    are relevant and may be proved as against the person who makes them, or his 
    representative in interest; but they cannot be proved by or on behalf of the 
    person who makes them or by his representative in interest, except in the 
    following cases:— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    An admission may be proved by or on 
    behalf of the person making it, when it is of such a nature that, if the 
    person making it were dead, it would be relevant as between third persons 
    under section 32. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    An admission may be proved by or on 
    behalf of the person making it, when it consists of a statement of the 
    existence of any state of mind or body, relevant or in issue, made at or 
    about the time when such state of mind or body existed, and is accompanied 
    by conduct rendering its falsehood improbable. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    An admission may be proved by or on 
    behalf of the person making it, if it is relevant otherwise than as an 
    admission. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> The question between A 
      and B is, whether a certain deed is or is not forged, A 
      affirms that it is genuine, B that it is forged.
 
A may prove a statement 
      by B that the deed is genuine, and B may prove a statement 
      by A that the deed is forged; but A cannot prove a statement 
      by himself that the deed is genuine, nor can B prove a statement by 
      himself that the deed is forged.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> A, the Captain of a 
      ship, is tried for casting her away.
 
Evidence is given to show that 
      the ship was taken out of her proper course. 
 
A produces a book kept 
      by him in the ordinary course of his business, showing observations 
      alleged to have been taken by him from day to day, and indicating that the 
      ship was not taken out of her proper course. A may prove these 
      statements, because they would be admissible between third parties, if he 
      were dead, under section 32, clause (2).
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> A is accused of a 
      crime committed by him at Calcutta.
 
He produces a letter written 
      by himself and dated at Lahore on that day, and bearing the Lahore 
      post-mark of that day.
 
The statement in the date of 
      the letter is admissible, because, if A were dead, it would be 
      admissible under section 32, clause (2).
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> A is accused of 
      receiving stolen goods knowing them to be stolen.
 
He offers to prove that he 
      refused to sell them below their value.
 
A may prove these 
      statements, though they are admissions, because they are explanatory of 
      conduct influenced by facts in issue.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> A is accused of 
      fraudulently having in his possession counterfeit coin which he knew to be 
      counterfeit.
 
He offers to prove that he 
      asked a skilful person to examine the coin, as he doubted whether it was 
      counterfeit or not, and that the person did examine it and told him it was 
      genuine.
 
A may prove these facts 
      for the reasons stated in the last preceding illustration.
  
 
Comments
 
Submission of a letter not 
      containing anything either in favour or against but simply a statement of 
      original defendant, then such letter cannot be taken as that of a 
      substituted defendant, confronting with admissions; Salil Kumar Roy 
      v. Badu Den Bhansali, AIR 1999 Cal 270. 
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> When 
    oral admissions as to contents of documents are relevant.—Oral 
    admissions as to the contents of a document are not relevant, unless and 
    until the party proposing to prove them shows that he is entitled to give 
    secondary evidence of the contents of such document under the rules 
    hereinafter contained, or unless the genuineness of a document produced is 
    in question. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>22A</number> When oral 
    admissions as to contents of electronic records are relevant.—Oral 
    admissions as to the contents of electronic records are not relevant, unless 
    the genuineness of the electronic record produced is in question.] 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Admissions in civil cases, when relevant.—In 
    civil cases no admission is relevant, if it is made either upon an express 
    condition that evidence of it is not to be given, or under circumstances 
    from which the Court can infer that the parties agreed together that 
    evidence of it should not be given. 
 

    Explanation.—Nothing in this 
    section shall be taken to exempt any barrister, pleader, attorney or 
    vakil from giving evidence of any matter of which he may be compelled to 
    give evidence under section 126. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Confession caused by inducement, threat or promise, when irrelevant in 
    criminal proceeding.—A 
    confession made by an accused person is irrelevant in a criminal proceeding, 
    if the making of the confession appears to the Court to have been caused by 
    any inducement, threat or promise,1 having 
    reference to the charge against the accused person, proceeding from a person 
    in authority and sufficient, in the opinion of the Court, to give the 
    accused person grounds, which would appear to him reasonable, for supposing 
    that by making it he would gain any advantage or avoid any evil of a 
    temporal nature in reference to the proceedings against him.—A 
    confession made by an accused person is irrelevant in a criminal proceeding, 
    if the making of the confession appears to the Court to have been caused by 
    any inducement, threat or promise,2 having 
    reference to the charge against the accused person, proceeding from a person 
    in authority and sufficient, in the opinion of the Court, to give the 
    accused person grounds, which would appear to him reasonable, for supposing 
    that by making it he would gain any advantage or avoid any evil of a 
    temporal nature in reference to the proceedings against him." 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Confession to police officer not to be proved.—No 
    confession made to a police officer1, 
    shall be proved as against a person accused of any offence.—No 
    confession made to a police officer1, 
    shall be proved as against a person accused of any offence." 
 
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Confession by accused while in custody of police not to be proved against 
    him.—No 
    confession made by any person whilst he is in the custody of a police 
    officer, unless it be made in the immediate presence of a Magistrate1, 
    shall be proved as against such person.—No 
    confession made by any person whilst he is in the custody of a police 
    officer, unless it be made in the immediate presence of a Magistrate2, 
    shall be proved as against such person." 
 


    2[Explanation.—In 
    this section “Magistrate” does not include the head of a village discharging 
    magisterial functions in the Presidency of Fort St. George 

    3[***] or elsewhere, 
    unless such headman is a Magistrate exercising the powers of a Magistrate 
    under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1882 (10 of 1882)4]. 
 
 

 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>27</number> How 
    much of information received from accused may be proved.—Provided 
    that, when any fact is deposed to as discovered in consequence of 
    information received from a person accused of any offence, in the custody of 
    a police officer, so much of such information, whether it amounts to a 
    confession or not, as relates distinctly to the fact thereby discovered, may 
    be proved. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Confession made after removal of impression caused by inducement, threat or 
    promise relevant.—If such a 
    confession as is referred to in section 24 is made after the impression 
    caused by any such inducement, threat or promise has, in the opinion of the 
    Court, been fully removed, it is relevant. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Confession otherwise relevant not to become irrelevant because of promise of 
    secrecy, etc.—If such a confession 
    is otherwise relevant, it does not become irrelevant merely because it was 
    made under a promise of secrecy, or in consequence of a deception practised 
    on the accused person for the purpose of obtaining it, or when he was drunk, 
    or because it was made in answer to questions which he need not have 
    answered, whatever may have been the form of those questions, or because he 
    was not warned that he was not bound to make such confession, and that 
    evidence of it might be given against him. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Consideration of proved confession affecting person making it and others 
    jointly under trial for same offence.—When 
    more persons than one are being tried jointly for the same offence, and a 
    confession made by one of such persons affecting himself and some other of 
    such persons is proved, the Court may take into consideration such 
    confession as against such other person as well as against the person who 
    makes such confession. 
 


    1[Explanation.—“Offence”, 
    as used in this section, includes the abetment of, or attempt to commit the 
    offence.] 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A and B are 
      jointly tried for the murder of C. It is proved that A 
      said—"B and I murdered C”. The Court may consider the effect 
      of this confession as against B.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A is on his trial 
      for the murder of C. There is evidence to show that C was 
      murdered by A and B, and that B said—“A and I 
      murdered C”.
 
This statement may not be 
      taken into consideration by the Court against A, as B is not 
      being jointly tried.
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Accused's 
      confession cannot be used against co-accused
 
The statement of the accused 
      leading to the discovery, or the informatory statement amounting to 
      confession of the accused, cannot be used against the co-accused with the 
      aid of section 303; Kamal Kishore v. State (Delhi 
      Administration), (1972) 2 Crimes 169 (Del).
 

 
</section>




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Admissions not conclusive proof, but may estop.—Admissions 
    are not conclusive proof of the matters admitted, but they may operate as 
    estoppels under the provisions hereinafter contained. 
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number> Cases in which statement of relevant fact by person who is dead or cannot be found, etc .,  is relevant. </title>—Statements,
written or verbal, of relevant facts made by a person who is dead, or
who cannot be found, or who has become incapable of giving evidence, or
whose attendance cannot be procured without an amount of delay or
expense which, under the circumstances of the case, appears to the
Court unreasonable, are themselves relevant facts in the following
cases:— 
 <section><title><number>1</number> when it relates to cause of death. </title>—When the
statement is made by a person as to the cause of his death, or as to
any of the circumstances of the transaction which resulted in his
death, in cases in which the cause of that person's death comes into
question. 
 Such statements are relevant whether the person who made them was or
was not, at the time when they were made, under expectation of death,
and whatever may be the nature of the proceeding in which the cause of
his death comes into question. 
 </section><section><title><number>2</number> or is made in course of business. </title>—When the
statement was made by such person in the ordinary course of business,
and in particular when it consists of any entry or memorandum made by
him in books kept in the ordinary course of business, or in the
discharge of professional duty; or of an acknowledgment written or
signed by him of the receipt of money, goods, securities or property of
any kind; or of a document used in commerce written or signed by him;
or of the date of a letter or other document usually dated, written or
signed by him. 
 </section><section><title><number>3</number> or against interest of maker. </title>—When the
statement is against the pecuniary or proprietary interest of the
person making it, or when, if true, it would expose him or would have
exposed him to a criminal prosecution or to a suit for damages. 
 </section><section><title><number>4</number> or gives opinion as to public right or custom, or matters of general interest. </title>—When
the statement gives the opinion of any such person, as to the existence
of any public right or custom or matter of public or general interest,
of the existence of which, if it existed he would have been likely to
be aware, and when such statement was made before any controversy as to
such right, custom or matter had arisen. 
 </section><section><title><number>5</number> or relates to existence of relationship. </title>—When the statement relates to the existence of any relationship <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[by blood, marriage or adoption] between persons as to whose relationship <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[by
blood, marriage or adoption] the person making the statement had
special means of knowledge, and when the statement was made before the
question in dispute was raised. 
 </section><section><title><number>6</number> or is made in will or deed relating to family affairs. </title>—When the statement relates to the existence of any relationship <footcitenum>25</footcitenum>[by
blood, marriage or adoption] between persons deceased, and is made in
any will or deed relating to the affairs of the family to which any
such deceased person belonged, or in any family pedigree, or upon any
tombstone, family portrait, or other thing on which such statements are
usually made, and when such statement was made before the question in
dispute was raised. 
 </section><section><title><number>7</number> or in document relating to transaction mentioned in section 13, clause (a). </title>—When
the statement is contained in any deed, will or other document which
relates to any such transaction as is mentioned in section 13,
clause (a). 
 </section><section><title><number>8</number> or is made by several persons, and expresses feelings relevant to matter in question. </title>—When
the statement was made by a number of persons, and expressed feelings
or impressions on their part relevant to the matter in question. 
 Illustrations 
 <subsection><number>a</number> The question is, whether A  was murdered by B ; or 
 A  dies of injuries received in a transaction in the course
of which she was ravished. The question is, whether she was ravished by
B;  or 
 The question is, whether A  was killed by B  under such circumstances that a suit would lie against B  by A's  widow. 
 Statements made by A  as to the cause of his or her death,
referring respectively to the murder, the rape, and the actionable
wrong under consideration, are relevant facts. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> The question is as to the date of A's  birth. An entry
in the diary of a deceased surgeon, regularly kept in the course of
business, stating that, on a given day he attended A's  mother and delivered her of a son, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> The question is, whether A  was in Calcutta on a given
day. A statement in the diary of a deceased solicitor, regularly kept
in the course of business, that, on a given day, the solicitor attended
A  at a place mentioned, in Calcutta , for the purpose of conferring with him upon specified business, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> The question is, whether a ship sailed from Bombay harbour on a
given day. A letter written by a deceased member of a merchant's firm,
by which she was chartered, to their correspondents in London to whom
the cargo was consigned, stating that the ship sailed on a given day
from Bombay harbour, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> The question is, whether rent was paid to A  for certain land. A letter from A's  deceased agent to A,  saying that he had received the rent on A's  account and held it at A's  orders, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> The question is, whether A  and B  were
legally married. The statement of a deceased clergyman that he married
them under such circumstances that the celebration would be a crime, is
relevant. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> The question is, whether A,  a person who cannot be
found, wrote a letter on a certain day. The fact that a letter written
by him is dated on that day, is relevant. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> The question is, what was the cause of the wreck of a ship. A
protest made by the Captain, whose attendance cannot be procured, is a
relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> The question is, whether a given road is a public way. A statement by A,  a deceased headman of the village, that the road was public, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> The question is, what was the price of grain on a certain day in
a particular market. A statement of the price, made by a deceased banya  in the ordinary course of his business is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> The question is, whether A,  who is dead, was the father of B. A statement by A  that B  was his son, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> The question is, what was the date of the birth of A. A letter from A's  deceased father to a friend, announcing the birth of A  on a given day, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> The question is, whether, and when, A  and B  were married. An entry in a memorandum-book by C,  the deceased father of B,  of his daughter's marriage with A  on a given date, is a relevant fact. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> A  sues B  for a libel expressed in a painted
caricature exposed in a shop window. The question is as to the
similarity of the caricature and its libellous character. The remarks
of a crowd of spectators on these points may be proved. 





















</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Relevancy of certain evidence for proving, in subsequent proceeding, the 
    truth of facts therein stated.—Evidence 
    given by a witness in a judicial proceeding, or before any person authorized 
    by law to take it, is relevant for the purpose of proving, in a subsequent 
    judicial proceeding, or in a later stage of the same judicial proceeding, 
    the truth of the facts which it states, when the witness is dead or cannot 
    be found, or is incapable of giving evidence, or is kept out of the way by 
    the adverse party, or if his presence cannot be obtained without an amount 
    of delay or expense which, under the circumstances of the case, the Court 
    considers unreasonable: 
 
Provided— 
 
that the proceeding was between the same 
    parties or their representatives in interest; 
 
that the adverse party in the first proceeding 
    had the right and opportunity to cross-examine; 
 
that the questions in issue were substantially 
    the same in the first as in the second proceeding. 
 
Explanation.—A 
    criminal trial or inquiry shall be deemed to be a proceeding between the 
    prosecutor and the accused within the meaning of this section. 
  
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number>
    

    1[Entries in books of 
    account including those maintained in an electronic form] when relevant.—1[Entries
in books of accounts 
    including those maintained in an electronic form], regularly kept in the 
    course of business, are relevant whenever they refer to a matter into which 
    the Court has to inquire, but such statements shall not alone be sufficient 
    evidence to charge any person with liability. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A sues B for Rs. 
      1,000, and shows entries in his account-books showing B to be 
      indebted to him to this amount. The entries are relevant, but are not 
      sufficient, without other evidence, to prove the debt.
 
COMMENTS 
 

      Admissibility
 
Entries in account books 
      regularly kept in the course of business are admissible though they by 
      themselves cannot create any liability; Ishwar Dass v. Sohan Lal, 
      AIR 2000 SC 426. 
 
Unbound sheets of paper are 
      not books of account and cannot be relied upon; Dharam Chand Joshi 
      v. Satya Narayan Bazaz, AIR 1993 Gau 35. 
 
Books of account being only 
      corroborative evidence must be supported by other evidence; Dharam
Chand Joshi v. Satya Narayan Bazaz, AIR 1993 Gau 35. 

 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Relevancy of entry in public 

    1[record or an 
    electronic record] made in performance of duty.—An 
    entry in any public or other official book, register or 

    1[record or an 
    electronic record], stating a fact in issue or relevant fact, and made by a 
    public servant in the discharge of his official duty, or by any other person 
    in performance of a duty specially enjoined by the law of the country in 
    which such book, register, or 

    1[record or an 
    electronic record] is kept, is itself a relevant fact. 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Relevancy of statements in maps, charts and plans.—Statements 
    of facts in issue or relevant facts, made in published maps or charts 
    generally offered for public sale, or in maps or plans made under the 
    authority of 

    1[the Central 
    Government or any State Government], as to matters usually represented or 
    stated in such maps, charts or plans, are themselves relevant facts.—Statements 
    of facts in issue or relevant facts, made in published maps or charts 
    generally offered for public sale, or in maps or plans made under the 
    authority of 

    2[the Central 
    Government or any State Government], as to matters usually represented or 
    stated in such maps, charts or plans, are themselves relevant facts." 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>37</number> Relevancy of statement as to fact of public nature, contained 
      in certain Acts or notifications.—When the Court has to form an 
      opinion as to the existence of any fact of a public nature, any statement 
      of it, made in a recital contained in any Act of Parliament 
      1[of the United Kingdom], or in any 
      2[Central Act, Provincial Act, or 
      3[a State Act], or in a Government 
      notification or notification by the Crown Representative appearing in the 
      Official Gazette or in any printed paper purporting to be the London 
      Gazette or the Government Gazette of any Dominion, colony or possession of 
      His Majesty is a relevant fact.]—When 
    the Court has to form an opinion as to the existence of any fact of a public 
    nature, any statement of it, made in a recital contained in any Act of 
    Parliament 

    3[of the United 
    Kingdom], or in any 

    4[Central Act, 
    Provincial Act, or 

    5[a State Act], or in a 
    Government notification or notification by the Crown Representative 
    appearing in the Official Gazette or in any printed paper purporting to be 
    the London Gazette or the Government Gazette of any Dominion, colony or 
    possession of His Majesty is a relevant fact.]" 
 4[***] 
  
  







 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Relevancy of statements as to any law contained in law-books.—When 
    the Court has to form an opinion as to a law of any country, any statement 
    of such law contained in a book purporting to be printed or published under 
    the authority of the Government of such country and to contain any such law, 
    and any report of a ruling of the Courts of such country contained in a book 
    purporting to be a report of such rulings, is relevant. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>39</number> What evidence 
    to be given when statement forms part of a conversation, document, 
    electronic record, book or series of letters or papers.—When 
    any statement of which evidence is given forms part of a longer statement, 
    or of a conversation or part of an isolated document, or is contained in a 
    document which forms part of a book, or is contained in part of electronic 
    record or of a connected series of letters or papers, evidence shall be 
    given of so much and no more of the statement, conversation, document, 
    electronic record, book or series of letters or papers as the Court 
    considers necessary in that particular case to the full understanding of the 
    nature and effect of the statement, and of the circumstances under which it 
    was made.]2[39. 
    What evidence to be given when statement forms part of a conversation, 
    document, electronic record, book or series of letters or papers.—When 
    any statement of which evidence is given forms part of a longer statement, 
    or of a conversation or part of an isolated document, or is contained in a 
    document which forms part of a book, or is contained in part of electronic 
    record or of a connected series of letters or papers, evidence shall be 
    given of so much and no more of the statement, conversation, document, 
    electronic record, book or series of letters or papers as the Court 
    considers necessary in that particular case to the full understanding of the 
    nature and effect of the statement, and of the circumstances under which it 
    was made.]" 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Previous 
    judgments relevant to bar a second suit or trial.—The 
    existence of any judgment, order or decree which by law prevents any Courts 
    from taking cognizance of a suit or holding a trial is a relevant fact when 
    the question is whether such Court ought to take cognizance of such suit, or 
    to hold such trial. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Relevancy of certain judgments in probate, etc., jurisdiction.—A 
    final judgment, order or decree of a competent Court, in the exercise of 
    probate, matrimonial admiralty or insolvency jurisdiction which confers upon 
    or takes away from any person any legal character, or which declares any 
    person to be entitled to any such character, or to be entitled to any 
    specific thing, not as against any specified person but absolutely, is 
    relevant when the existence of any such legal character, or the title of any 
    such person to any such thing, is relevant. 
 
Such judgment, 
    order or decree is conclusive proof— 
 
that any legal character, which it confers 
    accrued at the time when such judgment, order or decree came into operation; 
 
that any legal character, to which it 
    declares any such person to be entitled, accrued to that person at the time 
    when such judgment, 
1[order 
    or decree] declares it to have accrued to that person;
3[order 
    or decree] declares it to have accrued to that person;" 
 
that any legal character which it takes 
    away from any such person ceased at the time from which such judgment,
    1[order 
    or decree] declared that it had ceased or should cease;  
   
3[order 
    or decree] declared that it had ceased or should cease; " 
 
and that anything to which it declares 
    any person to be so entitled was the property of that person at the time 
    from which such judgment, 
1[order 
    or decree] declares that it had been or should be his property.
3[order 
    or decree] declares that it had been or should be his property." 
 
 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> 
    Relevancy and effect of judgments, orders or decrees, other than those 
    mentioned in section 41.—Judgments, 
    orders or decrees other than those mentioned in section 41, are relevant if 
    they relate to matters of a public nature relevant to the enquiry; but such 
    judgments, orders or decrees are not conclusive proof of that which they 
    state. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A sues B for trespass on his 
      land. B alleges the existence of a public right of way over the 
      land, which A denies.
 
The existence of a decree in favour of the 
      defendant, in a suit by A against C for a trespass on the 
      same land in which C alleged the existence of the same right of 
      way, is relevant, but it is not conclusive proof that the right of way 
      exists.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Judgments, etc., other than those mentioned in sections 40 to 42, 
    when relevant.—Judgments, orders 
    or decrees, other than those mentioned in sections 40, 41 and 42, are 
    irrelevant, unless the existence of such judgment, order or decree, is a 
    fact in issue, or is relevant under some other provisions of this Act.
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A and B 
      separately sue C for a libel which reflects upon each of them. C
      in each case says, that the matter alleged to be libellous is true, 
      and the circumstances are such that it is probably true in each case, or 
      in neither.
 
A obtains a decree 
      against C for damages on the ground that C failed to make 
      out his justification. The fact is irrelevant as between B and C.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A prosecutes B 
      for adultery with C, A's wife.
 
B denies that C 
      is A's wife, but the court convicts B of adultery.
 
Afterwards, C is 
      prosecuted for bigamy in marrying B during A's lifetime. 
      C says that she never was A's wife.
 
The judgment against B 
      is irrelevant as against C.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A prosecutes B 
      for stealing a cow from him, B, is convicted.
 
A afterwards sues C 
      for the cow, which B had sold to him before his conviction. As 
      between A and C, the judgment against B is 
      irrelevant.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A has obtained a 
      decree for the possession of land against B, C, B's son, murders 
      A in consequence.
 
The existence of the judgment 
      is relevant, as showing motive for a crime.
 

1[(e)
      A is charged with theft and with having been previously convicted 
      of theft. The previous conviction is relevant as a fact in issue.
 </section><section>
<number>f</number> A is tried for the 
      murder of B. The fact that B prosecuted A for libel 
      and that A was convicted and sentenced is relevant under section 8 
      as showing the motive for the fact in issue.]
 

 

-----------------------
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>   Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, 
      sec. 5. 
 

</subsection></section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Fraud or 
    collusion in obtaining judgment, or incompetency of Court, may be proved.—Any 
    party to a suit or other proceeding may show that any judgment, order or 
    decree which is relevant under section 40, 41 or 42 and which has been 
    proved by the adverse party, was delivered by a Court not competent to 
    deliver it, or was obtained by fraud or collusion. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> 
    Opinions of experts.—When 
    the Court has to form an opinion upon a point of foreign law or of science 
    or art, or as to identity of handwriting <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[or finger 
    impressions], the opinions upon that point of persons specially skilled in 
    such foreign law, science or art,
<footcitenum>36</footcitenum>[or in questions as to 
    identity of handwriting] <footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[or finger 
    impressions] are relevant facts.
 
Such persons 
    are called experts.
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> The question is, whether 
      the death of A was caused by poison.
 
The opinions of experts as to 
      the symptoms produced by the poison by which A is supposed to have 
      died are relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The question is, whether
      A, at the time of doing a certain act, was, by reason of 
      unsoundness of mind, incapable of knowing the nature of the Act, or that 
      he was doing what was either wrong or contrary to law.
 
The opinions of experts upon 
      the question whether the symptoms exhibited by A commonly show 
      unsoundness of mind, and whether such unsoundness of mind usually renders 
      persons incapable of knowing the nature of the acts which they do, or of 
      knowing that what they do is either wrong or contrary to law, are 
      relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The question is, whether a 
      certain document was written by A. Another document is produced 
      which is proved or admitted to have been written by A.
 
The opinions of experts on the 
      question whether the two documents were written by the same person or by 
      different persons, are relevant.
 

Comments
 
Conflict of 
      opinion of Experts
 
When there is a conflict of 
      opinion between the experts, then the Court is competent to form its own 
      opinion with regard to signatures on a document; Kishan Chand v. 
      Sita Ram, AIR 2005 P&amp;H 156. 
 
Expert 
      opinion admissibility
 
Requirement of expert evidence 
      about test firing to find out whether double barrel gun is in working 
      condition or not, not necessary; Jarnail Singh v. State of 
      Punjab, AIR 1999 SC 321. 
 
The evidence of a doctor 
      conducting post mortem without producing any authority in support 
      of his opinion is insufficient to grant conviction to an accused; Mohd 
      Zahid v. State of Tamil Nadu, 1999 Cr LJ 3699 (SC). 
 
Opinion to 
      be received with great caution
 
The opinion of a handwriting 
      expert given in evidence is no less fallible than any other expert opinion 
      adduced in evidence with the result that such evidence has to be received 
      with great caution; Ram Narain v. State of Uttar Pradesh, 
      AIR 1973 SC 2200. 
 

 
</section>





 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>37</footcitenum></title><title>[<number>45A</number> Opinion of Examiner of Electronic 
Evidence. </title>—When in a proceeding, the court has to form an opinion on 
any matter relating to any information transmitted or stored in any computer 
resource or any other electronic or digital form, the opinion of the Examiner of 
Electronic Evidence referred to in section 79A of the Information Technology 
Act, 2000 (21 of 2000) is a relevant fact. 
 Explanation .—For the purposes of this section, an Examiner of 
Electronic Evidence shall be an expert;] 
 <title>Illustrations </title>
 <section><number>a</number> The question is, whether the death of A was caused by poison. 

 The opinions of experts as to the symptoms produced by the poison by which 
A is supposed to have died are relevant. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> The question is, whether A, at the time of doing a certain act, 
was, by reason of unsoundness of mind, incapable of knowing the nature of the 
Act, or that he was doing what was either wrong or contrary to law. 
 The opinions of experts upon the question whether the symptoms exhibited by 
A commonly show unsoundness of mind, and whether such unsoundness of 
mind usually renders persons incapable of knowing the nature of the acts which 
they do, or of knowing that what they do is either wrong or contrary to law, are 
relevant. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> The question is, whether a certain document was written by A. 
Another document is produced which is proved or admitted to have been 
written by A. 
 The opinions of experts on the question whether the two documents were 
written by the same person or by different persons, are relevant. 










</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>46</number> Facts bearing upon opinions of 
      experts.—Facts not otherwise 
      relevant, are relevant if they support or are inconsistent with the 
      opinions of experts, when such opinions are relevant. 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> The question 
        is, whether A was poisoned by a certain poison.
 The fact that 
        other persons, who were poisoned by that person, exhibited certain 
        symptoms which experts affirm or deny to be the symptoms of that poison, 
        is relevant.
 </section><section><number>b</number> The question 
        is, whether an obstruction to a harbour is caused by a certain 
        sea-wall.
 The fact that 
        other harbours similarly situated in other respects, but where there 
        were no such sea-walls, began to be obstructed at about the same time, 
        is relevant.
 COMMENTS tc 
      "COMMENTS" 
 Admissibility
 The science of 
        identification of footprints is not a fully developed science and 
        therefore if in a given case, evidence relating to the same is found 
        satisfactory it may be used only to reinforce the conclusions as to the 
        identity of a culprit already arrived at on the basis of other evidence; 
        Mohd. Aman v. State of Rajasthan, (1997) 4 Supreme 
        635. </section>
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Opinion 
    as to handwriting, when relevant.—When 
    the Court has to form an opinion as to the person by whom any document was 
    written or signed, the opinion of any person acquainted with the handwriting 
    of the person by whom it is supposed to be written or signed that it was or 
    was not written or signed by that person, is a relevant fact. 
 
Explanation.—A 
    person is said to be acquainted with the handwriting of another person when 
    he has seen that person write, or when he has received documents purporting 
    to be written by that person in answer to documents written by himself or 
    under his authority and addressed to that person, or when, in the ordinary 
    course of business, documents purporting to be written by that person have 
    been habitually submitted to him. 
 
 
Illustration
 
The question is, whether a 
      given letter is in the underwriting of A, a merchant in London.
 
B is a merchant in 
      Calcutta, who has written letters addressed to A and received 
      letters purporting to be written by him. C is B's clerk, 
      whose duty it was to examine and file B's correspondence. D 
      is B's broker, to whom B habitually submitted the letters 
      purporting to be written by A for the purpose of advising him 
      thereon. 
 
The opinions of B, C 
      and D on the question whether the letter is in the handwriting of
      A are relevant, though neither B, C nor D ever saw 
      A write.


 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[<number>47A</number> Opinion as to 
</title><title><footcitenum>38</footcitenum>[electronic signature] when relevant 
</title>.—When the Court has to form an opinion as to the 
<footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[electronic signature] of any person, the opinion of the Certifying 
Authority which has issued the <footcitenum>40</footcitenum>[Electronic Signature Certificate] is 
a relevant fact.] 
  



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> Opinion 
    as to existence of right or custom, when relevant.—When 
    the Court has to form an opinion as to the existence of any general custom 
    or right, the opinions, as to the existence of such custom or right, of 
    persons who would be likely to know of its existence if it existed, are 
    relevant. 
 

    Explanation.—The expression 
    “general custom or right” includes customs or rights common to any 
    considerable class of persons. 
 
 
Illustration
 
The right of the villagers of 
      a particular village to use the water of a particular well is a general 
      right within the meaning of this section.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Opinions 
    as to usages, tenets, etc., when relevant.—When 
    the Court has to form an opinion as to— 
 
the usages and 
    tenets of any body of men or family,  
 
the 
    constitution and government of any religious or charitable foundation, or
     
 
the meaning of 
    words or terms used in particular districts or by particular classes of 
    people, 
 
the opinions of 
    persons having special means of knowledge thereon, are relevant facts. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Opinion 
    on relationship, when relevant.—When 
    the Court has to form an opinion as to the relationship of one person to 
    another, the opinion, expressed by conduct, as to the existence of such 
    relationship, or any person who, as a member of the family or otherwise, has 
    special means of knowledge on the subject, is a relevant fact: 
 
Provided that 
    such opinion shall not be sufficient to prove a marriage in proceedings 
    under the Indian Divorce Act, 1869 (4 of 1869) or in prosecutions under 
    section 494, 495, 497 or 498 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> The question is, whether
      A and B were married.
 
The fact that they were 
      usually received and treated by their friends as husband and wife, is 
      relevant.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> The question is, whether
      A was the legitimate son of B. The fact that A was 
      always treated as such by members of the family, is relevant.
  
 

Comments 
 
Contradiction in evidence of 
      relationship of witness of triffle nature, not material in a partition 
      suit; Gowhari Das v. Santilata Singh, AIR 1999 Ori 61. 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Grounds 
    of opinion, when relevant.—Whenever 
    the opinion of any living person is relevant, the grounds on which such 
    opinion is based are also relevant. 
 
 
Illustration
 
An expert may give an account 
      of experiments performed by him for the purpose of forming his opinion.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>52</number> In civil cases character to prove conduct 
      imputed, irrelevant.—In civil 
      cases, the fact that the character of any person concerned is such as to 
      render probable or improbable any conduct imputed to him, is irrelevant, 
      except in so far as such character appears from facts otherwise 
      relevant. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>53</number> In criminal cases, previous good character 
      relevant.—In criminal 
      proceedings, the fact that the person accused is of a good character, is 
      relevant. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>1[<number>54</number> Previous bad character not 
      relevant, except in reply.—In criminal proceedings the fact that the 
      accused person has a bad character is irrelevant, unless evidence has been 
      given that he has a good character, in which case it becomes 
      relevant. 
 Explanation 1.—This section does not apply to cases in which 
      the bad character of any person is itself a fact in issue. 
 Explanation 2.—A previous conviction is relevant as evidence 
      of bad character.] 
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>55</number> Character as affecting 
      damages.—In civil cases, the 
      fact that the character of any person is such as to affect the amount of 
      damages which he ought to receive, is relevant. 
 Explanation.—In sections 52, 53, 54 and 55, the 
      word “character” includes both reputation and disposition; but 
      1[except as provided in section 54], 
      evidence may be given only of general reputation and general disposition, 
      and not of particular acts by which reputation or disposition were 
      shown.In 
    sections 52, 53, 54 and 55, the word “character” includes both reputation 
    and disposition; but 

    2[except as provided in 
    section 54], evidence may be given only of general reputation and general 
    disposition, and not of particular acts by which reputation or disposition 
    were shown." 
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>56</number> Fact judicially noticeable need not be 
      proved.—No fact of which the 
      Court will take judicial notice need to be proved. 
 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>57</number> Facts of which Court must take judicial 
      notice.—The Court shall take 
      judicial notice of the following facts:—
 1[
<section><number>1</number>    All laws in force in the territory of 
      India;]
 </section><section><number>2</number>    All public 
      Acts passed or hereafter to be passed by Parliament 2[of the United    Kingdom], and all local and personal 
      Acts directed by Parliament 2[of the United Kingdom] to be judicially noticed;
 </section><section><number>3</number>    Articles of 
      War for 3[the Indian] Army, 4[Navy or Air Force]; 
 5[(4)    The course of proceeding of Parliament of the 
      United Kingdom, of the Constituent Assembly of India, of Parliament and of 
      the legislatures established under any law for the time being in force in 
      a Province or in the State;]
 </section><section><number>5</number>    The accession and 
      the sign manual of the Sovereign for the time being of the United Kingdom 
      of Great Britain and Ireland;
 </section><section><number>6</number>    All seals 
      of which English Courts take judicial notice: the seals of all the 
      6[Courts in 7[India]], and all Courts out of 5[India] established by the authority of 8[the Central Government or the Crown Representative]: the seals of 
      Courts of Admiralty and Maritime Jurisdiction and of Notaries Public, and 
      all seals which any person is authorized to use by 9[the Constitution or an Act of Parliament of the 
      United Kingdom or an] Act or Regulation having the force of law in 
      7[India];
 </section><section><number>7</number>    The 
      accession to office, names, titles, functions, and signatures of the 
      persons filling for the time being any public office in any State, if the 
      fact of their appointment to such office is notified in 10[any Official Gazette];
 </section><section><number>8</number>    The 
      existence, title and national flag of every State or Sovereign recognized 
      by 11[the Government of India];
 </section><section><number>9</number>    The divisions of 
      time, the geographical divisions of the world, and public festivals, fasts 
      and holidays notified in the Official Gazette;
 </section><section><number>10</number>    The 
      territories under the dominion of 11[the Government of India];
 </section><section><number>11</number>    The 
      commencement, continuance, and termination of hostilities between 
      11[the Government of India] and any other State or body of 
      persons;
 </section><section><number>12</number>    The names of the 
      members and officers of the Court and of their deputies and subordinate 
      officers and assistants, and also of all officers acting in execution of 
      its process, and of all advocates, attorneys, proctors, vakils, pleaders 
      and other persons authorized by law to appear or act before 
      it;
 </section><section><number>13</number>    The 
      rule of the road, 12[on land or at sea].
 In 
      all these cases, and also on all matters of public history, literature, 
      science or art, the Court may resort for its aid to appropriate books or 
      documents of reference.
 If 
      the Court is called upon by any person to take judicial notice of any 
      fact, it may refuse to do so, unless and until such person produces any 
      such book or document as it may consider necessary to enable it to do 
      so.
 
  















 
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>58</number> Facts admitted need not be 
proved. </title>—No fact need to be proved in any proceeding which the parties 
thereto or their agents agree to admit at the hearing, or which, before the 
hearing, they agree to admit by any writing under their hands, or which by any 
rule of pleading in force at the time they are deemed to have admitted by their 
pleadings: 
 Provided that the Court may, in its discretion, require the 
facts admitted to be proved otherwise than by such admissions. 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>59</number> Proof of facts by oral evidence.—All facts, except the 
      1[contents of documents or 
      electronic records], may be proved by oral evidence.—All 
    facts, except the 

    1[contents of documents 
    or electronic records], may be proved by oral evidence." 
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> Oral 
    evidence must be direct.—Oral 
    evidence must, in all cases whatever, be direct; that is to say— 
 
If it refers to a fact which could be seen, it 
    must be the evidence of a witness who says he saw it; 
 
If it refers to a fact which could be heard, 
    it must be the evidence of a witness who says he heard it;  
    
 
If it refers to a fact which could be 
    perceived by any other sense or in any other manner, it must be the evidence 
    of a witness who says he perceived it by that sense or in that manner; 
 
If it refers to an opinion or to the grounds 
    on which that opinion is held, it must be the evidence of the person who 
    holds that opinion on those grounds: 
 
Provided that 
    the opinions of experts expressed in any treatise commonly offered for sale, 
    and the grounds on which such opinions are held, may be proved by the 
    production of such treatises if the author is dead or cannot be found, or 
    has become incapable of giving evidence, or cannot be called as a witness 
    without an amount of delay or expense which the Court regards as 
    unreasonable: 
 
Provided also 
    that, if oral evidence refers to the existence or condition of any material 
    thing other than a document, the Court may, if it thinks fit, require the 
    production of such material thing for its inspection.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> Proof of 
    contents of documents.—The 
    contents of documents may be proved either by primary or by secondary 
    evidence. 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> Primary 
    evidence.—Primary evidence means 
    the document itself produced for the inspection of the Court. 
 
Explanation
    1.—Where a document is executed in 
    several parts, each part is primary evidence of the document; 
 
Where a 
    document is executed in counterpart, each counterpart being executed by one 
    or some of the parties only, each counterpart is primary evidence as against 
    the parties executing it. 
 
Explanation
    2.—Where a number of documents are 
    all made by one uniform process, as in the case of printing, lithography, or 
    photography, each is primary evidence of the contents of the rest; but, 
    where they are all copies of a common original, they are not primary 
    evidence of the contents of the original. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A person is shown to have been 
      in possession of a number of placards, all printed at one time from one 
      original. Any one of the placards is primary evidence of the contents of 
      any other, but no one of them is primary evidence of the contents of the 
      original.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
    Secondary evidence.—Secondary 
    evidence means and includes— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    Certified copies given under the 
    provisions hereinafter contained1;1;" 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    Copies made from the original by 
    mechanical processes which in themselves insure the accuracy of the copy, 
    and copies compared with such copies; 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    Copies made from or compared with the 
    original; 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    Counterparts of documents as against 
    the parties who did not execute them; 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>    Oral accounts of the contents of a 
    document given by some person who has himself seen it. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> A photograph of an 
      original is secondary evidence of its contents, though the two have not 
      been compared, if it is proved that the thing photographed was the 
      original.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> A copy compared with a 
      copy of a letter made by a copying machine is secondary evidence of the 
      contents of the letter, if it is shown that the copy made by the copying 
      machine was made from the original.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> A copy transcribed from a 
      copy, but afterwards compared with the original, is secondary evidence; 
      but the copy not so compared is not secondary evidence of the original, 
      although the copy from which it was transcribed was compared with the 
      original.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> Neither an oral account of 
      a copy compared with the original, nor an oral account of a photograph or 
      machine-copy of the original, is secondary evidence of the original.
 
COMMENTS 
 

      Admissibility
 
Application moved for 
      permission to lead secondary evidence based on ground of loss of document. 
      Presence of document proved from the facts pleaded - Allowing secondary 
      evidence not illegal; Sobha Rani v. Ravikumar, AIR 1999 P&amp;H 
      21. 
 
Tape-recorded statements are 
      admissible in evidence; K.S. Mohan v. Sandhya Mohan, AIR 
      1993 Mad 59. 
 
Certified copies of money 
      lender’s licences are admissible in evidence;  
      K. Shivalingaiah v. B.V. Chandrashekara Gowda, AIR 1993 Kant 
      29. 
</subsection>
 

 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> Proof of 
    documents by primary evidence.—Documents 
    must be proved by primary evidence except in the cases hereinafter 
    mentioned. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> Cases in 
    which secondary evidence relating to documents may be given.—Secondary 
    evidence may be given of the existence, condition, or contents of a document 
    in the following cases:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    When the original is shown or appears 
    to be in the possession or power— 
 
of the person against whom the document is 
    sought to be proved, or 
 
of any person out of reach of, or not subject 
    to, the process of the Court, or 
 
of any person legally bound to produce it, 
 
and when, after the notice mentioned in 
    section 66, such person does not produce it;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    when the existence, condition or 
    contents of the original have been proved to be admitted in writing by the 
    person against whom it is proved or by his representative in interest; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    when the original has been destroyed or 
    lost, or when the party offering evidence of its contents cannot, for any 
    other reason not arising from his own default or neglect, produce it in 
    reasonable time; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    when the original is of such a nature 
    as not to be easily movable; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    when the original is a public document 
    within the meaning of section 74;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    when the original is a document 
    of which a certified copy is permitted by this Act, or by any other law in 
    force in 
1[India] 
    to be given in evidence2;
1[India] 
    to be given in evidence2;" 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    when the originals consists of numerous 
    accounts or other documents which cannot conveniently be examined in Court, 
    and the fact to be proved is the general result of the whole collection. 
 
In cases (a), 
    (c) and (d), any secondary evidence of the contents of the document is 
    admissible. 
 
In case (b), 
    the written admission is admissible. 
 
In case (e) or 
    (f), a certified copy of the document, but no other kind of secondary 
    evidence, is admissible. 
 
In case (g), 
    evidence may be given as to the general result of the documents by any 
    person who has examined them, and who is skilled in the examination of such 
    documents. 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>65A</number> Special 
    provisions as to evidence relating to electronic record.—The 
    contents of electronic records may be proved in accordance with the 
    provisions of section 65B.]
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>65B</number> 
    Admissibility of electronic records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, any information contained in 
    an electronic record which is printed on a paper, stored, recorded or copied 
    in optical or magnetic media produced by a computer (hereinafter referred to 
    as the computer output) shall be deemed to be also a document, if the 
    conditions mentioned in this section are satisfied in relation to the 
    information and computer in question and shall be admissible in any 
    proceedings, without further proof or production of the original, as 
    evidence of any contents of the original or of any fact stated therein of 
    which direct evidence would be admissible. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    conditions referred to in sub-section (1) in respect of a computer output 
    shall be the following, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the computer output containing the 
    information was produced by the computer during the period over which the 
    computer was used regularly to store or process information for the purposes 
    of any activities regularly carried on over that period by the person having 
    lawful control over the use of the computer; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    during the said period, information of 
    the kind contained in the electronic record or of the kind from which the 
    information so contained is derived was regularly fed into the computer in 
    the ordinary course of the said activities; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    throughout the material part of the 
    said period, the computer was operating properly or, if not, then in respect 
    of any period in which it was not operating properly or was out of operation 
    during that part of the period, was not such as to affect the electronic 
    record or the accuracy of its contents; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the information contained in the 
    electronic record reproduces or is derived from such information fed into 
    the computer in the ordinary course of the said activities. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where over 
    any period, the function of storing or processing information for the 
    purposes of any activities regularly carried on over that period as 
    mentioned in clause (a) of sub-section (2) was regularly performed by 
    computers, whether— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    by a combination of computers operating 
    over that period; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    by different computers operating in 
    succession over that period; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    by different combinations of computers 
    operating in succession over that period; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    in any other manner involving the 
    successive operation over that period, in whatever order, of one or more 
    computers and one or more combinations of computers, 
 
all the computers used for that purpose during 
    that period shall be treated for the purposes of this section as 
    constituting a single computer; and references in this section to a computer 
    shall be construed accordingly. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> In any 
    proceedings where it is desired to give a statement in evidence by virtue of 
    this section, a certificate doing any of the following things, that is to 
    say,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    identifying the electronic record 
    containing the statement and describing the manner in which it was produced; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    giving such particulars of any device 
    involved in the production of that electronic record as may be appropriate 
    for the purpose of showing that the electronic record was produced by a 
    computer; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    dealing with any of the matters to 
    which the conditions mentioned in sub-section (2) relate, 
 
and purporting to be signed by a person 
    occupying a responsible official position in relation to the operation of 
    the relevant device or the management of the relevant activities (whichever 
    is appropriate) shall be evidence of any matter stated in the certificate; 
    and for the purposes of this sub-section it shall be sufficient for a matter 
    to be stated to the best of the knowledge and belief of the person stating 
    it. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> For the 
    purposes of this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    infomation shall be taken to be 
    supplied to a computer if it is supplied thereto in any appropriate form and 
    whether it is so supplied directly or (with or without human intervention) 
    by means of any appropriate equipment; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    whether in the course of activities 
    carried on by any official information is supplied with a view to its being 
    stored or processed for the purposes of those activities by a computer 
    operated otherwise than in the course of those activities, that information, 
    if duly supplied to that computer, shall be taken to be supplied to it in 
    the course of those activities; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a computer output shall be taken to 
    have been produced by a computer whether it was produced by it directly or 
    (with or without human intervention) by means of any appropriate equipment.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section any reference to information being derived from 
    other information shall be a reference to its being derived therefrom by 
    calculation, comparison or any other process.] 





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Rules as to notice to produce.—Secondary 
    evidence of the contents of the documents referred to in section 65, clause 
    
<section><number>a</number>, shall not be given unless the party proposing to give such secondary 
    evidence has previously given to the party in whose possession or power the 
    document is, 

    1[or to his attorney or 
    pleader,] such notice to produce it as is prescribed by law; and if no 
    notice is prescribed by law, then such notice as the Court considers 
    reasonable under the circumstances of the case:—Secondary 
    evidence of the contents of the documents referred to in section 65, clause 
    (a), shall not be given unless the party proposing to give such secondary 
    evidence has previously given to the party in whose possession or power the 
    document is, 

    1[or to his attorney or 
    pleader,] such notice to produce it as is prescribed by law; and if no 
    notice is prescribed by law, then such notice as the Court considers 
    reasonable under the circumstances of the case\:" 
 
Provided that 
    such notice shall not be required in order to render secondary evidence 
    admissible in any of the following cases, or in any other case in which the 
    Court thinks fit to dispense with it:— 
 <subsection>
<number>1</number>    when the document to be proved is 
    itself a notice; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>2</number>    when, from the nature of the case, the 
    adverse party must know that he will be required to produce it; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>3</number>    when it appears or is proved that the 
    adverse party has obtained possession of the original by fraud or force; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>4</number>    when the adverse party or his agent has 
    the original in Court; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>5</number>    when the adverse party or his agent has 
    admitted the loss of the document;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>6</number>    when the person in possession of the 
    document is out of reach of, or not subject to, the process of the Court. 
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Proof of 
    signature and handwriting of person alleged to have signed or written 
    document produced.—If a document 
    is alleged to be signed or to have been written wholly or in part by any 
    person, the signature or the handwriting of so much of the document as is 
    alleged to be in that person’s handwriting must be proved to be in his 
    handwriting.
 

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>59</footcitenum>[<number>67A</number> Proof as to 
</title><title>[electronic signature]. </title>—Except in the 
case of a secure [electronic signature], if the 
[electronic signature] of any subscriber is alleged to have been 
affixed to an electronic record the fact that such [electronic 
signature] is the [electronic signature] of the subscriber must be 
proved.] 

</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> Proof of 
    execution of document required by law to be attested.—If 
    a document is required by law to be attested, it shall not be used as 
    evidence until one attesting witness at least has been called for the 
    purpose of proving its execution, if there be an attesting witness alive, 
    and subject to the process of the Court and capable of giving evidence:
 


    1[Provided that it 
    shall not be necessary to call an attesting witness in proof of the 
    execution of any document, not being a Will, which has been registered in 
    accordance with the provisions of the Indian Registration Act, 1908 (16 of 
    1908), unless its execution by the person by whom it purports to have been 
    executed is specifically denied.]
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Proof 
    where no attesting witness found.—If 
    no such attesting witness can be found, or if the document purports to have 
    been executed in the United Kingdom, it must be proved that the attestation 
    of one attesting witness at least is in his handwriting, and that the 
    signature of the person executing the document is in the handwriting of that 
    person. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>70</number> 
    Admission of execution by party to attested document.—The 
    admission of a party to an attested document of its execution by himself 
    shall be sufficient proof of its execution as against him, though it be a 
    document required by law to be attested. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> Proof 
    when attesting witness denies the execution.—If 
    the attesting witness denies or does not recollect the execution of the 
    document, its execution may be proved by other evidence. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> Proof of 
    document not required by law to be attested.—An 
    attested document not required by law to be attested may be proved as if it 
    was unattested. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Comparison of signature, writing or seal with others admitted or proved.—In 
    order to ascertain whether a signature, writing or seal is that of the 
    person by whom it purports to have been written or made, any signature, 
    writing, or seal admitted or proved to the satisfaction of the Court to have 
    been written or made by that person may be compared with the one which is to 
    be proved, although that signature, writing, or seal has not been produced 
    or proved for any other purpose.
 
The Court may 
    direct any person present in Court to write any words or figures for the 
    purpose of enabling the Court to compare the words or figures so written 
    with any words or figures alleged to have been written by such person.
 


    1[This section applies 
    also, with any necessary modifications, to finger-impressions.]
 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>73A</number> Proof as to 
    verification of digital signature.—In 
    order to ascertain whether a digital signature is that of the person by whom 
    it purports to have been affixed, the Court may direct—2[73A. 
    Proof as to verification of digital signature.—In 
    order to ascertain whether a digital signature is that of the person by whom 
    it purports to have been affixed, the Court may direct—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    that person or the Controller or the 
    Certifying Authority to produce the Digital Signature Certificate; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any other person to apply the public 
    key listed in the Digital Signature Certificate and verify the digital 
    signature purported to have been affixed by that person. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “Controller” means the Controller appointed 
    under sub-section (1) of section 17 of the Information Technology Act, 
    2000.] 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> Public 
    documents.—The following documents 
    are public documents :— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>   Documents 
    forming the acts, or records of the acts— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    of the sovereign authority, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    of official bodies and tribunals, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    of public officers, 
    legislative, judicial and executive, 
1[of 
    any part of India or of the Commonwealth], or of a foreign country;
1[of 
    any part of India or of the Commonwealth], or of a foreign country;" 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number>   
    Public records kept 

    2[in any State] of 
    private documents. 
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> Private 
    documents.—All other documents are 
    private. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> 
    Certified copies of public documents.—Every
    

    1public officer having 
    the custody of a public document, which any person has a right to inspect, 
    shall give that person on demand a copy of it on payment of the legal fees 
    therefor, together with a certificate written at the foot of such copy that 
    it is a true copy of such document or part thereof, as the case may be, and 
    such certificate shall be dated and subscribed by such officer with his name 
    and his official title, and shall be sealed, whenever such officer is 
    authorized by law to make use of a seal; and such copies so certified shall 
    be called certified copies.—Every
    

    3public officer having 
    the custody of a public document, which any person has a right to inspect, 
    shall give that person on demand a copy of it on payment of the legal fees 
    therefor, together with a certificate written at the foot of such copy that 
    it is a true copy of such document or part thereof, as the case may be, and 
    such certificate shall be dated and subscribed by such officer with his name 
    and his official title, and shall be sealed, whenever such officer is 
    authorized by law to make use of a seal; and such copies so certified shall 
    be called certified copies." 
 
Explanation.—Any 
    officer who, by the ordinary course of official duty, is authorized to 
    deliver such copies, shall be deemed to have the custody of such documents 
    within the meaning of this section. 
 
 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> Proof of 
    documents by production of certified copies.—Such 
    certified copies may be produced in proof of the contents of the public 
    documents or parts of the public documents of which they purport to be 
    copies. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> Proof of 
    other official documents.—The 
    following public documents may be proved as follows:— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    Acts, orders or notifications of
    1[the 
    Central Government] in any of its departments, 
2[or 
    of the Crown Representative] or of any State Government or any department of 
    any State Government,—
4[the 
    Central Government] in any of its departments, 
5[or 
    of the Crown Representative] or of any State Government or any department of 
    any State Government,—" 
 
by the records of the departments, certified 
    by the head of those departments respectively,  
 
or by any document purporting to be 
    printed by order of any such Government 
2[or, 
    as the case may be, of the Crown Representative];5[or, 
    as the case may be, of the Crown Representative];" 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    The proceedings of the Legislatures,— 
 
by the journals of those bodies 
    respectively, or by published Acts or abstracts, or by copies purporting to 
    be printed 
3[by 
    order of the Government concerned];
6[by 
    order of the Government concerned];" 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    Proclamations, orders or 
    regulations issued by 
4[Her 
    Majesty] or by the Privy Council, or by any department of 
4[Her 
    Majesty’s] Government,—
7[Her 
    Majesty] or by the Privy Council, or by any department of 
7[Her 
    Majesty’s] Government,—" 
 
by copies or extracts contained in the London 
    Gazette, or purporting to be printed by the Queen’s printer; 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    The acts of the Executive or the 
    proceedings of the Legislature of a foreign country,— 
 
by journals published by their 
    authority, or commonly received in that country as such, or by a copy 
    certified under the seal of the country or sovereign, or by a recognition 
    thereof in some 
5[Central 
    Act];1[Central 
    Act];" 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>    The proceedings of a municipal 
    body in 
6[a 
    State],2[a 
    State]," 
 
by a copy of such proceedings, certified by 
    the legal keeper thereof, or by a printed book purporting to be published by 
    the authority of such body; 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>    Public documents of any other class in 
    a foreign country,— 
 
by the original, or by a copy certified 
    by the legal keeper thereof, with a certificate under the seal of a Notary 
    Public, or of 
7[an 
    Indian Consul] or diplomatic agent, that the copy is duly certified by the 
    officer having the legal custody of the original, and upon proof of the 
    character of the document according to the law of the foreign country.
3[an 
    Indian Consul] or diplomatic agent, that the copy is duly certified by the 
    officer having the legal custody of the original, and upon proof of the 
    character of the document according to the law of the foreign country." 
 
 
STATE AMENDMENT tc 
      "STATE AMENDMENT" 
 
West Bengal.—After 
      section 78, insert the following section, namely:— 
 
 
 










 



</section></article><article>
         
      <number>78A</number> Copies of public documents, to be as good as original documents in 
      certain cases.—Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or any 
      other law for the time being in force, where any public documents 
      concerning any areas within West Bengal have been kept in Pakistan, then 
      copies of such public documents shall, on being authenticated in such 
      manner as may be prescribed from time to time by the State Government by 
      notification in the Official Gazette, be deemed to have taken the place of 
      and to be, the original documents from which such copies were made and all 
      references to the original documents shall be construed as including 
      references to such copies."  
 
[Vide West Bengal Act 
      29 of 1955, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 6-10-1955) as amended by West Bengal Act 20 of 
      1960, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 5-1-1961)].
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Presumption as to genuineness of certified copies.—The 
    Court shall presume 

    1[to be genuine] every 
    document purporting to be a certificate, certified copy, or other document, 
    which is by law declared to be admissible as evidence of any particular fact 
    and which purports to be duly certified by any officer 

    2[of the Central 
    Government or of a State Government, or by any officer 

    3[in the State of Jammu 
    and Kashmir] who is duly authorized thereto by the Central Government]:
 
Provided that 
    such document is substantially in the form and purports to be executed in 
    the manner directed by law in that behalf. 
 
The Court shall 
    also presume that any officer by whom any such document purports to be 
    signed or certified held, when he signed it, the official character which he 
    claims in such paper. 
 
 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> 
    Presumption as to documents produced as record of evidence.—Whenever 
    any document is produced before any Court, purporting to be a record or 
    memorandum of the evidence, or of any part of the evidence, given by a 
    witness in a judicial proceeding or before any officer authorized by law to 
    take such evidence, or to be a statement or confession by any prisoner or 
    accused person, taken in accordance with law, and purporting to be signed by 
    any Judge or Magistrate, or by any such officer as aforesaid, the Court 
    shall presume—
 
that the document is genuine; that any 
    statements as to the circumstances under which it was taken, purporting to 
    be made by the person signing it, are true, and that such evidence, 
    statement or confession was duly taken. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>81</number> Presumption as to Gazettes, newspapers, private Acts of 
      Parliament and other documents.—The Court shall presume the 
      genuineness of every document purporting to be the London Gazette, or 
      1[any Official Gazette, or the 
      Government Gazette] of any colony, dependency of possession of the British 
      Crown, or to be a newspaper or journal, or to be a copy of a private Act 
      of Parliament 2[of the United Kingdom] printed by 
      the Queen’s Printer, and of every document purporting to be a document 
      directed by any law to be kept by any person, if such document is kept 
      substantially in the form required by law and is produced from proper 
      custody.
  





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>81A</number> Presumption as 
    to Gazettes in electronic forms.—The 
    Court shall presume the genuineness of every electronic record purporting to 
    be the Official Gazette or purporting to be electronic record directed by 
    any law to be kept by any person, if such electronic record is kept 
    substantially in the form required by law and is produced from proper 
    custody.]3[81A. 
    Presumption as to Gazettes in electronic forms.—The 
    Court shall presume the genuineness of every electronic record purporting to 
    be the Official Gazette or purporting to be electronic record directed by 
    any law to be kept by any person, if such electronic record is kept 
    substantially in the form required by law and is produced from proper 
    custody.]" 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> 
    Presumption as to document admissible in England without proof of seal or 
    signature.—When any document is 
    produced before any Court, purporting to be a document which, by the law in 
    force for the time being in England or Ireland, would be admissible in proof 
    of any particular in any Court of Justice in England or Ireland, without 
    proof of the seal or stamp or signature authenticating it, or of the 
    judicial or official character claimed by the person by whom it purports to 
    be signed, the Court shall presume that such seal, stamp or signature is 
    genuine, and that the person signing it held, at the time when he signed it, 
    the judicial or official character which he claims,  
 
and the document shall be admissible for the 
    same purpose for which it would be admissible in England or Ireland. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> 
    Presumption as to maps or plans made by authority of Government.—The 
    Court shall presume that maps or plans purporting to be made by the 
    authority of 

    1[the Central 
    Government or any State Government] were so made, and are accurate; but maps 
    or plans made for the purposes of any cause must be proved to be accurate.—The 
    Court shall presume that maps or plans purporting to be made by the 
    authority of 

    4[the Central 
    Government or any State Government] were so made, and are accurate; but maps 
    or plans made for the purposes of any cause must be proved to be accurate." 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>84</number> 
    Presumption as to collections of laws and reports of decisions.—The Court shall presume the genuineness of every book purporting to 
    be printed or published under the authority of the Government of any 
    country, and to contain any of the laws of that country, 
 
and of every book purporting to contain 
    reports of decisions of the Courts of such country. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>85</number> 
    Presumption as to powers-of-attorney.—The 
    Court shall presume that every document purporting to be a 
    power-of-attorney, and to have been executed before, and authenticated by, a 
    Notary Public, or any Court, Judge, Magistrate, 

    1[Indian] Consul or 
    Vice-Consul, or representative 

    2[***] of the 


    3[Central Government], 
    was so executed and authenticated.
 
 






 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>83</footcitenum>[<number>85A</number> Presumption as to electronic 
agreements.—</title>The Court shall presume that every electronic record 
purporting to be an agreement containing the [electronic signature] 
of the parties was so concluded by affixing the [electronic 
signature] of the parties.]

</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>84</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>85B</number> Presumption as to electronic 
records and </title><title>6 </title><title>[electronic signatures]. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> In any proceedings involving a secure electronic record, the Court 
shall presume unless contrary is proved, that the secure electronic record has 
not been altered since the specific point of time to which the secure status 
relates. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In any proceedings, involving secure [electronic signature], 
the Court shall presume unless the contrary is proved that— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the secure [electronic signature] is affixed by subscriber 
  with the intention of signing or approving the electronic record; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> except in the case of a secure electronic record or a secure 
  [electronic signature], nothing in this section shall cerate any 
  presumption, relating to authenticity and integrity of the electronic record 
  or any [electronic signature.]] </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>85</footcitenum>[<number>85C</number> Presumption as to 
</title><title><footcitenum>86</footcitenum>[Electronic Signature Certificates]. </title>—The 
Court shall presume, unless contrary is proved, that the information listed in a 
<footcitenum>86</footcitenum>[Electronic Signature Certificate] is correct, except for 
information specified as subscriber information which has not been verfied, if 
the certificate was accepted by the subscriber.] 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>86</number> 
    Presumption as to certified copies of foreign judicial records.—The 
    Court may presume that any document purporting to be a certified copy of any 
    judicial record of 

    1[2[***] 
    any country not forming part of India] or of Her Majesty’s dominions is 
    genuine and accurate, if the document purports to be certified in any manner 
    which is certified by any representative of 

    3[***] the 


    4[Central Government]
    

    5[in or for] 


    6[such country] to be 
    the manner commonly in use in 

    7[that country] for the 
    certification of copies of judicial records.
 


    8[An officer who, with 
    respect to 

    9[***] any territory or 
    place not forming part of 

    10[India or] Her 
    Majesty’s dominions, is a Political Agent therefore, as defined in section 
    3, 

    11[clause (43)], of the 
    General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), shall, for the purposes of this 
    section, be deemed to be a representative of the 

    12[Central Government]
    

    13[in and for the 
    country] comprising that territory or place].
 
 
 
 
















 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>87</number> 
    Presumption as to books, maps and charts.—The 
    Court may presume that any book to which it may refer for information on 
    matters of public or general interest, and that any published map or chart, 
    the statements of which are relevant facts and which is produced for its 
    inspection, was written and published by the person and at the time and 
    place, by whom or at which it purports to have been written or published. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>88</number> 
    Presumption as to telegraphic messages.—The 
    Court may presume that a message, forwarded from a telegraph office to the 
    person to whom such message purports to be addressed, corresponds with a 
    message delivered for transmission at the office from which the message 
    purports to be sent; but the Court shall not make any presumption as to the 
    person by whom such message was delivered for transmission. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>88A</number> Presumption as 
    to electronic messages.—The 
    Court may presume that an electronic message, forwarded by the originator 
    through an electronic mail server to the addressee to whom the message 
    purports to be addressed corresponds with the message as fed into his 
    computer for transmission; but the Court shall not make any presumption as 
    to the person by whom such message was sent.3[88A. 
    Presumption as to electronic messages.—The 
    Court may presume that an electronic message, forwarded by the originator 
    through an electronic mail server to the addressee to whom the message 
    purports to be addressed corresponds with the message as fed into his 
    computer for transmission; but the Court shall not make any presumption as 
    to the person by whom such message was sent." 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, the expressions “addressee” and “originator” 
    shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in clauses (b) 
    and (za) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 2 of the Information Technology Act, 
    2000.] 
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>89</number> 
    Presumption as to due execution, etc., of documents not produced.—The 
    Court shall presume that every document, called for and not produced after 
    notice to produce, was attested, stamped and executed in the manner required 
    by law. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>90</number> 
    Presumption as to documents thirty years old.—Where 
    any document, purporting or proved to be thirty years old, is produced from 
    any custody which the Court in the particular case considers proper, the 
    Court may presume that the signature and every other part of such document, 
    which purports to be in the handwriting of any particular person, is in that 
    person’s handwriting, and, in the case of a document executed or attested, 
    that it was duly executed and attested by the persons by whom it purports to 
    be executed and attested. 
 

    Explanation.—Documents are said to 
    be in proper custody if they are in the place in which, and under the care 
    of the person with whom, they would naturally be; but no custody is improper 
    if it is proved to have had a legitimate origin, or if the circumstances of 
    the particular case are such as to render such an origin probable. 
 
This 
    Explanation applies also to section 81. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A has been in 
      possession of landed property for a long time. He produces from his 
      custody deeds relating to the land showing his titles to it. The custody 
      is proper.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A produces deeds 
      relating to landed property of which he is the mortgagee. The mortgagor is 
      in possession. The custody is proper.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A, a connection of
      B, produces deeds relating to lands in B’s possession, which 
      were deposited with him by B for safe custody. The custody is 
      proper. 
 
STATE AMENDMENTS
 
Uttar Pradesh.—(a) 
      Renumber section 90 as sub-section (1) thereof;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> in sub-section (1) as so 
      renumbered, for the words “thirty years”, substitute the words “twenty 
      years”;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> after sub-section (1) as 
      so renumbered, insert the following sub-section, namely:—
 
                     “(2) 
      Where any such document as is referred to in sub-section (1) was 
      registered in accordance with the law relating to registration of 
      documents and a duly certified copy thereof is produced, the court may 
      presume that the signature and every other part of such document which 
      purports to be in the handwriting of any particular person, it is that 
      person's handwriting, and in the case of a document executed or attested, 
      that it was duly executed and attested by the person by whom it purports 
      to have been executed or attested”.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> After section 90, insert 
      the following section, namely:—
 
                     “90A. 
      (1) Where any registered document or a duly certified copy thereof or any 
      certified copy of a document which is part of the record of a Court of 
      Justice, is produced from any custody which the Court in the particular 
      case considers proper, the Court may presume that the original was 
      executed by the person by whom it purports to have been executed.
 <subsection>
                     <number>2</number> This 
      presumption shall not be made in respect of any document which is the 
      basis of a suit or of defence or is relied upon in the plaint or written 
      statement.”
 
                     The 
      Explanation to sub-section (1) of section 90 will also apply to this 
      section; 
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 
      24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Presumption
 
Assuming that the document is 
      more than thirty years old and comes from proper custody, there would be 
      no presumption that contents of the same are true; Mohinuddin v. 
      President, Municipal Committee, Khargone, AIR 1993 MP 5. 
</subsection></section>

 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>97</footcitenum></title><title>[<number>90A</number> Presumption as to electronic 
records five years old. </title>—Where any electronic record, purporting or 
proved to be five years old, is produced from any custody which the Court in the 
particular case considers proper, the Court may presume that the 
<footcitenum>98</footcitenum>[electronic signature] which purports to be the 
<footcitenum>98</footcitenum>[electronic signature] of any particular person was so affixed by 
him or any person authorised by him in this behalf. 
 Explanation. —Electronic records are said to be in proper custody if 
they are in the place in which, and under the care of the person with whom, they 
naturally be; but no custody is improper if it is proved to have had a 
legitimate origin, or the circumstances of the particular case are such as to 
render such an origin probable. 
 This Explanation applies also to section 81A.] 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>91</number> Evidence of terms of contracts, grants and other dispositions 
      of property reduced to form of documents.—When the terms of a contract, or 
      of a grant, or of any other disposition of property, have been reduced to 
      the form of a document, and in all cases in which any matter is required 
      by law to be reduced to the form of a document, no 
      evidence1 shall be given in proof of 
      the terms of such contract, grant or other disposition of property, or of 
      such matter, except the document itself, or secondary evidence of its 
      contents in cases in which secondary evidence is admissible under the 
      provisions hereinbefore contained.—When 
    the terms of a contract, or of a grant, or of any other disposition of 
    property, have been reduced to the form of a document, and in all cases in 
    which any matter is required by law to be reduced to the form of a document, 
    no evidence2 shall 
    be given in proof of the terms of such contract, grant or other disposition 
    of property, or of such matter, except the document itself, or secondary 
    evidence of its contents in cases in which secondary evidence is admissible 
    under the provisions hereinbefore contained." 
 Exception 1.—When a public officer is required by law to 
      be appointed in writing, and when it is shown that any particular person 
      has acted as such officer, the writing by which he is appointed need not 
      be proved. 
 Exception 2.—Wills 2[admitted to probate in 
      3[India]] may be proved by the 
      probate.
 Explanation 1.—This section applies equally to cases in 
      which the contracts, grants or dispositions of property referred to are 
      contained in one document, and to cases in which they are contained in 
      more documents than one. 
 Explanation. 2.—Where there are more originals than one, 
      one original only need be proved. 
 Explanation 3.—The statement, in any document whatever, of a 
      fact other than the facts referred to in this section, shall not preclude 
      the admission of oral evidence as to the same fact. 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> If a 
        contract be contained in several letters, all the letters in which it is 
        contained must be proved.
 </section><section><number>b</number> If a 
        contract is contained in a bill of exchange, the bill of exchange must 
        be proved.
 </section><section><number>c</number> If a bill of 
        exchange is drawn in a set of three, one only need be proved.
 </section><section><number>d</number> A 
        contracts, in writing, with B, for the delivery of indigo upon 
        certain terms. The contract mentions the fact that B had paid 
        A the price of other indigo contracted for verbally on another 
        occasion.
 Oral evidence is 
        offered that no payment was made for the other indigo. The evidence is 
        admissible.
 </section><section><number>e</number> A 
        gives B receipt for money paid by B.
 Oral evidence is 
        offered of the payment.
 The evidence is 
        admissible.</section>
  
  






 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>92</number> 
    Exclusion of evidence of oral agreement.—When 
    the terms of any such contract, grant or other disposition of property, or 
    any matter required by law to be reduced to the form of a document, have 
    been proved according to the last section, no evidence of any oral agreement 
    or statement shall be admitted, as between the parties to any such 
    instrument or their representatives in interest, for the purpose of 
    contradicting, varying, adding to, or subtracting from, its terms: 
 

    Proviso 
    
<section><number>1</number>.—Any fact may be proved which would invalidate any document, or which 
    would entitle any person to any decree or order relating thereto; such as 
    fraud, intimidation, illegality, want of due execution, want of capacity in 
    any contracting party, 

    1[want or failure] of 
    consideration, or mistake in fact or law:
(1).—Any fact may be proved 
    which would invalidate any document, or which would entitle any person to 
    any decree or order relating thereto; such as fraud, intimidation, 
    illegality, want of due execution, want of capacity in any contracting 
    party, 

    3[want or failure] of 
    consideration, or mistake in fact or law\:" 
 
Proviso
    (2).—The existence of any separate 
    oral agreement as to any matter on which a document is silent, and which is 
    not inconsistent with its terms, may be proved. In considering whether or 
    not this proviso applies, the Court shall have regard to the degree of 
    formality of the document: 
 
Proviso
    (3).—The existence of any separate 
    oral agreement, constituting a condition precedent to the attaching of any 
    obligation under any such contract, grant or disposition of property, may be 
    proved: 
 
Proviso 
    (4).—The existence of any distinct subsequent oral agreement to rescind or 
    modify any such contract, grant or disposition of property, may be proved, 
    except in cases in which such contract, grant or disposition of property is 
    by law required to be in writing, or has been registered according to the 
    law in force for the time being as to the registration of documents: 
 
Proviso 
    (5).—Any usage or custom by which incidents not expressly mentioned in any 
    contract are usually annexed to contracts of that description, may be 
    proved: 
 
Provided that 
    the annexing of such incident would not be repugnant to, or inconsistent 
    with, the express terms of the contract: 
 
Proviso
    (6).—Any fact may be proved which 
    shows in what manner the language of a document is related to existing 
    facts. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> A policy of 
      insurance is effected on goods “in ships from Calcutta to London”. The 
      goods are shipped in a particular ship which is lost. The fact that that 
      particular ship was orally excepted from the policy, cannot be proved.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> A agrees absolutely 
      in writing to pay B Rs. 1,000 on the 1st March, 1873. The fact 
      that, at the same time, an oral agreement was made that the money should 
      not be paid till the thirty-first March, cannot be proved.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> An estate called “the 
      Rampure tea estate” is sold by a deed which contains a map of the property 
      sold. The fact that land not included in the map had always been regarded 
      as part of the estate and was meant to pass by the deed, cannot be proved.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> A enters into a 
      written contract with B to work certain mines, the property of 
      B, upon certain terms. A was induced to do so by a 
      misrepresentation of B’s as to their value. This fact may be 
      proved.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> A institutes a suit 
      against B for the specific performance of a contract, and also 
      prays that the contract may be reformed as to one of its provisions, as 
      that provision was inserted in it by mistake. A may prove that such 
      a mistake was made as would by law entitle him to have the contract 
      reformed.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> A orders goods of
      B by a letter in which nothing is said as to the time of payment, 
      and accepts the goods on delivery. B sues A for the price.
      A may show that the goods were supplied on credit for a term still 
      unexpired.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> A sells B a 
      horse and verbally warrants him sound. A gives B a paper in 
      these words “Bought of A a horse for Rs. 500”. B may prove 
      the verbal warranty.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> A hires lodgings of
      B, and gives B a card on which is written—“Rooms, Rs. 200 a 
      month”. A may prove a verbal agreement that these terms were to 
      include partial board.
 
A hires lodgings of 
      B for a year, and a regularly stamped agreement, drawn up by an 
      attorney, is made between them. It is silent on the subject of board. A 
      may not prove that board was included in the term verbally.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> A applies to B
      for a debt due to A by sending a receipt for the money. B 
      keeps the receipt and does not send the money. In a suit for the amount,
      A may prove this.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> A and B make 
      a contract in writing to take effect upon the happening of a certain 
      contingency. The writing is left with B, who sues A upon it.
      A may show the circumstances under which it was delivered.
 

Comments 
 
Deed of 
      collateral security: manner of execution
 
If it is a deed of collateral 
      security of defendant, then the defendant would have had to execute a deed 
      in favour of plaintiff and not vice versa, where the plaintiff has 
      executed the mortgage the plea of evidence of collateral security offered 
      by defendant appears not to fit into a situation; Ishwar Dass v. 
      Sohan Lal, AIR 2000 SC 426. 
 
Inference can be drawn 
      regarding proof of document by admission of parties either oral or other 
      evidence; B.B. Lohar v. P.P. Goyal, AIR 1999 Sikkim 11. 
 
Position of 
      stranger
 
The rule as to exclusion of 
      oral by documentary evidence governs the parties to the deed in writing. A 
      stranger to the document is not bound by the terms of the document and is, 
      therefore, not excluded from demonstrating the untrue or collusive nature 
      of the document or the fraudulent or illegal purpose for which it was 
      brought into being; Parvinder Singh v. Renu Gautam, (2004) 4 
      SCC 794.
 

 
</subsection>
 

 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>93</number> 
    Exclusion of evidence to explain or amend ambiguous document.—When 
    the language used in a document is, on its face, ambiguous or defective, 
    evidence may not be given of facts which would show its meaning or supply 
    its defects. 
 
 
Illustrations 

 <section>
<number>a</number> A agrees, in 
      writing, to sell a horse to B for “Rs. 1,000 or Rs. 1,500”. 

 
Evidence cannot be given to 
      show which price was to be given.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A deed contains blanks. 
      Evidence cannot be given of facts which would show how they were meant to 
      be filled.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>94</number> 
    Exclusion of evidence against application of document to existing facts.—When 
    language used in a document is plain in itself, and when it applies 
    accurately to existing facts, evidence may not be given to show that it was 
    not meant to apply to such facts. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A sells to B, by 
      deed, “my estate at Rampur containing 100 bighas”. A has an estate 
      at Rampur containing 100 bighas. Evidence may not be given of the fact 
      that the estate meant to be sold was one situated at a different place and 
      of a different size.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>95</number> Evidence 
    as to document unmeaning in reference to existing facts.—When 
    language used in a document is plain in itself, but is unmeaning in 
    reference to existing facts, evidence may be given to show that it was used 
    in a peculiar sense. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A sells to B, by 
      deed, “my house in Calcutta”.
 
A had no house in 
      Calcutta, but it appears that he had a house at Howrah, of which B 
      had been in possession since the execution of the deed.
 
These facts may be proved to 
      show that the deed related to the house of Howrah.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>96</number> Evidence 
    as to application of language which can apply to one only of several 
    persons.—When the facts are such 
    that the language used might have been meant to apply to any one, and could 
    not have been meant to apply to more than one, of several persons or things, 
    evidence may be given of facts which show which of those persons or things 
    it was intended to apply to. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A agrees to sell to
      B, for Rs. 1,000, “my white horse”. A has two white horses. 
      Evidence may be given of facts which show which of them was meant.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A agrees to 
      accompany B to Haidarabad. Evidence may be given of facts showing 
      whether Haidarabad in the Dekkhan or Haidarabad in Sindh was meant.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>97</number> Evidence 
    as to application of language to one of two sets of facts, to neither of 
    which the whole correctly applies.—When 
    the language used applies partly to one set existing facts, and partly to 
    another set of existing facts, but the whole of it does not apply correctly 
    to either, evidence may be given to show to which of the two it was meant to 
    apply. 
 
 
Illustrations
 
A agrees to sell to 
      B “my land at X in the occupation of Y". A has 
      land at X, but not in the occupation of Y, and he has land 
      in the occupation of Y, but it is not at X. Evidence 
      may be given of facts showing which he meant to sell.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>98</number> Evidence as to meaning of illegible 
      characters, etc.—Evidence may be given to show the meaning of 
      illegible or not commonly intelligible characters, of foreign, obsolete, 
      technical, local and provincial expressions, of abbreviations and of words 
      used in a peculiar sense. 
 
 Illustration
 A, a 
        sculptor, agrees to sell to B, “all my mods”. A has both 
        models and modelling tools. Evidence may be given to show which he meant 
        to sell.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>99</number> Who may 
    give evidence of agreement varying term of document.—Persons 
    who are not parties to a document, or their representatives in interest, may 
    give evidence of any facts tending to show a contemporaneous agreement 
    varying the terms of the document. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A and B make a 
      contract in writing that B shall sell A certain cotton, to 
      be paid for on delivery. At the same time they make an oral agreement that 
      three months’s credit shall be given to A. This could not be shown 
      as between A and B, but it might be shown by C, if it 
      affected his interests.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>100</number> Saving of provisions of Indian Succession Act relating to 
      Wills.—Nothing in this Chapter contained shall be taken to affect any of 
      the provisions of the Indian Succession Act (10 of 
      1865)1 as to the construction of 
      Wills.
  



 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>101</number> Burden 
    of proof.—Whoever desires any 
    Court to give judgment as to any legal right or liability dependent on the 
    existence of facts which he asserts, must prove that those facts exist. 
 
When a person 
    is bound to prove the existence of any fact, it is said that the burden of 
    proof lies on that person. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A desires a Court 
      to give judgment that B shall be punished for a crime which A 
      says B has committed.
 
A must prove that B
      has committed the crime.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A desires a Court 
      to give judgment that he is entitled to certain land in the possession of
      B, by reason of facts which he asserts, and which B denies, 
      to be true.
 
A must prove the 
      existence of those facts.
 
COMMENTS 
 
Joint family 
      property
 
Merely because some of 
      properties continue to stand in the name of plaintiff that by itself 
      cannot lead to any conclusion that the property purchased by any one 
      member of the family would necessarily be a part of joint family property 
      and when evidence shows that the person who has purchased property had 
      been engaged in an independent business for a sufficient long period; 
      Baban Girju v. Namdeo Girju Bangar, AIR 1999 Bom 46.
 
Reasonable 
      proof of ownership
 
In absence of any reasonable 
      proof that defendant was the actual owner of the property, and plaintiff 
      was only a name given does not prove that respondent was owner and plaint 
      maker was only a name given to the property; Rama Kanta Jain v. 
      M.S. Jain, AIR 1999 Del 281. 
 
What to be 
      proved by prosecution
 
It is well settled that the 
      prosecution can succeed by substantially proving the very story it 
      alleges. It must stand on its own legs. It cannot take advantage of the 
      weakness of the defence. Nor can the court on its own make out a new case 
      for the prosecution and convict the accused on that basis; Narain Singh
      v. State, (1997) 2 Crimes 464 (Del). 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>102</number> On whom 
    burden of proof lies.—The burden 
    of proof in a suit or proceeding lies on that person who would fail if no 
    evidence at all were given on either side. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A sues B for 
      land of which B is in possession, and which, as A asserts, 
      was left to A by the will of C, B’s father.
 
If no evidence were given on 
      either side, B would be entitled to retain his possession.
 
Therefore the burden of proof 
      is on A.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A sues B for 
      money due on a bond.
 
The execution of the bond is 
      admitted, but B says that it was obtained by fraud, which A 
      denies.
 
If no evidence were given on 
      either side, A would succeed, as the bond is not disputed and the 
      fraud is not proved.
 
Therefore the burden of proof 
      is on B.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>103</number> Burden of proof as to particular 
      fact.—The burden of proof as to 
      any particular fact lies on that person who wishes the Court to believe in 
      its existence, unless it is provided by any law that the proof of that 
      fact shall lie on any particular person. 
 
 Illustration
 1[
<section><number>a</number>] A prosecutes B for theft, and 
        wishes the Court to believe that B admitted the theft to C. 
        A must prove the admission.
 B wishes 
        the Court to believe that, at the time in question, he was elsewhere. He 
        must prove it.
  
 COMMENTS 
 Plea of alibi
 Plea of 
        alibi taken by accused, it is he who has to prove it; State of 
        Haryana v. Sher Singh, AIR 1981 SC 1021: 1981 SC Cr R 317: 
        1981 Cr LJ 714: (1981) 2 SCC 300. 
  </section>




 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>104</number> Burden of proving fact to be proved to make 
      evidence admissible.—The burden 
      of proving any fact necessary to be proved in order to enable any person 
      to give evidence of any other fact is on the person who wishes to give 
      such evidence. 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> A 
        wishes to prove a dying declaration by B. A must prove B’s 
        death.
 </section><section><number>b</number> A 
        wishes to prove, by secondary evidence, the contents of a lost 
        document.
 A must 
        prove that the document has been lost.</section>
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>105</number> Burden 
    of proving that case of accused comes within exceptions.—When 
    a person is accused of any offence, the burden of proving the existence of 
    circumstances bringing the case within any of the General Exceptions in the 
    Indian Penal Code, (45 of 1860), or within any special exception or proviso 
    contained in any other part of the same Code, or in any law defining the 
    offence, is upon him, and the Court shall presume the absence of such 
    circumstances. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A, accused of 
      murder, alleges that, by reason of unsoundness of mind, he did not know 
      the nature of the act.
 
The burden of proof is on 
      A.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A, accused of 
      murder, alleges, that by grave and sudden provocation, he was deprived of 
      the power of self-control.
 
The burden of proof is on 
      A.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> Section 325 of the Indian 
      Penal Code, (45 of 1860), provides that whoever, except in the case 
      provided for by section 335, voluntarily causes grievous hurt, shall be 
      subject to certain punishments.
 
A is charged with 
      voluntarily causing grievous hurt under section 325.
 
The burden of proving the 
      circumstances bringing the case under section 335 lies on A.
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Plea of 
      self-defence
 
When the prosecution has 
      established its case, it is incumbent upon the accused, under section 105 
      to establish the case of his private defence by showing probability; 
      Samuthram alias Samudra Rajan v. State of Tamil Nadu, 
      (1997) 2 Crimes 185 (Mad). 
 
The burden of establishing the 
      plea of self-defence is on the accused and the burden stands discharged by 
      showing preponderance of probabilities in favour of that plea on the basis 
      of material on record; Rizan v. State of Chhattisgarh, AIR 
      2003 SC 976. 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>106</number> Burden of proving fact especially within 
      knowledge.—When any fact is 
      especially within the knowledge of any person, the burden of proving that 
      fact is upon him. 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> When a 
        person does an act with some intention other than that which the 
        character and circumstances of the act suggest, the burden of proving 
        that intention is upon him.
 </section><section><number>b</number> A is 
        charged with travelling on a railway without a ticket. The burden of 
        proving that he had a ticket is on him.</section>
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>107</number> Burden 
    of proving death of person known to have been alive within thirty years.—When 
    the question is whether a man is alive or dead, and it is shown that he was 
    alive within thirty years, the burden of proving that he is dead is on the 
    person who affirms it. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
 <number>108</number> 
    Burden of proving that person is alive who has not been heard of for seven 
    years.—1[Provided 
    that when] the question is whether a man is alive or dead, and it is proved 
    that he has not been heard of for seven years by those who would naturally 
    have heard of him if he had been alive, the burden of proving that he is 
    alive is 

    2[shifted to] the 
    person who affirms it.—1[Provided 
    that when] the question is whether a man is alive or dead, and it is proved 
    that he has not been heard of for seven years by those who would naturally 
    have heard of him if he had been alive, the burden of proving that he is 
    alive is 

    2[shifted to] the 
    person who affirms it." 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>109</number> Burden 
    of proof as to relationship in the cases of partners, landlord and tenant, 
    principal and agent.—When the 
    question is whether persons are partners, landlord and tenant, or principal 
    and agent, and it has been shown that they have been acting as such, the 
    burden of proving that they do not stand, or have ceased to stand, to each 
    other in those relationships respectively, is on the person who affirms it. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>110</number> Burden 
    of proof as to ownership.—When the 
    question is whether any person is owner of anything of which he is shown to 
    be in possession, the burden of proving that he is not the owner is on the 
    person who affirms that he is not the owner. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>111</number> Proof of good faith in transactions where 
      one party is in relation of active confidence.—Where there is a question as to the good faith 
      of a transaction between parties, one of whom stands to the other in a 
      position of active confidence, the burden of proving the good faith of the 
      transaction is on the party who is in a position of active 
      confidence. 
 
 Illustrations
 <section><number>a</number> The good 
        faith of a sale by a client to an attorney is in question in a suit 
        brought by the client. The burden of proving the good faith of the 
        transaction is on the attorney.
 </section><section><number>b</number> The good 
        faith of a sale by a son just come of age to a father is in question in 
        a suit brought by the son. The burden of proving the good faith of the 
        transaction is on the father.</section>
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>111A</number> Presumption as 
    to certain offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a person is accused of having committed any offence specified in 
    sub-section (2), in—1[111A. 
    Presumption as to certain offences.—(1) 
    Where a person is accused of having committed any offence specified in 
    sub-section (2), in—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any area declared to be a disturbed 
    areas under any enactment, for the time being in force, making provision for 
    the suppression of disorder and restoration and maintenance of public order; 
    or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any area in which there has been, over 
    a period of more than one month, extensive disturbance of the public peace, 
 
and it is shown that such person had been at a 
    place in such area at a time when firearms or explosives were used at or 
    from that place to attack or resist the members of any armed forces or the 
    forces charged with the maintenance of public order acting in the discharge 
    of their duties, it shall be presumed, unless the contrary is shown, that 
    such person had committed such offence.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    offences referred to in sub-section (1) are the following, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an offence under section 121, section 
    121A section 122 or section 123 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860); 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    criminal conspiracy or attempt to 
    commit, or abatement of, an offence under section 122 or section 123 of the 
    Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).] 
 
 




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>112</number> Birth 
    during marriage, conclusive proof of legitimacy.—The 
    fact that any person was born during the continuance of a valid marriage 
    between his mother and any man, or within two hundred and eighty days after 
    its dissolution, the mother remaining unmarried, shall be conclusive proof 
    that he is the legitimate son of that man, unless it can be shown that the 
    parties to the marriage had no access to each other at any time when he 
    could have been begotten.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>113</number> 
    Proof of cession of territory.—A 
    notification in the Official Gazette that any portion of British territory 
    has 

    1[before the 
    commencement of Part III of the Government of India Act, 1935 (26 Geo. 5, ch. 
    2)] been ceded to any Native State, Prince or Ruler, shall be conclusive 
    proof that a valid cession of such territory took place at the date 
    mentioned in such notification.—A 
    notification in the Official Gazette that any portion of British territory 
    has 

    2[before the 
    commencement of Part III of the Government of India Act, 1935 (26 Geo. 5, ch. 
    2)] been ceded to any Native State, Prince or Ruler, shall be conclusive 
    proof that a valid cession of such territory took place at the date 
    mentioned in such notification." 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>113A</number> Presumption 
    as to abetment of suicide by a married woman.—When 
    the question is whether the commission of suicide by a woman had been 
    abetted by her husband or any relative of her husband and it is shown that 
    she had committed suicide within a period of seven years from the date of 
    her marriage and that her husband or such relative of her husband had 
    subjected her to cruelty, the Court may presume, having regard to all the 
    other circumstances of the case, that such suicide had been abetted by her 
    husband or by such relative of her husband.1[113A. 
    Presumption as to abetment of suicide by a married woman.—When 
    the question is whether the commission of suicide by a woman had been 
    abetted by her husband or any relative of her husband and it is shown that 
    she had committed suicide within a period of seven years from the date of 
    her marriage and that her husband or such relative of her husband had 
    subjected her to cruelty, the Court may presume, having regard to all the 
    other circumstances of the case, that such suicide had been abetted by her 
    husband or by such relative of her husband." 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, “cruelty” shall have the same meaning as in 
    section 498A of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).] 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>113B</number> Presumption 
    as to dowry death.—When the question is whether a person has committed 
    the dowry death of a woman and it is shown that soon before her death such 
    woman has been subjected by such person to cruelty or harassment for, or in 
    connection with, any demand for dowry, the Court shall presume that such 
    person had caused the dowry death. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section, “dowry death” shall have the same meaning as in section 304B, 
    of the Indian Penal Code, (45 of 1860).] 
 




 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>114</number> Court may presume existence of certain facts. </title>—The 
Court may presume the existence of any fact which it thinks likely to have 
happened, regard being had to the common course of natural events, human conduct 
and public and private business, in their relation to the facts of the 
particular case. 
 Illustrations 
 The Court may presume— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> That a man who is in possession of stolen goods soon after the theft is 
  either the thief or has received the goods knowing them to be stolen, unless 
  he can account for his possession; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> That an accomplice is unworthy of credit, unless he is corroborated in 
  material particulars; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> That a bill of exchange, accepted or endorsed, was accepted or endorsed 
  for good consideration; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> That a thing or state of things which has been shown to be in existence 
  within a period shorter than that within which such things or state of things 
  usually cease to exist, is still in existence; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> That judicial and official acts have been regularly performed; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> That the common course of business has been followed in particular 
  cases; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> That evidence which could be and is not produced would, if produced, be 
  unfavourable to the person who withholds it; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> That if a man refuses to answer a question which he is not compelled to 
  answer by law, the answer, if given, would be unfavourable to him; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> That when a document creating an obligation is in the hands of the 
  obligor, the obligation has been discharged. </section>
 But the Court shall also have regard to such facts as the following, in 
considering whether such maxims do or do not apply to the particular case before 
it:— 
 As to illustration 
<section><number>a</number>— A shop-keeper has in his till a 
marked rupee soon after it was stolen, and cannot account for its possession 
specifically, but is continually receiving rupees in the course of his business; 

 As to illustration (b)—A, a person of the highest character, is 
tried for causing a man's death by an act of negligence in arranging certain 
machinery. B , a person of equally good character, who also took part 
in the arrangement, describes precisely what was done, and admits and explains 
the common carelessness of A and himself; 
 As to illustration (b)—A crime is committed by several persons. 
A, B and C, three of the criminals, are captured on the spot 
and kept apart from each other. Each gives an account of the crime implicating 
D , and the accounts corroborate each other in such a manner as to 
render previous concert highly improbable; 
 As to illustration (c)— A, the drawer of a bill of 
exchange, was a man of business. B , the acceptor, was young and 
ignorant person, completely under A's influence; 
 As to illustration (d)—It is proved that a river ran in a certain 
course five years ago, but it is known that there have been floods since that 
time which might change its course; 
 As to illustration (e)—A judicial act, the regularity of which is in 
question, was performed under exceptional circumstances; 
 As to illustration (f)—The question is, whether a letter was 
received. It is shown to have been posted, but the usual course of the post was 
interrupted by disturbances; 
 As to illustration (g)—A man refuses to produce a document which 
would bear on a contract of small importance on which he is sued, but which 
might also injure the feelings and reputation of his family; 
 As to illustration (h)—A man refuses to answer a question which he 
is not compelled by law to answer, but the answer to it might cause loss to him 
in matters unconnected with the matter in relation to which it is asked; 
 As to illustration (i)—A bond is in possession of the obligor, but 
the circumstances of the case are such that he may have stolen it. 




 
 <subsection><number>i</number> There would be presumption in favour of wedlock if the partners lived 
  together for long spell as husband and wife; but it would be rebuttable and 
  heavy burden lies on the person who seeks to deprive the relationship of legal 
  origin to prove that no marriage took place; Tulsa v. Durghatiya 
  , 2008 (1) SCR 709: 2008 (4) SCC 520. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Presumption is rebuttable. If there is any such circumstance weakening 
  such presumption, it cannot be ignored by the court; Sobha Hymavathi Devi 
  v. Setti Gangadhara Swamy , AIR 2005 SC 800. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> When oral and other reliable evidences are satisfactorily giving 
  evidence that the pair lived together as husband and wife, merely because 
  family register does not show them as husband and wife is not a clinching 
  evidence to deny their relationship of husband and wife; Lalta v. 
  District IVth upper Distt. Judge Basti , AIR 1999 All 342. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Genuine and correctness of document have to be proved by a person 
  believes upon it by cogent and direct evidence; Ashok Kumar Uttam Chand 
  Shah v. Patel Mohmad Asmal Chanchad , AIR 1999 Guj 108. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> A court may legitimately draw a presumption not only of the fact that 
  the person in whose possession the stolen articles were found committed the 
  robbery but also that he committed the murder; Mukund alias Kundu 
  Mishra v. State of Madhya Pradesh , (1997) 4 Supreme 359. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> The recovery made some days after the dacoity does not raise a 
  presumption under section 114(a) in respect of the offence of dacoity; 
  Vasant alias Roshan Sogaji Bhosale v . State of 
  Maharashtra, (1997) 2 Crimes 104 (Bom). 
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>114A</number> Presumption as 
    to absence of consent in certain prosecutions for rape.—In 
    a prosecution for rape under clause 
<section><number>a</number> or clause (b) or clause (c) or 
    clause (d) or clause (e) or clause (g) of sub-section (2) of section 376 of 
    the Indian Penal Code, (45 of 1860), where sexual intercourse by the accused 
    is proved and the question is whether it was without the consent of the 
    woman alleged to have been raped and she states in her evidence before the 
    Court that she did not consent, the Court shall presume that she did not 
    consent.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>115</number> Estoppel. </title>—When one person has, by his declaration, act 
or omission, intentionally caused or permitted another person to believe a thing 
to be true and to act upon such belief, neither he nor his representative shall 
be allowed, in any suit or proceeding between himself and such person or his 
representative, to deny the truth of that thing. 
 Illustration 
 A intentionally and falsely leads B to believe that certain 
land belongs to A , and thereby induces B to buy and pay for 
it. 
 The land afterwards becomes the property of A, and A seeks 
to set aside the sale on the ground that, at the time of the sale, he had no 
title. He must not be allowed to prove his want of title. 

















</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>116</number> 
    Estoppel of tenant; and of licensee of person in possession.—No 
    tenant of immovable property, or person claiming through such tenant, shall, 
    during the continuance of the tenancy, be permitted to deny that the 
    landlord of such tenant had, at the beginning of the tenancy, a title to 
    such immovable property; and no person who came upon any immovable property 
    by the licence of the person in possession thereof, shall be permitted to 
    deny that such person had a title to such possession at the time when such 
    licence was given. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>117</number> 
    Estoppel of acceptor of bill of exchange, bailee or licensee.—No 
    acceptor of a bill of exchange shall be permitted to deny that the drawer 
    had authority to draw such bill or to endorese it; nor shall any bailee or 
    licensee be permitted to deny that his bailor or licensor had, at the time 
    when the bailment or licence commenced, authority to make such bailment or 
    grant such licence. 
 
Explanation 
    1.—The acceptor of a bill of exchange may deny that the bill was really 
    drawn by the person by whom it purports to have been drawn. 
 
Explanation 
    2.—If a bailee delivers the goods bailed to a person other than the bailor, 
    he may prove that such person had a right to them as against the bailor. 
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>118</number> Who may testify. </title>—All persons shall be competent to 
testify unless the Court considers that they are prevented from understanding 
the questions put to them, or from giving rational answers to those questions, 
by tender years, extreme old age, disease, whether of body or mind, or any other 
cause of the same kind. <title></title>
 Explanation.— A lunatic is not incompetent to testify, unless he is 
prevented by his lunacy from understanding the questions put to him and giving 
rational answers to them. <title></title>











</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>119</number> Dumb 
    witnesses.—A witness who is unable 
    to speak may give his evidence in any other manner in which he can make it 
    intelligible, as by writing or by signs; but such writing must be written 
    and the signs made in open Court. Evidence so given shall be deemed to be 
    oral evidence. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>120</number> Parties 
    to civil suit, and their wives or husbands. Husband or wife of person under 
    criminal trial.—In all civil 
    proceedings the parties to the suit, and the husband or wife of any party to 
    the suit, shall be competent witnesses. In criminal proceedings against any 
    person, the husband or wife of such person, respectively, shall be a 
    competent witness. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>121</number> Judges 
    and Magistrates.—No Judge or 
    Magistrate shall, except upon the special order of some Court to which he is 
    subordinate, be compelled to answer any question as to his own conduct in 
    Court as such Judge or Magistrate, or as to anything which came to his 
    knowledge in Court as such Judge or Magistrate; but he may be examined as to 
    other matters which occurred in his presence whilst he was so acting. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A, on his trial 
      before the Court of Sessions, says that a deposition was improperly taken 
      by B, the Magistrate. B cannot be compelled to answer 
      questions as to this, except upon the special order of a superior Court.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A is accused 
      before the Court of Sessions of having given false evidence before B, 
      a Magistrate. B cannot be asked what A said, except 
      upon the special order of the superior Court.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A is accused 
      before the Court of Sessions of attempting to murder a police officer 
      whilst on his trial before B, a Sessions Judge. B may be 
      examined as to what occurred. 
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>122</number> 
    Communications during marriage.—No 
    person who is or has been married, shall be compelled to disclose any 
    communication made to him during marriage by any person to whom he is or has 
    been married; nor shall he be permitted to disclose any such communication, 
    unless the person who made it, or his representative in interest, consents, 
    except in suits between married persons, or proceedings in which one married 
    person is prosecuted for any crime committed against the other. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>123</number> 
    Evidence as to affairs of State.—No 
    one shall be permitted to give any evidence derived from unpublished 
    official records relating to any affairs of State, except with the 
    permission of the officer at the head of the department concerned, who shall 
    give or withhold such permission as he thinks fit. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>124</number> 
    Official communications.—No public 
    officer shall be compelled to disclose communications made to him in 
    official confidence, when he considers that the public interests would 
    suffer by the disclosure. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>125</number> Information as 
    to commission of offences.—No 
    Magistrate or Police officer shall be compelled to say whence he got any 
    information as to the commission of any offence, and no Revenue officer 
    shall be compelled to say whence he got any information as to the commission 
    of any offence against the public revenue.1[125. 
    Information as to commission of offences.—No 
    Magistrate or Police officer shall be compelled to say whence he got any 
    information as to the commission of any offence, and no Revenue officer 
    shall be compelled to say whence he got any information as to the commission 
    of any offence against the public revenue." 
 
Explanation.—"Revenue 
    officer” in this section means an officer employed in or about the business 
    of any branch of the public revenue.] 
 
 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>126</number> 
    Professional communications.—No 
    barrister, attorney, pleader or vakil shall at any time be permitted, 
    unless with his client’s express consent, to disclose any communication made 
    to him in the course and for the purpose of his employment as such 
    barrister, pleader, attorney or vakil, by or on behalf of his client, 
    or to state the contents or condition of any document with which he has 
    become acquainted in the course and for the purpose of his professional 
    employment, or to disclose any advice given by him to his client in the 
    course and for the purpose of such employment: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall protect from disclosure— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    Any such communication made in 
    furtherance of any 
1[illegal] 
    purpose;
2[illegal] 
    purpose;" 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    Any fact observed by any barrister, 
    pleader, attorney or vakil, in the course of his employment as such, 
    showing that any crime or fraud has been committed since the commencement of 
    his employment. 
 
It is 
    immaterial whether the attention of such barrister, 

    2[pleader], attorney or
    vakil was or was not directed to such fact by or on behalf of his 
    client. 
 
 Explanation.—The 
    obligation stated in this section continues after the employment has ceased. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> A, a client, says 
      to B, an attorney—“I have committed forgery, and I wish you to 
      defend me”.
 
As the defence of a man known 
      to be guilty is not a criminal purpose, this communication is protected 
      from disclosure.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> A, a client, says 
      to B, an attorney—“I wish to obtain possession of property by the 
      use of a forged deed on which I request you to sue”.
 
This communication, being made 
      in furtherance of a criminal purpose, is not protected from disclosure.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> A, being charged 
      with embezzlement, retains B, an attorney, to defend him. In the 
      course of the proceedings, B observes that an entry has been made 
      in A’s account-book, charging A with the sum said to have 
      been embezzled, which entry was not in the book at the commencement of his 
      employment.
 
This being a fact observed by
      B in the course of his employment, showing that a fraud has been 
      committed since the commencement of the proceedings, it is not protected 
      from disclosure.
 

 
</subsection>
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>127</number> Section 
    126 to apply to interpreters, etc.—The 
    provisions of section 126 shall apply to interpreters, and the clerks or 
    servants of barristers, pleaders, attorneys, and vakils. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>128</number> 
    Privilege not waived by volunteering evidence.—If 
    any party to a suit gives evidence therein at his own instance or otherwise, 
    he shall not be deemed to have consented thereby to such disclosure as is 
    mentioned in section 126; and if any party to a suit or proceeding calls any 
    such barrister, 

    1[pleader], attorney or
    vakil as a witness, he shall be deemed to have consented to such 
    disclosure only if he questions such barrister, attorney or vakil on 
    matters which, but for such question, he would not be at liberty to 
    disclose.—If 
    any party to a suit gives evidence therein at his own instance or otherwise, 
    he shall not be deemed to have consented thereby to such disclosure as is 
    mentioned in section 126; and if any party to a suit or proceeding calls any 
    such barrister, 

    1[pleader], attorney or
    vakil as a witness, he shall be deemed to have consented to such 
    disclosure only if he questions such barrister, attorney or vakil on 
    matters which, but for such question, he would not be at liberty to 
    disclose." 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>129</number> 
    Confidential communications with legal advisers.—No 
    one shall be compelled to disclose to the Court any confidential 
    communication which has taken place between him and his legal professional 
    adviser, unless he offers himself as a witness, in which case he may be 
    compelled to disclose any such communications as may appear to the Court 
    necessary to be known in order to explain any evidence which he has given, 
    but no others. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>130</number> 
    Production of title-deeds of witness not a party.—No 
    witness who is not a party to a suit shall be compelled to produce his 
    title-deeds to any property, or any document in virtue of which he holds any 
    property as pledgee or mortgagee, or any document the production of which 
    might tend to criminate him, unless he has agreed in writing to produce them 
    with the person seeking the production of such deeds or some person through 
    whom he claims. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>131</number> Production of 
    documents or electronic records which another person, having possession, 
    could refuse to produce.—No 
    one shall be compelled to produce documents in his possession or electronic 
    records under his control, which any other person would be entitled to 
    refuse to produce if they were in his possession, or control, unless such 
    last-mentioned person consents to their production.]2[131. 
    Production of documents or electronic records which another person, having 
    possession, could refuse to produce.—No 
    one shall be compelled to produce documents in his possession or electronic 
    records under his control, which any other person would be entitled to 
    refuse to produce if they were in his possession, or control, unless such 
    last-mentioned person consents to their production.]" 
 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>132</number> Witness 
    not excused from answering on ground that answer will criminate.—A 
    witness shall not be excused from answering any question as to any matter 
    relevant to the matter in issue in any suit or in any civil or criminal 
    proceeding, upon the ground that the answer to such question will criminate, 
    or may tend directly or indirectly to criminate, such witness, or that it 
    will expose, or tend directly or indirectly to expose, such witness to a 
    penalty or forfeiture of any kind: 
 <section>
<number>Proviso</number>—Provided 
    that no such answer, which a witness shall be compelled to give, shall 
    subject him to any arrest or prosecution, or be proved against him in any 
    criminal proceeding, except a prosecution for giving false evidence by such 
    answer. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>133</number> 
    Accomplice.—An accomplice shall be 
    a competent witness against an accused person; and a conviction is not 
    illegal merely because it proceeds upon the uncorroborated testimony of an 
    accomplice. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>134</number> Number 
    of witnesses.—No particular number 
    of witnesses shall in any case be required for the proof of any fact. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>135</number> Order 
    of production and examination of witnesses.—The 
    order in which witnesses are produced and examined shall be regulated by the 
    law and practice for the time being relating to civil and criminal procedure 
    respectively, and, in the absence of any such law, by the discretion of the 
    Court. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>136</number> Judge 
    to decide as to admissibility of evidence.—When 
    either party proposes to give evidence of any fact, the Judge may ask the 
    party proposing to give the evidence in what manner the alleged fact, if 
    proved, would be relevant; and the Judge shall admit the evidence if he 
    thinks that the fact, if proved, would be relevant, and not otherwise. 
 
If the fact 
    proposed to be proved is one of which evidence is admissible only upon proof 
    of some other fact, such last-mentioned fact must be proved before evidence 
    is given of the fact first mentioned, unless the party undertakes to give 
    proof of such fact, and the Court is satisfied with such undertaking. 
 
If the 
    relevancy of one alleged fact depends upon another alleged fact being first 
    proved, the Judge may, in his discretion, either permit evidence of the 
    first fact to be given before the second fact is proved, or require evidence 
    to be given of the second fact before evidence is given of the first fact. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> It is proposed to prove a 
      statement about a relevant fact by a person alleged to be dead, which 
      statement is relevant under section 32.
 
The fact that the person is 
      dead must be proved by the person proposing to prove the statement, before 
      evidence is given of the statement.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> It is proposed to prove, 
      by a copy, the contents of a document said to be lost.
 
The fact that the original is 
      lost must be proved by the person proposing to produce the copy, before 
      the copy is produced.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> 
      A is accused of receiving stolen property knowing it to have been 
      stolen.  
 
It is 
      proposed to prove that he denied the possession of the property.  
 
The 
      relevancy of the denial depends on the identity of the property. The Court 
      may, in its discretion, either require the property to be identified 
      before the denial of the possession is proved, or permit the denial of the 
      possession to be proved before the property is identified.  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> 
      It is proposed to prove a fact (A) which is said to have been the cause or 
      effect of a fact in issue. There are several intermediate facts (B, C 
      and D) which must be shown to exist before the fact (A) can be 
      regarded as the cause or effect of the fact in issue. The Court may either 
      permit A to be proved before B, C or D is proved, or 
      may require proof of B, C and D before permitting proof of
      A.  
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>137</number> 
    Examination-in-chief.—The 
    examination of a witness by the party who calls him shall be called his 
    examination-in-chief. 
 

    Cross-examination.—The examination 
    of a witness by the adverse party shall be called his cross-examination. 
 

    Re-examination.—The examination of 
    a witness, subsequent to the cross-examination by the party who called him, 
    shall be called his re-examination. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>138</number> Order 
    of examinations.—Witnesses shall 
    be first examined-in-chief, then (if the adverse party so desires) 
    cross-examined, then (if the party calling him so desires) re-examined. 
 
The examination 
    and cross-examination must relate to relevant facts, but the 
    cross-examination need not be confined to the facts to which the witness 
    testified on his examination-in-chief. 
 
Direction of 
    re-examination.—The re-examination 
    shall be directed to the explanation of matters referred to in 
    cross-examination; and, if new matter is, by permission of the Court, 
    introduced in re-examination, the adverse party may further cross-examine 
    upon that matter. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>139</number> 
    Cross-examination of person called to produce a document.—A 
    person summoned to produce a document does not become a witness by the mere 
    fact that he produces it, and cannot be cross-examined unless and until he 
    is called as a witness. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>140</number> Witnesses to character.—Witnesses to character may be cross-examined 
      and re-examined. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>141</number> Leading 
    questions.—Any question suggesting 
    the answer which the person putting it wishes or expects to receive, is 
    called a leading question. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>142</number> When 
    they must not be asked.—Leading 
    questions must not, if objected to by the adverse party, be asked in an 
    examination-in-chief, or in a re-examination, except with the permission of 
    the Court. 
 
The Court shall 
    permit leading questions as to matters which are introductory or undisputed, 
    or which have, in its opinion, been already sufficiently proved. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>143</number> When 
    they may be asked.—Leading 
    questions may be asked in cross-examination. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>144</number> 
    Evidence as to matters in writing.—Any 
    witness may be asked, whilst under examination, whether any contract, grant 
    or other disposition of property, as to which he is giving evidence, was not 
    contained in a document, and if he says that it was, or if he is about to 
    make any statement as to the contents of any document, which, in the opinion 
    of the Court, ought to be produced, the adverse party may object to such 
    evidence being given until such document is produced, or until facts have 
    been proved which entitle the party who called the witness to give secondary 
    evidence of it. 
 
Explanation.—A 
    witness may give oral evidence of statements made by other persons about the 
    contents of documents if such statements are in themselves relevant facts. 
 
 
Illustration
 
The question is, whether A
      assaulted B.
 
C deposes that he heard 
      A say to D—"B wrote a letter accusing me of theft, and I will 
      be revenged on him”. This statement is relevant as showing A’s 
      motive for the assault, and evidence may be given of it, though no other 
      evidence is given about the letter.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>117</footcitenum><number>145</number> 
    Cross-examination as to previous statements in writing.—A 
    witness may be cross-examined as to previous statements made by him in 
    writing or reduced into writing, and relevant to matters in question, 
    without such writing being shown to him, or being proved; but, if it is 
    intended to contradict him by the writing, his attention must, before the 
    writing can be proved, be called to those parts of it which are to be used 
    for the purpose of contradicting him.1145. 
    Cross-examination as to previous statements in writing.—A 
    witness may be cross-examined as to previous statements made by him in 
    writing or reduced into writing, and relevant to matters in question, 
    without such writing being shown to him, or being proved; but, if it is 
    intended to contradict him by the writing, his attention must, before the 
    writing can be proved, be called to those parts of it which are to be used 
    for the purpose of contradicting him." 
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>146</number> 
    Questions lawful in cross-examination.—When 
    a witness is cross-examined, he may, in addition to the questions 
    hereinbefore referred to, be asked any questions which tend— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    to test his veracity, 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    to discover who he is and what is his 
    position in life, or 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    to shake his credit, by injuring his 
    character, although the answer to such questions might tend directly or 
    indirectly to criminate him or might expose or tend directly or indirectly 
    to expose him to a penalty or forfeiture: 
 


    1[Provided that in a 
    prosecution for rape or attempt to commit rape, it shall not be permissible 
    to put questions in the cross-examination of the prosecutrix as to her 
    general immoral character.] 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>147</number> When 
    witness to be compelled to answer.—If 
    any such question relates to a matter relevant to the suit or proceeding, 
    the provisions of section 132 shall apply thereto. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>148</number> Court 
    to decide when question shall be asked and when witness compelled to answer.—If 
    any such question relates to a matter not relevant to the suit or 
    proceeding, except in so far as it affects the credit of the witness by 
    injuring his character, the Court shall decide whether or not the witness 
    shall be compelled to answer it, and may, if it thinks fit, warn the witness 
    that he is not obliged to answer it. In exercising its discretion, the Court 
    shall have regard to the following considerations:— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    Such questions are proper if they are 
    of such a nature that the truth of the imputation conveyed by them would 
    seriously affect the opinion of the Court as to the credibility of the 
    witness on the matter to which he testifies; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    Such questions are improper if the 
    imputation which they convey relates to matters so remote in time, or of 
    such a character, that the truth of the imputation would not affect, or 
    would affect in a slight degree, the opinion of the Court as to the 
    credibility of the witness on the matter to which he testifies; 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    Such questions are improper if there is 
    a great disproportion between the importance of the imputation made against 
    the witness’s character and the importance of his evidence; 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>    The Court may, if it sees fit, draw, 
    from the witness’s refusal to answer, the inference that the answer if given 
    would be unfavourable. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>149</number> 
    Question not to be asked without reasonable grounds.—No 
    such question as is referred to in section 148 ought to be asked, unless the 
    person asking it has reasonable grounds for thinking that the imputation 
    which it conveys is well-founded. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A barrister is instructed 
      by an attorney or vakil that an important witness is a dakait. 
      This is a reasonable ground for asking the witness whether he is a 
      dakait.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A pleader is informed by a 
      person in Court that an important witness is a dakait. The 
      informant, on being questioned by the pleader, gives satisfactory reasons 
      for his statement. This is a reasonable ground for asking the witness 
      whether he is a dakait.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A witness, of whom 
      nothing whatever is known, is asked at random whether he is a dakait. 
      There are here no reasonable grounds for the question.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A witness, of whom 
      nothing whatever is known, being questioned as to his mode of life and 
      means of living, gives unsatisfactory answers. This may be a reasonable 
      ground for asking him if he is a dakait.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>150</number> 
    Procedure of Court in case of question being asked without reasonable 
    grounds.—If the Court is of 
    opinion that any such question was asked without reasonable grounds, it may, 
    if it was asked by any barrister, pleader, vakil or attorney, report 
    the circumstances of the case to the High Court or other authority to which 
    such barrister, pleader, vakil or attorney is the subject in the 
    exercise of his profession. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>151</number> 
    Indecent and scandalous questions.—The 
    Court may forbid any questions or inquiries which it regards as indecent or 
    scandalous, although such questions or inquiries may have some bearing on 
    the questions before the Court, unless they relate to facts in issue, or to 
    matters necessary to be known in order to determine whether or not the facts 
    in issue existed. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>152</number> 
    Questions intended to insult or annoy.—The 
    Court shall forbid any question which appears to it to be intended to insult 
    or annoy, or which, though proper in itself, appears to the Court needlessly 
    offensive in form. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>153</number> 
    Exclusion of evidence to contradict answers to questions testing  veracity.—When 
    a witness has been asked and has answered any question which is relevant to 
    the inquiry only in so far as it tends to shake his credit by injuring his 
    character, no evidence shall be given to contradict him; but, if he answers 
    falsely, he may afterwards be charged with giving false evidence. 
 
Exception
    1.—If a witness is asked whether 
    he has been previously convicted of any crime and denies it, evidence may be 
    given of his previous conviction. 
 
Exception
    2.—If a witness is asked any 
    question tending to impeach his impartiality, and answers it by denying the 
    facts suggested, he may be contradicted. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <section>
<number>a</number> A claim against an 
      underwriter is resisted on the ground of fraud.
 
The claimant is asked whether, 
      in a former transaction, he had not made a fraudulent claim. He denies it.
 
Evidence is offered to show 
      that he did make such a claim.
 
The evidence is inadmissible.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> A witness is asked whether 
      he was not dismissed from a situation for dishonesty. He denies it.
 
Evidence is offered to show 
      that he was dismissed for dishonesty.
 
The evidence is not 
      admissible.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> A affirms that on a 
      certain day he saw B at Lahore.
 
A is asked whether he 
      himself was not on that day at Calcutta. He denies it.
 
Evidence is offered to show 
      that A was on that day at Calcutta.
 
The evidence is admissible, 
      not as contradicting A on a fact which affects his credit, but as 
      contradicting the alleged fact that B was seen on the day in 
      question in Lahore.
 
In each of these cases the 
      witness might, if his denial was false, be charged with giving false 
      evidence.
 </section><section>
<number>d</number> A is asked whether 
      his family has not had a blood feud with the family of B against 
      whom he gives evidence.
 
He denies it. He may be 
      contradicted on the ground that the question tends to impeach his 
      impartiality.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>154</number> 
    Question by party to his own witness.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    The Court may, in its discretion, permit the person who calls a witness to 
    put any question to him which might be put in cross-examination by the 
    adverse party.—1[(1)] 
    The Court may, in its discretion, permit the person who calls a witness to 
    put any question to him which might be put in cross-examination by the 
    adverse party." 
 


    2[(2) Nothing in this 
    section shall disentitle the person so permitted under sub-section (1), to 
    rely on any part of the evidence of such witness.] 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
155. 
    Impeaching credit of witness.—The 
    credit of a witness may be impeached in the following ways by the adverse 
    party, or with the consent of the Court, by the party who calls him:— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    By the evidence of persons who testify 
    that they, from their knowledge of the witness believe him to be unworthy of 
    credit; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    By proof that the witness has 
    been bribed, or has 
1[accepted] 
    the offer of a bribe, or has received any other corrupt inducement to give 
    his evidence;
1[accepted] 
    the offer of a bribe, or has received any other corrupt inducement to give 
    his evidence;" 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    By proof of former statements 
    inconsistent with any part of his evidence which is liable to be 
    contradicted; 
 

2[***] 2[***]" 
 
Explanation.—A 
    witness declaring another witness to be unworthy of credit may not, upon his 
    examination-in-chief, give reasons for his belief, but he may be asked his 
    reasons in cross-examination, and the answers which he gives cannot be 
    contradicted, though, if they are false, he may afterwards be charged with 
    giving false evidence. 
 
 
Illustrations
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> A sues B for 
      the price of goods sold and delivered to B. 
 
C says that he 
      delivered the goods to B.
 
Evidence is offered to show 
      that, on a previous occasion, he said that he had not delivered the goods 
      to B.
 
The evidence is admissible.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> A is indicted for 
      the murder of B.
 
C says the B, 
      when dying, declared that A had given B the wound of which 
      he died.
 
Evidence is offered to show 
      that, on a previous occasion, C said that the wound was not given 
      by A or in his presence.
 
The evidence is admissible.
 

 
</subsection>






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>156</number> 
    Questions tending to corroborate evidence of relevant fact, admissible.—When 
    a witness whom it is intended to corroborate gives evidence of any relevant 
    fact, he may be questioned as to any other circumstances which he observed 
    at or near to the time or place at which such relevant fact occurred, if the 
    Court is of opinion that such circumstances, if proved, would corroborate 
    the testimony of the witness as to the relevant fact which he testifies. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A, an accomplice, gives 
      an account of a robbery in which he took part. He describes various 
      incidents unconnected with the robbery which occurred on his way to and 
      from the place where it was committed.
 
Independent evidence of these 
      facts may be given in order to corroborate his evidence as to the robbery 
      itself.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>157</number> Former 
    statements of witness may be proved to corroborate later testimony as to 
    same fact.—In order to corroborate 
    the testimony of a witness, any former statement made by such witness 
    relating to the same fact, at or about the time when the fact took place, or 
    before any authority legally competent to investigate the fact, may be 
    proved. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>158</number> What 
    matters may be proved in connection with proved statement relevant under 
    section 32 or 33.—Whenever any 
    statement, relevant under section 32 or 33, is proved, all matters may be 
    proved, either in order to contradict or to corroborate it, or in order to 
    impeach or confirm the credit of the person by whom it was made, which might 
    have been proved if that person had been called as a witness and had denied 
    upon cross-examination of the truth the matter suggested. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>159</number> 
    Refreshing memory.—A witness may, 
    while under examination, refresh his memory by referring to any writing made 
    by himself at the time of the transaction concerning which he is questioned, 
    or so soon afterwards that the Court considers it likely that the 
    transaction was at that time fresh in his memory. 
 
The witness may 
    also refer to any such writing made by any other person, and read by the 
    witness within the time aforesaid, if when he read it he knew it to be 
    correct. 
 
When witness 
    may use copy of document to refresh memory.—Whenever 
    a witness may refresh his memory by reference to any document, he may, with 
    the permission of the Court, refer to a copy of such document: 
 
Provided the 
    Court be satisfied that there is sufficient reason for the non-production of 
    the original. 
 
An expert may 
    refresh his memory by reference to professional treatises. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>160</number> Testimony to facts stated in document 
      mentioned in section 159.—A 
      witness may also testify to facts mentioned in any such document as is 
      mentioned in section 159, although he has no specific recollection of the 
      facts themselves, if he is sure that the facts were correctly recorded in 
      the document. 
 
 Illustration
 A book-keeper 
        may testify to facts recorded by him in books regularly kept in the 
        course of business, if he knows that the books were correctly kept, 
        although he has forgotten the particular transactions 
      entered.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>123</footcitenum><number>161</number> Right of 
    adverse party as to writing used to refresh memory.—Any 
    writing referred to under the provisions of the two last preceding sections 
    must be produced and shown to the adverse party if he requires it; such 
    party may, if he pleases, cross-examine the witness thereupon.1161. 
    Right of adverse party as to writing used to refresh memory.—Any 
    writing referred to under the provisions of the two last preceding sections 
    must be produced and shown to the adverse party if he requires it; such 
    party may, if he pleases, cross-examine the witness thereupon." 
 

 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>162</number> 
    Production of documents.—A witness 
    summoned to produce a document shall, if it is in his possession or power, 
    bring it to the Court, notwithstanding any objection which there may be to 
    its production or to its admissibility. The validity of any such objection 
    shall be decided on by the Court. 
 
The Court, if 
    it sees, fit, may inspect the document, unless it refers to matters of 
    State, or take other evidence to enable it to determine on its 
    admissibility. 
 
Translation 
    of documents.—If for such a 
    purpose it is necessary to cause any document to be translated, the Court 
    may, if it thinks fit, direct the translator to keep the contents secret, 
    unless the document is to be given in evidence : and, if the interpreter 
    disobeys such direction, he shall be held to have committed an offence under 
    section 166 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>163</number> Giving, 
    as evidence, of document called for and produced on notice.—When 
    a party calls for a document which he has given the other party notice to 
    produce, and such document is produced and inspected by the party calling 
    for its production, he is bound to give it as evidence if the party 
    producing it requires him to do so. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>164</number> Using, 
    as evidence, of document, production of which was refused on notice.—When 
    a party refuses to produce a document which he has had notice to produce, he 
    cannot afterwards use the document as evidence without the consent of the 
    other party or the order of the Court. 
 
 
Illustration
 
A sues B on an 
      agreement and gives B notice to produce it. At the trial, A 
      calls for the document and B refuses to produce it. A gives 
      secondary evidence of its contents. B seeks to produce the document 
      itself to contradict the secondary evidence given by A, or in order 
      to show that the agreement is not stamped. He cannot do so.


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>165</number> Judge’s 
    power to put questions or order production.—The 
    Judge may, in order to discover or to obtain proper proof of relevant facts, 
    ask any question he pleases, in any form, at any time, of any witness, or of 
    the parties, about any fact relevant or irrelevant; and may order the 
    production of any document or thing; and neither the parties nor their 
    agents shall be entitled to make any objection to any such question or 
    order, nor, without the leave of the Court, to cross-examine any witness 
    upon any answer given in reply to any such question: 
 
Provided that 
    the Judgment must be based upon facts declared by this Act to be relevant, 
    and duly proved: 
 
Provided also 
    that this section shall not authorize any Judge to compel any witness to 
    answer any question, or to produce any document which such witness would be 
    entitled to refuse to answer or produce under sections 121 to 131, both 
    inclusive, if the questions were asked or the documents were called for by 
    the adverse party; nor shall the Judge ask any question which it would be 
    improper for any other person to ask under section 148 or 149; nor shall he 
    dispense with primary evidence of any document, except in the cases 
    hereinbefore excepted. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>166</number> Power 
    of jury or assessors to put questions.—In 
    cases tried by jury or with assessors, the jury or assessors may put any 
    question to the witnesses, through or by leave of the Judge, which the Judge 
    himself might put and which he considers proper. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>167</number> No new 
    trial for improper admission or rejection of evidence.—The 
    improper admission or rejection of evidence shall not be ground of itself 
    for a new trial or reversal of any decision in any case, if it shall appear 
    to the Court before which such objection is raised that, independently of 
    the evidence objected to and admitted, there was sufficient evidence to 
    justify the decision, or that, if the rejected evidence had been received, 
    it ought not to have varied the decision. 

 
  


</article><form>
 

 THE INDIAN EVIDENCE ACT, 1872 
 

 
 


 

SCHEDULE 
 

Enactments
repealed.—[Rep. by the Repealing Act, 1938 (1 of 1938) sec.
2 and Sch.]    
 

  

</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Cf. the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (Act 5 of 1908), sec. 
2, the Indian Penal Code (Act 45 of 1860), sec. 19; and, for a definition of 
“District Judge,” the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of  1897), sec. 3 (17).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Cf. the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), sec. 3 (32) 
and the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (Act 2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  See  now the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
1908) as to the settlement of issues,  see  Sch. I, Order XIV.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Cf. the Indian Penal Code (Act 45 of 1860), sec. 29 and the 
General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897), sec. 3 (18).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Cf. definition of “writing in the General Clauses Act, 1897 
(10 of 1897), sec. 3 (65).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–1(a), for “all 
documents produced for the inspection of the Court” (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for the definitions 
of “State“ and “States”. Earlier the definitions of “State” and “States” were 
inserted by the A.O. 1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–1(b) (w.e.f. 
17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2009, sec. 52(a), for “digital signature” 
and “Digital Signature Certificate” respectively (w.e.f. 27-10-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   See now the 
      Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908). tc " 1. 
    See now the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by the 
      A.O. 1950, for “Queen”. tc " 1. Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950, for “Queen”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950, for “Queen”. tc " 1. Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950, for “Queen”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
      1891, sec. 1, for the original Explanation. tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 3 of 1891, sec. 1, for the original Explanation."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
      1891, sec. 1, for Illustration (b). tc " 2. 
    Subs. by Act 3 of 1891, sec. 1, for Illustration (b)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Ins. by Act 3 of 
      1891, sec. 2. tc " 1. Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, sec. 2."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by Act 21 of 
    2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for “oral or documentary” (w.e.f. 17-10-2000). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for “oral or documentary” 
    (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Ins. by Act 21 of 
    2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000). tc " 1. 
    Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>   For prohibition of 
    such inducements, etc., see the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1973 (2 of 1974), section 316. tc " 2. For prohibition 
    of such inducements, etc., see the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1973 (2 of 1974), section 316."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   As to statements made 
    to a police officer investigating a case, see the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 162. tc " 1. As 
    to statements made to a police officer investigating a case, see the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 162."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   A Coroner has been 
    declared to be Magistrate for the purposes of this section, see the 
    Coroners Act, 1871 (4 of 1871), section 20.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, 
    sec. 3. tc " 3. Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, sec. 3."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>   The  words "or in 
    Burma" omitted by the A.O. 1937. tc " 4. The  words 
    \"or in Burma\" omitted by the A.O. 1937."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>   See now the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974). tc " 5.
    See now the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>   Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, 
    sec. 4. tc " 1. Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, sec. 4."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Ins. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>   Subs. by Act 21 of 
    2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for “Entries in the books of account” (w.e.f. 
    17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>   Subs. by the Act 21 of 
    2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for “record” (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1948, for “any Government in British India."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>   Ins. by 
      the A.O. 1950. tc 
    " 3. Ins. by the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number>   The 
      original words were "Act of the Governor General of India in Council or of 
      the Governors in Council of Madras or Bombay, or of the Lieutenant 
      Governor in Council of Bengal, or in a notification of the Government 
      appearing in the Gazette of India, or in the Gazette of any L.G. or in any 
      printed paper purporting to be the London Gazette or the Government 
      Gazette of any colony or possession of the Queen, is a relevant fact". 
      This was amended first by  the Repealing and Amending Act, 1914 (10 
      of 1914) and then by the A.O. 1937, the A.O. 1948 and the A.O. 1950 to 
      read as above. tc " 4. The 
    original words were \"Act of the Governor General of India in Council or of 
    the Governors in Council of Madras or Bombay, or of the Lieutenant Governor 
    in Council of Bengal, or in a notification of the Government appearing in 
    the Gazette of India, or in the Gazette of any L.G. or in any printed paper 
    purporting to be the London Gazette or the Government Gazette of any colony 
    or possession of the Queen, is a relevant fact\". This was amended first by  
    the Repealing and Amending Act, 1914 (10 of 1914) and then by the A.O. 1937, 
    the A.O. 1948 and the A.O. 1950 to read as above."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>   Subs. by 
      Act 3 of 1951 sec. 3 and Sch., for "an Act of the Legislature of 
      Part  A State or a Part C State". tc " 5. Subs. by Act 3 of 1951 sec. 3 and Sch., 
    for \"an Act of the Legislature of Part  A State or a Part C State\"."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number>   The last 
      para added by Act 5 of 1899, sec. 2, and omitted by Act 10 of 1914, sec. 3 
      and Sch. II. tc 
    " 1. The last para added by Act 5 of 1899, sec. 2, and omitted by Act 10 of 
    1914, sec. 3 and 
    Sch. II."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>   Subs. by Act 21 of 
    2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for section 39 (w.e.f. 17-10-2000). tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for section 39 (w.e.f. 
    17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number>   Ins. by Act 18 of 
    1872, sec. 3. tc " 3. Ins. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 3."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>  Ins. by Act 5 of 1899, sec. 
    3. For discussion in Council as to whether "finger impressions" include 
    "thumb impressions",  see Gazette of India, 1898, Pt. VI, p. 24. tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 5 of 1899, sec. 3. For discussion in Council as to whether 
    \"finger impressions\" include \"thumb impressions\",  see Gazette of 
    India, 1898, Pt. VI, p. 24."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number>   Ins. by Act 18 of 1872, 
    sec. 4. tc " 3. Ins. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 4."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number> Ins. by Act 10 of 2009, sec. 52(b) (w.e.f. 
27-10-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–7 (w.e.f. 
17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2009, sec. 52(c)(i), for “digital 
signature” (w.e.f. 27-10-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2009, sec. 52(c)(ii), for “Digital 
Signature Certificate” (w.e.f. 27-10-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
      1891, sec. 6, for section 54. tc " 1. Subs. by Act 3 
    of 1891, sec. 6, for section 54."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number>   Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, 
      sec. 7. tc " 2. Ins. by Act 3 of 1891, sec. 7."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, 
      for para (1).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 
      1950.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, 
      for "Her Majesty's".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number>   Subs. by Act 10 of 1927, 
      sec. 25 and Sch. I, for "or Navy".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, 
      for para 4.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1948, 
      for "Courts of British India".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, 
      sec. 3 and Sch., for "the States".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1937, 
      for the "the G.G. or any L.G. in Council".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 1950, 
      "any Act of Parliament or other".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>   Subs. by Act 21 of 2000, 
      sec. 92 and Sch. II, for “contents of documents” (w.e.f. 17-10-2000). tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for “contents of 
    documents” (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>   See section 76
    infra. tc " 1. See section 76 infra."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>   Subs. by Act 3 
    of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”.   tc  
    " 1. Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>  Cf. the 
    Bankers’ Books Evidence Act, 1891 (18 of 1891), section 4.   tc 
    " 2. Cf. the Bankers’ Books Evidence Act, 1891 (18 of 1891), section 4."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>   Ins. by Act 21 
    of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).   tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>   Ins. by Act 21 
    of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).   tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number>   Ins. by Act 18 
    of 1872, sec. 6.   tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 6."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–10 (w.e.f. 
17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number>   Ins. by Act 31 
    of 1926, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number>   Ins. by Act 5 
    of 1899, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number>   Ins. by Act 21 
    of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).   tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number>   The original words 
    “whether of British India, or of any other part of Her Majesty's dominions” 
    have successively been amended by the A.O. 1948 and the A.O. 1950 to read as 
    above.   tc 
    " 1. The original words “whether of British India, or of any other part of 
    Her Majesty's dominions” have successively been amended by the A.O. 1948 and 
    the A.O. 1950 to read as above."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number>   Subs. by the A.O. 
    1950, for “in any province”.   tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “in any province”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number>   A Village-officer 
    in the Punjab has been declared for the purposes of this Act to be a public 
    officer having the custody of a public document—see the Punjab Land 
    Revenue Act, 1887 (17 of 1887), section 151(2).   tc 
    " 3. A Village-officer in the Punjab has been declared for the purposes of 
    this Act to be a public officer having the custody of a public document—see 
    the Punjab Land Revenue Act, 1887 (17 of 1887), section 151 (2)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for “the Executive Government of British India”.   tc 
    " 4. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “the Executive Government of British 
    India”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number>   Ins. by the 
    A.O. 1937.   tc 
    " 5. Ins. by the A.O. 1937."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for “by order of Government”.   tc 
    " 6. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “by order of Government”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>69</number>   The words “Her 
    Majesty” stand unmodified see the A.O. 1950.   tc 
    " 7. The words “Her Majesty” stand unmodified see the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>70</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for “public Act of the Governor  General of India in Council”.   tc 
    " 1. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “public Act of the Governor  General of 
    India in Council”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>71</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O.  1950, for “a Province”.   tc 
    " 2. Subs. by the A.O.  1950, for “a Province”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>72</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950, for “a  British Consul”.   tc 
    " 3. Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “a  British Consul”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>73</number>   Ins. by the A.O. 
    1948.   tc 
    " 4. Ins. by the A.O. 1948."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>74</number>   The original word 
    beginning from “in British India” and ending with the words “to be genuine” 
    have been successively amended by the A.O. 1937, A.O. 1948 and A.O. 1950 to 
    read as above.   tc 
    " 5. The original word beginning from “in British India” and ending with the 
    words “to be genuine” have been successively amended by the A.O. 1937, A.O. 
    1948 and A.O. 1950 to read as above."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>75</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “in a Part B State”.   tc 
    " 6. Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “in a Part B State”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>76</number> 
        Subs. by A.O. 1937, for “the Gazette of India or the Government 
      Gazette of any L.G., or”.   tc 
    " 1. Subs. by A.O. 1937, for “the Gazette of India or the Government Gazette 
    of any L.G., or”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>77</number> 
        Ins. by the A.O. 1950.   tc 
    " 2. Ins. by the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>78</number>   Ins. by Act 21 
    of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).   tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>79</number>   The original word 
    “Government” has successively been amended by the A.O. 1937, A.O. 1948, Act 
    40 of 1949, A.O. 1950, to read as above.   tc 
    " 4. The original word “Government” has successively been amended by the 
    A.O. 1937, A.O. 1948, Act 40 of 1949, A.O. 1950, to read as above."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>80</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1950, for “British”.   tc 
    " 1. Subs. by the A.O. 1950, for “British”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>81</number>   The words “of 
    Her Majesty, or” omitted by the A.O. 1950.   tc 
    " 2. The words “of Her Majesty, or” omitted by the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>82</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for “Government of India”.   tc 
    " 3. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Government of India”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>83</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–13 (w.e.f. 
17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>84</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–13 (w.e.f. 
17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>85</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–13 (w.e.f. 
17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>86</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2009, sec. 52(g), for “Digital Signature 
Certificates” (w.e.f. 27-10-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>87</number>   Subs. by A.O. 
    1950, for “any country not forming part”.   tc  
    " 5. Subs. by A.O. 1950, for “any country not forming part”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>88</number>   The words “a 
    Part B State or of” omitted by Act 3 of 1951, sec.  3 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>89</number>   The words “Her 
    Majesty or of” omitted by the A.O. 1950.   tc 
    " 7. The words “Her Majesty or of” omitted by the A.O. 1950."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>90</number>   Subs. by the 
    A.O. 1937, for “Government of India”.   tc  
    " 8. Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “Government of India”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>91</number>   Subs. by Act 3 
    of 1891, sec 8, for “resident in”.   tc  
    " 9. Subs. by Act 3 of 1891, sec 8, for “resident in”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>92</number>   Subs. by Act 3 
    of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “such Part B State or country”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>93</number>   Subs. by  Act 3 
    of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “that State or country”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>94</number>   Subs. by Act 5 
    of 1899, sec. 4, for the para added by Act 3 of 1891, sec. 3.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>95</number>   The words “a 
    Part B State or” which were ins. by the A.O. 1950, omitted by Act 3 of 1951, 
    sec. 3 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>96</number>   Ins. by Act 21 
    of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).   tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II (w.e.f. 17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>97</number> Ins. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II–15 (w.e.f. 
17-10-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>98</number> Subs. by Act 10 of 2009, sec. 52(h), for “digital signature” 
(w.e.f. 27-10-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>99</number>   Where, however, a 
      criminal court finds that a confession or other statements of an accused 
      person has not been  recorded in the manner prescribed, evidence may 
      be taken that the recorded statement was duly made see the Code of 
      Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 463.   tc 
    " 2. Where, however, a criminal court finds that a confession or other 
    statements of an accused person has not been  recorded in the manner 
    prescribed, evidence may be taken that the recorded statement was duly made 
    see the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 463."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>100</number>   Subs. by Act 18 of 
      1872, sec. 7, for “under the Indian Succession Act”.   tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 7, for “under the Indian Succession 
    Act”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>101</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
      1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”.   tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “the States”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>102</number> Subs. by 
    Act 18 of 1872, sec. 8, “for want of failure”.   tc  
    " 3. Subs. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 8, “for want of failure”."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>103</number>   See now the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 
      1925), Pt. VI, Ch. VI.   tc 
    " 1. See now the Indian Succession Act, 1925 (39 of 1925), Pt. VI, 
    Ch. VI."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>104</number>   Sic. In the Act  as published in  Gazette 
      of India, 1872, Pt. IV, p. 1, there is no illustration (b).   tc 
    " 1. Sic. In the Act  as published in  Gazette of India, 1872, Pt. 
    IV, p. 1, there is no illustration (b)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>105</number>   Subs. by Act 18 
    of 1872, sec. 9, for "When".   tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 9, for \"When\"."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>106</number>   Subs. by  Act 
    18 of 1872, sec. 9, for "on".   tc 
    " 2. Subs. by  Act 18 of 1872, sec. 9, for \"on\"."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>107</number>   Ins. by Act 61 
    of 1984, sec. 20 (w.e.f. 14-7-1984).   tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 61 of 1984, sec. 20 (w.e.f. 14-7-1984)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>108</number>   Ins. by the 
    A.O. 1937, (Pt. III of the Government of India Act, 1935 came into force on 
    the 1st April, 1937).   tc 
    " 2. Ins. by the A.O. 1937, (Pt. III of the Government of India Act, 1935 
    came into force on the 1st April, 1937)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>109</number>   Ins. by Act 46 
    of 1983, sec. 7.   tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 46 of 1983, sec. 7."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>110</number>   Ins. by Act 43 
    of 1986, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 19-11-1986).   tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 43 of 1986, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 19-11-1986)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>111</number>   Ins. by Act  43 
    of 1983, sec. 6.   tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act  43 of 1983, sec. 6."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>112</number>   Subs. by Act 3 
    of 1887, sec. 1, for section 125.   tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 3 of 1887, sec. 1, for section 125."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>113</number>   Subs. by Act 18 
    of 1872, sec. 10, for "criminal".   tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 10, for \"criminal\"."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>114</number>   Ins. by Act 18 
    of 1872, sec. 10.   tc 
    " 3. Ins. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 10."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>115</number>   Ins. by Act 18 
    of 1872, sec. 10.   tc 
    " 1. Ins. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 10."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>116</number>   Subs. by Act 21 
    of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for section 131 (w.e.f. 17-10-2000).   tc 
    " 2. Subs. by Act 21 of 2000, sec. 92 and Sch. II, for section 131 (w.e.f. 
    17-10-2000)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>117</number>   As to the 
    application of section 145 to police-diaries, see the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 172.   tc 
    " 1. As to the application of section 145 to police-diaries, see the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 172."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>118</number>   Ins. by Act 4 
    of 2003, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 31-12-2002).   tc 
    " 2. Ins. by Act 4 of 2003, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 31-12-2002)."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>119</number>   Section 154 
    renumbered as sub-section (1) thereof by Act 2 of 2006, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 
    16-4-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>120</number>   Ins. by Act 
    2 of 2006, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 16-4-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>121</number>   Subs. by Act 18 
    of 1872, sec. 11, for "had".   tc 
    " 1. Subs. by Act 18 of 1872, sec. 11, for \"had\"."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>122</number>   Clause (4) 
    omitted by Act 4 of 2003, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 31-12-2002). Clause (a), before 
    omission, stood as under:   tc 
    " 2. Clause (4) omitted by Act 4 of 2003, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 31-12-2002). 
    Clause (a), before omission, stood as under\:"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>123</number>   As the 
    application of section 161 to Police-Diaries, see the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 172.   tc 
    " 1. As the application of section 161 to Police-Diaries, see the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), section 172."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>