<act><tid>1954823</tid>
<title>THE GENEVA CONVENTIONS ACT, <year>1960</year></title>

ACT NO. 6 OF <year>1960</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
[ 12th March, <year>1960</year>.]
An Act to enable effect to be given to certain international 
Conventions done at Geneva on the twelfth day of August, <year>1949</year>, to 
which India is a party, and for purposes connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eleventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY




<article><tid>1709076</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.-
<section><tid>1358111</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Geneva Conventions Act, <year>1960</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>613624</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1367210</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>962911</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions.- In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>200949</tid>
<number>a</number>" Conventions" means the Conventions set out in the 
Schedules; and the First Convention, the Second 
Convention, the Third Convention and the Fourth 
Convention mean the Conventions set out in the First, 
Second, Third and Fourth Schedules, respectively;

</section>

<section><tid>1681785</tid>
<number>b</number>" court" does not include a court- martial or military 
court;

</section>

<section><tid>299785</tid>
<number>c</number>" protected internee" means a person protected by the 
Fourth Convention and interned in India;

</section>

<section><tid>1569638</tid>
<number>d</number>" protecting power", in relation to a protected internee 
or a protected prisoner of war, means the power or 
organisation which is carrying out, in the interests of 
the power of which he is a national or of whose forces 
he is or was at any material time a member, the duties 
assigned to protecting powers under the Third 
Convention or, as the case may be, the Fourth 
Convention;

</section>

<section><tid>1583842</tid>
<number>e</number>" protected prisoner of war" means a person protected by 
the Third Convention.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, 
S. 3 and Schedule.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number> 14th August, <year>1961</year>; vide Notification No. S. R. O. 222, dated the 
2nd August, <year>1961</year>, see Gazette of India, <year>1961</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 4, p. 151.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


CHAP 
PUNISHMENT OF OFFENDERS AGAINST CONVENTIONS

CHAPTER II

PUNISHMENT OF OFFENDERS AGAINST CONVENTIONS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287166</tid>
<number> 3</number> Punishment of grave breaches of Conventions.-
<section><tid>1845263</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person  
within or without India commits or attempts to commit, or abets or 
procures the commission by any other person of, a grave breach of any 
of the Conventions he shall be punished--

<subsection><tid>1533244</tid>
<number>a</number>where the offence involves the wilful killing of a 
person protected by any of the Conventions, with death 
or with imprisonment for life; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1813166</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to fourteen years.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>121682</tid>
<number>2</number>Sub- section (1) applies to persons regardless of their 
nationality or citizenship.

</section>

<section><tid>819587</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>845903</tid>
<number>a</number>a grave breach of the First Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to in article 
 50 of that Convention committed against persons or 
property protected by that Convention;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1792975</tid>
<number>b</number>a grave breach of the Second Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to in Article 
 51 of that Convention committed against persons or 
property protected by that Convention;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1344101</tid>
<number>c</number>a grave breach of the Third Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to in article 
 130 of that Convention committed against persons or 
property protected by that Convention; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1815115</tid>
<number>d</number>a grave breach of the fourth Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to in article 
 147 of that Convention committed against persons or 
property protected by that Convention.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1294411</tid>
<number>4</number>Liability of persons for offences committed outside India.- 
When an offence under this Chapter is committed by any person outside 
India, he may be dealt with in respect of such offence as if it had 
been committed at any place within India at which he may be found.

</article>



<article><tid>1979793</tid>
<number>5</number>Jurisdiction of court.- No court inferior to that of a chief 
presidency magistrate or a Court of Session shall try any offence 
punishable under this Chapter.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>138460</tid>
<number>6</number>Proof of application of Convention.- If in any proceeding under 
this Chapter in respect of a grave breach of any of the Conventions a 
question arises under article 2 of that Convention (which relates to  
  the circumstances in which the Convention applies), a certificate 
under the hand of a Secretary to the Government of India certifying to 
any matter relevant to that question shall be conclusive evidence of 
the matter so certified.

</article>



<article><tid>1156264</tid>
<number>7</number>Jurisdiction of courts- martial.- The Army Act, <year>1950</year> (46 of  
  <year>1950</year>), the Air Force Act, <year>1950</year> (45 of <year>1950</year>), or the Navy Act, <year>1957</year> 
 (62 of <year>1957</year>), relating to trial by court- martial of persons who commit 
civil offences shall have effect for the purposes of the jurisdiction 
of courts- martial as if this Chapter had not been passed.
CHAP 
LEGAL PROCEEDINGS IN RESPECT OF PROTECTED PERSONS

CHAPTER III

LEGAL PROCEEDINGS IN RESPECT OF PROTECTED PERSONS


</article>



<article><tid>1082388</tid>
<number> 8</number> Notice of trial of protected persons to be served on 
protecting power, etc.-
<section><tid>1747161</tid>
<number>1</number>The court before which-- 

<subsection><tid>1736048</tid>
<number>a</number>a protected prisoner of war is brought up for trial for 
any offence; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1935166</tid>
<number>b</number>a protected internee is brought up for trial for an 
offence for which that court has power to sentence him 
to death or to imprisonment for a term of two years or 
more,
shall not proceed with the trial until it is proved to the 
satisfaction of the court that a notice containing the particulars 
mentioned in the next following sub- section, so far as they are known 
to the prosecutor, has been served not less than three weeks 
previously on the protecting power (if there is a protecting power) 
and, if the accused is a protected prisoner of war, on the accused and 
the prisoners' representative.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1558008</tid>
<number>2</number>The particulars referred to in the foregoing sub- section are--

<subsection><tid>305958</tid>
<number>a</number>the full name and description of the accused, including 
the date of his birth and his profession or trade, if 
any, and, if the accused is a protected prisoner of 
war, his rank and arm, regimental, personal or serial 
number;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1123054</tid>
<number>b</number>his place of detention, internment or residence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>240208</tid>
<number>c</number>the offence with which he is charged; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>472621</tid>
<number>d</number>the court before which the trial is to take place and 
the time and place appointed for the trial.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>496264</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section a document purporting--

<subsection><tid>370911</tid>
<number>a</number>to be signed on behalf of the protecting power or by the 
prisoners' representative or by the person accused, as 
the case may be; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1576804</tid>
<number>b</number>to be an acknowledgment of the receipt by that power, 
representative or person on a specified day of a notice 
described therein as a notice under this section,
shall, unless the contrary is shown, be sufficient evidence that the 
notice required by sub- section (1) was served on that power, 
representative or person on that day.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>834156</tid>
<number>4</number>In this section, the expression" prisoners' representative" 
in relation to a particular protected prisoner of war at a particular 
time means the person by whom the functions of prisoners' 
representative within the meaning of article 79 of the Third 
Convention were exercisable in relation to that prisoner at the camp 
or place at which that prisoner was, at or last before that time, 
detained as a protected prisoner of war.

</section>

<section><tid>89624</tid>
<number>5</number>Any court which adjourns a trial for the purpose of enabling 
the requirements of this section to be complied with may, 
notwithstanding anything in any other law, authorise the detention of 
the accused in such custody as it may think fit for the period of the 
adjournment.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>30208</tid>
<number> 9</number> Legal representation of certain persons.-
<section><tid>851563</tid>
<number>1</number>The court before  
which--

<subsection><tid>952186</tid>
<number>a</number>any person is brought up for trial for an offence under 
section 3 of this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1382092</tid>
<number>b</number>a protected prisoner of war is brought up for trial for 
any offence,
shall not proceed with the trial unless--


<subsubsection><tid>1392385</tid>
<number>i</number>the accused is represented by a legal practitioner; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>732217</tid>
<number>ii</number>it is proved to the satisfaction of the court that a 
period of not less than fourteen days has elapsed since 
instructions for the representation of the accused at 
the trial were first given to the legal practitioner,
and if the court adjourns the trial for the purpose of enabling the 
requirements of this sub- section to be complied with, then, 
notwithstanding anything in any other law, the Court may authorise 
the detention of the accused in such custody as it may think fit for 
the period of the adjournment.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1618834</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the accused is a protected prisoner of war, in the 
absence of a legal practitioner accepted by the accused as 
representing him, the legal practitioner instructed for the purpose on 
behalf of the protecting power shall, without prejudice to the 
requirements of clause (ii) of the foregoing sub- section, be regarded 
for the purposes of that sub- section as representing the accused.

</section>

<section><tid>318204</tid>
<number>3</number>If the court adjourns the trial in pursuance of sub- section 
 (1) by reason that the accused is not represented by a legal 
practitioner, the court shall direct that a legal practitioner be 
assigned to watch over the interests of the accused at any further 
proceedings in connection with the offence, and at any such further 
proceedings, in the absence of a legal practitioner either accepted by 
the accused as representing him or instructed as mentioned in the last 
foregoing sub- section, the legal practitioner assigned in pursuance of 
this sub- section shall, without prejudice to the requirements of 
clause (ii) of sub- section (1), be regarded regarded for the purposes 
of that sub- section as representing the accused.

</section>

<section><tid>173893</tid>
<number>4</number>A legal practitioner shall be assigned in pursuance of sub- 
section (3) in such manner as may be provided in the rules made under 
this Act or, in the absence of provisions in the rules, as the court 
directs, and the legal practitioner so assigned shall be entitled to 
such fees as may be provided in the rules made under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>412722</tid>
<number> 10</number> Appeals by protected prisoners of war and internees.-
<section><tid>571790</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where a protected prisoner of war or a protected internee has been 
sentenced by a court to death or to imprisonment for a term of two 
years or more, any time allowed in relation to the institution of an 
appeal against the conviction or sentence shall be deemed to continue 
to run until the day on which the convicted person receives a notice 
given,--

<subsection><tid>1412415</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a protected prisoner of war-- by an 
officer in the Armed Forces; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221165</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a protected internee-- by or on behalf of 
the governor or other person in charge of the prison or 
place in which he is confined,
that the protecting power has been notified of his conviction and 
sentence, and for such further time as would have been within the time 
allowed if the conviction or sentence had taken place or been 
pronounced on that day.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1877477</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, after an appeal against the conviction or sentence by 
a court of a protected prisoner of war or a protected internee

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

has been decided, the sentence remains a sentence of death, or remains 
or has become a sentence of imprisonment for a term of two years or 
more, any time allowed in relation to a further appeal in respect of 
the conviction or sentence as confirmed or varied upon the previous 
appeal shall be deemed to continue to run until the day on which the 
convicted person receives a notice given by a person referred to in 
clause (a) or clause (b) of the last preceding sub- section, as the 
case may require, that the protecting power has been notified of the 
decision of the court upon the previous appeal, and for such further 
time as would have been within the time allowed if that decision had 
been pronounced on that day.


</section>

<section><tid>1898521</tid>
<number>3</number>Where sub- section (1) applies in relation to a convicted 
person, then, unless the court otherwise orders, an order of the court 
relating to the restitution of property or the payment of compensation 
to an aggrieved person shall not take effect, and a provision of any 
law relating to the revesting of property on conviction shall not take 
effect in relation to the conviction, while an appeal by the convicted 
person against his conviction or sentence is possible without an 
extension of time other than the extension provided by the last 
preceding sub- section.

</section>

<section><tid>442339</tid>
<number>4</number>Sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall not apply in relation to 
an appeal against a conviction or sentence, or against the decision of 
a court upon a previous appeal, if, at the time of the conviction or 
sentence, or of the decision of the court upon the previous appeal, as 
the case may be, there is no protecting power.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>977800</tid>
<number> 11</number> Reduction of sentence and custody of protected prisoners of 
war and internees.-
<section><tid>349708</tid>
<number>1</number>When a protected prisoner of war or a protected  
internee is convicted of an offence, the court shall,--

<subsection><tid>219789</tid>
<number>a</number>in fixing a term of imprisonment in respect of the 
offence, deduct from the term which it would otherwise 
have fixed any period during which the convicted person 
has been in custody in connection with that offence 
before the trial; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1042860</tid>
<number>b</number>in fixing any penalty other than imprisonment in respect 
of the offence, take that period of custody into 
account.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>469778</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Central Government is satisfied that a protected 
prisoner of war accused of an offence has been in custody in 
connection with that offence, while awaiting trial, in a place other 
than a camp or place in which protected prisoners of war are detained, 
for an aggregate period of not less than three months, the Central 
Government may direct that the prisoner shall be transferred from that

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

custody to the custody of an officer of the Armed Forces of the Union 
and thereafter remain in military custody at a camp or place in which 
protected prisoners of war are detained, and be brought before the 
court at the time appointed for his trial.

CHAP 
ABUSE OF THE RED CROSS AND OTHER EMBLEMS

CHAPTER IV

ABUSE OF THE RED CROSS AND OTHER EMBLEMS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1739613</tid>
<number> 12</number> Prohibition of use of Red Cross and other emblems.- No person 
shall, without the approval of the Central Government, use for any 
purpose whatsoever--
<section><tid>1048341</tid>
<number>a</number>the emblem of a red cross with vertical and horizontal 
arms of the same length on, and completely surrounded 
by, a white ground, or the designation" Red Cross" or 
" Geneva Cross";

</section>

<section><tid>842307</tid>
<number>b</number>the emblem of a red crescent moon on, and completely 
surrounded by, a white ground, or the designation" Red 
Crescent";

</section>

<section><tid>441784</tid>
<number>c</number>the following emblem in red on, and completely 
surrounded by, a white ground, that is to say, a lion 
passing from right to left of, and with its face turned 
towards, the observer, holding erect in its raised 
right forepaw a scimitar, with, appearing above the 
lion' s back, the upper half of the sun shooting forth 
rays, or the designation" Red Lion and Sun";

</section>

<section><tid>571678</tid>
<number>d</number>the emblem of a white or silver cross with vertical and 
horizontal arms of the same length on, and completely 
surrounded by, a red ground, being the heraldic emblem 
of the Swiss Confederation; or

</section>

<section><tid>363427</tid>
<number>e</number>any design or wording so nearly resembling any of the 
emblems or designations specified in the preceding 
clauses of this section as to be capable of being 
mistaken for, or, as the case may be, understood as 
referring to, one of those emblems.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1578137</tid>
<number>13</number>Penalty.- If any person contravenes any of the provisions of 
section 12, he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees, and be liable to forfeit any goods upon or in 
connection with

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

which the emblem, designation, design or wording was used by that 
person.


</article>



<article><tid>1281566</tid>
<number> 14</number> Offences by companies.-
<section><tid>1524447</tid>
<number>1</number>If the person committing an  
offence under this Chapter is a company, the company as well as every 
person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the conduct 
of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly:
Provided that, nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence 
was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>371441</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Chapter has been committed by a company and it 
is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is attributable 
to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or 
other officer of the compny, such director, manager, secretary or 
other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and 
shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>817631</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>45322</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>902405</tid>
<number> 15</number> Saving.- In the case of a trade mark registered before the 
coming into force of this Act, the foregoing provisions of this 
Chapter shall not apply by reason only of its consisting of or 
containing a design or wording which reproduces or resembles an emblem 
or designation specified in clause (b) or clause (c) of section 12; 
and where a person is charged with using such a design or wording for 
any purpose and it is proved that he used it otherwise than as, or as 
part of, a trade mark so registered, it shall be a defence for him to 
prove--
<section><tid>1022917</tid>
<number>a</number>that he lawfully used that design or wording for that 
purpose before the coming into force of this Act; or

</section>

<section><tid>1191979</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where he is charged with using the design or 
wording upon goods, that the design or wording had been 
applied to the goods before he acquired them by some

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

other person who had manufactured or dealt with the 
goods in the course of trade and who lawfully used the 
design or wording upon similar goods before the coming 
into force of this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1801447</tid>
<number>16</number>Use of Red Cross' and other emblems on Indian ship or 
aircraft.- The provisions of this Chapter extend to the use in or 
outside India of any emblem, designation, design or wording as is 
referred to in section 12 on any Indian ship or aircraft.
CHAP 
MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS


</article>



<article><tid>1419260</tid>
<number>17</number>Cognizance of offences.- No court shall take cognizance of any 
offence under this Act except on complaint by the Government or of 
such officer of the Government as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify.

</article>



<article><tid>1953404</tid>
<number>18</number>Power to make rules.- The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of 
carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>651784</tid>
<number>19</number>Rules to be laid before Parliament.- Every rule made by the 
Central Government under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be 
after it is made or issued before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that 
any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.

</article>



<article><tid>68354</tid>
<number> 20</number> Repeal.-
<section><tid>1300002</tid>
<number>1</number>The Geneva Convention Implementing Act, <year>1936</year> (14   
  of <year>1936</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1774974</tid>
<number>2</number>The Geneva Convention Act, <year>1911</year>, 1 and 2 Geo. 5, C. 20 
shall cease to have effect as part of the law of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

CHAP 
PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1709076</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1358111</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Geneva Conventions Act, <year>1960</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>613624</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>1367210</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>962911</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>200949</tid>
<number>a</number>" Conventions" means the Conventions set out in the 
Schedules; and the First Convention, the Second Convention, 
the Third Convention and the Fourth Convention mean the 
Conventions set out in the First, Second, Third and Fourth 
Schedules, respectively;

</section>

<section><tid>1681785</tid>
<number>b</number>" court" does not include a court- martial or military 
court;

</section>

<section><tid>299785</tid>
<number>c</number>" protected internee" means a person protected by the 
Fourth Convention and interned in India:

</section>

<section><tid>1569638</tid>
<number>d</number>" protecting power", in relation to a protected internee 
or a protected prisoner of war, means the power or 
Organisation which is carrying out, in the interests of the 
power of which he is a national or of whose forces he is or 
was at any material

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 14. 8. 61, vide S. R. O. 222, dt. 2. 8. 61, Sec.. 903. India, M. D. 
Sec. 4. b. 151.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

time a member, the duties assigned to protecting powers under the 
Third Convention or, as the case may be, the Fourth Convention;


</section>

<section><tid>1583842</tid>
<number>e</number>" protected prisoner of war" means a person protected by 
the Third Convention.
CHAP 
PUNISHMENT OF OFFENDERS AGAINST CONVENTIONS

CHAPTER II

PUNISHMENT OF OFFENDERS AGAINST CONVENTIONS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1287166</tid>
<number> 3</number> Punishment of grave breaches of conventions.
<section><tid>1845263</tid>
<number>1</number>If any  
person within or without India commits or attempts commit, or abets or 
procures the commission by any other person of, a grave breach of any 
of the Conventions he shall be punished,-

<subsection><tid>1533244</tid>
<number>a</number>where the offence involves the wilful killing of a per- 
son protected by any of the Conventions, with death or with 
imprisonment for life; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1813166</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to fourteen years.,

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>121682</tid>
<number>2</number>Sub- section (1) applies to persons regardless of their 
nationality or citizenship.

</section>

<section><tid>819587</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section,-

<subsection><tid>845903</tid>
<number>a</number>a grave breach of the First Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to in article 50 of 
that Convention committed against persons or property 
protected by that Convention;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1792975</tid>
<number>b</number>a grave breach of the Second Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to in article 51 of 
that Convention committed against persons or property 
protected by that Convention;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1344101</tid>
<number>c</number>a grave breach of the Third Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to in article 130 
of that Convention committed against persons or property 
protected by that Convention; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1815115</tid>
<number>d</number>a grave breach of the Fourth Convention is a breach of 
that Convention involving an act referred to In article 147 
of that Convention committed against persons or property 
protected by that Convention.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1294411</tid>
<number>4</number>Liability of persons for offences committed outside India. 
When an offence under this Chapter is committed by any person outside 
India, he may be dealt with in respect of such offence as if it had 
been committed at any place within India at which he may be found.

</article>



<article><tid>1979793</tid>
<number>5</number>Jurisdiction of court. No court inferior to that of a chief 
presidency magistrate or a Court of Session shall try any offence 
punishable under this Chapter.

</article>



<article><tid>138460</tid>
<number>6</number>Proof of application of Convention. If in any proceeding 
under this Chapter in respect of a grave breach of any of the 
Conventions a question arises under article 2 of that Convention 
 (which relates to the circumstances in which the Convention applies), 
a certificate under the hand of a Secretary to the Government of India 
certifying to any matter relevant to that question shall be conclusive 
evidence of the matter so certified.

</article>



<article><tid>1156264</tid>
<number>7</number>Jurisdiction of courts martial. The Army Act, <year>1950</year>, (46 of  
  <year>1950</year>.) the Air Force Act, <year>1950</year>, (45 of <year>1950</year>.) or the Navy Act, <year>1957</year>, 
 (62 of <year>1957</year>.) relating to trial by court- martial of persons who commit 
civil offences shall have effect for the purposes of the jurisdiction 
of courts- martial as if this Chapter had not been passed.
CHAP 
LEGAL PROCEEDINGS IN RESPECT OF PROTECTED PERSONS

CHAPTER III

LEGAL PROCEEDINGS IN RESPECT OF PROTECTED PERSONS


</article>



<article><tid>1082388</tid>
<number> 8</number> Notice of trial of protected persons to be served on 
protecting power, etc.
<section><tid>1747161</tid>
<number>1</number>The court before which- 

<subsection><tid>1736048</tid>
<number>a</number>a protected prisoner of war is brought up for trial for 
any offence; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1935166</tid>
<number>b</number>a protected internee is brought up for trial for an 
offence for which that court has power to sentence him to 
death or to imprisonment for a term of two years or more,
shall not proceed with the trial until it is proved to the 
satisfaction of the court that a notice containing the particulars 
mentioned in the next following sub- section, so far as they are known 
to the prosecutor, has been served not less than three weeks 
previously on the protecting power (if there is a protecting power) 
and, if the accused is a protected prisoner of war on the accused and 
the prisoners' representative.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1558008</tid>
<number>2</number>The particulars referred to in the foregoing subsection 
are--

<subsection><tid>305958</tid>
<number>a</number>the full name and description of the accused, including 
the date of his birth and his profession or trade, if any, 
and if the accused is a protected prisoner of war, his rank 
and arm, regimental, personal or serial number;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1123054</tid>
<number>b</number>his place of detention, internment or residence;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>240208</tid>
<number>c</number>the offence with which he is charged; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>472621</tid>
<number>d</number>the court before which the trial is to take place and 
the time and place appointed for the trial.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>496264</tid>
<number>3</number>For the purposes of this section a document purporting-

<subsection><tid>370911</tid>
<number>a</number>to be signed on behalf of the protecting power or by 
the prisoners' representative or by the person accused, as 
the case may be; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1576804</tid>
<number>b</number>to be an acknowledgment of the receipt by that power, 
representative or person on a specified day of a notice 
described therein as a notice under this section,
shall, unless the contrary is shown, be sufficient evidence that the 
notice required by sub- section (1) was served on that power, re- 
presentative or person on that day.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>834156</tid>
<number>4</number>In this section, the expression" prisoners' representative" 
in relation to a particular protected prisoner of war at a particular 
time means the person by whom the functions of prisoners' repre- 
sentative within the meaning of article 79 of the Third Convention 
were exercisable in relation to that prisoner at the camp or place at 
which that prisoner was, at or last before that time, detained as a 
protected prisoner of war.

</section>

<section><tid>89624</tid>
<number>5</number>Any court which adjourns a trial for the purpose of enabling 
the requirements of this section to be complied with may, notwith- 
standing anything in any other law, authorise the detention of the 
accused in such custody as it may think fit for the period of the 
adjournment.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>30208</tid>
<number> 9</number> Legal presentation of certain porsons.
<section><tid>851563</tid>
<number>1</number>The court before  
which-

<subsection><tid>952186</tid>
<number>a</number>any person is brought up for trial for an offence under 
section 3 of this Act; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1382092</tid>
<number>b</number>a protected prisoner of war is brought up for trial for 
any offence,
shall not proceed with the trial unless-


<subsubsection><tid>1392385</tid>
<number>i</number>the accused is represented by a legal practitioner; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>732217</tid>
<number>ii</number>it is proved to the satisfaction of the court that a 
period of not less than fourteen days has elapsed since 
instructions for the representation of the accused at the 
trial were first given to the legal practitioner,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and if the court adjourns the trial for the purpose of enabling the 
requirements of this sub- section to be complied with, then, notwith- 
standing anything in any other law, the Court may authorise the 
detention of the accused in such custody as it may think fit for the 
period of the adjournment.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1618834</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the accused is a protected prisoner of war, in the 
absence of a legal practitioner accepted by the accused as represent- 
Ing him, the legal practitioner instructed for the purpose on behalf 
of the protecting power shall, without prejudice to the requirements 
of clause (ii) of the foregoing sub- section, be regarded for the pur- 
poses of that sub- section as representing the accused.

</section>

<section><tid>318204</tid>
<number>3</number>If the court adjourns the trial in pursuance of sub- section 
 (1) by reason that the accused is not represented by a legal practi- 
tioner, the court shall direct that a legal practitioner be assigned 
to watch over the interests of the accused at any further proceedings 
in connection with the offence, and at any such further proceedings, 
in the absence of a legal practitioner either accepted by the accused 
as representing him or instructed as mentioned in the last foregoing 
sub- section, the legal practitioner assigned in pursuance of this sub- 
section shall, without prejudice to the requirements of clause (ii) of 
sub- section (1), be regarded for the purposes of that sub- section as 
representing the accused.

</section>

<section><tid>173893</tid>
<number>4</number>A legal practitioner shall be assigned in pursuance of sub- 
section (3) in such manner as may be provided in the rules made under 
this Act or, in the absence of provisions in the rules, as the court 
directs, and the legal practitioner so assigned shall be entitled to 
such fees as may be provided in the rules made under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>412722</tid>
<number> 10</number> Appeals by protected prisoners of war and interness.
<section><tid>571790</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where a protected prisoner of war or a protected internee has been 
sentenced by a court to death or to imprisonment for a term of two 
years or more, any time allowed in relation to the institution of an 
appeal against the conviction or sentence shall be deemed to continue 
to run until the day on which the convicted person receives a notice 
given,-

<subsection><tid>1412415</tid>
<number>a</number>in the case of a protected prisoner of war- by an 
officer in the Armed Forces; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221165</tid>
<number>b</number>in the case of a protected internee- by or on behalf of 
the governor or other person in charge of the prison or place 
in which he is confined,
that the protecting power has been notified of his conviction and 
sentence, and for such further time as would have been within the time 
allowed if the conviction or sentence had taken place or been 
pronounced on that day.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1877477</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, after an appeal against the conviction or sentence by 
a court of a protected prisoner of war or a protected internee has 
been decided, the sentence remains a sentence of death, or remains or 
has become a sentence of imprisonment for a term of two years or more, 
any time allowed in relation to a further appeal in respect of the 
conviction or sentence as confirmed or varied upon the previous appeal 
shall be deemed to continue to run until the day on which the 
convicted person receives a notice given by a person referred to in 
clause (a) or clause (b) of the last preceding sub- section, as the 
case may require, that the protecting power has been notified of the 
decision of the court upon the previous appeal, and for such further 
time as would have been within the time allowed if that decision had 
been pronounced on that day.

</section>

<section><tid>1898521</tid>
<number>3</number>Where sub- section (1) applies in relation to a convicted 
person, then, unless the court otherwise orders, an order of the court 
relating to the restitution of property or the payment of compensation 
to an aggrieved person shall not take effect, and a provision of any 
law relating to the revesting of property on conviction shall not take 
effect in relation to the conviction, while an appeal by the convicted 
person against his conviction or sentence is possible without an 
extension of time other than the extension provided by the last 
preceding sub- section.

</section>

<section><tid>442339</tid>
<number>4</number>Sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) shall not apply in relation to 
an appeal against a conviction or sentence, or against the decision, 
of a court upon a previous appeal, if, at the time of the conviction 
or sentence, or of the decision of the court upon the previous 
appeal, as the case may be, there is no protecting power.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>977800</tid>
<number> 11</number> Reduction of sentence and custody of protected prisoners of 
war and interness.
<section><tid>349708</tid>
<number>1</number>When a protected prisoner of war or a protected  
internee is convicted of an offence, the court shall,-

<subsection><tid>219789</tid>
<number>a</number>in fixing a term of imprisonment in respect of, the 
offence, deduct from the term which it would otherwise have 
fixed any period during which the convicted person has been 
in custody in connection with that offence before the trial; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1042860</tid>
<number>b</number>in fixing any penalty other than imprisonment in res- 
Pect of the offence, take that period of custody into 
account.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>469778</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the Central Government is satisfied that a protected 
prisoner of war accused of an offence has betn in custody in 
connection with that offence, while awaiting trial, in a place other 
than a camp or place in which protected prisoners of war are detained, 
for

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

an aggregate period of not less than three months, the Central Gov- 
ernment may direct that the prisoner shall be transferred from that 
custody to the custody of. an officer of the Armed Forces of the Union 
and thereafter remain in military custody at a camp or place in which 
protected prisoners of war are detained, and be brought before the 
court at the time appointed for his trial.

CHAP 
ABUSE OF THE RED CROSS AND OTHER EMBLEMS

CHAPTER IV

ABUSE OF THE RED CROSS AND OTHER EMBLEMS



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1739613</tid>
<number> 12</number> Prohibition of use of Red Cross and other emblems. No person 
shall, without the approval of the Central Government, use for any 
purpose whatsoever-
<section><tid>1048341</tid>
<number>a</number>the emblem of a red cross with vertical and horizontal 
arms of the same length on, and completely surrounded by, a 
white ground, or the designation" Red Cross" or" Geneva 
Cross";

</section>

<section><tid>842307</tid>
<number>b</number>the emblem of a red crescent moon on, and completely 
surrounded by, a white ground, or the designation" Red 
Crescent";

</section>

<section><tid>441784</tid>
<number>c</number>the following emblem in red on, and completely sur- 
rounded by, a white ground, that is to say, a lion passing 
from right to left of, and with its face turned towards, the 
observer. holding erect in its raised right forepaw a 
scimitar, with, appearing above the lion' s back, the upper 
half of the sun shooting forth rays, or the designation" Red 
Lion and Sun";

</section>

<section><tid>571678</tid>
<number>d</number>the emblem of a white or silver cross with vertical an 
horizontal arms of the same length on, and completely 
surrounded by, a red ground, being the heraldic emblem of the 
Swiss Confederation; or

</section>

<section><tid>363427</tid>
<number>e</number>any design or wording so nearly resembling any of the 
emblems or designations specified in the preceding clauses of 
this section as to be capable of being mistaken for, or, as 
the ca. se may be, understood as referring to, one of those 
emblems


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1578137</tid>
<number>13</number>Penalty. If any person contravenes any of the provisions of 
section 12 he shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees, and be liable to forfeit any goods upon or in 
connection with which the emblem, designation, design or wording was 
used by that person.

</article>



<article><tid>1281566</tid>
<number> 14</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>1524447</tid>
<number>1</number>If the person committing an  
offence under this Chapter is a company, the company as well as every 
ptrson in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the conduct 
of its business at

<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the time of the commission of the offence shall be deemed to be guilty 
of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly:

Provided that, nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence 
was committed without his knowledge or that he exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>371441</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Chapter has been committed by a company and it 
is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or that the commission of the, offence is attributable 
to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or 
other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or 
other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and 
shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsection><tid>817631</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>45322</tid>
<number>b</number>" director" in relation to a firm means a partner in the 
firm.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>902405</tid>
<number> 15</number> Saving. In the case of a trade mark registered before the 
coming into force of this Act, the foregoing provisions of this 
Chapter shall not apply by reason only of its consisting of or 
containing a design or wording which reproduces or resembles an emblem 
or designation specified in clause (b) or clause (c) of section 12; 
and where a person is charged with using such a design or wording for 
any purpose and it is proved that he used it otherwise than as, or as 
part of, a trade mark so registered, it shall be a defence for him to 
prove-
<section><tid>1022917</tid>
<number>a</number>that he. lawfully used that design or wording for that 
purpose before the coming into force of this Act; or

</section>

<section><tid>1191979</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where he is charged with using the design or 
wording upon goods, that the design or wording had been 
applied to the goods before he acquired them by some other 
person who had manufactured or dealt with the goods in the 
course of trade and who lawfully used the design or wording 
upon similar goods before the coming into force of this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1801447</tid>
<number>16</number>Use of Red Cross and other emblems on Indian ship or 
aircraft. The provisions of this Chapter extend to the use in or 
outside India of any emblem, designation, design or wording as Is 
referred to in section 12 on any Indian ship or aircraft.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP 
MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS


</article>



<article><tid>1419260</tid>
<number>17</number>Cognizance of offences. No court shall take cognizance of 
any offence under this Act except on complaint by the Government or of 
such officer of the Government as the Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify.

</article>



<article><tid>1953404</tid>
<number>18</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for the purpose of 
carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.

</article>



<article><tid>651784</tid>
<number>19</number>Rules to be laid before Parliament. Every rule made by the 
Central Government under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be 
after it is made or issued before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two successive sessions, and if before the expiry of 
the session in which it is so laid or the session immediately 
following, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be, so however that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.

</article>



<article><tid>68354</tid>
<number> 20</number> Repeal.
<section><tid>1300002</tid>
<number>1</number>The Geneva Convention Implementing Act, <year>1936</year>,  
 (14 of <year>1936</year>.) is here. by repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1774974</tid>
<number>2</number>The Geneva Convention Act, <year>1911</year>, 1 and 2 Geo. 5, C. 20. 
shall cease to have effect as part of the law of India.


</section>

</article>



 </act>