<act><title>

THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    20041</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Biological Diversity Rules, 2004.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
    force on 15th April, 2004.
  


 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Biological 
    Diversity Act 2002 (18 of 2003);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Authority” means the National 
    Bio-diversity Authority established under sub-section (1) of section 8;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Bio-diversity Management 
    Committee” means a Bio-diversity Management Committee established by a local 
    body under sub-section (1) of section 41;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Chairperson” means the 
    Chairperson of the National Bio-diversity Authority or as the case may be, 
    of the State Bio-diversity Board;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “fee” means any fee stipulated 
    in the Schedule;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Form” means Form annexed to 
    these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “member” means a member of the 
    National Bio-diversity Authority or a State Bio-diversity Board and includes 
    the chairperson as the case may be;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “section” means a section of 
    the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “Secretary” means the full 
    time Secretary of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   words and expressions used but 
    not defined in these rules and defined in the Act shall have the meaning 
    respectively assigned to them in the Act.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>3</number> Manner of selection and 
    appointment of the Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson of the Authority shall be appointed by the Central 
    Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every appointment of 
    Chairperson under sub-section (1) shall be made either on deputation basis 
    or by selection from outside the Central Government. In case the appointment 
    is through deputation, the applicant should not be below the rank of 
    Additional Secretary to the Government of India.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>4</number> Term of office of the 
    Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson of the Authority shall hold the office for a term of three 
    years’ and shall be eligible for re-appointment,
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Provided that no 
    Chairperson shall hold office as such after he attains the age of sixty five 
    years or his term of office expires which is earlier.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson may 
    resign from his office by giving at least one month notice in writing to the 
    Central Government.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>5</number> Pay and allowances of 
    Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Chairperson shall be entitled to fixed pay of Rs. 26,000 per month. In 
    case of retired person is appointed as Chairperson, his pay shall be fixed 
    in accordance with the orders of the Central Government as applicable to 
    such persons.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Chairperson shall be 
    entitled to such allowances, leave, pension, provident fund, house and other 
    perquisites etc. to be decided by the Central Government from time to time.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>6</number> Term of office and 
    allowances of non-official members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every non-official member of the Authority shall hold his office for a term 
    not exceeding three years at a time from the date of publication of his 
    appointment in the Official Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every non-official 
    member attending the meeting of the Authority shall be entitled to sitting 
    allowance, travelling expenses, daily allowance and such other allowances as 
    are applicable to non-official member of commissions and committees of the 
    Central Government attending the meeting(s) of such Commissions or 
    Committees.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>7</number> Filling up of vacancies 
    of non-official members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A non-official member of the Authority may resign his office at any time by 
    giving in writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government and the 
    seat of that member in the Authority shall become vacant.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A casual vacancy of a 
    non-official member in the Authority shall be filled up by a fresh 
    nomination and the person nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office 
    only for the remainder of the term of the member in whose place he was 
    nominated.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>8</number> Removal of the members 
    of the Authority.—No 
    member of the Authority shall be removed from his office on any ground 
    specified in section 11, without a due and proper enquiry by an officer not 
    below the rank of a Secretary to the Government of India appointed by the 
    Central Government and without giving such member a reasonable opportunity 
    of being heard.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>9</number> Secretary of the 
    Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall appoint a Secretary to it.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The terms and 
    conditions of the appointment of the Secretary shall be determined by the 
    Authority by regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Secretary shall be 
    responsible for co-coordinating and convening the meetings of the Authority, 
    maintenance of the records of the proceedings of the Authority and such 
    other matters as may be assigned to him by the Authority.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>10</number> Meetings of the 
    Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall meet at least four times in a year normally after a 
    period of three months at the Head Quarters of the Authority or at such 
    place as may be decided by the Chairperson.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson shall, 
    upon a written request from not less than five members of the Authority or 
    upon a direction of the Central Government, call a special meeting of the 
    Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The members shall be 
    given at least fifteen days’ notice for holding an ordinary meeting and 
    atleast three days’ notice for holding a special meeting specifying the 
    purpose, the time and the place at which such meeting is to be held.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every meeting shall be 
    presided over by the Chairperson and in his absence, by a presiding officer 
    to be elected by the members present from amongst themselves.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The decision of the 
    Authority at a meeting shall, if necessary, be taken by a simple majority of 
    the members present and voting and the Chairperson or in his absence, the 
    member presiding shall have a second or casting vote.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Each member shall have 
    one vote.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The quorum at every 
    meeting of the Authority shall be five.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> No member shall be 
    entitled to bring forward for the consideration of a meeting any matter of 
    which he has not given ten days’ notice unless the Chairperson in his 
    discretion permits him to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Notice of the meeting 
    may be given to the members by delivering the same by messenger or sending 
    it by registered post to his last known place of residence or business or in 
    such other manner as the Secretary of the Authority may, in the 
    circumstances of the case, think fit.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>11</number> Appointment of Expert 
    Committee by the Authority and their entitlements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority may constitute any number of Committees for such purposes as 
    it may deem fit consisting wholly of members or wholly of other persons or 
    partly of members or partly of other persons.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The members of the 
    Committee other than the members of the Authority shall be paid such fees 
    and allowances for attending the meetings as the Authority may deem fit.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>12</number> General functions of 
    the Authority.—The 
    Authority may perform the following functions, namely:—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   lay down the procedure and 
    guidelines to govern the activities provided under sections 3, 4 and 6;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   advise the Central Government 
    on any matter concerning conservation of bio-diversity, sustainable use of 
    its components and fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the 
    use of biological resource and knowledge;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   coordinate the activities of 
    the State Bio-diversity Boards;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   provide technical assistance 
    and guidance to the State Bio-diversity Boards;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>   commission studies and sponsor 
    investigations and research;
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>   engage consultants, for a 
    specific period, not exceeding three years, for providing technical 
    assistance to the Authority in the effective discharge of its functions:
 
Provided that if it is necessary and expedient 
    to engage any consultant beyond the period of three years, the Authority 
    shall seek prior approval of the Central Government for such an engagement.
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>   collect, compile and publish 
    technical and statistical data, manuals, codes or guides relating to 
    conservation of bio-diversity, sustainable use of its components and fair 
    and equitable sharing of benefits arising out of the use of biological 
    resource and knowledge;
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>   organise through mass media a 
    comprehensive programme regarding conservation of bio-diversity, sustainable 
    use of its components and fair and equitable sharing of benefits arising out 
    of the use of biological resource and knowledge;
 </section><section>
<number>ix</number>   plan and organise training of 
    personnel engaged or likely to be engaged in programmes for the conservation 
    of bio-diversity and sustainable use of its components;
 </section><section>
<number>x</number>   prepare the annual Budget of 
    the Authority incorporating its own receipts as also the devaluation from 
    the Central Government provided that the allocation by the Central 
    Government shall be operated in accordance with the budget provisions 
    approved by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
<number>xi</number>   recommend creation of posts 
    to the Central Government, for effective discharge of the functions by the 
    Authority and to create such  posts, provided that no such post whether 
    permanent/temporary or of any nature, would be created without prior 
    approval of the Central Government;
 <subsection>
<number>xii</number>   approve the method of 
    recruitment to the officers and servants of the Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xiii</number>   take steps to build up data 
    base and to create information and documentation system for biological 
    resources and associated traditional knowledge through bio-diversity 
    registers and electronics data bases, to ensure effective management, 
    promotion and sustainable uses;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xiv</number>   give directions to State 
    Bio-diversity Boards and the Bio-diversity Management Committees in writing 
    for effective implementation of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xv</number>   report to the Central 
    Government about the functioning of the Authority and implementation of the 
    Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xvi</number>   recommend, modify, 
    collection of benefit sharing fee under sub-section (1) of section 6 or 
    changes of royalties under sub-section (2) of section 19 in respect of 
    biological resources from time to time;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xvii</number>   sanction grants-in-aid and 
    grants to the State Bio-diversity Board and Bio-diversity Management 
    Committees for specific purposes;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xviii</number>   undertake physical 
    inspection of any area in connection with the implementation of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xix</number>   take necessary measures 
    including appointment of legal experts to oppose grant of intellectual 
    property right in any country outside India on any biological resource and 
    associated knowledge obtained from India in an illegal manner;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xx</number>   do such other functions as 
    may be assigned or directed by the Central Government from time to time.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>13</number> Powers and duties of 
    Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson shall have the overall control of the day-to-day activities 
    of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  Subject to the 
    provisions of section 10, the Chairperson shall have the powers of general 
    superintendence over the officers and staff of the Authority and he may 
    issue necessary directions for the conduct and management of the affairs of 
    the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson shall 
    be in charge of all the confidential papers and records of the Authority and 
    shall be responsible for their safe custody.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All orders and 
    instructions to be issued by the Authority shall be under the signature of 
    the Chairperson or of any other officer authorized by the Chairperson in 
    this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Chairperson, either 
    himself or through an officer of the authority authorized for the purpose, 
    may sanction and disburse all payments against the approved budget.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Chairperson shall 
    have full powers for granting administrative and technical sanction to all 
    estimates.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Chairperson shall 
    convene and preside over all the meetings of the Authority and shall ensure 
    that all decisions taken by the Authority are implemented in proper manner.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Chairperson shall 
    exercise such other powers and perform such other functions as may be 
    delegated to him from time to time by the Authority or the Central 
    Government.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>14</number> Procedure for access to 
    biological resources and associated traditional knowledge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person seeking approval of the Authority for access to biological 
    resources and associated knowledge for research or for commercial 
    utilization shall make an application in Form I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application under 
    sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a fee of ten thousand rupees in the 
    form of a cheque or demand draft drawn in favour of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority shall 
    after consultation with the concerned local bodies and collecting such 
    additional information from the applicant and other sources, as it may deem 
    necessary, dispose of the application, as far as possible, within a period 
    of six months from the date of its receipts.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On being satisfied with 
    the merit of the application, the Authority may grant the approval for 
    access to biological resources and associated knowledge subject to such term 
    and conditions as it may deem fit to impose.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The approval to access 
    shall be in the form of a written agreement duly signed by an authorized 
    officer of the Authority and the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The form of the 
    agreement referred to in sub-rule (5), shall be laid down by the Authority 
    and shall include the following, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   general objectives and 
    purpose of the application for seeking approval;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   description of the biological 
    resources and traditional knowledge including accompanying information;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   intended uses of the 
    biological resources (research, breeding, commercial utilization etc.);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   conditions under which the 
    applicant may seek intellectual property rights;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   quantum of monetary and other 
    incidental benefits. If need be, a commitment to enter into a fresh 
    agreement particularly in case if the biological material is taken  for 
    research purposes and later on sought to be used for commercial purposes, 
    and also in case of any other change in use thereof subsequently.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   restriction to transfer the 
    accessed biological resources and the traditional knowledge to any third 
    party without prior approval of Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   to adhere to a limit set by 
    the Authority on the quantity and specification of the quality of the 
    biological resources for which the applicant is seeking access;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>   guarantee to deposit a 
    reference sample of the biological material sought to be accessed with the 
    repositories identified in section 39;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number>   submitting to the Authority a 
    regular status report of research and other developments;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>   commitment to abide with the 
    provisions of Act and rules and other related legislations in force in the 
    country;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>   commitment to facilitate 
    measures for conservation and sustainable use of biological resources 
    accessed;
 <subsubsection>
<number>xii</number>   commitment to minimize 
    environmental impacts of collecting activities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xiii</number>   legal provisions such as 
    duration of the agreement, notice to terminate the agreement, independent 
    enforceability of individual clauses, provision to the extent the 
    obligations in benefit sharing clauses survive the termination of the 
    agreement, events limiting liability (natural calamities), arbitration, any 
    confidentiality clause.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> The conditions for 
    access may specifically provide measures for conservation and protection of 
    biological resources to which the access is being granted.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Authority may for 
    reasons to be recorded in writing reject an application if it considers that 
    the request cannot be acceded to.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> No application shall be 
    rejected unless the applicant is given a reasonable opportunity of being 
    heard.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The Authority shall 
    take steps to widely publicize the approvals granted, through print or 
    electronic media and shall periodically monitor compliance of conditions on 
    which the approval was accorded.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>15</number> Revocation of access or 
    approval.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority may either on the basis of any complaint or suo moto 
    withdraw the approval granted for access under rule 15 and revoke the 
    written agreement under the following conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   on the basis of reasonable 
    belief that the person to whom the approval was granted has violated any of 
    the provisions of the Act or the condition on which the approval was 
    granted;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   when the person who has been 
    granted approval has failed to comply with the terms of the agreement;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   on failure to comply with 
    any of the conditions of access granted;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   on account of overriding 
    public interest or for protection of environment and conservation of 
    biological diversity;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority shall 
    send a copy of every order of revocation issued by it to the concerned State 
    Bio-diversity Board and the Bio-diversity Management Committees for 
    prohibiting the access and also to assess the damage, if any, caused and 
    take steps to recover the damage.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>16</number> Restriction on 
    activities related to access to biological resources.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority, if it deems necessary and appropriate, shall take the steps 
    to restrict or prohibit the request for access to biological resources for 
    the following reasons, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the request for access is 
    for any endangered taxa;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the request for access is for 
    any endemic and rare species;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the request for access may 
    likely to result in adverse effect on the livelihoods of the local people;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the request to access may 
    result in adverse environmental impact which may be difficult to control and 
    mitigate;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   the request for access may 
    cause genetic erosion or affecting the ecosystem function;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   use of resources for purposes 
    contrary to national interest and other related international agreements 
    entered into by India.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>17</number> Procedure for seeking 
    approval for transferring results of research.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person desirous of transferring results of research relating to 
    biological resources obtained from India for monetary consideration to 
    foreign nationals, companies and Non Resident Indians (NRIs), shall make an 
    application to the Authority in the Form II.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application under 
    sub-rule (i) shall be accompanied by a fee of five thousand rupees in the 
    form of a Bank draft or Cheque drawn in favour of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every application under 
    sub-rule (i) shall be decided upon by the Authority, as far as possible 
    within a period of three months from the receipt of the same.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On being satisfied that 
    the applicant has fulfilled all the requirements, the Authority may grant 
    the approval for transferring the results of research subject to such terms 
    and conditions as it may deem fit to impose in each case.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The approval for 
    transfer shall be granted in the form of a written agreement duly signed by 
    an authorized officer of the Authority and the applicant. The form of the 
    agreement shall be such as may be decided by the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Authority may for 
    reasons to be recorded in writing reject an application if it considers that 
    the application cannot be allowed:
 
Provided that the 
    application shall be rejected unless the applicant has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>18</number> Procedure for seeking 
    prior approval before applying for intellectual property protection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person desirous of applying for a patent or any other intellectual 
    property based on research on biological material and knowledge obtained 
    from India shall make an application in Form III.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application under 
    sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by paying a fee of five hundred rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority after due 
    appraisal of the application and after collecting any additional 
    information, on the basis of merit shall decide on the application, as far 
    as possible within a period of three months of receipt of the same.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On being satisfied that 
    the applicant has fulfilled all the necessary requirements, the Authority 
    may grant approval for applying for a patent or any other IPR subject to 
    such terms and conditions as it may deem fit to impose in each case.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The approval shall be 
    granted in the form of a written agreement duly signed by an authorized 
    officer of the Authority and the applicant. The form of the agreement may be 
    decided by the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Authority may 
    reject the application if it considers that the request cannot be acceded to 
    after recording the reasons. Before passing order of rejection, the 
    applicant shall be given an opportunity of hearing.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>19</number> Procedure for third 
    party transfer under sub-section (2) of section 20.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The persons who have been granted approval for access to biological 
    resources and associated knowledge, intend to transfer the accessed 
    biological resource or knowledge to any other person or organization shall 
    make an application to the Authority in Form IV.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application under 
    sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a fee of ten thousand rupees in the 
    form of Bank draft or Cheque drawn in favour of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Authority shall 
    after collecting any additional information, decide upon the application as 
    far as possible within a period of six months of receipt of the same.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On being satisfied that 
    the applicant has fulfilled all the necessary requirements, the Authority 
    may grant approval for third party transfer subject to such terms and 
    conditions it may deem fit to impose in each case.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The approval as may be 
    granted under sub-rule (4) in the form of a written agreement duly signed by 
    an authorized officer of the Authority and the applicant. The form of the 
    agreement shall be such as may be decided by the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Authority may for 
    reasons to be recorded in writing reject the application if it considers 
    that the request cannot be acceded to provided that no application shall be 
    rejected unless the applicant has been given an opportunity of being heard.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>20</number> Criteria for equitable 
    benefit sharing (section 21).—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Authority shall by notification in the Official Gazette formulate the 
    guidelines and describe the benefit sharing formula.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The guidelines shall 
    provide for monetary and other benefits such as royalty; joint ventures; 
    technology transfer; product development; education and awareness raising 
    activities; institutional capacity building and venture capital fund.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The formula for benefit 
    sharing shall be determined on a case-by-case basis.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Authority while 
    granting approval to any person for access or for transfer of results of 
    research or applying for patent and IPR or for third party transfer of the 
    accessed biological resource and associated knowledge may impose terms and 
    conditions for ensuring equitable sharing of the benefits arising out of the 
    use of accessed biological material and associated knowledge.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The quantum of benefits 
    shall be mutually agreed upon between the persons applying for such approval 
    and the Authority in consultation with the local bodies  and benefit 
    claimers and may be decided in due regard to the defined parameters of 
    access, the extent of use, the sustainability aspect, impact and expected 
    outcome levels, including measures ensuring conservation and sustainable use 
    of biological diversity.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Depending upon each 
    case, the Authority shall stipulate the time frame for assessing benefit 
    sharing on short, medium, and long term benefits.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Authority shall 
    stipulate that benefits shall ensure conservation and sustainable use of 
    biological diversity.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Where biological 
    resources or knowledge is accessed from a specific individual or a group of 
    individuals or organizations, the Authority may take steps to ensure that 
    the agreed amount is paid directly to them through the district 
    administration. Where such individuals or group of individuals or 
    organizations cannot be identified, the monetary benefits shall be deposited 
    in the National Bio-diversity Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Five percent of the 
    assessed benefits shall be earmarked for the Authority or Board as the case 
    may be, towards administrative and service charges.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The Authority shall 
    monitor the flow of benefits as determined under sub-rule (4) in a manner 
    determined by it.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>21</number> Application of National 
    Bio-diversity Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The National Bio-diversity Fund shall be operated by the Chairperson or by 
    such other officer of the Authority as may be authorized in this regard.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The National 
    Bio-diversity Fund shall have two separate heads of accounts, one relating 
    to the receipts from the Central Government and the other concerning the 
    fee, licence fee, royalty and other receipts of the Authority.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>22</number> Constitution of 
    Bio-diversity Management Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every local body shall constitute a Bio-diversity Management Committee (BMCs) 
    within its area of jurisdiction.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Bio-diversity 
    Management Committee as constituted under sub-rule (1) shall consist of a 
    Chairperson and not more than six persons nominated by the local body, of 
    whom not less than one third should be women and not less than 18% should 
    belong to the Scheduled Castes/Scheduled Tribes.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson of the 
    Bio-diversity Management Committee shall be elected from amongst the members 
    of the committee in a meeting to be chaired by the Chairperson of the local 
    body. The Chairperson of the local body shall have the casting votes in case 
    of a tie.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairperson of the 
    Bio-diversity Management Committee shall have a tenure of three years.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The local Member of 
    Legislative Assembly/Member of Legislative Council and Member of Parliament 
    would be special invitees to the meetings of the Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The main function of 
    the BMC is to prepare People’s Bio-diversity Register in consultation with 
    local people. The Register shall contain comprehensive information on 
    availability and knowledge of local biological resources, their medicinal or 
    any other use or any other traditional knowledge associated with them.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The other functions of 
    the BMC are to advise on any matter referred to it by the State 
    Bio-diversity Board or Authority for granting approval, to maintain data 
    about the local vaids and practitioners using the biological resources.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Authority shall 
    take steps to specify the form of the People’s Bio-diversity Registers, and 
    the particulars it shall contain and the format for electronic database.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Authority and the 
    State Bio-diversity Boards shall provide guidance and technical support to 
    the Bio-diversity Management Committees for preparing People’s Bio-diversity 
    Registers.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The People’s 
    Bio-diversity Registers shall be maintained and validated by the 
    Bio-diversity Management Committees.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> The Committee shall 
    also maintain a Register giving information about the details of the access 
    to biological resources and traditional knowledge granted, details of the 
    collection fee imposed and details of the benefits derived and the mode of 
    their sharing.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>23</number> Appeal for settlement 
    of disputes under section 50.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a dispute arises between the Authority or a State Bio-diversity Board or 
    between one Board and other Board(s) on account of implementation of any 
    order or direction or on any issue of policy decision, either of the 
    aggrieved parties, i.e., Authority or the Board, as the case may be, 
    prefer an appeal to the Central Government under section 50, in Form V to 
    the Secretary, Ministry of Environment and Forests, Government of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In case the dispute 
    arises between a State Bio-diversity Board and another State Bio-diversity 
    Board or Boards, the aggrieved Board or Boards, shall prefer the point or 
    points of dispute to the Central Government which shall refer the same to 
    the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The memorandum of 
    appeal shall state the facts of the case, the grounds relied upon by the 
    appellant, for preferring the appeal and the relief sought for.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The memorandum of 
    appeal shall be accompanied by an authenticated copy of the order, direction 
    or policy decision, as the case may be, by which the appellant is aggrieved 
    and shall be duly signed by the authorised representative of the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The memorandum of 
    appeal shall be submitted in quadruplicate, either in person or through a 
    registered post with an acknowledgment due, within 30 days from the date of 
    the orders, direction or policy decision, impugned provided that if the 
    Central Government is satisfied that there was good and sufficient reason 
    for the delay in preferring the appeal, it may, for reason to be recorded in 
    writing, allow the appeal to be preferred after the expiry of the aforesaid 
    period of 30 days but before the expiry of 45 days from the date of the 
    orders impugned, direction or policy decision, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The notice for hearing 
    of the appeal shall be given in Form VI by a registered post with an 
    acknowledgment due.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Central Government 
    shall, after hearing the appellant and the other parties, dispose of the 
    appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In disposing of an 
    appeal it may vary or modify or cancel impugned order, direction or policy, 
    as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> In adjudicating a 
    dispute, the Authority shall be guided by the principles of natural justice 
    and as far as practicable, follow the same procedure which the Central 
    Government is required to follow under this rule.

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>
<number>24</number> Manner of giving notice 
    under section 61.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The manner of giving notice, under clause (b) of section 61, shall be as 
    follows, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   The notice shall be in 
    writing in Form VII.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   The person giving the notice 
    may send it to,—
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   if the alleged offence has 
    taken place in a Union territory, to the Chairperson of the National 
    Bio-diversity Authority; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   if the alleged offence has 
    taken place in a State, to the Chairperson of the State Bio-diversity Board.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice referred to 
    in sub-rule (1) shall be sent by registered post acknowledgment due; and
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The period of thirty 
    days mentioned in clause (b) of section 61 shall be reckoned from the date, 
    the notice is received by the Authorities mentioned in sub-rule (1).

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    2004
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 


Schedule 

    Form I 

(See rule 14)
 



    Application form for access to Biological  

    resources and associated traditional knowledge
 


Part A
 



 


1. Full particulars of the applicant
 
 
 
 

Name:
 
 


        Permanent address:
 
 


        Address of the contact person/agent, if any, in India:
 
 


        Profile of the organization (personal profile in case the applicant is 
        an individual). Please attach relevant documents of authentication:
 
 


        Nature of business:
 
 


        Turnover of the organization in US $:


 


2. Details and specific information about 
    nature of access sought and biological material and associated knowledge to 
    be accessed.
 
 
 
 


Identification (scientific name) of 
        biological resources and its traditional use:
 
 


Geographical location of proposed 
        collection:
 
 


Description/nature of traditional 
        knowledge (oral/documented):
 
 


Any identified individual/community 
        holding the traditional knowledge:
 
 


Quantity of biological resources to be 
        collected (give the Schedule):
 
 


Time span in which the biological 
        resources is proposed to be collected:
 
 


Name and number of person authorized by 
        the company for making the selection:
 
 


The purpose for which the access is 
        requested including the type and extent of research, commercial use 
        being derived and expected to be derived from it:
 
 


Whether any collection of the resource 
        endangers any component of biological diversity and the risks which may 
        arise from the access:


 


3. Details of any national institution which 
    will participate in the Research and Development activities.
 


4. Primary destination of accessed resource 
    and identity of the location where the R&amp;D will be carried out.
 


5. The economic and other benefits including 
    those arriving out of any IPR, patent obtained out of accessed biological 
    resources and knowledge that are intended, or may accrue to the applicant or 
    to the country that he/she belongs.
 


6. The biotechnological, scientific, social or 
    any other benefits obtained out of accessed biological resources and 
    knowledge that are intended, or may accrue to the applicant or to the 
    country that he/she belongs.
 


7. Estimation of benefits, that would flow to 
    India/communities arising out of the use of accessed bioresources and 
    traditional knowledge.
 


8. Proposed mechanism and arrangements for 
    benefit sharing.
 


9. Any other information considered relevant.
 

 
 


Part B 

    Declaration
 

I/We declare 
    that—
 
 
 
 


Collection of proposed biological 
        resources shall not adversely affect the sustainability of the 
        resources;
 
 


Collection of proposed biological 
        resources shall not entail any environmental impact;
 
 


Collection of proposed biological 
        resources shall not pose any risk to ecosystems;
 
 


Collection of proposed biological 
        resources shall not adversely affect the local communities.


 


I/We further declare the information provided 
    in the application form is true and correct and I/we shall be responsible 
    for any incorrect/wrong information.
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

Signature 

        Name 

        Title
 
 

 


 


    Place.......................
 


    Date.........................
 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    2004
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 


Form II 

(See rule 17) 

Application for seeking prior approval of  

    National Bio-diversity Authority for transferring the results of  

    research to foreign nationals, companies, NRI’s, for commercial purposes
 



 



 


1. Full particulars of the applicant
 
 
 
 


Name:
 
 


Address:
 
 


Professional profile:
 
 


Organizational affiliation (Please attach 
        relevant documents of authentication):


 


2. Details of the results of research 
    conducted.
 


3. Details of the Biological resources and/or 
    associated knowledge used in the research.
 


4. Geographical location from where the 
    biological resources used in the research are collected.
 


5. Details of any traditional knowledge used 
    in the research and any identified individual/community holding the 
    traditional knowledge.
 


6. Details of institution where R&amp;D activities 
    carried out.
 


7. Details of the individual/organization to 
    whom the research results are intend to transfer.
 


8. Details of economic, biotechnological, 
    scientific or any other benefits that are intended, or may accrue to the 
    individual/organization due to commercialization of transferred research 
    results.
 


9. Details of economic, biotechnological, 
    scientific or any other benefits that are intended, or may accrue to the 
    applicant seeking approval for transfer of results of research.
 


10. Details of any agreement or MOU between by 
    the proposed recipient and applicant seeking approval for transfer of 
    results of research.
 



    Declaration
 


I/We declare the information provided in the 
    application form is true and correct and I/we shall be responsible for any 
    incorrect/wrong information.
 



                                                                                                       
    Signature
 



                                                                                                       
    Name
 



                                                                                                       
    Title
 


    Place......................
 


    Date........................
 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    2004
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 


Form III 

    (See rule 18) 

Application for seeking prior approval of National  

    Bio-diversity Authority for applying for Intellectual Property Right
 



 


1. Full particulars of the applicant
 
 
 
 


Name:
 
 


Address:
 
 


Professional profile:
 
 


Organizational affiliation (Please attach 
        relevant documents of authentication):


 


2. Details of the invention on which IPRs 
    sought.
 


3. Details of the Biological resources and/or 
    associated knowledge used in the invention.
 


4. Geographical location from where the 
    biological resources used in the invention are collected.
 


5. Details of any traditional knowledge used 
    in the invention and any identified individual/community holding the 
    traditional knowledge.
 


6. Details of institution where Research and 
    Development activities carried out.
 


7. Details of economic, biotechnological, 
    scientific or any other benefits that are intended, or may accrue to the 
    applicant due commercialization of the invention.
 

Declaration
 


I/We declare the information provided in the 
    application form is true and correct and I/we shall be responsible for any 
    incorrect/wrong information.
 



                                                                                                       
    Signature
 



                                                                                                       
    Name
 



                                                                                                       
    Title
 


    Place......................
 


    Date........................
 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    2004
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 


Form IV 

(See rule 19) 

Application form for seeking approval of National  

    Bio-diversity Authority for third party transfer of the accessed  

    Biological resources and associated traditional knowledge
 



 


1. Full particulars of the applicant
 
 
 
 


Name:
 
 


Address:
 
 


Professional profile:
 
 


Organizational affiliation (Please attach 
        relevant documents of authentication):


 


2. Details of the biological material and 
    traditional knowledge accessed.
 


3. Details of the access contract entered 
    (Copy to be enclosed).
 


4. Details of the benefits and 
    mechanism/arrangements for benefit sharing already implemented.
 


5. Full particulars of the third part to whom 
    the accessed material/knowledge is intended to transfer.
 


6. The purpose of the intended third party 
    transfer.
 


7. Details of economic, social, 
    biotechnological, scientific or any other benefits that are intended, or may 
    accrue to the third party due to transfer of accessed biological material 
    and knowledge.
 


8. Details of any agreement to be entered 
    between the applicant and the third party.
 


9. Estimation of benefits that would flow to 
    India/communities arising out of the third party transfer of accessed 
    biological resources and traditional knowledge.
 


10. Proposed mechanism and arrangements for 
    benefit sharing arising out of the proposed third party transfer.
 


11. Any other relevant information.
 

Declaration
 


I/We declare the information provided in the 
    application form is true and correct and I/we shall be responsible for any 
    incorrect/wrong information.
 



                                                                                            
    Signature
 



                                                                                            
    Name
 



                                                                                            
    Title
 


    Place.........................
 


    Date...........................
 

 
 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    2004
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 


Form V 

[See rule 23 (1)] 

Form of Memorandum of Appeal
 


Before 
    the ............... Ministry of Environment and Forests, 
New Delhi 

Or 

    National Bio-diversity Authority 

(as the case may be) 

    (Memorandum of appeal under section 50 of the Biological Diversity Act, 
    2002). 

    Appeal No. ................................... of 20.... 

 

    ................................................................................................................ 
    Appellant(s) 

Versus 


    ............................................................................................................ 
    Respondent(s) 

 

    (here mention the designation of the Authority/Board, as the case may be) 

 

    The appellant begs to prefer this Memorandum of Appeal against the order 
    dated ....................... passed by the Respondent on the following 
    facts and grounds.
 


1. Facts:
 


   (Here briefly mention the facts of the 
    case):
 


2. Ground:
 


   (Here mention the grounds on which the 
    appeal is made):
 


            (i)
 


           (ii)
 


          (iii)
 


3. Relief sought:
 


            (i)
 


           (ii)
 


          (iii)
 


4. Prayer:
 
 

(a)  In 
      the light of what is stated above, the appellant respectfully prays that 
      the order/decision of the respondent be quashed/set aside.
 

(b)  
      The policy/guidelines/regulation framed by the Respondent be 
      quashed/modified/annulled to the extent ......................
 

(c)  
      ....................................................................

 



    Place...................                                                      
    Signature of the appellant with seal
 



    Date.....................                                                     
    Address:
 


    VERIFICATION
 


I, the appellant do hereby declare that what 
    is stated above is true to the best of my information and belief.
 

Verified on 
    ............... day of................
 



                                                                                         
    Signature of the appellant with seal
 



                                                                                         
    Address
 


Signature of the Authorised representative of 
    the appellant
 


Enclosures: 1. Authenticated copy of the 
    order/direction/policy decision, against which the appeal has been 
    preferred.
 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    2004
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 


Form 
    VI 


[See rule 23(6)]
 


Before 
    the ..............Ministry of Environment and Forests, 
New Delhi 

Or 

    National Bio-diversity Authority
 


(as the case may be)
 


Appeal No. ............................ of 
    20....
 


Between
 



    ............................................................................................................. 
    Appellant(s)
 


Versus 

    ............................................................................................................. 
    Respondent(s)
 



    Notice
 


Please take notice that the above appeal filed 
    by the appellant, against the order/direction/policy decision (give details) 
    is fixed for hearing on ............................at
 


The copies of the appeal memorandum and other 
    annexure filed alongwith the appeal are sent herewith for your reference.
 


Please note that if you fails to appear on the 
    said date or other subsequent date of hearing of the appeal, the appeal 
    would be disposed of finally by placing you ex-parte.
 


Authorised signatory on behalf of the 
    Appellate Authority 
 


Date.....................
 



    Place...................                                            (Seal)
 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
BIOLOGICAL DIVERSITY RULES, 
    2004
 


 

 
 

 
 

 
 


Form 
    VII 

    Form of Notice 

[See rule 24 (1)] 

 

    By Registered Post/Acknowledgment due
 


From,
 


.......................................
 


.....................................
 


.....................................
 


To
 


.....................................
 


.....................................
 


Sub: Notice under section 61 (b) of the 
    Biological Diversity Act, 2002.
 


Whereas an offence under the Biological 
    Diversity Act, 2002 has been committed/is being committed by 
    ........................................................................
    
 


2. I/We hereby give notice of 30 days under 
    section 61 (b) of the Biological Diversity Act, 2002 of my/our intention to 
    file a complaint in the Court against ..................................... 
    for violation of the provisions of the Biological Diversity Act, 2002.
 


3. In support of my/our notice, I am/we are 
    enclosing herewith the following documents as evidence of proof.
 


Place.....................
 


Date......................
 


Signature
 


Explanation.—(1) In case the notice to 
    be given in the name of a company, documentary evidence authorising the 
    person to sign the notice on behalf of the company shall be enclosed to the 
    notice.
 


(2) Give the name and address of the alleged 
    offender. In case of using biological resource/knowledge/research/bio-survey 
    and bio-utilisation/the intellectual property right/patent, without the 
    approval of the Authority, the details thereof and the commercial 
    utilisation if any, may be furnished.
 


(3) Documentary evidence shall include 
    photograph, technical report, etc., for enabling enquiry into the alleged 
    violation/offence. 

 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>