<act><title>


the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—2[
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Pre-conception and Pre-natal Diagnostic 
    Techniques (Prohibition of Sex Selection) Rules, 1996.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of 
    their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 
 
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” 
    means The Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of 
    Misuse) Act, 1994 (57 of 1994)†;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    
    “employee” means a person working in or employed by a 

    1[Genetic Counselling 
    Centre, a Genetic Laboratory or a Genetic Clinic, or an Ultrasound
    clinic and
    imaging
    centre] and includes those 
    working on part-time, contractual, consultancy, honorary or on any other 
    basis;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     “Form” 
    means a form appended to these rules;
 

2[***]
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>     
    “section” means a section of the Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>     words 
    and expressions used herein and not defined in these rules but defined in 
    the Act, shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in the Act.
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” 
    means The Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of 
    Misuse) Act, 1994 (57 of 1994)†;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    
    “employee” means a person working in or employed by a 

    1[Genetic Counselling 
    Centre, a Genetic Laboratory or a Genetic Clinic, or an Ultrasound
    clinic and
    imaging
    centre] and includes those 
    working on part-time, contractual, consultancy, honorary or on any other 
    basis;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>     “Form” 
    means a form appended to these rules;
 

2[***]
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>     
    “section” means a section of the Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>     words 
    and expressions used herein and not defined in these rules but defined in 
    the Act, shall have the meanings, respectively, assigned to them in the Act.
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article>1[<number>3</number> The qualification of the employees, the requirement of 
      equipment etc., for a Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, 
      Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic and Imaging Centre shall be as under:  
 <section><number>1</number> Any person being or employing—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>   a gynaecologist or a 
      paediatrician having six months experience or four weeks training in 
      genetic counselling, or
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>  a medical 
      geneticists,
 having adequate space and 
      educational charts/models/equipments for carrying out genetic counselling 
      may set up a genetic counselling centre and get it registered as a genetic 
      counselling centre.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> (a) Any person having adequate 
      space and being or employing—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>   a Medical Geneticist 
      and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>  a laboratory technician, having 
      a B.Sc. degree in Biological Sciences or a degree or diploma in medical 
      laboratory course with at least one year experience in conducting 
      appropriate prenatal diagnostic techniques, tests or 
      procedures.
        may set up 
      a genetic laboratory.
 <subsubsection><number>b</number> Such laboratory should have or acquire such 
      of the following equipments as may be necessary for carrying out 
      chromosomal studies, bio-chemical studies and molecular 
      studies:—
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>i</number> Chromosomal studies:  
 <subsubsection><number>1</number>    Laminar flow hood with 
      ultraviolet and fluorescent light or other  suitable culture 
      hood.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>2</number>    Photo-microscope with 
      fluorescent source of light.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>3</number>    Inverted 
      microscope.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>4</number>    Incubator and oven. 
      
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>5</number>    Carbon dioxide incubator 
      or closed system with 5% CO2 atmosphere.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>6</number>    Autoclave. 
      
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>7</number>    
      Refrigerator.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>8</number>    Water 
      bath.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>9</number>    
      Centrifuge.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>10</number>  Vortex mixer.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>11</number>  Magnetic strirrer.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>12</number>  pH Meter.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>13</number>  A sensitive balance (preferably 
      electronic) with sensitivity of 0.1 milligram.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>14</number>  Double distillation apparatus 
      (glass).
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>15</number>  Such other equipments as may be 
      necessary.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Biochemical studies:  
   
         (requirements according to tests to be carried out)  
 <subsubsection><number>1</number>    Laminar flow hood with 
      ultraviolet and fluorescent light or other suitable culture 
      hood.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>2</number>    Inverted 
      microscope.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>3</number>    Incubator and 
      oven.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>4</number>    Carbon dioxide incubator 
      or closed system with 5% CO2 atmosphere.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>5</number>    
      Autoclave.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>6</number>    
      Refrigerator.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>7</number>    Water 
      bath.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>8</number>    
      Centrifuge.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>9</number>    Electrophoresis apparatus 
      and power supply.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>10</number>  Chromatography 
      chamber.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>11</number>  Spectro-photometer and Elisa reader 
      or Radioimmunoassay system (with gamma beta-counter) or fluorometer for 
      various biochemical tests.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>12</number>  Vortex mixer.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>13</number>  Magnetic stirrer.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>14</number>  pH meter.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>15</number>  A sensitive balance (preferably 
      electronic) with sensitivity of 0.1 milligram.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>16</number>  Double distillation apparatus 
      (glass).
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>17</number>  Liquid nitrogen 
      tank.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>18</number>  Such other equipments as may be 
      necessary.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Molecular studies:  
 <subsubsection><number>1</number>    Inverted 
      microscope.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>2</number>    
      Incubator.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>3</number>    Oven.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>4</number>    
      Autoclave.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>5</number>    Refrigerators (4 degree 
      and minus 20 degree Centigrade).
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>6</number>    Water 
      bath.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>7</number>    
      Microcentrifuge.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>8</number>    Electrophoresis apparatus 
      and power supply.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>9</number>    Vertex 
      mixer.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>10</number>  Magnetic stirrer.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>11</number>  pH meter.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>12</number>  A sensitive balance (preferably 
      electronic) with sensitivity of 0.1 milligram.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>13</number>  Double distillation apparatus 
      (glass).
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>14</number>  P.C.R. machine.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>15</number>  Refrigerated 
      centrifuge.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>16</number>  U.V. Illuminator with photographic 
      attachment or other documentation system.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>17</number>  Precision 
      micropipettes.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>18</number>  Such other equipments as may be 
      necessary.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>3</number> (1) Any person having adequate 
      space and being or employing—  
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number>    Gynaecologist having 
      experience of performing at least 20 procedures in chorionic villi 
      aspirations per vagina or per abdomen, chorionic villi biopsy, 
      amniocentesis, cordocentesis foetoscopy, foetal skin or organ biopsy or 
      foetal blood sampling etc., under supervision of an experienced 
      gynaecologist in these fields, or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number>    a Sonologist, Imaging 
      Specialist, Radiologist or Registered Medical Practitioner having 
      Post-Graduate degree or diploma or six months training or one year 
      experience in sonography or image scanning, or
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>c</number>     A medical 
      geneticist,
 may set up a genetic 
      clinic/ultrasound clinic/imaging centre.  
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection><number>2</number> The Genetic Clinic/ultrasound 
      clinic/imaging centre should have or acquire such of the following 
      equipments, as may be necessary for carrying out the tests or 
      procedures—
 <subsubsubsection><number>a</number>    equipment and accessories 
      necessary for carrying out clinical examination by an obstetrician or 
      gynaecologist;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>b</number>    an ultra-sonography 
      machine including mobile ultrasound machine, imaging machine or any other 
      equipment capable of conducting foetal ultrasonography;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>c</number>     appropriate 
      catheters and equipment for carrying out chorionic villi aspirations per 
      vagina or per abdomen;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>d</number>    appropriate sterile 
      needles for amniocentesis or cordocentesis;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>e</number>     a suitable 
      foetoscope with appropriate accessories for foetoscopy, foetal skin or 
      organ biopsy or foetal blood sampling shall be optional.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>f</number>     equipment for dry 
      and wet sterilization;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>g</number>    equipment for carrying out 
      emergency procedures such as evacuation of uterus or resuscitation in case 
      of need; 
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection><number>h</number>    genetic works 
      station.]
  
  





 
</subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

1[<number>3A</number> 
    Sale of ultrasound machines/imaging machines.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No organization including a commercial organization or a person, including 
    manufacturer, importer, dealer or supplier of ultrasound machines/imaging 
    machines or any other equipment, capable of detecting sex of foetus, shall 
    sell, distribute, supply, rent, allow or authorize the use of any such 
    machine or equipment in any manner, whether on payment or otherwise, to any 
    Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound 
    Clinic, Imaging Centre or any other body or person unless such Centre, 
    Laboratory, Clinic, body or person is registered under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provider of such machine/equipment to 
    any person/body registered under the Act shall send to the concerned 
    State/UT Appropriate Authority and to the Central Government, once in three 
    months a list of those to whom the machine/equipment has been provided.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any organization or person, including 
    manufacturer, importer, dealer or supplier of ultrasound machines/imaging 
    machines or any other equipment capable of detecting sex of foetus selling, 
    distributing, supplying or authorizing, in any manner, the use of any such 
    machine or equipment to any Genetic Counselling
    centre, Genetic Laboratory, 
    Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic, Imaging Centre or any other body or 
    person registered under the Act shall take an affidavit from the Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic, 
    Imaging Centre or any other body or person purchasing or getting 
    authorization for using such machine/equipment that the machine/equipment 
    shall not be used for detection of sex of foetus or selection of sex before 
    or after conception.]
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Registration of </title><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Genetic Counselling 
Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic and Imaging c 
entre.— </title>
<section><number>1</number> An application for registration shall be made to the 
Appropriate Authority, in duplicate, in Form A, duly accompanied by an affidavit 
containing— 
 <subsection><number>i</number> an undertaking to the effect that the Genetic 
Centre/Laboratory/Clinic/Ultrasound Clinic/Imaging Centre/Combination thereof, 
as the case may be, shall not conduct any test or procedure, by whatever name 
called, for selection of sex before or after conception or for detection of sex 
of foetus except for diseases specified in section 4 (2) nor shall the sex of 
foetus be disclosed to any body; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> an undertaking to the effect that the Genetic Centre/Laboratory/Clinic/ 
Combination thereof, as the case may be, shall display prominently a notice that 
they do not conduct any technique, test or procedure etc., by whatever name 
called, for detection of sex of foetus or for selection of sex before or after 
conception.] 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Appropriate Authority, or any person in his office authorised in this 
behalf, shall acknowledge receipt of the application for registration, in the 
acknowledgement slip provided at the bottom of Form A, immediately if delivered 
at the office of the Appropriate Authority, or not later than the next working 
day if received by post. 

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

1[<number>5</number> 
    Application Fee.—
<section><number>1</number> Every application for 
    registration under rule 4 shall be accompanied by an application fee of—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    Rs. 
    3000.00 for Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, 
    Ultrasound Clinic or Imaging Centre.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    Rs. 
    4000.00 for an institute, hospital, nursing home, or any place providing 
    jointly the service of a Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory and 
    Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic or 
    imaging Centre or any combination thereof:
 
Provided that if an application for 
    registration of any Genetic Clinic/Laboratory/Centre, etc., has been 
    rejected by the Appropriate Authority, no fee shall be required to be paid 
    on re-submission of the application by the applicant for the same body 
    within 90 days of rejection. Provided further that any subsequent 
    application shall be accompanied with the prescribed fee. Application fee 
    once paid will not be refunded.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The application fee shall be paid by a 
    demand draft drawn in favour of the Appropriate Authority, on any scheduled 
    bank payable at the headquarters of the Appropriate Authority concerned. The 
    fees collected by the Appropriate Authorities for registration of Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic 
    and Imaging Centre or any other body or person under sub-rule (1), shall be 
    deposited by the Appropriate Authority concerned in a bank account opened in 
    the name of the official designation of the Appropriate Authority concerned 
    and shall be utilized by the Appropriate Authority in connection with the 
    activities connected with implementation of the provisions of the Act and 
    these rules.]  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Appropriate Authority shall, after making such enquiry and after satisfying 
    itself that the applicant has complied with all the requirements, place the 
    application before the Advisory Committee for its advice.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Having regard to the advice of the 
    Advisory Committee the Appropriate Authority shall grant a certificate of 
    registration, in duplicate, in Form B to the applicant.  One copy of the 
    certificate of registration shall be displayed by the registered 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound
    clinic or Imaging
    centre] at a conspicuous 
    place at its place of business:  
 
Provided that the Appropriate Authority may 
    grant a certificate of registration to a Genetic Laboratory or a Genetic 
    Clinic to conduct one or more specified pre-natal diagnostic tests or 
    procedures, depending on the availability of place, equipment and qualified 
    employees, and standards maintained by such laboratory or clinic.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, after enquiry and after giving an 
    opportunity of being heard to the applicant and having regard to the advice 
    of the Advisory Committee, the Appropriate Authority is satisfied that the 
    applicant has not complied with the requirements of the Act and these rules, 
    it shall, for the reasons to be recorded in writing, reject the application 
    for registration and communicate such rejection to the applicant as 
    specified in Form C.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An enquiry under sub-rule (1), 
    including inspection at the premises of the 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound
    clinic or Imaging
    centre],  shall, be carried 
    out only after due notice is given to the applicant by the Appropriate 
    Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Grant of certificate of registration or 
    rejection of application for registration shall be communicated to the 
    applicant as specified in Form B or Form C, as the case may be, within a 
    period or ninety days from the date of receipt of application for 
    registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The certificate of registration 
    shall be non-transferable. In the event of change of ownership or change of 
    management or on ceasing to function as a 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound
    clinic or Imaging
    centre], both copies of the 
    certificate of registration shall be surrendered to the Appropriate 
    Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>  In the event of change of ownership 
    or change of management of the 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound
    clinic or Imaging
    centre], the new owner or 
    manager of such Centre, Laboratory or Clinic shall apply afresh for grant of 
    certificate of registration.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Validity of registration.—Every 
    certificate of regtistration shall be valid for a period of five years from 
    the date of its issue.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Renewal of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
    application  for renewal of certificate of registration shall be made in 
    duplicate in Form A, to the Appropriate Authority thirty days before the 
    date of expiry of the certificate of registration. Acknowledgement of 
    receipt of such application shall be issued by the Appropriate Authority in 
    the manner specified in sub-rule (2) of rule 4.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Appropriate Authority shall, after 
    holding an enquiry and after satisfying itself that the applicant has 
    complied with all the requirements of the Act and these rules and having 
    regard to the advice of the Advisory Committee in this behalf, renew the 
    certificate of registration, as specified in Form B, for a further period of 
    five years from the date of expiry of the certificate of registration 
    earlier granted.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, after enquiry and after giving an 
    opportunity of being heard to the applicant and having regard to the advice 
    of the Advisory Committee, the Appropriate Authority is satisfied that the 
    applicant has not  complied with the requirements of the Act and these 
    rules, it shall, for reasons to be recorded in writing, reject the 
    application for renewal of certificate of registration and communicate such 
    rejection to the applicant as specified in Form C.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The fees payable for renewal of 
    certificate registration shall be one half of the fees provided in sub-rule 
    (1) of rule 5.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On receipt of the renewed 
    certificate of registration in duplicate or on receipt of communication of 
    rejection of application for renewal, both copies of the earlier certificate 
    of registration shall be surrendered immediately to the Appropriate 
    Authority by the 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic Ultrasound
    clinic or Imaging
    centre].  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In the event of failure of the Appropriate 
    Authority to renew the certificate of registration or to communicate 
    rejection of application for renewal of registration within a period of 
    ninety days from the date of receipt of application for renewal of 
    registration, the certificate of registration shall be deemed to have been 
    renewed.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Maintenance and preservation of 
    records.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, 
    Ultrasound Clinic and Imaging Centre shall maintain a register showing, in 
    serial order, the names and addresses of the men or women given genetic 
    counselling, subjected to pre-natal diagnostic procedures or pre-natal 
    diagnostic tests, the names of their spouse or father and the date on which 
    they first reported for such counselling, procedure or test.]  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  The record to be maintained by every 
    Genetic Counselling Centre, in respect of each woman counselled shall be as 
    specified in Form D.  
 

1[(3) 
    The record to be maintained by every Genetic Laboratory, in respect of each 
    man or woman subjected to any pre-natal diagnostic procedure/technique/test, 
    shall be as specified in Form E.]  
 

1[(4) 
    The record to be maintained by every Genetic Clinic, in respect of each man 
    or woman subjected to any pre-natal diagnostic procedure/technique/test, 
    shall be as specified in Form F.]  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>  The Appropriate Authority shall maintain 
    a permanent record of applications for grant or renewal of certificate of 
    registration as specified in Form H. Letters of intimation of every change 
    of employee, place, address and equipment installed shall also be preserved 
    a permanent records.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> All case related-records, forms of 
    consent, laboratory results, microscopic pictures, sonographic plates or 
    slides, recommendations and letters shall be preserved by the 
2[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic or 
    Imaging centre for a period 
    of two years from the date of completion of counselling, pre-natal 
    diagnostic procedure or pre-natal diagnostic test, as the case may be. In 
    the event of any legal proceedings, the records shall be preserved till the 
    final disposal of legal proceedings, or till the expiry of the said period 
    of two years, whichever is later.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>  In case the 
2[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre or Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic or Ultrasound 
    Clinic or Imaging Centre maintains records on computer or other electronic 
    equipment, a printed copy of the record shall be taken and preserved after 
    authentication by a person responsible for such record.
 

1[(8) 
    Every Genetic Counselling centre, 
    Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic and Imaging Centre 
    shall send a complete report in respect of all pre-conception or pregnancy 
    related procedures/techniques/tests conducted by them in respect of each 
    month by 5th day of the following month to the concerned Appropriate 
    Authority.]  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Conditions for conducting 
    pre-natal  diagnostic  procedures.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Before conducting preimplantation genetic diagnosis, or any pre-natal 
    diagnostic technique/test/procedure such as amniocentesis, chorionic villli 
    biopsy, foetoscopy, foetal skin or organ biospsy or cordocentesis, a written 
    consent, as specified in Form G, in a language the person undergoing such 
    procedure understands, shall be obtained from her/him:]  
 
Provided that where a Genetic Clinic has taken 
    a sample of any body tissue or body fluid and sent it to a Genetic 
    Laboratory for analysis or test, it shall not be necessary for the Genetic 
    Laboratory to obtain a fresh consent in Form G.  
 

2[(1A) 
    Any person conducting ultrasonography/image scanning on a pregnant woman 
    shall give a declaration on each report on ultrasonography/image scanning 
    that he/she has neither detected nor disclosed the sex of foetus of the 
    pregnant woman to any body. The pregnant woman shall before undergoing 
    ultrasonography/image scanning declare that she does not want to know the 
    sex of her foetus.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  All the State Governments and Union 
    territories may issue translation of Form G in languages used in the State 
    or Union Territory and where no official translation in a language 
    understood by the pregnant woman is available, the Genetic Clinic may 
    translate Form G into a language she understands.
 
 






 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>11</number> Facilities for inspection. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every Genetic Counselling Centre, 
  Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic, Imaging Centre, nursing home, hospital, institute or any other place where any of the machines or 
equipments capable of performing any procedure, technique or test capable of pre-natal determination of sex or selection of sex before or after conception is used, shall afford all reasonable facilities for inspection of the place, equipment and records to the Appropriate Authority or to any other person authorised by the Appropriate Authority in this behalf for registration of such institutions, by whatever name called, under the Act, or for detection of misuse of such facilities or advertisement therefor or for selection of sex before or after conception or for detection/disclosure of sex of foetus or for detection of cases of violation of the provisions of the Act in any other manner. 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum></title>[<number>2</number> The Appropriate Authority or the officer authorised by it may seal and seize any ultrasound machine, scanner or any other equipment, capable of detecting sex of foetus, used by any organisation if the organisation has not got itself registered under the Act. These machines of such organisations shall be confiscated and further action shall be taken as per the provisions of the section 23 of the Act.] 





</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>11</number> Facilities for inspection. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every Genetic Counselling Centre, 
  Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic, Imaging Centre, nursing home, hospital, institute or any other place where any of the machines or 
equipments capable of performing any procedure, technique or test capable of pre-natal determination of sex or selection of sex before or after conception is used, shall afford all reasonable facilities for inspection of the place, equipment and records to the Appropriate Authority or to any other person authorised by the Appropriate Authority in this behalf for registration of such institutions, by whatever name called, under the Act, or for detection of misuse of such facilities or advertisement therefor or for selection of sex before or after conception or for detection/disclosure of sex of foetus or for detection of cases of violation of the provisions of the Act in any other manner. 
 </section><section><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum></title>[<number>2</number> The Appropriate Authority or the officer authorised by it may seal and seize any ultrasound machine, scanner or any other equipment, capable of detecting sex of foetus, used by any organisation if the organisation has not got itself registered under the Act. These machines of such organisations shall be confiscated and further action shall be taken as per the provisions of the section 23 of the Act.] 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Procedure for search and 
    seizure.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Appropriate authority or 
    any officer authorised in this behalf may enter and search at all reasonable 
    times any Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, 
    Imaging Centre or Ultrasound Clinic in the presence of two or more 
    independent witnesses for the purposes of search and examination of any 
    record, register, document, book, pamphlet, advertisement, or any other 
    material object found therein and seal and seize the same if there is reason 
    to believe that it may furnish evidence of commission of an offence 
    punishable under the Act.  
 
Explanation.—In these Rules—  
 </section><section>
<number>1</number>    
    'Genetic Laboratory/Genetic Clinic/Genetic Counselling Centre’ would include 
    an ultrasound
    centre/imaging
    centre/nursing 
    home/hospital/institute or any other place, by whatever name called, where 
    any of the machines or equipments capable of selection of sex before or 
    after conception or performing any procedure technique or test for pre-natal 
    detection of sex of foetus, is used; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    
    ‘material object’ would include records, machines and equipments; and
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    ‘seize’ 
    and ‘seizure’ would include ‘seal’ and ‘sealing’ respectively.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A list of any document, record, 
    register, book, pamphlet, advertisement or any other material object found 
    in the 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic 
    and Imaging Centre] and seized shall be prepared in duplicate at the place 
    of effecting the seizure. Both copies of such list shall be signed on every 
    page by the Appropriate Authority or the officer authorised in this behalf 
    and by the witnesses to the seizure:  
 
Provided that the list may be prepared, in the 
    presence of the witnesses, at a place other than the place of seizure if, 
    for reasons to be recorded in writing, it is not practicable to make the 
    list at the place of effecting the seizure.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> One copy of the list referred to in 
    sub-rule (2) shall be handed over, under acknowledgement, to the person from 
    whose custody the document, record, register, book, pamphlet advertisement 
    or any other material object have been seized:  
 
Provided that a copy of the list of such 
    document, record, register, book, pamphlet, advertisement or other material 
    object seized may be delivered under acknowledgement, or sent by registered 
    post to the owner or manager of the 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic 
    and Imaging Centre], if no person acknowledging custody of the document, 
    record, register, book, pamphlet, advertisement or other material object 
    seized is available at the place of effecting the seizure.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If any material object seized is 
    perishable in nature, the Appropriate Authority, or the officer authorised 
    in this behalf shall make arrangements promptly for sealing, identification 
    and preservation of the material object and also convey it to a facility for 
    analysis or test, if analysis or test be required:  
 
Provided that the refrigerator or other 
    equipment used by the 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory,  Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic 
    and Imaging Centre] for preserving such perishable material object may be 
    sealed until such time as arrangements can be made for safe removal of such 
    perishable material object and in such eventuality, mention of keeping the 
    material object seized, on the premises of the Genetic Counselling Centre, 
    Genetic Laboratory or Genetic Clinic shall be made in the list of seizure.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the case of non-completion of 
    search and seizure operation, the Appropriate Authority or the officer 
    authorized in this behalf may make arrangements, by way of mounting a guard 
    or sealing of the premises of the 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic 
    and Imaging Centre], for safe keeping, listing and removal of documents, 
    records, book or any other material object to be seized, and to prevent any 
    tampering with such documents, records, books or any other material object.  
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Intimation of changes in 
    employees, place or equipment.—Every 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic 
    and Imaging Centre] shall intimate every change of employee, place, address 
    and equipment installed, to the Appropriate Authority within a period of 
    thirty  days of such change.  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Conditions for analysis or test and 
    pre-natal diagnostic procedures.—
<section><number>1</number> No Genetic Laboratory shall accept 
    for analysis or test any sample, unless referred to it by a Genetic Clinic.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every pre-natal diagnostic procedure shall 
    invariably be immediately preceded by locating the foetus and placenta 
    through ultrasonography, and the pre-natal diagnostic procedure shall be 
    done under direct ultrasonographic monitoring so as to prevent any damage to 
    the foetus and placenta.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Meetings of the Advisory Committees.—The 
    intervening period between any two meetings of Advisory Commitees 
    constituted under sub-section (5) of section 17 to advise the 
    Appropriate Authority shall not exceed sixty days.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Allowances to members of the Central 
    Supervisory Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The ex-officio members, and other Central 
    and State Government officers appointed to the Board will be entitled to 
    Travelling Allowance and Daily Allowance for attending the meetings of the 
    Board as per the Travelling Allowances rules applicable to them.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The non-official members appointed to, and 
    Members of Parliament elected to, the Board will be entitled to Travelling 
    Allowance and Daily Allowance or attending the meetings of the Board as 
    admissible to non-official and Members of Parliament as the case may be, 
    under the Travelling Allowances rules of the Central Government.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Public Information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every 
    1[Genetic Counselling Centre, Genetic Laboratory, 
    Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic and Imaging Centre] shall prominently 
    display on its premises a notice in English and in the local language or 
    languages for the information of the public, to the effect that disclosure 
    of the sex of the foetus is prohibited under law.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At least one copy each of the Act 
    and these rules shall be available on the premises of every 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling, Centre, Genetic Laboratory, Genetic Clinic, Ultrasound Clinic 
    and Imaging Centre], and shall be made available to the clientele on demand 
    for perusal.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Appropriate Authority, the 
    Central Government, the State Government, and the Government/Administration 
    of the Union Territory may publish periodically lists of registered 
1[Genetic 
    Counselling Centres, Genetic Laboratories, Genetic Clinics, Ultrasound 
    Clinics and Imaging Centres] and findings from the reports and other 
    information in their possession, for the information of the public and for 
    use by the experts in the field.
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

1[<number>18</number> 
    Code of Conduct to be observed by persons working at Genetic Counselling 
    Centres, Genetic Laboratories, Genetic Clinics, Ultrasound Clinics, Imaging 
    Centres, etc.—All persons including the owners, 
    employee or any other persons associated with Genetic Counselling Centres, 
    Genetic Laboratories, Genetic Clinics, Ultrasound Clinics, Imaging Centres 
    registered under the Act/these rules shall—
 <section>
<number>i</number>     not 
    conduct or associate with, or help in carrying out detection or disclosure 
    of sex of foetus in any manner;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    not 
    employ or cause to be employed any person not possessing qualifications 
    necessary for carrying out pre-natal diagnostic techniques/procedures, 
    techniques and tests including ultra-sonography;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   not 
    conduct or cause to be conducted or aid in conducting by himself or through 
    any other person any techniques or procedure for selection of sex before or 
    after conception or for detection of sex of foetus except for the purposes 
    specified in sub-section (2) of section 4 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>   not 
    conduct or cause to be conducted or aid in conducting by himself or through 
    any other person any techniques or test or procedure under the Act at a 
    place other than a place registered under the Act/these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    ensure 
    that no provision of the Act and these rules are violated in any manner;
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>   ensure 
    that the person, conducting any techniques, test or procedure leading to 
    detection of sex of foetus for purposes not covered under section 4 (2) of 
    the Act or selection of sex before or after conception, is informed that 
    such procedures lead to violation of the Act and these rules which are 
    punishable offences;
 </section><section>
<number>vii</number>    help 
    the law enforcing agencies in bring to book the violators of the provisions 
    of the Act and these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>viii</number>    
    display his/her name and designation prominently on the dress worn by 
    him/her;
 </section><section>
<number>ix</number>   write 
    his/her name and designation in full under his/her signature;
 </section><section>
<number>x</number>    on no 
    account conduct or allow/cause to be conducted female foeticide;
 </section><section>
<number>xi</number>   not 
    commit any other act of professional misconduct.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

1[<number>19</number> 
    Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> Anybody aggrieved by the decision of 
    the Appropriate Authority at sub-district level may appeal to the 
    Appropriate Authority at district level within 30 days of the order of the 
    sub-district level Appropriate Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Anybody aggrieved by the decision of the 
    Appropriate Authority at district level may appeal to the Appropriate 
    Authority at State/UT level within 30 days of the order of the district 
    level Appropriate Authority.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Each appeal shall be disposed of by the 
    District Appropriate Authority or by the State/Union Territory Appropriate 
    Authority, as the case may be, within 60 days of its receipt.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If an appeal is not made within the time 
    as prescribed under sub-rule (1), (2) or (3), the Appropriate Authority 
    under that sub-rule may condone the delay in case he/she is satisfied that 
    appellant was prevented for sufficient cause from making such appeal.]
 
 




 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 

 
 



1[FORM 
    A
 


[See rules 4 (1) 
    and 8 (1)]
 


(To be submitted in 
    duplicate with supporting documents as enclosures)
 



form of application 
    for registration or renewal of  

    registration of a genetic counselling centre/genetic  

    laboratory/genetic clinic/ultrasound clinic/ 

    imaging centre
 

 
 



    1.    Name of the applicant
 



           (Indicate name of the organisation sought to be registered)
 



    2.    Address of the applicant
 



    3.    Type of facility to be registered
 



    (Please specify whether the application is for registration of a Genetic 
    Counselling Centre/Genetic Laboratory/Genetic Clinic/Ultrasound 
    Clinic/Imaging Centre or any combination of these)
 



    4.    Full name and address/addresses of Genetic Counselling Centre/Genetic 
    Laboratory/Genetic Clinic/Ultrasound Clinic/Imaging  Centre with 
    Telephone/Fax number(s)/Telegrahic/Telex/E-mail address(s).
 


5.     
    Type of ownership of Organisation  (individual 
    ownership/partnership/company/co-operative/any other to be specified). In 
    case type of organization is other than individual ownership, furnish copy 
    of articles of association and names and addresses of other persons 
    responsible for management, as enclosure.
 


6.     
    Type of Institution (Govt. Hospital/Municipal Hospital/Public 
    Hospital/Private Hospital /Private Nursing Home/Private Clinic/Private 
    Laboratory/any other to be stated.
 


7.     
    Specific pre-natal diagnostic procedures/tests for which approval is sought
 


(a) 
    Invasive                   Amniocentesis/Chorionic villi aspiration/
 



                                      Chromosomal/Biochemical/Molecular studies
 


(b) 
    Non-Invasive            Ultrasonography
 


Leave 
    blank if registration is sought for Genetic Counselling Centre only.
 


8.     
    Equipment available with the make and model of each equipment (List to be 
    attached on a separate sheet).
 


9.     
    (a) Facilities available in the Counselling Centre.
 


(b) 
    Whether facilities are or would be available in the Laboratory/Clinic for 
    the following tests:—
 


(i)    Ultrasound 

 


(ii)   Amniocentesis
 


(iii) Chorionic villi 
    aspiration
 


(iv)  Foetoscopy
 


(v)   Foetal biopsy
 


(vi)  Cordocentesis
 



    (c) Whether facilities are available in the Laboratory/Clinic for the 
    following:—
 


(i)    Chromosomal 
    studies 
 


(ii)   Biochemical 
    studies 
 


(iii) Molecular studies
 


(iv)  Preimplantation 
    genetic diagnosis
 


10. 
    Names, qualifications, experience and registration number of employees (may 
    be furnished as an enclosure).
 


11.   
    State whether the Genetic counselling Centre/Genetic Laboratory/Genetic 
    Clinic/ultrasound
    clinic/imaging
    centre* qualifies for 
    registration in terms of requirements laid down in rule 3]
 


12.   
    For renewal applications only:
 



    (a)     Registration No.
 


(b)    
    Date of issue and date of expiry of existing certificate of registration.
 


13.    
    List of Enclosures:
 



    (Please attach a list of enclosures/supporting documents attached to this 
    application.)
 



    Date...............................         
 



    Place..............................         
 


Name, designation and 
    signature of the person authorized
 


to sign on behalf of the 
    organisation to be registered
 

 
 



    DECLARATRION
 


I, Sh./Smt./Kum./Dr…………………………son/daughter/wife 
    of…………………… aged……………years resident of ……………………………………………………….working as 
    (indicate designation)……………………………………………………in (indicate name of the 
    organisation to be registered)………………………..hereby declare that I have read and 
    understood the Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of 
    Misuse) Act, 1994 (57of 1994)† and 
    the Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) 
    Rules, 1996††.
 


I also undertake to 
    explain the said Act and Rules to all employees of the Genetic Counselling 
    Centre/Genetic Laboratory/Genetic Clinic/ultrasound 
    Clinic/Imaging Centre in repect of which registration is sought and to 
    ensure that Act and rules are fully complied with.
 



    Date..............................          
 



    Place..............................         
 


Name, designation and 
    signature of the person authorized
 


to sign on behalf of the 
    organisation to be registered
 

 
 


[SEAL OF THE ORGANISATION 
    SOUGHT TO BE REGISTERED]
 

 
 


ACKNOWLEDGEMENT  
 


[See rules 4 (2) 
    and 8 (1)]  
 


The application in Form A 
    in duplicate for grant* renewal* of registration of Genetic Counselling 
    Centre*/Genetic  Laboratory*/Genetic  Clinic*/Ultrasound  Clinic*/Imaging  
    Centre*  by…………….(Name and address of applicant) has been received by the 
    Appropriate Authority……………….On (date).
 


*The list of enclosures 
    attached to the application in Form A has been verified with the enclosures 
    submitted and found to be correct.  
 


OR
 


*On verification it is 
    found that the following documents mentioned in the list of enclosures are 
    not actually enclosed.  
 


This acknowledgement does 
    not confer any rights on the applicant for grant or renewal of registration.  
 


 
 



                                                                           
     Signature and Designation of Appropriate 
 



    Date………………………..                                  
 



    Place……………………….                                  
 


Authority, or authorized 
    person in the 
 


Office of the Appropriate 
    Authority.
 



                                            SEAL]
 

 
 


*Strike out whichever is 
    not applicable or not necessary.  
 


All enclosures are to be 
    authenticated by signature of the applicant.  
 

 
 



                                                            ORIGINAL/DUPLICATE 
    FOR DISPLAY
 


 
 


 
 



    --------------------------------
 



    1.     Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 
    14-2-2003).
 


† 
         Now the Pre-conception and Pre-natal Diagnostic
    techniques (Prohibition of 
    Sex Selection) act, 1994 (57 
    of 1994).
 


†† 
       Now the Pre-conception and Pre-natal Diagnostic
    techniques (Prohibition of 
    Sex Selection) Rules, 1996.
 



    --------------------------------
 


 
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 



 



1[FORM 
    B
 


[See rules 6 (2), 
    6 (5) and 8 (2)]
 


CERTIFICATE OF 
    REGISTRATION
 


(To be issued in 
    duplicate)
 

 
 


1.    
    In exercise of the powers conferred under section 19 (1) of the Pre-natal 
    Diagnostic Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) Act, 1994 (57 of 
    1994)†, 
    the Appropriate Authority……….. hereby grants registration to the Genetic  

    Counselling Centre*/Genetic Laboratory*/Genetic Clinic*/Ultrasound 
    Clinic*/Imaging Centre* named below for purposes of carrying out Genetic 
    Counselling/Pre-natal Diagnostic Procedures*/Pre-natal Diagnostic Tests/ultrasonography
     

    under the aforesaid Act for a period of five years ending 
    on.................
 


2.    
    This registration is granted subject to the aforesaid Act and rules framed 
    thereunder and any contravention thereof shall result in suspension or 
    cancellation of this Certificate of Registration before the expiry of the 
    said period of five years apart from prosecution.
 


A.     
    Name and address of the Genetic counselling 
    Centre*/Genetic Laboratory*/Genetic Clinic*/Ultrasound Clinic*/Imaging 
    Centre*.
 



    B.      Pre-natal diagnostic procedures* approved for (Genetic Clinic). 
    Non-Invasive 
 


(i) Ultrasound Invasive
 


(ii) Amniocentesis
 


(iii) Chorionic villi 
    biopsy
 


(iv)  Foetoscopy
 


(v)   Foetal skin or 
    organ biopsy
 


(vi)  Cordocentesis
 


(vii) Any other (specify)
 


C.     
    Pre-natal diagnostic tests* approved (for Genetic Laboratory)
 


(i)    Chromosomal 
    studies
 


(ii)   Biochemical 
    studies
 


(iii) Molecular studies
 


D.     
    Any other purpose (please specify)
 


3.   
    Model and make of equipments being used (any
 


       
       change is to be intimated to the Appropriate
 


          
    Authority under rule 13).
 


4.   
    Registration No. allotted
 


5.   
    Period of validity of earlier Certificate of Registration.  

 


(For renewed Certificate 
    Registration only) 
    From.................to.....................................
 



    Date.................................                        

 


Signature, name and 
    designation of  
 


 

                                                                            
      the Appropriate Authority               
    
 




                                                                                                                            
    Seal]
 

 
 



* 
Strike out whichever is not applicable or 
    necessary
 
 


DISPLAY ONE COPY OF THIS 
    CERTIFICATE AT A CONsPICUOUS 
    PLACE AT THE PLACE OF BUSINESS
 


 
 


 
 



    ---------------------------------
 


   
    1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 109(E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).
 


   †   Now the 
    Pre-conception and Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Prohibition of Sex 
    Selection) Act, 1994 (57 of 1994).
 



    ---------------------------------
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 



 



1[FORM 
    C
 


[See rules 6 (3), 6 (5) 
    and 8 (3)]
 


FORM FOR REJECTION Of 
    APPLICATION FOR GRANT/RENEWAL OF  

    REGISTRATION
 

 
 


In exercise of the powers 
    conferred under section 19 (2) of the Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques 
    (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) Act, 1994 (57 of 1954)†, 
    the Appropriate Authority …………………hereby rejects the application for 
    grant*/renewal* of registration of the undermentioned Genetic Counselling 
    Centre*/Genetic Laboratory*/Genetic Clinic*/Ultrasound Clinic*/Imaging 
    Centre*.
 



    (1)     Name and address of the Genetic Counselling
 



             Centre*/Genetic Laboratory*/Genetic Clinic*/
 



             Ultrasound Clinic*/Imaging Centre*
 



    (2)     Reasons for rejection of application for
 



             grant/renewal of registration:
 



    Date...................................
 



    Place...................................
 



                                       Signature, name and designation of 

 


the Appropriate Authority 
    with         
 



Seal]                                        
    
 


*Strike out 
    whichever is not applicable or necessary.
 


 
 


 
 



    -----------------------------
 


  
    1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).
 


  †   Now the 
    Pre-conception and Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Prohibition of Sex 
    Selection) Act, 1994 (57 of 1994).
 



    -----------------------------
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 



 




    1[Form D
 


[See rule 9 (2)]
 



Form for 
    Maintenance of Records by the Genetic 

    Counselling Centre
 

 
 


1.     Name and address 
    of Genetic Counselling centre  
 


2.     Registration No.  
 


3.     Patient’s name  
 


4.     Age   
 


5.     Husband’s/Father’s 
    name  
 


6.     Full address with 
    Tel. No., if any  
 


7.     Referred by (Full 
    name and address of Doctor(s)  
 


        with registration 
    No.(s) Referral note to be  
 


        preserved 
    carefully with case papers)  
 


8.     Last metrual 
    period/weeks of pregnancy   
 


9.     History of 
    genetic/medical disease  
 


        in the family (specify)  
 


        Basis of 
    diagnosis:  
 


(a) Clinical  
 


(b) Bio-chemical   
 


(c) Cytogenetic  
 


(d) Other (e.g., 
    radiological,   
 


ultrasonography)  
 


10.   Indication for 
    pre-natal diagnosis  
 


        A. Previous 
    child/children with:  
 


(i) 
    Chromosomal disorders
 


(ii) 
    Metabolic disorders
 


(iii) 
    Congenital anomaly
 


(iv) 
    Mental retardation
 


(v) 
    Haemoglobinopathy
 


(vi) 
    Sex linked disorders
 


(vii) 
    Single gene disorder
 


(viii) 
    Any other (specify)
 


        B. Advanced 
    maternal age   
 


           (35 years or 
    above)  
 


        C. 
    Mother/father/sibling having  
 


            genetic 
    disease (specify)  
 


        D. Others (specify)  
 


11.   Procedure advised*  
 


(i) Ultrasound  
 


(ii) 
    Amniocentesis
 


(iii) 
    Chorionic villi biopsy
 


(iv) 
    Foetoscopy
 


(v) 
    Foetal skin or organ biopsy
 


(vi) 
    Cordocentesis
 


(vii) 
    Any other (specify)
 


12. Laboratory tests to 
    be carried out  
 


(i) Chromosomal 
    studies
 


(ii) 
    Biochemical studies
 


(iii) 
    Molecular studies
 


(iv) 
    Preimplantation genetic diagnosis
 


13.  Result of diagnosis 
    If abnormal give details.      Normal/Abnormal 
 


14.  Was MTP advised?  
 


15.  Name and address of 
    Genetic   
 


      Clinic to which 
    patient is referred.  
 


16.  Dates of 
    commencement and  
 


      completion of 
    genetic counselling.
 

 
 



        Date................................... 
 



        Place..................................
 



                                                            Name, Signature and 
    Registration No. of the      

 Medical Geneticist/Gynaecologist/Paediatrician 

    administering  Genetic Counselling]                 
    
 


*Strike out whichever is 
    not applicable or necessary.
 

 
 



    -----------------------------
 


1.
Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), 
    dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).
 



    -----------------------------
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 



 



1[FORM 
    E
 


[See rule 9 (3)]
 



form for  
    maintenance of records by genetic laboratory
 


1. Name and  address of 
    Genetic Laboratory                      
 


2. Registration 
    No                 
 


3. Patient’s name
 


4. Age
 


5. Husband’s/Father’s 
    name
 


6. Full address with Tel. 
    No., if any
 


7. Referred by/sample 
    sent by (full name
 


   and address of Genetic 
    Clinic) (Referral
 


   note to be preserved 
    carefully with case papers)
 


8. Type of sample: 
    Maternal blood/Chorionic
 


   villus sample/amniotic 
    fluid/Foetal
 


   blood or other foetal 
    tissue (specify)
 


9. Specify indication for 
    pre-natal diagnosis
 


   A. Previous 
    child/children with
 


(i)     
    Chromosomal disorders
 



    (ii)    Metabolic disorders
 


(iii)  
      Malformation(s)
 


(iv)   
    Mental retardation
 


(v)    
    Hereditary haemolytic anaemia
 



    (vi)   Sex linked disorder
 



    (vii)   Single gene disorder
 



    (viii)  Any other (specify)
 


   B. Advanced maternal 
    age  
 


            (35 
    years or above)  
 


      
      C. Mother/father/sibling having  
 


            genetic 
    disease (specify)  
 


     
       D. Other (specify)  
 


10. Laboratory tests 
    carried out (give details)  
 


(i)     
    Chromosomal studies
 



    (ii)    Biochemical studies
 



    (iii)   Molecular studies
 


(iv)   
    Preimplantation genetic diagnosis
 


11. Result of diagnosis  
 


       
       If abnormal give details.                                        
    Normal/Abnormal
 


12. Date(s) on which 
    tests carried out.  
 


The results of the 
    Pre-natal diagnostic tests were  conveyed 
    to.................................     on..……………………….
 

 
 



    Place................................... 
 



    Date...................................  
 


                Name, 
    Signature and Registration No. of the
 


                Medical 
    Geneticist/Director of the Institute]
 


Strike out whichever is 
    not applicable or necessary.
 


 
 


 
 



    -----------------------------
 


1.
Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), 
    dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).
 



    -----------------------------
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 



 




    1[Form F
 


[See proviso to 
    section 4 (3), rule 9 (4) and rule 10 (1A)]
 



Form for 
    maintenance of record in respect of pregnant woman by  

    genetic 
    clinic/ultrasound  clinic/imaging centre
 

 
 


1.     Name and address 
    of the Genetic Clinic/  
 


        Ultrasound 
    Clinic/Imaging  Centre.  
 


2.     Registration No.  
 


3.     Patient’s name and 
    her age  
 


4.     Number of children 
    with sex of each child  
 


5.     Husband’s/Father’s 
    name  
 


6.     Full address with 
    Tel. No., if any  
 


7.     Referred  by (full 
    name and address of  
 


       Doctor(s)/Genetic 
    Counselling Centre           
 


       
     (referral note to be preserved carefully   
 


        with case 
    papers)/self referral  
 


8.     Last menstrual 
    period/weeks of pregnancy  
 


9.     History of 
    genetic/medical disease in the  
 


        family (specify)  
 



            Basis of diagnosis:
 



               (a) Clinical
 



               (b) Bio-chemical
 



               (c) Cytogenetic
 



               (d) Other(e.g., radiological, 
 



                    ultrasonography etc., specify)
 


10.   Indication for 
    pre-natal diagnosis  
 


        A. Previous 
    child/children with:  
 



             (i)       Chromosomal disorders
 



             (ii)     Metabolic disorders
 



             (iii)    Congenital anomaly
 



             (iv)    Mental retardation
 



             (v)      Haemoglobinopathy
 



             (vi)    Sex linked disorders
 



             (vii)   Single gene disorder
 



             (viii)  Any other (specify)
 


        B. Advanced 
    maternal age (35 years)  
 


        C. 
    Mother/father/sibling has genetic  
 


            disease 
    (specify)  
 


        D. Other (specify)  
 


11. Procedures carried 
    out (with name and
 


     registration No. of 
    Gynaecologist/
 


     Radiologist/Registerd 
    Medical Practitioner)
 


     who performed it.
 


Non-Invasive
 


(i)     
    Ultrasound (specify purpose for which
 



             ultrasound is to done during pregnancy)
 



             [List of indications for ultrasonogrphy of
 



             pregnant women are given in the note below]
 


Invasive
 



    (ii)    Amniocentesis
 



    (iii)   Chorionic Villi aspiration
 


(iv)   
    Foetal biopsy
 


(v)    
    Cordocentesis
 


(vi)   
    Any other (specify)
 


12. Any complication of 
    procedure-please specify  
 


13. Laboratory tests 
    recommended*  
 



             (i)      Chromosomal studies
 



             (ii)     Biochemical studies
 



             (iii)   Molecular studies
 



             (iv)    Preimplantation genetic diagnosis
 


14. Result of  
 



             (a)   pre-natal diagnostic procedure (give details)
 



             (b)   Ultrasonography                                             
    Normal/Abnormal
 


                
    (specify abnormality detected, if any).
 


15. Date(s) on which 
    procedures carried out.  
 


16. Date on which consent 
    obtained. (In case of invasive)  
 


17. The result of 
    pre-natal diagnostic procedure were conveyed to................. 
    on.......................  
 


18. Was MTP advised/conducted?  
 


19. Date on which MPT 
    carried out.  
 

 
 



    Date………………….                   
 


Place…………………
 


Name, Signature and 
    Registration  number of  the
 


Gynaecologist/Radiologist/Director 
    of the Clinic
 

 
 



Declaration  of 
    Pregnant woman
 


I, Ms.………………(name of the 
    pregnant woman), declare that by undergoing ultrasonography/image scanning 
    etc. I do not want to know the sex of my foetus.
 

 
 


Signature/Thumb 
    impression of pregnant woman
 

 
 



Declaration of 
    doctor/person conducting  

    ultrasonography/image scanning
 


I,………………(name of the 
    person conducting ultrasonography/image scanning), declare that while 
    conducting ultrasonography/image scanning on Ms.………………(name of the pregnant 
    woman), I have neither detected nor disclosed the sex of her foetus to any 
    body in any manner.
 

 
 



                                                                    Name and 
    signature of the person conducting ultra  

    sonography/image scanning/Director or owner of      

    genetic clinic/ultrasound clinic/imaging centre        
    
 

 
 


Important Notes:—
 


(i)     
    Ultrasound is not indicated/advised/performed to determine the sex of foetus 
    except for diagnosis of sex-linked diseases such as Duchenne Muscular 
    Dystropy, Haemophilia A&amp;B, etc.
 



    (ii)    During pregnancy Ultrasonography should only be performed when 
    indicated. The following is the representative list of indications for 
    ultrasound during pregnancy:—
 


(1)   To diagnose 
    intra-uterine and/or ectopic pregnancy and confirm  

    viability.
 


(2)   Estimation of 
    gestational age (dating).
 


(3)   Detection of number 
    of foetuses and their chorionicity.
 


(4)   Suspected pregnancy 
    with IUCD in-situ or suspected pregnancy following cotraceptive failure/MTP 
    failure.
 


(5)   Vaginal 
    bleeding/leaking.
 


(6)   Follow-up of cases 
    of abortion.
 


(7)   Assessment of 
    cervical canal and diameter of internal os.
 


(8)   Discrepancy between 
    uterine size and period of amenorrhoea.
 


(9)   Any suspected 
    adenexal or uterine pathology/abnormality.
 


(10) Detection of 
    chromosomal abnormalities, foetal structural defects and other abnormalities 
    and their follow-up.
 


(11) To evaluate foetal 
    presentation and position.
 


(12) Assessment of liquor 
    amnii.
 


(13) Preterm labour/preterm 
    premature rupture of membranes.
 


(14) Evaluation of 
    placental position, thickness, grading and abnormalities (placenta praevia, 
    retroplacental haemorrhage, abnormal adherence, etc.).
 


(15) Evaluation of 
    umbilical cord—presentation, insertion, nuchal encirclement, number of 
    vessels and presence of true knot.
 


(16) Evaluation of 
    previous Caesarean Section scars.
 


(17) Evaluation of foetal 
    growth parameters, foetal weight and foetal well being.
 


(18) Colour flow mapping 
    and duplex Doppler studies.
 


(19) Ultrasound guided 
    procedures such as medical termination of pregnancy, external cephalic 
    version, etc., and their follow-up.
 


(20) Adjunct to 
    diagnostic and therapeutic invasive interventions such as chorionic villus 
    samplng (CVS), amniocenteses, foetal blood sampling, foetal skin biopsy, 
    amnioinfusion, intrauterine infusion, placement of shunts, etc.
 


(21) Observation of 
    intra-partum events.
 


(22) Medical/surgical 
    conditions complicating pregnancy.
 


(23) Research/scientific 
    studies in recognised institutions.
 


Person conducting 
    ultrasonography on a pregnant woman shall keep complete record thereof in 
    the clinic/centre in Form F and any deficiency or inaccuracy found therein 
    shall amount to contravention of provisions of section 5 or section 6 of the 
    Act, unless contrary is proved by the person conducting such 
    ultrasonography.]  
 


 
 


 
 



    ----------------------------
 



    1. Subs. by G.S.R. 109(E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).
 


†  Now the Pre-conception and 
    Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Prohibition of Sex selection) Act, 1994 (57 
    of 1994).
 



    -----------------------------
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 



 




    1[Form G
 


[See rule 10]
 


FORM OF CONSeNT 
 


(For invasive techniques) 
 


I,……………..,wife/daughter 
    of………………….age………………………years residing at…………………….hereby state that I have 
    been explained fully the probable side effects and after effects of the 
    pre-natal diagnostic procedures.  
 


I wish to undergo the 
    preimplantation/pre-natal diagnostic technique/test/procedures in my own 
    interest to find out the possibility of any abnormality (i.e., 
    disease/deformity/disorder) in the child I am carrying.
 


I undertake not to 
    terminate the pregnancy if the pre-natal procedure/technique/test conducted 
    show the absence of disease/deformity/disorder.
 


I understand that the sex 
    of the foetus will not be disclosed to me.
 


I understand that breach 
    of this undertaking will make me liable to penalty as prescribed in the
    pre-natal Diagnostic 
    Techniques (Regulation and Prevention of Misuse) Act, 1994 (57 of 1994)† and 
    rules framed thereunder.
 

 
 

 
 


Date………….…………
 



    Place………….………….                                                     

 


Signature of the pregnant 
    woman.
 

 
 


I have explained the 
    contents of the above to the patient and her companion 
    ……………….................. (Name ................…………………… Address 
    .................. ………………….………… Relationship ………………..) in a language 
    she/they understand.
 



                                            Name, Signature and/Registration 
    number of                    
    
 



                                            Gynaecologist/Medical 
    Geneticist/Radiologist/Paediatrician/
 



                                            Director of the 
    Clinic/Centre/Laboratory                          
    
 

 
 



                                                                            
    Name, Address and Registration number of
 



                                                                            
    Genetic Clinic/Institute                           
    
 


SEAL]                                                  
    
 



    Date……………………                                         
 

 
 

 
 



    ----------------------------------
 


 1.     
    Subs. by G.S.R. 109(E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).
 


 †      Now the 
    Pre-conception and Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Prohibition of Sex 
    Selection) Act, 1994 (57 of 1994).
 



    ----------------------------------
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic 
    techniques (prohibition of sex selection) RULES, 1996
 



 



1[FORM 
    H
 


[See rule 9 (5)]
 



Form for 
    maintenance of permanent record of applications for grant/rejection of 
    registration under the pre-natal diagnostic  

    techniques (regulation and 
    prevention of misuse) Act, 1994†
 

 
 



    1.      Sl.No.
 



    2.      File number of Appropriate Authority
 



    3.      Date of receipt of application for grant of registration
 



    4.      Name, Address, Phone/Fax, etc., of Applicant
 



    5.      Name and address(es) of Genetic Counselling Centre*/Genetic 
    Laboratory*/Genetic Clinic* /Ultrasound Clinic*/ Imaging Centre*
 



    6.      Date of consideration by Advisory Committee and recommendation of 
    Advisory Committee, in summary
 



    7.      Outcome of application (state granted/rejected and date of issue of 
    orders-record date of issue of order in Form B or Form C)
 



    8.      Registration number allotted and date of expiry of registration
 



    9.      Renewals (date of renewal and renewed upto)
 


10.    
    File number in which renewals dealt
 


11.    
    Additional information, if any
 


 
 



                                                                        Name, 
    Designation and Signature of 
 



                                                                        
    Appropriate Authority
 


Guidance for Appropriate 
    Authority  
 



    (a) Form H is a permanent record to be maintained as a register, in the 
    custody of the Appropriate  Authority.
 



    (b) *Means strike out whichever is not applicable.
 


(c) On 
    renewal, the Registration Number of the Genetic Counselling Centre/Genetic 
    Laboratory/Genetic Clinic/Ultrasound Clinic/Imaging Centre will not change. 
    A fresh registration Number will be allotted in the event of change of 
    ownership or management.
 



    (e) Registration number shall not be allotted twice.
 



    (f)  Each Genetic Counselling centre/Genetic 
    Laboratory/Genetic Clinic/Ultrasound Clinic/Imaging Centre may be allotted a 
    folio consisting of two pages of the Register for recording Form H.
 



    (g) The space provided for ‘additional information’ may be used for 
    recording suspension, cancellations, rejection of application for renewal, 
    change of  

    ownership/management, outcome of any legal proceedings, etc.
 


(h) Every folio (i.e.
    2 pages) of the Register shall be authenticated by signature of the 
    Appropriate Authority with date, and every subsequent entry shall also be 
    similarly authenticated.]
 


 
 


 
 


 
 



    ----------------------------
 



    1.    Subs. by G.S.R. 109(E), dated 14th February, 2003 
    (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).
 


†     Now the Pre-conception and 
    Pre-natal Diagnostic Techniques (Prohibition of Sex Selection) Act, 1994 (57 
    of 1994).
 



    ----------------------------
 


 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 

the
pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic techniques (prohibition of sex
selection) RULES, 1996
 

 
 

 
 

1[***]
 

 
 

----------
 

1. Schedule I omitted by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f.
14-2-2003).
</form><form>
 

the
pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic techniques (prohibition of sex
selection) RULES, 1996
 

 
 

 
 

1[***]
 

 
 

----------
 

1. Schedule II omitted by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f.
14-2-2003).
</form><form>
 

the
pre-conception and pre-natal diagnostic techniques (prohibition of sex
selection) RULES, 1996
 

 
 

 
 

1[***]
 

 
 

----------
 

1. Schedule III omitted by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f.
14-2-2003).
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 
14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Sub. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Sub. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Vide G.S.R. 1(E), dated 1st January, 1996, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (i), dated 1st January, 1996.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 109(E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 426(E), dated 31st May, 2011, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 2-6-2011). Sub- 
  rule (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Vide G.S.R. 1(E), dated 1st January, 1996, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
Sec. 3 (i), dated 1st January, 1996.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 109(E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 426(E), dated 31st May, 2011, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 2-6-2011). Sub- 
  rule (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 
    14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 
    14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>     Subs. by G.S.R. 109 (E), 
    dated 14th February, 2003 (w.e.f. 14-2-2003).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>