<act><tid>1958862</tid>
<title>THE KHADI AND VILLAGE INDUSTRIES COMMISSION ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 61 OF <footcitenum>1956</footcitenum>
[ 25th September, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the establishment of a Commission for the 
development of Khadi and Village Industries and for matters connected 
therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1831951</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1628712</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Khadi  
and Village Industries Commission Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>72321</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1484704</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1788468</tid>
<number>a</number>" the Board" means the Board constituted under <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 
10];

</section>

<section><tid>985506</tid>
<number>b</number>" chairman" means the chairman of the Commission;

</section>

<section><tid>497259</tid>
<number>c</number>" Commission" means the Khadi and Village Industries 
Commission established under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1980513</tid>
<number>cc</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" fixed capital investment" includes investment in 
plant and machinery and land and building of an 
industry;]

</section>

<section><tid>1196195</tid>
<number>d</number>" khadi" means any cloth woven on handlooms in India from 
cotton, silk or woollen yarn handspun in India or from 
a mixture of any two or all of such yarns;

</section>

<section><tid>1189555</tid>
<number>e</number>" member" means a member of the Commission <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and 
includes the chairman <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>];

</section>

<section><tid>1595501</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1978868</tid>
<number>ff</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>" rural area" means the area comprised in any 
village, and includes the area comprised in any town, 
the population of which does not exceed ten thousand or 
such other figure as the Central Government may specify 
from time to time;]
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>180</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu by Reg. 11 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and sch.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1957</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, for" section 9". 
2. Ins. by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Subs. by Act 32 of <year>1961</year>, s. 2, for" and includes the chairman". 
4. Certain words omitted by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
5. Ins. by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
6. Cls. (g) and (gg) omitted by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1542560</tid>
<number>h</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" village industry" means,--

</section>

<section><tid>533135</tid>
<number>i</number>any industry located in a rural area which produces any goods 
or renders any service with or without the use of power and in which 
the fixed capital investment per head of an artisan or a worker does 
not exceed fifteen thousand rupees or such other sum as may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, be specified from time to time 
by the Central Government:
Provided that any industry specified in the Schedule and located 
in an area other than a rural area and recognised as a village 
industry at any time before the commencement of the Khadi and Village 
Industries Commission (Amendment) Act, <year>1987</year> shall, notwithstanding 
anything contained in this sub- clause, continue to be a village 
industry under this Act;


<subsection><tid>942132</tid>
<number>ii</number>any other non- manufacturing unit established for the sole 
purpose of promoting, maintaining, assisting, servicing (including  
  mother units) or managing any village industry;]

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>214440</tid>
<number>3</number>[ Power to add to the Schedule.] omitted by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 
 3 (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>).
CHAP

THE KHADI AND VILLAGE INDUSTRIES COMMISSION

CHAPTER II

THE KHADI AND VILLAGE INDUSTRIES COMMISSION



</article>



<article><tid>864590</tid>
<number> 4</number> Establishment and constitution of the Commission.
<section><tid>598101</tid>
<number>1</number>With  
effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, fix in this behalf, there shall be 
established a Commission to be called the Khadi and village Industries 
Commission which shall be a body corporate having perpetual succession 
and a common seal, with power to acquire, hold and dispose of property 
and to contract, and may by the said name sue and be sued.

</section>

<section><tid>241986</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Commission shall consist of the following members 
appointed by the Central Government, namely:--

<subsection><tid>377922</tid>
<number>a</number>six non- official members having specialised knowledge 
and experience of khadi and village industries and representing 
such six geographical zones of the country, as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>702123</tid>
<number>b</number>two non- official members having expert knowledge and 
experience in one or more of the following disciplines, namely:--
Economics, Planning, Rural Development, Science and 
Technology or Technical Education and Training;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>212374</tid>
<number>c</number>one Financial Adviser, who shall also be the Chief 
Accounts Officer of the Commission, ex- officio; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1106913</tid>
<number>d</number>a Chief Executive Officer, ex- officio:
Provided that the ex- officio members shall not have the right to 
vote in any of the matters discussed at a meeting of the Commission.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1591922</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may appoint one of the members 
appointed under clause (a) of sub- section (2) to be the chairman who 
shall be a full- time member.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>666432</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Powers and functions of the Chief Executive Officer.
<section><tid>1762807</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Chief Executive Officer appointed under clause (d) of sub- section 
 (2) of section 4 shall exercise powers of general superintendence over 
the affairs of the Commission and its day- to- day management under the 
direction and control of the chairman.

</section>

<section><tid>1023840</tid>
<number>2</number>The Chief Executive Officer shall be responsible for the 
furnishing of all returns, reports and statements required to be 
furnished to the Central Government under section 24.

</section>

<section><tid>91206</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be the duty of the Chief Executive Officer to place 
before the Commission for its consideration and decision any matter of 
financial import if the Financial Adviser suggests to him in writing 
that such matter be placed before the Commission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1232051</tid>
<number>5A</number>Powers and functions of the Financial Adviser. The Financial 
Adviser appointed under clause (c) of sub- section (2) of section 4 
shall be in charge of all financial matters of the Commission 
including its budget, accounts and audit and it shall be the duty of 
the Financial Adviser to bring to the notice of the Commission through 
the Chief Executive Officer any matter of financial import, which, in 
his opinion, requires consideration and decision by the Commission.


</article>



<article><tid>553763</tid>
<number> 6</number> Disqualifications for membership of the Commission. A person 
shall be disqualified for being appointed as, and for being, a member 
of the Commission--
<section><tid>1284060</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is, or is found to be a lunatic or a person of 
unsound mind; or

</section>

<section><tid>1786803</tid>
<number>b</number>if he has been adjudged insolvent; or

</section>

<section><tid>513666</tid>
<number>c</number>if he has been convicted of an offence involving moral 
turpitude; or

</section>

<section><tid>1324618</tid>
<number>d</number>if he has any financial interest in any subsisting 
contract made with or in any work being done by the Commission, 
except as a shareholder (other than a Director), in a company as 
defined in section 3 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>):
Provided that where he is a shareholder, he shall disclose 
to the Central Government, the nature and extent of shares held 
by him in such a company; or


</section>

<section><tid>1151947</tid>
<number>e</number>if he has any financial interest in any business 
undertaking dealing with or any other village industry specified 
or deemed to be specified in the Schedule to the Act



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1541743</tid>
<number> 6A</number> Removal of Chairman, Member, etc., from the Commission. The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
remove from office any member of the Commission who--
<section><tid>501796</tid>
<number>a</number>is or becomes subject to any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in section 6; or

</section>

<section><tid>518552</tid>
<number>b</number>in the opinion of the Central Government has failed or 
is unable to carry out his duties; or

</section>

<section><tid>747327</tid>
<number>c</number>absents himself from three consecutive meetings of the 
Commission without the leave of the Commission:
Provided that before issuing any such notification, the 
Central Government shall give an opportunity to the member 
concerned to show cause against such removal.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>181</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1987</year> s. 2, (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 5, ibid. (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1669678</tid>
<number>7</number>Resignation of office by member. Any member may resign his 
office by giving notice in writing to the Central Government and, on 
such resignation being notified in the Official Gazette by that 
Government, shall be deemed to have vacated his office.


</article>



<article><tid>610760</tid>
<number>8</number>Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate acts and proceedings of the 
Commission. No act or proceeding of the Commission shall be invalid by 
reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its members or any 
defect in the constitution thereof.


</article>



<article><tid>340444</tid>
<number> 9</number> Temporary association of persons with the Commission for 
particular purposes.
<section><tid>862398</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission may associate with itself in  
such manner and for such purposes as may be determined by regulations 
made under this Act any persons whose assistance or advice it may 
desire in complying with any of the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1967766</tid>
<number>2</number>A person associated with it by the Commission under sub- 
section (1) for any purpose shall have the right to take part in the 
discussions of the Commission relevant to that purpose, but shall not 
have the right to vote, and shall not be a member for any other 
purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>357408</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, depute one or more officers of the Government to attend any 
meetings of the Commission and to take part in the discussions of the 
Commission, but such officer or officers shall not have the right to 
vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>44873</tid>
<number>10</number>Constitution of the Board. For the purpose of assisting the 
Commission in the discharge of its functions under this Act, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
constitute a Board to be called the Khadi and Village Industries Board 
consisting of a chairman and such number of other members as the 
Central Government may think fit, chosen from among persons who, in 
the opinion of the Central Government, are qualified as having had 
experience, and shown capacity, in matters relating to the development 
of khadi and village industries.


</article>



<article><tid>1776495</tid>
<number>11</number>Commission to consult the Board. The Commission shall 
ordinarily consult the Board with respect to the discharge of its 
functions under this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>182</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>255484</tid>
<number> 12</number> Meetings of the Commission.
<section><tid>507412</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall meet at  
such times and places and shall, subject to the provisions of sub- 
sections (2) and (3), observe such rules of procedure in regard to 
transaction of business at its meetings (including the quorum at  
  meetings) as may be provided by regulations made by the Commission 
under this Act;
Provided that the Commission shall meet at least once in every 
month.


</section>

<section><tid>89770</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The chairman or, in his absence, any member (other than  
  an ex- officio member) chosen by the members present from among 
themselves, shall preside at a meeting of the Commission.]

</section>

<section><tid>1422803</tid>
<number>3</number>All questions at a meeting of the Commission shall be decided 
by a majority of the votes of the members present and voting and in 
the case of an equality of votes, the chairman or, in his absence the 
person presiding, shall have a second or casting vote.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1262136</tid>
<number> 13</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Term of office and conditions of service of the chairman 
and other members.
<section><tid>766977</tid>
<number>1</number>Every members of the Commission, other than an  
ex- officio member, shall hold office for a term of five years:
Provided that the chairman shall, notwithstanding the expiration 
of his term, continue to hold office until his successor enters upon 
his office.


</section>

<section><tid>355215</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms and conditions of service of the chairman, Chief 
Executive Officer, Financial Adviser and other members shall be such 
as may be prescribed.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1856212</tid>
<number>14</number>Officers and servants of the Commission. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Subject to such rules as may be made by the Central 
Government in this behalf, the Commission may appoint such other 
officers and servants as it considers necessary for the efficient 
performance of its functions:

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

CHAP

FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMISSION

CHAPTER III

FUNCTIONS OF THE COMMISSION



</article>



<article><tid>559914</tid>
<number> 15</number> <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Functions of the Commission.
<section><tid>1867195</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of this Act, the functions of the Commission shall 
generally be to plan, promote, organise and assist in the 
establishment and development of khadi and village industries in the 
rural area in coordination with other agencies engaged in rural 
development wherever necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1683878</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, the Commission may take such other steps as it may 
think fit,--

<subsection><tid>632407</tid>
<number>a</number>to plan and organise training of persons employed or 
desirous of seeking employment in khadi and village industries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1487656</tid>
<number>b</number>to build up reserves of raw materials and implements and 
supply them to persons engaged or likely to be engaged in 
production of handspun yarn or khadi or village industries at 
such rates as the Commission may decide;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1921423</tid>
<number>c</number>to encourage and assist in the creation of common 
service facilities for the processing of raw materials or semi- 
finished goods and for otherwise facilitating production and 
marketing of khadi or products of village industries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1741671</tid>
<number>d</number>to promote the sale and marketing of khadi or products 
of village industries or handicrafts and for this purpose forge 
links with established marketing agencies wherever necessary and 
feasible;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>584512</tid>
<number>e</number>to encourage and promote research in the technology used 
in khadi and village industries, including the use of non- 
conventional energy and electric power with a view to increasing 
productivity, eliminating drudgery and otherwise enhancing their 
competitive capacity and to arrange for dissemination of salient 
results obtained from such research;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1334580</tid>
<number>f</number>to undertake directly or through other agencies studies 
of the problems of khadi or village industries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1840018</tid>
<number>g</number>to provide financial assistance to institutions or 
persons engaged in the development and operation of khadi or 
village industries and guide them through supply of designs, 
prototypes and other technical information for the purpose of 
producing goods and services for which there is effective demand 
in the opinion of the Commission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>737788</tid>
<number>h</number>to undertake experiments or pilot projects which in the 
opinion of the Commission are necessary for the development of 
khadi and village industries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>666487</tid>
<number>i</number>to establish and maintain separate organisations for the 
purpose of carrying out any or all of the above matters;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>226683</tid>
<number>j</number>to promote and encourage cooperative efforts among the 
manufacturers of khadi or persons engaged in village industries;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1935501</tid>
<number>k</number>to ensure genuineness and to set up standards of quality 
and ensure that products of khadi and village industries do 
conform to the said standards, including issue of certificates or 
letters of recognition to the concerned persons; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>822601</tid>
<number>l</number>to carry out any other matters incidental to the 
above.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>183</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 6 (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
2. Subs. by s. 7, ibid. (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Omitted by s. 8, ibid. (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
4. Subs. by s. 9, ibid. (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>424855</tid>
<number>16</number>Power of Central Government to give directions. In the 
discharge of its functions under this Act, the Commission shall be 
bound by such directions as the Central Government may give to it.
CHAP

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS

CHAPTER IV

FINANCE, ACCOUNTS, AUDIT AND REPORTS



</article>



<article><tid>1531524</tid>
<number>17</number>Payment to the Commission. The Central Government may, after 
due appropriation made by Parliament by law in this behalf, pay to the 
Commission in each financial year such sums as may be considered 
necessary for the performance of the functions of the Commission under 
this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>184</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>772851</tid>
<number>17A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commission to receive gifts, grants, etc. The Commission 
may, for the purpose of development of khadi <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the development of 
village industries or the development of khadi and village 
industries], receive gifts, grants donations or benefactions from the 
Government or any other person.


</article>



<article><tid>1900737</tid>
<number> 18</number> Funds of the Commission. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1465438</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall have  
three separate funds to be called the khadi fund, the village 
industries fund and the general and miscellaneous fund.

</section>

<section><tid>1308864</tid>
<number>1A</number>There shall be credited,--

<subsection><tid>1772788</tid>
<number>a</number>to the khadi fund, all sums received by the Commission 
for the purpose relating to khadi;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1180955</tid>
<number>b</number>to the village industries fund, all sums received by the 
Commission for the purposes relating to village industries and 
products of handicrafts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1771489</tid>
<number>c</number>to the general and miscellaneous fund, all other sums 
received by the Commission:
Provided that if the amount available in any of the said funds is 
in excess of the requirements of that fund and the amount available in 
any other of the said funds is insufficient to meet the requirements 
of that fund, the Commission may, with the previous approval of the 
Central Government, transfer from the first mentioned fund the excess 
amount or such part thereof as may be necessary to the other fund.

Explanation.-- For the purpose of computing the amount in any of 
the said funds, the amount received under section 17A shall not be 
taken into account.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>220062</tid>
<number>1B</number>The sums credited under sub- section (1),--

<subsection><tid>1230146</tid>
<number>a</number>to the khadi fund, shall be applied for the purposes 
relating to khadi;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1485396</tid>
<number>b</number>to the village industries fund, shall be applied for the 
purposes relating to village industries and products of 
handicrafts;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1038214</tid>
<number>c</number>to the general and miscellaneous fund, shall be applied 
for the purposes relating to khadi and village industries and for 
meeting the salary, allowances and other remuneration of the 
members, officers and other employees of the Commission and other 
administrative expenses of the Commission.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>782628</tid>
<number>2</number>Except as otherwise directed by the Central Government, all 
moneys belonging to such funds shall be deposited in the Reserve Bank 
of India or with the agents of the Reserve Bank of India or, where 
there is neither an office of the Reserve Bank of India nor an agent 
of the Reserve Bank of India, in a Government Treasury, or be invested 
in such securities as may be approved by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>196987</tid>
<number>19</number>Power of the Commission to spend. Subject to the provisions 
of section 20 the Commission shall have power to spend such sums as it 
thinks fit on purposes authorized by this Act:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>185</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1961</year>, s. 9. 
2. Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 10 (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 11, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1988</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Provided that nothing in this section shall be deemed to prevent 
the Commission from spending, with the previous approval of the 
Central Government, such moneys, as it thinks fit on any such purpose 
outside the territories to which this Act extends.



</article>



<article><tid>822674</tid>
<number> 19A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Standing Finance Committees.
<section><tid>339569</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
constituted from among the members of the Commission in the prescribed 
manner, a Standing Finance Committee in respect of each of the[ three 
funds] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> referred to in section 18.

</section>

<section><tid>1864763</tid>
<number>2</number>The Standing Finance Committee shall exercise such of the 
powers of the Commission under section 19 as are delegated to it by 
the Commission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>102696</tid>
<number> 19B</number> Recovery of monies due to the Commission as arrears of land- 
revenue.
<section><tid>1721429</tid>
<number>1</number>Any sum payable to the Commission under any agreement  
express or implied, or otherwise howsoever, may be recovered in the 
same manner as an arrear of land- revenue.

</section>

<section><tid>509286</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises whether a sum is payable to the 
Commission within the meaning of sub- section (1), it shall be referred 
to a Tribunal constituted by the Central Government for the purpose 
which shall, after making such inquiry as it may deem fit and after 
giving to the person by whom the sum is alleged to be payable an 
opportunity of being heard, decide the question; and the decision of 
the Tribunal shall be final and shall not be called in question by any 
court or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1921734</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal shall consist of one person who is not connected 
with the Commission or with the person by whom the sum is alleged to 
be payable.

</section>

<section><tid>259177</tid>
<number>4</number>The expenses of the Tribunal shall be borne by the 
Commission.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1080293</tid>
<number> 20</number> Budget.
<section><tid>1461581</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall, by such date in each year  
as may be prescribed, prepare and submit to the Central Government for 
approval <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> three separate budgets] in the prescribed form for the 
next financial year, to be called the khadi budget <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, the village 
industries budget and the general and miscellaneous budget], showing 
the estimated receipts and expenditure in respect of khadi <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, village 
industries and products of handicrafts and khadi and village 
industries respectively] during that financial year.

</section>

<section><tid>973444</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (3) and (4), no sum 
shall be expended by or on behalf of the Commission unless the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>186</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1961</year>, s. 11. 
2. Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 12 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1988</year>). 
3. Subs. by s. 13, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1988</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


expenditure is covered by a specific provision in the budget approved 
by the Central Government.


</section>

<section><tid>1332374</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Commission may within the respective limits of the 
khadi budget, the village industries budget and the general and 
miscellaneous budget, sanction any reappropriation from one head of 
expenditure to another or from a provision made for one scheme to that 
in respect of another, but subject to the proviso to sub- section (1) 
of section 18, in no case shall a reappropriation of fund be made from 
one budget to any of the other two budgets:
Provided that no reappropriation from the head" Loan" to any 
other head of expenditure and vice versa in any of the budgets shall 
be sanctioned by the Commission, except with the previous approval of 
the Central Government.]


</section>

<section><tid>807732</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commission may, within such limits and subject to such 
conditions as may be prescribed, incur expenditure in excess of the 
limit provided in the budget approved by the Central Government under 
any head of expenditure or in connection with any particular scheme, 
so long as the aggregate amount in[ the budget] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> approved by the 
Central Government is not exceeded.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>629882</tid>
<number>21</number>Borrowing of money. Subject to such rules as may be made in 
this behalf, the Commission shall have power to borrow on the security 
of the khadi fund or the village industries fund or any other asset 
for any purposes for which such funds may be applied.


</article>



<article><tid>552585</tid>
<number>22</number>Transfer of liabilities and obligations to the Commission. 
All liabilities incurred by, all contracts entered into with, and all 
matters and things engaged to be done by, or for, the Central 
Government in connection with the development of khadi or village 
industries at any time after the 14th day of January, <year>1953</year>, and before 
the commencement of this Act, shall, after such commencement, be 
deemed to have been incurred by, entered into with, or engaged to be 
done by, or for, the Commission.


</article>



<article><tid>1145768</tid>
<number> 23</number> Accounts and audit.
<section><tid>1050176</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall maintain proper  
accounts and other relevant records and prepare an annual statement of 
accounts, including the profit and loss account and the balance- sheet 
in such form as may be prescribed by the Central Government in 
consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor- General of India.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>187</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 13 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1988</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1595620</tid>
<number>2</number>The accounts of the Commission shall be audited by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India at such intervals as may be 
prescribed by him.

</section>

<section><tid>753370</tid>
<number>3</number>The Comptroller and Auditor- General of India and any person 
appointed by him in connection with the audit of the accounts of the 
Commission shall have the same rights and privileges and authority in 
connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor- General has 
in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books, 
accounts, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Commission.

</section>

<section><tid>397838</tid>
<number>4</number>The accounts of the Commission as certified by the 
Comptroller and Auditor- General of India or any other person appointed 
by him in this behalf together with the audit report thereon shall be 
forwarded annually to the Central Government and that Government shall 
cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>109465</tid>
<number> 24</number> Returns and reports.
<section><tid>171829</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission shall furnish to the  
Central Government, at such time and in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed or as the Central Government may direct, such returns and 
statements and such particulars in regard to any proposed or existing 
programme for the promotion and development of khadi and village 
industries, as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.

</section>

<section><tid>1189544</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Commission shall, as soon as possible after the end of each financial 
year, submit to the Central Government a report, in such form and 
before such date as may be prescribed, giving a true and full account 
of its activities, policy and programme during the previous financial 
year.

</section>

<section><tid>809906</tid>
<number>3</number>A copy of the report received under sub- section (2) shall be 
laid before each House of Parliament.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER V

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>444425</tid>
<number>24A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Exemption from liability to pay income- tax. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>), the Commission shall not be liable to pay any income- tax on 
its income, profits or gains.]


</article>



<article><tid>131112</tid>
<number> 25</number> Dissolution of the Commission.
<section><tid>133245</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that the 
Commission shall be dissolved from such date as
<pagefootnote><pagenum>188</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 34 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1962</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


may be specified in the notification and thereupon the Commission 
shall be deemed to be dissolved accordingly.


</section>

<section><tid>1895717</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the said date--

<subsection><tid>1128971</tid>
<number>a</number>all properties and funds which, immediately before the 
said date, were in the possession of the Commission for 
the purposes of this Act shall vest in the Central 
Government; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>125186</tid>
<number>b</number>all members shall vacate their office as members of the 
Commission.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>190022</tid>
<number> 26</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1624084</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1532916</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
fore- going power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>386247</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the manner of filling casual vacancies among the 
members of the Commission and the terms and conditions 
of service of the chairman, the Chief Executive 
Officer, the Financial Adviser and other members of the 
Commission including the salary and allowances to be 
paid to them and the travelling and daily allowances to 
be drawn by them when they are on tour;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>959009</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the procedure to be followed in removing a member 
who is or becomes subject to any disqualification;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>135925</tid>
<number>c</number>the term of office and other conditions of service of, 
the procedure to be followed in the discharge of 
functions by, and the manner of filling casual 
vacancies among, members of the Board;
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>495222</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the constitution of the Standing Finance Committees 
under sub- section (1) of section 19A;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>188A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
2. Omitted by s. 14, ibid (w. e. f. 24. 7. <year>1987</year>). 
3. Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1961</year>, s. 13.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1699763</tid>
<number>ddd</number>the procedure to be followed by the Tribunal in 
deciding questions referred to it under sub- section (2) 
of section 19B;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>296623</tid>
<number>e</number>the date by which, and the form in which, the budget 
shall be prepared and submitted in each year under sub- 
section (1) of section 20;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1925438</tid>
<number>f</number>the procedure to be followed for placing the Commission 
in possession of funds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1730548</tid>
<number>g</number>the procedure to be followed and the conditions to be 
observed in borrowing moneys or in granting loans;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>358460</tid>
<number>h</number>the conditions subject to which, and the mode in which, 
contracts may be entered into by or on behalf of the 
Commission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1517529</tid>
<number>i</number>the form and manner in which the accounts of the 
Commission shall be maintained under sub- section (1) of 
section 23;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1937747</tid>
<number>j</number>the form and manner in which the returns, reports or 
statements shall be submitted under section 24; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>80442</tid>
<number>k</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>806738</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power to make regulations.
<section><tid>1658831</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission may, with the  
previous sanction of the Central Government, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make regulations, not inconsistent with this Act and 
the rules made thereunder, for enabling it to discharge its functions 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>543180</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1301946</tid>
<number>a</number>the terms and conditions of appointment and service and 
the scales of pay of officers and servants of the
<pagefootnote><pagenum>188B</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (3) omitted by Act 12 of <year>1987</year>, s. 14 (w. e. f.  
  24. 7. <year>1987</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Commission, other than <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief Executive Officer] 
and the Financial Adviser to the Commission, including 
payment of travelling and daily allowances in respect 
of journeys undertaken by such officers and servants 
for the purposes of this Act;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1154663</tid>
<number>b</number>the time and place of meetings of the Commission, the 
procedure to be followed in regard to transaction of 
business at such meetings and the quorum necessary for 
the transaction of such business at a meeting;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>694438</tid>
<number>bb</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the summoning and holding of meetings, and the 
conduct of business of a Standing Finance Committee;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>562575</tid>
<number>c</number>the delegation of powers and duties to <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Chief 
Executive Officer] or any employee of the Commission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>6518</tid>
<number>d</number>the maintenance of minutes of meetings of the Commission 
and of the Board and the transmission of copies thereof 
to the Central Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>898677</tid>
<number>e</number>the persons by whom, and the manner in which, payments, 
deposits and investments may be made on behalf of the 
commission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>818486</tid>
<number>f</number>the custody of moneys required for the current 
expenditure of the Commission and investment of moneys 
not so required;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>312469</tid>
<number>g</number>the maintenance of accounts; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>352920</tid>
<number>h</number>the form in which certificates of genuineness of khadi 
and products of village industries may be granted by 
the Commission <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and the fees chargeable in respect 
thereof.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>986456</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The power to make regulations under this section with 
respect to the terms and conditions of service and the scales of pay 
and pension to be paid to the employees of the Commission shall 
include the power to give retrospective effect from a date not earlier 
than the commencement of this Act, to such regulations or any of them 
but no retrospective effect shall be given to any such regulation so 
as to prejudicially affect the interest of any person to whom such 
regulation may be applicable.]

</section>

<section><tid>1857090</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, rescind any regulation which it has sanctioned and thereupon 
the regulation shall cease to have effect.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1897816</tid>
<number>28</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament. Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or regulation.]

</article>



 </act>