<act><title>


The Review Committee (Qualifications For Appointment 
And Other Conditions Of Service Of The Chairperson 
And Members) Rules, 20021</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Review Committee (Qualifications for Appointment 
and Other Conditions of Service of the Chairperson and Members) Rules, 2002.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date2 of 
their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Review Committee 
constituted under sub-section (1) of section 60 of the Ordinance1;
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “member” means the member of the Review Committee constituted under 
sub-section (1) of section 60 of the Ordinance1;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Ordinance”1 means 
the Prevention of Terrorism (Second) Ordinance, 20011 (12 
of 2001);
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  all other words and expressions used in these rules but not defined in 
these rules and defined in the Ordinance1 shall 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Ordinance1.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Constitution.—The 
Review Committee constituted by the Central Government or, as the case may be, 
the State Government shall consist of Chairperson and such other members not 
exceeding three.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Qualifications for 
appointment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government or, as the case may be, the State Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint a person as the Chairperson of the 
Review Committee possessing the qualifications as specified in sub-rule (2) of 
this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Chairperson of the 
Committee shall be a person who is, or has been, a Judge of High Court, who 
shall be appointed by the Central Government, or as the case may be, the State 
Government, so however, that the concurrence of the Chief Justice of the High 
Court shall be obtained in the case of a sitting judge:
 
Provided that in the case 
of a Union territory, the appointment of a person who is a Judge of the High 
Court of a State shall be made as Chairperson with the concurrence of the Chief 
Justice of the concerned High Court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
or, as the case may be, the State Government, may by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint a person as a member of the Review Committee who is, 
or has been an officer not below the rank of a Secretary to the concerned 
Government or of an equivalent rank.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Salary and 
allowances of Chairperson and other members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson of the Review Committee shall be entitled to a monthly salary 
and allowances at the same rate as is admissible to a Judge of a High Court.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson of the 
Review Committee shall be entitled to a rent free accommodation.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A member of the Review 
Committee shall continue to draw such pay and allowances and other facilities as 
is admissible to the Secretary to the concerned Government.
 

1[***]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>


1[<number>5A</number> Fee or 
allowances of Chairperson and members on appointment after retirement.—Where 
a person, who has been a Judge of a High Court is appoint as Chairperson or, a 
person retired from service is appointed as a member of a Review Committee 
constituted by the Central Government or, as the case may be, the State 
Government, he shall be entitled to such fee or allowances on part-time or 
sitting or per case basis, as may be specified by the Central Government or, as 
the case may be, the State Government, from time to time.]
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Term of Office.—The 
Chairperson and every member shall hold office for a term of two years from the 
date on which he assumes office:
 
Provided that the term of 
office of the member shall be co-terminous with his tenure with the Central 
Government or, as the case may be, the State Government.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Resignation and 
Removal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson or any member may, by notice in writing under his hand addressed 
to President, resign his Post.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The President may, by 
order, remove a person from the Office of the Chairperson or member if that 
person—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  is adjudged an insolvent; or
 



1[(ii)  is 
engaged during his term of office in any paid or honorary employment which is 
not inconsonance with the duties cast on him as Chairperson or, as the case may 
be, member of the Review Committee constituted under the Act; or] 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  is, in the opinion of the President, unfit to continue in office by 
reason of infirmity of mind or body; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  gets convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which in 
the opinion of the President involves moral turpitude; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  refuses to act or becomes incapable of acting:
 
Provided that the 
Chairperson or any member shall not be removed under this sub-rule until he has 
been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.


</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Residuary 
Provisions.—The 
matters relating to the conditions of service of the Chairperson or other 
members of the Review Committee with respect to which no express provision has 
been made in these rules shall be referred in each case to the Central 
Government or, as the case may be, the State Government for decision and the 
decision of the concerned Government thereon shall be binding on the Review 
Committee constituted by that Government.
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>