<act><title>THE TRADE MARKS RULES, 20021</title> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Trade Marks Rules, 2002.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date 
on which the Act comes into force.<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
  




</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, 
unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Trade Marks Act, 1999 (47 of 
1999);
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  “agent” means a person authorised to act under 
section 145 of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  “application for registration of a trade mark” 
includes the trade mark for goods or services contained in it;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  “appropriate office of the Trade Marks 
Registry” means the relevant office of the Trade Marks Registry as specified in 
rule 4;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  “class fee” means the fee prescribed for the 
filing of an application for registration of a trademark in a particular class;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  “convention country” means a country or group 
of countries or union of countries or Inter-Governmental organisations of 
countries declared as such under sub-section (1) of section 154;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  “convention application” means an application 
for registration of a trade mark made by virtue of section 154;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  “divisional application” means—
 </subsection><subsection>             <number>i</number>  an application containing a request for 
the division of goods or services in a class for the registration of a trade 
mark; or 
 <subsubsection>            <number>ii</number>  a divided application made by the 
division of a single application for the registration of a trade mark for 
separate classes of goods or services;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>i</number>  “divisional fee” means fee prescribed against 
entry number 68 in the First Schedule;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>j</number>  “Form” means a form set forth in either the 
Second or the Third Schedule;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>k</number>  “graphical representation” means the 
representation of a trade mark for goods or services in paper form;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>l</number>  “Journal” means the Trade Marks Journal 
referred to in rule 43;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>m</number>  “notified date” means the date on which these 
rules come into force;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>n</number>  “old law” means the Trade and Merchandise Marks 
Act, 1958 and rules made thereunder existing immediately before the 
commencement of the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>o</number>  “opposition” means an opposition to the 
registration of a trade mark or a collective mark or a certification trade 
mark, as the case may be;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>p</number>  “principal place of business in India” means 
the relevant place of business in India as specified in rule 3;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>q</number>  “publish” means publish in the Trade Marks 
Journal;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>r</number>  “registered trade mark agent” means a trade 
marks agent whose name is actually on the register of trade marks agents 
maintained under rule 148;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>s</number>  “renewal” means and includes renewal of a trade 
mark, or a certification trade mark or collective mark, as the case may be;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>        <number>t</number>  “Schedule” means a Schedule to these rules;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>u</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>v</number>  “specification” means the designation of goods 
or services in respect of which a trade mark or a registered user of a trade 
mark is registered or proposed to be registered;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>       <number>w</number>  All other words and expressions used but not 
defined in these rules but defined in the Act or in the Geographical 
Indications of Goods (Registration and Protection) Act, 1999 (48 of 1999), the 
Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957) shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in those Acts.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In these rules, except as otherwise 
indicated, a reference to a section is a reference to that section in the Act, 
a reference to a rule is a reference to that rule in these rules, a reference 
to a Schedule is a reference to that Schedule to these rules and a reference to 
a Form is a reference to that Form contained in the Second Schedule or the 
Third Schedule as the case may be, to these rules.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>3</number> Principal place of business in 
India.—“Principal place of business” in India means— 
 <section>        <number>i</number>  where a person carries on business in the 
goods or services concerned in a trade mark—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number>  if the business is carried on in India at 
only one place, that place;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  if the business is carried on in India at 
more places than one, the place mentioned by him as the principal place of 
business in India;
 </subsection></section><section>        <number>ii</number>  where a person is not carrying on a business 
in the goods or services concerned in a trade mark—
 <subsection>            <number>a</number>  if he is carrying on any other business in 
India at only one place, that place;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>b</number>  if he is carrying on any other business in 
India at more places than one, the place mentioned by him as the principal 
place of business in India; and 
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>iii</number>  where a person does not carry on any business 
in India but has a place of residence in India, then such place of residence in 
India.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>4</number> Appropriate office of the Trade 
Marks Registry.—The appropriate office of the Trade Marks Registry for the 
purposes of making an application for registration of a trade mark under 
section 18 or for giving notice of opposition under section 21 or for making an 
application for removal of a trade mark under section 47 or cancelling or 
varying the registration of a trade mark under section 57 or for any other 
proceedings under the Act and the rules shall be—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  in relation to a trade mark on the Register of 
Trade Marks at the notified date, the office of the Trade Marks Registry within 
whose territorial limits—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  the principal place of business in India 
of the registered proprietor of the trade mark as entered in the register at 
such date is situate;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  where there is no entry in the register 
as to the principal place of business in India of the registered proprietor, 
the place mentioned in the address for service in India as entered in the 
register at such date is situate;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  in the case of jointly registered 
proprietors, the principal place of business in India of the proprietor whose 
name is entered first in the register as having such place of business in India 
at such date is situate;
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number>  where none of the jointly registered 
proprietors is shown in the register as having a principal place of business in 
India, the place mentioned in the address for service in India of the joint 
proprietors as entered in the register at such date, is situate;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>v</number>  if no principal place of business in India 
of the registered proprietor of the mark or in the case of joint registration, 
of any of the joint proprietors of the mark, is entered in the register, and 
the register does not contain any address for service in India, the place of 
the office of the Trade Marks Registry where the application for registration 
of the trade mark was made, is situate, and 
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>b</number>  in relation to a trade mark for which an 
application for registration is pending at the notified date or is made on or 
after the notified date, the office of the Trade Marks Registry within whose 
territorial limits—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  the principal place of business in India 
of the applicant as disclosed in the application or, in the case of joint 
applicants, the principal place of business in India of the applicant whose 
name is first mentioned in the application, as having such place of business is 
situate;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  where neither the applicant nor any of 
the joint applicants, as the case may be, has a principal place of business in 
India, the place mentioned in the address for service in India as specified in 
the application is situate.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>5</number> Jurisdiction of appropriate office 
not altered by change in the principal place of business or address for 
service.—No change in the principal place of business in India or in the 
address for service in India, as the case may be,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  of a registered proprietor or of any of the 
jointly registered proprietors in relation to any trade mark on the register at 
the notified date, made or effected subsequent to that date; or
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  of an applicant for registration or of any of 
the joint applicants for registration in relation to any trade mark for which 
an application for registration is either pending at the notified date or is 
made on or after that date, made or effected subsequent to that date or to the 
date of filing of such application, as the case may be, 
 shall affect the jurisdiction of the appropriate office of 
the trade marks registry.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>6</number> Entry of the appropriate office in 
the register.—In respect of every trade mark on the register at the 
notified date or registered thereafter the Registrar shall cause to be entered 
in the register, the appropriate office of the trade marks registry and the 
Registrar may, at any time, correct any error in the entry so made.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>7</number> Transfer of pending applications and 
proceedings to appropriate offices of the trade marks registry.—Every 
application and proceeding pending before the Registrar at the notified date in 
relation to a trade mark shall be deemed to have been transferred to the 
appropriate office of the trade marks registry.       
</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Leaving of documents, etc. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2), all applications, notices, statements or other documents or any fees authorised or required by the Act or the rules to be made, served, left or sent or paid at or to the trade marks registry in relation to a trade mark on the Register of Trade Marks on the notified date or for which an application for registration is pending on, or is made on or after the notified date, shall be made, served, left or sent or paid to the appropriate office of the trade marks registry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Documents or fees authorised or required by the Act or the rules to be sent or paid may be sent or paid at or to either the appropriate office or the head office of the trade mark registry in the following matters:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> communication and other documents including affidavits in relation to an application filed for registration of a trade mark; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> application or request in Forms TM-10, TM-12, TM-13, TM-14, TM-16, TM-17, TM-19, TM-20, TM-21, TM-23, TM-24, TM-25, TM-28, TM-29, TM-30, TM-31, TM-32, TM-33, TM-34, TM-35, TM-36, TM-38, TM-40, TM-46, TM-47, TM-50, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***], TM-55, TM-58, TM-59, TM-61 and  
    TM-62; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1) and under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (3) of rule 24, a request for search and issuance of certificate in Form TM-60, expedited examination in Form TM-63, or expedited certified copies of documents in Form TM-70, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[***] or for expedited search and issuance of a copyright certificate in Form TM-72 shall be filed at the head registry until the Registrar after informing the public in the Journals directs otherwise. 
</subsection>




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Leaving of documents, etc. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2), all applications, notices, statements or other documents or any fees authorised or required by the Act or the rules to be made, served, left or sent or paid at or to the trade marks registry in relation to a trade mark on the Register of Trade Marks on the notified date or for which an application for registration is pending on, or is made on or after the notified date, shall be made, served, left or sent or paid to the appropriate office of the trade marks registry. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Documents or fees authorised or required by the Act or the rules to be sent or paid may be sent or paid at or to either the appropriate office or the head office of the trade mark registry in the following matters:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> communication and other documents including affidavits in relation to an application filed for registration of a trade mark; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> application or request in Forms TM-10, TM-12, TM-13, TM-14, TM-16, TM-17, TM-19, TM-20, TM-21, TM-23, TM-24, TM-25, TM-28, TM-29, TM-30, TM-31, TM-32, TM-33, TM-34, TM-35, TM-36, TM-38, TM-40, TM-46, TM-47, TM-50, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[***], TM-55, TM-58, TM-59, TM-61 and  
    TM-62; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1) and under clause (a) or clause (b) of sub-rule (2) or sub-rule (3) of rule 24, a request for search and issuance of certificate in Form TM-60, expedited examination in Form TM-63, or expedited certified copies of documents in Form TM-70, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***] or for expedited search and issuance of a copyright certificate in Form TM-72 shall be filed at the head registry until the Registrar after informing the public in the Journals directs otherwise. 
</subsection>




</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>10</number> Issue of notices etc.—Any 
notice or communication relating to an application, matter or proceeding under 
the Act or the rules may be issued by the Head of Office or any other officers 
authorised by the Registrar.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>11</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> The fees to be paid 
in respect of applications, oppositions, registration, renewal, expedited 
examination or reports or any other matters under the Act and the rules shall 
be those specified in the First Schedule, hereinafter referred to as the 
prescribed fees.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where in respect of any matter, a fee 
is required to be paid under the rules, the form or the application or the 
request of the petition thereof, it shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Fees may be paid in cash or sent by 
money order addressed to the Registrar or by a bank draft issued or by a cheque 
drawn on a scheduled bank at the place where the appropriate office of the 
Trade Marks Registry is situated and if sent through post, shall be deemed to 
have been paid at the time when the money order or the properly addressed bank 
draft or cheque would be delivered in the ordinary course of post.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Bank drafts and cheques shall be 
crossed and made payable to the Registrar at the appropriate office of the 
Trade Marks Registry and they shall be drawn on a scheduled bank at the place 
where the appropriate office of the Trade Marks Registry is situate.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subject to the provisions contained in 
sub-rule (19) of rule 25, where a fee is payable in respect of filing of a 
document and where the document is filed without fee or with insufficient fee, 
such document shall be deemed not to have been filed for the purposes of any 
proceedings under these rules.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Registrar may, after informing the 
public in the Journal, make available electronic fee transfer facilities, 
subject to guidelines and instructions as may be specified on that behalf.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>12</number> Forms.—
<section><number>1</number> The Forms set forth 
in the Second and the Third Schedules shall be used in all cases to which they 
are applicable and may be modified as directed by the Registrar to meet other 
cases.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any Form, when filed at the Trade 
Marks Registry, shall be accompanied by the prescribed fee.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A requirement under this rule to use a 
Form as set forth in the Schedules is satisfied by the use either of a replica 
of that Form or of a Form which is acceptable to the Registrar and contains the 
information required by the Form as set forth and complies with any direction 
as to the use of such a Form. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may after informing the 
public in the Journal, specify such Forms as are required to be submitted in 
electronic mode. Thereafter, such Forms shall be completed in such a manner as 
may be specified as to permit an automated input of the content into a computer 
such as by character recognition or scanning.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>13</number> Size, etc. of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to any other directions that may be given by the Registrar, all 
applications, notices, statements, or other documents except trade marks, 
authorised or required by the Act or the rules to be made, served, left or 
sent, at or to the Trade Marks Registry or with or to the Registrar shall be 
neatly handwritten or typewritten or lithographed or printed in Hindi or in 
English in large and legible characters with deep permanent ink upon strong 
paper, and except in the case of affidavits, on one side only, and of size of 
approximately 33 centimetres by 20 centimetres and shall have on the left hand 
part thereof a margin of not less than 4 centimetres.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Duplicate documents including copies 
of trade marks shall be filed at the Trade Marks Registry if at any time 
required by the Registrar.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar may after informing the 
public in the Journal alter the size, of all applications, notices, statements 
or other document and forms required under the rules to make it compatible in 
electronic mode.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may, after informing the 
public in the Journal, permit the filing of applications, statements, notices 
or other documents by electronic modes subject to such guidelines and 
instructions as he may specify in the Journal .
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>14</number> Signing of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
document purporting to be signed by a partnership firm shall be signed by at 
least one of the partners stating that he signs on behalf of the firm and a 
document purporting to be signed by a body corporate shall be signed by a 
director or by the secretary or other principal officer of the body corporate. 
The capacity in which an individual signs a document on behalf of a partnership 
or a body corporate shall be stated below his signature.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Signatures to any documents shall be 
accompanied by the name of the signatory in Hindi or in capitals letters, if 
signed in English.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>15</number> Service of documents.—
<section><number>1</number> All 
applications, notices, statements, papers having representations affixed 
thereto, or other documents authorised or required by the Act or the rules to 
be made, served, left or sent, at or to the Trade Marks Registry or with or to 
the Registrar or any other person may be sent through the post by a prepaid 
letter. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application or document so sent 
shall be deemed to have been made, served, left or sent at the time when the 
letter containing the same would be delivered in the ordinary course of post.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In proving such sending, it shall be 
sufficient to prove that the letter was properly addressed and put into the 
post.
 </section><section><number>4</number> After the filing of an application at 
the Trade Marks Registry, any person while making any correspondence relating 
thereto shall furnish the following particulars, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the application number or numbers, if any;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the date and place of filing;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the appropriate class or classes, as the case 
may be, in relation to which the application is filed;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  an address for communication; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the concerned agent’s code, if any and the 
concerned Proprietor’s code if allotted.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> The Registrar may, after informing the 
public in the Journal permit transmission of any document by facsimile (fax) of 
specified documents not requiring payment of a fee.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Registrar may after informing the 
public in the Journal accept communications of a routine nature through E-Mail 
not requiring the payment of a fee thereof.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>16</number> Particulars of address of 
applicants and other persons.—
<section><number>1</number> Names and addresses of the applicants and 
other persons shall given in full, together with their nationality, calling and 
such other particulars as are necessary for identification.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the case of a firm, the full name 
and nationality of every partner thereof shall be stated.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the case of an application from a 
convention country and persons having no principal place of business in India, 
their addresses in their home country shall be given in addition to their 
address for service in India.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the case of a body corporate or 
firm, the country of incorporation or the nature of registration, if any, as 
the case may be, shall be given.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>17</number> Statement of principal place of 
business in India in an application.—
<section><number>1</number> Every application for registration 
of a trade mark shall state the principal place of business in India, if any, 
of the applicant or in the case of joint applicants, of such of the joint 
applicants as have a principal place of business in India.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of rules 18, 
19 and 21, any written communication addressed to an applicant, or in the case 
of joint applicants to a joint applicant, in connection with the registration 
of a trade mark, at the address of his principal place of business in India 
given by him in the application shall be deemed to be properly addressed.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>18</number> Address for service.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
address for service in India shall be given—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  by every applicant for registration of a trade 
mark who has no principal place of business in India;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  in the case of joint applicants for 
registration of a trade mark, if none of them has a principal place of business 
in India;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  by the proprietor of a trade mark who had his 
principal place of business in India at the date of making the application for 
registration but has subsequently ceased to have such place;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  by every applicant in any proceeding under the 
Act or the rules and every person filing a notice of opposition, who does not 
have a principal place of business in India;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  by every person granted leave to intervene 
under rule 94.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any written communication addressed to 
a person as aforesaid at an address for service in India given by him shall be 
deemed to be properly addressed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Unless an address for service in India 
as required in sub-rule (1) is given, the Registrar shall be under no 
obligation to send any notice that may be required by the Act or the rules and 
no subsequent order or decision in the proceedings shall be called in question 
on the ground of any lack or non-service of notice.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>19</number> Address for service in application 
and opposition proceedings.—An applicant for registration of a trade mark 
or an opponent filing a notice of opposition may notwithstanding that he has a 
principal place of business in India, if he so desires, may specifically 
request in writing, the Registrar with an address in India to which 
communications in relation to the application or opposition proceedings only 
may be sent. Such address of the applicant or the opponent shall be deemed, 
unless subsequently cancelled, to be the actual address of the applicant or the 
opponent, as the case may be, and all communications and documents in relation 
to the application or notice of opposition may be served by leaving them at, or 
sending them by post to such address of the applicant or the opponent, as the 
case may be.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>20</number> Non-availability of an address for 
service.—The Registrar may, at any time when a doubt arises as to the 
continued availability of an address for service in India entered in the 
register, request the person for whom it is entered, by letter directed to any 
other address entered in the register or if no such address is entered in the 
register to the address at which the Registrar considers that the letter would 
reach him, to confirm the address for service in India and if within two months 
of making such a request the Registrar receives no such confirmation, he may 
strike the entry in the register of the address for service in India and 
require such person to furnish a fresh address for service in India or his 
address at the principal place of business in India, if he has any at that 
time.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>21</number> Agency.—
<section><number>1</number> The authorisation 
of an agent for the purpose of section 145 shall be executed in Form TM-48 or 
in such other written form as the Registrar may deem sufficient and proper.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the case of such authorisation, 
service upon the agent of any document relating to the proceeding or matter 
shall be deemed to be service upon the person so authorising him; all 
communications directed to be made to such person in respect of the proceeding 
or matter may be addressed to such agent, and all appearances before Registrar 
relating thereto may be made by or through such agent.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In any particular case, the Registrar 
may require the personal signature or presence of an applicant, opponent, 
proprietor, registered user or other person.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>22</number> Classification of goods and  
services.—
<section><number>1</number> For the purposes of the registration of trade marks, goods 
and services shall be classified in the manner specified in the Fourth 
Schedule.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The goods and services specified in 
the Fourth Schedule only provide a means by which the general content of 
numbered international classes can be quickly identified. It corresponds to the 
major content of each class and are not intended to be exhaustive in accordance 
with the international classification of goods and services. For determining 
the classification of particular goods and services and for full disclosure of 
the content of international classification, the applicant may refer to the 
alphabetical index of goods and services, if any, published by the Registrar 
under section 8 or the current edition of the international classification of 
goods and services for the purpose of registration of trade mark published by 
the World International Property Organisation or subsequent edition as may be 
published. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar shall identify and 
include in the alphabetical index of classification of goods and services, as 
far as practicable, goods or services of Indian origin.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>23</number> Preliminary advice by Registrar as 
to distinctiveness.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for preliminary advice by the 
Registrar under sub-section (1) of section 133 shall be made in Form TM-55 in 
respect of any goods or services comprised within any one class in the Fourth 
Schedule, accompanied by three representations of the trade mark.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The advice referred to sub-rule (1) 
shall ordinarily be given within seven working days of such filing of the 
application and such advice shall contain the reasons therefor.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> Request to Registrar for search. </title>— <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***] 
 <section><number>3</number> Any person may request the Registrar, in Form TM-60 to cause a search to be made and for issue of certificate under sub-section (1) of section 45 of the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957) to the effect that no trade mark identical with or deceptively similar to such artistic work, as sought to be registered as copyright under the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957) has been registered as a trade mark under the Trade Marks Act, 1999 (47 of 1999) in the name of, or that no application has been made under that Act for such re-registration by any person other than the applicant. The certificate shall ordinarily be issued within thirty working days of the date of request: 
 Provided, however, the Registrar may call for a statement of requirements from the applicant and if the requirements are not complied within two month from the date of such calling of the statement, the request in Form TM-60 may be treated as abandoned. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may cancel the certificate issued under sub-rule (3) after giving notice and stating the grounds on which the Registrar proposes to cancel the certificate and after providing reasonable opportunity of being heard. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subject to proviso to sub-rule (3) or sub-rule (4), the Registrar shall ordinarily within seven working days issue an expedited search certificate under sub-section (1) of section 45 of the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957) on a request received in Form TM-72 on payment of five times the ordinary fee for such search. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Before abandoning the request in Form TM-60 or TM-72, as the case may be, for non-compliance of the statement of requirements when called for, the Registrar shall offer an opportunity of being heard in the matter. 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> Request to Registrar for search. </title>— <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[***] 
 <section><number>3</number> Any person may request the Registrar, in Form TM-60 to cause a search to be made and for issue of certificate under sub-section (1) of section 45 of the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957) to the effect that no trade mark identical with or deceptively similar to such artistic work, as sought to be registered as copyright under the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957) has been registered as a trade mark under the Trade Marks Act, 1999 (47 of 1999) in the name of, or that no application has been made under that Act for such re-registration by any person other than the applicant. The certificate shall ordinarily be issued within thirty working days of the date of request: 
 Provided, however, the Registrar may call for a statement of requirements from the applicant and if the requirements are not complied within two month from the date of such calling of the statement, the request in Form TM-60 may be treated as abandoned. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may cancel the certificate issued under sub-rule (3) after giving notice and stating the grounds on which the Registrar proposes to cancel the certificate and after providing reasonable opportunity of being heard. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Subject to proviso to sub-rule (3) or sub-rule (4), the Registrar shall ordinarily within seven working days issue an expedited search certificate under sub-section (1) of section 45 of the Copyright Act, 1957 (14 of 1957) on a request received in Form TM-72 on payment of five times the ordinary fee for such search. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Before abandoning the request in Form TM-60 or TM-72, as the case may be, for non-compliance of the statement of requirements when called for, the Registrar shall offer an opportunity of being heard in the matter. 






</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>25</number> Form and signing of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
An application to the Registrar for the registration of a trade mark shall be 
signed by the applicant or his agent.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application to register a trade 
mark for a specification of goods or services included in any one class shall 
be made in Form TM-1.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An application to register a trade 
mark under sub-section (2) of section 154 for a specification of goods or 
services included in any one class from a convention country shall be made in 
Form TM-2.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A single application for the 
registration of a trade mark for different classes of goods or services from 
convention country under sub-section (2) of section 154 shall be made in Form 
TM-52.
 </section><section><number>5</number> An application to register a textile 
trade mark (other than a collective mark or a certification trade mark) 
consisting exclusively of numerals or letters or any combination thereof for a 
specification of goods included in one item of the Fifth Schedule under rule 
145 shall be made in Form TM-22.
 </section><section><number>6</number> An application to register of a 
textile trade mark (other than a collective mark or a certification trade mark) 
consisting exclusively of numerals or letters or any combination thereof for a 
specification of goods included in one item of the Fifth Schedule under rule 
145 from a convention country under sub-section (2) of section 154 shall be 
made in From TM-45.
 </section><section><number>7</number> (a) An application under section 63(1) 
to register a collective trade mark for a specification goods or services in 
any one class shall be made in Form TM-3.
 <subsection><number>b</number> An application under section 63(1) to 
register a collective trade mark for a specification of goods or services in 
any one class from a convention country under sub-section (2) of section 154 
shall be made in Form TM-64.
 </subsection></section><section><number>8</number>(a) An application under section 71 to 
register a certification trade mark for a specification of goods or services 
included in any one class shall be made in Form TM-4.
 <subsection><number>b</number> An application under section 71 to 
register a certification trade mark for a specification of goods or services in 
any one class from a convention country under sub-section (2) of section 154 
shall be made in Form TM-65.
 </subsection></section><section><number>9</number> A single application for the 
registration of a trade mark for different classes of goods or services shall 
be made in Form TM-51.
 </section><section><number>10</number> An application to register a series 
trade marks under section 15 for a specification of goods or services included 
in a class or for different classes shall be made in Form TM-8.
 </section><section><number>11</number> An application to register a series 
trade mark under section 15 for a specification of goods or services included 
in a class or different classes from a convention country under sub-section (2) 
of section 154 shall be made in From  
TM-37.
 </section><section><number>12</number> An application for the registration 
of a trade mark for goods or services shall—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  explain with sufficient precision, a 
description by words, of the trade mark if necessary, to determine the right of 
the applicant;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  be able to depict the graphical representation 
of the trade mark;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  be considered as a three dimensional trade mark 
only if the application contains a statement to that effect;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  be considered as a trade mark consisting of a 
combination of colours only if the application contains a statement to that 
effect.
 </subsection></section><section><number>13</number> An amendment to divide an application 
under proviso to section 22 shall be made in Form TM-53.
 </section><section><number>14</number> An application, not being a series 
trade mark shall be in respect of one trade mark only for as many class or 
classes of goods or services as may be made.
 </section><section><number>15</number> In the case of an application for 
registration in respect of all the goods or services included in a class or of 
a large variety of goods or services in a class, the Registrar may refuse to 
accept the application unless he is satisfied that the specification is 
justified by the use of the mark which the applicant has made or intends to 
make if and when it is registered.
 </section><section><number>16</number> The specification of goods or 
services shall not ordinarily exceed five hundred characters for each class. An 
excess space fee as prescribed in the First Schedule is payable with each 
application in Form TM-61.
 </section><section><number>17</number> A single application for the 
registration of a collective mark—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> in different classes shall be made in Form 
TM-66;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  in different classes from a convention country 
shall be made in Form  
TM-67.
 </subsection></section><section><number>18</number> A single application for the 
registration of certification trade mark—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  in different classes shall be made in Form 
TM-68;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> in different classes from a convention country 
shall be made in Form TM-69.
 </subsection></section><section><number>19</number> Where an applicant files a single 
application for more classes than one and the Registrar determines that the 
goods or services applied for fall in class or classes in addition to those 
applied for, the applicant may restrict the specification of goods or services 
to the class applied for or amend the application to add additional class or 
classes on payment of the appropriate class fee and the divisional fee. The new 
class created through a division retains the benefit of the original filing 
date or in the case of an application from a convention country the convention 
application date under sub-section (2) of section 154 provided the claim was 
otherwise properly asserted in the initial application.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>26</number> Application under convention 
arrangement.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a right to priority is claimed by reason of an 
application for registration of a trade mark duly filed in a convention country 
under section 154, a certificate by the Registry or competent authority of that 
trade marks office shall be included in an application for registration under 
sub-rule (3), (4), (6), (7)(b), (8)(b), (11), (17)(b) or (18)(b) of rule 25, as 
the case may be, and it shall include the particulars of the mark, the country 
or countries and the date or dates of filing of application and such other 
relevant particulars as may be required by the Registrar.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Unless such certificate has been filed 
at the time of the filing of the application for registration, there shall be 
filed, within two months of the filing of such application certifying or 
verifying to the satisfaction of the Registrar, the date of the filing of the 
application, the country or countries, the representation of the mark, and the 
goods or services covered by the application. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The application shall include a 
statement indicating the filing date of the filing in the convention 
application, the name of the convention country where it was filed, the serial 
number, if any, and a statement indicating that priority is claimed:
 Provided that where the applicant files 
more priority claims than one under section 154 for some or all the goods or 
services in respect of the same trade mark, the Registrar shall also take the 
date of the earlier application in a convention country, as the priority date:
 Provided further that such priority date 
shall only be in respect of all or some of the goods or services referred to in 
the earlier convention application.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where a single application under 
sub-section (2) of section 18 is filed from a convention country for one or 
more classes of goods or services, the applicants shall establish a sufficient 
ground to the satisfaction of the Registrar for the date of filing of 
application in all such classes.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>27</number> Statement of user in applications.—An 
application to register a trade mark shall, unless the trade mark is proposed 
to be used, contain a statement of the period during which, and the person by 
whom it has been used in respect of the goods or services mentioned in the 
application. The Registrar may require the applicant to file an affidavit 
testifying to such user with exhibits showing the mark as used.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>28</number> Representation of mark.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application for the registration of a trade mark, and where additional 
copies of the application are required every such copy, shall contain a 
representation of the mark in the space (8cm x 8cm) provided on the application 
form for that purpose:
 Provided that in any case the size 
representation shall not exceed 33 centimetres by 20 centimetres with a margin 
of 4 centimetres on the left hand side.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>29</number> Additional representations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application for registration of a trade mark shall, except as hereinafter 
provided, be made in triplicate and shall be accompanied by five additional 
representations of the mark. The representations of the mark on the application 
and each of its copies and the additional representations shall correspond 
exactly with one another. The additional representations shall in all cases be 
noted with the specification and class or classes of goods or services for 
which registration is sought, the name and address of the applicant, together 
with the name and address of his agent, if any, the period of use, if any, and 
such other particulars as may from time to time be required by the Registrar 
and shall be signed by the applicant or his agent.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where an application contains a 
statement to the effect that the applicant wishes to claim combination of 
colours as the distinctive feature of the mark, the application shall be 
accompanied with one reproduction of the mark in black and white and four 
reproduction of the mark in colour.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the application contains a 
statement to the effect that the trade mark is a three dimensional mark, the 
reproduction of the mark shall consist of a two dimensional graphic or 
photographic reproduction as follows, namely:—
 <subsection>        <number>i</number>  The reproduction furnished shall consist of 
three different view of the trade mark;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>ii</number>  Where, however, the Registrar considers that 
the reproduction of the mark furnished by the applicants does not sufficiently 
show the particulars of the three dimensional mark, he may call upon the 
applicant to furnish within two months up to five further different views of 
the mark and a description by words of the mark;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  Where the Registrar considers the different 
views and/or description of the mark referred to in clause (ii) still do not 
sufficiently show the particulars of the three dimensional mark, he may call 
upon the applicant to furnish a specimen of the trade mark.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> (i) Where an application for the 
registration of a trade mark consists of shape of goods or its packaging, the 
reproduction furnished shall consist of at least five different views of the 
trade mark and a description by word of the mark.
 <subsection><number>ii</number> If the Register considers the 
different views and description of the mark in sub-clause (i) still does not 
sufficiently show the particulars of the shape of goods or its packaging, he 
may call upon the applicant to furnish a specimen of the goods or packaging as 
the case may be.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>30</number> Representations to be durable and 
satisfactory.—
<section><number>1</number> All representations of trade marks shall be of a durable 
nature, and each additional representation required to be filed with an 
application for registration shall be mounted on a sheet of strong paper of the 
size of approximately 33 centimetres by 20 centimetres, leaving a margin of not 
less than 4 centimetres on the left hand part of the sheet.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the Registrar is not satisfied with 
any representation of a mark he may at any time require another representation 
satisfactory to him to be substituted before proceedings with the application.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where representation of a trade mark 
cannot be given in the manner set forth hereinabove, a specimen or copy of the 
trade mark may be sent either in full size or on a reduced scale and in such 
form as the Registrar may think most convenient.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>31</number> Series trade marks.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
an application is made for the registration of series trade marks under 
sub-section (3) of section 15, copies of representation of each trade mark of 
the series shall accompany the application in the manner set forth in rules 28 
and 29.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An applicant claiming to be the 
proprietor of a series trade mark under sub-section (3) of section 15 may apply 
to the Registrar in Form TM-8 or TM-37, as the case may be, for its 
registration as a series for one registration and there shall be included in 
each such application a representation of the trade marks in a class or in of 
each class claimed to be in the series. The Registrar shall, if satisfied that 
the marks constitutes a series proceed further with the applications.
 </section><section><number>3</number> At any time before the publication of 
the application in the Journal, the applicant applying under sub-rule (2) may 
request in Form TM-53 for the division of the application into separate 
application or applications, as the case may be, in respect of one or more 
marks in that series and the Registrar shall, if he is satisfied that the 
division requested conforms with sub-section (3) of section 15, divide the 
application or applications accordingly. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The division of an application into 
one or more applications under sub-rule (3) shall be on the payment of a 
divisional fee and such class fees as are appropriate.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number></title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[***] 
  




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>32</number></title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[***] 
  




</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>33</number> Transliteration and translation.—Where 
a trade mark contains a word or words in scripts other than Hindi or English, 
there shall be endorsed on the application form and the additional 
representations thereof, a sufficient transliteration and translation to the 
satisfaction of the Registrar of each such word in English or in Hindi and 
every such endorsement shall state the language to which the word belongs and 
shall be signed by the applicant or his agent.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>34</number> Names and representations of living 
persons or persons recently dead.—Where the name or representation of any 
person appears on a trade mark the applicant shall, if the Registrar so 
requires, furnish him with the consent in writing of such person in case he is 
living or, in case his death took place within twenty years prior to the date 
of the application for registration of the trade mark, of his legal 
representative, as the case may be, to the use of the name or representation 
and in default of such consent the Registrar may refuse to proceed with the 
application for registration of the trade mark.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>35</number> Name or description of goods or 
services on a trade mark.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the name or description of any goods or 
services appears on a trade mark, the Registrar may refuse to register such 
mark in respect of any goods or services other than the goods or services so 
named or described.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the name or description of any 
goods or services appear on a trade mark, which name or description in use 
varies, the Registrar may permit the registration of the mark for those and 
other goods or services on the applicant giving an undertaking that the name or 
description will be varied when the trade mark is used upon goods or services 
covered by the specification other than the named or described goods or 
services. The undertaking so given shall be included in the advertisement of 
the application in the Journal under section 20. 
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>36</number> Deficiencies.—Subject to 
sub-rule (2) of rule 11, where an application for registration of a trade mark 
does not satisfy the requirement of any of the provisions of the Act or rules, 
the Registrar shall send notice thereof to the applicant to remedy the 
deficiencies and if within one month of the date of the notice the applicant 
fails to remedy any deficiency so notified to him, the application may be 
treated as abandoned.
  
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>37</number> Acknowledgement and Search.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application for the registration of a trade mark in respect of any goods 
or services shall on receipt, be acknowledged by the Registrar. The 
acknowledgement shall be by way of return of one of the additional 
representations of the trade mark filed by the applicant along with his 
application, with the official number of the application duly entered thereon.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Upon receipt of the application for 
registration of trade mark, the Registrar shall cause a search to be made 
amongst the registered trade marks and amongst the pending applications for the 
purpose of ascertaining whether there are on record in respect of the same 
goods or services or similar goods or services any mark identical with or 
deceptively similar to the mark sought to be registered and the Registrar may 
cause the search to be renewed at any time before the acceptance of the 
application but shall not be bound to do so.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>38</number> Expedited examination, objection to 
acceptance, hearing.—
<section><number>1</number> After the receipt of the official number of an 
application under sub-rule (1) of rule 37, an applicant may request for 
expedited examination of an application for the registration of a trade mark in 
Form TM-63 together with a declaration stating the reason for the request, on 
payment of five times the application fee.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the Registrar is satisfied on the 
basis of declaration filed under sub-rule (1) that an expedited examination of 
the application is warranted, he shall cause the expedited examination of such 
application in the order in which the requests are filed and may ordinarily 
issue the examination report within three months of the date of such request.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the Registrar declines the 
request under sub-rule (1), the applicant shall be entitled to have the fee 
refunded:
 Provided that before declining any such 
request, the Registrar shall provide the applicant an opportunity of being 
heard.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If on consideration of an application 
for registration of a trade mark or on an application for an expedited 
examination of an application referred to in sub-rule (1) and any evidence of 
use or of distinctiveness or of any other matter which the applicant may or may 
be required to furnish, the Registrar has any objection to the acceptance of 
the application or proposes to accept it subject to such conditions, 
amendments, modifications or limitations as he may think fit to impose under 
sub-section (4) of section 18, the Registrar shall communicate such objection 
or proposal in writing to the applicant.
 </section><section><number>5</number> If within one month from the date of 
communication referred to in sub-rule (4), the applicants fails to comply with 
any such proposal or fails to submit his comments regarding any objection or 
proposal to the Registrar or apply for a hearing or fails to attend the 
hearing, the application shall be deemed to have been abandoned.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>39</number> Notice of withdrawal of application 
for registration.—A notice of withdrawal of an application for the 
registration of a trade mark under sub-section (2) of section 133, or sub-rule 
(2) or rule 24, for the purpose of obtaining repayment of any fee paid on the 
filing of the application, shall be given in writing within one month from the 
date of the receipt of communication mentioned in sub-rule (4) of rule 38.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>40</number> Decision of Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
decision of the Registrar under rule 38 or rule 42 after a hearing or without a 
hearing if the applicant has duly communicated his observations in writing and 
has stated that he does not desire to be heard, shall be communicated to the 
applicant in writing and if the applicant intends to appeal from such decision 
he may within thirty days from the date of receipt of such communication apply 
in Form TM-15 to the Registrar requiring him to state in writing the grounds 
of, and the materials used by him in arriving at, his decision.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In a case where the Registrar makes 
any requirements to which the applicant does not object the applicant shall 
comply therewith before the Registrar issues a statement in writing under 
sub-rule (1).
 </section><section><number>3</number> The date when the statement in writing 
under sub-rule (1) is received shall be deemed to be the date of the 
Registrar’s decision for the purpose of an appeal.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>41</number> Correction and amendment of 
application.—An applicant for registration of a trade mark may, whether 
before or after acceptance of his application but before the registration of 
the mark, apply in Form TM-16 accompanied by the prescribed fee for the 
correction of any error in or in connection with his application or any 
amendment of his application:
 Provided however, no such amendment shall 
be permitted which shall have the effect of substantially altering the trade 
mark applied for or substitute a new specification of goods or services not 
included in the application as filed.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>42</number> Withdrawal of acceptance by the 
Registrar.—
<section><number>1</number> If, after the acceptance of an application but before the 
registration of the trade mark, the Registrar has any objection to the 
acceptance of the application on the ground that it was accepted in error, or 
that the mark ought not to have been accepted in the circumstances of the case, 
or proposes that the mark should be registered only subject to conditions, 
limitations, divisions or to conditions additional to or different from the 
conditions, or limitations, subject to which the application has been accepted, 
the Registrar shall communicate such objection in writing to the applicant.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Unless within thirty days from the 
date of receipt of the communication mentioned in sub-rule (1) the applicant 
amends his application to comply with the requirements of the Registrar or 
applies for a hearing, the acceptance of the application shall be deemed to be 
withdrawn by the Registrar, and the application shall proceed as if it had not 
been accepted.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the applicant intimates the 
Registrar within the period mentioned in sub-rule (2) that he desires to be 
heard, the Registrar shall give notice to the applicant of a date when he will 
hear him. Such appointment shall be for a date at least fifteen days after the 
date of the notice, unless the applicant consents to a shorter notice. The 
applicant may state that he does not desire to be heard and submit such 
submissions, as he may consider desirable.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may, after hearing the 
applicant, on considering the submissions, if any, of the applicant, pass such 
orders as he may deem fit.
  
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>43</number> Manner of Advertisement.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
application for the registration of a trade mark required or permitted to be 
advertised by sub-section (1) of section 20 or to be re-advertised by 
sub-section (2) of that section shall be advertised in the Journal ordinarily 
within six months of the acceptance of an application for registration or after 
the expiry of the period referred to sub-section (2) of section 154 whichever 
is later.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a trade mark applied is other 
than a word, the Registrar may call upon the applicant to furnish a 
camera-ready copy of the trade mark ordered to be advertised to scan 
electronically into a Desk Top publishing package.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar may after informing the 
public in the Journal, put the applications published in the Journal on the 
Internet, web site or any other electronic media.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may after informing the 
public in the Journal make available the Journal in CD-ROM on payment of the 
cost thereof.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>44</number> Advertisement of series.—Where 
an application relates to a series trade marks differing from one another in 
respect of the particulars mentioned in sub-section (3) of section 15, the 
Registrar may, if he thinks fit, insert with the advertisement of the 
application a statement of the manner in which the several trade marks differ 
from one another.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>45</number> Notification of correction or 
amendment of application.—In the case of an application to which clause (b) 
of sub-section (2) of section 20 applies, the Registrar may, if he so decides, 
instead of causing the application to be advertised again, insert in the 
Journal a notification setting out the number of the application, the class or 
classes in which it was made, the name and address of the principal place of 
business in India, if any, of the applicant or where the applicant has no 
principal place of business in India his address for service in India, the 
Journal number in which it was advertised and the correction or amendment made 
in the application.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>46</number> Request to Registrar for 
particulars of advertisement of a mark.—Any person may request the 
Registrar in Form TM-58 to be informed of the number, and date of the Journal 
in which a trade mark which is sought to be registered specified in the Form 
was advertised and the Registrar shall furnish such particulars to the person 
making the request.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>47</number> Notice of Opposition.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
notice of opposition to the registration of a trade mark under sub-section (1) 
of section 21 shall be given in triplicate in Form TM-5 within three months or 
within such further period not exceeding one month in the aggregate from the 
date the Journal is made available to the public (which date shall be certified 
by the Registrar as such). The notice shall include a statement of the grounds 
upon which the opponent objects to the registration. If the registration is 
opposed on the ground that the trade marks in question resembles marks already 
on the register, the registration numbers of such trade marks and the dates of 
the Journals in which they have been advertised shall be set out.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a notice of opposition has been 
filed in respect of a single application for the registration of a trade mark, 
it shall bear the fee in respect of each class in relation to which the 
opposition is filed in Form TM-5.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where an opposition is filed only for 
a particular class or classes in respect of a single application made under 
sub-section (2) of section 18, the application for remaining class or classes 
shall not proceed to registration until a request in Form TM-53 for division of 
the application together with the divisional fee is made by the applicant.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where in respect of a single 
application for the registration of a trade mark, no notice of opposition is 
filed in a class or classes, the application in respect of such class or 
classes shall subject to section 19 and sub-section (1) of section 23, proceed 
to registration after the division of the application in the class or classes 
in respect of which an opposition is pending.
 </section><section><number>5</number> All notices of opposition to the 
registration of a trade mark for goods or services received in respect of a 
particular Journal shall be published in the Journal:
 Provided that nothing in this sub-rule 
shall be construed to presume that all remaining trade marks from a particular 
journal so published shall automatically proceed to registration.
 </section><section><number>6</number> An application for an extension of the 
period within which a notice of opposition to the registration of a trade mark 
may be given under sub-section (1) of section 21, shall be made in Form TM-44 
accompanied by the fee prescribed in First Schedule before the expiry of the 
period of three months under sub-section (1) of section 21.
 </section><section><number>7</number> A copy of notice of opposition shall 
be ordinarily served by the Registrar to the applicants within three months of 
the receipt of the same by the appropriate office.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>48</number> Requirements of Notice of 
Opposition.—A notice of opposition shall contain,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  in respect of an application against which 
opposition is entered—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  the application number against which 
opposition is entered;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  an indication of the goods or services 
listed in the trade mark application against which opposition is entered; and
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  the name of the applicant for the trade 
mark.
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>b</number>  in respect of the earlier mark or the earlier 
right on which the opposition is based,—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  where the opposition is based on an 
earlier mark, a statement to that effect and an indication of the status of 
earlier mark;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  where available, the application number 
or registration number and the filing date, including the priority date of the 
earlier mark;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  where the opposition is based on an 
earlier mark which is alleged to be a well-known trade mark within the meaning 
of sub-section (2) of section 11, an indication to that effect and an 
indication of the country or countries in which the earlier mark is recognised 
to be well-known;
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number>  where the opposition is based on an 
earlier trade mark having a reputation within the meaning of paragraph (b) of 
sub-clause (2) of section 11 of the Act, an indication to that effect and an 
indication of whether the earlier mark is registered or applied for;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>v</number>  a representation of the mark of the 
opponent and where appropriate, a description of the mark or earlier right; and

 </subsection><subsection>           <number>vi</number>  where the goods or services in respect of 
which earlier mark has been registered or applied for or in respect of which 
the earlier mark is well known within the meaning of sub-section (2) of section 
11 or has a reputation within the meaning of that section, the opponent shall 
when indicating all the goods or services for which the earlier mark is 
protected, also indicate those goods or services on which the opposition is 
based.
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>c</number>  in respect of the opposing party—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  where the opposition is entered by the 
proprietor of the earlier mark or of the earlier right, his name and address 
and an indication that he is the proprietor of such mark or right;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  where opposition is entered by a licensee 
not being a registered user, the name of the licensee and his address and an 
indication that he has been authorised to enter the opposition;
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>iii</number>  where the opposition is entered by the 
successor in title to the registered proprietor of a trade mark who has not yet 
been registered as new proprietor, an indication to that effect, the name and 
address of the opposing party and an indication of the date on which the 
application for registration of the new proprietor was received by the 
appropriate office or, where this information is not available, was sent to the 
appropriate office; and 
 </subsection><subsection>           <number>iv</number>  where the opposing party has no place of 
business in India, the name of the opponents and his address for service in 
India.
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>d</number>  the grounds on which the opposition is based.
 <subsection><number>2</number> A notice of opposition shall be 
verified at the foot by the opponent or by some other person who is acquainted 
with the facts of the case.
 </subsection><subsection><number>3</number> The person verifying shall state 
specifically by reference to the numbered paragraphs of the notice of 
opposition, what he verifies of his own knowledge and what he verifies upon 
information received and believed to be true.
 </subsection><subsection><number>4</number> The verification shall be signed by 
the person making it and shall state the date on which and the place at which 
it was signed.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>49</number> Counter-statement.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
counter-statement required by sub-section (2) of section 21 shall be sent in 
triplicate in Form TM-6 within two months from the receipt by the applicant of 
the copy of the notice of opposition from the Registrar and shall set out what 
facts, if any, alleged in the notice of opposition, are admitted by the 
applicant. A copy of the counter-statement shall be ordinarily served by the 
Registrar to the opponent within two months from the date of receipt of the 
same.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The counter-statement shall be 
verified in the same manner as the notice of opposition as stated in clause (e) 
of sub-rule (1) of rule 48.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>50</number> Evidence in support of opposition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Within two months from services on him of a copy of the counterstatement or 
within such further period not exceeding one month in the aggregate thereafter 
as the Registrar may on request allow, the opponent shall either leave with the 
Registrar, such evidence by way of affidavit as he may desire to adduce in 
support of his opposition or shall intimate to the Registrar and to the 
applicant in writing that he does not desire to adduce evidence in support of 
his opposition but intends to rely on the facts stated in the notice of 
opposition. He shall deliver to the applicant copies of any evidence that he 
leaves with the Registrar under this sub-rule and intimate the Registrar in 
writing of such delivery.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If an opponent takes no action under 
sub-rule (1) within the time mentioned therein, he shall be deemed to have 
abandoned his opposition.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An application for the extension of 
the period of one month mentioned in sub-rule (1) shall be made in Form TM-56 
accompanied by the prescribed fee before the expiry of the period of two months 
mentioned therein.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>51</number> Evidence in support of application.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Within two months or within such further period not exceeding one month in the 
aggregate thereafter as the Registrar may on request allow, on the receipt by 
the applicant of the copies of affidavits in support of opposition or of the 
intimation that the opponent does not desire to adduce any evidence in support 
of his opposition, the applicant shall leave with the Registrar such evidence 
by way of affidavit as he desires to adduce in support of his application and 
shall deliver to the opponent copies thereof or shall intimate to the Registrar 
and the opponent that he does not desire to adduce any evidence but intends to 
rely on the facts stated in the counterstatement and or on the evidence already 
left by him in connection with the application in question. In case the 
applicant relies on any evidence already left by him in connection with the 
application, he shall deliver to the opponent copies thereof.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application for the extension of 
the period of one month mentioned in sub-rule (1) shall be made in Form TM-56 
accompanied by the prescribed fee before the expiry of the period of two months 
mentioned therein.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>52</number> Evidence in reply by opponent.—Within 
one month from the receipt by the opponent of the copies of the applicant’s 
affidavit or within such further period not exceeding one month in the 
aggregate thereafter as the Registrar may on request in Form TM-56 allow, the 
opponent may leave with the Registrar evidence by affidavit in reply and shall 
deliver to the applicant copies thereof. This evidence shall be confined to 
matters strictly in reply.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>53</number> Further evidence.—No further 
evidence shall be left on either side, but in any proceedings before the 
Registrar, he may at any time, if he thinks fit, give leave to either the 
applicant or the opponent to leave any evidence upon such terms as to costs or 
otherwise as he may think fit.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>54</number> Exhibits.—Where there are 
exhibits to affidavits filed in an opposition a copy or impression of each 
exhibit shall be sent to the other party on his request and at his expense, or, 
if such copies or impression cannot conveniently be furnished, the original 
shall be left with the Registrar in order that they may be open to inspection. 
The original exhibits shall be produced at the hearing unless the Registrar 
otherwise directs.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>55</number> Translation of documents.—Where 
a document is in a language other than Hindi or English and is referred to in 
the notice of opposition, counterstatement or an affidavit filed in an 
opposition proceeding, an attested translation thereof in Hindi or English 
shall be furnished in duplicate.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>56</number> Hearing and decision.—
<section><number>1</number> Upon 
completion of the evidence if any, the Registrar shall give notice to the 
parties of the first date of hearing. Such notice shall be ordinarily given 
within three months of completion of the evidence. The date of hearing shall be 
for a date at least one month after the date of the first notice. Within 
fourteen days from the receipt of the first notice, any party who intends to 
appear shall so notify the Registrar in Form TM-7. Any party who does not so 
notify the Registrar within the time as aforesaid may be treated as not 
desiring to be heard and the Registrar may act accordingly in the matter.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If sufficient cause for adjournment is 
not shown by either of the parties the Registrar may proceed with the matter 
forthwith.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the applicant is not present at the 
adjourned date of hearing and has not notified his intention to attend the 
hearing  in Form TM-7, the application may be treated as abandoned.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the opponent is not present at the 
adjourned date of hearing and has not notified his intention to attend the 
hearing in Form TM-7, the opposition may be dismissed for want of prosecution 
and the application may proceed to registration subject to section 19.
 </section><section><number>5</number> In every case of adjournment the 
Registrar shall fix a day for further hearing of the case and shall make such 
order as to cost occasioned by the adjournment or such higher costs as the 
Registrar deems fit.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The fact that the agent or advocate on 
record of a party is engaged in another court shall not be a ground for 
adjournment.
 </section><section><number>7</number> Where illness of legal practitioner or 
an agent or his inability to conduct the case for any reason is put forward as 
a ground for adjournment, the Registrar may refuse to grant the adjournment 
unless he is satisfied that the legal practitioner or an agent, as the case may 
be, could not have engaged another agent or legal practitioner in time.
 </section><section><number>8</number> The Registrar shall take on record 
written arguments if submitted by a party to the proceeding.
 </section><section><number>9</number> The decision of the Registrar shall be 
notified to the parties in writing.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>57</number> Security for costs.—The 
security for costs which the Registrar may require under sub-section (6) of 
section 21 may be fixed at any amount which he may consider proper, and such 
amount may be further enhanced by him at any stage in the opposition 
proceedings.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>58</number> Procedure for giving notice.—The 
notice which the Registrar is required by sub-section (3) of section 23 to give 
to an applicant, shall be sent in Form O-1 to the applicant at the address of 
his principal place of business in India or if he has no principal place of 
business in India at the address for service in India stated in the application 
but if the applicant has authorised an agent for the purpose of the 
application, the notice shall be sent to the agent and a duplicate thereof to 
the applicant. The notice shall specify twenty-one days time from the date 
thereof or such further time not exceeding one month as the Registrar may allow 
on a request made in Form TM-56 for completion of the registration.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>59</number> Entry in the Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where no notice of opposition to an application advertised or re-advertised in 
the Journal is filed within the period specified in sub-section (1) of section 
21, or where an opposition is filed and it is dismissed, the Registrar shall, 
subject to the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 23 or section 19, enter 
the trade mark on the register. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The entry of a trade mark in the 
register shall specify the date of filing of application, the actual date of 
the registration, the goods or services and the class or classes in respect of 
which it is registered, and all particulars required by sub-section (1) of 
section 6 including—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the address of the 
principal place of business in India, if any, of the proprietor of the trade 
mark or in the case of a jointly owned trade mark, of such of the joint 
proprietors of the trade mark as have a principal place of business in India;

 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  where the 
proprietor of the trade mark has no place of business in India, his address for 
service in India as entered in the application for registration together with 
his address in his home country;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  in the case of a 
jointly owned trade mark, where none of the joint proprietors has a principal 
place of business in India, the address for service in India as given in the 
application together with the address of each of the joint proprietors in his 
home country;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  particulars of the 
trade, business, profession, occupation or other description of the proprietor 
or, in the case of a jointly owned trade mark, of the joint proprietors of the 
trade mark as entered in the application for registration;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  particulars 
affecting the scope of the registration or the rights conferred by the 
registration;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>f</number>  the convention 
application date (if any), to be accorded pursuant to an application from 
applicants of a convention country made under section 154;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  where the mark is 
a collective or certification mark, that fact;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  where the mark is 
registered pursuant to sub-section (4) of section 11 with the consent of the 
proprietor of an earlier trade mark or other earlier right, that fact; and
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  the appropriate office of the Trade Marks 
Registry in relation to the trade mark.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar may from time to time, 
in consultation with computer experts, formulate guidelines for keeping 
official records in electronic forms.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>60</number> Associated marks.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a 
trade mark is registered as associated with any other marks, the Registrar 
shall note in the register in connection with the first mentioned mark the 
registration numbers of the marks with which it is associated and shall also 
note in the register in connection with each of the associated marks the 
registration number of the first mentioned mark as being a mark associated 
therewith.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application under sub-section (5) 
of section 16 to dissolve the association as respects any of the trade marks 
registered as associated trade marks shall be made in Form TM-14 and shall 
include statement of the grounds of the application.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>61</number> Death of applicant before 
registration.—In case of death of any applicant for the registration of a 
trade mark after the date of his application and before the trade mark has been 
entered in the register, the Registrar may, on proof of the applicant’s death 
and on proof of the transmission of the interest of the deceased person, 
substitute in the application his successor in interest in place of the name of 
such deceased applicant and the application may proceed thereafter as so 
amended.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>62</number> Certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The certificate of registration of a trade mark to be issued by the Registrar 
under sub-section (2) of section 23 shall be in Form O-2, with such 
modification as the circumstances of any case may require, and the Registrar 
shall annex a copy of the trade mark to the certificate.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The certificate of registration 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall not be used in legal proceedings or for 
obtaining registration abroad.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar may issue a duplicate or 
further copies of the certificate of registration on request by the registered 
proprietor in Form TM-59 accompanied by the prescribed fee. An unmounted 
representation of the mark exactly as shown in the form of application for 
registration thereof at the time of registration shall accompany such request.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>63</number> Renewal of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
application for the renewal of the registration of a trade mark shall be made 
in Form TM-12 and may be made at any time not more than six months before the 
expiration of the last registration of the trade mark.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Such application for renewal may be 
filed by the person who is the proprietor of the registered trade mark or his 
agent.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the proprietor, as set forth in the 
application for renewal is not the same person or the same legal entity as the 
registered proprietor, continuity of title from the registered proprietor in 
whose name the last renewal was effected to the present owner shall be shown in 
the first instance by way of affidavit along with supporting chain of 
documents.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Registrar may accept an 
application for renewal from the managing trustee, executors, administrators 
and the like, when supported by court order or other evidence of authority to 
act on behalf of the present proprietor.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>64</number> Notice before removal of trade mark 
from register.—
<section><number>1</number> At a date not less than one month and not more than 
three months before the expiration of the last registration of a trade mark, if 
no application in Form TM-12 for renewal of the registration together with the 
prescribed fee has been received, the Registrar shall notify the registered 
proprietor or in the case of a jointly registered trade mark each of the joint 
registered proprietors and each registered user, if any, in writing in Form O-3 
of the approaching expiration at the address of their respective principal 
places of business in India as entered in the register or where such registered 
proprietor or registered user has no principal place of business in India at 
his address for service in India entered in the Register.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where, in the case of a mark the 
registration of which (by reference to the date of application for 
registration) becomes due for renewal, the mark is registered at any time 
within six months before the date on which renewal is due, the registration may 
be renewed by the payment of the renewal fee within six months after the actual 
date of registration and where the renewal fee is not paid within that period 
the Registrar shall subject to rule 66, remove the mark from the register.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where, in the case of a mark the 
registration of which (by reference to the date of application for 
registration) becomes due for renewal, the mark is registered after the date of 
renewal, the registration may be renewed by the payment of the renewal fee 
within six months of the actual date of registration and where the renewal fee 
is not paid within that period the Registrar shall, subject to rule 66, remove 
the mark from the register.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The renewal of registration of a 
collective mark or a certification trade mark shall be made in Form TM-12 along 
with the prescribed fee specified in the First Schedule.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>65</number> Advertisement of removal of trade 
mark from the register.—If, at the expiration of last registration of a 
trade mark, the renewal fees has not been paid, the Registrar may remove the 
trade mark from the register and advertise the fact forthwith in the Journal:
 Provided that the Registrar shall not 
remove the trade mark from the register if an application for payment of 
surcharge is made under proviso to sub-section (3) of section 25 in Form TM-10 
within six months from the expiration of the last registration of the trade 
mark.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>66</number> Restoration and renewal of 
registration.—An application for the restoration of a trade mark to the 
register and renewal of its registration under sub-section (4) of section 25, 
shall be made in Form TM-13 after six months and within one year from the 
expiration of the last registration of the trade mark accompanied by the 
prescribed fee. The Registrar shall, while considering the request for such 
restoration and renewal have regard to the interest of other affected persons.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>67</number> Notice and advertisement of renewal 
and restoration.—Upon the renewal or restoration and renewal of 
registration, a notice to that effect shall be sent to the registered 
proprietor and every registered user and the renewal or restoration and renewal 
shall be advertised in the Journal.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>68</number> Application for entry of assignment 
or transmission.—An application to register the title of a person who 
becomes entitled by assignment or transmission to a registered trade mark shall 
be made in Form TM-24 or TM-23 according as it is made by such person alone or 
conjointly with the registered proprietor.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>69</number> Particulars to be stated in 
application.—An application under rule 68 shall contain full particulars of 
the instrument, if any, under which the applicant, or, in the case of a joint 
application, the person other than the registered proprietor claims to be 
entitled to the trade mark and such instrument or a duly certified copy thereof 
shall be produced at the Trade Marks Registry for inspection at the time of 
application. The Registrar may require and retain an attested copy of any 
instrument produced for inspection in proof of title.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>70</number> Case accompanying application.—Where 
a person applying under rule 68 for registration of his title, does not 
establish his claim under any document or instrument which is capable in itself 
of furnishing proof of his title, he shall, unless the Registrar otherwise 
directs, either upon or with the application, state a case setting forth the 
full particulars of the facts upon which his claim to be proprietor of the 
trade mark is based, and showing that the mark has been assigned or transmitted 
to him. If the Registrar so requires, the case shall be verified by an 
affidavit in Form TM-18. 
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>71</number> Proof of title.—The Registrar 
may call upon any person who applies to be registered as proprietor of a 
registered trade mark to furnish such proof or additional proof of title as he 
may require for his satisfaction.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>72</number> Impounding of Instruments.—If 
in the opinion of the Registrar any instrument produced in proof of title of a 
person is not properly or sufficiently stamped, the Registrar shall impound and 
deal with it in the manner provided by Chapter IV of the Indian Stamp Act, 1899 
(2 of 1899).
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>73</number> Assignments involving transmission 
of moneys outside India.—If there is in force any law regulating the 
transmission of moneys outside India, the Registrar shall not register the 
title of a person who becomes entitled to a trade mark by an assignment which 
involves such transmission except on production of the permission of the 
authority specified in such law for such transmission.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>74</number> Application for Registrar’s 
direction as to advertisement of an assignment of a trade mark without goodwill 
of the business.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for directions under section 42 shall 
be made in Form TM-20 and shall state the date on which the assignment was 
made. The application shall give particulars of the registration in the case of 
a registered trade mark, and in the case of an unregistered mark shall show the 
mark and give particulars including user of the unregistered trade mark that 
has been assigned therewith. The Registrar may call for any evidence or further 
information and if he is satisfied with regard to the various matters he shall 
issue directions in writing with respect to the advertisement of the 
assignment.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar may refuse to consider 
such an application in a case to which section 41 applies, unless his approval 
has been obtained under the said section and a reference identifying the 
Registrar’s notification of approval is included in the application.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A request for an extension of the 
period within which the application mentioned in sub-rule (1) may be made shall 
be made in Form TM-21.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>74</number> Application for Registrar’s 
direction as to advertisement of an assignment of a trade mark without goodwill 
of the business.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for directions under section 42 shall 
be made in Form TM-20 and shall state the date on which the assignment was 
made. The application shall give particulars of the registration in the case of 
a registered trade mark, and in the case of an unregistered mark shall show the 
mark and give particulars including user of the unregistered trade mark that 
has been assigned therewith. The Registrar may call for any evidence or further 
information and if he is satisfied with regard to the various matters he shall 
issue directions in writing with respect to the advertisement of the 
assignment.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar may refuse to consider 
such an application in a case to which section 41 applies, unless his approval 
has been obtained under the said section and a reference identifying the 
Registrar’s notification of approval is included in the application.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A request for an extension of the 
period within which the application mentioned in sub-rule (1) may be made shall 
be made in Form TM-21.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>75</number> Application for entry of assignment 
without goodwill.—An application under rule 68 relating to an assignment of 
a trade mark in respect of any goods or services shall state—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  whether the trade mark had been or was used in 
the business in any of those goods or services, and 
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  whether the assignment was made otherwise than 
in connection with the goodwill of that business, 
 and if both those 
circumstances subsisted, then the applicant shall leave at the Trade Marks 
Registry a copy of the directions to advertise the assignment, obtained upon 
application under rule 74, and such proof, including copies of advertisements 
or otherwise, as the Registrar may require, to show that his directions have 
been fulfilled and if the Registrar is not satisfied that the directions have 
been fulfilled, he shall not proceed with the application.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>76</number> Separate registration.—Where 
pursuant to an application under rule 68, and as the result of a division and 
separation of the goods or services of a registration or a division and 
separation of places or markets, different persons become registered separately 
under the same registration number as subsequent proprietors of a trade mark, 
each of the resulting separate registrations in the names of those different 
persons shall be deemed to be a separate registration for all the purposes of 
the Act.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>77</number> Registrar’s certificate or approval 
as to certain assignment and transmissions.—Any person who desires to 
obtain the Registrar’s certificate under sub-section (2) of section 40 or his 
notification of approval under section 41 shall send to the Registrar with his 
application in Form TM-17 or Form TM-19, as the case may be, a statement of 
case in duplicate setting out the circumstances and a copy of any instrument or 
proposed instrument effecting the assignment or transmission. The Registrar may 
call for any evidence or further information that he may consider necessary and 
the statement of case shall be amended if required to include all the relevant 
circumstances and shall, if required, be verified by an affidavit. The 
Registrar, after hearing (if so required) the applicant and any other person 
whom the Registrar may consider to be interested in the transfer, shall 
consider the matter and issue a certificate thereon or a notification in 
writing of approval or disapproval thereof, as the case may be, to the 
applicant and shall also inform such other person accordingly. Where a 
statement of case is amended, three copies thereof in its final form shall be 
left at the Trade Marks Registry. The Registrar shall seal a copy of the 
statement of case in its final form to the certificate or notification.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>77</number> Registrar’s certificate or approval 
as to certain assignment and transmissions.—Any person who desires to 
obtain the Registrar’s certificate under sub-section (2) of section 40 or his 
notification of approval under section 41 shall send to the Registrar with his 
application in Form TM-17 or Form TM-19, as the case may be, a statement of 
case in duplicate setting out the circumstances and a copy of any instrument or 
proposed instrument effecting the assignment or transmission. The Registrar may 
call for any evidence or further information that he may consider necessary and 
the statement of case shall be amended if required to include all the relevant 
circumstances and shall, if required, be verified by an affidavit. The 
Registrar, after hearing (if so required) the applicant and any other person 
whom the Registrar may consider to be interested in the transfer, shall 
consider the matter and issue a certificate thereon or a notification in 
writing of approval or disapproval thereof, as the case may be, to the 
applicant and shall also inform such other person accordingly. Where a 
statement of case is amended, three copies thereof in its final form shall be 
left at the Trade Marks Registry. The Registrar shall seal a copy of the 
statement of case in its final form to the certificate or notification.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>78</number> Entry in register, of particulars 
of assignment.—Where the Registrar has allowed the assignment of a trade 
mark under this Act, there shall be entered in the register the following 
particulars of assignment, namely:—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  the name and 
address of the assignee;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  the date of the 
assignment;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  where the 
assignment is in respect of any right in the mark, a description of the right 
assigned;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>  the basis under 
which the assignment is made; and
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  the date on which the entry is made in the 
register.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>79</number> Registration of assignment to a 
company under section 46.—For the purposes of sub-section (4) of section 
46, the period within which a company may be registered as the subsequent 
proprietor of a registered trade mark upon application made under rule 68 shall 
be six months from the date of advertisement in the Journal of the registration 
of the trade mark or such further period not exceeding six months as the 
Registrar may allow on application being made in Form TM-25 by the applicant 
for registration of title or the registered proprietor, as the case may be, at 
any time before or during the period for which the extension can be allowed.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>80</number> 
Application for registration as registered user.—
<section><number>1</number> An application to the 
Registrar for the registration under section 49, of a person as a registered 
user of a registered trade mark, shall be made jointly by that person and the 
registered proprietor of the trade mark, in Form TM-28 and shall be accompanied 
by the following:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the agreement in 
writing or a duly authenticated copy thereof, entered into between the 
registered proprietor and the proposed registered user with respect to the 
permitted use of the trade mark;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the documents and 
correspondence, if any mentioned in the agreement referred to in-clause (a) 
entered into between the registered proprietor and the proposed registered user 
with respect to the permitted use of the trade mark or duly authenticated 
copies thereof.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> There 
shall be filed along with the application, an affidavit by the registered 
proprietor or by some person authorised, to the satisfaction of the Registrar, 
to act on his behalf testifying to the genuineness of the documents 
accompanying the application and containing:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the particulars 
and statements required by clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 49;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the precise 
relationship between the registered proprietor and the proposed registered 
user, if any for instance, whether their relationship is as principal and 
subsidiary company or whether there is common control between their business;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  a statement as to 
the goods or services in which the registered proprietor is dealing together 
with details as to whether the trade mark which is the subject of the 
application has been used by him in the course of trade before the date of the 
application and if so the amount and duration of such user.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The 
registered proprietor and the proposed registered user shall also produce and 
file such other documents and furnish such other evidence and information as 
may be required in that behalf by the Registrar.
 </section><section><number>4</number> No application shall be entertained 
unless the same has been filed within six months from the date of the agreement 
referred to in clause (a) of sub-rule (1).
 </section><section><number>5</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-rule (1), where more than one 
application for registration as registered user is made by the same registered 
proprietor and the same proposed registered user in respect of trade marks 
covered by the same agreement, the documents mentioned in sub-rule (1) may be 
filed with any one of the applications and a cross reference to such documents 
given in the other application or applications.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>81</number> 
Particulars to be stated in the agreement.—The agreement referred to in 
clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-rule (1) of rule 80 shall—
 </section><section>       <number>a</number>  set out the 
particulars specified in sub-clauses (i) to (iv) of clause (b) of sub-section 
(1) of section 49;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  disclose the terms 
as to royalty and other remuneration payable to the registered proprietor by 
the proposed registered user for the permitted use of the trade mark;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  provide means for 
bringing the permitted use to an end when the relationship between the parties 
or the control by the registered proprietor over the permitted use ceases; and

 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  contain a 
condition that when the registered trade mark is used by the proposed 
registered user in relation to his goods or services, other than goods or 
services for export, the mark shall be so described as clearly to indicate that 
it is being used only by way of permitted use.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>82</number> 
Consideration by the Registrar.—The Registrar under sub-section (2) of 
section 49, shall, if satisfied that the application and the accompanying 
documents comply with the relevant provisions of the Act and the rules, and the 
matters specified in sub-clauses 
<section><number>i</number> to (iv) of clause (b) of sub-section (1) 
of section 49, register the proposed registered user in respect of the goods or 
services as to which he is so satisfied.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>83</number> 
Hearing before refusing an application or to accept it conditionally.— 

<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall give a notice in writing to the applicants where he 
proposes to accept the application subject to any conditions, restrictions or 
limitations. The notice shall state the grounds on which the Registrar proposes 
to issue such orders and shall inform the applicants that they are entitled to 
be heard.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Unless 
within one month from the receipt of the notice mentioned in sub-rule (1) the 
registered proprietor and the proposed registered user apply for a hearing, the 
Registrar may refuse the application or to accept it conditionally, as the case 
may be.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the 
registered proprietor and the proposed registered user apply for a hearing the 
Registrar shall appoint a time for the hearing within two months and shall give 
them not less than a month’s notice of the time so appointed.
 </section><section><number>4</number> After 
hearing the registered proprietor and the proposed registered user, the 
Registrar shall decide whether to accept the application or to refuse it or to 
accept it conditionally.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The 
Registrar shall, communicate in writing his order on the application to the 
applicants and to other registered users of the mark, if any.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>84</number> Entry in the register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Registrar under sub-section (2) of section 49 accepts an application 
for registration as registered user, he shall register the proposed registered 
user as registered user.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The entry 
of a registered user in the register shall state the date on which the 
application for registration of registered user was made, which date shall be 
deemed to be the date of registration as registered user of the person 
mentioned in the entry. The entry shall also state, in addition to the 
particulars and statements mentioned in paragraphs (i) to (iv) of sub-clause 
(b) of clause (1) of section 49, the name, description and principal place of 
business in India of the registered user and if he does not carry on business 
in India his address for service in India.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>85</number> 
Registration not to imply authorisation to transmit money outside India.—The 
registration as registered user of a trade mark, shall not be deemed to imply 
an approval, of the agreement in so far as it relates to the transmission of 
any money, as consideration for the use of the said trade mark, to any place 
outside India.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>86</number> 
Notification of registration as registered user.—A notification in writing 
of the registration of a registered user shall be sent by the Registrar to the 
registered proprietor of the trade mark, to the registered user and to every 
other registered user whose name is entered in relation to the same trade mark 
and shall also be inserted in the Journal within three months of such entry in 
the register.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>87</number> 
Registered proprietor’s application to vary entry.—An application by the 
registered proprietor of a trade mark for the variation of the registration of 
a registered user of that trade mark under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of 
section 50 shall be made in Form TM-29 and shall be accompanied by a statement 
of the grounds on which it is made, and where the registered user in question 
consents, by the written consent of the registered user.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>87</number> 
Registered proprietor’s application to vary entry.—An application by the 
registered proprietor of a trade mark for the variation of the registration of 
a registered user of that trade mark under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (1) of 
section 50 shall be made in Form TM-29 and shall be accompanied by a statement 
of the grounds on which it is made, and where the registered user in question 
consents, by the written consent of the registered user.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>88</number> 
Cancellation of registration of registered user.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for the 
cancellation of the registration of a registered user under sub-clause (b) to 
sub-clause (d) of sub-section (1) of section 50 shall be made in Form TM-30 or 
Form TM-31, as the case may be, and shall be accompanied by a statement of the 
grounds on which it is made.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case 
of the registration of a registered user for a period, in accordance with 
paragraph (iv) of sub-clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 49, the 
Registrar shall cancel the entry of the registered user at the end of that 
period. Where some or all the goods or services are omitted from those in 
respect of which a trade mark is registered, the Registrar shall at the same 
time omit them from those specifications of registered users of the trade mark 
in which they are comprised. The Registrar shall notify every cancellation or 
omission under this sub-rule to the registered users whose permitted use is 
effected thereby and to the registered proprietor of the trade mark.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>89</number> Power 
of the Registrar to call for information with respect to registered user.—The 
Registrar may at any time, by notice in writing, require the registered 
proprietor to furnish him information under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 51 and 
take action in accordance with sub-section (2) of that section.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>90</number> Procedure on application to vary 
entry or cancel registration.—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall notify in writing 
applications under section 50 to the registered proprietor and each registered 
user (not being the applicant in either case) of the trade mark.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person notified under sub-rule (1) 
who intends to intervene in the proceedings, shall within one month of the 
receipt of such notification give notice to the Registrar in Form TM-32 to the 
effect and shall send therewith a statement of the grounds of his intervention. 
The Registrar shall thereupon serve or cause to be served copies of such notice 
and statement on the other parties, namely, the applicant, the registered 
proprietor, the registered user whose registration is the subject-matter of the 
proceeding in question and any other registered user who intervenes.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the case of any application made 
under section 50, the applicant and any person notified under sub-rule (1), may 
within such time or times as the Registrar may appoint, leave evidence in 
support of his case, and the Registrar after giving the parties an opportunity 
of being heard, may accept or refuse the application or accept it subject to 
any conditions, amendments, modifications or limitations he may think right to 
impose and shall inform the parties in writing accordingly.
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the case of an application for 
varying any registration under paragraph (a) of sub-section (1) of section 50 
or cancelling any registration on any of the grounds mentioned in items (i) to 
(iv) of sub-clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 50, the Registrar shall 
consider the application together with any notice in Form TM-32 and statement 
of case filed and shall dispose of the application and also inform the parties 
in writing accordingly.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>91</number> Registered user’s application.—An 
application under sub-section (2) of section 58 shall be made in Form TM-16 or 
Form TM-33 or Form TM-34 or Form TM-50 as may be appropriate by a registered 
user of a trade mark or by such person as may satisfy the Registrar that he is 
entitled to act in the name of a registered user; and the Registrar may require 
such evidence by affidavit or otherwise as he may think fit as to the 
circumstances in which the application is made.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>92</number> Application to rectify or remove a 
trade mark from the register.—An application to the Registrar under section 
47, 57, 68 or 77 for the making, expunging or varying of any entry relating to 
a trade mark or a collective mark or certification trade mark in the register 
shall be made in triplicate in Form TM-26 or Form TM-43, as the case may be, 
and shall be accompanied by statement in triplicate setting out fully the 
nature of the applicant’s interest, the facts upon which he bases his case and 
the relief which he seeks. Where the application is made by a person who is not 
the registered proprietor of the trade mark in question, the application and 
the statement aforesaid shall be left at the Trade Marks Registry triplicate. 
In case there are registered users, such application and statements shall be 
accompanied by as many copies thereof as there are registered users. A copy 
each of the application and statement shall be ordinarily transmitted within 
one month by the Registrar to the registered proprietor and to each of the 
registered user and to any other person who appears from the register to have 
an interest in the trade mark. The application shall be verified in the manner 
prescribed under clause 
<section><number>i</number> of sub-rule (e) of rule 48 for verification of a 
notice of opposition.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>93</number> Further procedure.—Within two 
months from the receipt by a registered proprietor of the copy of the 
application mentioned in rule 92 or within such further period not exceeding 
one month in the aggregate, he shall sent to the Registrar in Form TM-6 a 
counterstatement in triplicate of the grounds on which the application is 
contested and if he does so, the Registrar shall serve a copy of the 
counterstatement on the person making the application within one month of the 
receipt of the same. The provisions of rules 50 to 57 shall thereafter apply 
mutatis mutandis to the further proceedings on the application. The 
Registrar shall not, however, rectify the register or remove the mark from the 
register merely because the registered proprietor has not filed a 
counterstatement unless he is satisfied that the delay in filing the 
counterstatement is wilful and is not justified by the circumstance of the 
case. In any case of doubt any party may apply to the Registrar for directions.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>94</number> Intervention by third parties.—Any 
person, other than the registered proprietor, alleging interest in a registered 
trade mark in respect of which an application is made under rule 92 may apply 
on Form TM-27 for leave to intervene, stating the nature of his interest, and 
the Registrar may refuse or grant such leave after hearing (if so required) the 
parties concerned, upon such conditions and terms including undertakings or 
conditions as to security for cost as he may deem fit to impose.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>95</number> Rectification of the register by 
the Registrar of his own motion.—
<section><number>1</number> The Notice, which the Registrar is 
required to give under sub-section (4) of section 57, shall be sent in writing 
to the registered proprietor, to each registered user, if any, and to any other 
person who appears from the register to have any interest in the trade mark, 
and shall state the grounds on which the Registrar proposes to rectify the 
register and shall also specify the time, not being less than one month from 
the date of such notice, within which an application for a hearing shall be 
made.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Unless within the time specified in 
the notice aforesaid, any person so notified sends to the Registrar a statement 
in writing setting out fully the facts upon which he relies to meet the grounds 
stated in the notice or applies for a hearing, he may be treated as not 
desiring to take part in the proceedings and the Registrar may act accordingly.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the Registrar decides to rectify 
the register he shall communicate his decision in writing to the registered 
proprietor and to each registered user, if any.
  
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>96</number> Alteration of address in register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A registered proprietor or a registered user of a trade mark, the address of 
whose principal place of business in India or whose address in his home 
country, as the case may be, is changed so that the entry in the register is 
rendered incorrect, shall forthwith request the Registrar in Form TM-34 to make 
the appropriate alteration of the address in the register, and the Registrar 
shall alter the register accordingly if he is satisfied in the matter.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A registered proprietor or a 
registered user of a trade mark, whose address for service in India entered in 
the register is changed, whether by discontinuance of the entered address or 
otherwise, so that the entry in the register is rendered incorrect, shall 
forthwith request the Registrar in Form TM-50 to make the appropriate 
alteration of the address in the register, and the Registrar shall alter the 
register accordingly if he is satisfied in the matter.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A registered proprietor or a 
registered user of a trade mark the address of whose principal place of 
business in India or whose address for service in India is altered by a public 
authority, so that the changed address designates the same premises as entered 
in the register, may make the aforesaid request to the Registrar in Form TM-34 
or TM-50 as the case may be, and if he does so he shall leave therewith a 
certificate of the alteration given by the said authority. If the Registrar is 
satisfied as to the facts of the case, he shall alter register accordingly but 
shall not require any fees to be paid on the forms, notwithstanding the 
provisions of sub-rule (2) of rule 11 or sub-rule (2) of rule 12.
 </section><section><number>4</number>(i) Where a registered proprietor makes 
a request under sub-rule (1), (2), or (3), he shall serve a copy of the request 
on the registered user or users, if any, and inform the Registrar accordingly.
 <subsection><number>ii</number> Where the request aforesaid is made 
by a registered user, he shall serve a copy thereof on the registered 
proprietor and every other registered users, if any, and inform the Registrar 
that he had done so.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> In case of the alteration of the 
address of a person entered in the register as the address for service in India 
of more than one registered proprietor or registered user of trade marks, the 
Registrar may, on proof that the said address is the address of the applicant 
and if satisfied that it is just to do so, accept an application from the 
person in Form TM-50 amended so as to suit the case, for the appropriate 
alteration of the entries of his address as the address for service in the 
several registrations, particulars of which shall be given in the Form and may 
alter the entries accordingly.
 </section><section><number>6</number> All applications under this rule in 
Form TM-50 shall be signed by the registered proprietor or the registered user, 
as the case may be, or by an agent expressly authorised by him for the purpose 
of such an application, unless in exceptional circumstances the Registrar 
otherwise allows.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>97</number> Application for correction of 
register.—Where an application has been made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
section 58 for the alteration of the register by correction, change, 
cancellation or striking out of goods or services or for the entry of a 
memorandum, the Registrar may require the applicant to furnish such evidence by 
affidavit or otherwise as he may think fit, as to the circumstances in which 
the application is made. Such application shall be made in Form TM-16, TM-33, 
TM-34, TM-35, TM-36 or TM-50 as may be appropriate and a copy thereof shall be 
served by the applicant on the registered user or users, if any, under the 
registration of the trade mark in question and to any other person who appears 
from the register to have an interest in the trade mark.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>98</number> Alteration of registered trade 
mark.—Where a person applies under section 59 for leave to add to or alter 
his registered trade mark, he shall make the application in writing in Form 
TM-38 and shall furnish five copies of the mark as it will appear when so added 
to or altered. A copy of the application and of the trade mark so amended or 
altered shall be served by the applicant on every registered user, if any.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>99</number> Advertisement before decision and 
opposition etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall consider the application and shall, 
if it appears to him expedient, advertise the application in the Journal before 
deciding it.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Within three months from the date of 
advertisement under sub-rule (1), or within such further period not exceeding 
one month in the aggregate as the Registrar may allow, any person may give 
notice of opposition to the application in Form TM-39 and may also send 
therewith a statement of his objections. The notice and the statement, if any, 
shall be sent in triplicate. In case there are any registered users under the 
registration of the trade mark in question, such notice and statement shall 
also be accompanied by as many copies thereof as there are registered users. A 
copy of each of the notice and statement shall be transmitted forthwith by the 
Registrar to the registered proprietor and each registered user, if any, and 
within two months from the receipt by the registered proprietor of such copies 
he shall sent to the Registrar in Form TM-6 a counterstatement in triplicate of 
the grounds on which the opposition is contested. If the registered proprietor 
sends such a counterstatement, the Registrar shall ordinarily serve a copy 
thereof on the person giving notice of opposition within one month and the 
provisions of rules 50 to 57 shall apply mutatis mutandis to the further 
proceedings on the opposition. The Registrar shall not, however, refuse the 
application merely because the registered proprietor has not filed a 
counterstatement unless he is satisfied that the delay in filing the 
counterstatement is wilful and is not justified by the circumstances of the 
case. In case of any doubt any party may apply to the Registrar for directions.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If there is no opposition, within the 
time specified in sub-rule (2), the Registrar shall, after hearing the 
applicant if he so desires, allow or refuse the application and shall 
communicate his decision in writing to the applicant.
</section></article> 
 The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>100</number> Decision, Advertisement, 
Notification.—If the Registrar decides to allow the application he shall 
alter the mark in the register accordingly and insert in the Journal a 
notification that the mark has been altered. If the application has not been 
advertised under rule 99, he shall also advertise in the Journal the trade marks 
as altered.</article> 
 The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>101</number> Re-classification in respect of 
existing registration.—
<section><number>1</number> On the classification set forth in the Fourth 
Schedule being amended, the registered proprietor of a trade mark may apply to 
the Registrar in Form TM-40 for the conversion of the specification relating to 
his trade mark, so as to bring that specification into conformity with the 
amended classification. The application shall include a request for the like 
conversion of the specification in respect of any registered users under that 
registration, and the registered proprietor shall serve a copy of the 
application on the registered user or users of the trade mark, if 
any.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall, thereupon, notify in 
writing to the registered proprietor and to the registered user or users, if 
any, a proposal showing the form which, in the Registrar’s view, the amendment 
of the register should take in consequence of the proposed conversion. Two or 
more registrations of a trade mark having the same date and in respect of goods 
which fall within the same class under the amended or substituted 
classification, may be amalgamated upon conversion in accordance with this 
rule.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The proposal referred to in sub-rule (2) 
shall be advertised in the Journal.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notice of opposition to such proposal shall 
be given in Form TM-41 in triplicate within three months from the date of the 
advertisement or within such period not exceeding one month in the aggregate and 
shall be accompanied by a statement in triplicate showing how the proposed 
amendment would contravene the provisions of sub-section (1) of section 60. 
Where there are any registered users under the registration of the trade mark in 
question, such notice and statement shall also be accompanied by as many copies 
thereof as there are registered users. The Registrar shall within two months 
send a copy each of the notice and the statement to the registered proprietor 
and to each registered user, if any, and within two months from the receipt by 
him of such copies the registered proprietor may send to the Registrar in Form 
TM-6 a counterstatement in triplicate setting out fully the grounds on which the 
opposition is contested. If the registered proprietor sends such 
counterstatement the Registrar shall serve a copy thereof on the person giving 
notice of opposition within two months and the further procedure for the 
disposal of the opposition shall be regulated by the provisions of rules 50 to 
57 mutatis mutandis. In any case of doubt, any party may apply to the 
Registrar for directions.
 </section><section><number>5</number> If there is no opposition within the time 
specified in sub-rule (4), or in case of opposition if the conversion of the 
specification is allowed, the proposal as allowed shall be advertised in the 
Journal, and all necessary entries shall be made in the register. The date when 
such entries are made in the register shall be recorded therein. Any entry made 
in the register in pursuance of this sub-rule shall not affect the date of the 
renewal of registration under section 25 which shall be determined in the same 
manner as before the allowing of the conversion.</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>101</number> Re-classification in respect of 
existing registration.—
<section><number>1</number> On the classification set forth in the Fourth 
Schedule being amended, the registered proprietor of a trade mark may apply to 
the Registrar in Form TM-40 for the conversion of the specification relating to 
his trade mark, so as to bring that specification into conformity with the 
amended classification. The application shall include a request for the like 
conversion of the specification in respect of any registered users under that 
registration, and the registered proprietor shall serve a copy of the 
application on the registered user or users of the trade mark, if any.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall, thereupon, notify 
in writing to the registered proprietor and to the registered user or users, if 
any, a proposal showing the form which, in the Registrar’s view, the amendment 
of the register should take in consequence of the proposed conversion. Two or 
more registrations of a trade mark having the same date and in respect of goods 
which fall within the same class under the amended or substituted 
classification, may be amalgamated upon conversion in accordance with this 
rule.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The proposal referred to in sub-rule 
(2) shall be advertised in the Journal.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Notice of opposition to such proposal 
shall be given in Form TM-41 in triplicate within three months from the date of 
the advertisement or within such period not exceeding one month in the 
aggregate and shall be accompanied by a statement in triplicate showing how the 
proposed amendment would contravene the provisions of sub-section (1) of 
section 60. Where there are any registered users under the registration of the 
trade mark in question, such notice and statement shall also be accompanied by 
as many copies thereof as there are registered users. The Registrar shall 
within two months send a copy each of the notice and the statement to the 
registered proprietor and to each registered user, if any, and within two 
months from the receipt by him of such copies the registered proprietor may 
send to the Registrar in Form TM-6 a counterstatement in triplicate setting out 
fully the grounds on which the opposition is contested. If the registered 
proprietor sends such counterstatement the Registrar shall serve a copy thereof 
on the person giving notice of opposition within two months and the further 
procedure for the disposal of the opposition shall be regulated by the 
provisions of rules 50 to 57 mutatis mutandis. In any case of doubt, any 
party may apply to the Registrar for directions.
 </section><section><number>5</number> If there is no opposition within the 
time specified in sub-rule (4), or in case of opposition if the conversion of 
the specification is allowed, the proposal as allowed shall be advertised in 
the Journal, and all necessary entries shall be made in the register. The date 
when such entries are made in the register shall be recorded therein. Any entry 
made in the register in pursuance of this sub-rule shall not affect the date of 
the renewal of registration under section 25 which shall be determined in the 
same manner as before the allowing of the conversion.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>102</number> Refusal or invalidation of 
registration of a trade mark conflicting with a geographical indication.—A 
request in Form TM-73 or TM-74 as the case may be, may be made to the Registrar 
for the refusal or invalidation of a registered trade mark by an interested 
party along with a statement of case together with an affidavit and which—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  contains or consists of a geographical 
indication with respect to goods or class or classes of goods not originating  
in the territory of a country, or a region or locality in that territory which 
such geographical indication indicates, if the use of such geographical 
indication in the trade mark for such goods, is of such nature as to confuse or 
mislead the persons as to the true place of origin of such goods or class or 
classes of goods;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  contains or consists of geographical indication 
identifying goods or class or classes of goods notified under sub-section (2) 
of section 22 of the Geographical Indications of Goods (Registration and 
Protection) Act, 1999 (48 of 1999).
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>103</number> Single application under 
sub-section (2) of section 18.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an application for the 
registration of a trade mark for different classes of goods or services is made 
under sub-section (2) of section 18, the specification of goods or services 
contained in it shall set out the classes in consecutive numerical order 
beginning with the lowest number and indicate in each class the goods or 
services appropriate to that class.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the 
specification of goods or services contained in the initial application for 
registration of a trade mark makes a reference to a class or classes in the 
Fourth Schedule in which they do not fall, the Registrar shall require the 
applicant to correct the classification error in Form TM-16.
 </section><section><number>3</number> 
Application filed under sub-section (2) of section 18 when ordered to be 
advertised shall be published in a separate section of the Journal.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The 
Registrar shall issue a single certificate of registration in respect of an 
application made under sub-section (2) of section 18, which has proceeded to 
registration.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>104</number> 
Divisional Application.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an application is made in Form TM-53 
under proviso to section 22 for the division of a single pending application, 
such application shall be divided into two or more separate applications on the 
payment of a divisional fee and such class fees as are appropriate in 
accordance with the division.
 </section><section><number>2</number> At any 
time before registration an applicant may request the Registrar in Form TM-53 
for a division of his initial application for registration into two or more 
separate applications (divisional applications), indicating for each division 
the specification of goods or services. The Registrar shall treat each 
divisional application as a separate application for registration with the same 
filing dates as the initial application.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In the 
case of a request to divide some goods or services, but not all in a class, a 
divisional fee for separate application to be created by division shall be 
paid. Any time limit for any action by the applicant in relation to the initial 
application at the time of division shall be applicable to each new separate 
application created by division irrespective of the date of the division.
 </section><section><number>4</number> If the 
request to divide is not accompanied by necessary fee or is otherwise 
deficient, the Registrar shall notify the applicant of the deficiency. The 
applicant may correct any such deficiency within thirty days. If the applicant 
fails to correct the deficiency within the time provided, the request shall be 
considered as abandoned and the application shall proceeded further without 
regard to the request. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Where a 
request to divide an application is received, the Registrar shall assign an 
additional separate new serial number or numbers, as the case may be, and it 
shall be cross referenced with the initial application. Such additional 
separate application or applications shall be assigned same filing date as the 
initial application. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> For the removal of doubt, it is 
clarified that no new registration is effected when a single application is 
divided. On the contrary, application already filed are merely separated or 
divided into individual files.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>105</number> 
Extension of time.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for extension of time under section 
131 (not being a time expressly provided in the Act or prescribed by rule 79 or 
by sub-rule (4) of rule 80 or a time for the extension of which provision is 
made in the rules) shall be made in Form TM-56.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Upon an 
application made under sub-rule (1) the Registrar, if satisfied that the 
circumstances are such as to justify the extension of the time applied for, 
may, subject to the provisions of the rules where a maximum time limit is 
prescribed and subject to such conditions as he may think fit to impose, extend 
the time and notify the parties accordingly and the extension may be granted 
though the time for doing the act or taking the proceeding for which it is 
applied for has already expired.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>106</number> 
Exercise of discretionary power of Registrar.—The time within which a 
person entitled under section 128 to an opportunity of being heard shall, 
exercise his option of requiring to be heard, shall, save as otherwise 
expressly provided in the Act or the rules, be one month from the date of a 
notice which the Registrar shall give to such person before determining the 
matter with reference to which such person is entitled to be heard. If within 
that month such person is required to be heard, the Registrar shall appoint a 
date for the hearing and shall give 10 days’ notice thereof.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>107</number> 
Notification of decision.—The decision of the Registrar in the exercise of 
any discretionary power given to him by the Act or the rules shall be notified 
to the person affected.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>108</number> 
Amendments and correction of irregularity in procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> Any document or 
drawing or other representation of a trade mark may be amended, and any 
irregularity in procedure which, in the opinion of the Registrar, may be 
obviated without detriment to the interests of any person, may be corrected, if 
the Registrar thinks fit and on such terms as he may direct.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The 
Registrar may require the amendment of any application or representation of a 
trade mark or any other document or the addition of any matter thereto in order 
to bring it in accordance with the formal requirements of the Act.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>109</number> 
Directions not otherwise prescribed.—Where in the opinion of the Registrar, 
it is necessary for the proper prosecution or completion of any proceedings 
under the Act or rules for a person to perform an act, file a document or 
produce evidence, which is not provided for by the Act or the rules, the 
Registrar may by notice in writing require the person to perform the Act, file 
the document or produce the evidence, specified in the notice.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>110</number> 
Opinion of the Registrar under section 115(4).—
<section><number>1</number> Where a matter has been 
referred to the Registrar for his opinion under proviso to sub-section (4) of 
section 115 such opinion shall be forwarded under a sealed cover within seven 
working days of the receipt of such written intimation to the referring 
authority and the Registrar shall ensure complete confidentiality in the matter 
so referred.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The opinion under this rule shall be 
given by the Registrar or an officer specially authorised for this purpose 
under sub-section (2) of section 3 and the name of the designated officer shall 
be published in the journal.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>111</number> Hearings.—
<section><number>1</number> In relation to a 
trade mark for which an application for registration is made on or after the 
notified date, the application as well as any proceeding under the Act and the 
rules shall, in the event of a hearing becoming necessary, be heard at the 
office of the Trade Marks Registry at which such application was made under 
sub-section (3) of section 18, or at such place within the territorial 
jurisdiction of that office as the Registrar may deem proper.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In relation to a trade mark for which 
an application for registration is pending before the Registrar, at the 
notified date, hearing, if any, in respect of such application or any 
proceeding under the Act and the rules shall be taken at the appropriate office 
of the Trade Marks Registry or at such place within the territorial 
jurisdiction of that office as the Registrar may deem proper.
 </section><section><number>3</number> In relation to a trade mark on the 
register of trade marks at the notified date, the hearing, if any, in respect 
of any proceeding under the Act and the rules shall take place at the 
appropriate office of the Trade Marks Registry or at such place within the 
territorial jurisdiction of that office as the Registrar may deem proper.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Where an officer exercising the powers 
of the Registrar who has heard any matter under the Act or the rules, has 
reserved orders therein, is transferred from one office of the Registry to 
another or reverts to another appointment before passing an order or rendering 
decision therein, he may, if the Registrar so directs, pass the order or render 
the decision as if he had continued to be the officer in the office of the 
Trade Marks Registry where the matter was heard.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>112</number> Costs in uncontested cases.—Where 
any opposition duly instituted under the rules is not contested by the 
applicant, the Registrar in deciding whether costs should be awarded to the 
opponent shall consider whether the proceedings might have been avoided if 
reasonable notice had been given by the opponent to the applicant before the 
notice of opposition was filed.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>113</number> Exception to rule 112.—Notwithstanding 
anything in rule 112, costs in respect of fees specified under entries, 12, 14 
and 15 of the First Schedule and of all stamps used on and affixed to 
affidavits used in the proceedings shall follow the event.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>114</number> Scale of costs.—Subject to the 
provisions of rules 112 and 113, in all proceedings before the Registrar, he 
may, save as otherwise expressly provided by the Act, award such costs, not 
exceeding the amount admissible thereof under the Sixth Schedule, as he 
considers reasonable having regard to all the circumstances of the case.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>115</number> Application for review of 
Registrar’s decision.—An application to the Registrar for the review of his 
decision under sub-section (c) of section 127 shall be made in Form TM-57 
within one month from the date of such decision or within such further period 
not exceeding one month thereafter as the Registrar may on request allow, and 
shall be accompanied by a statement setting forth the grounds on which the 
review is sought. Where the decision in question concerns any other person in 
addition to the applicant, such application and statement shall be left in 
triplicate and the Registrar shall forthwith transmit a copy each of the 
application and statement to the other person concerned. The Registrar may, 
after giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, reject or grant the 
application, either unconditionally or subject to any conditions or 
limitations, as he thinks fit.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>115</number> Application for review of 
Registrar’s decision.—An application to the Registrar for the review of his 
decision under sub-section (c) of section 127 shall be made in Form TM-57 
within one month from the date of such decision or within such further period 
not exceeding one month thereafter as the Registrar may on request allow, and 
shall be accompanied by a statement setting forth the grounds on which the 
review is sought. Where the decision in question concerns any other person in 
addition to the applicant, such application and statement shall be left in 
triplicate and the Registrar shall forthwith transmit a copy each of the 
application and statement to the other person concerned. The Registrar may, 
after giving the parties an opportunity of being heard, reject or grant the 
application, either unconditionally or subject to any conditions or 
limitations, as he thinks fit.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>116</number> Form, etc., of Affidavits.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Affidavits required by the Act and the rules to be filed at the Trade Marks 
Registry or furnished to the Registrar, unless otherwise provided in the Second 
Schedule, shall be headed in the matter or matters to which they relate, shall 
be drawn up in the first person, and shall be divided into paragraphs 
consecutively numbered; and each paragraph shall, as far as practicable, be 
confined to one subject. Every affidavit shall state the description and the 
true place of abode of the person making the same shall bear the name and 
address of the person filing it and shall state on whose behalf it is filed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where two or more persons join in an 
affidavit, each of them shall depose separately to such facts which are within 
his personal knowledge and those facts shall be stated in separate paragraphs.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Affidavits shall be taken—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  in India, before any court or person having by 
law authority to receive evidence, or before any officer empowered by such 
court as aforesaid to administer oaths or to take affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  in any country or place outside India, before a 
diplomatic or consular officer, within the meaning of the Diplomatic and 
Consular Officers (Oaths and Fee) Act, 1948, of such country or place, or 
before a notary public, or before a Judge or Magistrate, of the country or 
place.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> The person before whom an affidavit is 
taken shall state the date on which and the place where the same is taken and 
shall affix his seal, if any, or the seal of the court to which he is attached, 
thereto and sign his name and description at the end thereof.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any affidavit purporting to have 
affixed, impressed or subscribed thereto or thereon the seal or signature of 
any person authorised by sub-rule (3) to take an affidavit, in testimony of the 
affidavit having been taken before him, may be admitted by the Registrar 
without proof of the genuineness of the seal or signature or of the official 
character of that person.
 </section><section><number>6</number> Alterations and interlineations shall, 
before an affidavit is sworn or affirmed, be authenticated by the initials of 
the person before whom the affidavit is taken.
 </section><section><number>7</number> Where the deponent is illiterate, 
blind or unacquainted with the language in which the affidavit is written, a 
certificate by the person taking the affidavit that the affidavit was read, 
translated or explained in his presence to the deponent that the deponent 
seemed perfectly to understand it and that the deponent made his signature or 
mark in his presence, shall appear in the jurat.
 </section><section><number>8</number> Every affidavit filed before the 
Registrar in connection with any of the proceedings under the Act or the rules 
shall be duly stamped under the law for the time being in force.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>117</number> Inspection of documents.—The 
documents mentioned in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 148 shall be available for 
inspection at the head office of the Trade Marks Registry. A copy of the 
register and such of the other documents mentioned in section 148, as the 
Central Government may by notification in the Official Gazette direct, shall be 
available for inspection at each branch office of the Trade Marks Registry. The 
inspection shall be on payment of the prescribed fee and at such times on all 
the days on which the offices of the Trade Marks Registry are not closed to the 
public, as may be fixed by the Registrar.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>118</number> Distribution of copies of Journal 
and other documents.—The Central Government may direct the Registrar to 
distribute the Journal and any other document which it may consider necessary, 
to such places as may be fixed by the Central Government in consultation with 
the State Governments and notified from time to time in the Official Gazette.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>119</number> Certified copies of documents.—The 
Registrar may furnish certified copies of any entry in the register or 
certified copies of any documents referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 148 
or of any decision or order of the Registrar, or give a certificate other than 
a certificate under sub-section (2) of section 23 as to any entry, matter or 
thing which he is authorised or required by the Act or the rules to make or do, 
upon receipt from any person of an application therefore in Form TM-46 
accompanied by the prescribed fee. The Registrar shall not be obliged to 
include in any certificate or certified copy, a copy of any mark unless he is 
furnished by the applicant with a copy thereof suitable for the purpose:
 Provided that the Registrar may furnish an 
expedited certified copies of the documents aforementioned within thirty 
working days on a request in Form TM-70 received to that effect on payment of 
five times the ordinary fee for such request.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>120</number> Certificate for use in obtaining 
registration abroad.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a certificate relating to the registration 
of a trade mark is desired for use in obtaining registration in any territory 
outside India, the Registrar shall include in the certificate a copy of the 
mark and may require the applicant for the certificate to furnish him with a 
copy of the mark suitable for that purpose, and if the applicant fails to do 
so, the Registrar may refuse to issue the certificate.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a trade mark is registered 
without limitation of colour, the copy of the mark to be included in the 
certificate, may be either in the colour in which it appears upon the register 
or in any other colour or colours and it shall be stated in the certificate 
that the trade mark is registered without limitation of colour.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar may state in the 
certificate such particulars concerning the registration of the mark as may 
deem fit to him, and may specify the terms and conditions and other limitation 
appearing on the Register. The purpose for which the certificate is issued 
shall be stated therein.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>121</number> Power of Registrar to notify 
International Non-proprietary names.—The Registrar may from time to time 
may publish in the Journal, the words which are declared by the World Health 
Organisation as international non-proprietary names referred to in sub-section 
(b) of section 13.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>122</number> Time for appeal.—An appeal to 
the Intellectual Property Appellate Board from any decision of the Registrar 
under the Act or the rules shall be made within three months from the date of 
such decision.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>123</number> Service to the Registrar.—A 
copy of every application to Intellectual Property Appellate Board under the 
Act shall be served on the Registrar.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>124</number> Certificate of validity to be 
noted.—Where the Intellectual Property Appellate Board has certified as 
provided in section 141 with regard to the validity of a registered trade mark 
the registered proprietor thereof may request the Registrar in Form TM-47 to 
add to the entry in the register a note that the certificate of validity has 
been granted in the course of the proceedings, particulars of which shall be 
given in the request. An officially certified copy of the certificate shall be 
sent with the request, and the Registrar shall record a note to that effect in 
the register and publish the note in the Journal.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>125</number> Return of exhibits.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
the exhibits produced in any matter or proceeding under the Act or the rules 
are no longer required in the Trade Marks Registry, the Registrar may call upon 
the party concerned to take back the exhibits within a time specified by him 
and if the party fails to do so, such exhibits shall be destroyed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where, before the notified date any 
exhibits have been produced in any proceeding, the Registrar may, if satisfied 
that it is no longer necessary to retain them call upon the party concerned to 
take back the exhibits within a time specified by him and if the party fails to 
do so, such exhibit shall be destroyed.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>126</number> Destruction of records.—Where 
an application for the registration of a trade mark has been 
withdrawn/abandoned or refused or a trade mark has been removed from the 
register or in an opposition or rectification proceeding the matter has been 
concluded and no appeal is pending before the Intellectual Property Appellate 
Board, the Registrar may, at the expiration of three years after the 
application is withdrawn or is abandoned or is refused or after the trade mark 
is removed from the register or the opposition or rectification proceeding is 
closed, as the case may be, destroy all or any of the records relating to the 
application, opposition or rectification or the trade mark concerned.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>127</number> Rules to apply to collective 
marks.—The provisions of Part I, Part IV, and VII of the rules shall, in 
their application to collective marks, apply only subject to the provisions of 
this Part.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>128</number> Application for registration and 
proceedings relating thereto.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for the registration of a 
collective mark for goods or services under sub-section (1) of section 63 shall 
be made to the Registrar in Form TM-3, Form TM-64 or in the case of a single 
application Form TM-66 or Form TM-67 as the case may be, in triplicate and 
shall be accompained by five additional representations of the mark. The draft 
regulations to be submitted with the application under sub-section (1) of 
section 63 shall be in triplicate and shall be accompanied by Form TM-49.
 </section><section><number>2</number> References in Part I of the rules to 
the acceptance of an application for the registration of a trade mark for goods 
or services, shall, in their application to collective mark, be substituted by 
references to authorisation to proceed with the application.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An applicant for the registration of a 
collective mark shall not be deemed to have abandoned his application, if in 
the circumstances of sub-rule (5) of rule 38 he does not apply for a hearing or 
reply in writing.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The address in India, if any, of an 
applicant to register a collective mark shall be deemed to be the address of 
his principal place of business in India for all the purposes for which such an 
address is required by the rules.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The regulations governing collective 
marks shall specify inter alia—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the name of the association of persons and 
their respective office addresses;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the object of the association;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the details of members;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the conditions for membership and relation of 
each member with the group;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the persons authorised to use the mark and the 
nature of control the applicant exercise over the use of the collective mark;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  the conditions governing use of the collective 
mark, including sanctions;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  the procedure for dealing with appeals against 
the use of the collective mark;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  such other relevant particulars as may be 
called for by the Registrar.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>129</number> Case accompanying application.—The 
applicant shall submit to the Registrar along with his application a statement 
of case setting out the grounds on which he relies in support of his 
application. Such case shall be furnished in triplicate.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>130</number> Examination and Hearing.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar shall cause an application for the registration of a collective 
mark to be examined, in the first instance, as to whether it satisfies the 
requirement of the Act and the rules and issue a report to the applicant.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall not refuse an 
application for the registration of a collective mark or accept the application 
subject to any conditions or limitations or impose amendments or modifications 
to the application or to the regulation without giving the applicant an 
opportunity of being heard and the procedure thereto shall be regulated by the 
provision of sub-rule (4) of rule 38 to rule 42.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>131</number> Opposition to registration of 
collective marks.—
<section><number>1</number> On acceptance of the application the Registrar shall 
cause the application to be advertised in the Journal and the provisions of 
rules 47 to 57 shall apply mutatis mutandis to further proceedings in 
the matter as they in relation to an application for the registration of a 
trade mark. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> In any case of doubt with regard to 
proceedings on the opposition to the registration of a collective mark, any 
party may apply to the Registrar for directions.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>132</number> Amendment of regulations relating 
to collective marks and renewal.—
<section><number>a</number> An application by the registered 
proprietor of a collective mark for any amendment to the regulation under 
section 66 shall be made in Form TM-42 and where the Registrar accepts any such 
amendment he shall advertise, such application in the Journal and further 
proceedings in the matter shall be governed by rules 47 to 57.
 </section><section><number>b</number> A collective mark may be renewed from 
time to time and the provision of rules 63 to 67 shall apply mutatis 
mutandis in respect of such request for renewal.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>133</number> Removal of collective mark.—An 
application for removal of a collective mark from the register including on any 
of the grounds mentioned in section 68 shall be made in Form TM-43 and shall 
set forth particulars of the grounds on which the application is made. The 
provisions of rules 92 to 94 of these rules shall apply mutatis mutandis 
for further proceeding in the matter.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>134</number> Rules to apply to certification 
trade marks.—The provisions of Part I, Part IV and Part VII of the rules 
shall, in their application to certification trade marks, apply only subject to 
the provisions of this Part.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>135</number> Application for registration and 
proceedings relating thereto.—
<section><number>1</number> An application for the registration of a 
certification trade mark under sub-section (1) of section 71 shall be made to 
the Registrar in Form TM-4, Form TM-65 and in the case of a single application 
in Form TM-68 or Form TM-69 as the case may be, in triplicate and shall be 
accompanied by five additional representations of the mark. The draft 
regulations to be submitted with the application shall be in triplicate and 
shall be accompanied by Form TM-49.
 </section><section><number>2</number> References in Part I of the rules to 
the acceptance of an application for the registration of a trade mark, shall, 
in their application to certification trade mark, be substituted by references 
to authorisation to proceed with the application.
 </section><section><number>3</number> An applicant for the registration of a 
certification trade mark shall not be deemed to have abandoned his application, 
if, in the circumstances of sub-rule (5) of rule 38 he does not apply for a 
hearing or reply in writing. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The address in India, if any, of an 
applicant to register a certification trade mark shall be deemed to be the 
address of his principal place of business in India for all the purposes for 
which such an address is required by the rules.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The regulation governing a 
certification trade mark shall specify inter alia:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  a description of the applicant;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the nature of the applicant’s business;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  the particulars of infrastructure like R &amp; D, 
technical manpower support;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  the applicants competence to administer the 
certification scheme;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  the applicants financial arrangement;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  an undertaking from the applicant that there 
will be no discrimination of any party if they meet the requirements set down 
in the regulations;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  the characteristic the mark will indicate in 
the certified goods or in relation to the rendering of certified services;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  the manner of monitoring the use of the mark in 
India; and 
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  such other relevant particulars as may be 
called for by the Registrar.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>136</number> Statement of case accompanying 
application.—
<section><number>1</number> The applicant shall forward a statement of case to the 
Registrar with the application setting out the grounds in which he relies in 
support of the application. Such case shall be furnished in triplicate.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall cause the 
application for the registration of a certificate trade mark to be examined in 
the first instance as to whether it satisfies the requirement of the Act and 
the rules and issue a report to the applicant.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>137</number> Hearing by the Registrar before 
refusing an application or to accept it conditionally.—The Registrar shall 
not refuse an application for registration of a certification trade mark or 
accept the application subject to any conditions or limitations or impose 
amendments or modifications to the application or to the regulations without 
giving to the applicant an opportunity of being heard and the procedure thereto 
shall be regulated by the provisions of sub-rule (4) of rule 38 to rule 42 of 
these rules.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>138</number> Opposition to registration of 
certification trade mark and renewal.—
<section><number>1</number> On acceptance of the application 
the Registrar shall cause the application to be advertised in the Journal and 
the provisions of rules 47 to 57 shall apply mutatis mutandis as they 
apply in relation to an application for the registration of a trade mark.

 </section><section><number>2</number> In case of doubt with regard to the 
proceedings on the opposition to the registration of a certification trade 
mark, any party may apply to the Registrar for directions.
 </section><section><number>3</number> A certification trade mark may be 
renewed from time to time and the provisions of rules 63 to 67 shall apply 
mutatis mutandis in respect of such request for renewal.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>139</number> Rectification of certification 
trade mark.—An application for cancellation or variation of registration of 
a certification trade mark on any of the grounds mentioned in section 77 shall 
be made in Form TM-43 and shall set forth particulars of the grounds on which 
the application is made. The provisions of rules 92 to 94 shall apply 
mutatis mutandis to further proceeding in the matter.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>140</number> Alteration of deposited 
regulations and consent of the Registrar for assignment or transmission of 
certification trade marks.—
<section><number>1</number> An application by the registered proprietor 
of a certification trade mark under sub-section (2) of section 74 to alter the 
deposited regulation shall be made in Form TM-42 and where the Registrar 
decides to permit such alteration it shall be advertised in the Journal and 
further proceeding in the matter shall be governed by rules 47 to 57.
 </section><section><number>2</number> An application for the consent of the 
Registrar to the assignment or transmission of a certification trade mark under 
section 43 shall be made in Form TM-62.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>141</number> Definitions.—For the purposes 
of rules 146 and 147—
 
“balanced numeral” means a trade mark consisting of either 
identical numerals or identical letters of not less than three nor more than 
seven digits;
 “digit” includes a single letter;
 “letter fraction” means a fraction 
containing one or more letters.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>142</number> Rules to apply to textile marks.—Subject 
to the provisions of this Part, the provisions of Part I, Part II, Part III and 
Part VII of the rules shall apply to trade marks in respect of textile goods as 
they apply to trade marks in respect of non-textile goods.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>143</number> Textile Marks.—The expression 
“textile mark” means a trade mark used or proposed to be used in relation to 
goods specified in rule 144 as “textile goods” for the purpose of Chapter X of 
the Act.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>144</number> Textile Goods.—The classes of 
goods in relation to trade marks to which Chapter X of the Act shall apply and 
which are in the Act and the rules referred to as textile goods shall be 
classes 22 to 27 (inclusive) of the Fourth Schedule.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>145</number> Application to register letters or 
numerals or any combination thereof in respect of items of textile goods.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A separate application for the registration of a trade mark (other than a 
collective mark or a certification trade mark) shall be made in Form TM-22 or 
TM-45 as the case may be, in respect of each of the items of textile goods 
mentioned in the Fifth Schedule where the mark consists exclusively of letters 
or numerals or any combination thereof.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The items of the Fifth Schedule shall 
be grouped as follows; and goods falling in each group shall be deemed to be 
similar goods, and goods falling in different groups shall not be deemed to be 
similar goods for the purpose of an application for the registration of trade 
marks consisting exclusively of letters or numerals or any combination thereof 
made under sub-rule (1) and proceedings relating thereto but not for any other 
purpose—
 
Group 1—Items 1, 4, 5, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 16, 19, 20, 22, 
23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 30, 33, 36, 37, 39, 41, 42, 44, 45, 48, 49, 54, 55, 59, 61, 
62, 65 and 91.
 Group 
2—Items 2, 3, 14, 17, 18, 34, 35 and 47.
 Group 
3—Items 6, 7, 21, 38 and 52.
 Group 
4—Items 13, 29, 75, 77 and 78.
 Group 
5—Items 15, 28, 31, 40, 60, 66, 79, 88, 90 and 93.
 Group 
6—Items 32, 43, 64 and 94.
 Group 
7—Items 46, 83 and 85.
 Group 
8—Items 50, 51, 56, 57, 63, 76, 80, 84, 86, 87 and 89.
 Group 9—Item 
53.
 Group 
10—Items 58, 82 and 92
 Group 
11—Items 67, 68, 69, 70 and 71.
 Group 
12—Item 72.
 Group 
13—Item 73.
 Group 
14—Item 74.
 Group 
15—Item 81.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
sub-rule (2) in respect of any proceeding relating to trade marks consisting 
exclusively of letters, numerals or any combination thereof for the 
registration of which applications were made on or before the 31st July, 1945, 
the goods falling in different items of the Fifth Schedule shall not be deemed 
to be goods of the same description.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>146</number> Non-registrability of certain 
marks.—In respect of textile goods the following marks shall not be capable 
of registration, namely:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  any numerals of one digit or of more than six 
digits not being a balanced numerals;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  a single letter or any combination of letters 
of more than six letters, not being a balanced numeral;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  any combination of numerals and letters of more 
than eight digits; 
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  any fraction or letter fraction consisting of 
more than eight digits together;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  any fraction or letter fraction having less 
than three digits together;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  any combination of numerals, and fractions of 
more than six digits;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  any combination of numerals, letters, fractions 
and letter fractions either having more than eight digits or ending with a 
fraction of more than one digit in the numerator or in the denominator;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  numerals or letters representing cloth 
dimensions;
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>  a balanced numeral which does not consist of 
at least two more or two less digits than a balanced numeral of the same series 
already registered in the name of a different person, in respect of the same 
goods or description of goods.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>147</number> Marks likely to deceive or cause 
confusion.—
<section><number>1</number> A trade mark consisting of numerals, letters, fractions, 
letter fractions or any combination thereof, and not being a balanced numeral 
shall not be capable of being registered as a textile mark if it does not 
differ from a trade mark registered in the manner of a different person in 
respect of the same goods or similar goods—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  in the case of a numeral not exceeding four 
digits, in at least one corresponding digit;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  in the case of a numeral of five digits, in at 
least two corresponding digits;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  in the case of a numeral of six digits, in at 
least three corresponding digits;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  in the case of a combination of two letters, in 
at least one corresponding letter;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  in the case of a combination of three or four 
letters, in at least two corresponding letters;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  in the case of a combination of five or six 
letters, in at least three corresponding letters;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>g</number>  in the case of a mark consisting of one letter 
and one numeral digit, in at least one of them;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>h</number>  in the case of a mark consisting of one letter 
and two or three numeral digits, in at least one corresponding numeral digit;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  in the case of a mark consisting of one letter 
and four or more numeral digits, in at least two corresponding digits;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>j</number>  in the case of a mark consisting of two or 
more letters and one or more numeral digits, in at least one corresponding 
letter and one corresponding numeral digit;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number>  in the case of a fraction or letter fraction or 
any combination thereof in which the total number of digits in the numerator 
and denominator is three or four, in at least one corresponding digit from 
either the numerator or the denominator;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>l</number>  in the case of a fraction or letter fraction 
or any combination thereof in which the total number of digits in the numerator 
and denominator is five or more, in at least one corresponding digit in the 
numerator and one corresponding digit in the denominator or two corresponding 
digits in either the numerator or the denominator;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>m</number>  in the case of a combination consisting of a 
numeral and a fraction in at least one corresponding numeral digit;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>n</number>  in the case of a combination of letters, 
numerals and fractions (including letter fractions):
 <subsubsection> <number>i</number>  
where the total number of digits excluding the fraction is not more than three 
in at least one corresponding digit;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            <number>ii</number>  where the total number of digits, 
excluding the fraction, is four or more, in at least two corresponding digits.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Nothing in sub-rule (1) shall be 
construed to signify that where a trade mark does not come within the scope of 
any case specified in the said sub-rule, the mark shall necessarily be 
registered as not being likely to deceive or to cause confusion.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>148</number> Register of trade marks agents.—The 
Registrar of trade marks shall maintain a register of trade marks agents 
wherein shall be entered the name, address of the place of residence, address 
of the principal place of business, the nationality, qualifications and date of 
registration of every registered trade marks agent.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>149</number> Registration of existing 
registered trade marks agents, code of conduct etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
anything in rule 150, every person whose name has been entered in the register 
of trade marks agents maintained under the old law shall be deemed to be 
registered as a trade marks agent under these rules.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar may publish in the 
Journal a code of conduct for registered trade marks agent authorising them to 
act as such.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>150</number> Qualifications for registration.—Subject 
to the provisions of rule 151, a person shall be qualified to be registered as 
a trade marks agent if he—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  is a citizen of India;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  is not less than 21 years of age;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  has passed the examination prescribed in rule 
154 or is an Advocate within the meaning of the Advocates Act, 1961 (25 of 
1961) or is a Member of the Institute of Company Secretaries of India;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>  is a graduate of any university in India or 
possess an equivalent qualification; and 
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  is considered by the Registrar as a fit and 
proper person to be registered as a trade mark agent.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>151</number> Person debarred from registration.—A 
person shall not be eligible for registration as a trade marks agent if he—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  has been adjudged by a competent court to be 
of unsound mind;
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  is an undischarged insolvent;
 </section><section>       <number>iii</number>  being a discharged insolvent has not obtained 
from the court a certificate to the effect that his insolvency was caused by 
misfortune without any misconduct on his part;
 </section><section>       <number>iv</number>  has been convicted by a competent court, 
whether within or without India of an offence punishable with transportation or 
imprisonment, unless the offence of which he has been convicted has been 
pardoned or unless on an application made by him, the Central Government by 
order in this behalf, has removed the disability;
 </section><section>       <number>v</number>  being a legal practitioner has been held guilty 
of professional misconduct by any High Court in India or by any court beyond 
the limits of India;
 </section><section>       <number>vi</number>  being a chartered accountant, has been held 
guilty of negligence or misconduct by a High Court; or 
 </section><section>      <number>vii</number>  being a registered trade marks agent has been 
held guilty of professional misconduct by the Registrar.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>152</number> Manner of making application.—All 
applications under the provisions of this Part shall be made in triplicate and 
shall be sent to or left at that office of the Trade Marks Registry within 
whose territorial limits the principal place of business of the applicant is 
situate.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>153</number> Application for registration as a 
trade marks agent.—
<section><number>1</number> Every person desiring to be registered as a trade 
marks agent shall make an application in Form  
TMA-1.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The applicant shall furnish such 
further information bearing on his application as may be required of him at any 
time by the Registrar. 
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>154</number> Procedure on application and 
qualifying requirements.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an application for the 
registration of a person as a trade marks agent, the Registrar, if satisfied 
that the applicant fulfils the prescribed qualifications, shall appoint a date 
in due course on which the candidate will appear before him for a written 
examination in Trade Marks Law and practice followed by an interview. The 
candidate will be expected to possess a detailed knowledge of the provisions of 
the Act and the rules and knowledge of the elements of Trade Marks Law.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The qualifying marks for the written 
examination and for interview shall be forty per cent. and sixty per cent. 
respectively and a candidate shall be declared to have passed the examination 
only if he obtained an aggregate of fifty per cent. of the total marks.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>155</number> Certificate of registration.—After 
a candidate has been interviewed and any further information bearing on his 
application, which the Registrar may consider necessary has been obtained and 
if the Registrar considers the applicant eligible and qualified for 
registration as a trade marks agent, he shall send an intimation to that effect 
to the applicant and any person so intimated may pay the prescribed fee for his 
registration as a trade marks agent. Upon receipt of the prescribed fee the 
Registrar shall cause the applicant’s name to be entered in the register of 
trade marks agents and shall issue to him a certificate in Form O-4 of his 
registration as a trade marks agents.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>156</number> Continuance of a name in the 
register of trade marks agents.—The continuance of a person’s name in the 
Register of Trade Marks Agents shall be subject to his payment of the fees 
prescribed in First Schedule.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>157</number> Removal of agent’s name from the 
register of trade marks agents.— 

<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall remove from the register of trade marks agents the name 
of any registered trade marks agent—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  from whom a request has been received to that 
effect; or 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  from whom the annual fee has not been received 
on the expiry of three months from the date on which it became due.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
register of trade marks agents, the name of any registered trade marks agent—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  who is found to 
have been subject at the time of his registration, or thereafter has become 
subject, to any of the disabilities stated in clauses (i) to (vii) of rule 151; 
or 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  whom the Registrar 
has declared not to be a fit and proper person to remain in the Register by 
reason of any act of negligence, misconduct or dishonesty committed in his 
professional capacity;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  whose name has been entered in the register by 
an error or on account of misrepresentation or suppression of material fact:
 Provided that before making such 
declaration under clauses (b) and (c) the Registrar shall call upon the person 
concerned to show-cause why his registration should not be cancelled and shall 
make such further enquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
register of trade marks agents the name of any registered trade marks agent who 
is dead.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The removal of the name of any person 
from the register of trade marks agents shall be notified in the Journal and 
shall, wherever possible, be communicated to the person concerned.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>157</number> Removal of agent’s name from the 
register of trade marks agents.— 

<section><number>1</number> The Registrar shall remove from the register of trade marks agents the name 
of any registered trade marks agent—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  from whom a request has been received to that 
effect; or 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  from whom the annual fee has not been received 
on the expiry of three months from the date on which it became due.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
register of trade marks agents, the name of any registered trade marks agent—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  who is found to 
have been subject at the time of his registration, or thereafter has become 
subject, to any of the disabilities stated in clauses (i) to (vii) of rule 151; 
or 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  whom the Registrar 
has declared not to be a fit and proper person to remain in the Register by 
reason of any act of negligence, misconduct or dishonesty committed in his 
professional capacity;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  whose name has been entered in the register by 
an error or on account of misrepresentation or suppression of material fact:
 Provided that before making such 
declaration under clauses (b) and (c) the Registrar shall call upon the person 
concerned to show-cause why his registration should not be cancelled and shall 
make such further enquiry, if any, as it may consider necessary.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar shall remove from the 
register of trade marks agents the name of any registered trade marks agent who 
is dead.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The removal of the name of any person 
from the register of trade marks agents shall be notified in the Journal and 
shall, wherever possible, be communicated to the person concerned.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>158</number> Power of Registrar to refuse to 
deal with certain agents.—
<section><number>1</number> The Registrar may refuse to recognise—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  any individual whose name has been removed 
from, and not restored to the register;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  any person, not being registered as a trade 
marks agent, who in the opinion of the Registrar is engaged wholly or mainly in 
acting as agent in applying for trade marks in India or elsewhere in the name 
or for the benefit of the person by whom he is employed; 
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  any company or firm, if any person whom the 
Registrar could refuse to recognise as agent in respect of any business under 
these rules, is acting as a director or manager of the company or is a partner 
in the firm.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Registrar shall also refuse to 
recognise as agent in respect of any business under this rule any person who 
neither resides nor has a place of business in India.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>159</number> Restoration of removed names.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Registrar may, on an application made in Form TMA-2 within six months from 
the date of removal of his name from the Register of trade marks agents 
accompanied by the fee specified in the First Schedule from a person whose name 
has been removed under clause (b) of sub-rule (1) of rule 157, restore his name 
to the register of trade marks agents and continue his name therein for a 
period of one year from the date on which his last annual fee became due.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The restoration of a name to the 
register of trade marks agent shall be notified in the Journal and shall be 
communicated to the person concerned.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>160</number> Alteration in the register of 
trade marks agents.—
<section><number>1</number> A registered trade marks agent may apply in Form 
TMA-3 for alteration of his name, address of the place of residence, address of 
the principal place of business or qualifications entered in the register of 
trade marks agents. On receipt of such application and the fee prescribed in 
that behalf, the Registrar shall cause the necessary alteration to be made in 
the register of trade marks agents.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every alteration made in the register 
of trade marks agents shall be notified in the Journal.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>161</number> Publication of the register of 
trade marks agents.—The Registrar shall ordinarily publish the list of 
agents in the register of trade marks agents shall be published in the Journal 
from time to time, and at least once in two years together with his address as 
entered in the register, the entries being arranged in the alphabetical order 
of the surnames of the registered trade marks agents and copies thereof shall 
be placed for sale.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>162</number> Appeal.—An appeal shall lie to 
Intellectual Property Appellate Board from any order or decision of the 
Registrar in regard to the registration or removal of trade marks agents under 
Part V of these rules, and the decision of the Appellate Board shall be final 
and binding.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>163</number> Definitions.—For the purposes 
of this Part, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “count” in relation to yarn means the relation 
of length to weight thereof either in the English system or Metric system, as 
follows:—
 <subsection>             <number>i</number>  The English count for yarn shall be the 
number of hanks each of 840 yards in length that weight one pound avoirdupois 
or in other words the number of yards of yarn that weight 8.3 grains.
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  The metric count for all yarn with the 
exception of raw and prepared silk shall represent the relation between 1000 
metres of yarn to 500 grammes or 2 metres to 1 grammes or in other words half 
the number of hanks (each of 1,000 metres length) that weight 500 grammes. 
                   The English system of counts may be 
converted into the metric system of counts and vice versa by the 
following formulae:—
                   The English count No. of yarn X 0.847 the 
metric count. The metric count No. of yarn X 1.181 the English count.
 </subsection><subsection>            <number>ii</number>  The metric count for raw and prepared 
silk shall be the weight in grammes of 10,000 metres of yarn.
 </subsection></section><section>       <number>b</number>  “customs collector” shall have the meaning 
assigned to the term in the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962).
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>164</number> Testing for length and width of 
piece-goods.—
<section><number>1</number> In testing for length of piece-goods such as are 
ordinarily sold by the length or by the piece the measurement shall be made 
along the selvage.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In testing piece-goods aforesaid for 
width the cloth shall be measured by each of the following methods and the mean 
of the measurements so taken shall be adopted. Care shall be exercised in 
applying each method to select a portion of the cloth where the creases are 
fewest, and the warp and weft respectively as straight as possible:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  A double-fold of the cloth shall be laid on the 
table and the creases smoothed out, so that it may lie perfectly flat. The 
measuring rod shall then be placed across the cloth, and the finger and thumb 
run down the rod on each side of it across the cloth so as to once more flatten 
the creases. Care shall be taken in doing this to see that whilst the creases 
are smoothed out, stretching is avoided and the warp threads remain 
perpendicular to the rod. The measurement shall then be recorded.
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  A fold of the cloth shall be taken, and the 
doubled edge held between a finger and thumb at each end, and extended over the 
measuring rod which shall be kept flat on the table. The extension shall be 
sufficient to remove the creases but not to stretch the warp out of the 
perpendicular.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>165</number> 
Allowances for peculiarities of cloth and for stretching.—
<section><number>1</number> In taking the 
measurements aforesaid the peculiarities of the cloth under measure shall be 
taken into consideration and due allowances be made for these characteristics.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If owing 
to the peculiarities of the cloth it is found difficult to determine a 
reasonable degree of tension for purposes of measurement, the mean between 
stretching to the full and not stretching, shall be adopted.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The 
influence of stretching for length on the width shall always be taken into 
account in measuring cloth. Where the cloth has been stretched lengthwise in 
the making, it will lose in length as the weft is straightened to measure the 
width. It may then have to be ascertained, whether the trade description of 
length does not become false in the process of making that for width correct. 
To ascertain this a measurement along the selvages both lengthwise and across 
shall be made.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>166</number> 
Testing of yarns.—Yarns may be tested by the customs-collector for length 
and count when he has reason to suspect or on information by any informant that 
the trade description is false.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>167</number> 
Number of samples to be selected.—An examination of yarns to test the 
accuracy of the description of count or length shall be made, in the first 
instance, up to the limit of one bundle in every one hundred bales or fractions 
of one hundred bales in a consignment.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>168</number> 
Further testing.—If, on such examination the difference between the average 
count or length and the described count or length is in excess of the variation 
permitted in the notification to be issued by the Central Government under 
section 121 of the Act, the importer or any other person having any claim to or 
in relation to, goods in question or otherwise interested may apply for a 
further testing.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>169</number> 
Manner of selection and testing of Samples.—The test to determine length of 
yarns shall be as follows:—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  From every one 
hundred bales, or fraction of 100 bales, in a consignment one bundle, shall be 
selected at random. The hanks in this bundle shall then be measured on the warp 
wheel one after the other, in the presence of the importer or any other person 
interested as is referred to in the last foregoing rule, or his representative 
and the length noted, the process being continued (within the limits of the 
bundle) until either the importer or other person, as the case may be, is 
satisfied that the yarn is short or the average of the length noted shows that 
it is of full length.
 </section><section>        <number>ii</number>  When the 
importer or other person is dissatisfied with the test aforesaid he may, on 
payment of the cost, require the customs-collector to measure more hanks up to 
one per cent. of the total number of hanks in the consignment, such hanks being 
taken at random by an officer of the customs out of any bundles in the 
consignment.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>170</number> Stove Test.—
<section><number>1</number> The stove test 
may be applied by the customs officers only in cases where weighment by the 
ordinary methods shows the weight of the yarn to be short or in which the feel 
and appearance of yarn indicate that it is abnormally moist or over-conditioned 
or where the importer demands the test. Where the test is carried out on demand 
by the importer, the fee levied for carrying out the test shall be returned if 
the test fails to support the original determination of count and length by the 
customs officers. If more than one application of the test is demanded a 
further fee shall be levied for each fresh test, the whole sum charged being 
retained or refunded according to his final decision on the results of the 
tests.
 </section><section><number>2</number> (a) In carrying out the stove test, in 
the case of cotton yarn a regain of  
8 1/2 per 
cent. shall be added to the weight obtained after the yarn is reduced to an 
absolute dry conditions and the figure so obtained shall be regarded as the 
actual weight of the yarn under normal conditions.
 <subsection><number>b</number> In the case of silk, or woollen or 
other yarns other than cotton yarn the  
regain to be added to the weigh obtained after reducing such yarns to dry 
condition shall be according to the table of officials standards supplied with 
the stove test apparatus.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>171</number> Place of testing.—The testing 
of piece-goods and yarn referred to in rules 164 to 170 shall be made at the 
customs laboratories or at such place and by such officer as the 
customs-collector may direct.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>172</number> Security.—The 
customs-collector may require from any informant referred to in rule 166 
security not exceeding five hundred rupees and where he is satisfied that the 
information given is wilfully false, the security shall be forfeited.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>173</number> Piece-goods.—“Piece-goods such 
as are ordinarily sold by length or by the piece” (hereinafter referred as 
“piece-goods”) shall for the purposes of section 81 of the Act or the Customs 
Act, 1962 (52 of 1962) include cotton piece-goods, woollen piece-goods, silk 
piece-goods, art silk piece-goods of synthetic fiber and other piece-goods of 
mixed fabrics, shall not include the following descriptions of goods namely:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  Alhambras, except Alhambras quiltings
 <subsection>              <number>Blankets</number>
               Blind Cloth in cut-pieces.
               Book-Binding cloth in cut-pieces.
               Buckrams in cut-pieces.
               Carpets (in rolls).
 </subsection><subsection>              <number>Counterpanes</number>
               Decatising wrappers.
               Dusters in woven pieces.
               Embroidered all-overs and embroidered saris 
of all sorts.
               Embroidered flounces.
               Filter cloth.
               Glass clothe in woven pieces.
               Handkerchiefs in woven pieces.
               Laces and nets 
including Cotton Brettone nets.
               Lace curtain 
cloth.
               Pillow Calico 
(Tubular)
               Prayer Mats.
               Press cloth in 
cut pieces.
 </subsection><subsection>              <number>Quilts</number>
 </subsection><subsection>              <number>Rugs</number>
               Sarongs upto 21/2 yards 
2.28 metres in length.
               Shawls 
(finished) with ends hemmed or fringed, imported singly or in pieces, 
containing two or more shawls.
               Sponge Cloth 
(for swabs).
               Teddy Bear or 
imitation Seal Skin Cloth.
               Towels in woven 
pieces.
               Woollen cleaner 
cloth.
               Woollen knitted 
cloth.
               Woollen roller 
cloth.
               Woollen sizing 
Flannel.
 </subsection></section><section>    <number>b</number>(i)  Cotton remnants or 
cut lengths measuring less than fifteen yards (or fourteen metres) which are 
not in current ordinary trade practice sold by length or by the piece;
 <subsection>        <number>ii</number>  Fents regardless 
of their length, which are so defective owing to accidents in the weaving, 
dyeing or printing that they are not ordinarily capable of being sold by length 
or by the piece.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>174</number> 
Stamping of piece-goods.—
<section><number>1</number> Piece-goods which have been manufactured, 
bleached, dyed, printed or finished in India in premises which are a factory as 
defined in the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948) shall be stamped with the 
particulars required under sub-section (1) of section 81.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the 
case of piece-goods manufactured outside India (each piece shall be marked with 
the name of the manufacturer, exporter, or wholesale purchaser in India of the 
goods and with the real length of the piece in standard yards or in standard 
metres as required under the Customs Act, 1962 (52 of 1962).
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>175</number> Cases 
where requirement as to stamping may be waived.—
<section><number>1</number> The customs-collector 
may not detain any unstamped piece-goods if he is satisfied that although they 
are not mentioned in the list of excepted goods under rule 173 they are of such 
a nature that they would be liable to serious depreciation in value if stamped:
 Provided, however, where a 
customs-collector exercises his discretion under this sub-rule, he shall 
forthwith report the case, sending a sample of the goods to the Central 
Government through the Central Board of Revenue, so that the question of 
issuing general orders in favour of such goods may be considered.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Cotton and woollen piece-goods 
imported for the personal use of individuals or private associations of 
individuals and not for trade purposes need not be stamped.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>176</number> Nature of stamping required.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In marking the length of the piece-goods the words “yards” or “yds”, “metres” 
shall accompany the numerals, and in the case of cut-lengths or pieces of the 
kind other than that described in clause (b) of rule 173, the number of pieces 
shall be marked as well as the yards or metres on the front or outer face fold 
of the cut-piece, the figures being presented in a way to show clearly what 
they are intended to mean.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The length shall be in standard yards 
or fractions of such yards or standard metres or fractions of a metre and shall 
represent the actual length of the goods, and not the length before shrinkage 
or dryage, resulting from processes such as dyeing, or from atmospheric changes 
which can reasonably be foreseen. Marking in inches or centimetres may be 
permitted on cloths of small dimensions and delicate make in accordance with 
the custom of the trade.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The marking shall be such that it is 
not likely to be removal except by washing the fabric or in the case of goods 
that are not ordinarily washed, it shall be of such nature that it is not 
likely to be obliterated in the ordinary course of handling before the goods 
reach the purchaser.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The marking shall be conspicuous and 
in a different colour from that of the fabric, upon the fabric itself, and not 
upon a removable label or ticket. The marking shall not be upon an inner fold 
which cannot readily be seen, nor upon a wholly detached piece, but it may be 
upon piece that is partly detached without being entirely severed. In the case 
of sarongs which are required to be stamped, the stamping may be made on the 
selvage in the inner fold instead of one the uppermost fold of the cloth. 
Marks, which are stitched on the fabric and are easily removable by cutting, 
shall not be permitted. 
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>177</number> Languages and numerals to be used 
for marking.—All markings required by sub-section (2) of section 81 shall 
be in English and the international form of Indian numerals shall be used.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>178</number> Indications of weight, length, 
name of manufacturer etc.—
<section><number>1</number> The weight of yarn or thread in each bundle 
or unit shall ordinarily be indicated thereon in pounds or ounces in the 
English system or in grammes according to the metric system.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The length of threads in each bundle 
or unit shall be indicated thereon in yards or metres.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The name of the manufacturer or of the 
wholesale purchaser in India shall be indicated in full or, provided that the 
said name is clearly and unambiguously indicated thereby in an abbreviated 
form, on each bundle or unit.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>179</number> Manner of marking cotton yarn and 
cotton thread.—
<section><number>1</number> Each bundle of cotton yarn shall be marked with the 
particulars required under sub-section (2) of section 81 of the Act by one or 
more inscribed wrappers, labels or cards applied, affixed or stitched thereto, 
provided that all the required particulars shall be contained on the exposed 
surface.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Units of cotton thread shall be marked 
with the required particulars—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  when made up in skeins, by an inscribed label 
applied round each skein or bundle of skeins or secured by twine thereto;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  when made up in balls, by an inscribed label 
attached to each ball, or inserted therein but remaining exposed;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  when wound on cards, wheels, or stars, by 
inscription on the exposed portion of the card, wheel or star;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>d</number>  when wound on reels, by one or two inscribed 
label applied to the end or ends of the reel;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>e</number>  when wound on paper tubes or cones, by an 
inscribed label applied round or otherwise affixed to the thread or to the 
exposed portion of the outer surface of the tube or cone, or, where the 
diameter of the tube or cone is sufficient for the label to be clearly exposed 
to views, to the inner surface of the tube or cone, or, by inscription on the 
exposed portion of the outer surface of the tube or cone;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>f</number>  when made up in any other form, by an 
inscribed label or card applied, affixed or stitched to or enclosed or inserted 
in, such make up.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Labels or cards used in accordance 
with sub-rules (1) and (2) shall be so applied as not to be easily detachable 
or removable from a bundle of cotton yarn or from each unit of cotton thread in 
the ordinary course of handling before it reaches the normal consumer.
</section></article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>180</number> Marking of cover.—Where units 
of cotton thread are enclosed in a cover, such cover shall be marked with the 
required particulars.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>181</number> Markings to be clear and distinct.­—All 
markings on bundles of cotton yarn or units of cotton thread shall be legible, 
distinct and in a colour which is not likely to be easily obliterated and which 
shall be different from the colour of the surface marked.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>182</number> Manner of expressing count of 
cotton-yarn.—The count of cotton yarn shall ordinarily be expressed in 
English the metric system by adding the letter ‘S’ after the numeral or 
numerals where, however, a bundles is packed on the metric system, the count 
shall be accompanied by the words “metric count“ or by some other clear and 
definite indication conveying the fact and in the absence of such words or 
indication the marking shall be regarded as indicating that it is in the 
English system.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article><number>183</number> Indication of other particulars.—Nothing 
in rule 177 shall be construed as prohibiting the indication in any manner of 
other particulars relating to the cotton yarn or cotton thread so long as the 
conspicuousness of the required particulars is not affected thereby.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article>
<number>184</number> Exemptions.—All 
premises where the work is done by members of one family with or without the 
assistance of not more than ten other employees and all premises controlled by 
a co-operative society where not more than twenty workers are employed in the 
premises shall be exempted from the operation of rules 177 to 182.
</article> 
 
The trade marks rules, 2002
  
 <article>
<number>185</number> Repeal.—The 
Trade and Merchandise Marks Rules, 1959 are hereby repealed without prejudice 
to anything done under such rules before the coming into force of the rules.
  
  
  
</article><form>
 


The trade marks rules, 2002
 

 
 


The FoUrth Schedule
 

Classification of goods and 
services—Name of the classes
 

(Parts of an article or apparatus are, in 
general, classified with the actual article or apparatus, except where such 
parts constitute articles included in other classes).
 


 1.  Chemical used in industry, science, 
photography, agriculture, horticulture and forestry; unprocessed artificial 
resins, unprocessed plastics; manure; fire extinguishing compositions; 
tempering and soldering preparations; chemical substances for preserving 
foodstuffs; tanning substances; adhesive used in industry.
 


     2.  Paints, varnishes, lacquers; preservatives 
against rust and against deterioration of wood; colorants; mordents; raw 
natural resins; metals in-foil and powder form for painters; decorators; 
printers and artists.
 


     3.  Bleaching preparations and other substances for 
laundry use; cleaning; polishing; scouring and abrasive preparations; soaps; 
perfumery, essential oils, cosmetics, hair lotions, dentifrices.
 


     4.  Industrial oils and greases; lubricants; dust 
absorbing, wetting and binding compositions; fuels (including motor spirit) and 
illuminates; candles, wicks.
 


     5.  Pharmaceutical, veterinary and sanitary 
preparations; dietetic substances adapted for medical use, food for babies; 
plasters, materials for dressings; materials for stopping teeth, dental wax; 
disinfectants; preparation for destroying vermin; fungicides, herbicides.
 


     6.  Common metals and their alloys; metal building 
materials; transportable buildings of metal; materials of metal for railway 
tracks; non-electric cables and wires of common metal; ironmongery, small items 
of metal hardware; pipes and tubes of metal; safes; goods of common metal not 
included in other classes; ores.
 


     7.  Machines and machine tools; motors and engines 
(except for land vehicles); machine coupling and transmission components 
(except for land vehicles); agricultural implements other than hand-operated; 
incubators for eggs.
 


     8. Hand tools and implements (hand-operated); 
cutlery; side arms; razors.
 


     9. Scientific, nautical, surveying, electric, 
photographic, cinematographic, optical, weighing, measuring, signalling, 
checking (supervision), life saving and teaching apparatus and instruments; 
apparatus for recording, transmission or reproduction of sound or images; 
magnetic data carriers, recording discs; automatic vending machines and 
mechanisms for coin-operated apparatus; cash registers, calculating machines, 
data processing equivalent and computers; fire extinguishing apparatus.
 


    10. Surgical, medical, dental and veterinary apparatus 
and instruments, artificial limbs, eyes and teeth; orthopaedic articles; suture 
materials.
 


    11. Apparatus for lighting, heating, steam generating, 
cooking, refrigerating, drying, ventilating, water supply and sanitary 
purposes.
 


    12. Vehicles; apparatus for locomotion by land, air or 
water.
 


    13. Firearms; ammunition and projectiles; explosives; 
fire works.
 


    14.  Precious metals and their alloys and goods in 
precious metals or coated therewith, not included in other classes; jewellery, 
precious stones; horological and other chronometric instruments.
 


    15. Musical instruments.
 


    16. Paper, cardboard and goods made from these 
materials, not included in other classes; printed matter; book-binding 
material; photographs; stationery; adhesives for stationery or household 
purposes; artists, materials; paint brushes; typewriters and office requisites 
(except furniture); instructional and teaching material (except apparatus); 
plastic materials for packaging (not included in other classes); playing cards; 
printers type; printing blocks.
 


    17. Rubber, gutta percha, gum, asbestos, mica and 
goods made from these materials and not included in other classes; plastics in 
extruded form for use in manufacture; packing, stopping and insulating 
materials; flexible pipes, not of metal.
 


    18. Leather and imitations of leather, and goods made 
of these materials and not included in other classes; animal skins, hides, 
trunks and travelling bags; umbrellas, parasols and walking sticks; whips, 
harness and saddlery.
 


    19. Building materials (non-metallic), non-metallic 
rigid pipes for building; asphalt, pitch and bitumen; non-metallic 
transportable buildings; monument, not of metal.
 


    20. Furniture, mirrors, picture frames; goods (not 
included in other classes) of wood, cork, reed, cane, wicker, horn, bone, 
ivory, whalebone, shell, amber, mother-of-pearl, meerschaum and substitutes for 
all these materials, or of plastics.
 


    21. Household or kitchen utensils and containers (not 
of precious metal or coated therewith); combs and sponges; brushes (except 
paints brushes); brush making materials; articles for cleaning purposes; 
steelwool; unworked or semi-worked glass (except glass used in building); 
glassware, porcelain and earthenware not included in other classes.
 


    22. Ropes, string, nets, tents, awnings, tarpaulins, 
sails, sacks and bags (not included in other classes) padding and stuffing 
materials (except of rubber or plastics); raw fibrous textile materials.
 


    23. Yarns and threads, for textile use.
 


    24. Textiles and textile goods, not included in other 
classes; bed and table covers.
 


    25. Clothing, footwear, headgear.
 


    26. Lace and embroidery, ribbons and braid; buttons, 
hooks and eyes, pins and needles; artificial flowers.
 


    27. Carpets, rugs, mats and matting, linoleum and 
other materials for covering existing floors; wall hangings (non-textile).
 


    28. Games and playthings, gymnastic and sporting 
articles not included in other classes; decorations for Christmas trees.
 


    29. Meat, fish, poultry and game; meat extracts; 
preserved, dried and cooked fruits and vegetables; jellies, jams, fruit sauces; 
eggs, milk and milk products; edible oils and fats.
 


    30. Coffee, tea, cocoa, sugar, rice, tapioca, sago, 
artificial coffee; flour and preparations made from cereals, bread, pasty and 
confectionery, ices; honey, treacle; yeast baking powder; salt, mustard; 
vinegar, sauces (condiments); spices; ice.
 


    31. Agricultural, horticultural and forestry products 
and grain not included in other classes; live animals; fresh fruits and 
vegetables; seeds, natural plants and flowers; foodstuffs for animals, malt.
 


    32. Beers, mineral and aerated waters, and other 
non-alcoholic drinks, fruit drinks and fruit juices; syrups and other 
preparations for making beverages.
 


    33. Alcoholic beverages (except beers).
 


    34. Tobacco, smokers, articles, matches.
 


Services
 


 35. Advertising, business management, business 
administration, office functions.
 


    36. Insurance, financial affairs; monetary affairs; 
real estate affairs.
 


    37. Building construction; repair; installation 
services.
 


    38. Telecommunications.
 


    39. Transport; packaging and storage of goods; travel 
arrangement.
 


    40. Treatment of materials.
 


    41. Education; providing of training; entertainment; 
sporting and cultural activities.
 


    42. Providing of food and drink; temporary 
accommodation; medical, hygienic and beauty care; veterinary and agricultural 
services, legal services, scientific and industrial research; computer 
programming; services that cannot be classified in other classes.
</form><form>
 


The trade marks rules, 2002
 

 
 


The Fifth Schedule
 

List of items of textile goods referred 
to in rule 145
 

No. of item
 


     1. Grey Longcloth, Shirtings, Cellular, Limbric, 
Poplin, Sheetings, Printers and Lepard Cloth - Including all abovementioned 
grey cloths with no colour in the body except a woven coloured heading.
 


     2. Grey Drill, Jeans and Duck - Including only grey 
cloth and not striped drills with grey grounds.
 


     3. Grey Twills.
 


     4. Grey Salitha, T-Cloths and Domestics.
 


     5. Grey Coarse Cloth.
 


     6. Grey Chadars of Plain Weave and Khadi Chadars—Including 
all chadars of plain weave with no colour in the body but with or without a 
woven coloured heading or fancy heading, but not including check Chadars and 
striped Chadars.
 


     7. Grey Chadars of Twill Weave—Including only grey 
twill chadars with no colour in the body except a woven coloured heading.
 


     8. Grey Dhoties including Tahmad [This item relates 
only to grey ground dhoties (of all dimensions) with or without artificial 
silk, coloured yarn or printed borders and headings].
 


     9. Grey Saries and Scarves and Sari Cloth-Including 
only grey ground Saries (of all dimensions) with or without artificial silk, 
coloured yarn, folded yarn, or printed borders and headings and sari cloth in 
piece length but not including Saries with striped or check grounds, and dyed 
and printed Saries.
 


    10. Grey Dosuti.
 


    11. Grey Jaconets, Jagannathi, Mulls and Mulmulls.
 


    12. Grey pagree Cloth.
 


    13. Grey Matting Weave and Canvas including Filter 
cloth.
 


    14. Sambura Cloth - Grey Drill with red and black 
headings and coloured runner in the centre.
 


    15. Whole Grey Dobby Cloth and Doria.
 


    16. Bleached Longcloth, Shirtings, Cellular, Limbric, 
Poplin, Sheetings and Printers - Including all abovementioned plain cloths with 
no colour in the body except a woven coloured heading.
 


    17. Bleached drills, jeans and Duck - See note 
under item 16.
 


    18. Bleached Twills - See note under item 16. 
This item does not include Striped Twills on bleached ground.
 


    19. Bleached T-Cloths and Domestics - See note 
under item 16.
 


    20. Bleached Coarse cloth - See note under item 
16.
 


    21. Bleached Chadars - Including chadars of plain and 
twill weave.
 


    22. Bleached Mulls, Jaconets and Nainsooks - See
note under item 16.
 


    23. Bleached Madapollams and Cambrics - See 
note under item 16.
 


    24. Bleached Dhoties including Tahmad—This item 
relates only to plain bleached ground dhoties (of all dimensions) with 
artificial silk, coloured yarn, folded yarn, or printed borders and headings.
 


    25. Bleached Saries and Scarves—Including only plain 
bleached ground Saries (of all dimensions) with artificial silk, coloured yarn 
or printed borders and headings, but not including Saries with stripes or 
checks and dyed printed Saries.
 


    26. Bleached Dosuti—See note under item 16.
 


    27. Bleached Voiles and Muslines—See note under 
item 16.
 


    28. Bleached Dorias and Fancies—Including bleached 
cloth with bleached folded yarn stripes or checks.
 


    29.  Bleached Matting Weave and Canvas—See note 
under item 16.
 


    30. Bleached Pagree Cloth—See note under item 
16.
 


    31. Embroidered Voiles, Muslins etc. Bleached.
 


    32. Bleached Flannnel and Flannelettes and bleached 
cloths raised on one side kind cotton Velvet.
 


    33. Dyed Longcloth, Shirtings, Cellular, Limbric, 
Poplin and Sheetings—Including the abovementioned cloths dyed in the piece.
 


    34. Dyed Drills—See note under item 33. This 
item also includes coloured warp or weft drills.
 


    35. Dyed Twills—See note under item 33.
 


    36. Dyed T-Cloths and Domestics—See note under 
item 33.
 


    37. Dyed Coarse Cloth—See note under item 33.
 


    38. Dyed Chadars—See note under item 33.
 


    39. Dyed Dhoties including Tahmad, Saries and Shawals—This 
item includes dhoties, saries or shawls dyed in the piece.
 


    40. Dyed Fancies—Including fancies with single colour 
warp or weft fancies or printed yarn in the warp or weft or both.
 


    41. Dyed Pagree Cloth—See note under item 33.
 


    42. Dyed Voiles—Including bordered voiles.
 


    43. Dyed Flannelettes—Including Grey and self-coloured 
Flannelettes and all dyed cloths raised on one side and cotton velvet.
 


    44. Dyed Mulls.
 


    45. Dyed Umbrella Cloth.
 


    46. Coatings and Trouserings (including Sholapuri, 
Chennai, Cloth, Sunproof cloth, Tussore, Kashmere Cloth, Serges, Thana Cloth, 
Tweeds, Mazri, Malatia and Corduroy). - In addition to the goods enumerated 
above, this item includes cotton dyed coatings and coatings with artificial 
silk in the warp or in the weft as stripes or checks, either alone or in 
combination with dyed cotton yarn.
 


    47. Striped Drills and Jeans Striped Twills - 
Including striped drills or twills with grey, bleached or coloured ground.
 


    48. Bed ticking—With coloured warp and grey or 
bleached weft.
 


    49. Striped Coarse Cloth—Including both grey and 
bleached grounds.
 


    50. Striped shirtings, Striped Susis and Striped 
Zephyrs—Including striped shirtings, etc., with grey, bleached or coloured 
ground but not including artificial silk striped goods.
 


    51. Check shirtings, Check Susis and Check Zephyrs—See
note under item 50.
 


    52. Check Chadars—Including plain check chadar and 
will check chadar on grey, bleached or coloured grounds. 
 


    53. Lungis and Sarongs.
 


    54. Woven coloured Saries and Scarves—(This includes 
saries and scarves with striped or check grounds, but does not include saries 
and scarves in which there is artificial silk in the body of the cloth).
 


    55. Check Cholas and Gumchas.
 


    56. Artificial Silk Striped Shirtings—This includes 
(a) artificial silk shirtings with an artificial silk warp and weft, (b) an 
artificial slide warp, or (c) artificial silk only in stripes, either alone or 
in combination with coloured cotton yarn.
 


    57. Artificial Silk Check Shirtings—On grey, white and 
coloured grounds.
 


    58. Artificial Silk Brocades and “All over Styles”.
 


    59. Artificial Silk Dhoties, Saries and Scarves and 
Sari Cloth—(This item includes dhoties and saries in which an artificial silk 
warp or weft or both are used. It does not include dhoties, etc., in which 
artificial silk is used, only in the borders).
 


    60. Crepe Cloth—Grey, Bleached and dyed. This item 
also includes crepe cloth yarn printed.
 


    61. Dyed and striped Dosuti—Including striped Dosuti 
bleached in the piece.
 


    62. Printed dhoties, Shawls, Rumals, Saries and other 
printed garments—Including Voile Saries also.
 


    63. Printed longcloth, Shirtings, Cellular, Limbric, 
Poplins and Sheetings—Grey, bleached and dyed grounds.
 


    64. Striped, Check and printed flannelettes.
 


    65. Pure Silk Saries.
 


    66. Leno and Mackleno, Bandage cloth—Grey, bleached, 
dyed or striped including Gauze cloth also.
 


    67. Terry Towels including towelling cloth—Grey, 
bleached, dyed, printed, striped or checked.
 


    68. Huckaback towels including towelling cloth—Grey, 
bleached, dyed, printed, striped or checked.
 


    69. Honey Comb Towels including towelling cloth—Grey, 
bleached, dyed, printed, striped or checked.
 


    70. All other towels including towelling cloth.
 


    71. (a)  Dusters, Handkerchiefs, Rumals and Glass 
Cloth (serviettes)
 


          (b)  Table cloth and table covers, napkins.
 


    72. Dobby Jacquard Chadars, Bedspreads, Quilts and 
Counterpanes including Suzni—Grey, bleached or coloured.
 


    73. Blankets and Malida Cloth—All types, including 
cotton and wool union blankets; and shawls (not dyed or printed) or lobis of 
any fibres.
 


    74. Durries and carpets including Satranji (floor 
carpets).
 


    75. Dyed and coloured Canvas—Dyed or woven coloured.
 


    76. Artificial Silk zephyrs, Alpaca, Crepe, etc.—Plain 
and Fancy grounds (whole colour and unstriped).
 


    77. Motor hood cloth.
 


    78. Buckram cloth - grey, bleached and dyed.
 


    79. Striped voiles—Bleached and/or dyed in the piece.
 


    80. Printed voiles—Grey, bleached and dyed.
 


    81. Mookta cloth—This cloth is woven with cotton warp 
and flax weft.
 


    82. Artificial silk Tapestry and Upholstering Fabrics, 
including cotton furnishing fabrics and casement cloths—Grey, bleached, dyed 
and printed.
 


    83. Bedford Cord—Bleached and dyed.
 


    84. Printed Crepe—Grey, bleached or dyed grounds.
 


    85. Pure Silk Coatings—Plain, striped or checked. This 
item also includes coatings made of artificial fibres, filaments and yarns.
 


    86. Pure Silk Shirtings—Plain, striped or checked.
 


    87. Printed Drills, Twills and Jeans.
 


    88. Corded Voiles—Bleached coloured, printed kind 
bordered.
 


    89. Printed Boski—Artificial silk warp, weft or both.
 


    90. Artificial silk striped voiles—Grey, bleached and 
dyed voiles with artificial silk stripes in the body of the cloth.
 


    91. Bordered voiles—Bleached, dyed and printed (with 
or without artificial silk border).
 


    92. Artificial Silk Satins—Including satins made from 
100 per cent silk or artificial silk in the warp or weft.
 


    93. Check Voiles, Grey, bleached and dyed (This item 
contains cotton voiles with grey, bleached or coloured grounds with check 
designs all over the body of the cloth).
 


    94. Grey flannellettes—Including all grey cloths 
raised on one side and cotton velvet.
 

 
 



 

 
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  15th September, 2003 
vide S.O. 1048 (E), dated 15-9-2003, published in the Gazette of India, 
Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 15th September, 2003.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> The word “TM-54” omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> The words “or for expedited search report in Form TM-71” omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), 
  dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> The word “TM-54” omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> The words “or for expedited search report in Form TM-71” omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), 
  dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Sub-rules (1) and (2) omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010). Sub-rules (1) and (2), before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Sub-rules (1) and (2) omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010). Sub-rules (1) and (2), before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Rule 32 omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010). Rule 32, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Rule 32 omitted by G.S.R. 1024(E), dated 29th December, 2010 (w.e.f. 29-12-2010). Rule 32, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>