<act><title>

THE WILD LIFE (PROTECTION) LICENSING 
    (ADDITIONAL MATTERS FOR CONSIDERATION) RULES, 19831</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
        Short title, extent  and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Wild Life (Protection) Licensing (Additional 
    Matters for Consideration) Rules, 1983.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They 
    shall extend to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>  
    They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In 
    these Rules, unless the context otherwise requires, “Act” means the Wild 
    Life (Protection) Act, 1972 (53 of 1972).  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Additional matters  for consideration  for  grant  of  licence under 
    section  44 of the Act.—For 
    the purposes of granting a licence referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
    44 of the Act, the Chief Wild Life Warden or the authorized officer, as the 
    case may be, shall, in addition to the matters specified in clause (b) of 
    sub-section (4) of that section, have regard to the following other matters, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    capacity of the applicant to 
    handle the business concerned with reference to facilities, equipment and 
    suitability of the premises for such business;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    the source and the manner in 
    which the supplies for the business concerned would be obtained;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    number of licences for the 
    relevant business already in existence in the area concerned;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>    implications which the grant of 
    such licence would have on the hunting or trade of the wild animals 
    concerned:  
 
Provided 
    that no such licence shall be granted if the said implications relate to any 
    wild animal specified in Schedule I or Part II of Schedule II to the Act, 
    except with the previous consultation of the Central Government.  
  
  
 


 
  


</subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>