<act><title>THE CIGARETTES AND OTHER TOBACCO PRODUCTS 
(PACKAGING AND LABELLING) RULES, 20081</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>These rules may be called 
the Cigarettes and Other Tobacco Products (Packaging and Labelling) Rules, 2008 
and they shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Cigarettes and Other Tobacco Products (Prohibition of 
  Advertisement and Regulation of Trade and Commerce, Production, Supply and 
  Distribution) Act, 2003; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> package means box, pouch, conical, cylindrical or any other type of 
  pack used for packing cigarette and other tobacco products; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> principal display area means: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> for box type packages, two equal sized largest surface area of the 
    box that may be displayed or visible under normal or customary conditions of 
    sale or use; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> for pouch type packages, the entire surface area of the pack that 
    may be displayed or visible under normal conditions of sale or use; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> for conical or cylindrical type of packages, the entire curving 
    area of the pack that may be displayed or visible under normal or customary 
    conditions of sale or use; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> for any other form or type of package, the entire surface area of 
    the pack that may be displayed or visible under normal or customary 
    conditions of sale or use; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>d</number> specified health warning means, such health warnings as specified by 
  the Central Government from time to time, in the Schedule to these rules. 
</section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Prohibition on obscuring, masking, altering or detracting from the 
Specified Health Warnings. </title>No person shall sell or supply any product, 
device, or other thing that is intended to be used, or that can be used, to 
cover, obscure, mask, alter, or otherwise detract from the display of specified 
health warning on the tobacco product package. This includes prohibition to 
design the product package or parts of the package, or accessories thereto, with 
any cover that may obscure the prescribed messages. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Prohibition on obscuring, masking, altering or detracting from the 
Specified Health Warnings. </title>No person shall sell or supply any product, 
device, or other thing that is intended to be used, or that can be used, to 
cover, obscure, mask, alter, or otherwise detract from the display of specified 
health warning on the tobacco product package. This includes prohibition to 
design the product package or parts of the package, or accessories thereto, with 
any cover that may obscure the prescribed messages. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Rotation of specified health warnings. </title>The specified 
health warning on tobacco packs shall be rotated every twelve months from the 
date of notification of the rules or earlier as specified by the Central 
Government. 

</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Shall come into force on 30-11-2008 ,  vide  S.O. 
2130(E), dated 27th August, 2008 .</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>