<act><tid>1988422</tid>
<title>THE SPICES CESS ACT, <year>1986</year></title>

ACT NO. 11 OF <year>1986</year>
[ 20th March, <year>1986</year>.]

An Act to provide for imposition of cess on all spices which are 
exported for the purposes of carrying out measures for the development 
of export of spices.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>227978</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1058786</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Spices Cess Act, <year>1986</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1383651</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall extend to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>200514</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>36256</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1846140</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Spices Board constituted under sub- 
section (1) of section 3 of the Spices Board Act, <year>1986</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1709452</tid>
<number>b</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act; and

</section>

<section><tid>792258</tid>
<number>c</number>" spices" means the spices specified in the Schedule to 
the Spices Board Act, <year>1986</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>117106</tid>
<number> 3</number> Levy and collection of cess.
<section><tid>1925560</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and  
collected by way of cess for the purpose of the Spices Board Act, 
<year>1986</year>, a duty of customs <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> (on all spices which are exported) at such 
rate not exceeding five per cent. ad valorem, as the Central 
Government may, from time to time, specify by notification in the 
Official Gazette.

</section>

<section><tid>1691830</tid>
<number>2</number>The duty of customs levied under sub- section (1) shall be in 
addition to the duty of customs leviable on spices under the Customs 
Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>) or any other law for the time being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>1977422</tid>
<number>3</number>The provisions of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>) and 
the rules and regulations made thereunder, including those relatable 
to refund and exemption of duty, shall, so far as may be, apply in 
relation to levy and collection of the said duty of customs as they 
apply in relation to the levy and collection of the duty of customs on 
spices under that Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>863</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 26- 2- 87 Vide Notification No. S. O. 124 (E), dated 26- 2- <year>1987</year>, 
Gazette of India, <year>1987</year>, Extraordinary Part II, Section 3 (ii).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1988</year>, S. 3 and sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1777670</tid>
<number>4</number>The proceeds of the duty of customs levied under sub- section 
 (1) shall first be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India and the 
Central Government may, if Parliament, by appropriation made by law in 
this behalf so provides, pay to the Board from time to time, from out 
of such proceeds (after deducting the cost of collection) such sums of 
money as it may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of the 
Spices Board Act, <year>1986</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>255303</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to call reports and returns. The Board may require any 
exporter of spices to furnish for the purposes of this Act, such 
statistical and other information in such form and within such period 
as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>372848</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>501217</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1229326</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for the form in which and the 
period within which statistical and other information may be furnished 
to the Board under section 4.

</section>

<section><tid>67339</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>