<act><title>

The Citizenship 
    (Registration of Citizens and Issue of National Identity Cards) Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Citizenship (Registration of Citizens and Issue of 
    National Identity Cards) Rules, 2003. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “Act” means the Citizenship Act, 1955 (57 of 1955); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> “Chief Registrar of Births and Deaths” means the Chief Registrar of Births and Deaths appointed under the Registration of Births and Deaths Act, 1969 (18 of 1969); 
 </section><section><number>c</number> “citizen” means the citizen of India in terms of the Constitution of India and provisions of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> “Director of Citizen Registration” means the Director of Census in a State or Union territory appointed by the Central Government under the Census Act, 1948 (37 of 1948), who shall also function as the Director of Citizen Registration in that State, or as the case may be, in the Union territory; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> “District Register of Indian Citizens” means the register containing details of Indian citizens usually residing in the district; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> “District Registrar of Citizen Registration” means the District Magistrate of every revenue district, by whatever name known, who shall act as the District Registrar of Citizen Registration; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> “Local Register of Indian Citizens” means the register containing details of Indian citizens usually residing in a village or rural area or town or ward or demarcated area (demarcated by the Registrar General of Citizen Registration) within a ward in a town or urban area; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> “Local Registrar of Citizen Registration” means a local officer, or a revenue officer, appointed by the State Government at the lowest geographical jurisdiction, that is to say, of a village or rural area or town, or ward or demarcated area (demarcated by the Registrar General of Citizen Registration) within a ward in a town or urban area, who shall function as Local Registrar for the purpose of preparation of Local Register of Indian Citizens; 
 </section><section><number>i</number> “National Identity Card” means the identity card issued under  
    rule 13; 
 </section><section><number>j</number> “National Identity Number” means a unique identity number allotted to every Indian Citizen by the Registrar General of Citizen Registration, India ; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> “National Register of Indian Citizens” means the register containing details of Indian Citizens living in India and outside India ; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> “Population Register” means the register containing details of persons usually residing in a village or rural area or town or ward or demarcated area (demarcated by the Registrar General of Citizen Registration) within a ward in a town or urban area; 
 </section><section><number>m</number> “Registrar General of Citizen Registration” means the Registrar General, India, appointed under the Registration of Births and Deaths Act, 1969 (18 of 1969), who shall also function as the Registrar General of Citizen Registration, India; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>ma</number> “Schedule” means a Schedule appended to these rules;] 
 </section><section><number>n</number> “State Register of Indian Citizens” means the register containing details of Indian citizens usually residing in the State; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> “Sub-district or Taluk Registrar of Citizen Registration” means the Sub­district Magistrate or Taluk Executive Magistrate of every sub-district or taluk, by whatever name known, as the case may be, who shall function as Sub-district or Taluk Registrar of Citizen Registration; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> “Sub-district Register of Indian Citizens” means the register containing details of Indian citizens usually residing in a taluk, or by whatever name known, of the sub-district. 
</section>



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> National 
    Register of Indian Citizens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar General of Citizen Registration shall establish and maintain 
    the National Register of Indian Citizens.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    National Register of Indian Citizens shall be divided into sub‑parts 
    consisting of the State Register of Indian Citizens, the District Register 
    of Indian Citizens, the Sub‑district Register of Indian Citizens and the 
    Local Register of Indian Citizens and shall contain such details as the 
    Central Government may, by order, in consultation with the Registrar General 
    of Citizen Registration, specify.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    National Register of Indian Citizens shall contain the following particulars 
    in respect of every Citizen, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Name;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Father’s name;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Mother’s name;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   Sex;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   Date of birth;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   Place of birth;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   Residential address (present and 
    permanent);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>   Marital status—if ever married, name 
    of the spouse;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number>   Visible identification mark;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>   Date of registration of Citizen;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>   Serial number of registration; and  
 <subsubsection>
<number>xii</number>   National Identity Number.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central 
    Government may, by an order issued in this regard, decide a date by which 
    the Population Register shall be prepared by collecting information relating 
    to all persons who are usually residing within the jurisdiction of Local 
    Registrar.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Local 
    Register of Indian citizens shall contain details of persons after due 
    verification made from the Population Register.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Preparation of the National Register of Indian Citizens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, for the purpose of National Register of Indian 
    Citizens, cause to carry throughout the country a house‑to‑house enumeration 
    for collection of specified particulars relating to each family and 
    individual, residing in a local area including the Citizenship status.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration shall notify the period and 
    duration of the enumeration in the Official Gazette.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purposes of preparation and inclusion in the Local Register of Indian 
    Citizens, the particulars collected of every family and individual in the 
    Population Register shall be verified and scrutinized by the Local 
    Registrar, who may be assisted by one or more persons as specified by the 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> During the 
    verification process, particulars of such individuals, whose Citizenship is 
    doubtful, shall be entered by the Local Registrar with appropriate remark in 
    the Population Register for further enquiry and in case of doubtful 
    Citizenship, the individual or the family shall be informed in a specified 
    proforma immediately after the verification process is over.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> (a) Every 
    person or family specified in sub‑rule (4), shall be given an opportunity of 
    being heard by the Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar of Citizen Registration, 
    before a final decision is taken to include or to exclude their particulars 
    in the National Register of Indian Citizens.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar shall finalize his findings within a period 
    of ninety days of the entry being made, or within such reasonable extended 
    time for which he shall record the reasons in writing.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> (a) The 
    draft of the Local Register of Indian Citizens shall be published by the 
    Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar, for inviting any objections or for 
    inclusion of any name or corrections for the family or individual 
    particulars collected and proposed to be finally entered in the National 
    Register of Indian Citizens.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Any 
    objection against a particular entry or for inclusion of a name, or 
    corrections if any, in the Local Register of Indian Citizens may be made 
    within a period of thirty days from the date of publication of the draft of 
    the Local Register of Indian Citizens, spelling out the nature and reasons 
    for the objection in such form as may be specified by the Registrar General 
    of Citizen Registration.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Subject to 
    the provisions contained in clause (a) of sub‑rule (5), the Sub‑district or 
    Taluk Registrar shall consider such objections and summarily dispose off the 
    same within a period of ninety days, and thereafter submit the Local 
    Register of Indian Citizens so prepared to the District Registrar of Citizen 
    Registration who shall cause the entries in the Local Register of Indian 
    Citizens, to be transferred to the National Register of Indian Citizens.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> (a) Any 
    person aggrieved by the order of the Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar under 
    sub‑rule (5) or sub‑rule (6), may prefer an appeal within thirty days from 
    the date of such order, to the District Registrar of Citizen Registration.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    District Registrar of Citizen Registration shall take a final decision, 
    after giving an opportunity of being heard to the person so aggrieved, 
    within a period of ninety days from the date of appeal.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> In case the 
    appeal is allowed, the particulars shall be entered in the National Register 
    of Indian Citizens.  
 
 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>4A</number> Special provisions as to National Register of Indian Citizens in State of Assam. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Nothing in rule 4 shall, on and after the commencement of the Citizenship (Registration of Citizens and Issue of National Identity Cards) Amendment Rules, 2009, apply to the State of Assam. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall, for the purpose, of the National Register of Indian Citizens in the State of Assam, cause to carry out throughout the State of Assam for preparation of the National Register of Indian Citizens in the State of Assam by inviting applications from all the residents, for collection of specified particulars relating to each family and individual, residing in a local area in the State including the citizenship status based on the National Register of Citizens 1951 and the electoral rolls prior to the year 1971. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registrar General of Citizens Registration shall notify the period and duration of the enumeration in the Official Gazette. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The manner of preparation of the National Register of Indian Citizens in the State of Assam shall be such as specified in the Schedule appended to these rules.] 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Officials 
    of the Central Government, State Governments and local bodies to assist the 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration.—Every 
    official of the Central Government, State Government, local bodies or their 
    undertakings shall assist the Registrar General of Citizen Registration or 
    any person authorized by him in this behalf, in preparation of the database 
    relating to each family and every person, and in implementing the provisions 
    of these rules.
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Initialization of National Register of Indian Citizens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Registrar General of Citizen Registration shall, by order, notify the 
    date on which the National Register of Indian Citizens shall be initialized 
    throughout the country.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The order 
    made under sub‑rule (1) may provide for the initialization period specified 
    by the Registrar General of Citizen Registration for establishment of the 
    National Register of Indian Citizens.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    individual must get himself registered with the Local Registrar of Citizen 
    Registration during the period of initialization as specified under sub‑rule 
    (2).  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number> Head of family and individual to act as 
      informant.—
<section><number>1</number> It shall be 
      compulsory for every citizen of India to assist the officials responsible 
      for preparation of the National Register of Indian Citizens under rule 4 
      and get himself registered in the Local Register of Indian Citizens during 
      the period of initialization.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> It shall be the responsibility of the head 
      of every family, during the period specified for preparation of the 
      Population Register, to give the correct details of name and number of 
      members and other particulars, as specified in sub‑rule (3) of rule 3, of 
      the family of which he is the head.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall be the responsibility of every 
      Citizen to register once with the Local Registrar of Citizen Registration 
      and to provide correct individual particulars to that authority.  
 </section><section><number>4</number> In the case of dependents, such as minor who 
      has not attained the age of eighteen years, or who is disabled, the 
      responsibility of reporting the particulars under this rule shall be of 
      the head of the family:  
 Provided that in so far as inmates of 
      institutions, such as orphanages, old age homes, mental asylums are 
      concerned, the responsibility for providing the requisite details shall 
      lie with the head of the Institution.  
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power of 
    District Registrar, Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar or Local Registrar of 
    Citizen Registration to obtain information.—The 
    District Registrar, Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar or the Local Registrar 
    of Citizen Registration may, by order, require any person to furnish any 
    information within his knowledge in connection with the determination of 
    Citizenship status of any person and the person required to furnish 
    information shall be bound to comply with such requisition. 
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Procedure 
    as to making of entries in National Register of Indian Citizens.—The 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration may, by order, specify the 
    procedure to be followed in preparation of the National Register of Indian 
    Citizens and disposal of claims and objections with regard to family and 
    individual particulars proposed to be entered in that Register.
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Deletion 
    of name and particulars from National Register of Indian Citizens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The name and particulars of a Citizen may be removed from the National 
    Register of Indian Citizens by an order of the Registrar General of Citizen 
    Registration or any officer authorized by him in this behalf in the event 
    of— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   death of the person; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the person ceasing to be an Indian 
    citizen under section 8 of the Act; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   revocation of Indian citizenship under 
    section 9 of the Act; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the particulars provided by the 
    individual or the family found to be incorrect subsequently, thereby 
    affecting the Citizenship status of the person.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall be 
    the duty of the Indian Citizen concerned to inform the District Registrar of 
    Citizen Registration, within a period of thirty days, about the cessation of 
    his Indian citizenship under clause (ii) of sub‑rule (1).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> in the 
    event of an order under sub‑rule (1), the person concerned, or in the event 
    of his death his nearest relative, shall be duly informed about the deletion 
    of any entry from the National Register of Indian Citizens:  
 
Provided that 
    any person aggrieved by the order of an authorized officer may prefer an 
    appeal against such order to the Authority within a period of thirty days of 
    such order.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The appeal 
    under sub‑rule (3) shall be disposed off, after giving to the appellant an 
    opportunity of being heard, and produce any documentary or oral evidence in 
    support of his claim.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Maintenance and updating of National Register of Indian Citizens.—The 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration shall cause to maintain the 
    National Register of Indian Citizens in electronic or some other form which 
    shall entail its continuous updating on the basis of extracts from various 
    Registers specified under the Registration of Births and Deaths Act, 1969 
    (18 of 1969) and the Act.
 <section>
<number>2</number> It shall be 
    the responsibility of the head of each and every family to ensure that any 
    event of birth or death occurring in the family has been duly entered in, or 
    deleted from, the Local Register of Indian Citizens.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief 
    Registrar of Births and Deaths and all other officials engaged in the 
    registration of births and deaths shall assist the Registrar General of 
    Citizen Registration in updating the National Register of Indian Citizens as 
    required under sub‑rule (1).  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Modification of entries in National Register of Indian Citizens.—The 
    Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar may, on an application made by the concerned 
    person and after due verification, authorize the modification of any entry 
    in respect of the following particulars in National Register of Indian 
    Citizens, namely:— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   change of name; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the name of the applicant’s parent in 
    case his status has been altered by adoption under the relevant laws; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   change of residential address; or  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   change of marital status; or  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   change of sex.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Issue of 
    National Identity Cards.—The 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration, or any officer authorized by him 
    in this behalf, shall issue the National Identity Card to every Citizen 
    whose particulars are entered in the National Register of Indian Citizens 
    under sub‑rule (3) of rule 3. 
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> National 
    identity Cards to be Government property and responsibility of Citizens to 
    keep them properly.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    National Identity Card shall be the property at the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No person 
    shall wilfully destroy, alter, transfer or use in any form the National 
    Identity Card, except for the lawful purposes.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the 
    happening of any of the events specified under sub‑rule (1) of rule 10, the 
    National Identity Card shall be surrendered, by the Citizen concerned or his 
    nearest relative, as the case may be, to the Registrar General of Citizen 
    Registration or any other authorized officer acting on his behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the 
    event of a loss of the National Identity Card, it shall be the duty of the 
    Citizen or his nearest relative, as the case may be, to report the matter 
    immediately to the nearest police station and the concerned Authority.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Designation of National Registration Authority and officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On and from the date of commencement of these rules, the Registrar General, 
    India shall be designated as the Registrar General of Citizen Registration, 
    India who shall also function as such for the purposes of these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Central 
    Government may designate— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   one or more officers as Additional or 
    Joint or Deputy Registrar General of Citizen Registration and such other 
    officers and staff as may be required; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   an officer as a Director, and one or 
    more officers as Joint Director, Deputy Director, Assistant Director of 
    Citizen Registration for each of the States and the Union territories along 
    with requisite support staff, to assist the Registrar General of Citizen 
    Registration in discharging the functions and responsibilities under these 
    rules.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The State 
    Government shall notify a State Co‑ordinator of National Registration not 
    below the rank of a Secretary in the State Government or equivalent.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Supervision and Control of Registrar General of Citizen Registration over 
    District, Sub‑district or Taluk and Local Registrars of Citizen 
    Registration.—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
    Governments shall designate an officer or a person as Local Registrar of 
    Citizen Registration for each lowest geographical jurisdiction, that is to 
    say, of a village or rural area or town, or ward or demarcated area 
    (demarcated by the Registrar General of Citizen Registration) within a ward 
    in a town or urban area who shall function as Local Registrar for the 
    purpose of preparation of Local Register of Indian Citizens.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Local 
    Registrar of Citizen Registration shall function under the overall 
    supervision of the Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar of Citizen Registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar of Citizen Registration shall function under 
    the overall supervision of the District Registrar of Citizen Registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> For the 
    purposes of implementing and carrying out the provisions of these rules, the 
    District Registrar, the Sub‑district or Taluk Registrar and the Local 
    Registrar of Citizen Registration shall be under the supervision and control 
    of the Registrar General of Citizen Registration.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration or any officer authorized by him 
    at any time may call for any records for examination, and issue directions 
    regarding inclusion or exclusion of any individual or family particulars 
    from the Population Register or Local Register of Indian Citizens, to the 
    District Registrar, the Sub­district or Taluk Registrar and the Local 
    Registrar of Citizen Registration.  
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Penal 
    consequences in certain cases.—Any 
    violation of provisions of rules 5, 7, 8, 10, 11 and 14 shall be punishable 
    with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees. 
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Guidelines for collection of particulars of individuals, verification, issue 
    of National Identity Cards, etc.—The 
    Registrar General of Citizen Registration may, in consultation with the 
    Central Government, issue from time to time, such guidelines to the State 
    Governments as are considered necessary for implementation of these rules. 
 
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 803(E), dated 9th November, 2009 (w.e.f. 9-11-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 803(E), dated 9th November, 2009 (w.e.f. 9-11-2009).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>