<act><tid>1057059</tid>
<title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> THE LEGAL REPRESENTATIVES' SUITS ACT, <year>1855</year>]</title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1855</year> 
[ 27th March, <year>1855</year>]
An Act to enable Executors, Administrators or Representatives to sue 
and be sued for certain wrongs. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to enable executors, 
administrators or representatives in certain cases to sue and be sued 
in respect of certain wrongs which, according to the present law, do 
not survive to or against such executors, administrators or 
representatives;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>)

This Act has been declared to be in force in the whole of India, 
except Part B States and the Scheduled Districts, by the Laws Local 
Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 , of <year>1874</year>), s. 3.

This Act has been extended to and brought into force in Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>. s. 2 and Sch. I (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1963</year>) and to 
the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3, and Sch.

The Act came into forece in the State of Sikkim on 1- 9- <year>1984</year> vide 
Notifn. No. S. O. 653 (E), dt. 24- 8- <year>1984</year>.

It has also been declared in force in the Khondmals District by 
the Khondmals Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (4 of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 and Sch; in the 
Angul District by the Angul Laws Regulation, <year>1936</year> (5 of <year>1936</year>), s. 3 
and Sch.; and in the Sonthal parganas by Sonthal Parganas Settlements 
Regulation, <year>1872</year> (3 of <year>1872</year>), s. 3

It has been declared by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act. <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

West Jalpaiguri.. See Gazette of India <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 4.

The Districts of Hazaribagh, 
Lohardaga (now the Ranchi  
Districts see Calcutta Gazette, 
  <year>1899</year>, Pt, I, p. 44) and Manbhum, 
and Pargana Dhalbhum and the 
Kollhan in the District of 
Singhbhum.... Ditto <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

The Scheduled portion of 
the Mirzapur District... Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, P. 383.

Jaunsar Bawar. Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 382.

The District of Lahaul Ditto <year>1886</year>, Pt. I, p. 301.

The Scheduled Districts of 
the Madhya Pradesh. Ditto <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 771.

The Scheduled Districts 
in Ganjam and Vizagapatam Ditto <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 870.

Assam (except the North  
  Lushai Hills).. Ditto <year>1897</year> Pt. I, p. 299.

The Porahat Estate in the 
Singhbhum District. Ditto <year>1897</year>, Pt. I, p. 1059.

It has been extended, by notification und er s. 5 of the last- 
mentioned Act, to the following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

Kumaon and Garhwal. See Gazette of India, <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 606.

The Tarai of the Province of Agra Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 505.

It has been extended to the New Provinces and Merged States, See Act 
59 of <year>1949</year>, and to the States of Tripura, Manipur and Vindhya Pradesh, 
See Act of 30 of <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>See the Civil Procedure Act, <year>1833</year> (3 and 4 will. 4, c. 42), s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

It is enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>926945</tid>
<number>1</number>Executors may sue and be sued in certain cases for wrongs 
committed in lifetime of deceased.-- An action may be maintained by the 
executors, administrators or representatives of any person deceased, 
for any wrong committed in the time of such person, which has 
occasioned pecuniary loss to his estate, for which wrong an action 
might have been maintained by such person, so as such wrong shall have 
been committed within one year before his death <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>; and the 
damages, when recovered, shall be part of the personal estate of such 
person;
and further, an action may be maintained against the executors or 
administrators or heirs or representatives of any person deceased for 
any wrong committed by him in his lifetime for which he would have 
been subject to an action, so as such wrong shall have been committed 
within one year before such person' s death <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>; and the d amages to 
be recovered in such action shall, if recovered against an executor or 
administrator bound to administer according to the English law, be 
payable in like order of administration as the simple contract debts 
of such person.



</article>



<article><tid>1933262</tid>
<number>2</number>Death of either party not to abate suit. Proviso.-- No action 
commenced under the provisions of this Act shall abate by reason of 
the death of either party, but the same may be continued by or against 
the executors, administrators or representatives of the party 
deceased: Provided that, in any case in which any such action shall be 
continued against the executors, administrators or representatives of 
a deceased party, such executors, administrators or representatives 
may set up a want of assets as a defence to the action, either wholly 
or in part, in the same manner as if the action had been originally 
commenced against them.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" and provided such action shall be brought wihtin one 
year after the death of such person" rep. by Act 9 of <year>1871</year>, Sch. 
I. For limitation, see now the Inidian Limitation Act, <year>1963</year> (36  
  of <year>1963</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" and so as such action shall be commenced within two 
years after the committing of the wrong" rep. by Act 9 of <year>1871</year>, 
s. 2. For limitation, See now Act 36 of <year>1963</year>.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>