<act><tid>449758</tid>
<title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> THE GOVERNMENT SEAL ACT, <year>1862</year>]</title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>1862</year> 
[ 28th February, <year>1862</year>.]
An Act to amend the law relating to the use of a Government Seal.

Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to adapt the law relating to 
the use of a Government seal to the present form of the Government in 
India; It is enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>97553</tid>
<number>1</number>Seal to be used instead of seal of East India Company.-- Whenever 
it is required by any Regulation of a Local Government or by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any 
Act of the Central Legislature] that the seal of the East India 
Company shall be affixed on behalf or by the authority of the 
Government to any instrument or document, it shall be lawful, if the 
seal is to be affixed on behalf or by the authority of a State 
Government to affix in lieu of the seal of the East India Company a 
seal bearing the designation of such State Government or, if the seal 
is to be affixed on behalf or by the authority of the Central 
Government a seal bearing <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the inscription" Government of India" 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>] and such instrument or document so sealed shall to all intents 
and purposes be as valid and effectual as if the seal so used had been 
that of the East India Company.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>242</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>).

Legislation on the subject was originally suggested in order to 
meet a difficulty as regards the seal to be used under Act 19 of 
<year>1838</year> (for the registration of coasting- vessels in the Bombay  
  Presidency). S. 8 of that Act requires that certificates of 
registry' shall be sealed with the seal of the East India 
Company,' and the Government of Bombay were advised by their law 
officers that no other seal could properly be used for such 
certificates until some Act is passed prescribing the seal to be 
used in lieu of the seal of the East India Company.

The Act has been declared to be in force in the whole of India, 
except Part B States and the Scheduled Districts, by the Laws 
Local Extent Act, <year>1874</year> (15 of <year>1874</year>), s. 3.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

West Jalpaiguri and the Western Davars. see Gazette of India, 
<year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 74.

The districts of Hazaribagh, Lohardaga (now the Ranchi District,  
  see Calcutta Gazette, <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 44) and Manbhum, and Pargana 
Dhalbhum and the Kolhan in the district of Singhbhum, see Gazette 
of India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

The Scheduled Districts in Ganjam and Vizagapatam, see Gazette of 
India, <year>1898</year>, Pt. I, p. 870.

The Scheduled portion of the Mirzapur district, see Gazette of 
India, <year>1879</year>, Pt. I. p. 383.

Jaunsar Bawar, see Gazette of India, <year>1879</year>, Pt. I, p. 382.

Assam (except the North Lushai Hills), see Gazette of India, 
<year>1897</year>, Pt. I, p. 299.

It has been extended, by notification under s. 5 of the last- 
mentioned Act, to the Scheduled Districts of Kumaon and Garhwal, 
see Gazette of India, <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 606.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (b) of the same 
Act, not to be in force in the Scheduled District of Lahaul, see 
Gazette of India, <year>1886</year>, Pt. I, p. 306.

It has been extended to the new States and Merged States by the 
Merged States (Laws) Act, <year>1949</year> (59 of <year>1949</year>), and to the States of 
Manipur, Tripura and Vindhya Pradesh by the Part C States (Laws) 
Act, <year>1950</year> (30 of <year>1950</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" any Act of the Governor- General of 
India in Council".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. ibid., for' the inscription" G. of I.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words' or" Govt. of the Federation of India"' rep. by the A. 
O. <year>1948</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>