<act><tid>2077</tid>
<title>THE ELECTRICITY (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

NO. 57 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 30th December, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act to amend the Electricity Act, <year>2003</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>1359035</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1920423</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Electricity (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>78109</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>297479</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 14.- In section 14 of the Electricity Act, <year>2003</year> 
 (36 of <year>2003</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), in the 
sixth proviso, for the brackets and words" (including the capital  
  adequacy, creditworthiness, or code of conduct)", the words" relating 
to the capital adequacy, creditworthiness, or code of conduct" shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>243640</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 42.- In section 42 of the principal Act, in sub- 
section (2), after the fourth proviso, the following proviso shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" Provided also that the State Commission shall, not later than five 
years from the date of commencement of the Electricity (Amendment) Act, 
<year>2003</year>, by regulations, provide such open access to all consumers who 
require a supply of electricity where the maximum power to be made 
available at any time exceeds one megawatt.".



</article>



<article><tid>460404</tid>
<number>4</number>Substitution of new section for section 121.- For section 121 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
Power of Appellate Tribunal.

" 121. Power of Appellate Tribunal.- The Appellate Tribunal may, after 
hearing the Appropriate Commission or other interested party, if any, 
from time to time, issue such orders, instructions or directions as it 
may deem fit, to any Appropriate Commission for the performance of its 
statutory functions under this Act.".



</article>



<article><tid>1766119</tid>
<number> 5</number> Amendment of section 135.- In section 135 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>1262080</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words" has been, is being, or is likely to 
be,", the words" has been or is being" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1586540</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b), for the words" has been, is being, or is likely to 
be,", the words" has been or is being" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>859484</tid>
<number>6</number>Substitution of new sections for sections 139 and 140.- For sections 
 139 and 140 of the principal Act, the following sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
Negligently breaking or damaging works.

" 139. Negligently breaking or damaging works.- Whoever, negligently 
breaks, injures, throws down or damages any material connected with the 
supply of electricity, shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
to ten thousand rupees.

Penalty for intentionally injuring works.

</article>



<article><tid>46389</tid>
<number>140</number>Penalty for intentionally injuring works.- Whoever, with intent to 
cut off the supply of electricity, cuts or injures, or attempts to cut 
or injure, any electric supply line or works, shall be punishable with 
fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees.".


</article>



<article><tid>1712962</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 146.- In section 146 of the principal Act, the 
following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that nothing contained in this section shall apply to the 
orders, instructions or directions issued under section 121.".

T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.




</article>



 </act>