<act><tid>214169</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN BAR COUNCILS ACT, <year>1926</year></title>

ACT No. 38 OF <year>1926</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 9th September, <year>1926</year>.]

An Act to provide for the constitution of Bar Councils <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and for 
other purposes.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the constitution and 
incorporation of Bar Councils for certain Courts <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to confer powers 
and impose duties on such Bar Councils, and to consolidate and amend 
the law relating to legal practioners entitled to practise in such 
Courts; It is hereby enacted as follows:--

PRELIMINARY






<article><tid>846725</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and application.-
<section><tid>1113973</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Indian Bar Councils Act, <year>1926</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>472599</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and 
Kashmir, and shall apply to the High Court of <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> every State] other 
than the State of Jammu and Kashmir and also to such Judicial 
Commissioners Courts in <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Union territories] as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare to be 
High Courts to which this Act applies.]
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>30</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been amended in its application to-- 
 (1) the High Court of Judicature at Nagpur by the C. P. and Berar 
Act 24 of <year>1939</year>: 
 (2) the Province of Madras by Mad. Act 9 of <year>1947</year>. 
ss. 1, 2, 17, 18 and 19 came into force at once. The rest 
of the Act came into force in respect of- 
 (i) the Calcutta High Court, ss. 3 to 7 from 1st March, <year>1928</year> (see  
  Gazette of India, <year>1928</year>, Pt. I, p. 325) and ss. 8 to 16 from 
1st July <year>1928</year> (see ibid., p. 382); 
 (ii) the Madras High Court, from 16th July, <year>1928</year> (see ibid.,  
  p. 382); 
 (iii) the Bombay High Court from 1st January, <year>1929</year> (see ibid.,  
  p. 714); 
 (iv) the Allahabad High Court from 1st June, <year>1928</year> (see ibid.,  
  p. 400); 
 (v) the Patna High Court from 1st January, <year>1929</year> (see ibid.,  
  p. 703); 
 (vi) the Oudh Chief Court from 1st March, <year>1928</year> (see ibid.,  
  p. 325); 
 (vii) the Nagpur High Court, ss. 3 to 7 from 1st January, <year>1937</year> 
and ss. 8 to 16 from 1st April, <year>1937</year>, see Gazette of India, 
<year>1936</year>, Pt. I, p. 1170. 
2. The words" in the Provinces of India" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for sub- section (2). 
4. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" every 
Part A State and of every Part B State". 
5. Subs., ibid., for" Part C States". 
6. Sub- section (3) omitted, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>434204</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation.- <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1641362</tid>
<number>1</number>] In this Act, unless there is anything  
repugnant in the subject or context,--

<subsection><tid>1094811</tid>
<number>a</number>" advocate" means an advocate entered in the roll of advocates of a 
High Court under the provisions of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1034567</tid>
<number>b</number>" Advocate- General" includes, where there is no Advocate- General, 
the Government Advocate and, where there is no Advocate- General or 
Government Advocate, such officer as the State Government may declare 
to be the Advocate- General for the purposes of this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1161650</tid>
<number>c</number>" High Court" means a High Court to which this Act applies; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>416136</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1738177</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In this Act" the State Government" means, in relation to any 
High Court, the State Government of the State in which the High Court 
has its principal seat.]
CONSTITUTION OF BAR COUNCILS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1142694</tid>
<number> 3</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Constitution and incorporation of Bar Councils.-
<section><tid>542800</tid>
<number>1</number>For every  
High Court a Bar Council shall be constituted in the manner 
hereinafter provided.

</section>

<section><tid>1093331</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Bar Council so constituted shall be a body corporate having 
perpetual succession and a common seal with power to acquire and hold 
property, both movable and immovable, and to contract, and shall by 
the name of the Bar Council of the High Court for which it has been 
constituted sue and be sued.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1195757</tid>
<number> 4</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Composition of Bar Councils.-
<section><tid>898293</tid>
<number>1</number>Every Bar Council shall  
consist of fifteen members, of whom--

<subsection><tid>648959</tid>
<number>a</number>one shall be the Advocate- General;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1768194</tid>
<number>b</number>four shall be persons nominated by the High Court, of whom not 
more than two may be Judges of that Court; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>426527</tid>
<number>c</number>ten shall be elected by the advocates of the High Court from 
amongst their number.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>804766</tid>
<number>2</number>the elected members of every Bar Council not less than five shall 
be persons who have for not less than ten years been entitled as of 
right to--
<pagefootnote><pagenum>31</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 2 may be deemed to have been renumbered as sub- section (1) of 
that section by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 2. Ins., ibid. 3. The provision of 
ss. 3 to 7, sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) of section 9, section 15 
and section 20, shall stand repealed in the territory for which the 
State Bar Council is constituted vide Act 25 of <year>1961</year>, s. 50 (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


practise in the High Court for which the Bar Council has been 
constituted.

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Explanation.-- For the purpose of election to the Bar Council for 
the High Court of Gujarat, the period of ten years aforesaid shall be 
computed after taking into account the period for which the person 
concerned was entitled as of right to practise in the High Court of 
Bombay or of Saurashtra or in the Judicial Commissioner' s Court of 
Kutch before the 1st day of May, <year>1960</year>.]


</section>

<section><tid>1129203</tid>
<number>3</number>Of the elected members of the Bar Councils to be constituted for 
the High Courts of Judicature at Fort William in Bengal and at Bombay 
such proportion as the High Court may direct in each case shall be 
persons who have, for such minimum period as the High Court may 
determine, been entitled to practise in the High Court in the exercise 
of its original jurisdiction, and such number as may be fixed by the 
High Court out of the said proportion shall be barristers of England 
or Ireland or members of the Faculty of Advocates in Scotland.

</section>

<section><tid>800890</tid>
<number>4</number>There shall be a Chairman and Vice- Chairman of each Bar Council 
elected by the Council in such manner as may be prescribed:
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Provided that the Advocates- General of West Bengal, Madras 
Maharashtra and Gujarat shall be Chairmen ex officio, respectively, of 
the Bar Councils constituted for the High Courts of those States.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1092319</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Special provisions regarding constitution of first Bar 
Councils.-
<section><tid>1882542</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (c) of sub-  
section (1) of section 4, the elected members of the first Bar Council 
constituted under this Act for any High Court shall be elected by and 
from amongst the advocates, vakils and pleaders who are on the date of 
the election entitled as of right to practise in the High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>747140</tid>
<number>2</number>The terms of office of the nominated and elected members of any 
such first Bar Council shall be three years from the date of the first 
meeting of the Council.



<pagefootnote><pagenum>32</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1960</year>, s. 72. 2. Subs. by s. 72, ibid., for 
the proviso. 3. The provisions of ss. 3 to 7, sub- section (1), (2) 
and (3) of section 9, section 15 and section 20, shall stand repealed 
in the territory for which the State Bar Council is constituted vide 
Act 25 of <year>1961</year>, s. 50 (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1331548</tid>
<number> 6</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to make rules regarding constitution and procedure of Bar 
Councils.-
<section><tid>23815</tid>
<number>1</number>Rules, consistent with this Act, may be made to provide  
for the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>599396</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which elections of members of the Bar Council shall 
be held; the method of determining, in accordance with the provisions 
of sub- sections (2) and (3) of section 4, the candidates who shall be 
declared to have been elected; the manner in which the result of 
elections shall be published; and the manner in which and the 
authority by which doubts and disputes as to the validity of an 
election shall be finally decided;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>833506</tid>
<number>b</number>the terms of office of nominated and elected members of the 
Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>598618</tid>
<number>c</number>the filling of casual vacancies in the Council;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1346904</tid>
<number>d</number>the convening of meetings of the Council, and the quorum necessary 
for the transaction of business thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1041227</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner of election and the respective terms of office of the 
Chairman, in cases where the Chairman is to be elected, and of the 
Vice- Chairman; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>476279</tid>
<number>f</number>any matter incidental or ancillary to any of the foregoing 
matters.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1118014</tid>
<number>2</number>The first rules under this section shall be made by the High 
Court, but the Bar Council may thereafter, with the previous sanction 
of the High Court, add to, amend or rescind any rules so made.

</section>

<section><tid>378201</tid>
<number>3</number>No election of a member or members to the Council shall be called 
in question on the ground that due notice thereof has not been given 
to any person entitled to vote thereat, if notice of the date fixed 
for the election has, not less than thirty days before that date, been 
published in the Official Gazette of the State, or of each State, as 
the case may be, in which the High Court exercises jurisdiction.

</section>

<section><tid>1396570</tid>
<number>4</number>Rules made under clause (b) of sub- section (1) may provide for the 
retirement of members from office by rotation and for the manner in 
which the order of such retirement shall be determined.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1843393</tid>
<number> 7</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power of Bar Council to make bye- laws.- The Bar Council may make 
bye- laws consistent with this Act and any rules made thereunder to 
provide for any of the following matters, namely:--
<section><tid>1492107</tid>
<number>a</number>the appointment of such ministerial officers and servants as the 
Bar Council may deem necessary, and the pay and allowances
<pagefootnote><pagenum>32A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The provisions of ss. 3 to 7, sub- section (1), (2) and (3) of 
section 9, section 15 and section 20, shall stand repealed in the 
territory for which the State Bar Council is constituted vide Act 25 
of <year>1961</year>, s. 50 (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


and other conditions of service of such officers and servents; and


</section>

<section><tid>800954</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment and constitution of Committees of the Council, the 
procedure of such Committees, and the determination of the powers or 
duties of the Council which may be delegated to such Committees.
Admission and enrolment of advocates

Admission and enrolment of advocates

ADMISSION AND ENROLMENT OF ADVOCATES




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1981260</tid>
<number> 8</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Enrolment of advocates.-
<section><tid>1410299</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall be entitled as of  
right to practise in any High Court, unless his name is entered in the 
roll of the advocates of the High Court maintained under this Act:
Provided that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to any attorney 
of the High Court.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>33</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>So much of the section as relates to the admission and enrolment 
of legal practioners repealed by the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25 of  
  <year>1961</year>), s. 50 (2)  (w. e. f. 1- 12- <year>1961</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>217089</tid>
<number>2</number>The High Court shall prepare and maintain a roll of advocates of 
the High Court in which shall be entered the names of-

<subsection><tid>1480508</tid>
<number>a</number>all persons who were, as advocates, vakils or pleaders, entitled 
as of right to practise in the High Court immediately before the date 
on which this section comes into force in respect thereof; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1232455</tid>
<number>b</number>all other persons who have been admitted to be advocates of the 
High Court under this Act:
Provided that such persons shall have paid in respect of enrolment the 
stamp- duty, if any, chargeable under the Indian Stamp Act, <year>1899</year> (2 of  
  <year>1899</year>), and a fee, payable to the Bar Council, which shall be ten 
rupees in the case of the persons referred to in clause (a), and in 
other cases such amount as may be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1403838</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Entries in the roll shall be made in the order of seniority, 
and such seniority shall be determined as follows, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1781364</tid>
<number>a</number>all such persons as are referred to in clause (a) of sub- section 
 (2) shall be entered first in the order in which they were 
respectively entitled to seniority inter se immediately before the 
date on which this section comes into force in respect of the High 
Court; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>182313</tid>
<number>b</number>the seniority of any other person admitted to be an advocate of 
the High Court under this Act after that date shall be determined by 
the date of his admission or, if he is a barrister, by the date of his 
admission or the date on which he was called to the Bar, whichever 
date is earlier:
Provided that, for the purposes of clause (b), the seniority of a 
person who before his admission to be an advocate was entitled as of 
right to practise in another High Court shall be determined by the 
date on which he became so entitled.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1002455</tid>
<number>4</number>The respective rights of pre- audience of advocates of the High 
Court shall be determined by seniority:
Provided that the Advocate- General shall have pre- audience over all 
other advocates <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>34</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- sections (3) and (4) ins. by Act. 13 of <year>1927</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" and King' s Counsel shall have pre- audience over all 
advocates except the Advocate- General" omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 
and Sch.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>599196</tid>
<number>5</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The High Court shall issue a certificate of enrolment to every 
person enrolled under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1042670</tid>
<number>6</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] The High Court shall send to the Bar Council a copy of the 
roll as prepared under this section, and shall thereafter communicate 
to the Bar Council all alterations in, and additions to, the roll as 
soon as the same have been made.

</section>

<section><tid>1145219</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] The Bar Council shall enter in the copy of the roll all 
alterations and additions so communicated to it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>133576</tid>
<number> 9</number> Qualifications and admission of advocates.- <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1624089</tid>
<number>1</number>The Bar Council  
may, with the previous sanction of the High Court, make rules to 
regulate the admission of persons to be advocates of the High Court:
Provided that such rules shall not limit or in any way affect the 
power of the High Court to refuse admission to any person at its 
discretion.


</section>

<section><tid>974800</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules shall provide for the following matters, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>715632</tid>
<number>a</number>the qualifications to be possessed by persons applying for 
admission as advocates;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1096053</tid>
<number>b</number>the form and manner in which applications shall be made to the 
High Court for admission;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>668001</tid>
<number>c</number>the giving of notice by the High Court to the Bar Council of all 
such applications;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>445599</tid>
<number>d</number>the hearing by the High Court of any objection preferred on behalf 
of the Bar Council to the admission of any applicant; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1614119</tid>
<number>e</number>the charging of fees payable to the Bar Council in respect of 
enrolment.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>299618</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Rules made under this section shall provide that no woman shall 
be disqualified for admission to be an advocate by reason only of her 
sex.

</section>

<section><tid>1111913</tid>
<number>4</number>Nothing in this section or in any other provision of this Act 
shall be deemed to limit or in any way affect the powers of the High 
Courts of Judicature at Fort William in Bengal and at Bombay to 
prescribe the qualifications to be possessed by persons applying to 
practise in those High Courts respectively in the exercise of their 
original jurisdiction or the powers
<pagefootnote><pagenum>35</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Sub- section (3), (4) and (5) re- numbered as sub- sections (5), (6) 
and (7) respectively by Act 13 of <year>1927</year>, s. 2. 2. The provisions of 
ss. 3 to 7, sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) of section 9, section 15 
and section 20, shall stand repealed in the territory for which the 
State Bar Council is constituted vide Act 25 of <year>1961</year>, s. 50 (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of those High Courts to grant or refuse, as they think fit, any such 
applications <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or to prescribe the conditions under which such 
person shall be entitled to practise or plead].

MISCONDUCT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>821838</tid>
<number>10</number>[ Punishment of advocate for misconduct.]- Rep. by the Advocates 
Act, <year>1961</year> (25 of <year>1961</year>), s. 50 (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1963</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1857402</tid>
<number>11</number>[ Tribunal of Bar Council.]- Rep. by the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25  
  of <year>1961</year>), s. 50 (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1963</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1184357</tid>
<number>12</number>[ Procedure in inquiries.]- Rep. by the Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25  
  of <year>1961</year>), s. 50 (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1963</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>1478156</tid>
<number>13</number>[ Powers of the Tribunal and Courts in inquires.]- Rep. by the 
Advocates Act, <year>1961</year> (25 of <year>1961</year>), s. 50 (4)  (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1963</year>).
MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>408543</tid>
<number> 14</number> Right of advocates to practise.-
<section><tid>1789990</tid>
<number>1</number>An advocate shall be  
entitled as of right to practise--

<subsection><tid>1311383</tid>
<number>a</number>subject to the provisions of sub- section (4) of section 9, in the 
High Court of which he is an advocate, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>586719</tid>
<number>b</number>save as otherwise provided by sub- section (2) or by or under any 
other law for the time being in force in any other Court <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> and 
before any other Tribunal or person legally authorized to take 
evidence, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1766597</tid>
<number>c</number>before any other authority or person before whom such advocate is 
by or under the law for the time being in force entitled to practise.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>92641</tid>
<number>2</number>Where rules have been made by any High Court within the meaning of 
clause (24) of section 3 of the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of  
  <year>1897</year>), or in the case of a High Court for which a Bar Council has been 
constituted under this Act, by such Bar Council under section 15, 
regulating the conditions subject to which advocates of other High 
Courts may be permitted to practise in the High Court, such advocates 
shall not be entitled to practise therein otherwise than subject to 
such conditions.

</section>

<section><tid>1546262</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to limit or in any way 
affect the power of the High Court of Judicature at Fort William in 
Bengal or of the High Court of Judicature at Bombay to make rules
<pagefootnote><pagenum>36</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 13 of <year>1927</year>, s. 3. 2. The words" in the Provinces" 
omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


determining the persons who shall be entitled respectively to plead 
and to act in the High Court in the exercise of its original 
jurisdiction.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>670604</tid>
<number> 15</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> General power of Bar Councils to make rules.- A Bar Council 
may, with the previous sanction of the High Court for which it is 
constituted, make rules consistent with this Act to provide for and 
regulate any of the following matters, namely:--
<section><tid>1235589</tid>
<number>a</number>the rights and duties of the advocates of the High Court and their 
discipline and professional conduct;

</section>

<section><tid>527059</tid>
<number>b</number>the conditions subject to which advocates of other High Courts may 
be permitted to practise in the High Court;

</section>

<section><tid>1381842</tid>
<number>c</number>the giving of facilities for legal education and training and the 
holding and conduct of examinations by the Bar Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1594076</tid>
<number>d</number>the charging of fees payable to the Bar Council in respect of the 
enjoyment of educational facilities provided, or of the right to 
appear at examinations held, by the Bar Council;

</section>

<section><tid>1826709</tid>
<number>e</number>the investment and management of the funds of the Bar Council; 
and

</section>

<section><tid>41175</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter in respect of which the High Court may require 
rules to be made under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1456987</tid>
<number>16</number>Power to fix fees payable as costs.- The High Court shall make 
rules for fixing and regulating by taxation or otherwise the fees 
payable as costs by any party in respect of the fees of his 
adversary' s advocate upon all proceedings in the High Court or in any 
Court subordinate thereto.


</article>



<article><tid>1694818</tid>
<number>17</number>Indemnity against legal proceedings.- No suit or other legal 
proceeding shall lie against a Bar Council or any Committee, Tribunal 
or member of a Bar Council for any act in good faith done or intended 
to be done in pursuance of the provisions of this act or of any rule 
made thereunder.


</article>



<article><tid>945063</tid>
<number>18</number>Publication of rules.- All rules made under this Act shall be 
published in the Official Gazette of the State, or of each State, as 
the case may be, in which the High Court by which or with whose 
sanction the rules are made exercises jurisdiction.


</article>



<article><tid>1126417</tid>
<number> 19</number> Amendement of enactments, etc.-
<section><tid>188244</tid>
<number>1</number>When sections 8 to 16 come  
into force in respect of any High Court, any enactment mentioned in 
the first column of the Schedule which is in force in any State in
<pagefootnote><pagenum>37</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The provisions of ss. 3 to 7, sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) of 
section 9, section 15 and section 20, shall stand repealed in the 
territory for which the State Bar Council is constituted vide Act 25 
of <year>1961</year>, s. 50 (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


which the High Court exercises jurisdiction shall, for the purpose of 
its application to that State, be amended to the extent and in the 
manner specified in the second column of the Schedule.


</section>

<section><tid>755762</tid>
<number>2</number>When sections 8 to 16 come into force in respect of any High Court 
of Judicature established by Letters Patent, this Act shall have 
effect in respect of such Court notwithstanding anything contained in 
such Letters Patent, and such Letters Patent shall, in so far as they 
are inconsitent with this Act or any rules made thereunder, be deemed 
to have been repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1365754</tid>
<number>3</number>When sections 8 to 16 come into force in respect of the High Court 
of Judicature at Bombay, the Bombay Pleaders' Act, <year>1920</year> (Bom. Act 17  
  of <year>1920</year>) except section 7 thereof, shall cease to apply to or in 
respect of any person enrolled as an advocate of the High Court under 
this Act, and nothing in that Act shall be deemed to authorize the 
admission or enrolment of any person as a vakil or pleader of the High 
Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1574597</tid>
<number>4</number>When this Act has come into force in respect of any High Court, 
any provision of any other enactment or any order, scheme, rule, form 
or bye- law made thereunder, which was before that date applicable to 
advocates, vakils or pleaders entitled to practise in such High Court 
shall, unless such a construction is repugnant to the context or to 
any provision made by or under this Act, be construed as applying to 
advocates of the High Court enrolled under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1516729</tid>
<number> 20</number> Transitional provision regarding certain Bar Councils 
affected by States' reorganisation.
<section><tid>634992</tid>
<number>1</number>The Bar Councils for the High  
Courts of the States of Bombay, Madhya Pradesh, Mysore, Punjab, 
Rajasthan and Travancore- Cochin functioning immediately before the 1st 
day of November, <year>1956</year>, shall be deemed to be the Bar Councils for the 
High Courts of the corresponding new States of Bombay, Madhya Pradesh, 
Mysore, Punjab, Rajasthan and Kerala, respectively.

</section>

<section><tid>1577600</tid>
<number>2</number>As from the said day,--

<subsection><tid>1119780</tid>
<number>a</number>the Bar Councils for the High Courts of Hyderabad and Saurashtra 
shall stand dissolved, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>505221</tid>
<number>b</number>the assets and liabilities of the Bar Council for the High Court 
of Hyderabad shall stand transferred to, the Bar Councils for the High 
Courts of Andhra Pradesh, Bombay and Mysore and be divided among them 
in such proportion as may be agreed upon, and in default of such 
agreement, in the proportion of 57. 61: 27. 81: 14. 58.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>38</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>. 2. The 
porvision of ss. 3 to 7, sub- sections (1), (2) and (3) of section 9, 
section 15 and section 20, shall stand repealed in the territory for 
which the State Bar Council is constituted vide Act 25 of <year>1961</year>, s. 
50 (1).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


SCHEDULE

AMENDMENT OF ENACTMENTS

THE SCHEDULE

 (See section 19)

AMENDMENT OF ENACTMENTS


<pagefootnote><pagenum>39</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Enactments amended Extent and manner of amendment 
The Legal Practi- (1) In section 4, after the words" with the 
tioners Act, <year>1879</year>. permission of the Court" the words and 
figures" or in the case of a High Court 
in respect of which the Indian Bar Coun- 
cils Act, <year>1926</year>, is in force, subject to 
rules made under that Act" shall be ins- 
erted.

(2) In section 6, clauses (a) and (b), after 
the words" Royal Charter" the words and 
figures" in respect of which the Indian 
Bar Councils Act, <year>1926</year>, is not in force" 
shall be inserted.

(3) To section 38 the following words and fi- 
gures shall be added, namely:--

" and except as provided by section 36, 
nothing in this Act applies to persons 
enrolled as advocates of any High Court 
under the Indian Bar Council Act, <year>1926</year>".

(4) In section 41, sub- section (1), after the 
words" Royal Charter" the words and fig- 
ures" in respect of which the Indian Bar 
Councils Act, <year>1926</year>, is not in force" shall 
be inserted.


The Indian Stanp Act, In Article 30 of the First Schedule after 
<year>1899</year>. the words" High Court," where they first 
occur the words and figures" under the 
Indian Bar Councils Act, <year>1926</year>, or" shall 
be inserted.

The Madras Stamp In Article 25 of Schedule 1A, after the words 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1922</year>." High Court," where they first occur, the 
words and figures" under the Indian Bar 
Councils Act, <year>1926</year>, or" shall be inserted.

The Bengal Stamp In Article 30 of Schedule 1A, after the words 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1922</year>." High Court," where they first occur, the 
words and figures" under the Indian Bar 
Councils Act, <year>1926</year>, or" shall be inserted.

The Indian Stamp In Article 30 of Schedule 1A, after the words 
 (Punjab Amendment)" High Court," where they first occur, the 
Act, <year>1922</year>. words and figures" under the Indian Bar 
Councils Act, <year>1926</year>, or" shall be inserted.

The Assam Stamp In Article 30 of Schedule 1A, after the words 
 (Amendment) Act, <year>1922</year>." High Court," where they first occur, the 
words and figures" under the Indian Bar 
Councils Act, <year>1926</year>, or" shall be inserted.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



 </act>