<act><title>


The Suppression Of 
    Unlawful Acts Against Safety Of Civil 
    Aviation Act, 1982</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Suppression of Unlawful Acts against Safety of 
    Civil Aviation Act, 1982.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India and, save as otherwise provided in this Act, it 
    applies also to any offence under section 3 committed outside India by any 
    person.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 

 
 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “aircraft” means any aircraft, whether 
    or not registered in India, other than a military aircraft or an aircraft 
    used in customs or police service;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “aircraft registered in India” means an 
    aircraft which is for the time being registered in India;   
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>bb</number>    
    “airport” means an aerodrome as defined in clause (2) of section 2 of the 
    Aircraft Act, 1934 (22 of 1934);]  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “Convention country” means a country in 
    which the Montreal Convention is for the time being in force;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “military aircraft” means an aircraft 
    of the naval, military, air force or any other armed forces of any country 
    and includes every aircraft commanded for the time being by a person in such 
    force detailed for the purpose;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “Montreal Convention” means the 
    Convention for the Suppression of Unlawful Acts against the Safety of Civil 
    Aviation signed at Montreal on the 23rd day of September, 1971.   
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of this Act,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    an aircraft shall be deemed to be in 
    flight at any time from the moment when all its external doors are closed 
    following embarkation until the moment when any such door is opened for 
    disembarkation, and in the case of a forced landing, the flight shall be 
    deemed to continue until the competent authorities of the country in which 
    such forced landing takes place take over the responsibility for the 
    aircraft and for persons and property on board;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    an aircraft shall be deemed to be in 
    service from the beginning of the pre-flight preparation of the aircraft by 
    the ground staff or by the crew for a specific flight until twenty-four 
    hours after any landing and the period of such service shall include the 
    entire period during which the aircraft is in flight.
 
 
  




 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Offence 
    of committing violence on board an aircraft in flight, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever unlawfully and intentionally—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    commits an act of violence against a 
    person on board an aircraft in flight which is likely to endanger the safety 
    of such aircraft; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    destroys an aircraft in service or 
    causes damage to such aircraft in such a manner as to render it incapable of 
    flight or which is likely to endanger its safety in flight; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    places or causes to be placed on an 
    aircraft in service, by any means whatsoever, a device or substance which is 
    likely to destroy that aircraft, or to cause damage to it which renders it 
    incapable of flight, or to cause damage to it which is likely to endanger 
    its safety in flight; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    communicates such information which he 
    knows to be false so as to endanger the safety of an aircraft in flight,  
 
shall be punished with imprisonment for life 
    and shall also be liable to fine.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever 
    attempts to commit, or abets the commission of, any offence under 
    sub-section (1) shall also be deemed to have committed such offence and 
    shall be punished with the punishment provided for such offence.  
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> 
    Offence at airport.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever, at any airport, unlawfully and 
    intentionally, using any device, substance or weapon,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    commits an act of violence which is 
    likely to cause grievous hurt or death of any person; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    destroys or seriously damages any 
    aircraft or facility at an airport or disrupts any service at the airport,  
 
endangering or threatening to endanger safety 
    at that airport, shall be punished with imprisonment for life and shall also 
    be liable to fine.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever 
    attempts to commit, or abets the commission of, any offence under 
    sub-section (1) shall also be deemed to have committed such offence and 
    shall be punished with the punishment provided for such offence.]  
  







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Destruction of, or damage to, air navigation facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever unlawfully and intentionally destroys or damages air navigation 
    facilities or interferes with their operation in such a manner as is likely 
    to endanger the safety of the aircraft in flight shall be punished with 
    imprisonment for life and shall also be liable to fine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whoever 
    attempts to commit, or abets the commission of, any offence under 
    sub-section (1) shall also be deemed to have committed such offence and 
    shall be punished with the punishment provided for such offence.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the 
    provisions of sub-section (2), where an offence under section 3 is committed 
    outside India, the person committing such offence may be dealt with in 
    respect thereof as if such offence had been committed at any place within 
    India at which he may be found.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No Court 
    shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under section 3 which is 
    committed outside India unless—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    such offence is committed on board an 
    aircraft registered in India;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    such offence is committed on board an 
    aircraft which is for the time being leased without crew to a lessee who has 
    his principal place of business, or where he has no such place of business, 
    his permanent residence in India; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the alleged offender is a citizen of 
    India or is on board the aircraft in relation to which such offence is 
    committed when it lands in India or is found in India.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>5A</number> 
    Conferment of powers of investigation, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything 
    contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), for the 
    purposes of this Act, the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, confer on any officer of the Central Government, powers of 
    arrest, investigation and prosecution exercisable by a police officer under 
    the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All 
    officers of police and all officers of Government are hereby required and 
    empowered to assist the officer of the Central Government referred to in 
    sub-section (1), in the execution of the provisions of this Act.]
 
 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>5B</number> 
    Designated Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> For the 
    purpose of providing for speedy trial, the State Government shall, with the 
    concurrence of the Chief Justice of the High Court, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, specify a Court of Session to be a Designated Court for 
    such area or areas as may be specified in the notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
    (2 of 1974), a Designated Court shall, as far as practicable, hold the trial 
    on a day-to-day basis.]
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>5C</number> 
    Offences triable by Designated Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
    (2 of 1974),—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all offences under this Act shall be 
    triable only by the Designated Court specified under sub­-section (1) of 
    section 5B.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where a person accused of or suspected 
    of the commission of an offence under this Act is forwarded to a Magistrate 
    under sub-section (2) or sub-section (2A) of section 167 of the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), such Magistrate may authorise the 
    detention of such person in such custody as he thinks fit for a period not 
    exceeding fifteen days in the whole where such Magistrate is a Judicial 
    Magistrate and seven days in the whole where such Magistrate is an Executive 
    Magistrate:  
 
Provided that where such Magistrate 
    considers,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    when such person is forwarded to him as 
    aforesaid; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    upon or at any time before the expiry 
    of the period of detention authorised by him,  
 
that the detention of such person is 
    unnecessary, he shall order such person to be forwarded to the Designated 
    Court having jurisdiction;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Designated Court may exercise, in 
    relation to the person forwarded to it under clause (b), the same power 
    which a Magistrate having jurisdiction to try a case may exercise under 
    section 167 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) in relation 
    to an accused person in such case who has been forwarded to him under that 
    section;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a Designated Court may, upon a perusal 
    of a complaint made by an officer of the Central Government or the State 
    Government, as the case may be, authorised in this behalf, take cognizance 
    of that offence without the accused being committed to it for trial.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> When 
    trying an offence under this Act, a Designated Court may also try an offence 
    other than an offence under this Act, with which the accused may, under the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), be charged at the same trial.]
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>5D</number> 
    Application of the Code to proceedings before a Designated Court.—Save 
    as otherwise provided in this Act, the provisions of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) shall apply to the proceedings before a 
    Designated Court and the person conducting a prosecution before a Designated 
    Court shall be deemed to be a Public Prosecutor.] 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Provisions as to extradition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The offences under section 3 and section 4 shall be deemed to have been 
    included as extraditable offences and provided for in all the extradition 
    treaties made by India with Convention countries and which extend to, and 
    are binding on India on the date of commencement of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of the application of the Extradition Act, 1962 (34 of 1962) to 
    offences under this Act, any aircraft registered in a Convention country 
    shall, at any time while that aircraft is in flight, be deemed to be within 
    the jurisdiction of that country, whether or not it is for the time being 
    also within the jurisdiction of any other country.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>6A</number> 
    Provision as to bail.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code 
    of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), no person accused of an offence 
    punishable under this Act shall, if in custody, be released on bail or on 
    his own bond unless—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the Public Prosecutor 
    has been given an opportunity to oppose the application for such release; 
    and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    where the Public 
    Prosecutor opposes the application, the Court is satisfied that there are 
    reasonable grounds for believing that he is not guilty of such offence and 
    that he is not likely to commit any offence while on bail.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    limitations on granting of bail specified in sub-section (1) are in addition 
    to the limitations under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 or any other 
    law for the time being in force on granting of bail.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing 
    contained in this section shall be deemed to affect the special powers of 
    the High Court regarding bail under section 439 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Contracting parties to Convention.—The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, certify as 
    to who are the contracting parties to the Montreal Convention and to what 
    extent they have availed themselves of the provisions of the Convention, and 
    any such notification shall be conclusive evidence of the matters certified 
    therein.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Power to 
    treat certain aircraft to be registered in convention countries.—If 
    the Central Government is satisfied that the requirements of Article 9 of 
    the Montreal Convention have been satisfied in relation to any aircraft, it 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that such aircraft 
    shall, for the purposes of this Act, be treated as registered in such 
    Convention country as may be specified in the notification.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Previous 
    sanction necessary for prosecution.—No 
    prosecution for an offence under this Act shall be instituted except with 
    the previous sanction of the Central Government.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

<footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>9A</number> 
    Presumptions as to offences under sections 3, 3A and 4.—In a prosecution 
    for an offence under sections 3, 3A and 4, if it is proved—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>    that the arms, 
    ammunition or explosives were recovered from the possession of the accused 
    and there is reason to believe that such arms, ammunition or explosives of 
    similar nature were used in the commission of such offence; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    that there is evidence 
    of violence committed by the accused against any person in connection with 
    the commission of such offence, 
 
 the 
    Designated Court shall presume, unless the contrary is proved, that the 
    accused had committed such offence.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person 
    for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance 
    of the provisions of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No suit or 
    other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central Government for any 
    damage caused or likely to be caused for anything which is in good faith 
    done or intended to be done in pursuance of the provisions of this Act.  

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Came into force on 
    15-11-1982 vide notification No. S.O. 779(E), dated 12th November, 
    1982, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Ins. by Act 40 of 
    1994, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 40 of 
    1994, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   
    Ins. by Act 40 of 1994, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by Act 40 of 
    1994, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by Act 40 of 
    1994, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Ins. by Act 40 of 
    1994, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   
    Ins. by Act 40 of 1994, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   
    Ins. by Act 40 of 1994, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-10-1996).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>