<act><title>


The National Trust for welfare of persons with 
autism, cerebral palsy, mental retardation 
and multiple disabilities rules, 20001</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, 
Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disabilities Rules, 2000.
 </section></article><article>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  "Act" means the National Trust for Welfare of Persons with Autism, 
Cerebral Palsy, Mental Retardation and Multiple Disabilities Act, 1999 (44 of 
1999);
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  "Form" means the form annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  "State level agency" means any State authority or committee 
constituted by the Board under section 13 of the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  "year" means the financial year commencing from the 1st day of April 
and ending on the 31st day of March following;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  all other words and expressions used herein and not defined but 
defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
Act.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Procedure for 
election of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall make the initial appointment by nominating nine 
persons as members on the Board, from amongst the registered organisations out 
of which three members each shall be from voluntary organisations, association 
of parents of persons with autism, cerebral palsy, mental retardation and 
multiple disability and from association of persons with disability for a term 
of three years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board shall, three 
months prior to the expiry of the term of office of the nine members 
representing the registered organisations invite nominations from amongst the 
organisations registered with it under section 12 of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The vacancies caused 
on completion of the term of office of these nine members shall be distributed 
amongst the registered organisations with three members each from (a) voluntary 
organisations, (b) association of parents of persons with autism, cerebral 
palsy, mental retardation and multiple disability, and (c) association of 
persons with disability, in such manner that amongst three voluntary 
organisations under clause (a), one each shall be working in the area of mental 
retardation, in the area of autism and in the area of cerebral palsy; from 
amongst three association of parents of persons with disability under clause 
(b), one each shall be from the area of mental retardation, autism and multiple 
disabilities; and from amongst three representatives of associations of persons 
with disabilities under clause (c), one shall be from the area of cerebral palsy 
and two from the area of multiple disabilities.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the number of 
nominations received by the Board is more than the number of vacancies, the 
Board shall hold elections by postal ballot for the vacancies.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where nominations not 
received for any category representing registered organisation as specified in 
sub-rule (2), the Board may make appointment by nomination to the given vacancy.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Salary.—The 
salary of the Chairperson shall be equivalent to the basic pay of the Secretary 
to the Government of India and as admissible dearness allowance and city 
compensatory allowance:
 
Provided that where the 
Chairperson is a retired person from the Central Government or a State 
Government or Union Territory Administration or semi-Government body or Public 
Sector Undertaking or a recognised research institution or other autonomous or 
statutory body, the salary payable together with the pension or pensionary value 
of the terminable benefits or both received by him shall not exceed the basic 
pay of Secretary to the Government of India.
  
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> 

1[Daily allowance] 
and the travelling allowance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson shall be entitled to 

1[daily allowance], 
city compensatory allowance, travelling allowance as per rules applicable to the 
Secretary to the Government of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The non-official 
members shall be eligible for receiving sitting fee of rupees five hundred for 
each day of the meeting of the Board and they shall also be paid travelling 
allowances as per the rules of the Central Government for attending the Board 
meetings.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Powers and duties of 
the Chairperson.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson shall be responsible for calling and presiding over all the 
meetings of the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson shall 
move the Board to take into consideration his views in regard to any matter, 
which is required to be considered by it, or any matter required by the Central 
Government to be considered by the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson shall 
be responsible for the proper functioning of the Trust including local level 
committees and ensure implementation of the policies and programmes of the 
Trust.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairperson may 
give directions to the Chief Executive Officer for implementation of the 
decision taken by the Board.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Membership Roll.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Member-Secretary shall keep a record of names of the members and their 
addresses.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a member changes 
his address, he shall notify the new address to the Member-Secretary, who shall 
thereupon enter his new address, in the official records, and if he fails to 
notify his new address, the address as in the official records shall for all 
purposes be treated as his correct address.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Notice of meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The meetings of the Board shall ordinarily be held at the Trust headquarters on 
such dates as may be fixed by the Chairperson.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson shall 
upon the written request of not less than five members of the Board, call a 
special meeting of the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Fifteen clear days' 
notice of an ordinary meeting and five clear days' notice of special meeting 
specifying the time and the place at which such meeting is to be held and the 
business to be transacted thereat, shall be given by the Member-Secretary to the 
members.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The notice of a 
meeting may be given to the members by delivering the same by messenger or 
sending it by registered post to his last known place of residence or business 
in such other manner as the Chairperson, may, in the circumstances of the case 
thinks fit or by electronic mail.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No member shall be 
entitled to bring forward for the consideration of the meeting any matter of 
which he has not given ten clear days' notice to the Member-Secretary, unless 
the Chairperson in his discretion, permits him to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Board may adjourn 
its meetings from day to day or to any particular day.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where a meeting of the 
Board is adjourned from day to day, notice of such adjourned meeting shall be 
given to the members available at the place where the meeting was adjourned by a 
messenger and it shall not be necessary to give notice of the adjourned meeting 
to other members.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Where a meeting of the 
Board is adjourned not from day to day but from the day on which the meeting is 
to be held to another date, notice of such meeting shall be given to all the 
members as provided is sub-rule (4) of this rule.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Presiding Officer.—The 
Chairperson shall preside at every meeting of the Board and in his absence, the 
members present shall elect one of the members to preside over the meeting.
  
</article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>10</number> Quorum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
One-third of the total members shall form the quorum for any meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a meeting of the 
Board cannot be held for want of quorum, then, the meeting shall automatically 
stand adjourned till the same day in the next week, at the same time and place, 
or if that day is a public holiday, till the next succeeding date which is not 
public holiday, at the same time and place.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notice of the 
adjourned meeting shall be given to all the members.]
 
 









</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Minutes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The record of the names of the members who attend the meeting and of the 
proceedings shall be kept in a book to be maintained for that purpose by the 
Member-Secretary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The minutes of the 
meeting shall be circulated to all concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The minutes of the 
previous meeting shall be read at the beginning of every succeeding meeting, and 
shall be confirmed and signed by the presiding officer at such meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The proceedings shall 
be open to inspection by any member at the office of the Member-Secretary, 
during office hours.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Maintaining order 
at meeting.—The 
presiding officer shall maintain order at the meeting.
  
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Business to be 
transacted at a meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Except with the permission of the presiding officer, no business which is not 
entered in the agenda or of which notice has not been given by a member in 
advance under sub-rule (3) of rule 8, shall be transacted at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> At any meeting 
business shall be transacted in the order in which it is entered in the agenda, 
unless otherwise resolved in the meeting with the permission of the presiding 
officer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Either at the 
beginning of the meeting or after the conclusion of the debate on a motion 
during the meeting, the presiding officer or a member may suggest a change in 
the order of business as entered in the agenda and if the Chairperson agrees, 
such a change shall take place.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Decision by 
majority.—All 
questions considered at a meeting shall be decided by a majority of votes of the 
members present and voting and in the event of equality of votes, the 
Chairperson or in his absence, the member presiding at the meeting, as the case 
may be, shall have a second or casting vote.
  
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Appointment, powers 
and duties of the Chief Executive Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The appointment to the post of Chief Executive Officer shall be made through the 
Central Staffing Scheme of the Central Government:
 
Provided that experience 
in the field of disability, rehabilitation, administrative capability and any 
other such conditions as the Central Government may consider appropriate shall 
be kept in view.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer shall be of the rank of Joint Secretary to the Central Government and 
shall draw the salary and avail benefits availed by the Joint Secretary to the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The term of office of 
the Chief Executive Officer shall be for a period of three years or his 
superannuation at the age of 60 years, whichever is earlier.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Subject to the general 
control and directions of the Board, the Chief Executive Officer shall exercise 
powers of the Head of Department.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer shall be in-charge of the management of the Trust and exercise such 
powers in respect of the affairs of the Trust, as may be delegated to him by the 
Chairperson from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer shall be responsible for the administrative control and management of 
the office and shall perform such other duties as may be directed by the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer shall be responsible for maintaining proper accounts of the Trust.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> All contracts shall be 
executed by the Chief Executive Officer in consultation with the Board and as 
per the regulations made by the Board from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer as the Member-Secretary of the Board shall be responsible for 
maintaining all records pertaining to the meetings of the Board and business 
arising thereof.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Application for 
guardianship.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The application by a parent, relative or registered organisation for appointment 
of guardian for a person with disability shall be made to the local level 
committee in Form A.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The confirmation of 
appointment of guardian on such application shall be made in Form B.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A quarterly report in 
the prescribed format shall be given by the local level committee to the Board 
or to the State level agency authorised by the Board giving particulars of the 
applications received and orders passed thereon.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Procedure for 
removal of guardian.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) The local level committee upon receiving an application for removal of a 
guardian from a parent or a relative of a person with disability or a registered 
organisation on the grounds specified in clauses 
<subsection><number>a</number> and (b) of sub-section (1) 
of section 17 of the Act, shall appoint a team of investigators consisting not 
less than three persons.
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> The team shall 
consist of one representative of parent organization, one representative of the 
association for the disabled and one Government official associated with 
disability not below the rank of Assistant Director.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number> While taking a 
decision on the appointment of guardian, the local level committee shall ensure 
that the person whose name has been suggested for appointment as guardian is—
 <subsubsubsection>
       
<number>a</number>  a citizen of India;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>b</number>  is not of unsound mind or is currently undergoing treatment for mental 
illness;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>c</number>  does not have a history of criminal conviction;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>d</number>  is not a destitute and dependent on others for his own living; and
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>e</number>  has not been declared insolvent or bankrupt.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number> In case of an 
institution or organisation being considered by the local level committee for 
appointment as a guardian, the following guidelines shall be followed:—
 <subsubsubsection>
       
<number>a</number>  the institution should be recognised by the State or the Central 
Government;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>b</number>  the institution should have a minimum of 2 years' experience in 
offering disability rehabilitation services including running residential 
facilities or hostel to the respective category of persons with disability;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>c</number>  the residential facility or hostel for persons with disabilities shall 
maintain minimum standards in terms of space, staff, furniture, rehabilitation 
and medical facilities as specified by the Board.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number> The team of 
investigators while investigating a complaint for assessing the abuse or neglect 
of a person with disability shall follow the guidelines specified by the Board.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number> The following Acts of 
commission or omission shall constitute abuse or neglect on the part of the 
guardian, namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
       
<number>a</number>  solitary confinement of person which disability in a room for longer 
period of time;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>b</number>  chaining of the person with disability;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>c</number>  beating or treating a person with disability resulting in bruises, 
skin or tissue damage (not due to his injurious behaviour indulged by the 
persons with disabilities);
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>d</number>  sexual abuse;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>e</number>  long deprivation of physical needs such as food, water and clothing;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
        
<number>f</number>  no provision or non-compliance of rehabilitation or training 
programmes as specified by experts in the field of disability rehabilitation;
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>g</number>  misappropriation or misutilisation of the property of the person with 
disability; and
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       
<number>h</number>  lack of facilities or no provision of trained or adequate staff for 
meeting the training and management needs of the persons with disabilities.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The team of 
investigators shall submit their report within a period of ten days.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Upon receiving the 
report of the investigation team, the local level committee shall take the final 
decision within the period of ten days on the removal of the guardian against 
whom the complaint has been received after giving the said guardian an 
opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The local level 
committee shall record in writing its reasons for removal of the guardian or 
rejection of the application.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Form in which 
Budget of the Trust shall be forwarded to the Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief Executive Officer of the Trust shall prepare the budget estimates for 
the next financial year and submit the same to the Board by the 31st July.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board shall 
approve the budget estimates in its annual meeting by the 20th September.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The budget estimates 
shall be revised by the Chief Executive Officer keeping in view the observations 
of the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The duly approved 
budget estimates will be submitted by the Chief Executive Officer to the Central 
Government by 30th September of each year.
  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>19</number> Maintenance of fund, operation 
of accounts and preparation of annual statement of accounts.—
<section><number>1</number> The funds of the Trust shall 
be deposited in a nationalised bank and operated by any two of the three 
signatories nominated by the Board, one of the three being the Chief Executive 
Officer.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Trust shall maintain 
proper accounts and other relevant records and prepare the annual statement of 
accounts including the statement of income and expenditure, receipt and 
payments, and the balance sheet.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The accounts of the Trust 
shall be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor General of India at such 
intervals as may be specified by him and any expenses incurred in connection 
with such audit shall be payable by the Board to the Comptroller and Auditor 
General of India.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Comptroller and Auditor 
General of India and any other person appointed by him in connection with the 
audit of the accounts of the Trust shall have the same rights, privileges and 
authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor General 
of India has in connection with the audit of Government accounts and in 
particular, shall have the right to demand the production of books of account, 
connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect the offices of 
the Trust.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The accounts of the Trust as 
certified by the Comptroller and Auditor General of India or any other person 
appointed by him in this behalf, together with the audit report thereon, shall 
be forwarded by the 31st December every year to the Central Government, and that 
Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House of 
Parliament.
  </section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Appropriation and 
re-appropriation.—The 
Chief Executive Officer with the approval of the Board shall have the power to 
appropriate or re-appropriate for valid reasons the funds from one primary or 
secondary unit to another and to have the same ratified by the Board in its next 
meeting.
  
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Investments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The funds of the Trust may be invested in short or long term deposits to yield 
better returns if feasible after keeping sufficient balance at the disposal of 
Trust or in such manner as the Board may authorise.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer shall maintain a register of securities held by the Trust.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All investments of the 
funds of the Trust shall be made in the name of the Trust and all purchases, 
sales or alternations of such investment shall be effected and all contracts 
transfer deeds or other documents necessary for purchasing, selling or altering 
the investments of the Trust shall be executed by the Chief Executive Officer 
after approval of the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The safe custody of 
the receipts, securities shall remain in the personal charge of the Chief 
Executive Officer and shall be verified once in six months with the register of 
securities in his custody and a certificate of such verification shall be 
recorded in the register after every verification.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer after approval by the Board shall sign and execute all agreements, 
contracts, transfer deeds of conveyance and other documents in connection with 
the affairs of the Trust with consultation and advice of the legal advisers 
appointed by the Trust.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Trust shall invest 
and deal with funds and moneys of the Trust and shall have the right—
 <subsection>
        
<number>i</number>  to issue appeals and applications of money and funds in furtherance of 
the said objectives and to raise or collect funds by gifts, donations, 
subscriptions or otherwise of cash and securities and any movable property;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>ii</number>  to acquire, purchase or otherwise own or take on lease or hire 
temporarily or permanently buy any movable or immovable property necessary or 
convenient for the furtherance of the objects of the Trust;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iii</number>  to borrow and raise money with or without security or on the 
security of mortgage charge or on the security hypothecation or pledge of all or 
any of the movable or immovable properties belonging to the Trust or in any 
other manner whatsoever, provided that prior approval of Central Government in 
writing has been obtained in that behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>iv</number>  to sell, assign, mortgage, lease, exchange and otherwise transfer or 
dispose of all or any property movable or immovable of the Trust for the 
furtherance of the objects of the Trust provided prior approval of the Central 
Government in writing is obtained for the transfer of the immovable property;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>v</number>  to enter into any agreement with any Government or authority, 
municipal, local or otherwise to obtain from such Government or authority any 
rights, privileges, concessions, fiduciary or otherwise that the Trust may deem 
desirable to obtain and carry out, exercise and comply with such arrangements 
and rights, privileges and concessions;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>vi</number>  to draw, make, accept, endorse, discount, execute, sign, issue and 
otherwise deal with cheques, hundis, drafts, certificates, receipts, Government 
securities, promissory notes, bills of exchange or other instruments and 
securities whether negotiable or transferable or not;
 </subsection><subsection>
      
<number>vii</number>  to build, construct, maintain, repair, alter, improve or develop or 
furnish any buildings or works necessary or convenient for the purpose of the 
Trust;
 </subsection><subsection>
     
<number>viii</number>  to undertake and accept management of any endowment or trust fund 
or donation to further the objects of the Trust but so nevertheless that this 
shall exclude immovable property;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>ix</number>  to appoint or employ temporarily or permanently any person or persons 
that may be required for the purposes of the Trust and to pay them in return for 
services rendered to the society, salaries, wages, honorarium, fees, gratuities, 
provident funds and pensions provided that prior approval of the Central 
Government is obtained in this behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>x</number>  to establish a provident fund and other benefits for employees of the 
Trust provided that prior approval of the Central Government is obtained in this 
behalf;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>xi</number>  to institute, offer, or grant, prizes, awards, scholarships, 
fellowships and stipend in furtherance of the objects of the Trust;
 <subsubsection>
      
<number>xii</number>  to receive and accept grant, donations and other contributions but 
not immovable property.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> In case of movable 
property bequeathed by any person for the benefit of persons with disability 
under clause (b) of sub-section (1) of section 11 of the Act, the Board shall 
determine the differential treatment to be provided to the persons covered under 
the Trust on the basis of the bequests, donations and the agreement made in this 
regard with the person bequeathing the property.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Disposal of 
property.—The 
Chief Executive Officer with the approval of the Board shall form a condemnation 
board to dispose of the non-expendable and other articles and to write off all 
unserviceable and condemned articles.
  
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Drawl of funds.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief Executive Officer shall keep watch over expenditure and accord 
sanction to the payments within the grants sanctioned and not by exceeding the 
powers delegated to him by the Trust.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer shall be assisted by officers authroised under the financial regulations 
made in this behalf by the Trust.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The funds shall be 
drawn from the Bank by cheque to meet the expenditure.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Cheque Books shall 
remain in the personal custody of the Chief Executive Officer or any other 
officer as may be authorised by the Chief Executive Officer on his behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Chief Executive 
Officer shall be assisted in respect of receipts and expenditure by the Accounts 
Officer or Accountant, who shall maintain pro forma accounts and submit all 
claims in respect of pay and allowances, travelling allowances and contingent 
bills in the specified forms and shall be countersigned by the Chief Executive 
Officer or by the officer authorised in this behalf before those are passed for 
payment by means of demand drafts or cheques or cash, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Accounts Officer 
or Accountant shall apply a check of a nature of a pre-audit to all payments 
from the funds of the Trust.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Hiring of office 
accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief Executive Officer shall have the powers to acquire hired accommodation 
for office premises with the approval of the Board, whenever necessary at the 
rates not exceeding those specified by the Central Government for similar 
purposes and in the absence of such specified rates with the approval of the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson shall, 
with the prior approval of the Central Government have the powers to hire or 
purchase the residential accommodation for the staff of the Trust in case the 
alternative arrangements are not made from the Central pool of accommodation.
 

1[(3) In the event 
of the accommodation for the Chairperson or the staff of the Trust not being 
hired, purchased or alternative arrangements made, they may be paid house rent 
allowance as admissible to the officers and servants holding posts of 
corresponding scale of pay under the Central Government.]
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Maintenance of 
Registers.—The 
following books and registers shall be maintained by the Trust, namely:—
 <section>
       
<number>1</number>  Register of Grants;
 </section><section>
       
<number>2</number>  Register of Assets;
 </section><section>
       
<number>3</number>  Register of outstanding dues recoverable from parties other than 
employees of the Trust;
 </section><section>
       
<number>4</number>  Register of Loans and Advances give to employees with recovery 
position;
 </section><section>
       
<number>5</number>  Register of Rents;
 </section><section>
       
<number>6</number>  Register of Cheque Books;
 </section><section>
       
<number>7</number>  Register of Receipt Books;
 </section><section>
       
<number>8</number>  Register of sanctioned posts with authority of sanction;
 </section><section>
       
<number>9</number>  General provident fund accounts, Ledger and Balance Sheets;
 </section><section>
      
<number>10</number>  Service Books;
 </section><section>
      
<number>11</number>  Register of Section Committee's proceedings;
 </section><section>
      
<number>12</number>  Register of Library Books;
 </section><section>
      
<number>13</number>  Acquitance rolls and register of periodical increments;
 </section><section>
      
<number>14</number>  Cash Books and Imprest Cash Books;
 </section><section>
      
<number>15</number>  Bank Reconciliation Register (to be maintained with the Cash Book);
 </section><section>
      
<number>16</number>  Ledger for control of expenditure;
 </section><section>
      
<number>17</number>  Travelling Allowance, Dearness Allowance Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>18</number>  Pay Bill Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>19</number>  Contingent Bill Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>20</number>  Fuel Accounts Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>21</number>  Stamp Account Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>22</number>  Stock Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>23</number>  Stationery Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>24</number>  Bill Control Register;
 </section><section>
      
<number>25</number>  Register of Securities;
 </section><section>
      
<number>26</number>  Miscellaneous Expenditure Register; and
 </section><section>
      
<number>27</number>  Register of beneficiaries with photographs.
  
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Preparation and 
submission of Annual Report to the Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chief Executive Officer as soon as possible after the end of the financial 
year but not later than the 30th day of September in the next financial year 
ensuring, prepare and submit to the Central Government an Annual Report giving 
complete accounts of the activities of the Trust during the said financial year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, the 
Annual Report referred to in sub-rule (1) shall contain information in respect 
of each of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       
<number>a</number>  names of members, officers, staff of the Trust and a chart showing the 
organisational set up;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>b</number>  highlight performance of the Trust with respect of each of the 
activities carried out for furtherance of the objects of the Trust;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>c</number>  progress made in implementation of various programmes undertaken by 
the Trust including the work of local level committees;
 </subsection><subsection>
       
<number>d</number>  any other matter deemed appropriate for inclusion by the Trust or 
specified by the Central Government from time to time.
  
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Miscellaneous.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The return covering property of the ward shall be submitted by the guardian 
within 6 months of his appointment as guardian in Form C.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The account of 
property and assets to be furnished by the guardian within a period of 3 months 
of the close of every financial year shall be made in Form D.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The application for 
registration of a voluntary organisation or the association of parents or the 
association of persons with disability shall be made in Form E.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any organisation 
working in the field of autism, cerebral palsy, mental retardation, multiple 
disabilities and already registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 
(21 of 1860), or section 25 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or as a 
Public Charitable Trust shall not require separate recognition.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The registration of 
such organisations shall be necessary with the Trust for availing benefits under 
the Trust and for seeking decision of the Board.
  
</section></article><form>
 

The 
National Trust for welfare of persons with  
autism, cerebral palsy, mental 
retardation  
and multiple disabilities rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form 
A
 

[See rule 
16(1)]
 

Form of 
application to the Local Level Committee by a patient, relative or  
a 
registered organisation for appointment of guardian for 
a person with 
disability
 

From                                                                                                                                    
Date.......
 

      
.................................
 

      
..................................  
 

To,
 

      The 
Local Level Committee
 

      
Sir/Madam,
 

      
..........................is a person with disability and requires protection of 
his person and property through a guardian. We hereby request that…………………..be 
appointed as guardian of the said …………………………. for the protection of his person 
and property.
 

We furnish hereunder further 
details and request early decision:
 

         
1.  Particulars of the person to be provided guardian
 

              
Name:
 

              
Age:
 

              
Nature of disability:
 

              
Address:
 

         
2.  Particulars of the person proposed to be appointed as 
guardian
 

              
Name:
 

              
Age:
 

              
Relationship with the word, if any:
 

              
Address:
 

We enclose herewith disability 
certificate of the said ………………….. obtained from…………….
 

Yours 
faithfully
 

Witnesses                                                                                                                       
Authorised signatory...............
 

1st 
Witness:............................                                                                                       
Name:......................................
 

2nd 
Witness:..........................                                                                                        
Designation:............................
 

                                                                                                                                       
Office stamp:...........................
 

Consent of 
the person proposed to be appointed Guardian
 

I hereby agree to be the guardian 
of the person and property of …………………and shall discharge my obligations with due 
diligence.
 

                                                                                          
Signature....................................
 

                                                                                          
Name:.........................................
 

                                                                                          
Date:...........................................
 

Consent of 
the guardian, if any, to the aforesaid proposal
 

I hereby agree to the above 
proposal to appoint ………………………………… as the guardian of ………………………
 

                                                                                          
Signature....................................
 

                                                                                          
Name:.........................................
 

                                                                                          
Date:...........................................
 

 </form><form>
 

The 
National Trust for welfare of persons with  
autism, cerebral palsy, mental 
retardation  
and multiple disabilities rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form 
B
 

[See rule 
16(2)]
 

Form of 
confirmation of appointment of guardian on application made by (1)  
a 
registered organisation, or (2) parent or relative of person with 
disability
 

The Local Level Committee situated 
at……………………………………..having considered the application made by ………………….. for 
appointment of guardian for ……………….. hereby confirms its decision as 
under:
 

         
1.  Name of the ward:
 

         
2.  Name of the guardian:
 

         
3.  Obligations of the guardian:
 

             
(a) maintenance and residential care
 

             
(b) management of immovable property
 

             
(c) management of movable property
 

             
(d) any others
 

The guardian shall furnish property 
returns to this Committee as per Form C and Form D specified under these 
rules.
 

Signature(s)................................
 

Place:............................
 

Date:.............................                                                                                              
Stamp..........................................
 

 </form><form>
 

The 
National Trust for welfare of persons with  
autism, cerebral palsy, mental 
retardation  
and multiple disabilities rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form 
C
 

[See rule 
27(1)]
 

Form of 
return covering property of the ward to be submitted by the  
guardian within 
6 months of hisappointment as guardian
 

         
1.  Name of the guardian:
 

         
2.  Name of the ward:
 

         
3.  Date of appointment of the guardian:
 

         
4.  Inventory of immovable property of the ward received by the guardian 
(to be furnished 
item-wise):          
 

              
(i) Nature:
 

             
(ii) Estimated market value:
 

            
(iii) Location:
 

         
5.  Inventory of the movable property of the ward received by the guardian 
(to be furnished item-wise): 
 

              
(i) Description:
 

             
(ii) Value:
 

         
6.  Pending liabilities of the ward:
 

              
(i) Nature:
 

             
(ii) Amount:
 

        
 7.  Pending claims receivable by the ward 
 

              
(i) Nature:
 

            
 (ii) Amount:
 

I declare that the aforesaid 
information is true and accurate to the best of my knowledge, information and 
belief.
 

Place:............................                                                                             
Signature of the guardian.............................
 

Date:.............................
 

 
 

Witnesses
 

1st 
Witness:............................
 

2nd 
Witness:...........................
 

 </form><form>
 

The 
National Trust for welfare of persons with  
autism, cerebral palsy, mental 
retardation  
and multiple disabilities rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form 
D
 

[See rule 
27(2)]
 

Form of 
account of the property and assets to be: mished by the guardian  
within a 
period of 3 months of the close of every financial year
 

         
1.  Name of the guardian:
 

         
2.  Name of the ward:
 

         
3.  Immovable property of the ward held by the guardian as 
on............... (to be furnished item-wise)
 

              
(i) Nature :
 

             
(ii) Estimated marker value:
 

            
(iii) Location:
 

         
4.  Receipts and payments statement for the period from............... to 
..................... Period from ......................... to 
.....................:............................Payments.........................................................Receipts....................
 

              
Head  
Amount            
Head    Amount
 

         
5.  Movable assets of the ward in the charge of the guardian 
on............................. (to be furnished item-wise)
 

              
(i) Nature:
 

             
(ii) Amount :
 

         
6.  Investments redeemed or alienated for consideration during the year 
ended........
 

         
7.  New investments made during the year ended ................ : 
(including renewals)
 

         
8.  Increase/decrease in the value of movable assets of the ward during the 
year ended .......
 

         
9.  Brief explanation for the variation vide (8) above:
 

I hereby declare that the aforesaid 
information is true and accurate to the best of my knowledge, information and 
belief.
 

Place:............................                                                                             
Signature of the guardian.............................
 

Date:.............................
 

 
 

Witnesses
 

1st 
Witness:............................
 

2nd 
Witness:...........................
 

 </form><form>
 

The 
National Trust for welfare of persons with  
autism, cerebral palsy, mental 
retardation  
and multiple disabilities rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form 
E
 

[See rule 
27(3)]
 

Form of 
application for registration of a Voluntary Organisation/ 
association of 
Parents/Association of Persons with Disability
 

         
1.  Organisation:
 

              
Name :
 

              
Address (Office/Project) :
 

              
Phone/Fax/Telex (Office) :
 

              
(Project):
 

         
2.  (i) Name of the Act under which registered :
 

              
(ii)      Registration No. and date of 
registration
 

              
(Please attach a photocopy) :
 

         
3.  Memorandum of Association and Bye-Laws    
(Please attach a 
photocopy)  :
 

         
4.  Name, address, occupation and other particulars of the Members of the 
Board of Management/Governing body:
 

         
5.  Present activities of the organisation :
 

         
6.  Present membership strength and categorisation :
 

List of documents to be 
attached—
 

        
(a)  A copy of the annual report for the previous year
 

        
(b)  Audited statement of accounts duly certified by Chartered Account for 
the last two years:
 

              
(i) Receipt and Payment Account (by Chartered Accountant) for the last two 
years
 

             
(ii) Income and Expenditure Account (by Chartered Accountant) for the last two 
years
 

            
(iii) Balance Sheet for the last two years (by Chartered Accountant)
 

        
(c)  Details of Staff employed :
 

        
(d)  Details of beneficiaries to be covered :
 

        
(e)  If hostel is maintained, then number of hostellers :
 

         
(f)  Other items, if any :
 

        
(g)  Whether located on its own/rented building (Necessary evidence to be 
attached)
 

Signature of the 
Authorised Signatory
 

Name 
 

Designation
 

Address
 

Date
 

Office 
Stamp
 

 
 

 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>