<act><tid>227413</tid>
<title>THE FINANCE (No. 2) BILL, <year>1996</year></title>

ACT NO. 33 OF <year>1996</year>
[ 28th September <year>1996</year>]

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- seventh Year of 
the 
Republic of India as follows:-

An Act to give effect to the financial proposals of the 
Central 
Government for the financial year <year>1996</year>- 97.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>1049396</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>813971</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Finance (No. 2) Act, <year>1996</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1677291</tid>
<number>2</number>Save as otherwise provided in this Act, sections 2 to 58 and 
section 88 shall be deemed to have come into force on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1996</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

RATES OF INCOME- TAX

CHAPTER II

RATES OF INCOME- TAX




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>220577</tid>
<number> 2</number> Tax
<section><tid>586410</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- sections (2) and (3),  
for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1996</year>, (tax) 
income- tax shall be charged at the rates specified in Part I of the 
First Schedule and such tax shall be increased, in the cases to which 
Paragraph E, of that Part applies by a surcharge calculated in the 
manner provided therein.

</section>

<section><tid>1592382</tid>
<number>2</number>In the cases to which Sub- Paragraph I or Sub- Paragraph 11 of 
Paragraph A of Part I of the First Schedule applies, where the 
assessee has, in the previous year, any net agricultural income 
exceeding six hundred rupees, in addition to total income, and the 
total income exceeds,-

<subsection><tid>434392</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case to which the said Sub- Paragraph I applies, forty 
thousand rupees, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1790844</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case to which the said Sub- Paragraph 11 applies, 
eighteen thousand rupees,
then,-


<subsubsection><tid>1338207</tid>
<number>a</number>the net agricultural income shall be taken into account, in 
the manner provided in clause (b)[ that is to say, as if the net 
agricultural income were comprised in the total income after,-

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>434392</tid>
<number>i</number>in a case to which the said Sub- Paragraph I applies, the 
first forty thousand rupees, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1790844</tid>
<number>ii</number>in a case to which the said Sub- Paragraph II applies, the 
first eighteen thousand rupees,
of the total income but without being liable to tax], only for the 
purpose of charging income- tax in respect of the total income; and


<subsubsection><tid>1299124</tid>
<number>b</number>the income- tax chargeable shall be calculated as follows:-

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>434392</tid>
<number>i</number>the total income and the net agricultural income shall be 
aggregated and the amount of income- tax shall be determined in respect 
of the aggregate income at the rates specified in Sub- Paragraph I or, 
as the case may be, SubParagraph II of the said Paragraph A, as if 
such aggregate income were the total income;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1790844</tid>
<number>ii</number>the net agricultural income shall be increased,-

<subsubsection><tid>514122</tid>
<number>A</number>in a case to which the said Sub- Paragraph I applies, by a 
sum of forty thousand rupees; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>837994</tid>
<number>B</number>in a case to which the said Sub- Paragraph II applies, by a 
sum of eighteen thousand rupees,
and the amount of income- tax shall be determined in respect of the net 
agricultural income as so increased at the rates specified in Sub- 
Paragraph I or, as the case may be, Sub- Paragraph 11 of the said 
Paragraph A, as if the net agricultural income as so increased were 
the total income;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1682235</tid>
<number>iii</number>the amount of income- tax determined in accordance with 
sub- clause (i) shall be reduced by the amount of income- tax determined 
in accordance with sub- clause (ii) and the sum so arrived at shall be 
the income- tax in respect of the total income.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1804118</tid>
<number>3</number>In cases to which the provisions of Chapter XII or Chapter 
XII- A or sub- section (1A) of section 161 or section 164 or section 
 164A or section 167B of the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (hereinafter referred  
  to as the Income- tax Act)  (43 of <year>1961</year>). apply, the tax chargeable 
shall be determined as provided in that Chapter or that section, and 
with reference to the rates imposed by sub- section (1) or the rates as 
specified in that Chapter or section, as the case may be:
Provided that the amount of income- tax computed in accordance 
with the provisions of sections 112 and 113 of the Income- tax Act 
shall be increased in the case of a domestic company by a surcharge as 
provided in Paragraph E of Part I of the First Schedule:


<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided further that in respect of any income chargeable to tax 
under section 115B, or in the case of a domestic company having a 
total income exceeding seventy- five thousand rupees under section 
115BB, of the Income- tax Act, the income- tax computed shall be 
increased by a surcharge calculated at the rate of fifteen per cent. 
of such income- tax.


</section>

<section><tid>753729</tid>
<number>4</number>In cases in which tax has to be deducted under sections 193, 
194, 194A, 194B, 194BB, 194D and 195 of the Income- tax Act at the 
rates in force, the deduction shall be made at the rates specified in 
Part II of the First Schedule and shall be increased, in the cases to 
which the provisions of sub- item (a) of item 2 of that Part apply, by 
a surcharge calculated in the manner provided therein.

</section>

<section><tid>1362005</tid>
<number>5</number>In cases in which tax has to be deducted under sections 
194C, 194G, 194-I, 194J and 194K of the Income- tax Act, the deduction 
shall be made at the rates specified in those sections and shall be 
increased in the case of an assessee, being a domestic company, by a 
surcharge calculated at the rate of seven- and- a- half per cent. of such 
deduction.

</section>

<section><tid>1905659</tid>
<number>6</number>In cases in which tax has to be collected under section 206C 
of the Income- tax Act, the collection shall be made at the rates 
specified in that section and shall be increased in the case of a 
buyer, being a domestic company, by a surcharge calculated at the rate 
of seven- and- a- half per cent. of such collection.

</section>

<section><tid>783237</tid>
<number>7</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (8), in cases in 
which income- tax has to be calculated under the first proviso to sub- 
section (5) of section 132 of the Income- tax Act or charged under sub- 
section (4) of section 172 or sub- section (2) of section 174 or 
section 175 or Sub- section (2) of section 176 of the said Act or 
deducted under section 192 of the said Act from income chargeable 
under the bead" Salaries" or in which the" advance tax" payable under 
Chapter XVII- C of the said Act has to be computed, at the rate or 
rates in force, such income- tax or, as the case may be," advance tax" 
shall be so calculated, charged, deducted or computed at the rate or 
rates specified in Part III of the First Schedule and such tax shall 
be increased, in the cases to which Paragraph E of that Part applies, 
by a surcharge calculated in the manner provided therein:
Provided that in the cases to which the provisions of Chapter XII 
or Chapter XII- A or sub- section (1A) of section 161 or section 164 or 
section 164A or section 167B of the Income- tax Act apply," advance 
tax" shall be computed with reference to the rates imposed by this 
sub- section or the rates as specified in that Chapter or section, as 
the case may be:

Provided further that the amount of income- tax computed in 
accordance with the provisions of sections 112 and 113 of the Income- 
tax Act shall be increased in the case of a domestic company by a 
surcharge as provided in Paragraph E of Part III of the First 
Schedule:

Provided also that in respect of any income chargeable to tax 
under section 115B, or in the case of a domestic company, under 
section 115BB of the Income- tax Act, having a total income exceeding 
seventy- five thousand rupees, the" advance tax" computed under the 
first proviso shall be increased by a surcharge calculated at the rate 
of seven- and- a- half per cent. of such" advance tax".


</section>

<section><tid>1860780</tid>
<number>8</number>In the cases to which Paragraph A of Part III of the First 
Schedule applies, where the assessee has, in the previous year or, if 
by virtue of any provision of the Income- tax Act, income- tax is to be 
charged in respect of the income of a period other than the previous 
year, in such other period, any net agricultural income exceeding six 
hundred rupees, in addition to total income and the total income 
exceeds forty thousand rupees, then, in calculating income- tax under 
the first proviso to sub- section (5) of section 132 of the Income- tax 
Act or in charging income- tax under sub- section (2) of section 174 or 
section 175 or sub- section (2) of section 176 of the said Act or in 
computing the" advance tax" payable under Chapter XVII- C of the said 
Act, at the rate or rates in force,-

<subsection><tid>1388934</tid>
<number>a</number>the net agricultural income shall be taken into account, in 
the manner provided in clause (b)[ that is to say, as if the net 
agricultural income were comprised in the total income after the first 
forty thousand rupees of the total income but without

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

being liable to tax], only for the purpose of calculating, charging or 
computing such income- tax or, as the case may be," advance tax" in 
respect of the total income; and


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>849595</tid>
<number>b</number>such income- tax or, as the case may be," advance tax" shall 
be so calculated, charged or computed as follows:-

<subsubsection><tid>181283</tid>
<number>i</number>the total income and the net agricultural income shall be 
aggregated and the amount of income- tax or" advance tax" shall be 
determined in respect of the aggregate income at the rates specified 
in the said Paragraph A as if such aggregate income were the total 
income;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>120123</tid>
<number>ii</number>the net agricultural income shall be increased by a sum of 
forty thousand rupees, and the amount of income- tax or" advance tax" 
shall be determined in respect of the net agricultural income as so 
increased at the rates specified in the said Paragraph A as if the 
net agricultural income as so increased were the total income;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1866439</tid>
<number>iii</number>the amount of income- tax or" advance tax" determined in 
accordance with sub- clause (i) shall be reduced by the amount of 
income- tax or, as the case may be,
" advance tax" determined in accordance with sub- clause (ii) and the 
sum so arrived at shall be the income- tax or, as the case may be, 
" advance tax" in respect of the total income.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1261922</tid>
<number>9</number>For the purposes of this section and the First Schedule,-

<subsection><tid>659010</tid>
<number>a</number>" domestic company" means an Indian company, or any other 
company which, in respect of its income liable to income- tax under the 
Income- tax Act for the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
April, <year>1996</year>, has made the prescribed arrangements for the declaration 
and payment within India of the dividends (including dividends: on  
  preference shares) payable out of such income in accordance with the 
provisions of section 194 of the Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>154266</tid>
<number>b</number>" insurance commission" means any remuneration or reward, 
whether by way of commission or otherwise, for soliciting or procuring 
insurance business (including business relating to the continuance,  
  renewal or revival of policies of insurance);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1483565</tid>
<number>c</number>" net agricultural income", in relation to a person, means 
the total amount of agricultural income, from whatever source derived, 
of that person computed in accordance with the rules contained in Part 
IV of the First Schedule;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>351680</tid>
<number>d</number>all other words and expressions used in this section or in 
the First Schedule but not defined in this sub- section and defined in 
the Income- tax Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to 
them in that Act.
CHAP

DIRECT TAXES

CHAPTER III

DIRECT TAXES

Income- tax




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1797723</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 2. In section 2 of the Income- tax Act, 
with effect from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>,-
<section><tid>1386498</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (7A), for the words" Assistant Commissioner" and 
" Deputy Commissioner", the words" Assistant Commissioner" or 
" Assistant Director" and" Deputy Commissioner" or" Deputy Director" 
shall respectively be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1451247</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (24), after sub- clause (x), the following sub- 
clause shall be inserted, namely:-
' (xi) any sum received under a Keyman insurance policy including 
the sum allocated by way of bonus on such policy.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, the expression. 
" Keyman insurance policy" shall have the meaning assigned to it in the 
Explanation to clause (10D) of section 10;'.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>8417</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of Section 10. In section 10 of the Income- tax 
Act,-
<section><tid>1704105</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (10A), after sub- clause (ii), the following sub- 
clause shall be inserted with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, 
namely:-
" (iii) any payment in commutation of pension received from a fund 
under clause (23AAB);";


</section>

<section><tid>1197861</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (10D), after the words, brackets, figures and 
letters" other than any sum received under sub- section (3) of section 
80DDA", the following shall be inserted with effect from the 1st day 
of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-
or under a Keyman insurance policy.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause," Keyman 
insurance policy" means a life insurance policy taken by a person on 
the life of another person who is or was the employee of the first 
mentioned person or is or was connected in any manner whatsoever with 
the business of the first mentioned person;';


</section>

<section><tid>532687</tid>
<number>c</number>in clause (15), in sub- clause (iv), after item (i), in the 
Explanation, for clause (e), the following clause shall be substituted 
with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-
" (e) the operation of ships or aircrafts or construction or 
operation of rail systems;";


</section>

<section><tid>1249394</tid>
<number>d</number>after clause (23AAA), the following clause shall be inserted 
with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-
' (23AAB) any income of a fund, by whatever name called, set up by 
the Life Insurance Corporation of India on or after the 1st day of 
August, <year>1996</year> under a pension scheme,-


<subsection><tid>375919</tid>
<number>i</number>to which contribution is made by any person for the purpose 
of receiving pension from such fund;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>3056</tid>
<number>ii</number>which is approved by the Controller of Insurance.
Explanation.- For the- purposes of this clause, the expression 
" Controller of Insurance" shall have the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (5B) of section 2 of the Insurance Act, <year>1938</year> (4 of <year>1938</year>);';


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1957308</tid>
<number>e</number>after clause (23BBB), the following clause shall be inserted 
and shall be deemed to have been inserted with effect from the 1st day 
of April, <year>1992</year>, namely:-
" (23BBC) any income of the SAARC Fund for Regional Project set up 
by Colombo Declaration issued on the 21st day of December, <year>1991</year> by the 
Heads of State or Government of the Member Countries of South Asian 
Association for Regional Cooperation established on the 8th day of 
December, <year>1985</year> by the Charter of the South Asian Association for 
Regional Cooperation;";


</section>

<section><tid>1192747</tid>
<number>f</number>after clause (23F), the following clause shall be inserted 
with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-

<subsection><tid>455733</tid>
<number>G</number>any income by way of dividends, interest or long- term 
capital gains of an infrastructure capital fund or an infrastructure 
capital company from investments made by way of shares or long- term 
finance in any enterprise carrying on the business of developing, 
maintaining and operating any infrastructure facility, which fulfils 
the conditions specified in sub- section (4A) of section 80-IA.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause,- 
 (a)" infrastructure capital company" means such company as has 
made investments by way of acquiring shares or providing long- term 
finance to an enterprise carrying on the business of developing, main- 
taining and operating infrastructure facility; 
 (b)" infrastructure capital fund" means such fund operating 
under a trust deed, registered under the provisions of the 
Registration Act, <year>1908</year> (16 of <year>1908</year>), established to raise monies by 
the trustees for investment by way of acquiring shares or providing 
long- term finance to an enterprise carrying on the business of 
developing, maintaining and operating infrastructure facility; 
 (c)" infrastructure facility" shall have the meaning assigned to 
it in clause (ca) of sub- section (12) of section 80-IA; 
 (d)" long- term finance" shall have the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (viii) of sub- section (1) of section 36;'


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>413885</tid>
<number>g</number>for clause (24), the following clause shall be substituted 
with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-
' (24) any income chargeable under the heads" income from house 
property" and" Income from other sources" of-


</section>

<section><tid>1704105</tid>
<number>a</number>a registered union within the meaning of the Trade Unions 
Act, <year>1926</year> (16 of <year>1926</year>). formed primarily for the purpose of regulating 
the relations between workmen and employers or between workmen and 
workmen;

</section>

<section><tid>1197861</tid>
<number>b</number>an association of registered unions referred to in subclause 
 (a);'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>183551</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 12A. In section 12A of the Income- tax 
Act, in clause (a), for the words" whichever is later", the words, 
figures and letters" whichever is later and such trust or institution 
is registered under section 12AA" shall be substituted with effect 
from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>19901</tid>
<number> 6</number> Insertion of new section 12AA. After section 12A of the 
Income- tax Act, the following section shall be inserted with effect 
from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12AA</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Procedure for registration.

" 12AA. Procedure for registration. (1) The Chief Commissioner 
or Commissioner, on receipt of an application for registration of a 
trust or institution made under clause (a) of section 12A, shall-

<section><tid>1448450</tid>
<number>a</number>call for such documents or information from the trust or 
institution as he thinks necessary in order to satisfy himself about 
the genuineness of activities of the trust or institution and may also 
make such inquiries as he may deem necessary in this behalf, and

</section>

<section><tid>252832</tid>
<number>b</number>after satisfying himself about the objects of the trust or 
institution and the genuineness of its activities, be-

<subsection><tid>1431825</tid>
<number>i</number>shall pass an order in writing registering the trust or 
institution;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1647572</tid>
<number>ii</number>shall, if he is not so satisfied, pass an order in 
writing refusing to register the trust or institution,
and a copy of such order shall be sent to the applicant:

Provided that no order under sub- clause (ii) shall be passed 
unless the applicant has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard.


<subsubsection><tid>1374797</tid>
<number>2</number>Every order granting or refusing registration under clause 
 (b) of sub- section (1) shall be passed before the expiry of six months 
from the end of the month in which the application was received under 
clause (a) of section 12A.".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>524492</tid>
<number> 7</number> Amendment of section 16. In section 16 of the Income- tax 
Act, for clause (i), the following clauses shall be substituted with 
effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-
' (i) in the case of an assessee whose income from salary, before 
allowing a deduction under this clause, does not exceed sixty thousand 
rupees, a deduction of a sum equal to thirty- three and one- third per 
cent. of the salary or eighteen thousand rupees, whichever is less;


<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<section><tid>1779684</tid>
<number>ia</number>in any other case, a deduction of a sum equal to thirty- 
three and one- third per cent. of the salary or fifteen thousand 
rupees, whichever is less:
Provided that in the. case of an assessee, being a woman, whose 
total income before making any deduction under this clause, does not 
exceed seventy- five thousand rupees, the provisions of this clause 
shall have effect as if for the words" fifteen thousand rupees", the 
words" eighteen thousand rupees" had been substituted.

Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that where, in the case of an assessee, salary is due from, or paid or 
allowed by, more than one employer, the deduction under this clause 
shall be computed with reference to the aggregate salary due, paid or 
allowed to the assessee and shall in no case exceed the amount 
specified under clause (i) or clause (ia), as the case may be.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>813958</tid>
<number>8</number>Amendment of section 17. In section 17 of the Income- tax 
Act, in clause (3), in sub- clause (ii), for the words" interest on 
such contributions.", the following shall be substituted with effect 
from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-
' interest on such contributions or any sum received under a 
Keyman insurance policy including the sum allocated by way of bonus on 
such policy.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- clause, the expression 
" Keyman insurance policy" shall have the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (10D) of section 10.'



</article>



<article><tid>1464949</tid>
<number> 9</number> Amendment of section 24. In section 24 of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section (2), in the proviso,-
<section><tid>1363529</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" ten thousand rupees", the words" fifteen 
thousand rupees" shall be substituted with effect from the 1st day of 
April, <year>1997</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>669160</tid>
<number>b</number>after the words, brackets, figures and letters" sub- clause 
 (i) of clause (a) of sub- section (2) of section 23", the words, 
brackets and figures" or sub- section (3) of section 23" shall be 
inserted and shall be deemed to have been inserted with effect from 
the 1st day of April, <year>1995</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1352852</tid>
<number>10</number>Amendment of section 28. In section 28 of the Income- tax Act, 
after clause (v), the following clause shall be inserted with effect 
from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-
' (vi) any sum, received under a Keyman insurance policy including 
the sum allocated by way of bonus on such policy.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, the expression 
" Keyman insurance policy" shall have the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (10D) of section 10;'.



</article>



<article><tid>1671947</tid>
<number> 11</number> Amendment of section 32. In section 32 of the Income- tax 
Act, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>639893</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), after the words" plant or furniture 
owned", the words' wholly or partly," shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>1404434</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (1), after the third proviso, the following 
proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided also that the aggregate deduction, in 
respect of depreciation of buildings, machinery, plant 
or furniture allowable to the predecessor and the 
successor in the case of succession, referred to in 
section 170 or the amalgamating company and the 
amalgamated company in the case of amalgamation, as the 
case may be, shall not exceed in any previous year the 
deduction calculated at the prescribed rates as if the 
succession or the amalgamation had not taken place, and 
such deduction shall be apportioned between the 
predecessor and the successor, or the amalgamating 
company and the amalgamated company, as the case may be, 
in the ratio of the number of days for which the assets 
were used by them."


</section>

<section><tid>817797</tid>
<number>c</number>for sub- section (2), the following sub- section 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" (2) Where in the assessment of the assessee full 
effect cannot be given to any allowance under clause 
 (ii) of sub- section (1) in any previous year owing to 
there being no profits or gains chargeable for that 
previous year or owing to


<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

the profits or gains being less than the allowance, 
then, the allowance or the part of allowance to which 
effect has not been given (hereinafter referred to as  
  unabsorbed depreciation allowance), as the case may be,-


<subsection><tid>1762100</tid>
<number>i</number>shall be set off against the profits and 
gains, if any, of any business or profession carried on 
by him and assessable for that assessment year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1323771</tid>
<number>ii</number>if the unabsorbed depreciation allowance 
cannot be wholly set off, under clause (i), the amount 
not so set off shall be set off from the income under 
any other bead, if any, assessable for that assessment 
year;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>198374</tid>
<number>iii</number>if the unabsorbed depreciation allowance 
cannot be wholly set off under clause (i) and clause 
 (ii), the amount of allowance not so set off shall be 
carried forward to the following assessment year and- 
 (a) it shall be set off against the profits and 
gains, if any, of any business or profession 
carried on by him and assessable for that 
assessment year;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1404434</tid>
<number>b</number>if the unabsorbed depreciation allowance 
cannot be wholly so set off, the amount of 
unabsorbed depreciation allowance not so set off 
shall be carried forward to the following assess- 
ment year not being more than eight assessment 
years immediately succeeding the assessment year 
for which the aforesaid allowance was first 
computed: 
Provided that the business or profession for which 
the allowance was originally computed continued to be 
carried on by him in the previous year relevant for that 
assessment year:
Provided further that the time limit of eight 
assessment years specified in sub- clause (b) shall not 
apply in the case of a company for the assessment year 
beginning with the assessment year relevant to the 
previous year in which the said company has become a 
sick industrial company under sub- section (1) of section 
 17 of the Sick Industrial Company (Special Provisions) 
Act, <year>1985</year> (1 of <year>1986</year>). and ending with the assessment 
year relevant to the previous year in which the entire 
networth of such company becomes equal to or exceeds the 
accumulated losses.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, 
" networth" shall have the meaning assigned to it in 
clause (ga) of subsection (1) of section 3 of the Sick 
Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Act, <year>1985</year> (1  
  of <year>1986</year>),.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>196704</tid>
<number>12</number>Amendment of section 35. In section 35 of the Income- tax 
Act, in subsection (2AA), for the provisos, the following proviso 
shall be substituted with effect from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, 
namely:-
Provided that the prescribed authority shall, 
before granting approval, satisfy itself about the, 
feasibility or carrying out the scientific research and 
shall submit its report to the Director General in Such 
form as may be prescribed.".



</article>



<article><tid>121019</tid>
<number> 13</number> Amendment of section 35AC. In section 35AC of the Income- 
tax Act, after sub- section (3) and before the Explanation, the 
following sub- sections shall be inserted with effect from the 1st day 
of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-
" (4) Where an association or institution is 
approved by the National Committee under sub- section 
 (1), and subsequently that Committee is satisfied that 
the project or the scheme is not being carried on in 
accordance with all or any of the conditions subject to 
which approval was granted, it may, at any time, after 
giving a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against 
the proposed withdrawal to the concerned association or 
institution, withdraw the approval.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

<section><tid>639829</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any project or scheme has been notified 
as an eligible project or scheme under clause (b) of the 
Explanation and subsequently the National Committee is 
satisfied that the project or the scheme is not being 
carried out in accordance with all or any of the 
conditions subject to which such project or scheme was 
notified, such notification may be withdrawn in the same 
manner in which it was issued:
Provided that a reasonable opportunity of showing 
cause against the proposed withdrawal shall be given by 
the National Committee to the concerned association, 
institution, public sector company or the local 
authority, as the case may be."




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1745225</tid>
<number> 14</number> Amendment of section 36. In section 36 of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, in clause (viii),-
<section><tid>727076</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" before making any deduction 
under this section", the words" before making any 
deduction under this clause" shall be substituted and 
shall be deemed to have been substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>310699</tid>
<number>b</number>in the second proviso, for the brackets and 
words" (excluding the amounts capitalised from  
  reserves)", the words" and of the general reserves" 
shall be substituted with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1512010</tid>
<number>c</number>in the Explanation, after clause (d), the 
following clause shall be inserted and shall be deemed 
to have been inserted, namely:-
' (e)" long- term finance" means any loan or 
advance where the terms under which moneys are loaned or 
advanced provide for repayment along with interest 
thereof during a period of not less than seven years.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>827987</tid>
<number>15</number>Amendment of section 40A. In section 40A of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section (3), for the words" ten thousand" wherever they 
occur, the words" twenty thousand" shall be substituted with effect 
from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1780278</tid>
<number> 16</number> Amendment of section 41. In section 41 of the Income- tax 
Act, Explanation occurring below sub- section
<section><tid>1849945</tid>
<number>1</number>shall be renumbered  
as Explanation 2, and before Explanation 2 as so renumbered, the 
following Explanation shall be inserted with effect from the 1st day 
of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-
' Explanation 1.- For the purposes of this sub- section, 
the expression" loss or expenditure or some benefit in 
respect of any such trading liability by way of remis- 
sion or cessation thereof' shall include the remission 
or cessation of any liability by a unilateral act by the 
first mentioned person under clause (a) or the successor 
in business under clause (b) of that sub- section by way 
of writing off such liability in his accounts.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>820971</tid>
<number>17</number>Amendment of section 43. In section 43 of the Income- tax 
Act, in clause 1, after Explanation 4, the following Explanation 
shall be inserted with effect from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, 
namely:
" Explanation 4A.- Where before the date of acquisition by 
the assessee (hereinafter referred to as the first  
  mentioned person), the assets were at any time used by 
any other person (hereinafter referred to as the second  
  mentioned person) for the purposes of his business or 
profession and depreciation allowance has been claimed 
in respect of such assets in the case of the second 
mentioned person and such person acquires on lease, hire 
or otherwise assets from the first mentioned person, 
then, notwithstanding anything contained in Explanation 
3, the actual cost of the transferred assets, in the 
case of first mentioned person, shall be the same as the 
written down value of the said assets at the time of 
thereof by the second mentioned person.".



</article>



<article><tid>1441325</tid>
<number> 18</number> Amendment of section 43B. In section 43B of the Income- tax 
Act, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>1328610</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (d), after the words" governing such 
loan or borrowing" the words" governing such loan or 
borrowing; or" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1785449</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (d), the following clause shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (e) any sum payable by the assessee as 
interest on any term loan from a scheduled bank in 
accordance with the terms and conditions of the 
agreement governing such loan.";


<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1681802</tid>
<number>c</number>after Explanation 3, the following 
Explanation shall be inserted, namely:-
" Explanation 3A.- For the removal of doubts, 
it is hereby declared that where a deduction in respect 
of any sum referred to in clause (e) of this section is 
allowed in computing the income referred to in section 
 28 of the previous year (being a previous year relevant  
to the assessment year commencing on the 1st day of 
  April, <year>1996</year>, or any earlier assessment year) in which 
the liability to pay such sum was incurred by the 
assessee, the assessee shall not be entitled to any 
deduction under this section in respect of such sum in 
computing the income of the previous year in which the 
sum is actually paid by him.";


</section>

<section><tid>1393866</tid>
<number>d</number>in Explanation 4, after clause (a), the 
following clause shall be inserted, namely:-

</section>

<section><tid>1189727</tid>
<number>aa</number>" scheduled bank' shall have the meaning 
assigned to it in clause (ii) of the Explanation to 
clause (viia) of sub- section (1) of the section 36;'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>31566</tid>
<number>19</number>Amendment of section 45. In section 45 of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, after the figures and letter" 54E,", the 
figures and letters" 54EA, 54EB," shall be inserted with effect from 
the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>691652</tid>
<number> 20</number> Insertion of new sections 54 EA and 54 EB. After section 
 54E of the Income- tax Act, the following sections shall be inserted 
with effect from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>54EA</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Capital gain on transfer of long- term capital assets not to be charged in the 
case of investment in specified bonds or debentures.

' 54EA. Capital gain on transfer of long- term 
capital assets not to be charged in the case of 
investment in specified bonds or debentures. (1) Where 
the capital gain arises from the transfer of a long- term 
capital asset (the capital asset so transferred being  
hereafter in this section referred to as the original 
  asset) and the assessee has, at any time within a period 
of six months after the date of such transfer, invested 
the whole or any part of the net consideration in any of 
the bonds, debentures or units of any mutual fund 
referred to in clause (23D) of section 10 specified by 
the Board in this behalf by notification in the Official 
Gazette (such assets hereafter in this section referred  
  to as the specified bonds or debentures), the capital 
gain shall be dealt with in accordance with the 
following provisions of this section, that is to say,-

<section><tid>337308</tid>
<number>a</number>if the cost of the specified bonds 
or debentures is not less than the net 
consideration in respect of the original asset, the 
whole of such capital gain shall not be charged 
under section 45;

</section>

<section><tid>616254</tid>
<number>b</number>if the cost of the specified bonds 
or debentures is less than the net consideration in 
respect of the original asset, so much of the 
capital gain as bears to the whole of the capital 
gain the same proportion as the cost of acquisition 
of the specified bonds or debentures bears to the 
net consideration shall not be charged under 
section 45. 
 (2) Where the specified bonds or debentures are 
transferred or converted (otherwise than by transfer) 
into money at any time within a period of three years 
from the date of their acquisition, the amount of 
capital gain arising from the transfer of the original 
asset not charged under section 45 on the basis of the 
cost of such specified bonds or debentures as provided 
in clause (a) or clause (b) of sub- section (1) shall be 
deemed to be the income chargeable under the head 
" capital gains" relating to long- term capital assets of 
the previous year in which the specified bonds or 
debentures are transferred or converted (otherwise than  
  by transfer) into money.
Explanation.- In a case where the original asset 
is transferred and the assessee invests the whole or any 
part of the net consideration in respect of the original 
asset in any specified bonds or debentures and such 
assessee takes any loan or advance on the security of 
such specified bonds or debentures, he shall be deemed 
to have converted (otherwise than by transfer) such 
specified bonds or debentures into money on the date on 
which such loan or advance is taken:


<subsection><tid>1807539</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the cost of the specified bonds or 
debentures has been taken into

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

account for the purposes of clause (a) or clause (b) of 
sub- section (1), a rebate with reference to such cost 
shall not be allowed under section 88. 
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section,-


<subsubsection><tid>1799602</tid>
<number>a</number>" cost", in relation to any 
specified bonds or debentures, means the amount 
invested in such specified bonds or debentures out 
of the net consideration received or accruing as a 
result of the transfer of the original asset;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1123971</tid>
<number>b</number>" net consideration", in relation to 
the transfer of a capital asset, means the full 
value of the consideration received or accruing as 
a result of the transfer of the capital asset as 
reduced by the expenditure incurred wholly and 
exclusively in connection with such transfer.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>54EB</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Capital gain on transfer of long- term capital assets not to be charged certain 
cases.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1345991</tid>
<number> 54EB</number> Capital gain on transfer of long- term capital assets 
not to be charged certain cases.
<section><tid>1587258</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the capital gain arises  
from the transfer of a long- term capital asset (the capital asset so  
transferred being hereafter in this section referred to as the 
  original asset), and the assessee has, at any time within a period of 
six months after the date of such transfer invested the whole or any 
part of capital gains, in any of the assets specified by the Board in 
this behalf by notification in the Official Gazette (such assets  
hereafter in this section referred to as the long- term specified 
  assets)., the capital gain shall be dealt with in accordance with the 
following provisions of this section, that is to say,- 
 (a) if the cost of the long- term specified 
asset is not less than the capital gain arising 
from the transfer of the original asset, the whole 
of such capital gain shall not be charged under 
section 45;

<subsection><tid>1622056</tid>
<number>b</number>if the cost of the long- term specified 
asset is less than the capital gain arising from 
the transfer of the original asset, so much of the 
capital gain as bears to the whole of the capital 
gain the same proportion as the cost of acquisition 
of the long- term specified asset bears to the whole 
of the capital gain, shall not be charged under 
section 45. 
Explanation.-" Cost", in relation to any long- term 
specified asset, means the amount invested in such 
specified asset out of capital gains received or 
accruing as a result of the transfer of the original 
asset.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>775011</tid>
<number>2</number>Where the long- term specified asset is 
transferred or converted (otherwise than by transfer) 
into money at any time within a period of seven years 
from the date of its acquisition, the amount of capital 
gains arising from the transfer of the original asset 
not charged under section 45 on the basis of the cost of 
such long- term specified asset as provided in clause 
 (a), or as the case may be, clause (b) of sub- section 
 (1) shall be deemed to be the income chargeable under 
the bead" Capital gains" relating to long- term capital 
assets of the previous year in which the long- term 
specified asset is transferred or converted (otherwise  
  than by transfer) into money.
Explanation.- In a case where the original asset 
is transferred and the assessee invests the whole or any 
part of the capital gain received or accrued as a result 
of transfer of the original asset in any long- term 
specified asset and such assessee takes any loan or 
advance on the security of such specified asset, he 
shall be deemed to have converted (otherwise than by  
  transfer) such specified asset into money oh the date on 
which such loan or advance is taken.


</section>

<section><tid>541246</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the cost of the long- term specified 
asset has been taken into account for the purposes of 
clause (a) or clause (b) of sub- section (1), a deduction 
from the amount of income- tax with reference to such 
cost shall not be allowed under section 88.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1953166</tid>
<number>21</number>Amendment of section 56. In section 56, in sub- section (2), 
after clause (iii), the following clause shall be inserted with effect 
from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-
' (iv) income referred to in sub- clause (xi) of 
clause (24) of section 2, if such income is not 
chargeable to income- tax under the head" Profits and 
gains of business or profession" or under the head 
" Salaries".'.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>862917</tid>
<number>22</number>Omission of section 80CC. Section 80CC of the Income- tax 
Act shall be omitted and shall be deemed to have been omitted with 
effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1993</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>160148</tid>
<number>23</number>Insertion of new section 80CCC. After section 80CCB of the 
income- tax Act, the following section shall be insert with effect from 
the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>80CC</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Deduction respect of contribution to certain pension funds.

</article>



<article><tid>987413</tid>
<number> 80CCC</number> Deduction respect of contribution to 
certain pension funds.
<section><tid>1318499</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an assessee being an  
individual has in the previous year paid or deposited 
any amount out of his income chargeable to tax to effect 
or keep in force a contract for any annuity plan of Life 
Insurance Corporation of India for receiving pension 
from the fund referred to in clause (23AAB) of section 
10, he shall, in accordance with, and subject to the 
provisions of this section be allowed a deduction in the 
computation of his total income of the whole of the 
amount paid or deposited (excluding interest or bonus  
  accrued or credited to the assessee' s account if any) as 
does not exceed the amount of ten thousand rupees in the 
previous year.

</section>

<section><tid>735372</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any amount standing to the credit of 
the assessee in a fund, referred to in sub- section (1) 
in respect of which a deduction has been allowed under 
sub- section (1), together with the interest or bonus 
accrued or credited to the assessee' s account, if any, 
is received by the assessee or his nominee- 
 (a) on account of the surrender of the 
annuity plan whether in whole or in part, in any 
previous year, or

<subsection><tid>1767586</tid>
<number>b</number>as pension received from the 
annuity plan. 
an amount equal to the whole of the amount 
referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) shall be deemed 
to be the income of the assessee or his nominee, as the 
case may be, in that previous year in which such 
withdrawal is made or, as the case may be,, pension is 
received, and shall accordingly be chargeable to tax as 
the case may be, pension is received, and shall 
accordingly be chargeable to tax as income of that 
previous year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>999540</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any amount paid or deposited by the 
assessee has been taken into account for the purposes of 
this section, a rebate with reference to such amount 
shall not be allowed under section 88."



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>342294</tid>
<number>24</number>Amendment of section 80D. In section 80D of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, for the words" six thousand rupees", wherever 
they occur, the words" ten thousand rupees" shall be substituted with 
effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, name; y:-


</article>



<article><tid>384748</tid>
<number>25</number>Insertion of new section 80 DDB. After section 80DDA of the 
Income- tax Act, the following section shall be inserted with from the 
 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>80DD</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Deduction in respect of medical treatment, etc.

</article>



<article><tid>1785504</tid>
<number> 80DDB</number> Deduction in respect of medical treatment, 
etc. Where an assessee who is resident in India has, 
during the previous year, incurred any expenditure for 
the medical treatment of such disease or ailment as may 
be specified in the rules made in this behalf by the 
Board- 
 (a) for himself or a dependent relative, 
in case the assessee is an individual; or
<section><tid>469743</tid>
<number>b</number>for any member of a Hindu undivided 
family, in case the assessee is Hindu Undivided 
family. 
the assessee shall be allowed a deduction of a sum of 
fifteen thousand rupees in respect of that previous year 
in which such expenditure was incurred:
Provided that no such deduction shall be allowed 
unless the assessee furnishes a certificate in such from 
and from such authority as may be prescribed.

Explanation- For the purposes of this section, 
" dependant" means a person who is not dependant for his 
support or maintenance on any person other than the 
assessee.'




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>118516</tid>
<number> 26</number> Amendment of section 80G. In section 80G of the Income- tax 
Act with, effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>564525</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1) in clause (i), after the 
words brackets figures and letter sub- clause (iiih) or", 
the words, brackets, figures and letters" sub- clause 
 (iiiha) or sub- clause (iiihb) or sub- clause (iiihc) or" 
shall be inserted:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>13</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1177919</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), in clause (a), after sub- 
clause (iiih), the following subclauses shall be inserted, 
namely:- 
' (iiiha) the National Blood Transfusion Council or 
to any State Blood Transfusion Council which has its 
sole object the control, supervision, regulation or 
encouragement in India of the services related to 
operation and requirements of blood banks.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- clause,-


</section>

<section><tid>564525</tid>
<number>a</number>" National Blood Transfusion Council" 
means a society registered under the Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>). and has an 
officer not below the rank of an Additional 
Secretary to the Government of India dealing with 
the AIDS Control Project as its Chairman, by 
whatever name called;

</section>

<section><tid>1177919</tid>
<number>b</number>" State Blood Transfusion Council" means 
a society registered, in consultation with the 
National Blood Transfusion Council, under the 
Societies Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>). or 
under any law corresponding to that Act in force in 
any part of India and has Secretary to the 
Government of that State dealing with the 
Department of Health, as its Chairman, by whatever 
name called; or

</section>

<section><tid>1280217</tid>
<number>iiihb</number>any fund set up by a State Government 
to provide medical relief to the poor; or

</section>

<section><tid>1082499</tid>
<number>iiihc</number>the Army Central Welfare Fund or the 
Indian Naval Benevolent Fund or the Air Force 
Central Welfare Fund established by the armed 
forces of the Union for the welfare of the past and 
present members of such forces or their dependents; 
or'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>977205</tid>
<number>27</number>Amendment of section 80GG. In section 80GG of the Income- tax 
Act, for the words" one thousand rupees", the words" two thousand 
rupees" shall be substituted with effect from the 1st day of April, 
<year>1997</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>175534</tid>
<number> 28</number> Amendment of section 80-IA. In section 80-IA of the Income- 
tax Act, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>214101</tid>
<number>a</number>in subsection (1), after the words 
" infrastructure facility", the words" or scientific and 
industrial research and development" shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>1519756</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (4A), the following sub- 
section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (4B) This section applies to any company 
registered in India carrying on scientific and 
industrial research and development which fulfils all 
the following conditions, namely:-


<subsection><tid>140219</tid>
<number>i</number>the company has the main object of scientific 
and industrial research and development;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1255395</tid>
<number>ii</number>the company is for the time being approved by 
the prescribed authority at any time before the 1st day 
of April, <year>1998</year>.";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1423876</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (5), after clause (ia), the 
following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (ib) in the case of a company referred to in sub- 
section (4B), hundred percent. of the profits and gains 
derived from such business;";


</section>

<section><tid>1082993</tid>
<number>d</number>in sub- section (6), after clause (iv), the 
following clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (v) five in the case of an assessee, being a company 
referred to in sub-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

section (4B), deriving profits and gains from scientific 
and industrial research and development.";


</section>

<section><tid>526312</tid>
<number>e</number>in sub- section (12),-

<subsection><tid>663526</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (c), after sub- clause (2), the 
following sub- clause, shall be inserted, namely:-
" (3) in the case of a company carrying on 
scientific and industrial research and development, 
means the assessment year relevant to the previous year 
in which the company is approved by the prescribed 
authority for the purposes of sub- section (4B)";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1281568</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (ca), the following clause shall be 
substituted, namely-.-
' (ca)" infrastructure facility" means-


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>663526</tid>
<number>i</number>a road, highway, bridge, airport, port, rail 
system or any other public facility of a similar nature 
as may be notified by the Board in this behalf in the 
Official Gazette;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1281568</tid>
<number>ii</number>a water supply project, irrigation project, 
sanitation and sewerage system;'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1382842</tid>
<number>29</number>Omission of section 80J. Section 80J of the Income- tax shall 
be omitted and shall be deemed to have been omitted with effect from 
the 1st day of April, <year>1989</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1823814</tid>
<number> 30</number> Amendment of section 80L. In section 80L of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section
<section><tid>758264</tid>
<number>1</number>with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>.- 

<subsection><tid>1701828</tid>
<number>a</number>in caluse (1) and (2), for the words 
" thirteen thousand", the words" twelve thousand" shall 
be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>961717</tid>
<number>b</number>after caluse (2), the following, proviso 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that where any income referred in clause 
 (iv), clause (v) or clause (va) remains unallowed after 
the deduction under the foregoing provision of this 
section, there shall be allowed in computing the total 
income of the assessee, an additional deduction of an 
amount equal to so much of such income as has remained 
unallowed so, however, that the amount of such 
additional deduction shall not exceed three thousand 
rupees."




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1247176</tid>
<number>31</number>Amendment of section 80R. In section 80R of the Income- tax 
Act, for the portion beginning with the words" equal. to" and ending 
with the words" whichever is higher", the following shall be substi- 
tuted with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-
" equal to seventy- five per cent. of such remuneration, 
as is brought into India by, or on behalf of, the 
assessee in convertible foreign exchange within a period 
of six months from the end of the previous year or where 
the Chief Commissioner or Commissioner is satisfied (for  
  reasons to be recorded in writing) that the assessee is, 
for reasons beyond his control unable to do so within 
the said period of six months, within such further 
period as the Chief Commissioner or Commissioner may 
allow in this behalf;

Provided that no deduction under this section 
shall be allowed unless the assessee furnishes a 
certificate, in the prescribed form, along with the 
return ofincome, certifying that the, deduction has been 
correctly claimed in accordance with the provisions of 
this section.".


<pagefootnote><pagenum>15</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>510127</tid>
<number>32</number>Amendment of Section 80RR. In section 80RR of the Income- 
tax Act, for the portion begining with the words" equal to" and 
ending with the words" whichever is higher", the following shall be 
substituted with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely;-
" equal to seventy- five per cent of such income, as is 
brought into India by, or on behalf of, the assessee in 
convertible foreign exchange within a period of six 
months from the end of the previous year or where the 
Chief Commisioner or Commissioner is satisfied (for  
  reasons to be recorded in writing) that the assessee is, 
for reasons beyond his control unable to do so within 
the said period of six months, within such further 
period as the Chief Commissioner or Commissioner may 
allow in this behalf:

Provided that no deduction under this section shall be 
allowed unless the assessee furnishes a certificate, in 
the prescribed form along with the return of income 
certifying that the education has been correctly claimed 
in accordance with the provisions of this section."



</article>



<article><tid>1925963</tid>
<number>33</number>Amendment of section 80RRA. In section 80RRA of the Income- 
tax Act, in sub- section 1, for the portion beginning with the words 
" equal to" and ending with the words" whichever is higher", the 
following shall be substituted with effect from the 1st day of April 
<year>1997</year>, namely;-
" equal to seventy- five per cent of such remuneration, as 
is brought into India by, or on behalf of, the assessee 
in convertible foreign exchange within a period of six 
months from the end of the previous year or where the 
Chief Commissioner or Commissioner is satisfied (for  
  reasons to be recorded in writing) that the assessee is, 
for reasons beyond his control unable to do so within 
the said period of six months within such further period 
as the Chief Commissioner or Commissioner may allow in 
this behalf:

Provided that no deduction under this sub- section 
shall be allowed unless the assessee furnishes a 
certificate in the prescribed form along with the return 
of income, certifying that the deduction has been 
correctly claimed in accordance with the provisions of 
this section."



</article>



<article><tid>1180760</tid>
<number> 34</number> Amendment of section 88. In section 88 of the Income- tax 
Act, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>154146</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (2) after clause (xv), the 
following clause shall be inserted namely:-

</section>

<section><tid>1695326</tid>
<number>xvi</number>as subscription to equity shares or 
debentures forming part of any eligible issue of capital 
approved by the Board on an application made by a public 
company in the prescribed form:
Provided that where a deduction is claimed 
and allowed under this clause with reference to the cost 
of any equity shares or debentures, the cost of such 
shares of debentures shall not be taken into account for 
the purposes of sections 54EA and 54EB.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause,-


<subsection><tid>1938389</tid>
<number>i</number>" eligible issue of capital" means an issue 
made by a public company formed and registered in India 
and the issue is wholly and exclusively for the purposes 
of developing, maintaining and operating an 
infrastructure facility or for generating, or for 
generating and distributing, power;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1052790</tid>
<number>ii</number>" infrastructure facility" shall have the 
meaning assigned to it in clause (ca) of sub- section 
 (12) of section 80-IA;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>16</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1545723</tid>
<number>iii</number>" public company" shall have the meaning 
assigned to it in section 3 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (1 of <year>1956</year>);.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>456263</tid>
<number>xvii</number>as subscription to any units of any 
mutual fund referred to in clause (23D). of section 10 
and approved by the Board on an application made by such 
mutual fund in the prescribed form:
Provided that where a deduction is claimed and 
allowed under this clause with reference to, the cost of 
units, the cost of such units shall not be taken into 
account for the purposes of section 54EA and 54EB:

Provided further that this clause shall apply if 
the amount of subscription to such units is subscribed 
only in the eligible issue of capital of any company.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, 
" eligible issue of capital" means an issue referred to 
in clause (i) of Explanation to clause (xvi) of sub- 
section (2) of section 88.';


</section>

<section><tid>1516274</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (5), the following sub- section shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (5A) Where the aggregate of any sums specified in 
clause (i) to clause (xv) of sub- section (2) exceeds an 
amount of sixty thousand rupees, a deduction under sub- 
section (1) shall be allowed with reference to so much of the 
aggregate as does not exceed an amount of sixty thousand 
rupees:

Provided that, in the case of an individual referred to 
in the proviso to sub- section (1) the provisions of this sub- 
section shall have effect as if for the words" sixty thousand 
rupees", the words" seventy thousand rupees" had been 
substituted.".


</section>

<section><tid>151953</tid>
<number>c</number>in sub- section (6), in clause (ii), for the words 
" twelve thousand rupees", the words" fourteen thousand 
rupees" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>246978</tid>
<number>d</number>after sub- section (7), the following sub- section 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" (7A) If any equity shares or debentures, with 
reference to the cost of which a deduction is allowed under 
sub- section (1), are sold or otherwise transferred by the 
assessee to any person at any time within a period of three 
years from the date of their acquisition, the aggregate 
amount of the deductions of income- tax so allowed in respect 
of such equity shares or debentures in the previous year or 
years preceding the previous year in which such sale or 
transfer has taken place shall be deemed to be tax payable by 
the assessee for the assessment year relevant to such 
previous year and shall be added to the amount of income- tax 
on the total income of the assessee with which he is 
chargeable for such assessment year.

Explanation.- A person shall be treated as having 
acquired any shares or debentures on the date on which his 
name is entered in relation to those shares or debentures in 
the register of members or of debenture- holders, as the case 
may be, of the public company."




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1475719</tid>
<number>35</number>Omission of section 88A. Section 88A of the Income- tax Act 
shall be omitted and shall be deemed to have been omitted with effect 
from the 1st day of April, <year>1994</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>980191</tid>
<number>36</number>Amendment of section 88B. In section 88B of the Income- tax 
Act, for the words" one hundred thousand rupees, the words", one 
hundred and twenty thousand rupees" shall be substituted with effect 
from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>17</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>449720</tid>
<number> 37</number> Amendment of section 112. In section 112 of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section
<section><tid>1699585</tid>
<number>1</number>with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,- 

<subsection><tid>1750927</tid>
<number>a</number>in clause (b), in sub clause (ii), for the words" thirty per 
cent:', the words" twenty per cent:' shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1634216</tid>
<number>b</number>in clause (d), in sub- clause (ii), for the words" thirty per 
cent.", the words" twenty per cent." shall be substituted.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>707256</tid>
<number>38</number>Amendment of section 115AC. In section 115AC of the Income- 
tax Act, in sub- section 1, in clause (a), after the words" specify 
in this behalf', the words" or on bonds or shares of a public sector 
company, sold by the Government" shall be inserted with effect from 
the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>464238</tid>
<number>39</number>Insertion of new section 115JA. After section 115J of the 
Income- tax Act, the following section shall be inserted with effect 
from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>115J</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Deemed income relating to certain companies.

</article>



<article><tid>405429</tid>
<number> 115JA</number> Deemed income relating to certain companies. 
 (1) Notwithstanding anything contained in any other 
provisions of this Act, where in the case of an assessee, 
being a company, the total income, as computed under this Act 
in respect of any previous year relevant to the assessment 
year commencing on or after the 1st day April, <year>1997</year> 
 (hereafter in this section referred to as the relevant  
  previous year) is less than thirty per cent. of its 
book 
profit the total income of such assessee chargeable to tax 
for the relevant previous year shall be deemed to be an 
amount equal to thirty per cent. of such book profit.
<section><tid>1251179</tid>
<number>2</number>Every assessee, being a company, shall, for the 
purposes of this section prepare its profit and loss account 
for the relevant previous year in accordance with the 
provisions of Parts II and III of Schedule VI to the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>):.
Provided that while preparing profit and loss account, 
the depreciation shall be calculated on the same method and 
rates which have been adopted for calculating the 
depreciation for the purpose of preparing the profit and loss 
account laid before the company at its annual general meeting 
in accordance with the provisions of section 210 of the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>):.

Provided further that where a company has adopted or 
adopts the financial year under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of  
  <year>1956</year>). which is different from the previous year under the 
Act, the method and rates for calculation of depreciation 
shall correspond to the method and rates which have been 
adopted for calculating the depreciation for such financial 
year or part of such financial year falling within the 
relevant previous year.

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," book 
profit" means the net profit as shown in the profit and loss 
account for the relevant previous year prepared under sub- 
section (2), as increased by-


<subsection><tid>231921</tid>
<number>a</number>the amount of income- tax paid or payable, and 
the provision therefor; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>5187</tid>
<number>b</number>the amounts carried to any reserves by 
whatever name called; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>679676</tid>
<number>c</number>the amount or amounts set aside to provisions 
made for meeting liabilities, other than ascertained 
liabilities; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1663103</tid>
<number>d</number>the amount by way of provision for losses of 
subsidiary companies; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>165866</tid>
<number>e</number>the amount or amounts of dividends paid or 
proposed; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>823155</tid>
<number>f</number>the amount or amounts of expenditure 
relatable to any income to which any of the provisions 
of Chapter III applies;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

if any amount referred to in clauses (a) to (f) is debited to the 
profit and loss account, and as reduced by,-


<subsubsection><tid>780516</tid>
<number>i</number>the amount withdrawn from any reserves or 
provisions if any such amount is credited to the profit and 
loss account:
Provided that, where this section is applicable to an 
assessee in any previous year (including the relevant  
  previous year), the amount withdrawn from reserves created or 
provisions made in a previous year relevant to the assessment 
year commencing on or after the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year> shall 
not be reduced from the book- profit unless the book profit of 
such year has been increased by those reserves or provisions 
 (out of which the said amount was withdrawn) under this 
Explanation; or


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>579881</tid>
<number>ii</number>the amount of income to which any of the 
provisions of Chapter III applies, if any such amount is 
credited to the profit and loss account; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1247085</tid>
<number>iii</number>the amount of loss brought forward or 
unabsorbed depreciation, whichever is less as per books of 
account.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause, the loss 
shall not include depreciation; or


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1605848</tid>
<number>iv</number>the amount of profits derived by an industrial 
undertaking from the business of, generation or generation 
and distribution of power; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>124932</tid>
<number>v</number>the amount of profits derived by an industrial 
undertaking located in an industrially backward State or 
district as referred to in sub- clause (b) or subclause (c) of 
clause (iv) of sub- section (2) of section 80-IA, for the 
assessment years such industrial undertaking is eligible to 
claim a deduction of hundred per cent. of the profits and 
gains under sub- section (5) of section 80-IA; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1975698</tid>
<number>vi</number>the amount of profits derived by an industrial 
undertaking from the business of developing, maintaining and 
operating any infrastructure facility as defined under sub- 
section (12) of section 80- 1A, and subject to fulfilling the 
conditions laid down in sub- section (4A) of section 80-IA; or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>88091</tid>
<number>vii</number>the amount of- profits of a sick industrial 
company for the assessment year commencing from the 
assessment year relevant to the previous. year in which the 
said company has become a sick industrial company under sub- 
section (1) of section 17 of the Sick Industrial Companies 
 (Special Provisions) Act, <year>1985</year> (1 of <year>1986</year>) and ending with 
the assessment year during which the entire net worth of such 
company becomes equal to or exceeds the accumulated losses.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this clause," net 
worth" shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (ga) 
of sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Sick Industrial 
Companies (Special Provisions) Act, <year>1985</year> (1 of <year>1986</year>).


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>481203</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing contained in subsection (1) shall affect the 
determination of the amounts in relation to the relevant previous year 
to be carried forward to the subsequent year or years under the 
provisions of sub- section (2) of section 32 or subsection (3) of 
section 32A or clause (ii) of sub- section (1) of section 72 or section 
 73 or section 74 or sub- section (3) of section 74A.

</section>

<section><tid>1323450</tid>
<number>4</number>Save as otherwise provided in this section, all other 
provisions of this Act shall apply to every assesses, being a company, 
mentioned in this section.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>392652</tid>
<number> 40</number> Amendment of section 115K. In section 115K of the Income- tax 
Act, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>348810</tid>
<number>a</number>for the words" forty- seven thousand rupees", 
wherever they occur, the words" forty- nine thousand three 
hundred and thirty rupees" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1448261</tid>
<number>b</number>for the words" six lakh rupees", at both the 
places where they occur, the words" seven lakh rupees" shall 
be substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>973513</tid>
<number>41</number>Amendment of section 120. In section 120 of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section (4), in clause (b), for the words" a Deputy 
Commissioner" and" such Deputy Commissioner", the words" a Deputy 
Commissioner or a Deputy Director" and" such Deputy Commissioner or 
Deputy Director" shall respectively be substituted with effect from 
the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>123851</tid>
<number> 42</number> Amendment of section 139. In section 139 of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>1664072</tid>
<number>a</number>the Explanation shall be renumbered as Explanation 
 1 and in the Explanation 1 as so renumbered, in clause (b), 
for sub- clause (i), the following sub- clause shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (i) in a case where the accounts of the assessee 
are required under this Act or any other law to be 
audited or where the report of an accountant is required 
to be furnished under section 80HHC or section 80HHD or 
where the prescribed certificate is required to be 
furnished under section 80R or section 80RR or sub- 
section (1) of section 80RRA, or in the case of a co- 
operative society or in the case of a working partner of 
a firm whose accounts are required under this Act or any 
other law to be audited, the 31st day of October of the 
assessment year;";


</section>

<section><tid>1036855</tid>
<number>b</number>after Explanation 1 as so renumbered, the 
following Explanation shall be inserted, namely:-
Explanation 2.- For the purposes of sub- clause (i) 
of clause (b) of Explanation 1, the expression" working 
partner" shall have the meaning assigned to it in 
Explanation 4 of clause (b) of section 40.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>419789</tid>
<number>43</number>Amendment of section 148. In section 148 of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, the words" not being less than thirty days," 
shall be omitted and shall be deemed to have been omitted with effect 
from the 1st day of April, <year>1989</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>488853</tid>
<number>44</number>Amendment of section 153. In section 153 of the Income- tax 
Act, in Explanation 1, in clause (iii), for the words" the date on 
which the assessee furnishes", the words" the last date on which the 
assessee is required to furnish" shall be substituted with effect from 
the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1320263</tid>
<number>45</number>Amendment of section 158B. In section 158B of the Income- tax 
Act, in clause (a), for the words" period of ten previous years"', the 
words" previous years relevant to ten assessment years" shall be 
substituted and shall be deemed to have been substituted with effect 
from the 1st day of July, <year>1995</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1432584</tid>
<number>46</number>Amendment of section 158BB. In section of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, in the Explanation, for clause (b), the 
following clause shall be substituted and shall be deemed to have been 
substituted with effect from the 1st day of July, <year>1995</year>, namely:-
" (b) of a firm, returned income and total income 
assessed for each of the previous years falling within the 
block period shall be the income determined before allowing 
deduction of salary, interest, commission, bonus or 
remuneration by whatever name called:

Provided that undisclosed income of the firm so 
determined shall not be chargeable to tax in the hands of the 
partners, whether on allocation or on account of 
enhancement.".



</article>



<article><tid>827776</tid>
<number> 47</number> Amendment of section 158BE. In section 158BE of the Income- 
tax Act, after sub- section (2), the following Explanation shall be 
inserted and shall be deemed to have been inserted with effect from 
the 1st day of July, <year>1995</year>, namely:-
" Explanation.- In computing the period of limitation for 
the purposes of this section, the period-

<section><tid>532841</tid>
<number>i</number>- during which the assessment proceeding is stayed by 
an order or injunction of any court, or

</section>

<section><tid>492902</tid>
<number>ii</number>commencing from the day on which the Assessing 
Officer directs the assessee to get his accounts audited 
under sub- section (2A) of section 142

<pagefootnote><pagenum>20</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and ending on the day on which the assessee is required to 
furnish a report of such audit under that sub- section,

shall be excluded.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1760663</tid>
<number>48</number>Amendment of section 158G. In section 158BG of the Income- tax 
Act, for the proviso, the following proviso shall be substituted with 
effect from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-
" Provided that no such order shall be passed without 
the previous approval of the Commissioner or Director, as the 
case may be.".



</article>



<article><tid>765290</tid>
<number> 49</number> Amendment of section 194A. In section 194A of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section (3), in clause (i), for the proviso, the following 
proviso shall be substituted with effect from the 1st day of October, 
<year>1996</year>, namely:-
" Provided that in respect of the income credited or paid 
in respect of-

<section><tid>1657648</tid>
<number>a</number>time deposits with a banking company to which 
the Banking Regulation Act, <year>1949</year> (10 of <year>1949</year>) applies 
 (including any bank or banking institution referred to  
  in section 51 of that Act); or

</section>

<section><tid>1281349</tid>
<number>b</number>time deposits with a co- operative society 
engaged in carrying on the business of banking;

</section>

<section><tid>1707180</tid>
<number>c</number>deposits with a public company which is 
formed and registered in India with the main object of 
carrying on the business of providing long- term finance 
for construction or purchase of houses in India for 
residential purposes and which is for the time being 
approved by the Central Government for the purpose of 
clause (viii) of sub- section (1) of section 36,
the provisions of this clause shall have effect as if for the 
words" two thousand five hundred rupees", the words" ten 
thousand rupees" had been substituted and the aforesaid 
amount shall be computed with reference to the income 
credited or paid by a branch of the banking company or the 
co- operative society or the public company, as the case may 
be;".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1965978</tid>
<number> 50</number> Amendment of section 199. In section 199 of the Income- tax 
Act, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>590657</tid>
<number>i</number>for the words" owner of the security", the words 
" owner of the security, or depositor or owner of property or 
of unit- holder" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1972783</tid>
<number>ii</number>in the first proviso, for the word" owner", the 
words" owner or depositor or unit- holder" shall be 
substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1385059</tid>
<number>iii</number>for the second proviso, the following proviso 
shall be' substituted, namely:-
" Provided further that where any property, 
deposit, security, unit or share is owned jointly by two 
or more persons not constituting a partnership, the 
payment shall be deemed to have been made on behalf of, 
and credit shall be given to, each such person in the 
same proportion in which rent, interest on deposit or on 
security or income in respect of unit or dividend on 
share is assessable as his income.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1873770</tid>
<number>51</number>Omission of section 206A and 206B. Sections 206A and 206B of 
the Income- tax Act shall be omitted with effect from the 1st day of 
October, <year>1996</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>21</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>374090</tid>
<number>52</number>Amendment of section 206C. In section 206C of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, for the Table, the following Table shall be 
substituted with effect from the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>, namely:-
" TABLE 
S. No. Nature of Goods Percentage 
 (1)  (2)  (3) 
 (i) Alcoholic liquor for human consumption 
 (other than Indian- made foreign liquor) 
and tendu leaves Ten per cent. 
 (ii) Timber obtained under a forest lease Fifteen per cent. 
 (iii) Timber obtained by any mode other 
than under a forest lease Five per cent. 
 (iv) Any other forest produce not being 
timber or tendu leaves. Fifteen per cent.",



</article>



<article><tid>1555963</tid>
<number>53</number>Amendment of section 208. In section 208 of the Income- tax 
Act, for the words" one thousand five hundred rupees", the words" five 
thousand rupees" shall be substituted with effect from the 1st day of 
October, <year>1996</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>415296</tid>
<number> 54</number> Amendment of section 234C. In section 234C of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section 1, with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>,-
<section><tid>1628860</tid>
<number>a</number>in the first proviso, for the words" instalment of 
advance tax which is immediately due or where no such 
instalment is so due", the words" remaining instalments of 
advance tax which are due or where no such instalments are 
due" shall be substituted;.

</section>

<section><tid>536418</tid>
<number>b</number>the second proviso shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1868350</tid>
<number>55</number>Amendment of section 272A. In section 272A of the Income- tax 
Act, in sub- section (2), in clause (c), the words, figures and letters 
" or section 206A or section 206B" shall be omitted with effect from 
the 1st day of October, <year>1996</year>.
Wealth- tax



</article>



<article><tid>1388288</tid>
<number> 56</number> Amendment of section 2. In section 2 of the Wealth- tax Act, 
 <year>1957</year> (27 of <year>1957</year>). (hereinafter referred to as the Wealth- tax Act), in 
clause (ea), for sub- clause (i), the following sub- clause shall be 
substituted with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, narnely:-
<section><tid>1847725</tid>
<number>i</number>any building or land appurtenant thereto 
 (hereinafter referred to as" house"), whether used for 
residential or commercial purposes or for the purpose of 
maintaining a guest- house or otherwise including a farmhouse 
situated within twenty- five kilometers from local limits of 
any municipality (whether known as municipality, municipal  
  corporation or by any other name) or a cantonment board, but 
does not include-

<subsection><tid>154283</tid>
<number>1</number>a house meant exclusively for residential 
purposes and which is allotted by a company to an 
employee or an officer or director who is in whole- time 
employment, having a gross annual salary of less than 
two lakh rupees;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1994494</tid>
<number>2</number>any house for residential or commercial 
purposes which forms part of stock- in- trade;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1278608</tid>
<number>3</number>any house which the assessee may occupy for 
the purposes of any business or profession carried on by 
him;'.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1992049</tid>
<number> 57</number> Amendment of section 4. In section 4 of the Wealth- tax Act, 
with effect from the 1st day of April, <year>1997</year>, for subsection (7), the 
following sub- sections shall be substituted, namely:-
" (7) Where the assessee is a member of a co- operative 
society, company or other association of persons and a 
building or part thereof is allotted or leased to him under a 
house building scheme of the society, company or association, 
as the


<pagefootnote><pagenum>22</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

case may be, the assessee shall, notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act or any other law for the time being in 
force, be deemded to be the owner of such building or part 
and the value of such building or part shall be included in 
computing the net wealth of the assessee; and, in determining 
the value of such building or part, the value of any 
outstanding instalments of the amount payable under such 
scheme by the assessee to the society, company or association 
towards the cost of such building or part and the land 
appurtenant thereto shall, whether the amount so payable is 
described as such or in any other manner in such scheme, be 
deducted as a debt owed by him in relation to such building 
or part.

<section><tid>1636420</tid>
<number>8</number>A person-

<subsection><tid>348216</tid>
<number>a</number>who is allowed to take or retain possession 
of any building or part thereof in part performance of a 
contract of the nature referred to in section 53A of the 
Transfer of Property Act, <year>1882</year> (43 of <year>1882</year>);.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>71882</tid>
<number>b</number>who acquires any rights (excluding any rights  
by way of a lease from month to month or for a period 
  not exceeding one year) in or with respect to any 
building or part thereof by virtue of any such 
transaction as is referred to in clause (f) of section 
 269UA of the Income- tax Act,
shall be deemed to be the owner of that building or part 
thereof and the value of such building or part shall be 
included in computing the net wealth of such person.".




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1069046</tid>
<number>58</number>Amendment of 21A. In section 21A of the Wealth- tax Act, for 
the words" Where any property is held", the words, brackets and 
figures" Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (i) of section 
5, where any property is held" shall be substituted and shall be 
deemed to have been substituted with effect from the 1st day of April, 
<year>1993</year>.
CHAP

INDIRECT TAXES

CHAPTER IV

INDIRECT TAXES

Customs



</article>



<article><tid>1463896</tid>
<number>59</number>Amendment of section 15. In the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of  
  <year>1962</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the Customs Act), in section 15, in 
sub- section 1, for the proviso, the following proviso shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" Provided that if a bill of entry has been presented 
before the date of entry inwards of the vessel or the arrival 
of the aircraft by which the goods are imported, the, bill of 
entry shall be deemed to have been presented on the date of 
such entry inwards or the arrival, as the case may be.".



</article>



<article><tid>1974114</tid>
<number>60</number>Amendment of section 27. In section 27 of the Customs Act, in 
sub- section 1, after the second proviso, the following proviso shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" Provided also that in the case of goods which are 
exempt from payment of duty by a special order issued under 
sub- section (2) of section 25, the limitation of one year or 
six months, as the case may be, shall be computed from the 
date of issue of such order.".



</article>



<article><tid>1871817</tid>
<number>61</number>Amendment of section 28AA. In section 28AA of the Customs 
Act, in the opening paragraph, for the words" Where a person", the 
words, figures and letters" Subject to the provisions contained in 
section 28AB, where a person" shall- be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>399646</tid>
<number>62</number>Insertion of new section 28AB. After section 28AA of the 
Customs Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>28AB</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Interest on delayed payment of duty in special cases.

</article>



<article><tid>1851315</tid>
<number> 28AB</number> Interest on delayed payment of duty in special 
cases.
<section><tid>1400300</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any duty has not been levied or has been  
short levied or erroneously refunded by reason of collusion 
or any wilful mis- statement or suppression of facts, the 
person who is liable to pay the duty as determined under sub- 
section (2) of section 28, shall, in addition to the duty, be 
liable to pay interest at such rate not below ten per cent. 
and not exceeding thirty per cent. per annum, as is for the 
time being fixed by the Board, from the first day of the 
month succeeding the month in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>23</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

which the duty ought to have been paid under this Act, or 
from the date of such erroneous refund, as the. case may be, 
but for the provisions contained in sub- section (2) of 
section 28, till the date of payment of such duty.


</section>

<section><tid>1473890</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that the provisions of subsection (1) shall not apply to 
cases where the duty became payable before the date on which 
the Finance (No. 2) Bill, <year>1996</year> receives the assent of the 
President.
Explanation 1.- Where the duty determined to be payable 
is reduced by the Commissioner (Appeals), the Appellate 
Tribunal or, as the case may be, the court, the interest 
shall be payable on such reduced amount of duty.

Explanation 2.- Where the duty determined to be payable 
is increased or further increased by the Commissioner 
 (Appeals), the Appellate Tribunal or, as the case may be, the 
court, the interest shall be payable on such increased or 
further increased amount of duty.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>369672</tid>
<number>63</number>Amendment of section 46. In section 46 of the Customs Act, 
in sub- section (3), for the second proviso, the following proviso 
shall be substituted, namely:-
" Provided further that a bill of entry may be presented 
even before the delivery of such manifest if the vessel or 
the aircraft by which the goods have been shipped for 
importation into India is expected to arrive within thirty 
days from the date of such presentation."



</article>



<article><tid>488493</tid>
<number>64</number>Insertion of new section 114A. After section 114 of the 
Customs Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>114A</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Penalty for short- levy or non- levy of duty in certain cases.

" 114A. Penalty for short- levy or non- levy of duty in 
certain cases. Where the duty has not been levied or has been 
short- levied or the interest has not been charged or paid or 
has not been part paid or the duty or interest has been 
erroneously refunded by reason of collusion or any wilful 
misstatement or suppression of facts, the person who is 
liable to pay the duty or interest, as the case may be, as 
determined under sub- section (2) of section 28 shall also be 
liable to pay a penalty equal to the duty or interest so 
determined;

Provided that where the duty or interest determined to 
be payable is reduced or increased by the Commissioner 
 (Appeals), the Appellate Tribunal or, as the case may be, the 
court, then, for the purposes of this section, the duty or 
interest as reduced or increased, as the case may be, shall 
be taken into account:

Provided further that where any penalty has been levied 
under this section, no penalty shall be levied under section 
 112 or section 114."



</article>



<article><tid>52149</tid>
<number> 65</number> Amendment of section 129. In section 129 of the Customs Act, 
for sub- section (3), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (3) The Central Government shall appoint-

<section><tid>1820530</tid>
<number>a</number>a person who is or has been a Judge of a High 
Court; or

</section>

<section><tid>1012934</tid>
<number>b</number>one of the members of the Appellate Tribunal,
to be the President thereof.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>500237</tid>
<number>66</number>Amendment of section 129C. In section 129C of the Customs 
Act, in sub- section (4), for the words" one lakh rupees", the words 
" ten lakh rupees" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1911215</tid>
<number>67</number>Amendment of Act 51 of <year>1975</year>. The Customs Tariff Act, <year>1975</year> 
 (hereinafter referred to as the Customs Tariff Act) shall be amended 
in the manner specified in the Second Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>294389</tid>
<number> 68</number> Special duties of customs.
<section><tid>1189446</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of goods mentioned  
in the First Schedule to the Customs Tariff Act, or in that Schedule, 
as amended from time to time, there shall be levied and collected as a 
special duty of customs, an amount equal to two per cent. of the value 
of the goods as determined in accordance with the provisions of 
section 14 of the Customs Act.

</section>

<section><tid>872497</tid>
<number>2</number>Sub- section (1) shall cease to have effect after the 31st 
day of March, <year>1999</year>, and upon such cesser, section 6 of the General 
Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of <year>1897</year>). shall apply as if the said subsection 
had been repealed by Central Act.

</section>

<section><tid>449315</tid>
<number>3</number>The special duties of customs referred to in sub- section (1) 
shall be in addition to any duties of customs chargeable on such goods 
under the Customs Act or any other law for the time being in force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1990532</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of the Customs Act and the rules and 
regulations made thereunder including those relating to refunds and 
exemptions from duties shall, as far as may be, apply in relation to 
the levy and collection of the special duties of customs leviable 
under this section in respect of any goods as they apply in relation 
to the levy and collection of- the duties of customs on such goods 
under that Act or those rules and regulations, as the case may be.
Excise


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>507635</tid>
<number>69</number>Amendment of long title. In the Central Excises and Salt 
Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of <year>1944</year>). (hereinafter referred to as the Central Excises  
  Act), in the long tide, the words" and to salt" shall be omitted.

</article>



<article><tid>1171708</tid>
<number>70</number>Amendment of preamble. In the preamble to the Central Excises 
Act, the words" and to salt" shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1635385</tid>
<number>71</number>Amendment of section 1. In section 1 of the Central Excises 
Act, for sub- section 1, the following subsection shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (1) This Act may be called the Central Excise Act, <year>1944</year>.".



</article>



<article><tid>1160130</tid>
<number>72</number>Amendment of section 2. In section 2 of the Central Excises 
Act, clauses (i) and (j) shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1341634</tid>
<number>73</number>Amendment of section 3. In section 3 of the Central Excises 
Act, in sub- section 1, for the words" other than salt which are 
produced or manufactured in India and a duty on salt manufactured in, 
or imported by land into, any part of India", the words" which are 
produced or manufactured in India" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>376845</tid>
<number> 74</number> Amendment of section 4. In section 4 of the Central Excises 
Act,-
<section><tid>385368</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1),- in clause (a), in the proviso, 
after clause (i), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ia) where the price at which such goods are 
ordinarily sold by the assessee is different for different 
places of removal, each such price shall, subject to the 
existence of other circumstances specified in clause (a), be 
deemed to be the normal price of such goods in relation to 
each such place of removal;";


</section>

<section><tid>314171</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (4),-

<subsection><tid>1783615</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (b),-

<subsubsection><tid>542837</tid>
<number>A</number>in sub- clause (i), the word" or" occurring at the 
end shall be omitted;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1640392</tid>
<number>B</number>after sub- clause (ii), the following sub- clause shall 
be inserted, namely:-

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>757863</tid>
<number>iii</number>a depot, premises of a consignment agent or 
any other place or premises from where the excisable goods 
are to be sold after their clearance from the factory and";

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>772694</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (b), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1369288</tid>
<number>ba</number>" time of removal", in respect of goods removed from 
the place of removal referred to in sub- clause (iii) of 
clause (b), shall be deemed to be the time at which such 
goods are cleared from the factory.'.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>860291</tid>
<number>75</number>Amendment of section 11AA. In section 11AA of the Central 
Excises Act, in the opening paragraph, for the words"' Where a person", 
the words figures and letters" Subject to the provisions contained 
in section 11AB, where a person" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1044907</tid>
<number> 76</number> Insertion of new sections 11AB and 11AA. After section 11AA 
of the Central Excises Act, the following sections shall be inserted, 
namely:-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11AB</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Interest on delayed payment of duty.

" 11AB. Interest on delayed payment of duty. (1) Where 
any duty of excise has not been levied or paid or has been 
short- levied or short- paid or erroneously refunded by reason 
of fraud, collusion or any wilful misstatement or suppression 
of facts, or contravention of any of the provisions of this 
Act or the rules made thereunder with intent to evade payment 
of duty, the person liable to pay duty as determined under 
sub- section (2) of section 11A shall, in


<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

addition to the duty, be liable to pay interest at such rate 
not below ten per cent. and not exceeding thirty per cent. 
per annum, as is for the time being fixed by the Board, from 
the first day of the month succeeding the month in which the 
duty ought to have been paid under this Act or the rules made 
thereunder or from the date of such erroneous refund, as the 
case may be, but for the provisions contained in sub- section 
 (2) of section 11A, till the date of payment of such duty.

<section><tid>1176923</tid>
<number>2</number>For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that the provisions of subsection (1) shall not apply to 
cases where the duty became payable before the date on which 
the Finance (No. 2) Bill, <year>1996</year> receives the assent of the 
President.
Explanation 1-Where the duty determined to be payable 
is reduced by the Commissioner (Appeals), the Appellate 
Tribunal or, as the case may be, the court, the interest 
shall be payable on such reduced amount of duty.

Explanation 2.- Where the duty determined to be payable 
is increased or further increased by the Commissioner 
 (Appeals), the Appellate Tribunal or, as the case may be, the 
court, the interest shall be payable on such increased or 
further increased amount of duty.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>11AC</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Penality for short- levy, of duty in certain cases.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1012339</tid>
<number>11AC</number>Penality for short- levy or non- levy, of duty 
in certain cases. Where any duty of excise has not been 
levied or paid or has been shortlevied or short- paid or 
erroneously refunded by reasons of fraud, collusion or 
any wilful mis- statement or suppression of facts, or 
contravention of any of the provisions of this Act or of 
the rules made thereunder with intent to evade payment 
of duty, the person who is liable to pay duty as 
determined under sub- section (2) of section 11A, shall 
also be liable to pay a penalty equal to the duty so 
determined:
Provided that where the duty determined to be payable 
is reduced or increased by the Commissioner (Appeals), the 
Appellate Tribunal or, as the case may be, the court, then, 
for the purposes of this section, the duty as reduced or 
increased. as the case may be, shall be taken into account.".



</article>



<article><tid>96955</tid>
<number>77</number>Amendment of section 11B. In section 11B of the Central 
Excises Act, in the Explanation, in clause (B), after sub- clause (e), 
the following sub- clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (e) in the case of goods which are exempt from payment 
of duty by a special order issued under sub- section (2) of 
section 5A, the date of issue of such order;".



</article>



<article><tid>1678266</tid>
<number>78</number>Amendment of section 12. In section 12 of the Central Excises 
Act, for the words and figures" Sea Customs Act, <year>1878</year> (8 of <year>1878</year>).", 
the words and figures" Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>)." shall be 
substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1522193</tid>
<number>79</number>Omission of Chapter V. Chapter V of the Central Excises Act 
shall be omitted.


</article>



<article><tid>1412347</tid>
<number>80</number>Amendment of section 35D. In section 35D of the Central 
Excises Act, in sub- section (3), for the words" one lakh rupees", the 
words" ten lakh rupees" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1671423</tid>
<number> 81</number> Amendment of Act 32 of <year>1985</year>. In the Finance Act, <year>1985</year>,-
<section><tid>1236000</tid>
<number>a</number>sections 44 and 49 shall be omitted;

</section>

<section><tid>1917382</tid>
<number>b</number>Fifth Schedule shall be omitted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>581804</tid>
<number>82</number>Amendment of Act 5 of <year>1986</year>. The Central Excise Tariff Act, 
 <year>1985</year> (hereinafter referred to as the Central Excise Tariff Act) shall 
be amended in the manner specified in the Third Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>849432</tid>
<number>83</number>Amendment of Act 58 of <year>1986</year>. The Additional Duties of Excise 
 (Goods of Special Importance) Act, <year>1957</year> (hereinafter referred to as  
  the Additional Duties of Excise Act) shall be amended in the manner 
specified in the Fourth Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1444300</tid>
<number> 84</number> Amendment of Act 40 of <year>1978</year>. In the Additional Duties of 
Excise (Textiles and Textile Articles) Act, <year>1978</year>,-
<section><tid>924930</tid>
<number>a</number>in section 3, in sub- section (1), for the words" twenty per 
cent.", the words" fifteen per cent." shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>923749</tid>
<number>b</number>the Schedule shall be amended in the manner specified in 
the Fifth Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

SERVICE TAX

CHAPTER V

SERVICE TAX




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1134705</tid>
<number> 85</number> Amendment of Act 32 of <year>1994</year>. In the Finance Act, <year>1994</year>, with 
effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, appoint,-
<section><tid>723015</tid>
<number>1</number>in section 65,-

<subsection><tid>113165</tid>
<number>a</number>clause (1) shall be renumbered as clause (1B) and 
before the clause as so renumbered, the following clauses 
shall be inserted, namely:-

<subsubsection><tid>1618983</tid>
<number>1</number>' advertisement" includes any notice, 
circular, label, wrapper, document, boarding or any 
other audio or visual representation made by means of 
light, sound, smoke or gas;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1839462</tid>
<number>1A</number>" advertising agency" means any commercial 
concern engaged in providing any service connected with 
the making, preparation, display or exhibition of 
advertisement and includes an advertising consultant;';

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>232754</tid>
<number>b</number>after clause (4), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>604006</tid>
<number>4A</number>" courier agency" means a commercial concern 
engaged in the door- to- door transportation of time- 
sensitive documents, goods or articles utilising the 
services of a person, either directly or indirectly, to 
carry or accompany such documents, goods or articles.';

<subsection><tid>1419567</tid>
<number>c</number>after clause (6), the following clause shall 
be inserted, namely:-

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>496666</tid>
<number>6A</number>" pager" means an instrument, apparatus or 
appliance which is a non- speech, one way personal 
calling system with alert and has the capability of 
receiving, storing and displaying numeric or alpha- 
numeric messages.';

<subsection><tid>608263</tid>
<number>d</number>in clause (15), for the words" telephone 
connection", the words" telephone connection or pager" 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>515511</tid>
<number>e</number>in clause (16),-

<subsubsection><tid>1586529</tid>
<number>i</number>after sub- clause (b), the following sub- 
clause shall be inserted, namely:-
" (ba) to a subscriber, by the telegraph authority, 
in relation to a pager;";


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>845314</tid>
<number>ii</number>after sub- clause (c), the following sub- 
clauses shall be inserted, namely:-
" (d) to a client, by an advertising agency, in 
relation to advertisements in any manner;


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>515511</tid>
<number>e</number>to a customer, by a courier agency, in 
relation to door- to- door transportation of time- 
sensitive documents, goods or articles;";

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>165484</tid>
<number>2</number>for section 66, the following section shall be 
substituted, namely:-



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>500237</tid>
<number> 66</number> Charge of service tax.
<section><tid>1064790</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the  
commencement of this Chapter, there shall be charged a tax 
 (hereinafter referred to as the service tax), at the rate of 
five per cent. of the value of the taxable services referred 
to in sub- clauses (a), (b) and (c) of clause (16) of section 
 65 which are provided to any person by the person responsible 
for collecting the service tax.

</section>

<section><tid>1292532</tid>
<number>2</number>With effect from the date notified under section 
 85 of the Finance (No. 2) Act, <year>1996</year>, there shall be charged a 
service tax at the rate of five per cent. of the value of the 
taxable services referred to in sub- clauses (ba), (d) and (e) 
of clause (16) of section 65 which are provided to any person 
by the person responsible for collecting the service tax.";

<pagefootnote><pagenum>27</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1594254</tid>
<number>3</number>in section 67,-

<subsection><tid>308394</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (b), for the words" telephone 
connections", at both the places where they occur, the 
words" telephone connections or pagers" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1478767</tid>
<number>ii</number>after clause (c) the following clauses shall 
be inserted, namely:-
" (d) in relation to service provided by an 
advertising agency to a client shall be the gross amount 
charged by such agency from the client for services in 
relation to advertisements;


<subsubsection><tid>1330109</tid>
<number>e</number>in relation to service provided by a courier 
agency to a customer shall be the gross amount charged 
by such agency from the customer for services in 
relation to door- to- door transportation of time 
sensitive documents, goods and articles;";

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1961750</tid>
<number>4</number>in section 68, in sub- section (1), for the words 
" or the insurer", the words", the insurer, the advertising 
agency or the courier agency" shall be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>217451</tid>
<number>86</number>Validation. Notwithstanding anything contained in section 93 
of the Finance Act, <year>1994</year> (32 of <year>1994</year>), the notification of the 
Government of India in the Ministry of Finance, Department of Revenue 
No. G. S. R. 174 (E), dated the 3rd April, <year>1996</year>, shall have and shall be 
deemed always to have had, effect on and from the 1st day of July, 
<year>1994</year>.
CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER VI

MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>604888</tid>
<number>87</number>Amendment of Act 74 of <year>1956</year>. In section 15 of the Central 
Sales Tax Act, <year>1956</year>, after clause (c), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (ca) where a tax on sale or purchase of paddy referred 
to in sub- clause (i) of clause (1) of section 14 is leviable 
under that law and the rice procured out of such paddy is 
exported out of India, then, for the purposes of sub- section 
 (3) of section 5, the paddy and rice shall be treated as a 
single commodity.".



</article>



<article><tid>1934049</tid>
<number>88</number>North- Eastern Development Finance Corporation Limited to be 
exempt for a certain period from liability to pay income- tax. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, the North- 
Eastern Development Finance Corporation Limited (a company formed and  
  registered under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>)  (1 of <year>1956</year>.) shall not be 
liable to pay tax on its income for the previous year relevant to the 
assessment year commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1996</year> and for the 
nine previous years next following that previous year.


</article>



<article><tid>1835908</tid>
<number>89</number>Amendment of Act 6 of <year>1898</year>. In the Indian Post Office Act, 
<year>1898</year>, with effect from such date as the, Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint, for the First Schedule, 
the following Schedule shall be substituted, namely:-

</article>



 </act>