<act><title>

The 
    Passports Act, 1967</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
    may be called the Passports Act, 1967.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India and applies also to citizens of India who are outside 
    India.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “departure”, with its grammatical 
    variations and cognate expressions, means departure from India by water, 
    land or air; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “passport” means a passport issued or 
    deemed to have been issued under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “passport authority” means an officer or 
    authority empowered under rules made under this Act to issue passports or 
    travel documents and includes the Central Government; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “travel document” means a travel 
    document issued or deemed to have been issued under this Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Passport 
    or travel document for departure from India.—No 
    person shall depart from, or attempt to depart from India, unless he holds 
    in this behalf a valid passport or travel document. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “passport” includes a passport which 
    having been issued by or under the authority of the Government of a foreign 
    country satisfies the conditions prescribed under the Passport (Entry into 
    India) Act, 1920 (34 of 1920), in respect of the class of passports to which 
    it belongs; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “travel document” includes a travel 
    document which having been issued by or under the authority of the 
    Government of a foreign country satisfies the conditions prescribed. 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Classes 
    of passports and travel documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The following classes of passports may be issued under this Act, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   ordinary passport; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   official passport; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   diplomatic passport. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    following classes of travel documents may be issued under this Act, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   emergency certificate authorising a 
    person to enter India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   certificate of identity for the purpose 
    of establishing the identity of a person; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   such other certificate or document as 
    may be prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Central Government shall, in consonance with the usage and practice followed 
    by it in this behalf, prescribe the classes of persons to whom the classes 
    of passports and travel documents referred to respectively in sub-section 
    (1) and sub-section (2) may be issued under this Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Applications for passports, travel documents, etc., and orders 
    thereon.—<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    An application for the issue of a passport under this Act for visiting such 
    foreign country or countries (not being a named foreign country) as may be 
    specified in the application may be made to the passport authority and shall 
    be accompanied by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[such 
    fee as may be prescribed to meet the expenses incurred on special security 
    paper, printing, lamination and other connected miscellaneous services in 
    issuing passports and other travel documents].
 

    Explanation.—In this section, 
    “named foreign country” means such foreign country as the Central Government 
    may, by rules made under this Act, specify in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>1A</number> An 
    application for the issue of— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   a passport under this Act for visiting a 
    named foreign country; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   a travel document under this Act, for 
    visiting such foreign country or countries (including a named foreign 
    country) as may be specified in the application or for an endorsement on the 
    passport or travel document referred to in this section,
 
may be made to the passport authority and 
    shall be accompanied by such fee (if any) not exceeding rupees fifty, as may 
    be prescribed.
 <subsubsection>
<number>IB</number> Every 
    application under this section shall be in such form and contain such 
    particulars as may be prescribed.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    receipt of an application <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[under 
    this section], the passport authority, after making such inquiry, if any, as 
    it may consider necessary, shall, subject to the other provisions of this 
    Act, by order in writing,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   issue the passport or travel document 
    with endorsement, or, as the case may be, make on the passport or travel 
    document the endorsement, in respect of the foreign country or countries 
    specified in the application; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   issue the passport or travel document 
    with endorsement, or, as the case may be, make on the passport or travel 
    document the endorsement, in respect of one or more of the foreign countries 
    specified in the application and refuse to make an endorsement in respect of 
    the other country or countries; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   refuse to issue the passport or travel 
    document or, as the case may be, refuse to make on the passport or travel 
    document any endorsement. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    passport authority makes an order under clause (b) or clause (c) of 
    sub-section (2) on the application of any person, it shall record in writing 
    a brief statement of its reasons for making such order and furnish to that 
    person on demand a copy of the same unless in any case the passport 
    authority is of the opinion that it will not be in the interests of the 
    sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of India, friendly 
    relations of India with any foreign country or in the interests of the 
    general public to furnish such copy. 
  














 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Refusal 
    of passports, travel documents. etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the other provisions of this Act, the passport authority shall 
    refuse to make an endorsement for visiting any country under clause (b) or 
    clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5 on any one or more of the 
    following grounds, and on no other ground, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the applicant may, or is likely to, 
    engage in such country in activities prejudicial to the sovereignty and 
    integrity of India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the presence of the applicant in 
    such country may, or is likely to, be detrimental to the security of India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that the presence of the applicant in 
    such country may, or is likely to, prejudice the friendly relations of India 
    with that or any other country;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that in the opinion of the Central 
    Government the presence of the applicant in such country is not in the 
    public interest. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the other provisions of this Act, the passport authority shall refuse to 
    issue a passport or travel document for visiting any foreign country under 
    clause (c) of sub-section (2) of section 5 on any one or more of the 
    following grounds, and on no other ground, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the applicant is not a citizen of 
    India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the applicant may, or is likely to, 
    engage outside India in activities prejudicial to the sovereignty and 
    integrity of India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that the departure of the applicant from 
    India may, or is likely to, be detrimental to the security of India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that the presence of the applicant 
    outside India may, or is likely to, prejudice the friendly relations of 
    India with any foreign country; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   that the applicant has, at any time 
    during the period of five years immediately preceding the date of his 
    application, been convicted by a court in India for any offence involving 
    moral turpitude and sentenced in respect thereof to imprisonment for not 
    less than two years; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   that proceedings in respect of an 
    offence alleged to have been committed by the applicant are pending before a 
    criminal court in India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   that a warrant or summons for the 
    appearance, or a warrant for the arrest, of the applicant has been issued by 
    a court under any law for the time being in force or that an order 
    prohibiting the departure from India of the applicant has been made by any 
    such court; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   that the applicant has been repatriated 
    and has not reimbursed the expenditure incurred in connection with such 
    repatriation; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   that in the opinion of the Central 
    Government the issue of a passport or travel document to the applicant will 
    not be in the public interest. 
  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Duration 
    of passports and travel documents.—A 
    passport or travel document shall, unless revoked earlier, continue in force 
    for such period as may be prescribed and different periods may be prescribed 
    for different classes of passports or travel documents or for different 
    categories of passports or travel documents under each such class: 
 
Provided that 
    a passport or travel document may be issued for a shorter period than the 
    prescribed period— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   if the person by whom it is required so 
    desires; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if the passport authority, for reasons 
    to be communicated in writing to the applicant, considers in any case that 
    the passport or travel document should be issued for a shorter period. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>8</number> 
    Extension of period of passport.—Where a passport is issued for a 
    shorter period than the prescribed period under section 7, such shorter 
    period shall, unless the passport authority for reasons to be recorded in 
    writing otherwise determines, be extendable for a further period (which 
    together with the shorter period shall not exceed the prescribed period) and 
    the provisions of this Act shall apply to such extension as they apply to 
    the issue thereof.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Conditions and forms of passports and travel documents.—The 
    conditions subject to which, and the form in which, a passport or travel 
    document shall be issued or renewed shall be such as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    different conditions and different forms may be prescribed for different 
    classes of passports or travel documents or for different categories of 
    passports or travel documents under each such class: 
 
Provided 
    further that a passport or travel document may contain in addition to the 
    prescribed conditions such other conditions as the passport authority may, 
    with the previous approval of the Central Government, impose in any 
    particular case. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Variation, impounding and revocation of passports and travel documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The passport authority may, having regard to the provisions of sub-section 
    (1) of section 6 or any notification under section 19, vary or cancel the 
    endorsements on a passport or travel document or may, with the previous 
    approval of the Central Government, vary or cancel the conditions (other 
    than the prescribed conditions) subject to which a passport or travel 
    document has been issued and may, for that purpose, require the holder of a 
    passport or a travel document, by notice in writing, to deliver up the 
    passport or travel document to it within such time as may be specified in 
    the notice and the holder shall comply with such notice. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    passport authority may, on the application of the holder of a passport or a 
    travel document, and with the previous approval of the Central Government 
    also vary or cancel the conditions (other than the prescribed conditions) of 
    the passport or travel document. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    passport authority may impound or cause to be impounded or revoke a passport 
    or travel document,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if the passport authority is satisfied 
    that the holder of the passport or travel document is in wrongful possession 
    thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   If the passport or travel document was 
    obtained by the suppression of material information or on the basis of wrong 
    information provided by the holder of the passport or travel document or any 
    other person on his behalf: 
 
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[Provided that if the 
    holder of such passport obtains another passport, the passport authority 
    shall also impound or cause to be impounded or revoke such other passport.] 1[Provided 
    that if the holder of such passport obtains another passport, the passport 
    authority shall also impound or cause to be impounded or revoke such other 
    passport.]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   if the passport authority deems it 
    necessary so to do in the interests of the sovereignty and integrity of 
    India, the security of India, friendly relations of India with any foreign 
    country, or in the interests of the general public; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   if the holder of the passport or travel 
    document has, at any time after the issue of the passport or travel 
    document, been convicted by a court in India for any offence involving moral 
    turpitude and sentenced in respect thereof to imprisonment for not less than 
    two years; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   if proceedings in respect of an offence 
    alleged to have been committed by the holder of the passport or travel 
    document are pending before a criminal court in India; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   if any of the conditions of the passport 
    or travel document has been contravened; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   if the holder of the passport or travel 
    document has failed to comply with a notice under sub-section (1) requiring 
    him to deliver up the same; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   if it is brought to the notice of the 
    passport authority that a warrant or summons for the appearance, or a 
    warrant for the arrest, of the holder of the passport or travel document has 
    been issued by a court under any law for the time being in force or if an 
    order prohibiting the departure from India of the holder of the passport or 
    other travel document has been made by any such court and the passport 
    authority is satisfied that a warrant or summons has been so issued or an 
    order has been so made. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    passport authority may also revoke a passport or travel document on the 
    application of the holder thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the 
    passport authority makes an order varying or cancelling the endorsements on, 
    or varying the conditions of, a passport or travel document under 
    sub-section (1) or an order impounding or revoking a passport or travel 
    document under sub-section (3), it shall record in writing a brief statement 
    of the reasons for making such order and furnish to the holder of the 
    passport or travel document on demand a copy of the same unless in any case 
    the passport authority is of the opinion that it will not be in the 
    interests of the sovereignty and integrity of India, the security of India, 
    friendly relations of India with any foreign country or in the interests of 
    the general public to furnish such a copy. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    authority to whom the passport authority is subordinate may, by order in 
    writing, impound or cause to be impounded or revoke a passport or travel 
    document on any ground on which it may be impounded or revoked by the 
    passport authority and the foregoing provisions of this section shall, as 
    far as may be, apply in relation to the impounding or revocation of a 
    passport or travel document by such authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> A court 
    convicting the holder of a passport or travel document of any offence under 
    this Act or the rules made thereunder may also revoke the passport or travel 
    document: 
 
Provided that 
    if the conviction is set aside on appeal or otherwise the revocation shall 
    become void. 
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> An order 
    of revocation under sub-section (7) may also be made by an appellate court 
    or by the High Court when exercising its powers of revision. 
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> On the 
    revocation of a passport or travel document under this section the holder 
    thereof shall, without delay, surrender the passport or travel document, if 
    the same has not already been impounded, to the authority by whom it has 
    been revoked or to such other authority as may be specified in this behalf 
    in the order of revocation. 
  











 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>10A</number> Suspension of 
    passports or travel documents in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in section 
    10, if the Central Government or any designated officer is satisfied that 
    the passport or travel document is likely to be impounded or caused to be 
    impounded or revoked under clause (c) of sub-section (3) of section 10 and 
    it is necessary in the public interest so to do, it or he may,—1[10A. 
    Suspension of passports or travel documents in certain cases.—(1) 
    Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions contained in section 
    10, if the Central Government or any designated officer is satisfied that 
    the passport or travel document is likely to be impounded or caused to be 
    impounded or revoked under clause (c) of sub-section (3) of section 10 and 
    it is necessary in the public interest so to do, it or he may,—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   by order, suspend, with immediate 
    effect, any passport or travel document; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   pass such other appropriate order which 
    may have the effect of rendering any passport or travel document invalid, 
 
for a period not exceeding four weeks: 
 
Provided that 
    the Central Government or the designated officer may, if it or he considers 
    appropriate, extend, by order and for reasons to be recorded in writing, the 
    said period of four weeks till the proceedings relating to variation, 
    impounding or revocation of passport or travel document under section 10 are 
    concluded: 
 
Provided 
    further that every holder of the passport or travel document, in respect of 
    whom an order under clause (a) or clause (b) of this sub-section had been 
    passed, shall be given an opportunity of being heard within a period of not 
    later than eight weeks reckoned from the date of passing of such order and 
    thereupon the Central Government may, if necessary, by order in writing, 
    modify or revoke the order passed under this sub-section. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    designated officer shall immediately communicate the orders passed under 
    sub-section (1), to the concerned authority at an airport or any other point 
    of embarkation or immigration, and to the passport authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every 
    authority referred to in sub-section (2) shall, immediately on receipt of 
    the order passed under sub-section (1), give effect to such order.]
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>10B</number> 
    Validation of intimations.—Every 
    intimation given by the Central Government or the designated officer, before 
    the commencement of the Passports (Amendment) Act, 2002, to any immigration 
    authority at an airport or any other point of embarkation or immigration, 
    restricting or in any manner prohibiting the departure from India of any 
    holder of the passport or travel document under sub-section (3) of section 
    10, shall be deemed to be an order under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 10A and 
    such order shall continue to be in force for a period of three months from 
    the date of commencement of the Passports (Amendment) Act, 2002, or the date 
    of giving such intimation, whichever is later.1[10B. 
    Validation of intimations.—Every 
    intimation given by the Central Government or the designated officer, before 
    the commencement of the Passports (Amendment) Act, 2002, to any immigration 
    authority at an airport or any other point of embarkation or immigration, 
    restricting or in any manner prohibiting the departure from India of any 
    holder of the passport or travel document under sub-section (3) of section 
    10, shall be deemed to be an order under sub-section (1) of section 10A and 
    such order shall continue to be in force for a period of three months from 
    the date of commencement of the Passports (Amendment) Act, 2002, or the date 
    of giving such intimation, whichever is later." 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    sections 10A and 10B, the expression "designated officer" means such officer 
    or authority designated, by order in writing, as such by the Central 
    Government.]
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> Any person aggrieved 
    by an order of the passport authority under clause (b) or clause (c) of 
    sub-section (2) of section 5 or clause (b) of the proviso to section 7 or 
    sub-section (1), or sub-section (3) of section 10 or by an order under 
    sub-section (6) of section 10 of the authority to whom the passport 
    authority is subordinate, may prefer an appeal against that order to such 
    authority (hereinafter referred to as the appellate authority) and within 
    such period as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    no appeal shall lie against any order made by the Central Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal 
    shall be admitted if it is preferred after the expiry of the period 
    prescribed therefor: 
 
Provided that 
    an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor 
    if the appellant satisfies the appellate authority that he had sufficient 
    cause for not preferring the appeal within that period. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The period 
    prescribed for an appeal shall be computed in accordance with the provisions 
    of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963), with respect to the computation of 
    the periods of limitation thereunder. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Every appeal under this section shall be made by a petition in writing and 
    shall be accompanied by a copy of the statement of the reasons for the order 
    appealed against where such copy has been furnished to the appellant and
    <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[by 
    such fee as may be prescribed for meeting the expenses that may be incurred 
    in calling for relevant records and for connected services]. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    disposing of an appeal, the appellate authority shall follow such procedure 
    as may be prescribed: 
 
Provided that 
    no appeal shall be disposed of unless the appellant has been given a 
    reasonable opportunity of representing his case. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every 
    order of the appellate authority confirming, modifying or reversing the 
    order appealed against shall be final.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Offences and penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   contravenes the provisions of section 3; 
    or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   knowingly furnishes any false 
    information or suppresses any material information with a view to obtaining 
    a passport or travel document under this Act or without lawful authority 
    alters or attempts to alter or causes to alter the entries made in a 
    passport or travel document; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   fails to produce for inspection his 
    passport or travel document (whether issued under this Act or not) when 
    called upon to do so by the prescribed authority; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   knowingly uses a passport or travel 
    document issued to another person; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   knowingly allows another person to use a 
    passport or travel document issued to him; 
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[two 
    years or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees] or with both.
 </subsection></section><section>
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> Whoever, not 
    being a citizen of India,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   makes an application for a passport or 
    obtains a passport by suppressing information about his nationality, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   holds a forged passport or any travel 
    document, 
 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which shall not be less than one year but which may extend to five 
    years and with fine which shall not be less than ten thousand rupees but 
    which may extend to fifty thousand rupees.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Whoever abets any offence punishable under <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[sub-section (1) or 
    sub-section (1A)] shall, if the act abetted is committed in consequence of 
    the abetment, be punishable with the punishment provided in that sub-section 
    for that offence.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whoever 
    contravenes any condition of a passport or travel document or any provision 
    of this Act or any rule made thereunder for which no punishment is provided 
    elsewhere in this Act shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
    may extend to three months or with fine which may extend to five hundred 
    rupees or with both. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Whoever, 
    having been convicted of an offence under this Act, is again convicted of an 
    offence under this Act shall be punishable with double the penalty provided 
    for the latter offence. 
 
 
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Power to arrest.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any officer of customs empowered by a general or special order of the 
    Central Government in this behalf and any <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[officer 
    of police or emigration officer] not below the rank of a sub-inspector may 
    arrest without warrant any person against whom a reasonable suspicion exists 
    that he has committed any offence punishable under section 12 and shall, as 
    soon as may be, inform him of the grounds for such arrest.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every officer making an arrest under this section shall, without unnecessary 
    delay, take or send the person arrested before a magistrate having 
    jurisdiction in the case or to the officer in charge of the nearest police 
    station and the provisions of <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[section 
    57 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], shall, so far as 
    may be, apply in case of any such arrest.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Power of search and seizure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any officer of customs empowered by a general or special order of the 
    Central Government in this behalf and any <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[officer 
    of police or emigration officer] not below the rank of a sub-inspector may 
    search any place and seize any passport or travel document from any person 
    against whom a reasonable suspicion exists that he has committed any offence 
    punishable underv section 12.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of the <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Code 
    of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], relating to searches and seizures 
    shall, so far as may be, apply to searches and seizures under this section.
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Previous sanction of Central Government necessary.—No 
    prosecution shall be instituted against any person in respect of any offence 
    under this Act without the previous sanction of the Central Government or 
    such officer or authority as may be authorised by that Government by order 
    in writing in this behalf. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government 
    or any officer or authority for anything which is in good faith done or 
    intended to be done under this Act. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Passports and travel documents to be property of Central Government.—A 
    passport or travel document issued under this Act shall at all times remain 
    the property of the Central Government. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Passports, etc. not to be issued to persons who cannot emigrate under 
    Act 7 of 1922.—[Rep. by the 
    Passports (Amendment) Act, 1993 (35 of 1993), sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).] 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Passports and travel documents to be invalid for travel to certain 
    countries.—Upon the issue of a 
    notification by the Central Government that a foreign country is— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   a country which is committing external 
    aggression against India; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   a country assisting the country 
    committing external aggression against India; or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   a country where armed hostilities are in 
    progress; or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   a country to which travel must be 
    restricted in the public interest because such travel would seriously impair 
    the conduct of foreign affairs of the Government of India. 
 
a passport or travel document for travel 
    through or visiting such country shall cease to be valid for such travel or 
    visit unless in any case a special endorsement in that behalf is made in the 
    prescribed form by the prescribed authority. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Issue 
    of passports and travel documents to persons who are not citizens of India.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the foregoing provisions relating to issue of a 
    passport or travel document, the Central Government may issue, or cause to 
    be issued, a passport or travel document to a person who is not a citizen of 
    India if that Government is of the opinion that it is necessary so to do in 
    the public interest. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Power 
    to delegate.—The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any 
    power or function which may be exercised or performed by it under this Act 
    other than the power under clause (d) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 6 or the 
    power under clause (1) of sub-section (2) of that section or the power under 
    section 24, may, in relation to such matters and subject to such conditions, 
    if any, as it may specify in the notification, be exercised or performed— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   by such officer or authority subordinate 
    to the Central Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   by any State Government or by any 
    officer or authority subordinate to such Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   in any foreign country in which there is 
    no diplomatic mission of India, by such foreign Consular Officer; 
 
as may be specified in the notification. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> Power 
    to exempt.—Where the Central 
    Government is of the opinion that it is necessary or expedient in the public 
    interest so to do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette and 
    subject to such conditions, if any, as it may specify in the notification,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   exempt any person or class of persons 
    from the operation of all or any of the provisions of this Act or the rules 
    made thereunder; and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   as often as may be, cancel any such 
    notification and again subject, by a like notification, the person or class 
    of persons to the operation of such provisions. 
  



 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Act to be in addition to certain enactments . </title>—The provisions of this Act shall be in addition to and not in derogation of the provisions of the Passport (Entry into India) Act, 1920 (34 of 1920), <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[the Emigration Act, 1983 (31 of 1983)], the Registration of Foreigners Act, 1939 (16 of 1939), the Foreigners Act, 1946 (31 of 1946), <footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[***] the Trading with the Enemy (Continuance of Emergency Provisions) Act, 1947 (16 of 1947), the Foreigners Law (Application and Amendment) Act, 1962 (42 of 1962), <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 1973)] and other enactments relating to foreigners and foreign exchange. 





 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> Power 
    to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for 
    carrying out the purposes of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the appointment, jurisdiction, control 
    and functions of passport authorities; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the classes of persons to whom passports 
    and travel documents referred to respectively in sub-section (1) and 
    sub-section (2) of section 4 may be issued; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the form and particulars of application 
    for the issue or renewal of a passport or travel document or for endorsement 
    on a passport or travel document and where the application is for the 
    renewal, the time within which it shall be made; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the period for which passports and 
    travel documents shall continue in force; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the form in which and the conditions 
    subject to which the different classes of passports and travel documents may 
    be issued, renewed or varied; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[<number>ee</number>   
    specifying the foreign country for the purposes of the Explanation to 
    sub-section (1) of section 5;] 
    4[(ee) specifying the foreign country for the purposes 
    of the Explanation to sub-section (1) of section 5;]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the fees payable in respect of <footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[any 
    application for the issue of a passport under sub-section (1) of section 5 
    or issue of a passport] <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[for 
    visiting a foreign country referred to in sub-section (1A) of section 5] or 
    travel document or for varying any endorsement or making a fresh endorsement 
    on a passport or a travel document and the fees payable in respect of any 
    appeal under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the appointment of appellate authorities 
    under sub-section (1) of section 11, the jurisdiction of, and the procedure 
    which may be followed by, such appellate authorities;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   the services (including the issue of a 
    duplicate passport or travel document in lieu of a passport or travel 
    document lost, damaged or destroyed) which may be rendered in relation to a 
    passport or travel document and the fees therefor; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   any other matter which is to be or may 
    be prescribed or in respect of which this Act makes no provision or makes 
    insufficient provision and provision is, in the opinion of the Central 
    Government, necessary for the proper implementation of the Act. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[in two or more 
    successive sessions and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], both House 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.
 
 









 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>25</number> Change of short title of Act 34 of 
      1920.—In the Indian Passport 
      Act, 1920, in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 1, for the words and figures “the 
      Indian Passport Act, 1920”, the words, brackets and figures “the Passport 
      (entry into India) Act, 
      1920” shall be substituted. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> Savings 
    as to certain passports and applications.—[Rep. 
    by the Passports (Amendment) Act, 1993 (35 of 1993), sec. 8 (w.e.f. 
    1-7-1993).] 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Repeal 
    and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Passports 
    Ordinance, 1967 (4 of 1967) is hereby repealed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action taken or purporting 
    to have been done or taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have 
    been done or taken under this Act as if this Act had commenced on the 5th 
    day of May, 1967. 

 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of 
    1978, sec. 2, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 
    1993, sec. 2, for “a fee of rupees fifty” (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Ins. by Act 31 of 
    1978, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 
    1993, sec. 3, for section 8 (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>   Ins. by Act 35 of 
    1993, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   Ins. by Act 17 of 
    2002, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 23-10-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>   Ins. by Act 17 of 
    2002, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 23-10-2001).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 
    1993, sec. 5, for “by such fee (if any) not exceeding rupees twenty-five as 
    may be prescribed” (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 1993, sec. 6 for “six months or with fine which 
    may extend to two thousand rupees" (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Ins. by Act 35 of 1993, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 1993, sec. 6, for “sub-section (1)” (w.e.f. 
    1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 1993, sec. 7, for "officer of police" (w.e.f. 
    1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of 1978, sec. 3, for “section 61 of the Code of 
    Criminal Procedure, 1898 
     
    (5 of 1898)” (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 1993, sec. 7, for "officer of police" (w.e.f. 
    1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of 1978, sec. 4, for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1898 (5 of 1898)” (w.e.f. 8-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Subs. by Act 35 of 1993, sec. 9 for “the Emigration Act, 1922 (7 of 1922)” (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> The words and figures “the Foreign Exchange Regulation Act, 1947 (7 of 1947)” omitted by Act 31 of 1978, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Ins. by Act 31 of 1978, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>   Ins. by Act 31 of 1978, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by Act 35 of 1993, sec.10, for “any application for the 
    issue or renewal of a passport” (w.e.f. 1-7-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>   Subs. by Act 31 of 1978, sec. 6, for “issue or renewal of a 
    passport" (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Subs. by Act 31 of 
    1978, sec. 6, for certain words (w.e.f. 18-8-1978).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>