<act><tid>230202</tid>
<title>THE SUGAR UNDERTAKINGS (TAKING OVER OF MANAGEMENTS) ACT, <year>1978</year></title>

ACT NO. 49 OF <year>1978</year>
[ 30th December, <year>1978</year>.]

An Act to provide for the temporary taking over, in the public 
interest, of the management of certain sugar undertakings in certain 
circumstances.

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>297311</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1689003</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Sugar Undertakings (Taking Over of Management) Act, <year>1978</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>163832</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>863750</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 9th day of 
November, <year>1978</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1613265</tid>
<number> 2</number> Difinitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1936242</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day", in relation to any sugar year, means 
such day in the year as the Central Government may, by 
notification, specify having regard to the agro- 
climatic conditions prevailing or likely to prevail, 
the quantity of cane available or likely to be 
available for crushing and other relevant factors:
Provided that for the sugar year <year>1978</year>- 79, the appointed day 
shall be the 15th day of November, <year>1978</year>;


</section>

<section><tid>595412</tid>
<number>b</number>" cane" means sugarcane;

</section>

<section><tid>891901</tid>
<number>c</number>" date of vesting", in relation to a sugar undertaking, 
means the date on which the management of the 
undertaking vests in the Central Government under 
section 3;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>742</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>979947</tid>
<number>d</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>732299</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1481617</tid>
<number>f</number>" sugar undertaking" means an undertaking engaged in the 
manufacture or production of sugar by means of vacuum 
pans and with the aid of mechanical power and" notified 
sugar undertaking" means a sugar undertaking in respect 
of which a notification has been issued under section 
3;

</section>

<section><tid>1030927</tid>
<number>g</number>" sugar year" means the period of twelve months 
commencing on the 1st day of October and ending with 
the 30th day of September next following;

</section>

<section><tid>950741</tid>
<number>h</number>words and expressions used but not defined in this Act 
and demmed in the industries (Development and  
  Regulation) Act, <year>1951</year> (65 of <year>1951</year>) shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act and 
for this purpose a sugar undertaking shall be deemed to 
be an industrial undertaking within the meaning of that 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1233772</tid>
<number>i</number>words and expressions used but not defined in this Act 
or in the Industries (Development and Regulation) Act, 
 <year>1951</year> (65 of <year>1951</year>) but defined in the Companies Act, 
 <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>.
CHAP

TAKING OVER OF MANAGEMENT

CHAPTER II

TAKING OVER OF MANAGEMENT




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1868752</tid>
<number> 3</number> Vesting of management of a sugar undertaking in Central 
Government.
<section><tid>137237</tid>
<number>1</number>Where the Central Government is satisfied-- 

<subsection><tid>1648627</tid>
<number>a</number>that any sugar undertaking has in any sugar year failed 
to commence the manufacture of sugar on or before the 
appointed day in respect of that year, or having 
started the manufacture of sugar on or before that day 
ceased to manufacture sugar before the expiry of the 
average period of manufacture of sugar in relation to 
that undertaking; or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>743</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>540846</tid>
<number>b</number>that on any date in any sugar year any sugar undertaking 
has, in relation to the cane <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> purchased, at any time 
 (whether in that sugar year or in any earlier sugar  
year or sugar years and whether before or after the 
  commencement of this Act), before that date] for the 
purposes of the undertaking, arrears of cane dues to 
the extent of more than ten per cent. of the total 
price of the cane purchased for the purposes of the 
undertaking during the immediately preceding sugar 
year; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1130619</tid>
<number>c</number>that in either case the effective functioning of the 
undertaking is necessary for the purposes of this Act'
the Central Government may issue a notice in such form and in such 
manner as may be prescribed to the owner or the manager of such sugar 
undertaking calling upon such owner or manager to report in writing 
within such time, not being less than five days, as may be specified 
in the notice, the circumstances under which such undertaking has so 
failed to commence or ceased to manufacture sugar or, as the case may 
be, clear the said arrears of cane dues and to show cause as to why 
the management of such undertaking should not be taken over by the 
Central Government under this Act.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>979193</tid>
<number>2</number>As soon as may be, after the receipt of the report under sub- 
section (1) from the sugar undertaking, or where the sugar undertaking 
has failed to make such report within the time specified in the notice 
to that undertaking under sub- section (1), after the expiry of such 
time, the Central Government may make such further inquiry (if any) as 
it may deem fit, and--

<subsection><tid>729756</tid>
<number>a</number>if the Central Government is satisfied that having 
regard to all the circumstances of the case and the 
purposes of this Act that it would be expedient to give 
further time to the undertaking to enable it to 
commence or resume production of sugar or, as the case 
may be, clear the arrears of cane dues, it may, by 
order in writing, specify the date on or before which 
and the manner in which such undertaking shall commence 
or resume production of sugar or, as the case may be, 
clear the said arrears of cane dues; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>221526</tid>
<number>b</number>if the Central Government is not satisfied as provided 
in clause (a), declare by notification that the 
management
<pagefootnote><pagenum>744</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 18 of <year>1979</year>, s. 2 (with retrospective effect).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


of such undertaking shall vest in the Central 
Government on and from such date as may be specified in 
such notification.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>566781</tid>
<number>3</number>If a sugar undertaking has failed to comply with an order 
made under clause (a) of sub- section (2), or having commenced or 
resumed the production of sugar on or before the date specified in 
such order, ceased to manufacture sugar before the expiry of the 
average period of manufacture of sugar in relation to that 
undertaking, and the Central Government is satisfied that it is 
necessary so to do for the purposes of this Act, it may, by 
notification, declare that the management of such sugar undertaking 
shall vest in the Central Government on and from such date as may be 
specified in such notification.

</section>

<section><tid>1442531</tid>
<number>4</number>Any failure on the part of the owner or manager of the sugar 
undertaking to utilise the undertaking for the manufacture of sugar 
during any period shall not be taken into account for the purpose of 
issuing a notification in respect of that undertaking under clause (b) 
of sub- section (2) or sub- section (3) where such failure is 
attributable to any circumstances (other than financial difficulties) 
beyond his control.

</section>

<section><tid>266997</tid>
<number>5</number>Every notification issued under sub- section (2) or sub- 
section (3) for vesting the management of a sugar undertaking in the 
Central Government shall be in force for such period not exceeding 
three years from the date of vesting as may be specified in the 
notification <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> xxx the Central Government is of opinion that it is 
expedient in the public interest that the management of the sugar 
undertaking should continue to vest in the Central Government after 
the expiry of the period so specified, it may, from time to time, 
issue, by notification, directions for such continuance for such 
further period as may be specified in the directions:
Provided that the total period for which the management of the 
undertaking may remain vested in the Central Government shall in no 
case exceed <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> seven years] from the date of vesting.


</section>

<section><tid>1131283</tid>
<number>6</number>For the purposes of this section--

<subsection><tid>545160</tid>
<number>a</number>" cane dues", in relation to any cane purchased by a 
sugar undertaking, means the price payable in 
accordance with the agreement (whether express or  
  implied) or arrangement relating to such purchase and 
where there is no such agreement or arrangement, the 
price as determined in accordance with the law 
applicable to such purchase;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>745</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 44 of <year>1981</year>, s. 2. 
2 Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 20- 11- <year>1984</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>957879</tid>
<number>b</number>any cane dues being the price payable for any cane 
acquired for the purposes of a sugar undertaking shall 
not be deemed to be in arrears at any time before the 
expiry of fourteen days from the date of delivery of 
such cane to the undertaking;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1550500</tid>
<number>c</number>the average period of manufacture of sugar in relation 
to any sugar undertaking with respect to any sugar year 
 (hereafter in this clause referred to as the current  
  sugar year) shall be calculated by dividing the total 
number of calendar days during which the undertaking 
manufactured sugar during the period of three sugar 
years immediately preceding the current sugar year by 
the number of sugar years in which the undertaking 
manufactured sugar during the said period of three 
years.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1286062</tid>
<number> 4</number> Assets etc., of notified sugar undertaking.
<section><tid>318121</tid>
<number>1</number>The notified  
sugar undertaking shall be deemed to include all assets, rights, 
powers, authorities and privileges, in relation to the said 
undertaking and all property, movable and immovable, including lands, 
buildings, workshops, stores, instruments, machinery, automobiles and 
other vehicles and goods under production or in transit, cash 
balances, reserve funds, investments and all other rights and 
interests in, or arising out of, such property as were, immediately 
before the date of vesting, in the ownership, possession, power or 
control of that undertaking, whether within or outside India, and all 
books of account, registers and all other documents of whatever nature 
relating thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>549041</tid>
<number>2</number>Any contract, whether express or implied, or other 
arrangement (whether under any statute or otherwise) in so far as it 
relates to the management of the business and affairs of the notified 
sugar undertaking, and in force immediately before the date of 
vesting, or any order made by any Court in so far as it relates to the 
management of the business and affairs of that undertaking and in 
force immediately before the said date, shall be deemed to have 
terminated on that date.

</section>

<section><tid>1499797</tid>
<number>3</number>All persons in whom the management of the business and 
affairs of the notified sugar undertaking vests immediately before the 
date of vesting shall, as from that date, cease to be so vested.

</section>

<section><tid>1557106</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding any judgement, decree or order of any Court, 
tribunal or other authority or anything contained in any law (other  
  than this Act) for the time being in force, every Receiver, Official 
Liquidator or other person in whose possession or costody or under

<pagefootnote><pagenum>746</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

whose control the notified sugar undertaking or any part thereof may 
be immediately before the date of vesting, shall, on that date, 
deliver the possession of the said undertaking or such part thereof, 
as the case may be, to the Custodian, appointed under section 5, or, 
where no Custodian has been appointed, to such other person as the 
Central Government may direct.


</section>

<section><tid>1620011</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may take, or cause to be taken, all 
necessary steps for securing the possession of the notified sugar 
undertaking.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1010804</tid>
<number> 5</number> Appointment of Custodian.
<section><tid>477060</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, as  
soon as it is convenient administratively so to do, appoint an 
individual or a body of individuals or a Government company as the 
Custodian of a notified sugar undertaking or a group of notified sugar 
undertakings for the purpose of taking over the management of such 
undertaking or undertakings and the Custodian so appointed shall carry 
on the management of such undertaking or undertakings for and on 
behalf of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1837421</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may also appoint an individual or a 
Government company as the Custodian- General for exercising supervision 
and control over all the notified sugar undertakings, and on such 
appointment, every Custodian appointed under sub- section (1) shall act 
under the guidance, control and supervision of the Custodian- General.

</section>

<section><tid>97793</tid>
<number>3</number>On the appointment of a Custodian under sub- section (1), the 
charge of management of the notified sugar undertaking or group of 
notified sugar undertakings, as the case may be, shall vest in such 
Custodian and all persons in charge of the management of such 
undertaking or undertakings immediately before such appointment shall 
cease to be in charge of such management and shall be bound to deliver 
to the Custodian all assets, books of account, registter or other 
documents in their costody relating to such undertaking or group of 
undertakings.

</section>

<section><tid>1896472</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government may issue such directions (including  
directions as to initiating, defending or continuing any legal 
  proceedings before any Court, tribunal or other authority) to the 
Custodian or Custodian- General as to his or its powers and duties as 
the Central Government deems desirable and the Custodian- General or, 
if there is no Custodian- General, the Custodian may apply to the 
Central Government at any time for instructions as to the manner in 
which the Custodian or the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>747</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Custodian- General shall conduct the management of the notified sugar 
undertaking or in relation to any matter arising in the course of such 
management.


</section>

<section><tid>718837</tid>
<number>5</number>Any person, who, on the appointed day, has in his possession 
or under his control any books, papers or other documents relating to 
the notified sugar undertaking, shall notwithstanding anything 
contained in any other law for the time being in force, be liable, to 
account for the books, papers and other documents, to the Custodian 
and shall deliver them up to the Custodian or to such other person as 
may be authorised by the Central Government or the Custodian in this 
behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>1709556</tid>
<number>6</number>Every person in charge of the management of the notified 
sugar undertaking, immediately before the date of vesting, shall, 
within ten days from that date or within such further period as the 
Central Government may allow in this behalf, furnish to the Custodian 
a complete inventory of all the properties and assets (including  
  particulars of book debts, investments and belongings) forming part of 
the undertaking immediately before the date of vesting and of all 
liabilities and obligations of the undertaking subsisting immediately 
before that date and also of all agreements entered into by the owner 
or manager of the undertaking, in relation to the said undertaking, 
and in force immediately before that date.

</section>

<section><tid>83384</tid>
<number>7</number>The Custodian- General shall hold office during the pleasure 
of the Central Government and shall receive such remuneration as may 
be fixed by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1458228</tid>
<number>8</number>Every Custodian or where a body of individuals has been 
appointed as the Custodian, each such individual shall hold office 
during the pleasure of the Central Government and shall receive from 
the funds of the sugar undertakings or group of sugar undertakings 
concerned, such remuneration as may be fixed by the Central 
Government.
Explanation.-- The remuneration payable to the Custodian of two or 
more notified undertakings shall be allocated among the funds of the 
undertakings in such proportion as the Central Government may, having 
regard to the quantum of work in respect of such undertakings and 
other relevant circumstances, by order determine.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>748</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>490239</tid>
<number> 6</number> Payment of amount.
<section><tid>248426</tid>
<number>1</number>The owner of every notified sugar  
undertaking shall be given by the Central Government an amount in cash 
for vesting in it under section 3 the management of such undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>1935853</tid>
<number>2</number>For every months during which the management of the notified 
sugar undertaking remains vested in the Central Government under this 
Act, the amount, referred to in sub- section (1), shall be,--

<subsection><tid>352096</tid>
<number>a</number>where the daily cane crushing capacity of the 
undertaking is five hundred tonnes or less, an amount 
of five hundred rupees; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>791716</tid>
<number>b</number>where the daily cane crushing capacity of the 
undertaking is more than five hundred tonnes, an amount 
computed at the rate of one rupee for each tonne of 
such capacity or an amount of one thousand two hundred 
and fifty rupees, whichever is less.
CHAP

RELIEF TO SUGAR UNDERTAKINGS AND CANE PRODUCING FARMERS

CHAPTER III

RELIEF TO SUGAR UNDERTAKINGS AND CANE PRODUCING FARMERS




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>92411</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power of Central Government to make certain declarations.
<section><tid>634258</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, if it is satisfied, in relation to a 
notified sugar undertaking that it is necessary so to do in the 
interests of the general public with a view to preventing the fall in 
the volume of production of the sugar industry, it may, by 
notification, declare that--

<subsection><tid>1536591</tid>
<number>a</number>all or any of the enactments specified in the Schedule 
shall not apply or shall apply with such adaptations, 
whether by way of modification, addition or omission 
 (which does not, however, affect the policy of the said  
  enactments) to such sugar undertaking, as may be 
specified in such notification, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1183518</tid>
<number>b</number>the operation of all or any of the contracts, assurances 
of property, agreements, settlements, awards, standing 
orders or other instruments in force (to which such  
sugar undertaking or the person owning such undertaking 
is a party or which may be applicable to such sugar 
  undertaking or person) immediately before the date of 
issue of the notification shall remain suspended or 
that all or any of the rights, privileges, obligations

<pagefootnote><pagenum>749</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

and liabilities accruing or arising thereunder before 
the said date, shall remain suspended or shall be 
enforceable with such adaptations and in such manner as 
may be specified in the notification.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1660236</tid>
<number>2</number>The notification made under sub- section (1) in relation to a 
notified sugar undertaking shall remain in force, in the first 
instance, for such period not exceeding one year as may be specified 
in the notification but the duration of such notification may be 
extended from time to time by a further notification by a period not 
exceeding one year at a time.

</section>

<section><tid>618151</tid>
<number>3</number>Any notification made under sub- section (1) shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in any other law, 
agreement, or instrument or any decree or order of a Court, tribunal, 
officer or other authority or of any submission, settlement or 
standing order.

</section>

<section><tid>1264229</tid>
<number>4</number>Any remedy for the enforcement of any right, privilege, 
obligation or liability referred to in clause (b) of sub- section (1) 
and suspended or modified by a notification made under that sub- 
section shall, in accordance with the terms of the notification, 
remain suspended or modified and all proceedings relating thereto 
pending before any Court, tribunal, officer or other authority shall 
accordingly remain stayed or be continued subject to such adaptations, 
so, however, that on the notification ceasing to have effect--

<subsection><tid>389639</tid>
<number>a</number>any right, privilege, obligation or liability so 
remaining suspended or modified shall become revived 
and enforceable as if the notification had never been 
made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>406091</tid>
<number>b</number>any proceeding so remaining stayed shall be proceeded 
with subject to the provisions of any law which may 
then be in force, from the stage which had been reached 
when the proceedings become stayed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>663271</tid>
<number>5</number>In computing the period of limitation for the enforcement of 
any right, privilege, obligation or liability referred to in clause 
 (b) of sub- section (1), the period during which it or the remedy for 
the enforcement thereof remained suspended shall be excluded.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>750</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>744994</tid>
<number> 8</number> Assistance to notified sugar undertakings to clear arrears of 
cane dues.
<section><tid>1020750</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may issue such directions as it  
deems fit to the Custodian- General and the Custodians to facilitate 
the speedy clearance of arrears of cane dues so as to avoid undue 
hardship to cane producing farmers.

</section>

<section><tid>441753</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Central Government may render such assistance in such manner as it may 
deem fit to any notified sugar undertaking to enable the undertaking 
to clear the whole or any part of its arrears of cane dues so as to 
avoid undue hardship to cane producing farmers.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section, the expression 
" arrears of cane dues" shall be construed in accordance with the 
provisions of clauses (a) and (b) of sub- section (6) of section 3.

CHAP

MISCELLANEOUS

CHAPTER IV

MISCELLANEOUS




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1854992</tid>
<number> 9</number> Notified sugar undertaking, if a company, not to be wound up.

<section><tid>1485431</tid>
<number>1</number>No proceeding for the winding up of a notified sugar undertaking,  
being a company, shall lie in any Court or be continued whether by or 
under the supervision of any Court or voluntarily, except with the 
consent of the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>731539</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the period of limitation prescribed by any law 
for the time being in force for any application which may be made in 
the course of winding up of any such notified sugar undertaking in 
respect of any matter arising out of any transaction in relation to 
such undertaking, the time during which the making of such application 
was barred by this Act shall be excluded.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>688303</tid>
<number> 10</number> Contracts, etc., in bad faith may be cancelled or varied.
<section><tid>1050503</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If the Central Government is satisfied, after such inquiry as it may 
think fit, that any contract or agreement entered into by the owner or 
manager of a notified sugar undertaking, in relation to the said 
undertaking, at any time within twelve months immediately preceding 
the date of vesting, has been entered into in bad faith or is 
detrimental to the interests of the undertaking, it may make an order 
cancelling or varying (either unconditionally or subject to such  
  conditions as it may think fit to impose) the contract or agreement 
and thereafter the contract or agreement shall have effect 
accordingly:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>751</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Provided that no contract or agreement shall be cancelled or 
varied except after giving to the parties to the contract or agreement 
a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</section>

<section><tid>1291440</tid>
<number>2</number>Any person aggrieved by an order made under sub- section (1) 
may make an application to the principal Court of civil jurisdiction 
within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the registered office of 
the sugar undertaking is situated for the variation or reversal of 
such order and, thereupon such Court may confirm, vary or reverse such 
order.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>934211</tid>
<number>11</number>Power to terminate the contract of employment. If the 
Custodian or Custodian- General is of opinion that any contract of 
employment entered into by any owner or member of a notified sugar 
undertaking or its agent in relation to the said undertaking, at any 
time before the date of vesting, is unduly onerous, he may, by giving 
to the employee one month' s notice in writing or the salary or wages 
for one month in lieu thereof, terminate such contract of employment.


</article>



<article><tid>557613</tid>
<number> 12</number> Management of notified sugar undertakings pending taking over 
physical possession by the Custodian.
<section><tid>1625289</tid>
<number>1</number>Pending the taking over by a  
Custodian, appointed under section 5, of the physical possession of 
any notified sugar undertaking, the person in charge of the management 
of such undertaking immediately before the date of vesting shall, on 
and from that date, be in charge of the management such undertaking 
shall for and on behalf of the Central Government; and the management 
of such undertaking shall be carried on by such person subject to the 
provisions contained in sub- section (2) and such directions, if any, 
as the Central Government may give to him, and no other person, 
including the said undertaking shall, so long as such management 
continues, exercise any powers of management in relation to the said 
undertaking.

</section>

<section><tid>1905958</tid>
<number>2</number>No person in charge, under sub- section (1), of a notified 
sugar undertaking shall, without the previous approval of the 
Custodian- General appointed under section 5,--

<subsection><tid>1683917</tid>
<number>i</number>incur any expenditure from the assets appertaining to 
the undertaking otherwise than for the purpose of 
making routine payments of salaries or commissions to 
employees, agents or for the purpose of meeting the 
routine day to day expenditure;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>752</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1626921</tid>
<number>ii</number>transfer or otherwise dispose of any such assets or 
create any charge, hypothecation, lien or other 
incumbrance thereon;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>245765</tid>
<number>iii</number>invest in any manner any moneys forming part of such 
assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1067115</tid>
<number>iv</number>acquire any immovable property out of the moneys 
forming part of such assets;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>837512</tid>
<number>v</number>enter into any contract of service or agency, whether 
expressly or by implication, for purposes connected 
wholly or partly with the undertaking or vary the terms 
and conditions of any contract relating to any such 
transaction subsisting on the date of vesting.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1024637</tid>
<number>3</number>The approval of the Custodian- General may be given either 
generally in relation to certain classes of transactions relating to 
the notified sugar undertaking or specially in relation to any of its 
transactions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1881416</tid>
<number> 13</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>1193244</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Government, the Custodian- General or any other officer of Government 
or any Custodian in respect of anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>931213</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Government, the Custodian- General or any other officer of Government 
or any Custodian for any damage caused, or likely to be caused, by 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>437560</tid>
<number> 14</number> Delegation of powers.
<section><tid>226187</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, direct that all or any of the powers exercisable by it 
under this Act, other than those under this section or section 8 or 
section 20 may also be exercised by any person or persons as may be 
specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>83462</tid>
<number>2</number>Whenever any delegation of power is made under sub- section 
 (1), the person to whom such power has been delegated shall act under 
the direction, control and supervision of the Central Government.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>753</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>784688</tid>
<number> 15</number> Debts incurred for the purposes of notified sugar 
undertakings to have priority. Every debt arising out of any loan 
advanced to a notified sugar undertaking by the Central Government or 
a State Government for carrying on the management of such undertaking-
<section><tid>1444872</tid>
<number>a</number>shall have priority over all other debts, whether 
secured or unsecured, incurred before the management of 
such undertaking was taken over under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>927088</tid>
<number>b</number>shall be a preferential debt within the meaning of 
section 530 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>,
and such debts shall rank equally among themselves and be paid in full 
out of the assets of the undertaking unless such assets are 
insufficient to meet them, in which case they shall abate in equal 
proportions.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>138994</tid>
<number> 16</number> Penalties. If any person--
<section><tid>872001</tid>
<number>a</number>fails to deliver to the Custodian any assets, books of 
account, registers or any other documents in his 
custody relating to any notified sugar undertaking, or

</section>

<section><tid>554623</tid>
<number>b</number>retains any property of such undertaking or removes or 
destroys its, or

</section>

<section><tid>521771</tid>
<number>c</number>fails to comply with the provisions of section 5, or

</section>

<section><tid>1711752</tid>
<number>d</number>fails to comply with any direction made under this Act,
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years, and shall also be liable to fine.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1758976</tid>
<number> 17</number> Offences by companies.
<section><tid>745654</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under this Act  
has been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment, if he proves that the 
offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised 
all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>754</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>326097</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
any offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to be 
guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section,--


<subsection><tid>980174</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1887642</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>791195</tid>
<number> 18</number> Act not to apply to certain sugar undertakings.
<section><tid>1959771</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
provisions of this Act shall not apply to any sugar undertaking which 
is owned by or is under the management of the Central Government or a 
State Government or a corporation established by or under an enactment 
 (including an Ordinance) or a Government company as defined in section 
 617 of the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1514556</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1), the management of a 
sugar undertaking by a receiver or an authorised controller appointed 
by the Central Government or a State Government under any law for the 
time being in force shall also be deemed to be management of the 
undertaking by the Central Government or a State Government, as the 
case may be.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1728919</tid>
<number>19</number>Act to have overriding effect. The provisions of this Act 
shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
contained in any law (other than this Act) or any judgment, decree or 
order of any Court, tribunal or other authority or any instrument 
having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>455307</tid>
<number>20</number>Power to make rules. The Central Government may, by 
notification, make rules to carry out the provisions of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1360349</tid>
<number>21</number>Laying of rules and certain notifications. Every rule made by 
the Central Government under this Act and every notification made 
under section 7 shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of Parliament,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>755</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or notification or both Houses agree that the 
rule or notification should not be made, the rule or notification 
shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule or notification.



</article>



<article><tid>243193</tid>
<number> 22</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>61764</tid>
<number>1</number>The Sugar Undertakings (Taking Over of   
  Management) Ordinance, <year>1978</year> (5 of <year>1978</year>), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1099525</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the Ordinance so repealed shall be deemed to have been 
done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>