<act><title>


The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 19841</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Cine-Workers Welfare Fund Rules, 1984.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on 1st day of November, 1984. 
 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In these rules, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>1</number>   ‘Act’ means the Cine-Workers Welfare 
    Fund Act, 1981 (33 of 1981);  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   ‘Advisory Committee” means an Advisory 
    Committee constituted under section 5 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   ‘Central Advisory Committee’ means a 
    Central Advisory Committee constituted under section 6 of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>   ‘Chairman’ means the Chairman of an 
    Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee as the case may be;  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number>   ‘Commissioner’ means a Welfare 
    Commissioner appointed by the Central Government under section 8 for any 
    State or States concerned;  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>   ‘form’ means form in Schedule V;  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number>   ‘member’ means a member of an Advisory 
    Committee or the Central Advisory Committee, as the case may be;  
 </section><section>
<number>8</number>   ‘Schedule’ means a Schedule appended to 
    these rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>9</number>   ‘section’ means a section of the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>10</number>   ‘treasury’ means any Government 
    Treasury or Sub-treasury;  
 </section><section>
<number>11</number>   ‘family’ includes the husband/wife of 
    the Cine-workers wholly dependent children or legally adopted children and 
    parents who are mainly dependent on the Cine-worker.  
 </section><section>
<number>12</number>   ‘dependent’ means any of the following 
    relatives of a deceased cine-worker, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   a widow, a minor legitimate son, an 
    unmarried legitimate daughter, or a widowed mother; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   if wholly dependent on the earnings of 
    the cine worker at the time of his death a son or a daughter who has 
    attained the age of 18 years and who is infirm;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   if wholly or in part dependent on the 
    earnings of the cine-worker at the time of his death—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   a widower  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   parents  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>   a minor illegitimate son, an unmarried 
    illegitimate daughter or a daughter legitimate or illegitimate.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>d</number>   a minor brother or unmarried sister.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>e</number>   a widowed daughter-in-law.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f</number>   a minor child of a pre-deceased son.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>g</number>   a minor child of a pre-deceased daughter 
    where no parent of the child is alive or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>h</number>   a paternal a grandparent if no parent of 
    the Cine-Worker is alive.  

 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Composition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> The Central 
    Advisory Committee constituted under section 6 shall consist of the 
    following persons to be appointed by the Central Government, namely:— 
 

1[<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[(i)   Chairman
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   An officer to be nominated by the 
    Central Government who shall be the Vice-Chairman.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   Two officers of the Central Government 
    to be nominated by the Government.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   Welfare Commissioners.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   Such number of persons to represent the 
    producers as are equal to the aggregate of those provided in sub-clause 
    (ii), (iii) and (iv) to be appointed after consultation with such 
    organisations, if any of the producers as may be recognised by the Central 
    Government in this behalf.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>   Such number of persons of whom one 
    shall be a woman to represent the Cine-Workers as are equal to the aggregate 
    of those provided in sub-clauses (ii), (iii) and (iv) to be appointed after 
    consultation with such organisations, if any, of the persons so employed as 
    may be recognised by the Central Government in this behalf.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>   Three persons of whom one shall be a 
    woman to represent the cine-workers to be appointed after consultation with 
    such organisations, if any, of the Cine-workers, as may be recognised by the 
    Central Government in this behalf.]  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> An officer 
    of the Central Government shall be appointed by that Government as Secretary 
    of the Central Advisory Committee and shall be entitled to attend and take 
    part in the meetings of the Committee but shall not be entitled to vote.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) Each 
    Advisory Committee constituted under section 5 shall consist of the 
    following persons to be appointed by the Central Government, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the chairman;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the commissioner or commissioners 
    having jurisdiction in the State or States for which Advisory Committee is 
    constituted, who shall be Vice-Chairman ex-officio.  
 
Provided that where more than one Commissioner 
    is appointed to the Committee, the Central Government may appoint any one of 
    them to be the Vice-Chairman;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   one representative of the Central 
    Government;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   one representative each of the 
    concerned State Government or States Governments as the case may be, ex-officio;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   such number of persons to represent the 
    producers as are equal to the aggregate of those provided in sub-clause 
    (ii), (iii) and (iv) to be appointed after consultation with the 
    organisations of the producers, if any, as may be recognised by the Central 
    Government, in this behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   such number of persons to represent the 
    cine-workers as are equal to the aggregate of those provided in sub-clause 
    (ii), (iii) and (iv) to be appointed after consultation with such 
    organisations if any of the persons so employed as may be recognised by the 
    Central Government in this behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   a woman, if no woman has been 
    appointed under sub-clause (v) or sub-clause (vi).  
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> An officer 
    of the Cine-Workers Welfare Organisation/Welfare Department concerned shall 
    be appointed as the Secretary of the Advisory Committee and the Secretary so 
    appointed shall be entitled to attend and take part in the meetings of the 
    Committee but shall not be entitled to vote.  
 
 
 
 






 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Term of 
    Office of Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
<subsection><number>a</number> A 
    member (other than an ex-officio) member) shall, unless he resigns 
    office or dies or otherwise vacates his office at an earlier date, hold 
    office for a period not exceeding three years as may be specified by the 
    Central Government in each case while making the appointment from the date 
    of publication in the Official Gazette of the notification appointing him as 
    member of the Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee as the 
    case may be, and shall be eligible for re-appointment:  
 
Provided that 
    an outgoing member shall continue in office until the appointment of his 
    successor is notified in the Official Gazette.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> An 
    ex-officio member shall hold office during the pleasure of the Central 
    Government.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A member 
    appointed to fill a casual vacancy shall hold office as long as the member 
    whose place he fills would have been entitled to hold office if the vacancy 
    had not occurred.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If a member 
    is unable to attend a meeting of the Central Advisory Committee or the 
    Advisory Committee, then, the case of a member appointed under sub-clause 
    (v) or sub-clause (vi) of clause (a) of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 or under 
    sub-clause (v) or sub-clause (vi) of clause (a) of sub-rule (2) of that 
    rule, the body which is represented by him in the Central Advisory Committee 
    or the Advisory Committee as the case may be, may notice in writing signed 
    on its behalf and by the said member addressed to the Chairman of the 
    Committee depute, and in other cases the Central Government may nominate a 
    substitute in his place to attend the meeting and such deputed or nominated 
    member shall have all the right of a member in respect of that meeting.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairman of 
    an Advisory Committee may resign his office by writing under his hand 
    addressed to the Central Government.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    non-official member (other than the Chairman) of an Advisory Committee may 
    resign his office by writing under his hand addressed to the Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    resignation shall take effect from the date of its acceptance or on the 
    expiry of thirty days from the date of its receipt by the Chairman or, as 
    the case may be, by the Central Government, whichever is earlier.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Absence 
    from India.—
<section><number>1</number> Before a 
    non-officio member leaves India, he shall intimate to the Chairman the date 
    of his departure from and the date of his expected return to India, and if 
    he intends to be absent from India for a period longer than six months, he 
    shall tender this resignation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any such 
    member leaves India without intimation as required under sub-rule (1) he 
    shall be deemed to have resigned with effect from the date of his departure 
    from India.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Absence 
    from India.—
<section><number>1</number> Before a 
    non-officio member leaves India, he shall intimate to the Chairman the date 
    of his departure from and the date of his expected return to India, and if 
    he intends to be absent from India for a period longer than six months, he 
    shall tender this resignation.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any such 
    member leaves India without intimation as required under sub-rule (1) he 
    shall be deemed to have resigned with effect from the date of his departure 
    from India.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>8</number> Allowances payable 
    to members.—A 
    non-official member including a non-official co-opted member or invitees 
    shall be entitled to receive travelling allowance and daily allowance as per 
    the orders issued by the Central Government from time to time in this 
    behalf.]
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Disposal 
    of business.—
<section><number>1</number> Every question 
    which an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee is required to 
    take into consideration shall be considered either at a meeting or, if the 
    Chairman so directs, by sending the necessary papers to every member for 
    opinion:  
 
Provided that 
    the papers are sent to the members by registered post with acknowledgment 
    due and with the request that the views of the members should reach the 
    office of the Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee, as the 
    case may be, within a period of fifteen days from the date of issue of the 
    papers. Provided further that the papers will not be sent to a member who is 
    absent from India.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When a 
    question is referred to the members for opinion by sending papers, any 
    member may request that the question be considered at a meeting and 
    thereupon the Chairman shall direct that it be so considered.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If a member 
    of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee, requests the 
    Chairman to refer any matter to the Committee, the Chairman shall refer that 
    matter to it accordingly.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Time, 
    place and date of meeting.—An 
    Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee shall meet at such 
    place and on such date and at such time as may be appointed by the Chairman.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Notice 
    of meetings and list of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notice shall be given to every member present in India of the time and place 
    fixed for each ordinary meeting at least fifteen days before such meeting 
    and every member shall be furnished with a list of business to be considered 
    at the meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) An 
    emergency meeting of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee 
    may be called by the Chairman thereof to discuss matters on which a decision 
    had to be taken immediately.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Notice 
    shall be given either by registered post or by telegram or in person to 
    every member present in India, of the place, time and date of an emergency 
    meeting at least four days before such meeting and every member shall be 
    furnished with a list of business to be considered at the meeting.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No business 
    which is not included in the list shall be considered at a meeting without 
    the permission of the Chairman.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Presiding at meeting.—The Chairman 
    shall preside at every meeting at which he is present and in his absence 
    Vice-Chairman shall preside.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Quorum.—No 
    business shall be transacted at a meeting (whether it be an ordinary or 
    emergency meeting) of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory 
    Committee unless at least one third of the total number of members of the 
    Advisory Committee of the Central Advisory Committee, as the case may be, 
    having the right to vote are present and at least one of the member so 
    present is the Chairman or the Vice-Chairman:  
 
Provided that 
    if at any meeting less than one third of the total number of members are 
    present the Chairman or in the absence of Chairman the Vice-Chairman may 
    adjourn the meeting to a date not less than seven days and no more than 
    thirty days from the date of the meeting.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Recommendation by majority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every question at a meeting of the Advisory Committee or the Central 
    Advisory Committee shall be decided by a majority of votes of the members 
    present and voting on that question, but the minority shall in all cases 
    have the right of requiring their dissent to be noted.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    question referred to the members for opinion shall, unless the Chairman in 
    pursuance of sub-rule (2) of rule 9 reserves it for consideration at a 
    meeting, be decided in accordance with the opinion of the majority of 
    members recording opinion within a period of fortnight.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the case 
    of an equal division of votes or opinion the Chairman shall have casting 
    vote whether the matter is considered at the meeting of the Central Advisory 
    Committee or the Advisory Committee or by sending the papers for the opinion 
    of members. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Minutes 
    of meetings.—The proceedings of 
    each meeting of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory Committee 
    shall be circulated to all members present in India, as soon as may be after 
    the meeting and shall be read out and confirmed at the next meeting of the 
    Committee, and shall be signed by the Chairman or as the case may be, the 
    Vice-Chairman presiding at such next meeting and shall thereafter be 
    recorded in a minute book which shall be kept for permanent record.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Headquarters of an Advisory Committee or the Central Advisory
    Committee Advisory.—The 
    headquarters of the Central Advisory Committee shall be in New Delhi and the 
    headquarters of an Advisory Committee shall be at such place or places as 
    may be fixed by the Central Government from time to time.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Executive of an Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commissioner shall be the Chief Executive of an Advisory Committee and 
    exercise the executive functions of the Committee on its behalf.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Secretary of an Advisory Committee shall carry out routine duties and shall 
    exercise such powers and discharge such duties as the Commissioner may, with 
    the approval of the Central Government delegate to him.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Staff 
    powers of the Commissioner.—The 
    Commissioner may authorise the staff of the advisory Committee to give 
    assistance to any member of an Advisory Committee or of a Sub-committee of 
    the Advisory Committee or to any other authority exercising executive or 
    advisory functions in connection with the Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>19</number> Scheme of 
    Expenditure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Welfare Commissioner shall have power, subject to the provisions in the 
    sanctioned budget, to incur expenditure on administrative staff and Welfare 
    Schemes, provided that, he shall have no power to sanction any scheme if it 
    involves expenditure exceeding Rs. 50,000 non-recurring and Rs. 5,000 
    recurring a year.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Welfare 
    Commissioner may sanction, without reference to the Advisory Committee 
    expenditure on contingencies, supplies and services and purchases of 
    articles required for the smooth and efficient running of the organisation 
    under him subject to financial provision in the sanctioned budget and to the 
    condition that the expenditure on any single object or service shall not 
    exceed Rs. 2,000 non-recurring and Rs. 400 recurring.]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Budget.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The annual budget as prepared by the Commissioner in consultation with the 
    Finance Sub-Committee shall be considered by the Advisory Committee 
    concerned each year and thereafter a copy of the Budget as approved by the 
    Advisory Committee, shall be forwarded not later than 1st day of October 
    each year for sanction to the Central Government which may make such 
    alternations therein as it consider necessary before its sanction.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The budget 
    to be forwarded to the Central Government shall be accompanied by detailed 
    self contained notes explaining new schemes included therein.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Other 
    matters to be considered by an Advisory Committee.—An 
    Advisory Committee shall consider the budget and any other matter that may 
    be laid before it by the Commission with the permission of the Chairman.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Committee to be informed of Expenditure.—A 
    memorandum setting forth any grant made or expenditure incurred since the 
    last meeting shall be laid at each meeting of an Advisory Committee.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Finance 
    Sub-Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> An Advisory 
    Committee shall elect from among its members two persons of whom one shall 
    be a person to represent producers and the other to represent the 
    cine-workers to constitute a Finance Sub-Committee of which the Commissioner 
    shall be a Chairman.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An Advisory 
    Committee may at any time co-opt a person or persons to the Finance 
    Sub-Committee and any person so co-opted shall exercise all the powers and 
    functions of a member of the Finance Sub-Committee but shall not be entitled 
    to vote and shall not solely by reason of being so co-opted be a member of 
    the Advisory Committee.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notice of 
    every meeting of the Finance Sub-Committee shall be sent to the Chairman of 
    the Advisory Committee shall who may attend such meeting if he so desires 
    and if he does so attend, he shall, notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub-rule (1), preside at the meeting and shall be entitled to vote.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Duties of the Finance Sub-Committee.—The 
    duties of the Finance Sub-Committee shall be to frame schemes of 
    expenditure, to advise on the budget drawn up by the executive of the 
    Advisory Committee and on the accounts of the Advisory Committee and also in 
    regard to all expenditure. 

    1[***].  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> Other 
    Sub-Committees.—An Advisory 
    Committee may as and when considered necessary constitute from its members 
    as many sub-committees as it may deem necessary for considering and 
    reporting on such matters as may be specifically assigned to it.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> Meeting 
    of the Sub-Committees.—The 
    meetings and proceedings of the Finance Sub-Committee and any other 
    sub-committees which may be constituted under rule 25 shall be governed by 
    the provisions herein contained for regulating the meeting and proceedings 
    of an Advisory Committee in so far as the same are applicable.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Grants.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government while making a grant to a State Government, a local 
    authority the producer in aid of any scheme approved by the Central 
    Government for the purposes of the Act, may impose conditions necessary for 
    ensuring—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   that the work for which the 
    grant made promptly executed and the money is actually utilised for the 
    purpose for which it is granted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   that the data on which the 
    grant is calculated are in accordance with facts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   that any particulars which the 
    Central Government may from time to time require for the proper discharge of 
    its responsibilities are promptly supplied;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   that all necessary facilities 
    for inspection are accorded to persons duly authorised by the Central 
    Government for the purpose of satisfying itself that the provisions of 
    clause (a) are complied with or for checking the correctness of any 
    particulars supplied under clause (c) or for the collection of any such 
    particulars;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   that proper accounts of the 
    money granted are kept and are submitted for audit by such persons as the 
    Central Government may authorise in this behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   that an additional statement 
    of accounts together with a certificate of a registered Accountant or other 
    recognised body of auditors to the effect that the accounts are correct, is 
    furnished by the grantees: and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   that the labour employed on 
    regular basis and those employed on contract basis are given similar welfare 
    facilities.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Before 
    making a grant to a State Government, a local authority, or the producer, 
    the Central Government shall require such State Government, local authority 
    or producer to execute a bond for the fulfilment of the conditions imposed 
    by the Central Government under sub-rule (I).  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be 
    the condition of every bond executed under sub-rule (2) that in the event of 
    the State Government, local authority or producer violating any condition 
    imposed under sub-rule (1) such State Government local authority or producer 
    shall be liable to refund the entire grant alongwith simple interest at the 
    rate of twelve per cent per annum and, where the amount of the grant and 
    interest is huge, refund may be allowed in two or three instalments.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> Standard 
    of Dispensary or Hospital Services.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The standard of dispensary service to be provided by producers for the 
    purpose of getting the grant-in-aid envisaged in clause (c) of sub-section 
    (1) of section 4 of the Act shall be as specified in Schedule II hereinafter 
    in this rule and in rules 29 and 30 referred to as the prescribed standard.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall 
    be maintained an independent dispensary or hospital at each studio according 
    to the prescribed standard:  
 
Provided that a 
    common main dispensary may be maintained for several studios with branch 
    dispensaries attached to each studio subject to the following conditions, 
    namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the common main dispensary 
    shall maintain the standards prescribed for the aggregate number of 
    cine-workers of all studios served by it.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   every branch dispensary shall 
    have a qualified doctor and a qualified pharmacist (compounder).   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the common main dispensary 
    shall be so situated that none of the studios served by it is more than 
    fifteen kilometres away from it; and   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   The common main dispensary 
    shall maintain an ambulance van for taking serious cases of injury and 
    sickness from the branch dispensaries to the common main dispensary.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that any dispensary or hospital is 
    being efficiently run and served the purpose for which it is established, 
    waive any of the requirements specified in the prescribed standard;  
 
Provided that 
    no such dispensary or hospital shall contain any room other than a store 
    room which is less than four metres by three metres in area;  
 
Provided 
    further that a registered medical practitioner may be appointed to be 
    incharge of dispensary catering to more than 250 workers, only if he has ten 
    years, experience as medical officer in independent charge of a dispensary.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Inspection.—The dispensary 
    services maintained by producers shall be inspected at intervals not 
    exceeding one year by such medical or other officer as may be authorised by 
    the Commissioner for the purpose or by the Commissioner himself whenever he 
    considers it necessary and the inspecting officer or the Commissioner as the 
    case may be, shall, if the dispensary conforms to the prescribed standard 
    issue a certificate in Form A which shall be valid for a period of one year 
    from the date of issue.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Submission of periodic returns.—Every 
    producer who maintains a dispensary service according to the prescribed 
    standard shall submit to the Commissioner.—  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   in January and July of each 
    year, a statement showing the total number of persons employed by him in the 
    production of films during the preceding year and;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   in January of each year, a 
    certified statement of expenditure incurred on the dispensary, during the 
    preceding twelve months.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>31</number> Standard 
    of maternity centre.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    standard of maternity centre to be provided by producers for the purpose of 
    getting the grants-in-aid envisaged in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of 
    section 4 of the Act shall be as specified in Schedule III, hereinafter in 
    this rule and in rules 32, 33 and 34 referred to as the prescribed standard.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall 
    be maintained an independent maternity centre at each studio according to 
    the prescribed standard:  
 
Provided that a 
    common main maternity centre may be maintained for several studios with 
    branch maternity centre attached to each studio subject to the following 
    conditions, namely.:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the common main maternity 
    centres shall maintain prescribed standard for the aggregate number of 
    workers of all the studios served by it;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   every branch maternity centre 
    shall have a qualified doctor and a qualified compounder;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the common main maternity 
    centre shall be situated that none of the studios served by it are more than 
    fifteen kilometres away from it; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the common maternity centre 
    shall maintain an ambulance van for taking serious cases from the branch 
    maternity centres to the common maternity centre.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that a maternity centre is being 
    efficiently run and serves the purpose for which it is established, waive 
    any of the requirements specified in the prescribed standard:  
 
Provided that 
    the functions of a lady health visitor may be performed by a fully qualified 
    and registered mid-wife who has not less than ten years, experience as a 
    mid-wife.  
 
Provided 
    further that a lady medical licentiate may be appointed to be incharge of 
    maternity centre catering to more than 1,000 cine-workers if she has ten 
    years’ experience as a medical officer in independent charge of a maternity 
    centre.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Inspection.—The maternity centre 
    maintained by producers shall be inspected at intervals not exceeding one 
    year by such medical or other officer as may be authorised by the 
    Commissioner for the purpose or by the Commissioner himself whenever he 
    considers it necessary and the inspecting officers or the Commissioner, as 
    the case may be, shall, if the centre conforms to the prescribed standard, 
    issue a certificate in Form B which shall be valid for a period of one year 
    from the date of issue.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Submission of periodic returns.—Every 
    producer who maintains maternity centre according to the prescribed standard 
    shall submit to the Commissioner in January of each year a certified 
    statement of the expenditure incurred on the maternity centre during the 
    preceding twelve months.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>34</number> Extent 
    of grant-in-aid.—Every producer 
    who maintains a dispensary or a maternity centre for the benefit of 
    cine-workers which conforms to the prescribed standard under rule 28 or 31 
    as the case may be, and is subject to inspection under rule 29 or 32, as the 
    case may be if he desires, to carry on improvement on the facilities 
    existing be eligible for such grant-in-aid in respect of non-recurring 
    expenditure on such improvement as the Commissioner may decide with the 
    approval of the Central Advisory Committee, subject to the condition that it 
    shall not exceed 50% of the said expenditure or Rs. 10,000 whichever is 
    less. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>35</number> Standard 
    of facilities for education and recreation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The standard of facilities for eduction and recreation of cine-workers to be 
    provided by producers for the purpose of getting grant-in-aid as envisaged 
    in clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Act shall be as 
    specified in Schedule IV hereinafter in this rule and in rules 36, 37 and 38 
    referred to as the prescribed standard.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> There shall 
    be maintained an independent welfare centre at each studio according to the 
    prescribed standard.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the centre is being efficiently 
    maintained and serves the purpose for which it is established, waive any of 
    the requirements specified in the prescribed standard.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Inspection.—The welfare centre 
    maintained by producers shall be inspected at intervals not exceeding one 
    year by such officer as may be authorised by the Commissioner for the 
    purpose or by the Commissioner himself whenever he considers it necessary 
    and the inspecting officer or the Commissioner, as the case may be, shall, 
    if the centre conforms to the prescribed standards, issue a certificate in 
    Form C which shall be valid for a period of one year from the date of issue. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Submission of periodic returns.—Every 
    producer who maintains a welfare centre according to the prescribed standard 
    shall submit to the Commissioner,  
 <section>
<number>i</number>   immediately on the 
    establishment of the welfare centre, adequate proof to the satisfaction of 
    the Commissioner showing the capital expenditure incurred on the 
    construction and equipment of the welfare centre;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   in January, each year a 
    certified statement of the expenditure incurred on the welfare during the 
    preceding twelve months;  
 
Provided that 
    the statement shall not include expenditure if any incurred on repairs and 
    replacements.   

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>38</number> Extent 
    of grant-in-aid.—Every producer 
    who maintains a welfare centre for the benefit of the cine-workers employed 
    in his establishment which conforms to the prescribed standard under rule 35 
    and is subject to inspection under rule 36 be eligible to a grant-in-aid in 
    respect of non-recurring expenditure which shall not exceed 50% of the 
    amount spent by the owner of the establishment in the construction and 
    equipment of the welfare centre subject to the maximum of Rs. 5,000. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>39</number> Assistance in the 
    form of grant to indigent Cine-Workers.—The 
    Welfare Commissioner may sanction the payment of grant, to a cine-worker who 
    becomes totally disabled due to accident while on duty or to a member of his 
    family or to a dependent in case the cine-worker dies or becomes totally 
    disabled due to accident while on duty, subject to a maximum of Rs. 5,000.]  
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>40</number>—
<section><number>1</number> The Commissioner, with the approval of the 
      Central Advisory Committee may sanction the payment of a loan to any 
      cine-worker subject to a maximum of Rs. 5,000 for one or more the 
      following purposes, namely:—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>   to pay expenses in 
      connection with the illness or confinement of the cine-worker and members 
      of his family or any person actually dependent on him;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   to meet the cost 
      of higher education of the cine-worker and members of his family or any 
      actually dependent on him;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   to pay obligatory 
      expenses on a scale appropriate to the cine-workers status which by 
      customary usage the cine-worker has to incur in connection with the 
      betrothal or marriages, funerals or other ceremonies;  
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   building or 
      acquiring a suitable house for his residence including the cost of site.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In the event of sanction of a loan the 
      cine-worker has to execute a bond in Form E before receiving payment and 
      shall be liable to pay simple interest at the rate of 9.5% per annum. The 
      entire loan including interest thereon, should be repaid within a period 
      of five years from the date in which the loan is sanctioned.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Statistics and other information.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every producer shall maintain such registers as the Central Government may 
    specify and shall also furnish such statistics and other information as that 
    Government or any person so authorised may, by written order, require for 
    the purposes of the Act, in Form D and within such time (being not less than 
    thirty days from the date on which the order is served on the person 
    concerned), and in such manner, as may be specified in the order.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The 
    Commissioner may require the executive authority of any local body such as 
    Municipality, District Board, Panchayat Boards, Block Development Units in 
    any State or Union Territory to prepare a register of cine-worker residing 
    within the jurisdiction of that authority.  
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The 
    registers referred to in clause (a) shall contain the following particulars 
    relating to the cine-worker in the area under the jurisdiction of the local 
    authority:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>1</number> Name  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>2</number> Age  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>3</number> Sex  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>4</number> Address  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>5</number> Place of 
    work  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>6</number> Distance of 
    place of work, from their residence.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>7</number> Name of 
    person or establishment by whom employed.  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>8</number> Name of the 
    Trade work holder.  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Officers 
    deputed by the Commissioner shall be accorded all necessary facilities by 
    the owners and local authorities to collect statistics or other information 
    from the register referred to in clause (a) for the purposes of the Act.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    producer who, without reasonable excuse fails to furnish the statistics or 
    other information required under sub-rule (1) or furnishes statistics or 
    other information containing a statement, entry or detail which is not to 
    the best of his knowledge or belief true or any executive authority 
    enumerated under sub-rule (2) who without reasonable excuse, fails to 
    prepare a register as required under the sub-rule shall be punishable with 
    fine which may extend to Rs. 2,000.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    1[<number>42</number> Identity Card.—Every 
    producer shall issue to every Cine-Worker an identity card as prescribed in 
    Form F, on which a photograph of the Cine-Worker would also be affixed. In 
    case the bona fides of a Cine-Worker is challenged, the competent 
    authority defined in clause (d) of section 2 of the Cine-Workers and Cinema 
    Theatre Workers (Regulation of Employment) Act, 1981 (50 of 1981), shall 
    enquire into the matter and decide the same.]
 
 






 



</article><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 1984
 



 



Schedule V
 



FORM A
 


(see rule 29)
 


CERTIFICATE OF INSPECTION
 


Inspection report 
    of............................................... Dispensary 
    at.................by the.....................................for the 
    year............................ending...............................20.......
 


1.   Name of establishment (including 
    factory)/contractor, engaged in the production of films, served by dispensary.  
 


2.   Number of workers for which it caters.  
 


3.   Date and hour of inspection.  
 


4.   Date of last inspection.  
 


5.   Dispensary buildings.  
 


(a)   Condition of dispensary building  
 


(b)   Does the accommodation 
    provided conform to the prescribed standard  
 


6.   Medicines—  
 


(a) Is the supply sufficient and 
    according to the prescribed scale?  
 


(b) Are the poisons labelled and 
    kept separately under lock and key?  
 


7.   Surgical instruments and 
    equipment—  
 


      Are they sufficient and in good order?  
 


8.   Staff acquittance rolls— Are they 
    in order and up-to-date?  
 


9.   Registers and returns—Are these 
    properly kept and regularly submitted?  
 


10.   Establishment—  
 


(a)   Officer-in-charge—  
 


(i)      Part-time/whole 
    time  
 


(ii)     Name and qualifications  
 


(b)   Designation and pay of 
    staff—  
 


(i)      Medical graduate  
 


(ii)     Medical licentiate  
 


(iii)    Lady Doctor  
 


(iv)    Nurse  
 


(v)     Compounder   
 


(vi)    Auxiliary Nurse Midwife  
 


(vii)   Male Dresser  
 


(viii) Female Dresser  
 


(ix)    Sweeper  
 


(x)      Chowkidar  
 


(xi)    Peon  
 


(c)  Attendance register—  
 


              Do the staff attend regularly?  
 


11.   Annual expenditure on—  
 


(a)   Establishment  
 


(b)   Medicines  
 


12.   Out-patients—  
 


(a)   Number seen at the time of visit  
 


(b)   Total number of new 
    patients treated in current year up-to-date.  
 


(c)    Total number of old 
    patients treated in current year up-to-date.  
 


(d)   Total treated during the 
    last year.  
 


(e)   Do the entries on tickets 
    of  patients present tally with the entries on the registers?
 


(f)    Are there any arrangements 
    for treating women apart from men?  
 


13.   Are you satisfied with the working 
    of the dispensary?  
 


       If not, what suggestions can be 
    made for its improvement?  
 


I certify that I have inspected the dispensary 
    noted above and that it conforms/ does not conform in the following 
    respects* to the standards laid down in the Cine-workers Welfare Fund Rules, 
    1984.  
 



 


Signature of Inspecting Officer          
 


Date..........................................
 


Counter-signature of Commissioner    
 


Date..........................................
 


       *   Give details below
 


—————
 


           Note.—The counter-signature 
    of the Commissioner is not necessary when the Commissioner himself is the 
    inspecting authority.
 



 




  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 1984
 



 



FORM B
 


 (See rule 32)
 


CERTIFICATE OF INSPECTION
 



 


Inspection report of the Maternity Centre 
    at............................................by the . 
    ..........................................for the 
    year...............................ending...................20....  
 


1.   Name of establishment (including 
    factory contractor) engaged in the production of films served by the 
    Maternity Centre.  
 


2.   Number of workers for which it caters.  
 


3.   Date and hour of inspection.  
 


4.   Date of last inspection.  
 


5.   Maternity Centre Buildings—  
 


(a)   Condition of Maternity 
    Centre Buildings.  
 


(b)   Does the accommodation 
    provided conform to the prescribed standard?  
 


6.   Medicines—  
 


(a)   Is the supply sufficient 
    and according to the prescribed scale?  
 


(b)   Are the poisons labelled 
    and kept separately under lock and key?  
 


7.   Surgical instruments and 
    equipments—  
 


Are they sufficient and in good order?  
 


8.   Staff acquittance rolls—Are they 
    in order and up-to-date.  
 


9.   Registers and returns—Are these 
    properly kept and regularly submitted?  
 


10.   Establishments—  
 


(a)   Officer-in-charge—  
 


(i)      Part-time/whole-time  
 


(ii)     Name and qualifications  
 


(b)   Designation and pay of 
    staff—  
 


(i)      Medical graduate  
 


(ii)     Medical licentiate  
 


(iii)    Lady Doctor  
 


(iv)    Compounder  
 


(v)     Nurse   
 


(vi)    Midwife  
 


(vii)   Ayah  
 


(viii) Sweeper  
 


(ix)    Ward attendant  
 


(x)      Cook  
 


(c)    Attendance register—Do the 
    staff attend regularly?  
 


11.   Annual expenditure on—  
 


(a)   Establishment  
 


(b)   Medicines  
 


12.   Out-patients—  
 


(a)   Number seen at the time of visit  
 


(b)   Total number of new 
    patients treated in current year up-to-date.  
 


(c)    Total number of old 
    patients treated in current year up-to-date.  
 


(d) Total treated during the last year.  
 


(e) Do the entries on tickets of 
    patients present tally with the entries on the register?  
 


13.   Are you satisfied with the working 
    of the Maternity Centre? If not, what suggestion can you make for its improvement?  
 


I certify that I have inspected the Maternity 
    Centre noted above and that conforms/does not conform in the following 
    respects* to the standards laid down in the Cine-Workers Welfare Fund Rules, 
    1984.  
 



                                                                                       
    Signature of the Inspecting Officer
 



                                                                                       
    Date.................................................
 



                                                                                       
    Counter-signature of Commissioner 
 



                                                                                       
    with date.
 


       *   Give details below
 


—————
 


           Note.—The counter-signature 
    of the Commissioner is not necessary when the Commissioner himself is the 
    inspecting authority.
 



 




  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 1984
 



 



FORM C
 


(See rule 36)
 


CERTIFICATE OF INSPECTION OF THE WELFARE
 


Inspection report of the Welfare Centre 
    at...................................by the  
    ........................................... for the 
    year ........................................ ending .......................... 20......
 


1.   Name of establishment (including 
    factory) contractor engaged in the production of films served by the Centre.
 


2.   Number of workers for which it caters.  
 


3.   Date and hour of inspection.  
 


4.   Date of last inspection.  
 


5.   Centre Building:—  
 


(a) Condition of the building.  
 


(b) Does the accommodation 
    provided conform to the prescribed standard?  
 


6.   Equipment  
 


(a) Are the equipments provided 
    according to the prescribed standard?  
 


(b) Is timely 
    repairs/replacements done where necessary?  
 


(c) Are the equipments all in 
    serviceable condition?  
 


7.   Establishments—  
 


(a)  Officer-in-charge  
 


(i)      Part-time/whole 
    time  
 


(ii)     Name and qualifications  
 


(b)   Designation and pay of staff  
 


(i)      Adult Education 
    Instructor.  
 


(ii)     Sevika  
 


(iii)    Sweeper.  
 


(c)   Attendance register—Do the 
    staff attend regularly?  
 


8.   Annual expenditure  
 


(a)   Establishment  
 


(b)   Repairs and replacement of equipments  
 


9.   Activities—  
 


(a)   Total number of rolls 
    attending the centre.  
 


(b)   Number seen at the time of inspection.  
 


(c)    Number of adults attending 
    literacy classes.  
 


(d)   Number of women attending 
    craft classes.  
 


(e)   Number of adults 
    participating in games and sports.  
 


10.   Are you satisfied with the working 
    of the Centre?  
 


If not, what suggestions can be made for its 
    improvement?  
 


I certify that I have inspected the Welfare 
    Centre noted above and that conforms/it does not conform in the following 
    respects* to the standards laid down in the Cine-Workers Welfare Fund Rules, 
    1984.  
 



    Signature of Inspecting Officer        
 



    Date.........................................
 



    Counter-signature of Commiss-ioner with date.
 



 


       *   Give details below
 



 


      Note.—The counter-signature 
    of the Commissioner is not necessary when the Commissioner himself is the 
    inspecting authority.
 



 




  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 1984
 



 



FORM D
 


(See rule 41)
 


STATISTICS AND OTHER INFORMATION
 



 


1. Name of factory/establishment or contractor 
    engaged in the production of films.
 


2. Location and full postal address of 
    factory/establishment/contractor.
 


3. Name of the employers of the 
    factory/establishment/contractor.
 


4. Number of films produced during the 
    period................................ to..............................
 


5. Number of persons employed by the 
    employers/contractors in factories /establishments during the period 
    from......................................... 
    to................................
 
 


Factories/
 


establishments
 
 


Male 
 


Female
 


Children
 


Total
 
 


6. Details of welfare facilities provided by 
    the employers of the factory/establishment or contractor to persons employed 
    by him.
 


(a) Housing  
 


(b) Medical  
 


(c) Water Supply  
 


(d) Recreation  
 


(e) Any other activities.  
 


7. Quantum of cess paid by the employer of the 
    factory establishment or contractor under the Cine-worker Welfare Fund 
    Rules, 1984 during the period from..................... 20............to 
    ......................... 20.........  
 


8. Any other information considered necessary 
    regarding employment wages, welfare facilities allowed to the workers.  
 


Certified that the above particulars are true 
    to the best of my knowledge and belief and are based on the records 
    maintained in my establishment/factory.  
 



 


No.
 


Date and place      
 


Employer 
 




  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 1984
 



 



FORM E
 


(See rule 40)
 


SURETY BOND
 



 


KNOW ALL MEN BY THESE PRESENT THAT 
    I..................son of Shri.................. 
    .......................................a resident 
    of ............................................... in the District 
    of............................................................... at present 
    employed as a ............................. in 
    the ........................................ (hereinafter called “the Surety” 
    am held and firmly bond upto the President of India (hereinafter called “the 
    Government” which expression shall include his successors and assigns) in 
    the sum of Rs ..................................  (rupees................................... only) to be paid to the Government 
    for which payment to be well and truly made. I hereby bind myself my heirs, 
    executors, administrators and representatives firmly by these presents. As 
    witness my hand this day of .............................. one thousand nine 
    hundred and.................................................................
 


WHEREAS................................... son 
    of Shri ............................................ a resident 
    of .................................................. in the District 
    of ............................... at present employed 
    as ............................    in 
    the ............................................... (hereinafter called “the 
    borrower”)  has; at his own request has been granted by the Government an 
    advance of Rs ........................................ (Rupees only) 
    for...........................................
 


AND WHEREAS the borrower has undertaken to 
    repay the said amount in .................................  equal monthly instalments and WHEREAS in consideration of Government has agreed to execute 
    the above bond with such condition as hereunder written.  
 


NOW THE CONDITION OF THIS OBLIGATION is such 
    that if the said borrower shall, while employed in the 
    said ........................................... duly and regularly pay or 
    cause to be paid to the Government the amount of the aforesaid advance owing 
    to the Government by instalments until the said sum of Rs ............................... 
    (rupees ................................... only) shall be duly paid then this 
    bond shall be void, otherwise the same shall be and remain in full force and 
    virtue. BUT SO NEVERTHELESS that if the borrower shall die or become 
    insolvent or at any time cease to be a cine-worker the whole or so much of 
    the said principle sum of Rs......................... 
    .......................................... (rupees..............................only) 
    as shall then remain unpaid shall immediately become due and payable to the 
    Government and be recoverable from the surety in one instalment by virtue of 
    this bond.  
 


This obligation undertaken by the surety shall 
    not be discharged or in any way affected by an extention of time or any 
    indulgence granted by the Government to the said borrower.  
 


The Government have agreed to bear the stamp 
    duty if any, for this document.  
 



 


Signed and delivered by the             
     
    
 



    said........................................            
 


at 
    this.....................................            
 


Signature of the surety                                              
 



    Name....................................................................
 



    Designation............................................................
 



        Office  to 
    which attached                                           
 



              In the 
    presence of:                                                   
 



                                                                    
    1.........................................................................
 



                                                                    
    2.........................................................................
 




  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 1984
 



 




1[FORM 
    F
 


(see rule 42)
 


IDENTITY CARD
 
 


Serial 
    No.                                                                  Photo 
    of the Worker
 
 


1.  Name and address of the present employer 
    (name          

       
    of the Producer of Film may be mentioned).
 


2. Name of the worker:
 


3. Father/Husband’s name:
 


4. Number and Names of Feature films in which  
                    

    he/she has worked/is working within the wage             

    ceiling  prescribed in Section 2(b)  of the           

    Cine-Workers Welfare Fund Act, 1981.
 


5. 
    Address                                          Residence:
 



                                                            Place of work:
 


6. Age (Date of birth);
 


7. Particulars of Dependents:
 
 
 
 Sl. No.
 Name 

 Age
 
        Relationship

 
  

 
 
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 


4.

  
  
  

 
  


 


8. Signature of worker :  
 


9. Date of issue:  
 



 


Signature of employer/competent authority]

  


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




The Cine-Workers Welfare Fund
    Rules, 1984
 



 


SCHEDULE I
 


TRAVELLING AND DAILY ALLOWANCES
 


[See rule 81]
 



 



A. 
    Non-officials other than Members of
    Parliament  

    and State Legislatures.
 


(a)  
    Travelling allowance:
 


1. Journey by rail.—Normally,  a member 
    should travel by first class by rail and in respect of such journeys, he 
    shall be entitled to first class rail-fare.  
 


Provided that the Central Government may allow 
    a member to travel by air conditioned coach, where this concession is, in 
    the opinion of the Central Government, justified by fulfilment of one or 
    more of the following conditions, namely:—  
 


(a)  the member concerned is required to 
    travel in air conditioned accommodiation on grounds  of health or because of 
    very advanced age or infirmity.  
 


(b)  the member is or immediately before he 
    retired from employment was entitled to travel in air conditioned coach 
    under the rules of the organisation to which he belongs or might have 
    belonged immediately before retirement.  
 


(c)  the Central Government is satisfied that 
    travel by air-conditioned is the customary mode of travel by non-official 
    member concerned in respect of journeys connected with the performances of 
    Government duty.  
 


2. Journey by road.—(i) In respect of 
    journeys by road between places not connected by rail, a member shall be 
    entitled to road mileage at 60 paise per kilometre for travel in own car or 
    full taxi or 20 paise per kilometre for travel on motor cycle or scooter.  
 


(ii) Where journey between two places by rail 
    is performed by road, he shall be entitled to the prescribed road mileage 
    limited to first class fare by rail.  
 


Provided that, where in an individual case the 
    Central Government is satisfied that the journey by road was performed in 
    public interest, full road mileage allowance may be allowed without 
    restricting it to rail fair.  
 


3. Journey by sea or by river steamer.—In 
    respect of journeys by sea or by river steamer, a member shall be entitled 
    to one fare at the lowest rate (exclusive of diet) of the highest  class of 
    accommodation.  
 


4. Journey by air.—(a) Air travel shall 
    not be permitted as a matter  of course and each case will be examined on 
    merits by the Central Government and permission for air-travel granted only 
    if it can be certified that air-travel is urgent and necessary in public 
    interest. Travel shall be by economy class in such a case.  
 



    (b)   Daily allowance:  
 


Daily allowance for the entire absence from 
    headquarters will be regulated as follows:—  
 


(1) Full daily allowance may be granted for 
    each completed calender day of absence from headquarters reckoned from mid-night.  
 


(2) For absence from the headquarters for less 
    than twenty-four hours, the daily allowance  will be admissible at the 
    following rates:—  
 


(i)  if the absence from the headquarters does 
    not exceed six hours, 30% of the full daily allowance;  
 


(ii)  if the absence from the headquarters 
    exceeds six hours but not exceed twleve hours, 50% of the full daily 
    allowance;  
 


(iii)  if the absence from the headquarters 
    exceeds, twelve hours, full daily allowance shall be paid.  
 


(3) In case  the period of absence from 
    headquarters fall on two calendar days, it is reckoned as two days and daily 
    allowance shall be calculated for each as above and daily allowance for days 
    of departure from and arrival at headquarters will also be regulated in the 
    manner specified above.  
 


(4) The rates of daily allowance will be as 
    follows:  
 


(A) When the member avails of Government or 
    public sector guest house facilties or makes his own arrangement.
 

 
 



 
 
 
 



1
 
 



2
 
 



3

 
 
 



Ordinary 
          localities
 
 




          Cities of Delhi, Shimla and  

          Madras, the whole of the Union Territory of Lakshadweep and the whole 
          of Jammu and Kashmir.
 
 




          Bombay, Calcutta, Darjeeling District (except Siliguri Subdivision) 
          and Darjeeling  town/NEFA area beyond. Inner Line/Naga Hills Tuensange 
          area beyond Inner Line,  Spiti and Lahaul area of Punjab/Chini Tahsil 
          Parganas of Dassan and Antharabis and Pandarabis of Rampur Tehsil 
          Dodra Kawar of Rohru Tehsil in the District of Mahasu, Pangi sub-tehsil 
          of Chamba District.

 
 
 



Rs. 21.00
 
 



Rs. 
          23.50
 
 



Rs. 
          28.00




 


 
 



    (B) When the member stays in hotel or other establishments providing board 
    or lodging or both at scheduled tariffs  
 



 
 
 
 


(1)
 
 


(2)

 
 
 



Cities of Delhi, 
          Shimla, and Madras, the whole  of the Union Territories of Lakshadweep  
          and the whole of Jammu and Kashmir.
 
 



Bombay, Calcutta, 
          Darjeeling District (except siliguri sub-division) and Darjeeling town 
          NEFA areas, beyond the Inner Line/Spiti and Lahaul area of Punjab/Chini 
          Tehsil Parganas of Dassan/Antharabis and Pandarabis of Rampur/Dodra 
          Kanwar of Rohru Tehsil in the District  of Mahasu, Pangi sub-Tehsil of 
          Chamba District.

 
 
 



Rs. 40.00
 
 



Rs. 50.00




 


 
 


 (5) Whenever the claim for daily allowance is 
    preferred with reference to the rates at (B) above, it shall be accompanied 
    by a certificate in the following terms and the vouchers in support of the 
    stay in the hotel or establishment be annexed to Travelling allowance claim.  
 


CERTIFICATE
 


“Certified that I stayed 
    from..................to................at..........................................
 


                                         
    (Date)           (Date)      
    (Name of Hostel/Establishment)
 



    at............................................which provided board/lodging 
    at  Scheduled Tariffs”. 

         (Name of Place)
 


If he is provided with free board and lodging 
    he shall draw only 1/4th of the daily allowance for the day or days. If he 
    is provided with only free boarding, he will draw 1/2 daily allowance for 
    that (these) day(s). If he is provided with only free lodging he shall draw 
    3/4 daily allowance for that (those) day(s).  
 


(6) For the time spent on journey, only 
    ordinary rate of allowance as in the Table at (A) above shall be admissible.  
 


(7) When the total absence from headquarters 
    is partly spent in journeys in ordinary locality and partly in expensive 
    locality, the total number of daily allowances, above will first be 
    calculated. From this the number of daily allowance for being in expensive 
    locality, for which daily allowance from at special rate will be allowed, 
    will be deducted. The remaining number of daily allowance will then be 
    calculated at ordinary rates prescribed in column I of the Table at (A) 
    above.  
 


The allowances under this rule shall be 
    admissible only on production of a certificate by the members concerned to 
    the effect that they have not claimed or drawn travelling or daily 
    allowances in respect of the journeys and halts from any other source.  
 



 



B. MEMBERS OF PARLIAMENT
 


(a)  
    Travelling Allowance  
 


(1) In respect of journeys performed by rail, 
    road, air and steamer, a member of Parliament will be entitled to travelling 
    allowance on the same scale as is admissible to him under section 4 of the 
    Salaries and Allowance of members of Parliament Act 1954 (30 of 1954).  
 


(2) A member of Parliament will ordinarily 
    travel by  rail utilising the free first class rail pass issued to him. He 
    may also travel by air at his discretion. Air travel should not, however, be 
    resorted to as  a matter of course and in exercising his discretion, the 
    member should take into account factors like urgency or work, distance to be 
    travelled, time at his disposal, etc., and where two classes of 
    accommodation, i.e. first and economy (tourist) class accommodation 
    are available on the air-lines, a Member of Parliament may travel by first 
    class.  
 


(b) 
    Daily allowance  
 


(1) He shall be entitled for each day of the 
    meeting, daily allowance at the rate of  Rs. 51/  
 


(2) In addition to the daily allowance for the 
    day(s) of the meeting a member shall also be entitled to full daily 
    allowance for the day preceding and/or the day following the meeting if—  
 


(i)  he arrives in the forenoon of 
    the day preceding the day of the meeting of an earlier day, or   
 


(ii)  he departs at 12 noon or in 
    the afternoon of the day following the day of the meeting or on a later day.  
 


Provided that he will be entitled to only half 
    daily allowance for the day preceding or for the day following the meeting 
    if:—  
 


(i)  he arrives at 12 noon or in 
    the afternoon of the day of the meeting, and/or  
 


(ii)  he departs in the forenoon of 
    the day following the day of the meeting.  
 



 


C. MEMBERS OF THE STATE LEGISLATURES  
 


The travelling allowance and daily allowance 
    payable to members of the State Legislatures shall be the same as admissible 
    to them under the rules regulating the  travelling allowance and daily 
    allowance payable for attending the meetings of the State Legislature or any 
    committees thereof.  
 


NOTE: The travelling and daily 
    allowance shall be admissible only on production of a certificate by the 
    members concerned to the effect that they have not claimed or drawn 
    travelling or daily allowance in respect of the journey and halts from any 
    other source.  
 



 




 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



    THE CINE-WORKERS WELFARE FUND RULES, 1984
 



 



SCHEDULE II
 


STANDARD OF DISPENSARY SERVICES
 


(See rule 28)
 



 


I. BUILDING
 


1. Dispensary catering for 1,000 workers or 
    less—Three rooms to be used as follows:—
 


(i)  consulting rooms (5 metres x  
    4 metres)
 


(ii)  dressing room (5 metres x 4 
    metres)
 


(iii)  dispensary and store room (5 metres x 4 metres) covered waiting accommodation—15 square metres, two 
    latrines (flush type) each 2 metres x 3 metres.
 


2. Dispensary catering for 1,001 to 2,000 
    workers—Six rooms to be used as follows:— 
 


(i)  consulting room for males (5 
    metres x 4 metres)   
 


(ii)  consulting room for females 
    (5 metres x 4 metres)  
 


(iii)  minor operation room  (5 metres x 4 metres)  
 


(iv)  dispensary room (5 metres x 4 
    metres)  
 


(v)  laboratory room (15 to 18 
    square metres)  
 


(vi)  store room (5 metres x 4 
    metres)   
 


Covered waiting 
    accommodation 20 square metres, two latrines (flush type) each (2 metres x 3 
    metres)  
 


3. Dispensary catering for 2,001 workers or 
    more—Nine rooms to be used as follows:—  
 


(i)  consulting room for males (5 
    metres x 4 metres)  
 


(ii)  consulting room for females 
    (5 metres x 4 metres)  
 


(iii)  minor operation room (5 metres x 4 metres)  
 


(iv) dispensary room (5 metres x 4 
    metres)  
 


(v)  laboratory room (15 to 18 
    square metres)  
 


(vi)  dressing room (3 metres x 3 
    metres)  
 


(vii)  dark room (3 metres x 3 
    metres)  
 


(viii)   store room (5 metres x 4 
    metres)  
 


(ix)  registration and record office 
    room (16 square metres) covered waiting  accommodation—25 square metres, 
    three latrines (flush type) each (2 metres x 3 metres)  
 


Each dispensary shall provide emergency beds 
    for treatment of simple and emergency cases at the rate of one bed for every 
    250 workers subject to a minimum of two beds, one for males and one for 
    females. For this purpose separate rooms shall be provided for males and 
    females. The rooms shall have air space of 18 cubic metres per bed and door 
    and window space not less than one-third of the floor space with varandah 
    2.5 metres wide along the front of the room.  
 


Producers employing cine-workers  who have no 
    provision for emergency beds on the lines mentioned above at their 
    dispensaries at the commencement of the Cine-workers Welfare Fund Rules, 
    1984 may within a period of three years from such commencement provide for 
    such beds. Those producers, who fail to provide emergency  beds within such 
    period shall not be entitled to any subsidy thereafter even if they may be 
    otherwise qualified for it.  
 


II. STAFF
 


1. Dispensary catering for 250 workers or 
    less:—
 


Registered Medical 
    Practitioner                      1(whole-time)
 


Auxiliary Nurse 
    Midwife                                 1(whole-time)
 


Compounder-cum-dresser                             1(whole-time)
 



    Sweeper                                                    1(whole-time)
 


2. Dispensary catering for 250 to 500 
    workers:—
 


Registered Medical 
    Practitioner                      1(whole-time)
 


Auxiliary Nurse 
    Midwife                                 1(whole-time)
 


Compounder-cum-dresser                             1(whole-time)
 



    Sweeper                                                    1(whole-time)
 


3. Dispensary catering  for 501 to 1,000 
    workers:—
 


Registered Medical 
    Practitioner                       1   
    (whole time)
 


Auxiliary Nurse 
    Midwife                                  1   
    (whole time)
 


Compounder-cum-dresser                              1   (whole-time)
 



    Sweeper                                                     1   
    (whole time)
 



    Attendants                                                  2   
    (whole time)
 



    Cook                                                          1  (whole 
    time)
 


4. Dispensary catering for 1,001 to 2,000 
    workers:—
 


Registered Medical 
    Practitioner                        1   
    (whole time)
 


Compounder                                                 1   
    (whole time)
 



    Dresser                                                       1   
    (whole time)
 


Auxiliary Nurse 
    Midwife                                   1   
    (whole time)
 



    Sweepers                                                    2   
    (whole time)
 



    Attendants                                                  3   
    (whole time)
 



    Cook                                                           1   
    (whole time)
 


5. Dispensary catering for 2,001 workers or 
    more:—
 


Registered Medical 
    Practitioner                         1   
    (whole time)
 


Compounder                                                  1   
    (whole time)
 



    Dresser                                                        2   
    (whole time)
 


Auxiliary Nurse 
    Midwife                                    1   
    (whole time)
 



    Nurse                                                           1   
    (whole time)
 



    Sweepers                                                      2   
    (whole time)
 



    Attendants                                                    4   
    (whole time)
 



    Cooks                                                           2   
    (whole time)
 


 
 


III. LIST OF DRUGS, SURGICAL EQUIPMENTS, 
    DRESSINGS, ETC. FOR DISPENSARY
 



A. DRUGS
 


1. Acid Acetic  
 


2. Acid Boric  
 


3. Acid Carbolic  
 


4. Acid Salicylic  
 


5. Acua Distillate  
 


6. Ammon Carb  
 


7. Aspirin  
 


8. Acriflavin or other anti-septic dye  
 


9. Benedict’s solution  
 


10. Calcium lactate  
 


11. Copper sulphate  
 


12. Galamina Preparate  
 


13. Cod Liver Oil  
 


14. Ephedrine Hydrocholor (1/2 gr. tab.)  
 


15. Ether  
 


16. Esct. Glycrr. Iiq.  
 


17. Ferri Sulph  
 


18. Ferriet ammoni citras  
 


19. Glucose   
 


20. Glycerine  
 


21. Gum Acacia  
 


22. Hydrarg ammoniate  
 


23. Hydrarg oxide flava  
 


24. Ethyol  
 


25. Kaoline  
 


26. Lint saponis  
 


27. Liq. Ammon acetate  
 


28. Liq. Plumbi suacatrs fort  
 


29. Lysol  
 


30. Mag. Oxide Powder or Mag Trisillicate  
 


31. Mag. Sulph  
 


32. Monthol  
 


33. Multi vitamin tab  
 


34. Oil Ricini  
 


35. Oil menthipin  
 


36. Oil olive or Oil of arachis  
 


37. Paludrine tabs  
 


38. Phano Barbitone  
 


39. Pot. Bromide  
 


40. Pot. Citrate  
 


41. Pot. Iodide  
 


42. Pot. Permanganate  
 


43. Protargol or Argyrol  
 


44. Pulv. Ipecas co.  
 


45. Pulv. Quinine sulph  
 


46. Sodi Sicarb  
 


47. Sodi Salicylate  
 


48. Spt. Ammon Aromate  
 


49. Sodi Choloride  
 


50. Spt. Mothyl.  
 


51. Spt. Rect.  
 


52. Sulphaulamide or Sulphadizine tablets  
 


53. Sulphaguanidine  
 


54. Sulphalinamide powder  
 


55. Tab. Digzone or Pill Digitalis co. B.P.C.  
 


56. Tabs Laxativ Co. B.P.C.  
 


57. Tetraclorethylene  
 


58. Tinct. Balladonna  
 


59. Tinct. Benoin Co.  
 


60. Tinct. Oppl camphorata.  
 


61. Tinct. Card Co.  
 


62. Tinct. Hyescyamus  
 


63. Tinct. Iodine  
 


64. Ung. Sulphuric B.P.C.  
 


65. Vaseline  
 


66. Vin Lpecac or tinct/or/liq.  
 


67. Zine  Oxide  
 


68. Adrenalin Hydrochloride Liquor (100)  
 


69. Coramine Nikethmide  
 


70. Ematine Hydrocholor (amp or tab)  
 


71. Gr. I  
 


72. Gr. 1/2  
 


73. Injection Quinine Gt. 10  
 


74. Percaune Hydrochlo or Novocian 2% amp.  
 


75. Serum Anti-venom  
 


76. Serum Tatanus anti-toxin 1500 units.  
 


77. Soluseptasine or other injectable 
    sulphamide  
 


78. Tab Atropine (1/100gr.)  
 


79. Tab Morphine (1/60 mg.)  
 


80. Penicillin 100,000 unit ampoules or 
    4,00,000 unit ampoules.
 


81. Streptomycine.  
 


82. 90. P.A.S.  
 


83. Isonicotinic Acid Mydrazide  
 


84. Introdex.  
 


85. Dextrose and sodium chloride injection 
    U.S.P. intransfusion bottles.
 


86. Distilled water ampoules.  
 


87. Liquid paraffin.  
 


88. Vinegarse  
 


89. Tenamus Toxiod.  
 


90. Inj Decadron  
 


91. Inj. Avil                                                    Life Saving drugs
 


92. Tetracycline Cap.
 


93. Choloremphanicol Cap.
 


94. Cholorostrop 
    Cap.                                      Broad spectrum antibite
 


     (Chloremycatine 
    Cap.)                                Medicines generally required
 


95. Vit. B. Complex tab.
 


96. Inj. Vit. B. 12
 



 



B. DRESSING
 
 
  


 
  
 
Number 

 
  
 
250 workers  

        of below
 
251-1000  

        workers

 
  


 
 1. Bandage, 
        roller 15 cm.
 
6
 
6

 
 2. Bandage, 
        roller 10 cm.
 
6
 
6

 
 3. Bandage, 
        roller 8 cm.
 
6
 
6

 
 4. Bandage 
        triangular
 
6
 
6

 
 5. Cotton 
        wool
 
450 gms.
 
450 gms.

 
 6. Gauge 
        meter each
 
6
 
12

 
 7. lint
 
100 gms.
 
100 gms.

 
     
        Number
 
 

 
 8. Plaster of 
        paris bandage 10 cm.
 
--
 
6

 
 9. Plaster of 
        paris bandage 8 cm.
 
--
 
6

 
 10. Strapping 
        adhesive 12 roller
 
1
 
1

 
 11. Strapping 
        adhesive 2 roller
 
1
 
1

 
 12. Strapping 
        adhesive 3 roller
 
1
 
1

 
 13. Burn 
        Dressing
 
5
 
12

 
  



 



 



C. MEDICAL AND SURGICAL 
    EQUIPMENTS
 
 
  


 
  
 
250 Worker  

        of Below
 
251-1000  

        Workers

 
  


 
 1. Basin 35 
        cm.
 
1
 
1

 
 2. Bowls E. 5 
        cm.
 
1
 
1

 
 3. Bowls E. 
        4.5 cm.
 
1
 
1

 
 4. Catheter 
        rubber (size 8 &amp; 10)
 
2
 
2

 
 5. Cup 
        Feeding
 
1
 
1

 
 6. Douche can 
        with fittings
 
--
 
1

 
 7. Drums 
        dressing
 
1
 
1

 
 8. 
        Examination lamp
 
1
 
1

 
 9. Foreceps 
        artery
 
2
 
2

 
 10. Foreceps 
        Chealte
 
1
 
1

 
 11. Foreceps 
        Disecting toothed
 
--
 
1

 
 12. Foreceps 
        Disceting Plain
 
1
 
1

 
 13. Hammer 
        percussion
 
1
 
1

 
 14. Jug 
        measures
 
1
 
1

 
 15. Lancet 
        vaccination
 
--
 
1

 
 16. Mirror 
        forehead
 
--
 
1

 
 17. Needle 
        ansurysum
 
1
 
1

 
 18. Needle 
        suture assorted
 
6
 
6

 
 19. Probe
 
1
 
2

 
 20. Rojer 
        Safety
 
1
 
1

 
 21. Roger's 
        cholera apparatus or apparatus intravenous
 
1
 
1

 
 22. 
        Stethoscope
 
1
 
1

 
 23. Syringes 
        2 cc.
 
1
 
1

 
 24. Syringes 
        10 cc.
 
1
 
1

 
 25. Syringes 
        22 cc. or above
 
----
 
1

 
 26. 
        Spygmonanometer
 
----
 
1

 
 27. Speculam 
        Nasal
 
1
 
1

 
 28. Speculam 
        Aural
 
1 set
 
1 set

 
 29. Store 
        primus
 
1
 
1

 
 30. Scaples
 
1
 
1

 
 31. Skinner's 
        mask
 
--
 
1

 
 32. Stretcher
 
1
 
1

 
 33. Syrunges 
        ear
 
---
 
1

 
 34. Spud eye
 
---
 
1

 
 35. Splint 
        leg Thomas (medium)
 
---
 
1

 
 36. Splinting 
        wire crammor
 
---
 
1

 
 37. Scissors 
        Straight Mayo
 
---
 
1

 
 38. Scissors 
        Straight both ends sharp
 
---
 
1

 
 39. Streliser 
        instrument portable
 
---
 
1

 
 40. 
        Thrrmometres
 
1
 
2

 
 41. Tongue 
        depresspr
 
1
 
1

 
 42. Tape 
        measure
 
1
 
1

 
 43. Test Type 
        Chart
 
1
 
1

 
 44. Tray 
        dressing
 
1
 
2

 
 45. Tray 
        Kidney
 
1
 
2

 
 46. 
        Tourniquet
 
1
 
1

 
 47. Undine
 
1
 
1

 
 48. Weighing 
        machine
 
1
 
1

 
 49. Water 
        proof sheets of 2 metres
 
1
 
1

 
 50. Aotoclave
 
1
 
1

 
 51. Stomach 
        tube
 
1
 
1

 
 52. Mouth gag
 
1
 
1

 
 53. Outgut 
        (assorted number)
 
6 tubes
 
12 tubes

 
 54. Silk work 
        gut or nylon thread
 
3 metres
 
6 metres

 
 55. Sets of 
        wooden splints 

     (41/2' , 3", 1'6")
 
1 set
 
2 set

 
 56. Lifter
 
1
 
1

 
 57. Enamel 
        Bucket
 
1
 
1

 
 58. 
        Staineless Steel dekchi 12" with cover 
 
1
 
2

 
 59. Wooden 
        board 7' x 11/2 x 1"
 
1
 
1

 
 60. Torch 
        with spare cells
 
1
 
1

 
 61. Stretcher
 
2
 
2

 
 62. Eye Cups
 
1
 
1

 
  



 




 

  


</form><form>
 
 
  
 
 



    THE CINE-WORKERS WELFARE FUND RULES, 1984
 



 

 
 



SCHEDULE  IV
 



    Standard of Facilities for Education and  

    Recreation Welfare Centre
 


(see rule 35)
 


WELFARE CENTRE
 


I. Accommodation  
 


(a)    1.     One hall of 45 square metres.
 


            2.     Two rooms of 15 square 
    metres each.
 


            3.     Covered verandah 18 square 
    metres.
 


            4.     One lavatory for men.
 


            5.     One lavatory for women.
 


            6.     One bath room for children.
 


(b)   Play-ground of the size of 36 metres 
    x 18 metres.
 


(c)   Children’s Park equipments—
 



    (i)    
    Swing                                                         
    1 set
 


(ii)   Ocean 
    wage                                                 
    1
 


(iii) Sea 
    saw                                                        
    1
 


(iv)  
    Slides                                                          
    1
 


II. Staff  
 


1.   Adult Education 
    Instructor-cum-Games                      
    1
 


     Supervisor
 


2.   Sevika                                                                 1
 


III. Furniture and Equipment
 


      1.   
    Table                                                                 
    1
 


      2.   
    Chair                                                                  
    2
 


      3.   Chair Stool Foldings                                               
    6
 


      4.   Notice 
    Board                                                        
    1
 


      5.   
    Benches                                                              
    2
 


      6.   Black 
    Board                                                          
    1
 


      7.   Steel Almirah                                                        
    1
 


      8.   Coir mat 15 x  1 metres                                          
    1
 


      9.   Radio with loud 
    speaker                                          
    1
 


    10.   Slates, pencils, chalk 
    etc.                                       As necessary
 


    11.   Books, Charts, Maps 
    etc.                                        As necessary
 


    12.   Patromax (if no electricity is 
    available)                      1
 


    13.   Dholak                                                                 1
 


    14.   Jhals                                                                   4 pairs
 


    15.   Volley Ball court equipment, ball 
    etc.                         1 set
 


    16.   Tannikoit 
    set                                                        1
 


    17.   Carrom 
    Board                                                        2
 


    18.   
    Chess                                                                  2
 


    19.   Ludo                                                                   
    3
 


    20.   Newspapers and 
    Periodicals                                     As necessary
 


    21.   Sewing 
    machine                                                    
    1
 


    22.   Scissors                                                               
    1 pair
 


    23.   Tape                                                                   
    1
 


    24.   Knitting and crochat 
    needles                                    As necessary
 


    25.   Raw 
    materials                                                        As necessary
 


    26.   
    Gong                                                                   1
 



 

  


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 1214(E), dated 28th 
    December, 1988, for items (i) to (vi).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>