<act><title>

THE 
    CENTRAL INDUSTRIAL SECURITY FORCE ACT, 1968</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Central Industrial Security Force Act, 1968.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government 
    may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.





 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, unless the context 
otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>a</number> “Director-General” means the Director-General of the Force 
  appointed under section 4; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>aa</number> “enrolled member of the Force” means any subordinate officer, under 
  officer or any other member of the Force of a rank lower than that of an under 
  officer; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ab</number> “Force” means the Central Industrial Security Force constituted under 
  section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ac</number> “Force custody” means the arrest or confinement of a member of the 
  Force in accordance with rules made under this Act;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “industrial undertaking” means any undertaking pertaining to a 
  scheduled industry and includes an undertaking engaged in any other industry, 
  or in any trade, business or service which may be regulated by Parliament by 
  law; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “industrial undertaking in public sector” means an industrial 
  undertaking owned, controlled or managed by— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> a Government company as defined in section 617 of the Companies Act, 
    1956 (1 of 1956); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> a corporation established by or under a Central Provincial or State 
    Act, which is controlled or managed by the Government; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ca</number> “industrial establishment” means an industrial 
  undertaking or a company as defined under section 3 of the Companies Act, 1956 
  (1 of 1956) or a firm registered under section 59 of the Indian Partnership 
  Act, 1932 (9 of 1932) which is engaged in any industry, or in any trade, 
  business or service;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>cb</number> “joint venture” means a venture jointly undertaken by the 
  Central Government or State Government with private industrial undertaking;] 
  
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “Managing Director”, in relation to an industrial undertaking, means 
  the person (whether called a managing agent, general manager, manager, chief 
  executive officer or by any other name) who exercises control over the affairs 
  of that undertaking; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “members of the Force” means a person appointed to the Force under this 
  Act <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[***]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>ga</number> “private industrial undertaking” means an industry owned, 
  controlled or managed by a person other than the Central or State Government 
  or any industrial undertaking in public sector;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “scheduled industry” means any industry engaged in the manufacture or 
  production of the articles mentioned in the First Schedule to the Industries 
  (Development and Regulation) Act, 1951; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>ha</number> “subordinate officer” means a person appointed to the 
  Force as an Inspector, a Sub-Inspector or an Assistant Sub-inspector;] 
 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “supervisory officer” means any of the officers appointed under 
    section 4 and includes any other officer appointed by the Central Government 
    as a supervisory officer of the Force; </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>j</number> “under officer” means a person appointed to the Force as a 
  Head Constable, Naik or Lance Naik.] </subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Any reference in this Act to a law which is not in force in 
any area shall, in relation to that area, be construed as a reference to the 
corresponding law, if any, in force in that area.] 








</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Constitution of the Force. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> There shall be 
constituted and maintained by the Central Government <footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[an armed force 
of the Union] to be called the Central Industrial Security Force for the better 
protection and security of industrial undertakings owned by that Government 
<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[, Joint venture or private industrial undertaking] <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[and 
to perform such other duties as may be entrusted to it by the Central 
Government]. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The force shall be constituted in such manner, shall consist of such 
number of <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[supervisory officers, subordinate officers, under 
officers and other enrolled members] of the Force who shall receive such pay and 
other remuneration as may be prescribed. 






</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Appointment and powers of supervisory officers. </title>— 
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may appoint a person to be the 
Director-General of the Force and such other supervisory officers as considered 
necessary.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[Director General] and every other supervisory officer so 
appointed shall have, and may exercise, such powers and authority as is provided 
by or under this Act. 





</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Appointment of enrolled member of the Force.—The
    <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[appointment of the enrolled members of the Force shall rest 
    with the Director-General] who shall exercise that power in accordance with 
    rules made under this Act:
 

    Provided that the power of appointment under this section may also be 
    exercised by such other supervisory officer as the Central Government may by 
    order specify in this behalf.
 







 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Certificates of members of the Force.—<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every enrolled member of the Force shall receive on his appointment a 
    certificate in the form specified in the Schedule, under the seal of the 
    Director-General or such other supervisory officer as the Director-General 
    may specify in this behalf by virtue of which the person holding such 
    certificate shall be vested with the powers of an enrolled member of the 
    Force.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Such certificate shall cease to have effect whenever the person named in it 
    ceases for any reason to be <footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[an enrolled member] of the Force.
 









 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Superintendence and administration of the Force. </title>— 
<footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> The super-intendence of the Force shall vest in the Central 
Government, and subject thereto and to the provisions of this Act and of any 
rules made thereunder, the command, supervision and administration of the Force 
shall vest in the Director-General.] 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Subject to the provisions of sub-section (1), the administration of the 
Force within such local limits as may be prescribed shall be carried on by 
<footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[such other supervisory officers as considered necessary] in 
accordance with the provisions of this Act and of any rules made thereunder and 
every supervisory officer placed in charge of the protection and security of an 
industrial undertakings <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[, joint venture or private industrial 
undertaking] shall, subject to any directions that may be given by the 
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[Central Government or the Director-General] in this behalf, 
discharge his functions under the general supervision, direction and control of 
the Managing Director of that undertaking. 




</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Dismissal, removal, 
    etc., of members of the Force.—Subject 
    to the provisions of article 311 of the Constitution and to such rules as 
    the Central Government may make under this Act, any supervisory officer may—
 <section>
             <number>i</number>  dismiss, 
1[remove]
    2[, 
    order for compulsory retirement of,] or reduce in rank, any 
3[enrolled 
    member] of the Force whom he thinks remiss or negligent in the discharge of 
    his duty, or unfit for the same; or
 </section><section>
            <number>ii</number>  award any one or more of the 
    following punishments to any 
3[enrolled 
    member] of the Force who discharges his duty in a careless or negligent 
    manner, to who by any act of his own renders himself unfit for the discharge 
    thereof, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  fine to any amount not exceeding 
    seven days’ pay or reduction in pay scale;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  drill, extra guard, fatigue or other 
    duty;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  removal from any office of 
    distinction or deprivation of any special emolument;
 
4[(d)  
    withholding of increment of pay with or without cumulative effect;
 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>e</number>  withholding of 
    promotion;
 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>f</number>  censure.]
  










 


 
 

 

 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Appeal and revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any 

    1[enrolled member] 
    of the Force aggrieved by an order made under section 8 may, within thirty 
    days from the date on which the order is communicated to him, prefer an 
    appeal against the order to such authority as may be prescribed, and 

    2[subject to the 
    provisions of sub-section (2A), sub-section (2B) and sub-section (3)] the 
    decision of the said authority thereon shall be final:
 
Provided that the 
    prescribed authority may entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said 
    period of thirty days, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented 
    by sufficient cause from filing the appeal in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In disposing of an 
    appeal, the prescribed authority shall follow such procedure as may be 
    prescribed.
 

    3[(2A) Any enrolled 
    member of the Force aggrieved by an order passed in appeal under sub-section 
    (1) may, within a period of six months from the date on which the order is 
    communicated to him, prefer a revision petition against the order to such 
    authority as may be prescribed and in disposing of the revision petition, 
    the said authority shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2B</number> The authority, as may 
    be prescribed for the purpose of this sub-section, on a revision petition 
    preferred by an aggrieved enrolled member of the force or suo moto, 
    may call for, within a prescribed period, the records of any proceeding 
    under section 8 or sub-section (2) or sub-section (2A) and such authority 
    may, after making inquiry in the prescribed manner, and subject to the 
    provisions of this Act, pass such order thereon as it thinks fit.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Central Government 
    may call for and examine the record of any proceeding 

    4[under section 8, 
    sub-section (2), sub-section (2A) or sub-section (2B)] of this section and 
    may make such inquiry or cause such inquiry to be made and subject to the 
    provisions of this Act, may pass such order thereon as it thinks fit:
 
Provided that no order 
    imposing an enhanced penalty under sub-section (2) or sub-section (3) shall 
    be made unless a reasonable opportunity of being heard has been given to the 
    person affected by such order.
  















 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Duties of members of the Force. </title>—It shall be the duty of 
every <footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[***] member of the Force— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> promptly to obey and execute all orders lawfully issued to him by his 
  superior authority; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> to protect and safeguard the industrial undertakings owned by the 
  Central Government together with such other installations as are specified by 
  that Government to be vital for the carrying on of work in those undertakings, 
  situate within the local limits of his jurisdiction: 
 Provided that before any installation not owned or controlled by the 
  Central Government is so specified, the Central Government shall obtain the 
  consent of the Government of the State in which such installation is situate; 
  
 </section><section><number>c</number> to protect and safeguard <footcitenum>34</footcitenum>[any joint venture, private 
  industrial undertaking and] such other industrial undertakings and 
  installations for the protection and security of which he is deputed under 
  section 14; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[<number>d</number> to protect and safeguard the employees of the industrial 
  undertakings and installations referred to in clauses (b) and (c); 
 </section><section><number>e</number> to do any other act conducive to the better protection and security of 
  the industrial undertakings and installations referred to in clauses (b) and 
  (c) and the employees referred to in clause (d);] </section>



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Power to arrest without 
    warrant.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any member of the Force may, without any order from a Magistrate and without 
    a warrant, arrest—
 
2[(i)  
    any person who voluntarily causes hurt to, or attempts voluntarily to cause 
    hurt to, or wrongfully restrains or attempts wrongfully to restrain or 
    assaults, threatens to assault, or uses, or threatens or attempts to use, 
    criminal force to any employee, referred to in clause (d) of section 10, or 
    to him or any other member of the Force, in discharge of his duty as such 
    employee or in execution of his duty as such member, as the case may be, or 
    with intent to prevent or to deter him from discharging his duty as such 
    member, or in consequence of anything done or attempted to be done by him in 
    the lawful discharge of his duty as such member;]
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number>  any person who has been 
    concerned in, or against when a reasonable suspicion exists of his having 
    been concerned in, or who is bound taking precautions to conceal his 
    presence under circumstances which afford reason to believe that he is 
    taking such precautions with a view to committing a cognizable offence which 
    relates to property belonging to, or in the premises of, any industrial 
    undertaking referred to in clauses (b) (c) of section 10, or relates to the 
    other installations or to property in the premises of the other 
    installations, referred to in those clauses;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>  any person who commits or 
    attempts to commit a cognisable offence which involves or which is likely to 
    involve 
3[***] 
    danger to the life of any person engaged in carrying on any work relating to 
    any undertaking or installations referred to in clauses (b) and (c) of 
    section 10.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If any person is found 
    trespassing on the premises of any industrial undertaking referred to in 
    clauses (b) and (c) of section 10, he may, without prejudice to any other 
    proceedings which may be taken against him, be removed from such premises by 
    an 

    4[***] member of the 
    Force.
  










 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Power to search without 
    warrant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever 

    1[***] any member of 
    the Force, not below the prescribed rank, has reasons to believe that any 
    such offence as is referred to in section 11 has been or is being committed 
    and that a search warrant cannot be obtained without affording the offender 
    an opportunity of escaping or of concealing evidence of the offence, he may 
    detain the offender and search his person and belongings forthwith and, if 
    he thinks proper, arrest any person whom he has reason to believe to have 
    committed the offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of the
    

    2[Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)], relating to searches under that Code shall, so 
    far as may be, apply to searches under this section.
  









 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Procedure to be 
    followed after arrest.—Any
    

    1[***] member of the 
    force making an arrest under this Act, shall, without unnecessary delay, 
    make over the person so arrested to a police officer, or, in the absence of 
    a police officer, take such person or cause him to be taken to the nearest 
    police station together with a report of the circumstances occasioning the 
    arrest.
 







 


 
 

 

 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Deputation of the Force to industrial undertakings in public 
sector </title><footcitenum>43</footcitenum><title>[, joint venture or private sector]. 
</title>—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to any general directions which may be issued by the 
Central Government, it shall be lawful for the <footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[Director-General], 
on a request received in this behalf from the Managing Director concerned of an 
industrial undertaking in public sector <footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[, joint venture or private 
sector] showing the necessity thereof, to depute such number of 
<footcitenum>46</footcitenum>[***] members of the Force as the <footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[Director-General] may 
consider necessary for the protection and security of that industrial 
undertaking and any installations attached thereto and the <footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[***] 
members of the Force so deputed shall be at the charge of the Managing Director: 

 Provided that in the case of an undertaking owned, controlled or managed,— 

 
 <subsection><number>i</number> by a Government company of which the Central Government is not a 
  member; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> by a corporation established by or under a Provincial or State Act, 
  </subsection>
 no such request shall be entertained unless it is made with the consent of 
the Government of the State in which the undertaking is situate.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the <footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[Director-General] is of the opinion that 
circumstances necessitating the deputation of the <footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[***] members of 
the Force in relation to an industrial undertaking under sub-section (1) have 
ceased to exist, or for any other reason it is necessary so to do, he may, after 
informing the Managing Director of that industrial undertaking, withdraw the 
<footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[***] members of the Force so deputed: 
 Provided that the Managing Director may, on giving <footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[three month's 
notice] in writing to the <footcitenum>44</footcitenum>[Director-General] require that the 
<footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[***] members of the Force so deputed shall be withdrawn, and the 
Managing Director shall be relieved from the charge from the date of expiration 
of such notice or from any earlier date on which the Force is so withdrawn. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every <footcitenum>48</footcitenum>[***] member of the Force, while discharging his 
functions during the period of deputation, shall continue to exercise the same 
powers and be subject to the same responsibilities, discipline and penalties as 
would have been applicable to him under this Act, if he had been discharging 
those functions in relation to an industrial undertaking owned by the Central 
Government. 







</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>

    1[<number>14A</number> Technical 
    Consultancy Service to industrial establishments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to any general directions which may be issued by the Central 
    Government, it shall be lawful for the Director-General, on a request 
    received from the Managing Director of an industrial establishment in the 
    private sector or any other person authorised by him in this behalf, to 
    direct the members of the Force to provide technical consultancy services 
    relating to security, to such industrial establishments in such manner and 
    on payment of such fee as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The fee received under 
    sub-section (1) shall be credited to the Consolidated Fund of India.
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section, the expression “Managing Director”, in 
    relation to an industrial establishment, means the person (whether called 
    General Manager, Manager, Chief Executive Officer or a partner of a firm or 
    by any other name) who exercises control over the affairs of the 
    establishment.]
  







 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Officers and members of the Force to be considered always on duty 
and liable to be employed anywhere in India. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
<footcitenum>51</footcitenum>[***] member of the Force shall, for the purpose of this act, be 
considered to be always on duty, and shall, at any time, be liable to be 
employed at any place within <footcitenum>52</footcitenum>[or outside] India. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Save as provided in section 14, no <footcitenum>51</footcitenum>[***] member of the force 
shall engage himself in any employment or office other than his duties under 
this Act. 


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>

    1[<number>15A</number> Restrictions 
    respecting right to form association, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No member of the Force shall, without the previous sanction in writing of 
    the Central Government of the prescribed authority,—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  be a member of, or be associated in 
    any way with, any trade union, labour union, political association or with 
    any class of trade unions, labour unions or political associations; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  be a member of, or be associated in 
    any way with, any other society, institution, association or organisation 
    that is not recognised as part of the Force or is not of a purely social, 
    recreational or religious nature; or
 </subsection><subsection>
 <number>c</number>  communicate with the press or 
    publish or cause to be published any book, letter or other document except 
    where such communication or publication is in the bona fide discharge 
    of his duties or is of a purely literary, artistic or scientific character 
    or is of a prescribed nature.
 
Explanation.—If 
    any question arises as to whether any society, institution, association or 
    organisation is of a purely social, recreational or religious nature under 
    clause (b) of this sub-section, the decision of the Central Government 
    thereon shall be final.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No member of the Force 
    shall participate in, or address, any meeting or take part in any 
    demonstration organised by any body of persons for any political purposes or 
    for such other purposes as may be prescribed.]
  








 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Responsibilities of 
    members of the Force during suspension.—A 
    member of the Force shall not by reason of his suspension from office cease 
    to be a member of the Force; and he shall, during that period, be subject to 
    the same responsibilities, discipline and penalties to which he would have 
    been subject if he were on duty.
 
 
 
 

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Surrender of 
    certificate, arms, etc., by persons ceasing to be members of the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every person who for any reason ceases to be 

    1[an enrolled 
    member] of the Force, shall forthwith surrender to any supervisory officer 
    empowered to revive the same, his certificate of appointment, the arms, 
    accoutrements, clothing and other articles which have been furnished to him 
    for the performance of duties as a member of the Force.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person who wilfully 
    neglects or refuses to surrender his certificate of appointment or the arms, 
    accoutrements, clothing and other articles furnished to him, as required by 
    sub-section (1), shall on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to one month, or with fine which may extend to two 
    hundred rupees, or with both.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in this section 
    shall be deemed to apply to any article which, under the orders of the
    

    2[Director General], 
    has become the property of the person to whom the same was furnished.
  








 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Penalties for neglect 
    of duty, etc.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    Without prejudice to the provisions contained in section 8, every member of 
    the Force who shall be guilty of any violation of duty or wilful breach or 
    neglect of any rule or regulation or lawful order made by a supervisory 
    officer, or who shall withdraw from the duties of his office without 
    permission, or who, being absent on leave, fails, without reasonable cause, 
    to report himself for duty on the expiration of the leave, or who engages 
    himself without authority in any employment other than his duty as a member 
    of the Force, or who shall be guilty of cowardice, may be taken into Force 
    custody and shall, on conviction, be punished with imprisonment for a term 
    which may extend to one year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, an offence 
    punishable under this section shall be cognizable and non-bailable.
 </section><section>
<number>2A</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973, the Central 
    Government may invest the Commandant with the powers of a Magistrate of any 
    class for the purpose of inquiring into or trying any offence committed by 
    an enrolled member of the Force and punishable under this Act, or any 
    offence committed by an enrolled member of the Force against the person or 
    property of another member of the Force:
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>  when the offender is on leave or 
    absent from duty; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>  when the offence is not connected 
    with the offender’s duties as an enrolled member of the Force; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>  when it is a petty offence even if 
    connected with the offender’s duties as an enrolled member of the Force; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>  when, for reasons to be recorded in 
    writing, it is not practicable for the Commandant invested with the powers 
    of a Magistrate to inquire into or try an offence,
 
the offence may, if the prescribed authority 
    within the limits of whose jurisdiction the offence has been committed so 
    requires, be inquired into or tried by an ordinary criminal court having 
    jurisdiction in the matter.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing contained in 
    this section shall be construed to prevent any member of the Force from 
    being prosecuted under any other law for any offence made punishable by that 
    law, or for being liable under any such law to any other or higher penalty 
    or punishment than is provided for such offence by this section:
 
Provided that no person 
    shall be punished twice for the same offence.
  







 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Application of Act 22 
    of 1922 to 

    1[***] members of 
    the Force.—The 
    Police (Incitement to Disaffection) Act, 1922, shall apply to 

    2[***] members of 
    the Force as it applies to members of a police force.
 

 









 


 
 

 

 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Certain Acts not to 
    apply to members of the Force.—Nothing 
    contained in the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936), or the Industrial 
    Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947), or the Factories Act, 1948 (63 of 1948), or 
    any corresponding law relating to investigation and settlement of industrial 
    disputes in force in a State shall apply to members of the Force.
 
 
 
 
 
 

 
  

 
 
  
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>21</number> Protection of acts of
    

    1[***] members of 
    the Force.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any suit or proceeding against any 

    2[***] member of the 
    force for any act done by him in the discharge of his duties, it shall be 
    lawful for him to plead that such act was done by him under the orders of a 
    competent authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any such plea may be 
    proved by the production of the order directing the act, and if it is so 
    proved, the 

    2[***] member of the 
    Force shall thereupon be discharged from any liability in respect of the act 
    so done by him, notwithstanding any defect in the jurisdiction of the 
    authority which issued such order.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, any legal 
    proceeding, whether civil or criminal, which may lawfully be brought against 
    any 

    2[***] member of the 
    Force for anything done or intended to be done under the powers conferred 
    by, or in pursuance of, any provision of this Act or the rules thereunder 
    shall be commenced with three months after the act complained of shall have 
    been committed and not otherwise; and notice in writing of such proceeding 
    and of the cause thereof shall be given to the person concerned and his 
    supervisory officer at least one month before the commencement of such 
    proceeding.
  









 


 
 

 

 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>22</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
    without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may 
    provide for—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  regulating the classes, ranks, 
    grades, pay and remuneration of 
1[***] 
    members of the Force and their conditions of service in the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  regulating the powers and duties of 
1[***] 
    members of the Force authorised to exercise any functions by or under this 
    Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  fixing the period of service for 
    1[***] members of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  prescribing the description and 
    quantity of arms, accoutrements, clothing and other necessary articles to be 
    furnished to the members of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>  prescribing the places of residence 
    of members of the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>  institution, management and 
    regulation of any fund for any purpose connected with the administration of 
    the Force;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>  regulating the punishments and 
    prescribing authorities to whom appeals shall be preferred from orders of 
    punishment, or remission of fines or other punishments, and the procedure to 
    be followed for the disposal of such appeals;
 
2[(gg)  
    regulating matters with respect to Force custody under this Act including 
    the procedure to be followed for taking persons into such custody;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ggg</number>  regulating matters with respect to 
    disposal of cases relating to offences under this Act and specifying the 
    places in which persons convicted under this Act may be confined;]
 
3[(gggg)  
    prescribing authority under sub-section (2A) of section 9 and the procedure 
    to be followed by such authority in disposing of the revision petition;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ggggg</number>  prescribing authority under 
    sub-section (2B) of section 9, the period within which such authority may 
    call for the records and the manner in which such authority may make 
    inquiry;]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>  the terms and conditions subject to 
    which 
4[***] 
    of the Force may be deputed under section 14 and the charges therefor;
    5[***]
 
6[(hh)  
    the manner in which and the fee on payment of which the technical 
    consultancy services shall be provided under sub-section (1) of section 14A; 
    and]
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>  any other matter which has to be, or 
    may be, prescribed 
7[ 
    or in respect of which rules are required to be made under this Act].
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made under 
    this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each 
    House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty 
    days, which may be comprised in one session 

    8[or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.
  


















 


 
 

 

 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



THE 
    CENTRAL INDUSTRIAL SECURITY FORCE ACT, 1968
 

 
 



 



    The Schedule
 


(See
    section 6)
 


A.B. 
    has been appointed 
1[an enrolled member] of 
    the Central Industrial Security Force under the Central Industrial Security 
    Force Act, 1968, and is vested with the powers, functions and privileges of
    1[an 
    enrolled member] of the Force.
 


 
 



    ------------------------------------------------------
 



1.

Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 
    and Sch., for “a member” (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).
 



    ------------------------------------------------------ 


 
 


 
 


 

 
 

 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
 Came into force on 
    10-3-1969. vide S.O. 924, dated 3rd March, 1969</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 3, for clause (a) (w.e.f. 
15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 2(a) (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Clause (d) omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> The words “, other than a supervisory officer” omitted by 
Act 14 of 1983, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 2(b) (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 3, for sub-section (2) (w.e.f. 
15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 4, for “a Force” (w.e.f. 
15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 3 (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 5, for “supervisory officers 
and members” (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Subs. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 4, for sub-section (1) 
(w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ). Earlier sub-section (1) was substituted by Act 14 of 
1983, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ). Sub-section (1), before substitution by Act 22 
of 2009, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 5, for “Inspector-General” 
(w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 6, for “appointment of members of the Force shall 
    rest with the Inspector-General” (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> 
 
Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 7, 
    for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> 
 
Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 7, 
    for “a member” (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 8, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 
15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Subs. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 5(i), for “an Inspector 
General, a Deputy Inspector-General, a Commandant, a Deputy Commandant or an 
Assistant Commandant” (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ). Earlier these words were 
substituted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 5(ii) (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 8, for “Central Government” 
(w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 20 of 1989, sec. 3, for “suspend” (w.e.f. 18-5-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch., for “member” (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch., for “member” (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 6, for “subject to the provisions of 
    sub-section (3)”</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 6 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 6, for “under section 8 or under sub-section 
    (2)” (w.e.f.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number> 
 
The 
    words “supervisory officer and” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 20 of 1989, sec. 4, for clause (d) (w.e.f. 18-5-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number> The words “supervisory officer and” omitted by Act 14 of 
1983, sec. 13 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 6(i) (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number> Subs. by Act 20 of 1989, sec. 4, for clause (d) (w.e.f. 
18-5-1989 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 9, for sub-section (1) (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 20 of 1989, sec. 5, for clause (i) (w.e.f. 18-5-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> 
 
The 
    word “imminent“ omitted by Act 20 of 1989, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 18-5-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number> 
 
The 
    words “supervisory officer or” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 9 (w.e.f.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number> 
 
The 
    words “any supervisory officer” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch. 
    (w.e.f. 15-6-</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch., for “Code of Criminal Procedure, 
    1898 (5 of 1898)</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch., for “supervisory officer or” (w.e.f.
    15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 7(a) (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number> Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch., for 
“Inspector-General” (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 7(b) (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 )</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number> The words “supervisory officers and” omitted by Act 14 of 
1983, sec. 13 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number> The words “officers and” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 
and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number> The words “officers and” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 
and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number> Subs. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 7(c), for “one month's notice” 
(w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number> The words “supervisory officer and” omitted by Act 14 of 
1983, sec. 13 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number> Ins. by Act 22 of 2009, sec. 8 (w.r.e.f. 10-1-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch., for “a member” (w.e.f. 
    15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch., for “Inspector-General” (w.e.f. 
    15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 11, for sub-sections (1) and (2) (w.e.f. 
    15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number> 
 
The words “officers and” omitted 
    by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983). Ed.: though 
    the words “officers and” in the heading have not been omitted by the said 
    Act but due to omission of the words “supervisory officers and” in the text 
    of the section the omission in the heading  is necessary.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number> 
 
The words “supervisory officers 
    and” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6- 1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number> 
 
The words “officers and” omitted 
    by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983). 
    Ed.: though the words “officers and” in the heading have not been 
    omitted by the said Act but due to omission of the words “supervisory 
    officers and” in the text of the section the omission in the heading  
    is necessary.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>60</number> 
 
The words “supervisory officer 
    or” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 13 and Sch. (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>61</number> 
 
The words “supervisory officers 
    and” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 12 (w.e.f.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>62</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>63</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>64</number>   The 
    words “supervisory officers and” omitted by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 12 (w.e.f.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>65</number> 
 
The word “and” omitted by Act 40 
    of 1999, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>66</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 40 of 1999, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 29-12-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>67</number> 
 

    Ins. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 12 (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>68</number> 
 

    Subs. by Act 14 of 1983, sec. 12, for certain words (w.e.f. 15-6-1983).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>