<act><title>The
Securities Contracts (Regulation) (Procedure for Holding Inquiry and imposing
Penalties by Adjudicating Officer) Rules, 2005


</title> 
 The
Securities Contracts (Regulation) (Procedure for Holding Inquiry and imposing
Penalties by Adjudicating Officer) Rules, 2005
 


   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Securities Contracts (Regulation) (Procedure for
Holding Inquiry and Imposing Penalties by Adjudicating Officer) Rules, 2005.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette.
 


   




</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number>
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of
1956); 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
“adjudicating officer” means the officer appointed by the Securities
and Exchange Board of India as adjudicating officer under section 23-I of the
Act; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
“inquiry” means the inquiry referred in section 23-I. 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Words and expressions used herein and not defined in these rules but defined in
the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 shall have the same meanings
respectively assigned to them under that Act.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>3</number>
Appointment of adjudicating officer for holding inquiry.—Whenever
the Securities and Exchange Board of India is of the opinion that there are
grounds for adjudging under sections 23A, 23B, 23C, 23D, 23E, 23F, 23G and 23H
of the Act, it may appoint any of its officer not below the rank of Division
Chief to be an adjudicating officer for holding an inquiry for the said purpose.

</article> 

   


   


 <article><number>5</number>
Order of the adjudicating officer.—
<section><number>1</number>
If, upon consideration of the evidence produced before the adjudicating officer,
the adjudicating officer is satisfied that the person has become liable to
penalty under any of the sections specified in sub-section (1) of the section
23-I of the Act, he may, by order in writing, impose such penalty as he thinks
fit in accordance with the provisions of the relevant section or sections
specified in section 23-I of the Act.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
While adjudging the quantum of penalty under section 23-I of the Act, the
adjudicating officer shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:—
 


 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the amount of disproportionate gain or unfair advantage, wherever
quantifiable, made as a result of the default; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the amount of loss caused to an investor or group of investors as a
result of the default; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the repetitive nature of the default. 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every order made under sub-rule (1) shall specify the provisions of the Act in
respect of which default has taken place and shall contain brief reasons for
such decisions.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every such order shall be dated and signed by the adjudicating officer.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>5</number>
Order of the adjudicating officer.—
<section><number>1</number>
If, upon consideration of the evidence produced before the adjudicating officer,
the adjudicating officer is satisfied that the person has become liable to
penalty under any of the sections specified in sub-section (1) of the section
23-I of the Act, he may, by order in writing, impose such penalty as he thinks
fit in accordance with the provisions of the relevant section or sections
specified in section 23-I of the Act.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
While adjudging the quantum of penalty under section 23-I of the Act, the
adjudicating officer shall have due regard to the following factors, namely:—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
the amount of disproportionate gain or unfair advantage, wherever
quantifiable, made as a result of the default; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
the amount of loss caused to an investor or group of investors as a
result of the default; 
 
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
the repetitive nature of the default. 
 
 


 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
Every order made under sub-rule (1) shall specify the provisions of the Act in
respect of which default has taken place and shall contain brief reasons for
such decisions.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every such order shall be dated and signed by the adjudicating officer.

</section></article> 

   


 <article>  

<number>6</number> Copy of the Order.—The
adjudicating officer shall send a copy of every order made under rules by it to
the person concerned and to the Securities and Exchange Board of India.

  
</article> 

   


 <article><number>7</number>
Service of notices and orders.—A
notice or an order issued under these rules shall be served on the person in the
following manner, that is to say,—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
by delivering or tendering it to that person or his duly authorised
agent; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
by sending it to the person by registered post with acknowledgment due to
the address of his place of residence or his last known place of residence or
the place where he carried on, or last carried on, business or personally works,
or last worked, for gain; or 
 
 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
if it cannot be served under clause (a) or clause (b), by affixing it on
the outer door or some other conspicuous part of the premises in which that
person resides or is known to have last resided, or carried on business or
personally works or last worked for gain and that written report thereof should
be witnessed by two persons. 
 

 

  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>