<act><title>


the MINERAL CONSERVATION AND DEVELOPMENT RULES, 19881</title> 

 



 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Mineral Conservation and Development Rules, 1988.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force from the date of their publication in Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>2</number> Application.—These 
rules shall apply to all minerals except—
 <section>
          
<number>i</number>  petroleum and natural gas;
 
        
1[(ii)  coal, 
lignite and sand for stowing;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>iii</number>  any mineral declared as prescribed substances for the purpose of the 
Atomic Energy Act, 1962 (33 of 1962); and
 </section><section>
        
<number>iv</number>  minor minerals.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
        
1[
<section><number>a</number>  
“abandonment of mine” means final closure of a mine either whole or part thereof 
when the mineral deposits within mine or part thereof, have been fully extracted 
or when the mining operations have become uneconomic;]
 
 

2[(aa)]  “Act” 
means the *Mines and Minerals (Regulation and Development) Act, 1957 (67 of 
1957);
 </section><section>
         
<number>b</number>  “agent”, when used in relation to a mine, means any person whether 
appointed as such or not, who acts as the representative of the owner in respect 
of the management of the mine or any part thereof;
 </section><section>
         
<number>c</number>  “authorised officer” means any officer of the Indian Bureau of Mines 
duly authorised in writing by the Controller General, Indian Bureau of Mines to 
perform the functions under these rules;
 </section><section>
         
<number>d</number>  “beneficiation” means processing of minerals or ores for the purpose 
of—
 <subsection>
               
<number>i</number>  regulating the size of a desired produce;
 </subsection><subsection>
              
<number>ii</number>  removing unwanted constituents; and
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  improving quality, purity or assay grade of desired product;
 </subsection></section><section>
         
<number>e</number>  “boring” or “drilling” means the penetration of alluvial material, 
rocks or formations by holes for obtaining geological information, and for 
drawing samples therefrom;
 </section><section>
         
<number>f</number>  “Chief Controller of Mines” means the Chief Controller of Mines of the 
Indian Bureau of Mines;
 </section><section>
         
<number>g</number>  “Controller General” means the Controller General of the Indian Bureau 
of Mines;
 </section><section>
         
<number>h</number>  “Controller of Mines” means the Controller of Mines of the Indian 
Bureau of Mines;
 </section><section>
          
<number>i</number>  “development” means the driving of an opening to, or in an ore-body or 
seam or removing overburden or unproductive or waste materials as preparatory to 
mining or stoping;
 </section><section>
          
<number>j</number>  “environment” and “environmental pollution”, shall have the same 
meanings, assigned respectively to these terms in Environment (Protection) Act, 
1986 (29 of 1986);
 



3[(jj)  “final 
mine closure plan” means a plan for the purpose of decommissioning, reclamation 
and rehabilitation in the mine or part thereof after cessation of mining and 
mineral processing operations that has been prepared in the manner specified in 
the standard format and guidelines issued by the Indian Bureau of Mines;
 </section><section>
        
<number>jjj</number>  “financial assurance” means the sureties furnished by the 
leaseholder to the competent authority so as to indemnify the authorities 
against the reclamation and rehabilitation cost.;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>k</number>  “Form” means a Form set forth in Schedule to these rules;
 </section><section>
          
<number>l</number>  “geologist” means a person appointed in writing by the owner or agent 
to perform the duties of a geologist under these rules;
 </section><section>
        
<number>m</number>  “manager” when used in relation to a mine, means any person appointed 
by the owner or agent and includes the owner or the agent if he appoints himself 
to be such manager, under section 17 of the Mines Act, 1952 (35 of 1952);
 
 

3[(mm)  “mine 
closure” means steps taken for reclamation, rehabilitation measures taken in 
respect of a mine or part thereof commencing from cessation of mining or 
processing operations in a mine or part thereof;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>n</number>  “mining engineer” means a person appointed in writing by the owner or 
agent to perform the duties of a mining engineer under these rules;
 </section><section>
         
<number>o</number>  “mining plan” means a mining plan prepared under section 5 of the Act 
and the rules made thereunder;
 



3[(oo)  
“progressive mine closure plan” means a progressive plan, for the purpose of 
providing protective, reclamation and rehabilitation measures in a mine or part 
thereof that has been prepared in the manner specified in the standard format 
and guidelines issued by Indian Bureau of Mines;]
 </section><section>
         
<number>p</number>  “prospect” means an area where prospecting operations for minerals are 
being carried out and includes any area held under prospecting licence;
 </section><section>
         
<number>q</number>  “recognised person” means a person granted recognition by the 
competent authority to prepare mining plan;
 </section><section>
         
<number>r</number>  “Regional Controller” means the Regional Controller of Mines of the 
Indian Bureau of Mines;
 </section><section>
         
<number>s</number>  “shaft” means a vertical or inclined way or opening leading from the 
surface to workings below ground or from one part of the workings below ground 
to another, and includes an incline;
 </section><section>
         
<number>t</number>  “stoping” means making any underground excavation other than 
development working made for the purpose of winning ores or minerals and 
includes extraction or splitting or reduction of pillars or blocks of minerals;
 



4[(tt)  
“temporary discontinuance” means the planned or unplanned suspension of mining 
operations in a mine or part thereof and where the operations are likely to be 
resumed after certain time.]
 </section><section>
         
<number>u</number>  “year” means the twelve months period beginning from the first day of 
April and ending on the thirty-first day of March of the following year;
 </section><section>
         
<number>v</number>  all other words and expressions used in these rules but not defined 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
 
 







</section></article> 

 



 <article>
*<number>3A</number> Scheme of 
reconnaissance.—Every 
holder of a reconnaissance permit shall submit to the Controller General and the 
Regional Controller or the authorised officer within a period of sixty days from 
the date of execution of the reconnaissance permit, a scheme of reconnaissance 
operations indicating the manner in which he proposes to carry out 
reconnaissance operations in the area covered by the permit and in particular—
 <section>
         
<number>a</number>  particulars of the area such as aerial extent, boundaries;
 </section><section>
         
<number>b</number>  the scale of the plan and the area of geological mapping; and
 </section><section>
         
<number>c</number>  the particulars of the machines and instruments to be used.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
*<number>3B</number> Modification of 
scheme of reconnaissance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A reconnaissance scheme prepared and submitted under rule 3A may be modified at 
any time on geological considerations by the holder of a reconnaissance permit 
during continuance of the reconnaissance permit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any modification 
carried out under sub-rule (1) shall be intimated to the Controller General and 
the Regional Controller or the authorised officer by the holder of 
reconnaissance permit within a period of fifteen days.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
*<number>3C</number> Reconnaissance 
operations to be carried out in accordance with the scheme of reconnaissance.—Every 
holder of the reconnaissance permit shall carry out the reconnaissance 
operations in accordance with the scheme of reconnaissance submitted under rule 
3A or with such modifications, if any, as intimated under rule 3B, or as 
directed by the Controller General or Regional Controller or the authorised 
officer.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
*<number>3D</number> Intimation about 
reconnaissance operations.—Every 
holder of a reconnaissance permit shall send to the Controller General, 
Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller, an intimation in Form AA of the 
commencement of reconnaissance operations so as to reach them within a period of 
fifteen days of such commencement.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
*<number>3E</number> Submission of 
reports about reconnaissance operations.—Every 
holder of reconnaissance permit shall send to the Controller General, Controller 
of Mines and the Regional Controller any yearly report in Form BB along with all 
the aerial, photogeological, geophysical, geochemical and such other data 
collected by him as per the conditions stipulated in the reconnaissance permit 
so as to reach them within thirty days after expiry of every year from the date 
of execution of the reconnaissance permit or the expiry of the reconnaissance 
permit or the abandonment of the reconnaissance permit or termination of 
reconnaissance permit, whichever is earlier.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>4</number> Scheme of 
prospecting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a prospecting licence shall submit to 

1[the Controller 
General and the Regional Controller or the authorised officer] within a period 
of 60 days from the date of execution of the prospecting licence, a scheme of 
prospecting indicating the manner in which he proposes to carry out the 
prospecting operations, in the area covered by the licence and in particular—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  particulars of the area;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  the scale of the plan and the area of geological mapping;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>c</number>  the number of pits, trenches, and bore holes which he proposes to put 
in the area;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>d</number>  the particulars of the machines to be used;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>e</number> the details of exploratory mining 

2[if any, proposed] 
to be undertaken;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>f</number>  the number of samples proposed to be drawn and analysed;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>g</number>  the beneficiation studies proposed to be undertaken; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>h</number>  any other matter relevant for the preparation of a scheme of 
prospecting, as directed by the Controller General or the authorised officer 
from time to time by a general or specific order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-rule (1) a scheme of prospecting shall include—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  baseline information of prevailing environmental conditions before the 
beginning of the prospecting operations;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  

3[steps proposed to 
be taken for protection of environment which will include] prevention and 
control of air and water pollution, progressive reclamation and rehabilitation 
of the land disturbed by the prospecting operations, a scheme for the plantation 
of trees, and such other measures, as may be directed from time to time by the 
Controller General or the authorised officer for minimising the adverse effect 
of prospecting operations on the environment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The prospecting scheme 
under sub-rule (1) shall be prepared by a recognised person or a geologist or a 
mining engineer employed under clause (a) of sub-rule (1) of rule 42.
 
 





</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>5</number> Modification of 
scheme of prospecting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A prospecting scheme prepared and submitted under rule 4 may be modified at any 
time on geological considerations by the holder of a prospecting licence during 
continuance of the prospecting licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any modification 
carried out under sub-rule (1) shall be intimated to 

1[the Controller 
General and the Regional Controller or the authorised officer] by the holder of 
a prospecting licence within a period of fifteen days.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>6</number> Prospecting 
operation to be carried out in accordance with scheme of prospecting.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence shall carry out the prospecting operations in 
accordance with the scheme of prospecting submitted under rule 4 or with such 
modifications, if any, as intimated under rule 5 or as directed by the 
Controller General or the authorised officer.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>7</number> Intimation about 
prospecting operations.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence shall send to the Controller General, Controller 
of Mines and the Regional Controller, an intimation in Form A of the 
commencement of prospecting operations so as to reach them within a period of 
fifteen days of such commencement.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>8</number> Report of 
prospecting operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a prospecting licence shall submit to the Controller General, 
Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller—
 
        
1[***]
 <subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  an yearly report in 

2[Form B] so as to 
reach them within thirty days after the expiry of 

3[twelve months] 
from the date of execution of the prospecting licence or the expiry of the 
prospecting licence whichever is earlier:
 
Provided that in case the 
prospecting operations are abandoned, the report in 

4[Form B] shall be 
submitted within a period of thirty days from the date of such abandonment:
 
Provided further that in 
case the prospecting operations are continued for a period exceeding one year, 
the report in 

4[Form B] shall be 
submitted once every year and a final report in 

4[Form B] within a 
period of three months after the completion of the prospecting operations or the 
expiry of the prospecting licence, whichever is earlier.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where prospecting 
operations are carried out by the authorities specified in the second proviso to 
sub-section (1) of section 4 of the Act without a prospecting licence, such 
authority shall submit the annual report in 

4[Form B] to the 
Controller General in respect of each area where prospecting operations have 
been undertaken by them:
 
Provided that this 
sub-rule shall not apply in a case where field operation consists of only 
geological mapping or geo-physical or geo-chemical investigations.
 
 






</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>9</number> Mining Plan.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person shall commence mining operations in any area except in accordance with 
a mining plan approved under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 5 of the 
Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller General 
or the authorised officer 

1[or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the case may be,] may 
require the holder of a mining lease to make such modifications in the mining 
plan referred to in sub-rule (1) or impose such conditions as he may consider 
necessary by an order in writing if such modifications or imposition of 
conditions are considered necessary—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  in the light of the experience of operation of mining plan;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  in view of the change in the technological development.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>10</number> Modification of 
mining plan.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A holder of a mining lease desirous of seeking modifications in the approved 
mining plan as are considered expedient, in the interest of safe and scientific 
mining, conservation of minerals, or for the protection of environment, shall 
apply to the Controller General, 

1[or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the case may be,] setting 
forth the intended modifications and explaining the reasons for such 
modifications.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Controller General 
or the authorised officer 

1[or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the case may be,] may 
approve the modifications under sub-rule (1) 

2[or approve with 
such alterations as he may consider expedient within a period of ninety days].
 
 




</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>11</number> Mining plan to be 
submitted by the existing lessee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where mining operations have been undertaken before the commencement of these 
rules without an approved mining plan, the holder of such mining lease, shall 
submit a mining plan within a period of one year from the date of commencement 
of these rules, 

1[to the Regional 
Controller or the authorised officer or the officer authorised in this behalf by 
the State Government as the case may be, for approval].
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a holder of a 
mining lease has not been able to submit the mining plan within the specified 
time for reasons beyond his control, he may apply for extension of time giving 
reasons to the following authorities:—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  to the Regional Controller for extension of time up to six months;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  to the Controller of Mines for extension of time exceeding six months 
but not exceeding one year;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>c</number>  to the Chief Controller of Mines for extension of time beyond one 
year;
 
          
2[(d)  to the 
officer authorised in this behalf by the State Government in respect of mining 
plan approved by the State Government.]
 

1[(3) The Regional 
Controller, Controller of Mines, the Chief Controller of Mines or the authorised 
officer or the officer authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the 
case may be, on receiving an application made under sub-rule (2) may, on being 
satisfied, extend the period for submission of the mining plan for the period 
mentioned in clause (a), (b), (c) or (d) of the said sub-rule.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Regional 
Controller 

2[or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the case may be,] may 
approve the plan as submitted by the lessee under sub-rule (1) or may require 
modifications to be carried out in the plan and the lessee shall carry out such 
modifications and resubmit the modified plan for 

3[***] approval.
 

1[(5) The Regional 
Controller or the officer authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as 
the case may be, shall, within a period of 90 days from the date of receipt of 
the mining plan or the modified mining plan, convey, approval for disapproval to 
the applicant and in case of disapproval shall also convey the reasons for 
disapproving the said mining plan or the modified mining plan.]
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> If no decision is 
conveyed within the period stipulated under sub-rule (5), the mining plan or the 
modified mining plan, as the case may be, shall be deemed to have been 
provisionally approved and such approval shall be subject to the final decision 
whenever communicated.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The mining plan 
submitted under sub-rule (1) shall be prepared by a recognised person.
 
 





</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>12</number> Review of mining 
plan.—1[***]
 <section>
<number>2</number> The owner, agent, 
mining engineer or manager of every mine shall review the mining plan as 
prescribed under sub-rule (1) and submit a scheme of mining for the next five 
years of the lease to the Regional Controller 

2[or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the case may be,] for 
approval.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The scheme of mining 
shall be submitted to the Regional Controller 

2[or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the case may be,] at least 
one hundred twenty days before the expiry of the five years’ period, for which 
it was approved on the last occasion.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Regional 
Controller or the authorised officer 

2[or the officer 
authorised in this behalf by the State Government, as the case may be,] shall 
convey his approval or refusal to the scheme of mining within ninety days of the 
date of its receipt.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If approval or refusal 
of the scheme of mining is not conveyed to the holder of the mining lease within 
the stipulated period the scheme of mining shall be deemed to have been 
provisionally approved and such approval shall be subject to final decision 
whenever communicated.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The provisions of 
rules 9, 10 and 13 shall apply to the scheme of mining in the same way as they 
are applicable to the mining plan.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every scheme of mining 
submitted under sub-rule (2) shall be prepared by a recognised person or a 
person employed under clause (b) of sub-rule (1) of rule 42.
 
 




</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>13</number> Mining operations 
to be in accordance with mining plans.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a mining lease shall carry out mining operations in accordance 
with the approved mining plan with such conditions as may have been prescribed 
under sub-rule (2) of rule 9 or with such modifications, if any, as permitted 
under rule 10 or the mining plan or scheme approved under rule 11 or 12, as the 
case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the mining 
operations are not carried out in accordance with the mining plan as referred to 
under sub-rule (1), the Regional Controller or the authorised officer may order 
suspension of all or any of the mining operations and permit continuance of only 
such operations as may be necessary to restore the conditions in the mine as 
envisaged under the said mining plan.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>14</number> Prospecting and 
mining operations.—The 
prospecting and mining operations shall be carried out in such a manner so as to 
ensure systematic development of mineral deposits, conservation of minerals and 
protection of environment.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>15</number> Opencast working.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In opencast workings the benches formed shall be so arranged that the benches in 
ore/mineral and overburden are separate so as to avoid mixing of waste with the 
ore/minerals.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The benches in 
overburden shall be kept sufficiently in advance so that their workings do not 
interfere with the working of ore/minerals.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Orientation of the 
workings and sequence of mining operations shall be such that different grades 
of ore/minerals can be obtained simultaneously for blending with a view to 
achieve optimum recovery of ore/minerals from the deposit.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>16</number> Separate stacking 
of non-salable minerals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The overburden and waste material obtained during mining operations shall not be 
allowed to be mixed with non-salable or sub-grade minerals/ores. They shall be 
dumped and stacked separately on the ground earmarked for the purpose.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The ground selected 
for dumping of overburden, waste material, the sub-grade or non-salable 
ores/minerals shall be away from working pit. It shall be proved for absence or 
presence of underlying mineral deposits before it is brought into use for 
dumping.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Before starting mining 
operations, the ultimate size of the pit shall be determined and the dumping 
ground shall be so selected that the dumping is not carried out within the 
limits of the ultimate size of the pit except in cases where concurrent 
backfilling is proposed.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>17</number> Underground mining 
operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Mining operations in underground shall be carried out in such a way so as to 
achieve optimum ore/mineral recovery.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The method of 
underground development of the deposit shall be planned in accordance with the 
method of stoping which shall be selected with due consideration of the geology 
of the deposit and geo-mechanical properties of the ore and the adjoining rocks.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The size of 
development openings, size of blocks and pillars shall be such that the workings 
remain stable during the development and stoping stages and between such stages.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The stoping practices 
shall be such as to cause minimum disturbance to the surface.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In case of a doubt as 
to the optimum ore/mineral recovery under sub-rule (1), or the method of 
underground development under sub-rule (2), or size of openings, blocks or 
pillars under sub-rule (3) or the stoping practices under sub-rule (4), it shall 
be referred to the Chief Controller of Mines for decision.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Chief Controller 
of Mines may order such investigations and tests to be carried out as are 
considered necessary before arriving at a decision on any matter referred to him 
under sub-rule (5).
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>18</number> Sub-grade minerals 
to be brought to surface.—
<section><number>1</number> 
All the sub-grade ore/minerals wherever obtained in underground workings shall 
be brought to the surface instead of leaving or packing them in underground.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> As far as practicable 
the complete width of the ore/mineral body shall be worked:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller of Mines may permit in writing leaving of certain portions in 
underground if it is necessary for the support or protection to the mine 
workings.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>19</number> Prohibition of 
reduction of blocks.—All 
the blocks formed in underground workings shall be regular in size and shape. 
Once a block is formed it shall not be split or reduced in size until the stage 
of commencement of stoping:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Controller of Mines may permit reduction in the size of blocks on an application 
in writing made by the owner, agent, mining engineer or manager giving reasons 
for doing the same.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>20</number> Beneficiation 
studies to be carried out.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the Controller General or the authorised officer, having due regard to the 
nature of mining operations and grade of ore/mineral is of the view that the 
sub-grade or/mineral contains certain recoverable product, he may direct the 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of the mine to get the beneficiation 
investigations carried out.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The report of the 
beneficiation investigation so carried out shall be submitted to the Controller 
General or the authorised officer as the case may be immediately after the 
investigation is over.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In a mine having a 
beneficiation plant, feed products and tailings shall be regularly sampled and 
analysed at suitable intervals and records of the same maintained in bound paged 
book:
 
Provided that the 
Controller General or the authorised officer may require the sampling and 
analysis to be done at any other interval than in practice.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>21</number> Machinery and 
plant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where heavy earth moving is used in mines, the owner, agent, mining engineer or 
manager of the mine shall maintain Log Books in respect of each machine showing 
date-wise account of hours worked, hours not worked, reasons for non-working, 
consumption of fuel/energy and lubricants and output of the machine during the 
corresponding working hours. The summary of operation of each machine shall be 
recorded in the Log Book at the end of each month bringing out the percentage 
availability and percentage utilisation of the machine, average hourly 
performance and average fuel/energy consumption per hour.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each page of the Log 
Book shall be numbered and the summary shall be signed and dated by the mining 
engineer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Log Book shall be 
made available to the authorised officer on demand.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>22</number> Notice for opening 
of a mine.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine shall send to the 
Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller an 
intimation in 

1[Form C] of the 
opening of a mine so as to reach them within fifteen days of such opening.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The intimation in


1[Form C] sent to 
the Regional Controller under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied with a copy of 
mining plan approved under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 5 of the Act


2[only when the 
mine is being opened after a lapse of 5 years’ period from the date of approval 
of mining plan].
 
 




</section></article> 

 <title></title>
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>23</number> Abandonment of mines. </title> —
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent, mining engineer, or manager of every mine shall not abandon a mine or a part of mine during the subsistence of the lease except with prior permission in writing of the Controller General or the authorised officer. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The owner, agent, mining engineer, or manager of every mine shall send to the Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller under  
  registered cover, a notice in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Form D] of his intention to abandon a mine or a part of a mine so as to reach them at least ninety days before the intended date of such abandonment. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Such a notice shall be accompanied by plans and sections on a scale of not less than 1 cm - 10 metres setting forth accurately the work done in the mine upto the time of submission of the notice including the measures envisaged for the protection of the abandoned mine or part thereof, the approaches thereto, and the environment: 
 Provided that the Controller General may require the plans and sections to be prepared on any other suitable scale. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Controller General or the authorised officer may an order in writing made before the proposed date of abandonment, prohibit abandonment or allow it to be done with such conditions as he may specify in the order. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> The leaseholder shall not abandon a mine or part thereof unless a final mine closure plan duly approved by the Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorized by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, is implemented. For this purpose, the lessee shall be required to obtain a certificate from the Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorized by the State Government in this behalf to the effect that protective, reclamation and rehabilitation work in accordance with the final mine closure plan or with such modifications as approved by the competent authority, have been carried out before abandonment of Mine.] 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>

1[<number>23A</number> Mine 
Closure Plan.—Every mine shall have Mine Closure Plan, which shall be of two 
types:—
 <section>
          
<number>i</number>  a progressive mine closure plan; and
 </section><section>
         
<number>ii</number>  a final mine closure plan.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 <title></title>
  
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title> <number>23B</number> Submission of Progressive Mine Closure Plan. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent, manager or mining engineer shall, in case of fresh grant or renewal of mining lease, submit a progressive mine closure plan as a component of mining plan to the Regional Controller of Mines or officer authorized by the State Government in this behalf as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The owner, agent manager or mining engineer shall, in case of existing mining lease submit a progressive mine closure plan to the Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorized by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, for approval <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[on or before 31st December, 2004]. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The owner, agent, manager or mining engineer shall review the progressive mine closure plan every five years from the date of its approval in case of existing mine or from the date of opening of the mine in case of fresh grant or from the date of renewal of mining lease, as the case may be, and shall submit to the Regional Controller of Mines or officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, for its approval. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, shall convey his approval or refusal of the progressive mine closure plan within ninety days of the date of its receipt. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If approval or refusal of the progressive mine closure plan is not conveyed to the owner, agent, manager or mining engineer of the mining lease within the period as specified in sub-rule (4), the progressive mine closure plan shall be deemed to have been provisionally approved, and such approval shall be subject to final decision whenever communicated. 


</section></article> 

  
  
  
 <article><title><number>23C</number> Submission of final mine closure plan</title>.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent, manager or mining engineer shall submit a final mine closure plan to Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, for approval one year prior to the proposed closure of the mine. 
  (2) The Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, shall convey his approval or refusal of the final mine closure plan within ninety days of the date of its receipt to the owner, agent, manager or mining engineer. 
  (3) If approval or refusal of the final mine closure plan is not conveyed to the owner, agent, manager or mining engineer of the mining lease within the period as specified in sub-rule (2), the final mine closure plan shall be deemed to have been provisionally approved, and such approval shall be subject to final decision whenever communicated.
</section></article> 

  
  
  
 <article><title><number>23D</number> The modification of mine closure plan. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The holder of a mining lease desirous of seeking modifications in the approved mine closure plan, shall submit to the Controller General or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, for approval setting forth the intended modifications and explaining the reasons for such modifications. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Controller General or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, may approve the modifications as submitted under clause (1) or approve with such alterations as he may consider expedient. <title></title>
</section></article> 

 <title></title>
  
  
 <title></title>
 <article><title><number>23E</number> Responsibility of the holder of mining lease. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The owner, agent, manager or mining engineer shall have the responsibility to ensure that the protective measures contained in the mine closure plan referred to in this rule including reclamation and rehabilitation works have been carried out in accordance with the approved mine closure plan or with such modifications as approved by the Regional Controller or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf under this rule. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The owner, agent, manager or mining engineer shall submit to the Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, a yearly report before 1st July of every year setting forth the extent of protective and rehabilitative works carried out as envisaged in the approved mine closure plan, and if there is any deviation, reasons thereof. <title></title>
</section></article> 

 <title></title>
  
  
 <article><title><number>23F</number> Financial assurance. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Financial assurance, has to be furnished by every leaseholder. The amount of financial assurance shall be Rupees Twenty-five thousand for A category mines and Rupees Fifteen thousand for B category mines, per hectare of the mining lease area put to use for mining and allied activities. However, the minimum amount of financial assurance to be furnished in any of the forms referred to in clause (2) shall be Rupees Two lakh for A category mines and Rupees One lakh for B category mines: 
 Provided that a leaseholder shall be required to enhance the amount of financial assurance with the increase in the area of mining and allied activities: 
 Provided further that where a leaseholder undertakes reclamation and rehabilitation measures as part of the progressive closure of mine, the amount so spent shall be reckoned as sum of the financial assurance already spent by the leaseholder and the total amount of financial assurance, to be furnished by the lessee, shall be reduced to that extent. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The financial assurance shall be submitted in one of the following forms to Regional Controller of mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, or any amendment to it: 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Letter of Credit from any Scheduled Bank; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> Performance or surety bond; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Trust fund build up through annual contributions from the revenue generated by mine and based on expected amount sum required for abandonment of mine; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> Any other form of security or any other guarantees acceptable to the authority. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> The lessee shall submit the financial assurance to the Regional Controller of mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, before executing the mining lease deeds. In case of an exiting mining lease, the lessee shall submit the financial assurance along with the progressive mine closure plan. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Release of financial assurance shall be effective upon the notice given by the lessee for the satisfactory compliance of the provisions contained in the mine closure plan and certified by the Regional Controller of mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If the Regional Controller of mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, has reasonable grounds for believing that the protective, reclamation and rehabilitation measures as envisaged in the approved mine closure plan in respect of which financial assurance was given has not been or will not be carried out in accordance with the mine closure plan, either full or partially, the Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, shall give the lessee a written notice of his intention to issue the orders for forfeiting the sum assured at least thirty days prior to the date of the order to be issued. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Within the thirty days of the receipt of notice referred to in sub-rule (5), if no satisfactory reply has been received in writing from the lessee, the Regional Controller of mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, shall pass an order for forfeiting the surety amount and a copy of such order shall be endorsed to the concerned State Government. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Upon the issuance of order by the Regional Controller of Mines or the officer authorised by the State Government in this behalf, as the case may be, the concerned State Government may realise any letter of credit or bond or any other surety, guarantee provided or obtained as financial assurance for the purpose of performance of protective, reclamation, rehabilitation measures and shall carry out those measures, or appoint an agent to do so.] 
</section></article> 

 



 <article>

1[<number>24</number> Notice of 
temporary discontinuance of work in mines and obligations of the lease holder.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine shall send to 
Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller of Mines a 
notice in Form D-1 when the mining or mineral processing operations in the mine 
or part thereof are discontinued for a period exceeding ninety days so as to 
reach them within one hundred and five days from the date of such temporary 
discontinuance.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
discontinuance takes place as a result of the occurrence of natural calamity 
beyond the control of the owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of a mine, or 
in compliance with any order or directions issued by any statutory authority 
established under any law in force or any tribunal or a Court, a telegraphic 
intimation shall be sent to the Controller General and the Regional Controller 
within a period of twenty-four hours of such discontinuance, and a notice of 
discontinuance, under this sub-rule shall be submitted to the Controller 
General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller within a period of 
fifteen days of such discontinuance in Form D-1.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> During the temporary 
discontinuation of mine or part thereof, it shall be the responsibility of the 
owner, agent, manager or mining engineer to comply with the reasonable 
prohibitive measures to restrict access for unauthorised entry, provide 
protective measures to potentially dangerous sources of electrical and 
mechanical installations, the mine opening or workings and all other structures. 
It shall be ensured that all contaminated effluents are controlled and all 
physical, chemical, biological monitoring programs have been continued. It shall 
also be ensured that all rock piles, overburden piles and stock piles and 
tailings and other water impoundment structure have been maintained in stable 
and safe conditions.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>25</number> Intimation of 
reopening of a mine.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine shall send to the 
Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller an 
intimation in 

1[Form C] of 
reopening of a mine after temporary discontinuance, so as to reach them within 
fifteen days from the date of such reopening.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>26</number> Stoping of vein, 
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No stoping shall be commenced, conducted or carried out except with prior 
permission in writing of the Controller General, or the authorised officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The owner, agent, 
mining engineer or manager of every mine shall send to the Controller General, 
Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller under registered cover a notice 
in 

1[Form E] 
intimating his intention to commence the stoping of any vein, lode, reef or 
mineral deposit, so as to reach them at least sixty days before the date of 
commencement of such operations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Such notice shall be 
accompanied by plans and sections on a scale of not less than 1 cm=10 metres 
showing the details of the block proposed to be stoped, the manner of stoping, 
the mineralised and barren zones indicating estimated percentage recovery from 
stopes:
 
Provided that the 
Controller General 

2[or the Chief 
Controller of Mines, as the case may be,] may, by an order in writing and 
subject to such conditions as he may specify therein, permit or require the 
plans and sections to be prepared on any other suitable scale.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Controller General 
or the authorised officer may by an order in writing made before the proposed 
date of commencement of stoping operations prohibit the stoping or allow it to 
be done under such conditions as may be specified in the order.
 
 




</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>27</number> General 
requirements about plans and sections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every plan or section prepared or submitted in accordance with the provisions of 
these rules shall—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  show the name of the mine and of the owner and the purpose for which 
the plan or section is prepared;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  show the true north or the magnetic meridian and the date of the 
latter;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>c</number>  show a scale of the plan at least twenty-five centimetres long and 
suitably sub-divided;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>d</number>  unless otherwise provided, be on a scale having a representative 
factor of—
 <subsubsection>
               
<number>i</number>  200:1 in case of mica mines and other mines having small-scale 
workings below ground;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              
<number>ii</number>  2000:1 in case of mines having large open cast working and also in 
case of surface plans of large leasehold areas; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  1000:1 in other cases:
 
                      
Provided that the Chief Controller of Mines may, by an order in writing and 
subject to such conditions as he may specify therein, permit or require the 
plans to be prepared on any other suitable scale;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
         
<number>e</number>  be properly inked in on a durable paper or on tracing cloth or other 
suitable material and be kept in good condition.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The conventions 
prescribed under the Metalliferous Mines Regulations, 1961, shall be used in 
preparing all plans and sections required under these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The plans and sections 
shall be accurate within such limits of error as the Controller General may 
specify by a general or special order.
 

1[(4) The plans and 
sections required under these rules shall be maintained up to date within three 
months in case of category ‘A’ mines as referred to in clause (b) of sub-rule 
(1) of rule 42, and within twelve months in the case of any other mine.].
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>28</number> Types of plans and 
sections.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine shall keep the 
following plans and sections:—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  a surface plan showing every surface feature within the mining lease 
boundaries such as building, telephone, telegraph or power transmission line, 
watermain, tramline, railway, road, river, water-course, reservoir, tank, 
bore-hole, shaft and incline opening, opencast working, dumps and dumping 
ground, the waste land, forest, sanctuaries, agricultural land and grazing land 
and subsidence on the surface;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  a surface geological plan of the area of leasehold, on a scale 
specified or approved by the Controller General by a general or special order in 
writing showing—
 <subsubsection>
               
<number>i</number>  all the lithological units exposed in the area, in the pits, trenches 
and in any other openings made for prospecting and mining operations showing 
contact between lithological units;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              
<number>ii</number>  structural details like strike, dip, fold, fault, plunge of ore body;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  location of prospecting pits, trenches, boreholes and any other 
openings made for prospecting and/or mining operations;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iv</number>  existing mine workings, dumps;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
         
<number>c</number>  a transverse section or sections of the workings through the shaft or 
shafts and main adits indicating clearly the strike and dip of the vein, lode, 
reef, or mineral bed or deposit at different points, and such sections of the 
strata sunk or driven through in the mine or proved by boring, as may be 
available;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>d</number>  a longitudinal mine section or sections showing a vertical projection 
of the mine working including outlines of all stoped out areas, where a reef, 
vein, lode or mineral bed/deposit or part thereof has dip exceeding thirty 
degrees from the horizontal plane:
 
              
  Provided that, with the permission in writing of the Controller General 

1[or the Chief 
Controller of Mines, as the case may be,] and subject to such conditions as he 
may specify therein, such sections may be prepared in relation to any other 
suitable plan;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>e</number>  an underground plan showing—
 <subsubsection>
               
<number>i</number>  the position of the workings of the mine below ground;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              
<number>ii</number> every boreholes and shaft (with depth), drive, cross-cut, winze, raise, 
excavation (stoped ground) and every tunnel and air passage connected therewith;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  every pillar or block of mineral left for the support of any 
structure on the surface; and underground magazines, if any;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iv</number>  the general strike of the veins, lodes, reefs and mineral beds or 
deposits;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              
<number>v</number>  the position of every dyke, fault and other geological disturbance 
with the amount and direction of throw.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever the 
underground plan referred to in clause (e) of sub-rule (1) is brought 
up-to-date, the then position of the workings shall be shown by a dotted line 
drawn through the ends of the workings, and such dotted line shall be marked 
with the date of the last survey:
 
Provided that the 
Controller General 

2[or the Chief 
Controller of Mines, as the case may be,] may, by an order in writing and 
subject to such conditions as he may specify therein approve any other method of 
showing the up-to-date position of the working of the mine.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where different reefs, 
lodes, veins or mineral beds or deposits overlie or run parallel to one another, 
the workings of each reef, lode, vein or mineral bed or deposit shall be shown 
on separate plant and/or longitudinal section or sections; however if two reefs, 
lodes, veins, or mineral beds or deposits are so situated in relation to each 
other that the parting between workings made therein is less than ten metres at 
any place, such workings shall also be shown on a combined plan and/or 
longitudinal section, as the case may be, in different colours.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The plans kept under 
clauses (a) and (e) of sub-rule (1) shall also show the settled boundary of the 
mining lease, or where the boundary is in dispute, the boundaries claimed by the 
owner of the mine and by the owners of the mines adjacent to the disputed 
boundary:
 
Provided that where it is 
not possible to show the complete boundary of leasehold on the same plan an 
additional key plan on any other suitable scale showing such boundaries and the 
outline of the workings shall also be maintained.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The owner, agent, 
mining engineer or manager of every mine shall keep the following:—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  A key plan on a scale of 1:63,000 or 1:50,000 incorporating the 
following:—
 
                    
2[(i)  an 
administrative surface map showing the boundary of the mining lease, and the 
adjoining area lying preferably within five kilometres thereof;]
 <subsubsection>
              
<number>ii</number>  contours at not more than 

3[twenty] metres 
intervals;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  natural drainage system such as rivers, streams, nalahs, water 
reservoirs, ponds, lakes, irrigation dams and canals;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iv</number>  roadways and railways;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              
<number>v</number>  places of historical and archaeological importance, monuments, places 
of worship, pilgrimage and of tourist interest;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>vi</number>  forests with tree density, sanctuaries, wastelands, agricultural 
lands, grazing lands;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            
<number>vii</number>  boundaries of all villages and towns with their population;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
           
<number>viii</number>   predominant wind direction;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>ix</number>  any other relevant features:
 
                                
 4[Provided that 
where topographical map is classified as restricted, the particulars referred to 
in items (i) to (ix) shall be incorporated in the key plan to the extent 
available in the administrative 

5[surface] maps.]
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  An environment plan of the area of mining lease inclusive of the 
adjoining area within five hundred metres of the boundary of a lease area on 
1:5000 scale incorporating the following:—
 <subsubsection>
               
<number>i</number>  

6[an administrative 
surface map showing the boundary of the mining lease];
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              
<number>ii</number>  contour lines at five metres intervals;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  all features indicated in sub-clauses (iii) to (ix) of clause (a) 
above;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>iv</number>  area occupied by mine workings, area deforested, area covered by dump 
with the height of the dump, processing plant, surface building, workshop, 
mining township;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
              
<number>v</number>  area reclaimed and area afforested, location of protective barriers, 
check dams erected to contain solid and liquid effluents generated by 
prospecting, mining, beneficiation or metallurgical operations carried out in 
the mine;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
             
<number>vi</number>  all pumping stations and the courses of discharge of mine water:
 
                                     
4[Provided that the 
particulars with regard to items (ii), (iv) and (v) shall be applicable only 
upto sixty metres beyond the boundary of lease area.]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number>(a) The Controller 
General may, by an order in writing, require such additional details to be shown 
on the plans and sections required to be kept under these rules or the 
preparation and maintenance of such plans and sections showing such details and 
on such scale and within such time as he may specify in the order.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The Controller General 
or the authorised officer may, by an order in writing, require the owner, agent, 
mining engineer or manager of a mine to submit to him within such time, such 
plans and sections, or tracings thereof, as he may specify in the order.
 
 








</subsection></section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>29</number> Copies of plans and 
sections to be submitted.—The 
owner, agent mining engineer or manager of every mine shall, 

1[on or before the 
30th day of June] every year submit to the Controller General, Controller of 
Mines and the Regional Controller a copy of the plans and sections maintained 
under rule 28.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>30</number> Preparation of 
plans.—
<section><number>1</number> All 
plans, sections and tracings or copies thereof kept at the mine shall be 
serially numbered or suitably indexed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every plan, section or 
part thereof prepared under these rules shall carry thereon a certificate for 
its correctness and shall be signed by the mining engineer with date:
 
Provided that the 
geological plans and sections shall be certified and signed by the geologist 
employed under rule 42.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every copy of a plan 
and section or part thereof submitted or maintained under these rules shall bear 
a reference to the original plan or section from which it was copied and shall 
be certified thereon by the owner, agent, mining engineer or manager to be a 
true copy of the original plan or section.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>31</number> Protection of 
environment.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence or a mining lease shall take all possible 
precautions for the protection of environment and control of pollution while 
conducting prospecting, mining, beneficiation or metallurgical operations in the 
area.
</article> 

 



 <article>


1[<number>32</number> Removal and 
utilisation of top soil.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a prospecting licence or a mining lease shall, wherever top soil 
exists and is to be excavated for prospecting or mining operations, remove it 
separately.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The top soil so 
removed shall be utilised for restoration or rehabilitation of the land which is 
no longer required for prospecting or mining operations or for stabilising or 
landscaping the external dumps.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever the top soil 
cannot be utilised concurrently, it shall be stored separately for future use.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>33</number> Storage of 
overburden, waste rock, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of a prospecting licence or a mining lease shall take steps so that 
the overburden, waste rock, rejects and fines generated during prospecting and 
mining operations or tailings, slimes and fines produced during sizing, sorting 
and beneficiation or metallurgical operations shall be stored in separate dumps.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The dumps shall be 
properly secured to prevent escape of material therefrom in harmful quantities 
which may cause degradation of environment and to prevent causation of floods.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The site for dumps, 
tailings or slimes shall be selected as far as possible on impervious ground to 
ensure minimum leaching effects due to precipitations.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Wherever possible, the 
waste rock, overburden, etc. shall be back-filled into the mine 
excavations with a view to restoring the land to its original use as far as 
possible.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Wherever back-filling 
of waste rock in the area excavated during mining operations is not feasible, 
the waste dumps shall be suitably terraced and stabilised through vegetation or 
otherwise.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The fines, rejects or 
tailings from mine, beneficiation or metallurgical plants shall be deposited and 
disposed in a specially prepared tailings disposal area such that they are not 
allowed to flow away and cause land degradation or damage to agricultural field, 
pollution of surface water bodies and ground water or cause floods.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>34</number> Reclamation and 
rehabilitation of lands.—Every 
holder of prospecting licence or mining lease shall undertake the phased 
restoration, reclamation and rehabilitation of lands affected by prospecting or 
mining operations and shall complete this work before the conclusion of such 
operations and the abandonment of prospect or mine.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>35</number> Precaution against 
ground vibrations.—Whenever 
any damage to public buildings or monuments is apprehended due to their 
proximity to the mining lease area, scientific investigations shall be carried 
out by the holder of mining lease so as to keep the ground vibrations caused by 
blasting operations within safe limit.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>36</number> Control of surface 
subsidence.—Stoping 
in underground mines shall be so carried out as to keep surface subsidence under 
control.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>37</number> Precaution against 
air pollution.—Air 
pollution due to fines, dust, smoke or gaseous emissions during prospecting, 
mining, beneficiation or metallurgical operations and related activities shall 
be controlled and kept within ‘permissible limits’ specified under various 
environmental laws of the country including the Air (Prevention and Control of 
Pollution) Act, 1981 (14 of 1981) and the Environment (Protection) Act, 1986 (29 
of 1986) by the holder of prospecting licence or a mining lease.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>38</number> Discharge of toxic 
liquid.—Every 
holder of prospecting licence or a mining lease shall take all possible 
precautions to prevent or reduce the discharge of toxic and objectionable liquid 
effluents from mine, workshop, beneficiation or metallurgical plants, tailing 
ponds, into surface water bodies, ground water aquifer and usable lands, to a 
minimum. These effluents shall be suitably treated, if required, to conform to 
the standards laid down in this regard.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>39</number> Precaution against 
noise.—Noise 
arising out of prospecting, mining beneficiation or metallurgical operations 
shall be abated or controlled by the holder of prospecting licence or a mining 
lease at the source so as to keep it within the permissible limit.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>40</number> Permissible limits 
and standards.—The 
standards and permissible limits of all pollutants, toxins and noise referred to 
in rules 37, 38 and 39 shall be those notified by the concerned authorities 
under the provisions of the relevant statutes from time to time.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>41</number> Restoration of 
flora.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every holder of prospecting licence or a mining lease shall carry out 
prospecting or mining operations, as the case may be, in such a manner so as to 
cause least damage to the flora of the area held under prospecting licence or 
mining lease and the nearby areas.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every holder of 
prospecting licence or a mining lease shall—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  take immediate measures for planting in the same area or any other 
area selected by the Controller General or the authorised officer not less than 
twice the number of trees destroyed by reason of any prospecting or mining 
operations;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  look after them during the subsistence of the licence/lease after 
which these trees shall be handed over to the State Forest Department or any 
other authority as may be nominated by the Controller General or the authorised 
officer; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>c</number>  restore, to the extent possible, other flora destroyed by prospecting 
or mining operations.
</subsection></section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>43</number> Duties of 
geologist.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the geologist to conduct prospecting operations in 
accordance with the provisions of these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> He shall—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  prepare the necessary geological plans and sections which are required 
to delineate the ore body;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  calculate ore reserves and its grade;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>c</number>  be responsible for providing all the necessary information required 
for controlling the quality of the minerals produced;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>d</number>  maintain proper records of the prospecting operations and records of 
sinking of shafts and boreholes as provided under these rules;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>e</number>  work out the appropriate method of sampling and ensure preparation of 
samples accordingly;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>f</number>  maintain an assay plan in cases of underground workings;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>g</number>  maintain all technical data for determining the shape and size of each 
stope block;
 </subsection><subsection>
        
<number>h</number>  update the reserve figures, grade-wise and category-wise at the end of 
every year in case of a working mine;
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>i</number>  identify the associated rocks and minerals and maintain proper records 
of the stacks of non-salable/sub-grade ores and minerals produced;
 </subsection><subsection>
          
<number>j</number>  carry out all such orders and directions as may be given in writing 
under these rules by the Controller General or the authorised officer 

1[and shall forward 
a copy of all such orders or directions to the holder of the prospecting licence 
or, as the case may be, the mining lease].
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>44</number> Duties of mining 
engineer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the mining engineer to take all necessary steps to plan 
and conduct mining operations, so as to ensure conservation of minerals, 
systematic development of the mineral deposits and protection of environment in 
and around the mining lease area in accordance with these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> He shall be 
responsible for the preparation and maintenance of the plans, sections, reports 
and schemes in accordance with these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> He shall be 
responsible for carrying out the study of the associated rocks and minerals, 
identifying them and stacking the various minerals produced separately.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> He shall carry out all 
such orders and directions as may be given in writing under these rules by the 
Controller General or the authorised officer 

1[and shall forward 
a copy of such orders or directions to the holder of prospecting licence or, as 
the case may be, the mining lease].
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Wherever the mining 
engineer is appointed to supervise the prospecting operations under rule 42, he 
shall also carry out the duties of the geologist.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number>(a) The mining engineer 
shall ensure that there is sufficient provision of proper materials, appliances 
and facilities at all times at the mine for the purpose of carrying out the 
provisions of these rules and orders issued thereunder and where he is not the 
owner or agent of the mine, he shall make requisition in writing to the owner or 
agent for anything required for the aforesaid purpose. A copy of every such 
requisition shall be recorded in a bound paged book kept for the purpose.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> On receipt of a 
requisition under clause (a), the owner or agent shall provide as soon as 
possible the materials and facilities requisitioned by the mining engineer.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>45</number> Monthly, quarterly 
and annual returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine shall submit to the 
Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller, returns in 
respect of each mine as per category ‘A’ or ‘B’ specified in clause (b) of 
sub-rule (1) of rule 42, in the relevant form and within the time specified in 
respect of such returns, namely:—
 
          
1[(a) a monthly 
return which shall be submitted before the 15th of every month in respect of 
preceding month in the Form as indicated below:
 
              
In respect of category ‘A’ mines
 <subsection>
               
<number>i</number>  for iron ore in Form F1;
 </subsection><subsection>
              
<number>ii</number>  for manganese ore in Form F2;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  for 

2[bauxite and 
laterite] in Form F3;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iv</number>  for chromite in Form F4;
 </subsection><subsection>
              
<number>v</number>  for copper, lead, zinc, pyrites, gold and tungsten in Form F5;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>vi</number>  for mica in Form F6;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>vii</number>  for precious and semi-precious stones in Form F7;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>viii</number>  for all other minerals in Form F8; and
 
                   
In respect of category ‘B’ mines
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>ix</number>  for all minerals in Form F9;
 <subsubsection>
         
<number>b</number>  an annual return in Form G which shall be submitted before 1st July 
each year for the preceding year in respect of mines using explosives.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         
<number>c</number>  an annual return which shall be submitted before the 1st July each 
year for the preceding year in the Form as indicated below:
 
              
In respect of category ‘A’ mines
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
               
<number>i</number>  for iron ore in Form H1;
 </subsection><subsection>
              
<number>ii</number>  for manganese ore in Form H2;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iii</number>  for 

3[bauxite and 
laterite] in Form H3;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>iv</number>  for chromite in Form H4;
 </subsection><subsection>
              
<number>v</number>  for copper, lead, zinc, pyrite, gold, and tungsten in Form H5;
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>vi</number>  for mica in Form H6;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>vii</number>  for precious and semi-precious stones in Form H7;
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>viii</number>  for all other minerals in Form H8; and
 
                   
In respect of category ‘B’ mines
 </subsection><subsection>
             
<number>ix</number>  for all minerals in Form H9:
 
                      
Provided that in case of abandonment of a mine, the annual return of that mine 
shall be submitted within ninety days of abandonment.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where under the 
provisions of clauses (a) and (c) of sub-rule (1), the monthly and the annual 
returns have been sent in the form prescribed for category ‘A’ mine, they shall 
not, except with the previous permission in writing of the Controller General, 
be sent in the form prescribed for category ‘B’ mines, notwithstanding any 
reduction in the average employment of the mine during the succeeding periods.
 
 





</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>46</number> Notice of certain 
appointments.—When 
any new appointment is made of an agent, mining engineer, geologist, manager or 
any person under sub-rule (6) of rule 42 or when the employment of any such 
person is terminated or any such person leaves, the said employment or when any 
change occurs in the address of any such person, the owner of the mine or the 
holder of the prospecting licence shall, within fifteen days from the date of 
such appointment, termination, leaving or change in address give a notice in


1[Form I] to the 
Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>47</number> Notice of shaft 
sinking and boreholes.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of every mine or the holder 
of a prospecting licence shall send intimation in 

1[Form J] to the 
Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller within 
fifteen days after the commencement of any of the following operations:
 <section>
         
<number>a</number>  the sinking of trial shaft or borehole to a depth exceeding ten metres 
from the surface, or
 </section><section>
         
<number>b</number>  the extension of an existing shaft or borehole to a depth exceeding 
ten metres, or
 </section><section>
         
<number>c</number>  the sinking of a new shaft or boreholes commencing from underground 
workings:
 
                 
Provided that the Controller General or the authorised officer may permit such 
intimation to be given collectively within such extended period as may be 
specified by him.
 
 



</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>48</number> Records of shafts 
and boreholes.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of every mine or the holder 
of a prospecting licence shall keep a record in 

1[Form K] of all 
shafts or boreholes exceeding ten metres in depth and shall retain all records 
and sample of the strata passed through for a period of not less than twelve 
months after the completion of the work or abandonment thereof:
 
Provided that the records 
of boreholes and shafts exceeding one hundred metres length shall not be 
destroyed except with the prior approval of the Controller General or the 
Regional Controller.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>49</number> Change in the name 
of mine to be notified.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine shall send a notice in


1[Form C] to the 
Controller General, the Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller, of any 
change in the name of the mine within thirty days of such change.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>50</number> Notice of transfer 
of prospecting licence or mining lease.—Without 
prejudice to the provisions of the Act or any rules made thereunder or the terms 
and conditions of a prospecting licence or a mining lease, prohibiting or 
restricting the transfer of a prospecting licence or a mining lease, every 
holder of a prospecting licence or a mining lease who transfers or assigns his 
licence or lease or any right, title or interest thereunder to any other person, 
shall, within thirty days of the date of such transfer or assignment send an 
intimation thereof in 

1[Form L] to the 
Controller General, the Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller.
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>


1[<number>50A</number> Notice of 
amalgamation of mining lease.—Without 
prejudice to the provisions of the act 
or any rules made thereunder or the terms and conditions of a mining lease, 
every holder of a mining lease shall within thirty days of the date of 
amalgamation of mining leases carried out under rule 38 of Mineral Concession 
Rules, 1960, send an intimation thereof to the Controller General and the State 
Government.]
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>51</number> Transfer of records 
to transferees.—When 
the ownership of a prospecting licence or a mining lease is transferred, the 
previous owner or his agent shall make over to the new owner or his agent within 
a period of seven days of the transfer of the ownership, borehole cores 
preserved, if any, all plans, sections, reports, registers and other records 
maintained in pursuance of the Act, Rules or Orders made thereunder, and all 
correspondence relevant thereto relating to the prospecting licence or mining 
lease; and when the requirements of these rules have been duly complied with, 
both previous and the new owners or their respective agents shall forthwith send 
to the Controller General, Controller of Mines and the Regional Controller a 
detailed list of borehole cores, plans, sections, reports, registers and other 
records that have been transferred.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>52</number> Copies of 
notices/returns to be submitted to the State Government.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine or a holder of a 
prospecting licence shall simultaneously submit a copy each of the 
notice/return/intimation required to be submitted under these rules to the State 
Government concerned in whose territory the mine or the prospecting area is 
situated or to such authority as that Government may specify in this behalf.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>53</number> Copies of notices 
and returns to be maintained.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer or manager of every mine or a holder of a 
prospecting licence shall maintain the labour attendance register, production 
and despatch register, explosives consumption register, mineral analysis reports 
and details of mining machinery and copies of all notices and returns, plans, 
sections and schemes submitted to the Controller General under these rules, at 
an office established in the area where mining or prospecting operations are 
carried on, and these shall be made available at all reasonable times to the 
officers of the Indian Bureau of Mines for inspection.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>54</number> Power to issue 
directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of every mine shall 
comply with such directions being directions for purposes of providing for 
systematic development of mineral deposits, conservation of minerals and for the 
protection of the environment by preventing or controlling pollution which may 
be caused by prospecting, mining, beneficiation or metallurgical operations, as 
the Controller General may issue from time to time. A copy of the proposed 
directions to be issued to any particular mine will be sent by the Controller 
General to the owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of the mine 
concerned, and to the State Government concerned, and any comments received from 
the owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of the mine and the 
State Government within thirty days of the date of service of the notice, shall 
be duly considered by him before issuing any such directions. General directions 
applicable to a class of mines shall be issued by the Controller General with 
the previous approval of the Central Government in consultation with the State 
Government concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An order made under 
sub-rule (1) shall—
 <subsection>
         
<number>a</number>  in the case of an order of a general nature or affecting a class of 
persons, be notified in Official Gazette; and
 </subsection><subsection>
         
<number>b</number>  In the case of an order directed to a specified individual, be served 
on such individual, (i) by delivering or tendering it to that individual, or if 
it cannot be so delivered or tendered, by affixing it on the outer door or some 
other conspicuous part of the premises in which that individual lives, and a 
written report thereof shall be prepared and witnessed by two persons living in 
the neighbourhood.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><number>55</number> Examination of mineral 
deposits and taking of samples.—The Controller General or any 
officer duly authorised by the Government to enter and inspect a mine, any 
examine any mineral deposit in any area under prospecting licence or mining 
lease and take samples therefrom at any time for the purpose of these 
rules.</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>56</number> Prohibition of 
deployment in certain cases.—If 
any mine or part thereof, which in the opinion of the Controller General, Chief 
Controller of Mines or the Controller of Mines poses a grave and immediate 
threat to the conservation of minerals or to environment, he may, by an order in 
writing to the owner, agent, mining engineer or manager, require him to take 
such measures as may be specified in the order and may prohibit, until the 
requirements as specified in the order are complied with to his satisfaction, 
the deployment of any person other than those required for compliance with the 
requirement of the order.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>57</number> Revision.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person aggrieved by any order made or direction issued under these rules by 
any officer subordinate to the Controller General, 

1[or an officer of 
the State Government, as the case may be,] may within thirty days of the 
communication of such order or direction, apply to the Controller General for a 
revision of the order or direction, provided that any such application may be 
entertained after the said period of thirty days if the applicant satisfies the 
Controller General that he had sufficient cause for not making the application 
within time:
 

1[Provided that if 
any order made or direction issued as aforesaid by an officer subordinate to the 
Chief Controller of Mines, the application shall be made to the Chief Controller 
of Mines who shall deal with the application in the manner prescribed 
hereunder.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order against 
which a revision application is preferred under sub-rule (1) shall be complied 
with pending receipt of the decision of the appellate officer:
 

2[Provided that the 
Controller General or Chief Controller of Mines, as the case may be, may suspend 
operation of the order appealed against, pending disposal of the revision 
application.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of an 
application for revision under sub-rule (1), the Controller General 

3[or the Chief 
Controller of Mines, as the case may be,] after giving a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard to the aggrieved person, may confirm, modify or set aside the 
order passed by an officer subordinate to him.
 

4[(4) Any person 
aggrieved by any order made or direction issued by the Chief Controller of Mines 
may within thirty days of the communication of such order or direction, apply to 
the Controller General for a revision of the order or direction, provided that 
any such application may be entertained after the said period of thirty days, if 
the applicant satisfies the Controller General that he had sufficient cause for 
not making the application within time.]
 

3[(5) On receipt of 
any such application under sub-rule (4), the Controller General may confirm, 
modify or set aside the order or direction made or issued by the Chief 
Controller of Mines or may pass such orders in relation to the applicant, as it 
may deem fit and such decision shall be final.] 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every order against 
which a revision application is preferred under sub-rule (4), shall be complied 
with pending receipt of the decision of the 

3[Controller 
General]:
 
Provided that the 

3[Controller 
General] may, on an application made by the applicant, suspend operation of the 
order appealed against pending disposal of the revision application.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every application 
submitted under the provisions of this rule shall be accompanied by a Treasury 
Receipt showing that a fee of Rs. 500 has been paid into a Government Treasury 
or any branch of the State Bank of India doing Treasury Business to the credit 
of the Central Government under ‘Major Head—0853—Non-Ferrous Mining &amp; 
Metallurgical Industries, 800 —Other receipts’ or by a Bank Draft on a 
Nationalised Bank for 

5[Rs. 1,000 (Rupees 
One thousand)] in the name of Pay &amp; Accounts Officer, Indian Bureau of Mines 
payable at Nagpur.
 
 







</section></article> 

 



 <article>


1[<number>58</number> Penalty.—Whoever 
contravenes any of the provisions of these rules shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend up to two years, or with fine extending 
to fifty thousand rupees or with both, and in the case of continuing 
contravention with an additional fine which may extend up to five thousand 
rupees for every day during which such contravention continues, after conviction 
for the first such contravention:
 
Provided that for repeated 
contravention the punishment should be in the form of imprisonment only:
 
Provided further that any 
offence punishable under these rules may either before or after the institution 
of the prosecution, be compounded by the authorized officer to make a complaint 
to the court with respect to that offence, on payment to that officer for credit 
to the Government, of such sum that officer may specify:
 
Provided also that in case 
of an offence punishable with fine only, such sum shall not exceed the maximum 
amount of fine which may be imposed for that offence: 
 
Provided further that 
where an offence is compounded under these rules, no proceeding or further 
proceeding, as the case may be, shall be taken against the offender in respect 
of the offence so compounded, and the offender, if in custody shall be released 
forthwith.]
 
 



</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>59</number> Preservation of 
cores, etc.—The 
owner, agent, mining engineer, geologist or manager of every mine or the holder 
of a prospecting licence shall preserve intact all cores and specimens of 
different types of rocks and minerals obtained during drilling or sinking 
operations and arrange for them to be laid out in a serial order with 
identification marks, showing the progressive depth at which they are obtained. 
Such specimens shall not be broken except for the purpose of analysis and 
testing in which case, representative samples of the specimens so broken will be 
preserved for a period of not less than six months from the date of completion 
of drilling or sinking operations. The Controller General, by an order in 
writing, may require the cores or specimens of rocks and minerals obtained from 
specific boreholes or shafts to be preserved for any specific period or relax 
the provisions of this rule to such an extent as he may deem fit.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>60</number> Facilities for 
undertaking research or training.—Every 
holder of a prospecting licence or a mining lease shall afford all reasonable 
facilities to persons authorised by the Controller General for the purpose of 
undertaking research or training in matters relating to mining or geology.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>61</number> Submission of 
records/reports regarding research in geology or mining.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person, institution or agency carrying on prospecting or mining operations 
related to any research in geology or mining, shall inform the Controller 
General and the Regional Controller, within a period of thirty days of 
commencement of such research related operations, indicating briefly the aspects 
proposed to be covered under such research together with the name and address of 
the person, institution, or agency carrying out such research work and the 
expected duration of the research related operations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) On completion of 
the said research work, a report describing the observations, analysis and 
conclusions reached as a result of the said research work shall be submitted to 
the Controller General within thirty days of its completion.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> The information so 
received will be kept confidential, if required. The Government will, however, 
be free to utilise the information for general studies, planning or policy 
making purpose.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of 
sub-rules (1) and (2) shall also apply mutatis mutandis to any agency of 
the Central Government or State Government carrying out the research work.
</section></article> 

 



 <article>
<number>62</number> Territorial 
jurisdiction of Controller of Mines/Regional Controller.—The 
Controller General may by a notification in the Official Gazette prescribe the 
limits of the territorial jurisdiction of the Controller of Mines and the 
Regional Controller for purposes of these rules.
</article> 

 



 <article>


1[<number>63</number> Obligation to 
supply other information.—The 
holder of reconnaissance permit, prospecting licence or mining lease, or his 
agent shall furnish such information regarding his reconnaissance or prospecting 
operations or mine or any matter connected therewith as the Controller General 
or the authorised officer may require by an order in writing and the information 
shall be furnished within such time as may be specified in the aforesaid order.]
 
 



</article> 

  
 <article><number>64</number> Provisions of these rules to 
be applicable to Government.—The Government or its agencies 
carrying out mining operations without a mining lease shall be bound by all the 
provisions of these rules in the same manner as they are applicable to holders 
of mining leases.</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>65</number> Chief Controller of 
Mines, etc. to exercise powers of the Regional Controller of mines.— 
Any power granted under these rules to the Regional Controller of Mines may be 
exercised by the Controller of Mines or the Chief Controller of Mines.
</article> 

 



 <article>
<number>66</number> Repeal and savings.—The 
Mineral Conservation and Development Rules, 1958 are hereby repealed.
 
Notwithstanding such 
repeal, anything done or any action taken, including any order made, direction 
given or notice issued under the Mineral Conservation and Development Rules, 
1958 shall insofar as it is not inconsistent with the provisions of these rules, 
be deemed to have been done, taken, made, given or issued, as the case may be, 
within the corresponding provisions of these rules.
</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 580 (E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 227 (E), dated 22nd April, 1991 and again subs. by G.S.R. 330 (E), dated 10th April, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-4-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Ins. 
by G.S.R. 330(E), dated 10th April, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-4-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by G.S.R. 963 (E), dated 23rd December, 2003 (w.e.f. 24-12-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 330(E), dated 10th April, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-4-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>  Ins. 
by G.S.R. 55(E), dated 17th January, 2000.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 22(E), dated 11th January, 2002 (w.e.f. 11-1-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>  Ins. 
by G.S.R. 55(E), dated 17th January, 2000.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 55(E), dated 17th January, 2000.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 22(E), dated 11th January, 2002 (w.e.f. 11-1-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 227(E), dated 22nd April, 1991.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Added 
by G.S.R. 227(E), dated 22nd April, 1991.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Added 
by G.S.R. 227(E), dated 22nd April, 1991.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 330(E), dated 10th April, 2003 (w.e.f. 10-4-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 580(E), dated 4th August, 1995.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>  Ins. 
by G.S.R. 22(E), dated 11th January, 2002 (w.e.f. 11-1-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>  Ins. 
by G.S.R. 55(E), dated 17th January, 2000.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 55(E), dated 17th January, 2000.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 22(E), dated 11th January, 2002 (w.e.f. 11-1-2002).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number>  Subs. 
by G.S.R. 22(E), dated 11th January, 2002 (w.e.f. 11-1-2002).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>