<act><title>

The 
    State Armed Police Forces (Extension of Laws) Act, 1952</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
    may be called the State Armed Police Forces (Extension of Laws) Act, 1952.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***]
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In this Act, “armed 
    police force” means any police force constituted by any of the enactments 
    specified in the Schedule for the time being in force.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Extension of disciplinary laws of any State to members of the armed police 
    force of that State when serving outside that State.—Where 
    any detachment of an armed police force of a State is serving in any part of 
    any other State, whether independently or by being attached to the police 
    force of that other State than notwithstanding anything contained in section 
    3 of the Police Act, 1888 (3 of 1888), every member of the said detachment, 
    while discharging the functions of a police officer in that other State, 
    shall continue to be subject to the same laws in respect of discipline and 
    liabilities as would have been applicable to him, if he had been discharging 
    those functions within the State to which the said force belongs.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Power to 
    add to, or omit from, the Schedule.—The 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, add to, or 
    omit from, the Schedule any enactment and on the publication of such a 
    notification, the Schedule shall be deemed to be amended accordingly.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
[Repeal.] Rep. by the 
    Repealing and Amending Act, 1957 (36 of 1967), s. 2 and 
    Sch. I. 
 


 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



The 
    State Armed Police Forces (Extension of Laws) Act, 1952
 

 
 



Schedule
 


(See sections 2 and 4)
 


             1.  The Bengal Military Police 
    Act, 1892 (5 of 1892).
 


             2.  The Eastern Frontier Rifles 
    (Bengal Battalion) Act, 1920 (2 of 1920).
 


             3.  The Bombay State Reserve 
    Police Force Act, 1951 (38 of 1951).
 


             4.  The Central Provinces and 
    Berar Special Armed Constabulary Act, 1942 (7 of 1942).
 


             5.  The Madhya Bharat Special 
    Armed Force Act, Samvat 2007 (75 of 1950).
 


             6.  The Orissa Military Police 
    Act, 1946 (7 of 1946).
 


             7.  The Rajasthan Armed 
    Constabulary Act, 1950 (12 of 1950).
 


             8.  The United Provinces 
    Provincial Armed Constabulary Act, 1948 (40 of 1948).
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   The words “except the 
    State of Jammu and Kashmir” omitted by Act 62 of 1956, sec. 2 and Sch. tc 
    " 1. The words “except the State of Jammu and Kashmir” omitted by Act 
    62 of 1956, sec. 2 and Sch."</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>