<act><title>


    The Cine-Workers Welfare Cess Rules, 19841</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
 <number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Cine-workers Welfare Cess Rules, 1984.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on 1st day of January, 1984.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires:—
 <section>
<number>1</number> “Act” 
    means the Cine-workers Welfare Cess Act, 1981;
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> “Cess” 
    means the cess levied and collected under section 3 of the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    “Applicant” means a person applying for a film to be certified for public 
    exhibition;
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> “Board” 
    means the Board of Film Certification constituted under section 3 of the 
    Cinematograph Act 1952;
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> “Chairman” 
    means the Chairman of the Board of Film Certification.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> “Regional 
    officer” means the regional officer appointed under Cinematograph Act 
    (Censorship rules);
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> “Fund” 
    means the Cine-workers Welfare Fund;
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> “Producer” 
    means the producer of a film or a person making an application under section 
    4 of the Cinematograph Act, 1952 for a certificate. 
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
 <number>3</number> 
    Levy and collection of Cess.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every application for a certificate under section 4 of the Cinematograph Act 
    1952 shall be accompanied by a crossed demand draft drawn in favour of the 
    Chairman, Central Board of Film Certification and payable at the station at 
    which he is stationed for an amount of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[cess levied under 
    sub-section (1) of section 3 of Cine-workers Welfare Cess Act, 1981] towards 
    payment of duty of excise under section 3(1) of the Act:
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Provided 
    that this sub-rule shall not apply to an application for re-certification 
    made under section 5A of the Cinematograph Act, 1952 (37 of 1952), read with 
    sub-rule (2) of rule 29 of the Cinematograph (Certification) Rules, 1983.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairman, Central Board of Film Certification and in his absence whoever is 
    discharging the duties and functions of the Chairman, Central Board of Film 
    Certification, shall in addition to his duties specified in the 
    Cinematograph Act, 1952, collect the cess referred to in section 3(1) of the 
    Act.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Chairman will be assisted by a supporting staff in the collection of cess 
    and in the maintenance of the records and accounts.
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>4</number> Duties 
    of the Chairman.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Chairman, in addition to the duties prescribed under the Cinematograph 
    (Censorship) Rules, 1958 shall have the following responsibilities:—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   collection of the cess on or before 
      the date of which the producer of a feature film makes an application;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   submit the account of the collection 
      of cess on each financial year to the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   prescribe the manner in which the 
      register, records and accounts on the collection of cess should be 
      maintained;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   credit the duty of excise levied to 
      the Consolidated Fund of India.
</subsection>
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
 <number>5</number> Manner 
    of assessment and collection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The duty of excise referred to in section 3 of the Act shall be collected by 
    the regional offices of the Central Board of Film Certification on or before 
    the date on which the producer makes an application for a certificate under 
    the Cinematograph Act, 1952. The application shall be addressed to the Board 
    and delivered to the regional office concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An 
    amount of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[cess levied under sub-section (1) of section 3 of 
    Cine-workers as Welfare Cess Act, 1981] shall be paid by the producer along 
    with an application for a certificate under the Cinematograph Act, 1952 in 
    the prescribed proforma set out in the Schedule.
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Refund 
    and recovery of the duty of Cess.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a producer decides to withdraw the film before its certification or 
    the film has been refused a certificate and he does not intend to appeal 
    against or seek revision of such order, or as the case may be, that the said 
    order has been confirmed on appeal or revision under the Cinematograph Act, 
    1952, he may make an application in the prescribed proforma set out in the 
    Schedule to the Chairman of the Board for refund of the amount paid by him 
    towards the cess.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any refund 
    under sub-rule (i) shall be made by the Chairman, Central Board of Film 
    Certification by crossed cheque or demand draft by drawing the amount from 
    the concerned pay and accounts office, on an ordinary contingent bill on 
    which shall be specified the name and address of the applicant and name of 
    the film and the amount and date of challan with which the deposit was made 
    by him in the State Bank of India or its subsidiary.
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
 <number>7</number> 
    Authority for imposition of penalty for non-payment of duty of excise.—Penalty 
    not exceeding rupees fifty under section 7 of the Act shall be imposed by 
    the Chairman, Central Board of Film Certification.
 
 

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The 
      Cine-Workers Welfare Cess Rules, 1984
 

 
 

SCHEDULE
 

FORM I|
 

(See sub-rule (2) of rule 
      5)
 

Form of application for payment of cess 
      under  
the Cine-workers Welfare Cess Act, 1981
 

 (to be submitted at the 
      time of making an application for a  
certificate for public exhibition 
      of a film)
 

No. and date (to be entered by the Board’s 
      Office)
 

To
 

The Central Board of Film Certification (through the 
      Regional Officer)
 
 

(i)  Name and address of the 
        applicant;
 

(ii)  Name of the film;
 

(iii)  Language of the film;
 

(iv)  Name and address of producer;
 

(v)  Number and date of the crossed cheque or 
        demand draft for Rs. 1000.
 

(vi)  Has any previous application been made to 
        certify the film for public exhibition.
 

YES/NO
 
 
 

(a)   If yes, to whom the application 
          was made;
 

(b)   The result of such 
          application:
 

I declare that the statement recorded above is true 
      and correct to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 

Dated:                                                                      
      Signature of the Applicant
 

                                                                                           
      Tel No.
 

 
 
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Cine-Workers Welfare Cess Rules, 1984
 



 

FORM II 

    (See sub-rule (1) of rule 6)
 


Form of application for the refund 
    of cess  

    paid by a producer
 


No. and date of the application (to be entered 
    by the Board’s office)
 


To
 


The Central Board of Film Certification 
    (through the Regional Officer)
 
 


1. Name and address of the applicant;
 


2. Name of the film;
 


3. Language of the film;
 


4. Name and address of the producer:
 


5. The reasons for applying for refund;

 


6. Has a certificate been issued by the Board 
    for exhibiton in India:    
 


YES/NO
 


(a)   If yes the number and date of the 
    certificate:
 


(b)   Category of certificate:
 


7. Has certificate been refused to the 
    film        
 


YES/NO
 


(a)   If yes, the reason for refusing;
 


(b)   Whether the producer has preferred 
    appeal against the decision of the Board and details thereof;
 


8. Whether payment of the cess was made at the 
    time of application for certificate;
 


YES/NO
 


(a)   If yes, the date of such application;
 


(b)   The number and date of receipt 
    acknowledging the payment.
 



    Dated:                                                                                       
 



    Signature of Applicant
 



    Tele:
 


 

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 11(E), 
    dated 10th January, 1994.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 
    588(E), dated 4th August, 1984.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>    Subs. by G.S.R. 11(E), dated 10th January, 1994.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>