<act><title>



    The Madras Ancient and Historical Monuments and Archaeological Sites and 
    Remains Act, 1966</title> 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>1</number> Short title, 
    extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called The Madras Ancient and Historical Monument and 
    Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1966.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> It extends to the 
    whole of the State of Madras.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> It shall come into 
    force on such datel 
as the 
    Government may, by notification, appoint.





  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>

<number>a</number>   
    “ancient monument” means any structure, erection or monument or any tumulus 
    or place of internment, or any cave, rock‑sculpture, inscription, or 
    monolith, which is of historical, archaeological or artistic interest and 
    which has been in existence for not less than one hundred years and 
    includes—
 
 <subsection>

<number>i</number>   the 
    remains of an ancient monument,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>   the 
    site of an ancient monument,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iii</number>   such 
    portion of land adjoining the site of an ancient monument as may be required 
    for fencing or covering in or otherwise preserving such monument,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iv</number>   the 
    gardens, if any, appurtenant to an ancient monument, and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>v</number>   the 
    means of access to, and convenient inspection of, an ancient monument,
 

but does not include 
    any ancient or historical monument declared by or under law made by 
    Parliament to be of national importance;
 


 
    [Madras—section 2(a); Assam—section 2(a); Gujarat—section 2(1); Jammu and 
    Kashmir—section 2(1); Madhya Pradesh—section 2 (a); Maharashtra—section 
    2(1); Mysore—section 2(1); Orissa—section 2(a); Punjab—section 2(a); 
    Rajasthan—section 2(1); Andhra Pradesh—section 2(a); West Bengal—section 
    2(3).]
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>   
    “antiquity’ includes—
 
 <subsection>

<number>i</number>   any 
    coin, sculpture, manuscript, epigraph, or other work of art or 
    craftsmanship,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>   any 
    article, object or thing detached from a building or cave,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iii</number>   any 
    article, object or thing illustrative of science, art, crafts, literature, 
    religion, customs. morals or politics in bygone ages,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iv</number>   any 
    article, object or thing of historical interest, and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>v</number>   any 
    article, object or thing declared by the Government, by notification, to be 
    an antiquity for the purposes of this Act,
 

which has been in 
    existence for not less than one hundred years;
 


 
    [Madras—section 2(b); Andhra Pradesh—section 2(b); Gujarat—section 2(2); 
    Jammu and Kashmir—section 2(2); Madhya Pradesh—section 2(b); Maharashtra—section 
    2(2); Mysore—section 2(2); Punjab—section 2(b); Rajashtan—section 2(2).]
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>c</number>   
    “archaeological officer” means any officer appointed by the Government, by 
    notification, to be an archaeological officer for the purposes of this Act 
    for such area as may be specified in the notification;
 

 
    [Madras—section 2(c); Andhra Pradesh—section 2(c); Gujarat—section 2(3); 
    Maharashtra—section 2(3); Punjab—section 2(c); Rajasthan—section 2(3).]   
 

 </section><section>

<number>d</number>   
    “archaeological site and remains” means any areas which contains or is 
    reasonably believed to contain ruins or relics of historical or 
    archaeological importance which have been in existence for not less than one 
    hundred years, and includes—
 
 <subsection>

<number>i</number>   such 
    portion of land adjoining the area as may be required for fencing or 
    covering in or otherwise preserving it, and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>   the 
    means of access to, and convenient inspection of, the area;
 

but does not include 
    any archaeological site or remains declared by or under law made by 
    Parliament to be of national importance;
 


 
    [Madras—section 2(d); Gujarat—section 2(4); Madhya Pradesh—section 2(c); 
    Maharashtra—section 2(4); Mysore—section 2(3); Punjab—section 2(d); 
    Rajasthan—section 2(4); Andhra Pradesh—section 2(d).]
</subsection>
</section>
 



    State Amendments
 
 

“Central Act”
 <section>

<number>Rajasthan</number>—Section 
    2(v).—“Central Act” means the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and 
    Remains Act, 1958 (Central Act 24 of 1958) as amended from time to time;
 

“Collector”
 </section><section>

Gujarat.—Section 
    2(5).—“Collector” includes any officer authorised by the State Government to 
    perform all or any of the functions of a Collector by or under this Act;
 </section><section>

<number>Maharashtra</number>—Section 
    2(5).—“Collector” means in the City of Bombay the Collector of Bombay and 
    elsewhere the Collector of the District and includes any officer authorised 
    by the State Government to perform all or any of the functions of a 
    Collector by or under this Act.
 

West Bengal.—Section 
    2(l).—“Collector” means the Collector of a district.
 

“Commissioner”
 </section><section>

<number>Orissa</number>—Section 
    2(b).—“Commissioner” means any officer authorised by the State Government to 
    perform the duties of a Commissioner under this Act.
 

West Bengal.—Section 
    2(2).—Same as that of Orissa except that the definition uses the word 
    ‘includes’ in place of the word ‘means’. 
 

 <subsection>

<number>e</number>   
    “Director” means the Director of Archaeology and includes any officer 
    authorised by the Government, by notification, to exercise the powers 
    conferred on, and discharge the duties imposed upon, the Director under this 
    Act;
 

 

[Madras—section 2(e); 
    Gujarat—section 2(6); Madhya Pradesh—section 2(d); Maharashtra 2(6); Mysore—section 
    2(4); Punjab—section 2(a); Rajasthan 2(6); Andhra Pradesh—section 2(e).]
 

 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>   
    “Government” means the” State Government;
 

 

[Madras—section 2(f); 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 2(f); Mysore—section 2(5); Punjab—section 2(f).]
</subsection></section>
 



    State Amendments
 
 

“Historical 
    object”
 

West Bengal.—Section 
    2(4).—“historical object” means—
 
 <section>

<number>a</number>  any document, 
    manuscript, printed matter, picture or painting or any movable object or any 
    matter containing any inscription or carving,
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>  any movable 
    object other than those specified above, which the State Government by 
    reason of its historical association, considers it necessary to protect 
    against destruction, injury, alteration, mutilation, defacement, removal, 
    dispersion or falling into decay;
</section>
 

“Land”
 <section>

<number>Assam</number>—Section 
    2(b).—“Land” includes a revenue‑free estate, a revenue‑paying estate, and a 
    permanent transferable tenure, whether such an estate or tenure be subject 
    to encumbrances or not.
 

Jammu and Kashmir.—Section 
    2(5).—Same as that of Assam.
 

“Land Acquisition 
    Act”
 </section><section>

<number>Gujarat</number>—Section 
    2(7).—“Land Acquisition Act” means the Land Acquisition Act, 1894, as 
    applicable in the State of Gujarat:
 

 
 <subsection>

<number>g</number>   
    “maintain “with its grammatical variations and cognate expressions, includes 
    the fencing, covering in, repairing, restoring and cleansing of a protected 
    monument, and the doing of any act which may be necessary for the purpose of 
    preserving a protected monument or of securing convenient access thereto;
 

 

[Madras—section 2(g); 
    Assam—section 2(c); Gujarat—section 2(8); Jammu and Kashmir—section 2(4); 
    Madhya Pradesh—section 2(e); Maharashtra—section (7); Mysore—section 2(6); 
    Orissa—section 2(c); Punjab—section 2(g); Rajasthan—section 2(7); West 
    Bengal—section 2(5); Andhra Pradesh—section 2(g).]
</subsection></section>
 

 



    State Amendment
 
 

“Minister”
 

Jammu and Kashmir.—Section 
    2(5A).—“Minister” means the Minister‑in‑charge of the Archaeological 
    De­partment.
 

 <section>

<number>h</number>   “owner” 
    Includes—
 </section><section>

<number>i</number>   a joint 
    owner invested with powers of management on behalf of himself and other 
    joint owners and the successor-in-title of any such owner, and
 <subsection>

<number>ii</number>   any 
    manager or trustee exercising powers of management and the 
    successor‑in­‑office of any such manager or trustee;
 

 


    [Madras—section 2(h); Assam—section 2(d); Gujarat—section 2(9); Jammu and 
    Kashmir—section 2(6); Madhya Pradesh—section 2(f); Maharashra—section 2(8); 
    Mysore—section 2(7); Orissa—section 2(d); Punjab—section 2(h); 
    Rajasthan—section 2(8); West Bangal—section 2(6); Andhra Pradesh—section 
    2(h).]
</subsection></section>
 

 



    State Amendments
 
 

“Prescribed’
 

Andhra Pradesh.—Section 
    2
<section><number>i</number>.—“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act.
 


                            
    [Assam—section 2(e); Gujarat—section 2(10); Maharashtra—section 2(9); Mysore—section 
    2(8); Punjab—section 2(i), Rajasthan—section 2(ix).]
 

“Protected”
 <subsection>

<number>Rajasthan</number>—Section 
    2(x).—“protected”, when used with reference to an ancient or historical 
    monument or an archaeological site, means such monument or site which may be 
    declared by the State Government under section 3 to be a protected monument 
    or a protected area.
 

“Protected 
    antiquity”
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>Rajasthan</number>—Section 
    2(xi).—“protected antiquity” means an antiquity declared by the State 
    Govern­ment under section 3 to be a protected antiquity and includes any 
    article, object or thing referred to in sub‑clause (b) of clause (ii).
</subsection></section>
 

 
 <section>

<number>i</number>   
    “protected area” means any archaeological site and remains which is declared 
    to be a protected area under this Act,
 

[Madras—section 2(i); 
    Gujarat—section 2(l1); Madhya Pradesh—section 2(g), Maharashtra—section 
    2(10); Mysore—section 2(9); Punjab—section 2(j); Rajasthan—section 2(10); 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 2(j).]
 

 </section><section>

<number>j</number>   
    “protected monument” means any ancient monument which is declared to be a 
    protected monument under this Act.
 

[Madras—section 2(j); 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 2(k), Gujarat—section 2(2) and—section 3; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 2(h); Maharashtra—section 2(11); Mysore—section 2(10); 
    Punjab—section 2(k).]
</section>
 

 



    State Amendment
 

“Protected 
    monument”
 
 <section>

<number>Gujarat</number>—Section 
    2(12).—“protected monument” means an ancient and historical monument which 
    is deemed or declared to be protected monument by or under this Act.
 

Gujarat tc 
    "Gujarat"
 </section>
 

 


 
  


</article><article>

<number>3</number> Certain ancient 
    and historical monuments deemed to be protected monuments.—­All 
    ancient and historical monuments in the State of Gujarat, which, before the 
    commencement of this Act, have been declared by or under the Saurashtra 
    Ancient Monuments Preservation Act, 1956, to be protected monuments, and 
    have not been declared by or under any law made by Parliament to be of 
    national importance, shall be deemed to be protected monuments for the 
    purposes of this Act.
 <section>

<number>Mysore</number>—Section 
    2(10).—”protected monument” means an ancient monument which is declared to 
    be protected by or under this Act.
 



    Protected monuments
 </section></article><article>

<number>3</number> Ancient and 
    historical monuments and archaeological sites and remains deemed to be 
    protected monuments and areas.—All 
    ancient, and historical monuments and all archaeological sites and remains 
    which have been declared by the Ancient Monuments Preservation Act, 1904 
    (Central Act VII of 1904), or the Ancient Monuments Preservation Act. 1337 
    F. (Hyderabad Act VIIII of 1337 F) or the Mysore Ancient Monuments 
    Preservation Act. 1925 (Mysore Act IX of 1925), to be protected monuments 
    but which have not been declared by or under law made by Parliament to be of 
    national importance, shall be deemed to be ancient and historical monuments 
    or archaeological sites and remains declared to be protected monuments or 
    protected areas, as the case may be, under this Act.
 

Maharashtra tc 
    "Maharashtra"
 



    Protected monuments
 </article><article>

<number>3</number> Certain ancient 
    and historical monuments deemed to be protected monuments.—All 
    ancient and historical monuments in the State of Maharashtra which before 
    the commencement of this Act have been declared by or under the Ancient 
    Monuments Preservation Act to be protected monuments, and have not been 
    declared by or under any law made by Parliament to be of national 
    importance, shall be deemed to be protected monuments for the purposes of 
    this Act.
 

Punjab
 



    Protection of Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and Remains
 </article><article>

<number>3</number> Certain ancient 
    and historical monuments etc., deemed to be protected monuments, or areas.—All 
    ancient and historical monuments and all archaeological sites and remains 
    which have been declared by the Ancient Monuments Preservation Act, 1904 
    (Central Act VII of 1904), to be protected monuments or protected areas 
    respectively, but which have not been declared by or under the law made by 
    Parliament to be of national importance, shall be deemed to be ancient and 
    historical monuments or archaeological sites and remains declared to be 
    protected monuments or areas for the purposes of this Act.
 


    “Superintendent”
 <section>

<number>Assam</number>—Section 
    2(f).—“Superintendent” means the Superintendent of Archaeology, and includes 
    any officer authorised by the State Government to perform the duties of the 
    Superintendent.
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article><number>3</number> Power 
      of Government to declare ancient monuments, etc., to be protected 
      monuments and areas.—
<section><number>1</number> Where 
      the Government are of opinion that any ancient monument or archaeological 
      site and remains requires protection under this Act, they may, by 
      notification, give two months’ notice of their intention to declare such 
      ancient monument or archaeological site and remains to be a protected 
      monument or a protected area, as the case may be, and a copy of every such 
      notification shall be affixed in a conspicuous place near the monument or 
      the site and remains, as the case may be.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any 
      person interested in any such ancient monument or archaeological site and 
      remains may, within two months after the issue of the notification, object 
      to the declaration of the monument, or the archaeological site and 
      remains, as the case may be, to be a protected monument or a protected 
      area.
 </section><section><number>3</number> On the 
      expiry of the said period of two months, the Government may, after 
      considering the objections, if any, received by them, declare by 
      notification, the ancient monument or the archaeological site and remains, 
      as the case may be, to be a protected monument or a protected 
      area.
 </section><section><number>4</number> A 
      notification issued under sub‑section (3) shall, unless and until it is 
      withdrawn, be conclusive evidence of the fact that the ancient monument or 
      the archaeological site and remains to which it relates, is a protected 
      monument or a protected area for the purposes of this 
      Act.
 [Madras—section 3; Assam—section 3; 
      Gujarat—section 4; Jammu and Kashmir—section 3; Madhya Pradesh—section 3; 
      Maharashtra—section 4; Mysore—section 4; Orissa—section 3; Punjab—section 
      4; Rajasthan—section 3; Andhra Pradesh—section 4; West Bengal—section 
      3.]
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>3</number> Power of 
    Government to declare ancient monuments, etc., to be protected monuments and 
    areas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Government are of opinion that any ancient monument or 
    archaeological site and remains requires protection under this Act, they 
    may, by notification, give two months’ notice of their intention to declare 
    such ancient monument or archaeological site and remains to be a protected 
    monument or a protected area, as the case may be, and a copy of every such 
    notification shall be affixed in a conspicuous place near the monument or 
    the site and remains, as the case may be.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Any person 
    interested in any such ancient monument or archaeological site and remains 
    may, within two months after the issue of the notification, object to the 
    declaration of the monument, or the archaeological site and remains, as the 
    case may be, to be a protected monument or a protected area.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> On the expiry of 
    the said period of two months, the Government may, after considering the 
    objections, if any, received by them, declare by notification, the ancient 
    monument or the archaeological site and remains, as the case may be, to be a 
    protected monument or a protected area.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> A notification 
    issued under sub‑section (3) shall, unless and until it is withdrawn, be 
    conclusive evidence of the fact that the ancient monument or the 
    archaeological site and remains to which it relates, is a protected monument 
    or a protected area for the purposes of this Act.
 

[Madras—section 3; 
    Assam—section 3; Gujarat—section 4; Jammu and Kashmir—section 3; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 3; Maharashtra—section 4; Mysore—section 4; Orissa—section 
    3; Punjab—section 4; Rajasthan—section 3; Andhra Pradesh—section 4; West 
    Bengal—section 3.]
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>4</number> Acquisition of 
    rights in a protected monument.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Director may, with the sanction of the Government, purchase, or take a 
    lease of, or accept a gift or bequest of, any protected monument.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Where a protected 
    monument is without an owner, the Director may, by notification, assume the 
    guardianship of the monument.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The owner of any 
    protected monument may, by written instrument, constitute the Director the 
    guardian of the monument, and the Director may, with the sanction of the 
    Government, accept such guardianship.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> When the Director 
    has accepted the guardianship of a monument under sub‑section (3), the owner 
    shall, except as expressly provided in this Act, have the same estate, 
    right, title and interest in and to the monument, as if the Director had not 
    been constituted a guardian thereof; and the provisions of this Act relating 
    to agreements executed under section 5 shall apply to the written instrument 
    executed under sub‑section (3).
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> Nothing in this 
    section shall affect the use of any protected monument for customary 
    religious observances.  
 

[Madras—section 4; 
    Assam—section 4; Gujarat—section 5; Jammu and Kashmir—section 4; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 4; Maharashtra—section 5, Mysore—section 5; Orissa—section 
    4; Punjab—section 5; Rajasthan—section 4; Andhra Pradesh—section 5; West 
    Bangal—section 4.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>5</number>
Preservation of protected monument by agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> The Director, 
    when so directed by the Government, shall propose to the owner of a 
    protected monument to enter into an agreement with the Government within a 
    specified period, for the maintenance of the monument.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> An agreement under 
    this section may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>   the 
    maintenance of the monument;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>   the 
    custody of the monument and the duties of any person who may be employed to 
    watch it;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>   the 
    restriction of the owner’s right—
 
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number>   to use 
    the monument for any purpose,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number>   to 
    charge any fee for entry into, or inspection of the monument,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iii</number>   to 
    destroy, remove, alter or deface the monument, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>iv</number>   to 
    build on or near the site of the monument,
</subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>   the 
    facilities of access to be permitted to the public or any section thereof or 
    to archaeological officers or to persons deputed by the owner or any 
    archaeological officer or other officer or authority authorised by the 
    Government to inspect or maintain the monument;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>   the 
    notice to be given to the Government in case the land on which the monument 
    is situated or any adjoining land is offered for sale by the owner, and the 
    right to be reserved to the Government to purchase such land, or any 
    specified portion of such land, at its market value;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>   the 
    payment of any expenses incurred by the owner or by the Government in 
    connection with the maintenance of the monument;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>g</number>   the 
    proprietary or other rights which are to vest in the Government in respect 
    of the monument when any expenses are incurred by the Government in 
    connection with the maintenance of the monument;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>h</number>   the 
    appointment of an authority to decide any dispute arising out of the 
    agreement; and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>i</number>   any 
    matter connected with the maintenance of the monument which is a proper 
    subject of agreement between the owner and the Government.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The Government or 
    the owner may, at any time, after the expiration of three years from the 
    date of execution of an agreement under this section, terminate it on giving 
    six months’ notice in writing to the other party:
 

Provided that where the 
    agreement is terminated by the owner, he shall pay to the Gov­ernment the 
    expenses, if any, incurred by them on the maintenance of the monument during 
    the five years immediately preceding the termination of the agreement or, if 
    the agreement has been in force for a shorter period, during the period the 
    Agreement was in force.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> An agreement under 
    this section shall be binding on any person claiming to be the owner of the 
    monument to which it relates, from, through or under a party by whom or on 
    whose behalf the agreement was executed.
 

[Madras—section 5; 
    Assam—section 5; Gujarat—section 6; Jammu and Kashmir—section 5; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 5; Maharashtra—section 6; Mysore—section 6; Orissa—section 
    5; Punjab—section 6; Rajasthan—section 5; Andhra Pradesh—section 6; West 
    Bengal—section 5.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>6</number> Persons competent 
    to exercise power of owner under section 5, in respect of a protected 
    monument, when owner is under disability or when it is a village property.—­
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the owner of a protected monument is unable, by reason of minority or 
    other disability, to act for himself, the person legally competent to act on 
    his behalf may exercise the powers conferred upon an owner by  
    section 5.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> In the case of a 
    protected monument which is a village property, the headman or other village 
    officer exercising powers of management over such property may exercise the 
    powers conferred upon an owner by section 5.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Nothing in this 
    section shall be deemed to empower any person not being of the same religion 
    as the person on whose behalf he is acting to make or execute an agreement 
    relating to a protected monument which or any part of which is periodically 
    used for the religious worship or observances of that religion. 

 

[Madras—section 6; 
    Assam—section 6; Gujarat—section 7; Jammu and Kashmir—section 6; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 6; Maharashtra—section 7; Mysore—section 7; Orissa—section 
    6; Punjab—section 7; Rajasthan—section 6; Andhra Pradesh—section 7; West 
    Bengal—section 7.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>7</number> Application of 
    endowment to repair a protected monument.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any owner or other person competent to enter into an agreement under 
    section 5 for the maintenance of a protected monument refuses or fails to 
    enter into such an agreement, and if any endowment has been created for the 
    purpose of keeping such monument in repair or for that purpose among others, 
    the Government may institute a suit in the Madras City Civil Court if the 
    protected monument is situated in the Presidency‑town or in the Court of the 
    District Judge if the protected monument is situated elsewhere, or, if the 
    estimated cost of repairing the monument does not exceed one thousand 
    rupees, may make an application to the Madras City Civil Court, or the Court 
    of the District Judge, as the case may be, for the proper application of 
    such endowment or part thereof.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> On the hearing of 
    an application under sub-section (1), the Madras City Civil Court or the 
    Court of the District Judge may, summon and examine the owner and any person 
    whose audience appears to the Court necessary and may pass an order for the 
    proper application of the endowment or any part thereof, and any such order 
    may be executed as if it were a decree of a Civil Court.
 

[Madras—section 7 
    Assam—section 7; Gujarat—section 8; Jammu and Kashmir—section 9; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 7; Maharashtra—section 8; Mysore—section 8; Orissa—section 
    9; Punjab—section 8; Rajasthan—section 8; Andhra Pradesh—section 8; West 
    Bengal—section 9.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>8</number> Failure or 
    refusal to enter into an agreement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any owner or other person competent to enter into an agreement under 
    section 5 for the maintenance of a protected monument refuses or fails to 
    enter into such an agreement, the Government may make an order providing for 
    all or any of the matters specified in sub‑section (2) of section 5, and 
    such order shall be binding on the owner or such other person and on every 
    person claiming title to the monument from, through or under, the owner or 
    such other person.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Where an order made 
    under sub‑section (1) provides that the monument shall be maintained by the 
    owner or other person competent to enter into an agreement, all reasonable 
    expenses for the maintenance of the monument shall be payable by the 
    Government.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> No order under 
    sub‑section (1) shall be made unless the owner or other person has been 
    given an opportunity of making a representation against the proposed order.
 

[Madras—section 8; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 9; Assam—section 8; Gujarat—section 9; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 8; Maharashtra—section 9; Mysore—section 9; Punjab—section 
    9; Rajasthan—section 7.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article><number>9</number> 
      Power to make order 
      prohibiting contravention of agreement under section 
      5.—­
<section><number>1</number> If the Director apprehends that the owner or 
      occupier of a protected monument intends to destroy, remove, injure, 
      alter, deface, imperil, or misuse the monument or to build on or near the 
      site thereof in contravention of the norms of an agreement executed under 
      section 5, the Director may, after giving the owner or occupier an 
      opportunity of making a representation, make an order prohibiting any such 
      contravention of the agreement:
 Provided 
      that no such opportunity need be given in any case where the Director, for 
      reasons to be recorded, is satisfied that it is not expedient or 
      practicable to do so.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any 
      person aggrieved by an order made under this section may appeal to the 
      Government within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed, and 
      the decision of the government shall be final.
 [Madras—section 9; Andhra Pradesh—section 10; 
      Assam—section 9; Gujarat—section 10; Madhya Pradesh—section 9; 
      Maharashtra—section 10; Mysore—section 10; Punjab—section 10; 
      Rajasthan—section 10.]
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>9</number> Power
    to make order prohibiting contravention of agreement under section 5.—­
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Director apprehends that the owner or occupier of a protected 
    monument intends to destroy, remove, injure, alter, deface, imperil, or 
    misuse the monument or to build on or near the site thereof in contravention 
    of the norms of an agreement executed under section 5, the Director may, 
    after giving the owner or occupier an opportunity of making a 
    representation, make an order prohibiting any such contravention of the 
    agreement:
 

Provided that no such 
    opportunity need be given in any case where the Director, for reasons to be 
    recorded, is satisfied that it is not expedient or practicable to do so.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Any person 
    aggrieved by an order made under this section may appeal to the Government 
    within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed, and the decision 
    of the government shall be final.
 

[Madras—section 9; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 10; Assam—section 9; Gujarat—section 10; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 9; Maharashtra—section 10; Mysore—section 10; Punjab—section 
    10; Rajasthan—section 10.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>10</number> Enforcement of 
    agreements.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If an owner or other person who is bound to maintain a monument by an 
    agreement executed under section 5 refuses or fails within such reasonable 
    time as the Director may fix to do any act which in the opinion of the 
    Director is necessary for the maintenance of the monument, the Director may 
    authorise any person to do any such act, and the owner or other person shall 
    be liable to pay the expenses of doing any such act or such portion of the 
    expenses as the owner may be liable to pay under the agreement.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> If any dispute 
    arises regarding the amount of expenses payable by the owner or other person 
    under sub‑section (1), it shall be referred to the Government whose decision 
    shall be final.
 

[Madras—section 10; 
    Assam—section 10. Gujarat—section 11; Jammu and Kashmir—section 7; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 10; Maharashtra—section 11; Mysore—section 11; Orissa—section 
    7; Punjab—section 11; Rajasthan—section 9; Andhra Pradesh—section 11; West 
    Bengal—section 7.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>11</number> Purchasers at 
    certain sales and persons claiming through owner bound by instrument 
    executed by owner. 
—Every person who 
    purchases, at a sale for arrears of land venue or any other public demand, 
    any land on which is situated a monument in respect of which any instrument 
    has been executed by the owner for the time being under section 4 or section 
    5, and every person claiming any title to a monument from, through, or 
    under, an owner who executed any such instrument, shall be bound by such 
    instrument.
 

[Madras—section 11; 
    Assam—section 11. Gujarat—section 12; Jammu and Kashmir—section 8; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 11; Maharashtra—section 12; Mysore—section 12; Orissa—section 
    8; Punjab—section 12; Rajasthan—section 11; Andhra Pradesh—section 12; West 
    Bengal—section 8.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>12</number>
Acquisition of protected monument.—If the Government are of opinion 
    that a protected monument is in danger of being destroyed, injured, misused, 
    or allowed to fall into decay, they may acquire the protected monument under 
    the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (Central Act I of 1894), as 
    if the maintenance of the protected monument were a public purpose within 
    the meaning of that Act.
 

[Madras—section 12; 
    Assam—section 12. Gujarat—section 13; Jammu and Kashmir—section 10; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section12; Maharashtra—section 13; Mysore—section 13; Orissa—section 
    10; Punjab—section 13; Rajasthan—section 12; Andhra Pradesh—section 13; West 
    Bengal—section 10.]
 



    State Amendments
 
 

Jammu and Kashmir
 <section>

<number>10A</number> Power of 
    Government to control mining etc., near ancient monument.—(1) 
    If the Government is of opinion that mining, quarrying, excavating, blasting 
    and other operations of a like nature should be restricted or regulated for 
    the purpose of protecting or preserving any ancient monument, the Government 
    may, by notification in the Government Gazette, make rules—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  fixing the 
    boundaries of the area to which the rules are to apply,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  forbidding the 
    carrying on of mining, quarrying, excavating, blasting or any operation of a 
    like nature except in accordance with the rules and with the terms of a 
    licence, and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>  prescribing 
    the authority by which and the terms on which licences may be granted to 
    carry on any of the said operations.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> The power to make 
    rules given by this section is subject to the condition of the rules being 
    made after previous publication.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> A rule made under 
    this section may provide that any person committing a breach thereof shall 
    be punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> If any person or 
    occupier of land included in a notification under sub‑section (1) proves to 
    the satisfaction of the Government that he has sustained loss by reason of 
    such land being so included, the Government shall pay compensation in 
    respect of such loss.
 

West Bengal
 

Section 11.—Same 
    as—section 10A of Jammu and Kashmir.
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>13</number> Maintenance of 
    certain protected monuments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Government shall maintain every monument which has been acquired under 
    section 12 or in respect of which any of the rights mentioned in section 4 
    have been acquired.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> When the Director 
    has assumed the guardianship of a monument under section 4, he shall, for 
    the purpose of maintaining such monument, have access to the monument at all 
    reasonable times, by himself and by his agents, subordinates and workmen, 
    for the purpose of inspecting the monument and for the purpose of bringing 
    such materials and doing such acts as he may consider necessary or desirable 
    for the maintenance thereof.
 

[Madras—section 13; 
    Assam—section 13. Gujarat—section 14; Jammu and Kashmir—section 11; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 13; Maharashtra—section 14; Mysore—section 14; Orissa—section 
    11; Punjab—section 14; Rajasthan—section 13; Andhra Pradesh—section 14; West 
    Bengal—section 12.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>14</number> Voluntary 
    contributions.—The 
    Director may receive voluntary contributions towards the cost of maintaining 
    a protected monument and may issue orders for the management and application 
    of the contribution so received by him;
 

Provided that no 
    contribution received under this section shall be applied to any purpose 
    other than the purpose for which it was contributed.
 

[Madras—section 14; 
    Assam—section 14. Gujarat—section 15; Jammu and Kashmir—section 12; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 14; Maharashtra—section 15; Mysore—section 15; Orissa—section 
    12; Punjab—section 15; Rajasthan—section 14; Andhra Pradesh—section 15; West 
    Bengal—section 13.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>15</number> Protection of 
    place of worship from misuse.—A 
    protected monument maintained by the Government under this Act, which is a 
    place of worship or shrine shall not be used for any purpose inconsistent 
    with its character.
 

[Madras—section 15; 
    Assam—section 15; Gujarat—section 16; Jammu and Kashmir—section 13; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 15; Maharashtra—section 16; Mysore—section 16; Orissa—section 
    13; Punjab—section 16; Rajasthan—section 15; Andhra Pradesh—section 16.]
 



    State Amendments
 

Gujarat
 
 <section>

<number>17</number> Preservation of 
    amenities of protected monuments.—(1) 
    If the State Government  is of opinion that, for the purpose of 
    preserving the reasonable amenities of any protected monument, it is 
    necessary so to do, the State Government may, subject to the provisions of 
    this action, by notification in the Official Gazette, in respect of any area 
    comprising or adjacent to the site of such monument specified in such 
    notification (hereinafter referred to as “the controlled area”),—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  prohibit or 
    restrict the construction, erection or execution of building, structures and 
    other works above ground within the controlled area, or the alteration or 
    extension of any such buildings, structures or works in such manner as 
    materially to affect their external appearance;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  prescribe the 
    position, height, size, design, materials, colour and screening and 
    other­wise regulate the external appearance of buildings, structures and 
    other works above ground within the controlled area;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>  require any 
    local authority—
 <subsubsection>

<number>i</number> to construct any 
    approach road to any protected monument, or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

<number>ii</number> to demolish any 
    public convenience vesting in it, that is to say, a latrine, urinal, 
    dustbin, rubbish dump and the like, located close to or in the vicinity of 
    any protected monument;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>  prohibit or 
    restrict the felling of trees within the controlled area;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>  otherwise 
    restrict the user of land within the controlled area to such extent as is 
    necessary for the purpose of preserving the reasonable amenities of the 
    protected monument;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>  provide for 
    such matters as appear to the State Government to be incidental to or 
    consequential on the foregoing provisions of this section, or to be 
    necessary for giving effect to those provisions.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> Not less than 
    forty‑five days before issuing a notification under sub‑section (1), the 
    State Government shall cause to be published in the Official Gazette, in the 
    controlled area, and in the village and at the headquarters of the taluka or 
    mahal of the district in which the controlled area is situated, a 
    notification stating that it proposes to issue a notification in terms of 
    sub‑section (1) together with a notice requiring all persons affected by 
    such notification, who wish to make any objection to the issuing of such 
    notification, to submit their objections in writing to the State Government 
    or appear before any officer duly authorised in that behalf to hear 
    objections on behalf of the State Government, within one month of the 
    publication of the notification in the official Gazette or within fifteen 
    days from the date of the publication of the notification in the controlled 
    area, whichever period expires later.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> If on the expiration 
    of the time allowed by sub‑section (2) for the filing of objections, no 
    objection has been made, the State Government shall proceed at once to issue 
    the notification under sub‑section (1). If any such objection has been made, 
    the State Government may, after all the objections have been considered or 
    heard, as the case may be, either—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  abandon the 
    proposal to issue the notification under sub‑section (1); or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  issue the 
    notification under sub‑section (1) with such modifications (if any) as it 
    thinks fit.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>4</number> The decision of the 
    State Government on the question of issuing the notification under 
    sub‑section (1) shall be final and conclusive.
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> Nothing contained in 
    any notification under sub‑section (1) shall affect any building, structure 
    or other work above ground or any alteration or extension thereof, if it was 
    constructed, erected, or executed before the date when notice of intention 
    to issue such a notification was given under sub‑section (2), and for the 
    purpose of this provision a building, structure, or other work and any 
    alteration or extension thereof shall be deemed to have been constructed, 
    erected or executed before that date—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  if its 
    construction, erection or execution was begun before that date, or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  if, and so far 
    as its construction, erection or execution was necessary for the purpose of 
    performing a contract made before that date.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>6</number> Any person whose 
    property is injuriously affected by the coming into force of a notification 
    under sub‑section (1) shall, subject to the provisions of section 27, be 
    entitled to obtain compensation in respect thereof from the State 
    Government.
 </section><section>

<number>27</number> Special provision 
    as to compensation under section 17.—(1) 
    No person shall be entitled to compensation under sub‑section (6) of section 
    17 unless, within three months from the date on which the notification 
    issued under sub‑section (1) of that section comes into force, or within 
    such further time as the State Government may in special circumstances 
    allow, he makes a claim for the purpose in such manner as may be prescribed 
    by the State.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> A person shall not 
    be entitled to compensation by reason of the fact that any act or thing done 
    or caused to be done by him has been rendered abortive by the notification 
    referred to in sub‑section (1) if or so far as the act or thing was done 
    after the date on which the notification was issued or by reason of the fact 
    that the performance of any contract made by him after that date is 
    prohibited on account of the notification.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Where any provision 
    of such notification was, immediately before the notification came into 
    force, already in force by virtue of any other enactment, no compensation 
    shall be payable by reason of any property being injuriously affected by 
    that provision if compensation therefor has been paid or could have been 
    claimed, or was not payable, under the provision before its inclusion in the 
    notification.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> Where any provision 
    of such notification could, immediately before it came into force, has been 
    validly included in a scheme, order, regulation or by‑law by virtue of any 
    other enactment, then—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  if no 
    compensation would have been payable by reason of the inclusion of that 
    provision in that scheme, order, regulation or bye‑law, no compensation 
    shall be payable in respect of that provision of the notification; and
    
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  if 
    compensation would have been so payable, the compensation payable in respect 
    of that provision of the notification shall not be greater than the 
    compensation which would have been so payable.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>5</number> Any dispute as to 
    the amount of the sum which is to be paid as compensation under sub‑section 
    (6) of section 17 shall be determined in accordance with the provisions of 
    section 26.
 

Madhya Pradesh
 

Section 16.—Same 
    as section 17 in Gujarat.
 

Section 27.—Same 
    as section 27 in Gujarat.
 

 
    Maharashtra
 

Section 17.—Same 
    as section 17 in Gujarat.
 

Section 29.—Same 
    as section 27 in Gujarat.
 

 
    Rajasthan
 

Section 19.—Same 
    as section 17 of Gujarat Act except that for sub‑section (6) of Gujarat read 
    the following:—
 

                     
    “(6) if any person contravenes any of the provisions of a notification 
    issued under sub-­section (1), he shall, on conviction, be punished with 
    fine not exceeding one hundred rupees for every day on which the 
    contravention occurs or continues.
 </section><section>

                     
    <number>7</number> if, after any person has been convicted under sub‑section (6) by reason 
    of the fact that any building, structure or other work is not in conformity 
    with the provisions of the notifica­tion issued under sub‑section (1), the 
    contravention continues after the expiration of such period as the Court 
    before whom he was convicted may determine, the State Government shall have 
    power to do all such acts as in its opinion are necessary for removing so 
    much of the building, structure or work as is not in conformity with the 
    provisions of the notification aforesaid for making it conform with the 
    provisions of the notification and any expenses incurred by the State 
    Government in so doing shall be recoverable as an arrear of land revenue 
    from the person convicted.”
</section>
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>16</number>
Relinquishment of Government right in a monument.—With the sanction 
    of the Government, the Director may,—
 
 <section>

<number>a</number>   where 
    rights have been acquired by the Director in respect of any monument under 
    this Act, by virtue of any sale, lease, gift or will, relinquish, by 
    notification, the rights so acquired to the person who would for the time 
    being be the owner of the monument if such rights had not been acquired; or
 </section><section>

<number>b</number>   
    relinquish any guardianship of a monument which he has assumed under this 
    Act.
 

[Madras—section 16; 
    Assam—section 16: Gujarat—section 18: Jammu and Kashmir—section 14; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 17; Maharashtra—section 18; Mysore—section 17; Orissa—section 
    14; Punjab—section 17; Rajasthan—section 16; Andhra Pradesh—section 17; West 
    Bengal—section 14.]
</section>

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>17</number> Right of access 
    to protected monuments.—Subject 
    to any rules made under this Act, the public shall have a right of access to 
    any protected monument.
 

[Madras—section 17; 
    Assam—section 17: Gujarat—section 19; Jammu and Kashmir—section 15; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 18; Maharashtra—section 19; Mysore—section 18; Orissa—section 
    15; Punjab—section 18; Rajasthan—section 20; Andhra Pradesh—section 18; West 
    Bengal—section 15.]
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>18</number> Restrictions on 
    enjoyment of property rights in protected areas.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No person, including the owner or occupier of a protected area, shall 
    construct any building within the protected area or carry on any mining, 
    quarrying, excavating, blasting, or any operation of a like nature in such 
    area, or utilise such area or any part thereof in any other manner without 
    the permission of the Government:
 

Provided that nothing 
    in this sub‑section shall be deemed to prohibit the use of any such area or 
    part thereof for purposes of cultivation if such cultivation does not 
    involve the digging of not more than 0.5 metre of soil from the surface.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The Government may, 
    by order, direct that any building constructed by any person within a 
    protected area in contravention of the provisions of sub‑section (1) shall 
    be removed within a specified period and, if the person refuses or fails to 
    comply with the order, the Director may cause the building to be removed and 
    the person shall be liable to pay the cost of such removal.
 

[Madras—section 18; 
    Gujarat—section 21; Madhya Pradesh—section 19; Maharashtra—section 21; 
    Mysore—section 20; Orissa—section 19; Punjab—section 19; Rajasthan—section 
    22; Andhra Pradesh—section 19.]
 



    State Amendments
 
 

Gujarat
 

 
  


</section><section>

<number>20</number> Power of State 
    Government to declare archaeological sites and remains to be protected 
    areas.—(1) 
    Where the State Government is of opinion that any archaeological site and 
    remains, not declared by or under any law made by Parliament to be of 
    national importance, should be a protected area, it may, by notification in 
    the official Gazette, give two months’ notice of its intention to declare 
    such archaeological site and remains to be a protected area, and a copy of 
    every such notification shall be affixed in a conspicuous place near the 
    site and remains.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> If any person 
    interested in any such archaeological site and remains has any objection to 
    the same being declared a protected area, he may, within two months of the 
    publication of the notification under sub‑section (1), submit his objection 
    in writing to the State Government.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> On the expiry of the 
    said period of two months, the State Government may, after considering the 
    objections, if any, received by it under sub‑section (2), declare by 
    notification in the official Gazette the archaeological site and remains to 
    be a protected area.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> A notification 
    published under sub‑section (3) shall, unless and until it is withdrawn, be 
    conclusive evidence of the fact that the archaeological site and remains to 
    which it relates is a protected area for the purposes of this Act.
 

Maharashtra
 

Section 20.—Same 
    as section. 20 of Gujarat.
 

Rajasthan
 </section></article><article>

<number>18</number> Power to control 
    mining, etc., near protected monuments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the State Government is of opinion that mining, quarrying, excavating, 
    blasting and other operations of a like nature should be restricted or 
    regulated for the purpose of protecting or preserving any protected 
    monument, the State Government may, by notification in the official Gazette, 
    make rules—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  fixing the 
    boundaries of the area to which the rules are to apply;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  forbidding the 
    carrying on of mining, quarrying, excavating, blasting or other opera­tions 
    of a like nature except in accordance with such rules and otherwise than 
    under and in accordance with terms of a licence; and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>  prescribing 
    the authority by which, and the terms on which licences may be granted to 
    carry on any of the said operations.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> A rule made under 
    this section may provide that any person committing a breach hereof shall be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees.
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>19</number> Power to acquire 
    a protected area.—If 
    the Government are of opinion that any protected area contains an ancient 
    monument or antiquities of regional interest and value, they may acquire 
    such area under the provisions of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 (Central 
    Act I of 1894), as if the acquisition were for a public purpose within the 
    meaning of that Act.
 

[Madras—section 19; 
    Gujarat—section 22; Jammu and Kashmir—section 20(c); Madhya Pradesh—section 
    20; Maharashtra—section 22; Mysore—section 21; Orissa—section 22; 
    Punjab—section 20; Rajasthan—section 21; West Bengal—section 19; Andhra 
    Pradesh—section 20.]
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>20</number> Excavations in 
    protected areas.—Subject 
    to the provisions of section 24 of the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological 
    Sites and Remains Act, 1958 (Central Act 24 of 1958), an archaeological 
    officer or an officer authorised by him in this behalf or any person holding 
    a licence granted in this behalf under this Act (hereafter in this Act 
    referred to as the licensee) may, after, giving notice in writing to the 
    Director and the owner, enter upon and make excavations in any protected 
    areas.
 

[Madras—section 20; 
    Jammu and Kashmir—section 20A; Madhya Pradesh—section 21; Maharashtra—section 
    23; Mysore—section 19; Orissa—section 20; Punjab—section 21; 
    Rajasthan—section 23; Andhra Pradesh—section 21.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>21</number> Excavation in 
    areas other than protected areas.—Subject 
    to the provisions of section 24 of the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological 
    Sites and Remains Act, 1959 (Central Act 24 of 1958), where an 
    archaeological officer has reason to believe that any area not being a 
    protected area, contains ruins or relics of historical or archaeological 
    importance, he or an officer authorised by him in this behalf may, after 
    giving notice in writing to the Director and the owner, enter upon and make 
    excavations in the area.
 

[Madras—section 21; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 22; Punjab—section 22.]
 



    State Amendments
 
 

West Bengal
 

 
  


</article><article>

<number>21</number> Power of State 
    Government to make rules regulating archaeological excavations in 
    State‑protected archaeological sites.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may make rules—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  prescribing 
    the authorities by whom licences to excavate for archaeological purposes in 
    a State‑protected site may be granted;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  regulating the 
    conditions on which such licences may be granted, the form of such licences, 
    and the taking of security from licensees;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>  prescribing 
    the manner in which antiquities found by a licensee shall be divided between 
    the State Government and the licensee; and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>  generally to 
    carry out the purposes of section 19.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> The power to make 
    rules given by this section is subject to the condition of the rules being 
    made after previous publication.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Such rules may be 
    general for all State‑protected archaeological sites for the time being, or 
    may be special for any particular protected site or sites.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> Such rules may 
    provide that any person committing a breach of any rule or of any condition 
    of a licence shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand 
    rupees and may further provide that, where the breach has been by the agent 
    or servant of a licensee the licensee himself shall be punishable.
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article><number>22</number> 
      Compulsory purchase of antiquities, etc., discovered during excavation 
      operations.—
<section><number>1</number> Where, as a 
      result of any excavations made in any area under section 20 or section 21, 
      any antiquities are discovered, the archaeological officer or the 
      licensee, as the case may be, shall,—
 
 <subsection><number>a</number>   as soon as 
        practicable, examine such antiquities and submit a report to the 
        Government in such manner and containing such particulars as may be 
        prescribed,
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   at the 
        conclusion of the excavation operations, give notice in writing to the 
        owner of the land from which such antiquities have been discovered, as 
        to the nature of such antiquities.</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Until 
      an order for the compulsory purchase of any such antiquities is made under 
      sub‑section (3), the archaeological officer or the licensee, as the case 
      may be, shall keep them in such safe custody as he may deem 
      fit.
 </section><section><number>3</number> On 
      receipt of a report under sub‑section (1), the Government may make an 
      order for the compulsory purchase of any such antiquities at their market 
      value.
 </section><section><number>4</number> When an 
      order for the compulsory purchase of any antiquities is made under 
      sub‑section (3), such antiquities shall vest in the Government with effect 
      from the date of the order.
 [Madras—section 22; Madhya Pradesh;—section 22; 
      Maharashtra—section 24; Mysore—section 23; Punjab—section 23; 
      Rajasthan—section 25; Andhra Pradesh—section 23.]
  State 
      Amendment
 
 Jammu 
        and Kashmir
 Archaeological 
        excavation
 
 
  </section><section><number>20</number> 
        Power of Government to notify Jammu and Kashmir areas as 
        protected.—(1) If the Government 
        is of opinion that excavation for archaeological purposes in any area 
        should be restricted or regulated in the interest of archaeological 
        research, the Government may, by notification in the Government Gazette 
        specifying the boundaries of the area, declare it to be a protected 
        area.
 </section><section><number>2</number> From 
        the date of such notification all antiquities buried in the protected 
        area shall be the property of Government and shall be deemed to be in 
        the possession of the Government and shall remain the property and in 
        the possession of the Government until ownership thereof is transferred; 
        but in all other respects the rights of any owner or occupier of land in 
        such area, shall not be affected.</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>22</number> Compulsory 
    purchase of antiquities, etc., discovered during excavation operations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where, as a result of any excavations made in any area under section 20 or 
    section 21, any antiquities are discovered, the archaeological officer or 
    the licensee, as the case may be, shall,—
 
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>   as soon 
    as practicable, examine such antiquities and submit a report to the 
    Government in such manner and containing such particulars as may be 
    prescribed,
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>   at the 
    conclusion of the excavation operations, give notice in writing to the owner 
    of the land from which such antiquities have been discovered, as to the 
    nature of such antiquities.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Until an order for 
    the compulsory purchase of any such antiquities is made under sub‑section 
    (3), the archaeological officer or the licensee, as the case may be, shall 
    keep them in such safe custody as he may deem fit.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> On receipt of a 
    report under sub‑section (1), the Government may make an order for the 
    compulsory purchase of any such antiquities at their market value.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> When an order for 
    the compulsory purchase of any antiquities is made under sub‑section (3), 
    such antiquities shall vest in the Government with effect from the date of 
    the order.
 

[Madras—section 22; 
    Madhya Pradesh;—section 22; Maharashtra—section 24; Mysore—section 23; 
    Punjab—section 23; Rajasthan—section 25; Andhra Pradesh—section 23.]
 



 
    State Amendment
 
 

Jammu and Kashmir
 



    Archaeological excavation
 

 
  


</section><section>

<number>20</number> Power of 
    Government to notify Jammu and Kashmir areas as protected.—(1) 
    If the Government is of opinion that excavation for archaeological purposes 
    in any area should be restricted or regulated in the interest of 
    archaeological research, the Government may, by notification in the 
    Government Gazette specifying the boundaries of the area, declare it to be a 
    protected area.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> From the date of 
    such notification all antiquities buried in the protected area shall be the 
    property of Government and shall be deemed to be in the possession of the 
    Government and shall remain the property and in the possession of the 
    Government until ownership thereof is transferred; but in all other respects 
    the rights of any owner or occupier of land in such area, shall not be 
    affected.
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>23</number> Excavation, 
    etc., for archaeological purposes.—Subject 
    to the provisions of section 20 and save as provided in sections 21 and 22, 
    no archaeological officer or other authority, shall undertake, or authorise 
    any person to undertake any excavation or other like operation for 
    archaeological purposes in any area which is not a protected area except 
    with the previous approval of the Government and in accordance with such 
    rules or directions, if any as the Government may make or give in this 
    behalf.
 

[Madras—section 23; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 24; Jammu and Kashmir—section 20B; Orissa—section 21; 
    Punjab—section 24; Rajasthan—section 24; West Bengal—section 20.]
 
 
 
 
 
 
 



    State Amendment





 

Rajasthan
 <section>

<number>26</number> Contraventions of 
    chapter.—Whoever 
    does any act in contravention of the provisions of this chapter for which 
    contravention no punishment is provided for elsewhere therein, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or 
    with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or with both.
 </section><section>

<number>27</number> Regulation of 
    excavations in protected areas.—(1) 
    The State Government may make rules—
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>  prescribing 
    the authorities by whom licences to excavate for archaeological and 
    his­torical purposes in a protected area may be granted;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>  regulating the 
    conditions on which such licences may be granted, the form of such licences 
    and the taking of security from licensees;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>  prescribing 
    the manner in which antiquities found by a licensee shall be disposed of; 
    and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>  generally to 
    carry out the purposes of this chapter.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>2</number> Such rules may be 
    general for all protected areas for the time being or may be special for any 
    particular protected area or areas and may provide that any person 
    committing a breach of any rule or of any condition of a licence shall be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, and may 
    further provide that, where the breach has been by the agent or servant of a 
    licensee, the licensee himself shall be punishable.
</section>
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>24</number>
Power of Government to control moving of antiquities.—
<section><number>1</number> If the 
    Government consider that any antiquities or class of antiquities ought not 
    to be moved from the place where they are without their sanction, the 
    Government may, by notification, direct that any such antiquity or any class 
    of such antiquities shall not be moved except with the written permission of 
    the Director.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Every application 
    for permission under sub‑section (1) shall be in such form and contain such 
    particulars as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Any person 
    aggrieved by an order refusing permission under sub‑section (1) may, appeal 
    to the Government within such time and in such manner as may be prescribed, 
    and the, decision of the Government shall be final.
 

[Madras—section 24; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 25; Gujarat—section 23; Jammu and Kashmir—section 18; 
    Madhya Pradesh—section 23; Maharashtra—section 25; Orissa—section 17; 
    Punjab—section 25; Rajasthan—section 28; West Bengal—section 17.]
 



 
    State Amendment
 
 

Jammu and Kashmir
 



    Traffic in antiquities
 
 


 
  


</section><section>

<number>17</number> Power of 
    Government to control traffic in antiquities.—(1) 
    If the Government apprehends that antiquities are being sold or removed to 
    the detriment of the State or of any neighbouring country, it, may, by 
    notification in the Government Gazette, prohibit or restrict the bringing or 
    taking of any antiquities or class of antiquities described in the 
    notification into or out of the State or any specified part of the State.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Any person who 
    brings or takes or attempts to bring or take any such antiquities into or 
    out of the State or any part of the State in contravention of a notification 
    issued under sub­-section (1), shall be punishable with fine which may 
    extend to five hundred rupees.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Antiquities in 
    respect of which an offence referred to in sub‑section (2) has been 
    committed shall be liable to confiscation.
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> A Revenue Officer 
    not lower in rank than a Naib‑Tahsildar, an Officer of Customs, or an 
    Officer of Police of a grade not lower than Assistant Inspector or Deputy 
    Inspector, duly empowered by the Government in this behalf, may search any 
    vessel, cart or other means of conveyance and may open any baggage or 
    package of goods, if he has reason to believe that goods in respect of which 
    an offence has been committed under sub‑section (2) are contained therein.
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> A person who 
    complains that the power of search mentioned in sub‑section (4) has been 
    vexatiously or improperly exercised may address his complaint to the 
    Government and the Government shall pass such order and may award such 
    compensation, if any, as appears to it to be just.
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>25</number> Purchase of 
    antiquities by Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Government are of opinion that any antiquity mentioned in a 
    notification issued under sub‑section (1) of section 24 is in danger of 
    being destroyed, removed, injured, misused or allowed to fall into decay or 
    that, by reason of its historical or archaeological importance, it is 
    desirable to preserve such antiquity in a public place, the Government may 
    make an order for the compulsory purchase of such antiquity at its market 
    value and the Director shall thereupon give notice to the owner of the 
    antiquity to be purchased.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Where a notice of 
    compulsory purchase is given under sub‑section (1) in respect of any 
    antiquity, such antiquity shall vest in the Government with effect from the 
    date of the notice.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The power of 
    compulsory purchase conferred by this section shall not extend to an image 
    or symbol actually used for bona fide religious observances.
 

[Madras—section 25; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 26; Gujarat—section 24; Jammu and Kashmir—section 19; 
    Madhya Pradesh—section 24; Maharashtra—section 26; Punjab—section 26; 
    Rajasthan—section 29; West Bengal—section 18.]
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>26</number>
Compensation for loss or damage.—Any owner or occupier of land who 
    has sustained any loss or damage or any diminution of profits from the land 
    by reason of any entry on, or excavations in, such land or the exercise of 
    any other power conferred by this Act shall be paid compensation by the 
    Government for such loss, damage or diminution of profits.
 

[Madras—section 26; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 27; Assam—section 18; Gujarat—section 25; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 25; Maharashtra—section 27; Punjab—section 27; Mysore—section 
    24; Orissa—section 18; Rajasthan—section 31.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>27</number> Assessment of 
    market value or compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The market value of any property which the Government is empowered to 
    purchase at such value under this Act, or the compensation to be paid by the 
    Government in respect of anything done under this Act, shall, where any 
    dispute arises in respect of such market value or compensation, be 
    ascertained in the manner provided in sections 3, 5, 8 to 34, 45 to 47, 51 
    and 52 of the Land Acquisition Act. 1894 (Central Act I of 1894), so far as 
    they can be made applicable.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub‑section (1) or in the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 
    (Central Act I of 1894), in determining the market value of any antiquity in 
    respect of which an order for compulsory purchase is made under sub‑section 
    (3) of section 22 or under sub‑section (1) of section 25, any increase in 
    the value of the antiquity by reason of its being of historical or 
    archaeological importance shall not be taken into consideration
 

[Madras—section 27; 
    Assam—section 19; Gujarat—section 26; Jammu and Kashmir—section 21; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 26; Maharashtra—section 28; Mysore—section 25; Orissa—section 
    23; Punjab—section 28; Rajasthan—section 32; Andhra Pradesh—section 28; West 
    Bengal—section 22.]
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>28</number> Delegation or 
    powers by the Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Government may, by notification, authorise any officer or authority 
    subordinate to them to exercise any one or more of the powers vested in them 
    by or under this Act; except the power to make rules under any of the 
    provisions of this Act, and may in like manner withdraw such authority.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The exercise of any 
    powers delegated under sub‑section (1) shall be subject to such restrictions 
    and conditions as may be prescribed or as may be specified in the 
    notification, and also to control and revision by the Government or by such 
    officer or authority subordinate to them as may be empowered by them in this 
    behalf. The Government shall also have power to control and revise the acts 
    or proceedings of any officer or authority so empowered.     
 

[Madras—section 28; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 29; Gujarat—section 29; Madhya Pradesh—section 28; 
    Maharashtra—section 31; Punjab—section 29: Rajasthan—section 33.]
 



 
    State Amendments
 
 

Gujarat
 



    Chapter Vi
 



    Miscellaneous
 
 


 
  


</section></article><article>

<number>28</number> State Advisory 
    Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    For the purpose of advising the State Government in the matter of the 
    preservation and maintenance of protected monuments and protected areas, and 
    such other matters incidental to the administration of this Act as may be 
    referred to it by the State Government, the State Government may constitute 
    a State Advisory Board under such name as it may specify.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The constitution of 
    the Advisory Board, the term of office of its members and the procedure 
    regarding its work, shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The members of the 
    Board shall be entitled to payment of such travelling allowance, as may be 
    prescribed.
 <subsection>

<number>Maharashtra</number>—Section 
    30.—Same as section 28 in Gujarat.
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>Rajasthan</number>—Section 
    30.—Same as section 28 in Gujarat omitting sub‑section (3). 

 

Gujarat
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>30</number> Power to issue 
    directions.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act, the State Government may from time to time 
    issue directions for the guidance of its officers in matters connected with 
    the administration of this Act, and the officers shall comply with such 
    directions
 <subsection>

Maharashtra.—Section 
    32.—Same as 
    section 30 in Gujarat.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>29</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whoever—
 
 <subsection>

<number>i</number>   
    destroys, removes, injures, alters, defaces, imperils or misuses a protected 
    monument, or encroaches upon or builds on such monument or site thereof, or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>   being 
    the owner or occupier of a protected monument, contravenes an order made 
    under sub‑section (1) of section 8 or under sub‑section (1) of section 9; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iii</number>   
    removes from a protected monument any sculpture, carving, image, bas‑relief, 
    in­scription or other like object, or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iv</number>   does 
    any act in contravention of sub‑section (1) of section 18, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months or 
    with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees or with both.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Any person who 
    moves any antiquity in contravention of a notification issued under 
    sub‑section (1) of section 24 shall be punishable with fine which may extend 
    to five thousand rupees; and the Court convicting a person of any such 
    contravention may, by order direct such person to restore the antiquity to 
    the place from which it was moved.
 

[Madras—section 29; 
    Assam—section 20; Gujarat—section 31; Jammu and Kashmir—section 16; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 29; Maharashtra—section 33; Mysore—section 26; Orissa—section 
    16; Punjab—section 30; Rajasthan—section 17; Andhra Pradesh—section 30; West 
    Bengal—section 16.]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>30</number> Jurisdiction of 
    criminal courts.—No 
    court inferior to that of a Presidency Magistrate or a Magistrate of the 
    first-class shall try any offence under this Act.
 

[Madras—section 30; 
    Assam—section 21; Gujarat—section 32; Jammu and Kashmir—section 22; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 30; Maharashtra—section 34; Mysore—section 27; Orissa—section 
    24; Punjab—section 31; Rajasthan—section 34; Andhra Pradesh—section 31; West 
    Bengal—section 23.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>31</number> Certain offences 
    to be cognizable.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (Central Act V of 
    1898), an offence under clause 
<section><number>i</number> or clause (iii) of sub-section (1) of 
    section 29, shall be deemed to be a cognizable offence within the meaning of 
    that Code.
 

[Madras—section 31; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 32; Assam—section 22; Gujarat—section 33; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 31; Maharashtra—section 35; Mysore—section 28; 
    Punjab—section 32; Rajasthan—section 35(a).]

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>32</number> Special Provision regarding fine.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in section 32 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 
    (Central Act V of 1898), it shall be lawful for any Magistrate of the first 
    class specially empowered by the Government in this behalf and for any 
    Presidency Magistrate to pass a sentence of fine exceeding two thousand 
    rupees on any person convicted of an offence which under this Act is 
    punishable with fine exceeding two thousand rupees.
 

[Madras—section 32; Andhra Pradesh—section 
    33; Gujarat—section 34; Madhya Pradesh—section 32; Maharashtra—section 36; 
    Punjab—section 33; Rajasthan—section 35(b).]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

33. 
    Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the person committing an offence under this Act is a company, the company 
    as well as every person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for 
    the conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence 
    shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
    proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 

Provided that nothing 
    contained in this sub‑section shall render any such person liable to any 
    punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge 
    or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
    offence.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in sub‑section (1), where an offence under this Act has 
    been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been 
    committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any 
    neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of 
    the company, such director, manager, secretary or, other officer shall also 
    be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
    against and punished accordingly.
 

Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of this section,—
 
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>   
    “company” means any body corporate, and includes a firm or other association 
    of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>   
    “director” in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>34</number> Recovery of 
    amounts due to the Government.—Any 
    amount due to the Govern­ment from any person under this Act may, on a 
    certificate issued by the Director or an archaeological officer authorised 
    by him in this behalf be recovered in the same manner as an arrear of land 
    revenue.
 

[Madras—section 34; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 34; Gujarat—section 35; Madhya Pradesh—section 33; 
    Maharashtra—section 37; Mysore—section 29; Punjab—section 34; 
    Rajasthan—section 36.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>35</number>
Ancient monuments, etc., no longer requiring protection.—If the 
    Government are of opinion that it is no longer necessary to protect any 
    ancient monument or archaeological site and remains under the provisions of 
    this Act, they may, by notification, declare that the ancient monument or 
    archaeological site and remains, as the case may be, has ceased to be a 
    protected monument or a protected area for the purpose of this Act.
 

[Madras—section 35; Andhra Pradesh—section 
    35; Gujarat—section 36; Madhya Pradesh—section 34; Maharashtra—section 38; 
    Punjab—section 35.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>36</number> Power to correct 
    mistakes, etc.—Any 
    clerical mistake, patent error or error arising from accidental slip or 
    omission in the description of any ancient monument or archaeological site 
    and remains declared to be a protected monument or a protected area under 
    this Act may, at any time, be corrected by the Government by notification.
 

[Madras—section 36; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 36; Assam—section 23; Gujarat—section 37; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 35; Maharashtra—section 39; Punjab—section 36]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>37</number> Protection of 
    action taken under the Act.—No 
    suit for compensation and no criminal proceeding shall lie against any 
    public servant in respect of any act which is in good faith done or intended 
    to be done in the exercise of any power conferred by this Act.       
 

[Madras—section 37; 
    Assam—section 24; Gujarat—section 38; Jammu and Kashmir—section 24; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 36; Maharashtra—section 40; Mysore—section 30; Orissa—section 
    26; Punjab—section 37; Rajasthan—section 37; Andhra Pradesh—section 37; West 
    Bengal—section 25.]

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>38</number> Power to make 
    rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Government may make rules io carry out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> in particular, and 
    without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
    provide for all or any of the following matters,  
    namely;—
 
 <subsection>

<number>a</number>   the 
    prohibition or regulation by licensing or otherwise of mining, quarrying, 
    excavat­ing, blasting or any operation of a like nature near a protected 
    monument or the construction of buildings on land adjoining such monument 
    and the removal of un­authorised buildings;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>b</number>   the 
    grant of licences and permissions to make excavations for archaeological 
    pur­poses in protected areas, the authorities by whom, and the restrictions 
    and condi­tions subject to which, such licences and permissions may be 
    granted, the taking of securities from licensees or holders of such 
    permissions and the fees that may be charged for such licences and 
    permissions;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>c</number>   the 
    right of access of the public to a protected monument and the fee, if any, 
    to be charged therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>d</number>   the 
    form and contents of the report of an archaeological officer or a licensee 
    under clause (a) of sub‑section (1) of section 22;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>e</number>   the 
    form in which an application for permission under section 18 or section 24 
    may be made and the particulars which such application shall contain;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>f</number>   the 
    form and manner of preferring appeals under this Act and the time within 
    which they may be preferred;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>g</number>   the 
    manner of service of any order or notice under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>h</number>   the 
    manner in which excavations and other like operations for archaeological 
    pur­poses may be carried on;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>i</number>   any 
    other matter which is to be or may be prescribed.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Any rule made under 
    this section may provide that a breach thereof shall be punishable,—
 
 <subsection>

<number>i</number>   in the 
    case of a rule made with reference to clause (a) of sub‑section (2), with 
    imprisonment for a term which may extend to three months, or with fine which 
    may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>   in the 
    case of a rule made with reference to clause (b) of sub‑section (2), with 
    fine which may extend to five thousand rupees;
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iii</number>   in 
    the case of a rule made with reference to clause (c) of sub‑section (2), 
    with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.
 

[Madras—section 38; 
    Assam—section 25; Gujarat—section 39; Jammu and Kashmir—section 23; Madhya 
    Pradesh—section 37; Maharashtra—section 41; Mysore—section 31; Orissa—section 
    25; Punjab—section 38; Rajasthan—section 38; Andhra Pradesh—section 38; West 
    Bangal—section 24.]
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article><number>39</number> Publication of rules, 
      commencement of rules and notifications and placing of rules and 
      notifications before the Legislature. —
<section><number>1</number> All rules made under 
      this Act shall be published in the Fort St. George Gazette, and, unless 
      they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, shall come into 
      force on the day on which they are so published.
 </section><section><number>2</number> All notifications 
      issued under this Act shall, unless they are expressed to come into force 
      on a particular day, come into force on the day on which they are 
      published.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made and 
      notification issued under this Act shall, as soon as possible, after it is 
      made or issued, be placed on the table of both Houses of the Legislature, 
      and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so placed or the 
      next session, both Houses agree in making any modification in any such 
      rule or notification, or both Houses agree that the rule or 
      notifi­cation should not be made or issued, the rule or notification 
      shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
      effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modifica­tion or 
      annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
      previously done under that rule or notification.
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>39</number> Publication of 
    rules, commencement of rules and notifications and placing of rules and 
    notifications before the Legislature. 
—
<section><number>1</number> All rules made 
    under this Act shall be published in the Fort St. George Gazette, and, 
    unless they are expressed to come into force on a particular day, shall come 
    into force on the day on which they are so published.
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> All notifications 
    issued under this Act shall, unless they are expressed to come into force on 
    a particular day, come into force on the day on which they are published.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> Every rule made and 
    notification issued under this Act shall, as soon as possible, after it is 
    made or issued, be placed on the table of both Houses of the Legislature, 
    and if, before the expiry of the session in which it is so placed or the 
    next session, both Houses agree in making any modification in any such rule 
    or notification, or both Houses agree that the rule or notifi­cation should 
    not be made or issued, the rule or notification shall thereafter have effect 
    only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so 
    however, that any such modifica­tion or annulment shall be without prejudice 
    to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or notification.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 <article></article><article>

<number>40</number> Repeals and 
    savings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any law corresponding to this Act in force in the added territories 
    immediately before the commencement of this Act, including the Andhra 
    Pradesh Ancient and Historical Monuments and Archaeological Sites and 
    Remains Act, 1960 (Andhra Pradesh Act VII of 1960) (hereafter in this 
    section referred to as the corresponding law), shall stand repealed on such 
    commencement,
 </section><section>

<number>2</number> The Ancient 
    Monuments Preservation Act, 1904 (Central Act VII of 1904), shall cease to 
    have effect in relation to ancient monuments and archaeological sites and 
    remains declared under this Act to be protected monuments or protected 
    areas, except as respects things done or omitted to be done before the 
    commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>

<number>3</number> The repeal by 
    sub‑section (1) of the corresponding law shall not affect—
 
 <subsection>

<number>i</number>   the 
    previous operation of the corresponding law or anything duly done or 
    suf­fered thereunder; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>   any 
    right, privilege, obligation or liability acquired, accrued or incurred 
    under the corresponding law; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>ii</number>   any 
    penalty, forfeiture or punishment incurred in respect of any offence 
    com­mitted against the corresponding law; or
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>iv</number>   any 
    investigation, legal proceeding or remedy in respect of any such right, 
    privilege, obligation, liability, penalty, forfeiture or punishment as 
    aforesaid; and any such investigation, legal proceeding or remedy may be 
    instituted, con­tinued or enforced and any such penalty, forfeiture or 
    punishment may be im­posed as if this Act had not been passed.
</subsection>
 </section><section>

<number>4</number> Notwithstanding the 
    repeal by sub‑section (1) of the corresponding law, all ancient monuments or 
    archaeological sites and remains declared to be protected monuments or 
    pro­tected areas under the corresponding law shall be deemed to be ancient 
    monuments or archaeological sites and remains declared to be protected 
    monuments or protected areas under this Act.
 </section><section>

<number>5</number> Subject to the 
    provisions of sub‑sections (3) and (4), anything done or any action taken 
    before the commencement of this Act under the corresponding law shall be 
    deemed to have been done or taken under this Act and shall continue to have 
    effect accordingly, unless and until superseded by anything done or any 
    action taken under this Act.
 </section><section>

<number>6</number> For the purpose of 
    facilitating the application of this Act in the added territories, any Court 
    or other authority may construe this Act with such alterations not affecting 
    the substance as may be necessary or proper to adapt it to the matter before 
    the Court or other authority.
 </section><section>

<number>7</number> Any reference to 
    the corresponding law in any law which continues to be in force in the added 
    territories after the commencement of this Act shall, in relation to those 
    territories, be construed as a reference to this Act.
 

Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this section, the expression “added territories” shall mean 
    the territories specified in the Second Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and 
    Madras. (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, 1959 (Central Act 56 of 1959).
 

[Madras—section 40; 
    Andhra Pradesh—section 39; Gujarat—section 41; Madhya Pradesh—section 38.]
 

 


    State Amendments
 
 

Gujarat
 
 


 
  


</section></article><article>

<number>40</number> Application of 
    certain other laws not barred.—Save 
    as expressly provided, the provisions of this Act, shall be in addition to 
    and not in derogation of the provisions of the Ancient Monuments and 
    Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, in so far as it relates to Entry 
    40 in List III in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution of India, or any 
    other law relating to that entry for the time being in force.
 <section>

<number>Maharashtra</number>—Section 
    42.—Same as section 40 of Gujarat.
 

Mysore
 <subsection>

<number>33</number>—Act in addition 
    to and not in derogation of Central Act 24 of 1958.—The 
    provisions of this Act shall be in addition and not in derogation, of the 
    provisions of the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and Remains 
    Act, 1958.
 

Gujarat
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>42</number> Act not 
    applicable to ancient monuments etc., of national importance.—(1) 
    Nothing in this Act shall apply to ancient and historical monuments, or 
    archaeological sites or remains, declared by or under any law made by 
    Parliament to be of national importance, or to any antiquities to which the 
    Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958, applies.
 </subsection><subsection>

<number>2</number> Where any ancient 
    and historical monument or any archaeological site and remains which is a 
    protected monument, or protected area, by or under the provisions of this 
    Act is declared at any time by or under any law made by Parliament to be of 
    national importance, the provisions of this Act shall cease to apply to such 
    monument or area; and accordingly, it shall cease to be a protected monument 
    or area for the purposes of this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>

<number>Maharashtra</number>—Section 
    44.—Same as section 42 of Gujarat.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>