<act><tid>251080</tid>
<title>THE CENTRAL LAWS (EXTENSION TO ARUNACHAL PRADESH) ACT, <year>1993</year></title>

ACT NO. 44 OF <year>1993</year> 
[ 27th May, <year>1993</year>.]
An Act to provide for the extension of certain Central laws to 
the 
State of Arunachal Pradesh.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-




<article><tid>835927</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>116160</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Central Laws (Extension to Arunachal Pradesh) Act <year>1993</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>703457</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Govern- 
ment may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>127534</tid>
<number>2</number>Extension of certain laws. The Acts mentioned in the Schedule 
and all rules, orders, regulations and schemes made thereunder are 
hereby extended to, and shall be in force in, the State of 
Arunachal Pradesh.

</article>



<article><tid>274861</tid>
<number>3</number>Construction of references to laws not in force in 
Arunachal Pradesh. Any reference in any Act, mentioned in the 
Schedule, to a law which is not in force in the State of Arunachal 
Pradesh shall, in relation to that State, be construed as a reference 
to the corresponding law, if any in force in that State.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 7. <year>1994</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 491 (E), dated 1. 7. <year>1994</year>.





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</article>



<article><tid>384285</tid>
<number>4</number>Construction of references to authorities where new 
authorities have been constituted. Any reference by whatever form of 
words in any law for the time being in force in the State of Arunachal 
Pradesh to any authority competent at the date of the passing of that 
law to exercise any powers or discharge any functions in that State 
shall, where a corresponding new authority has been constituted by or 
under any law now extended to that State, have effect as if it were a 
reference to the new authority.

</article>



<article><tid>257834</tid>
<number> 5</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>169293</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises  
in giving effect to the provisions of any Act now extended to the 
State of Arunachal Pradesh, the Central Government may, by order 
notified in the Official Gazette, make such provisions or give such 
directions as appear to it, necessary for the removal of the 
difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>778908</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, any such notified order may-

<subsection><tid>208243</tid>
<number>a</number>specify the corresponding authorities within the 
meaning of section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1189367</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for the transfer of any matter pending 
immediately before the commencement of this Act before any 
court, tribunal or other authority, to any corresponding 
court, tribunal or other authority for disposal:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of 
two years from the date of commencement of this Act.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1968230</tid>
<number>3</number>Every order made under this section shall be laid before 
each House of Parliament.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>