<act><title>

the indian wireless 
    telegraphy act, 1933</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Indian Wireless Telegraphy Act, 1933.
 

2[(2) 
    It extends to the whole of India] 
3[***].2[(2) 
    It extends to the whole of India] 
3[***]."
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date4
    as the Central Government may, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.4
    as the Central Government may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, appoint." 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— 
 


    1[
<section><number>1</number>   “wireless 
    communication” means any transmission, omission or reception of signs, 
    signals, writing, images and sounds, or intelligence of any nature by means 
    of electricity, magnetism, or Radio waves or Hertzian waves, without the use 
    of wires or other continuous electrical conductors between the transmitting 
    and the receiving apparatus.
 

    Explanation.—“Radio waves” or 
    “Hertzian waves” means electromagnetic waves of frequencies lower than 3,000 
    gigacycles per second propagated in space without artificial guide;]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>   
    “wireless telegraphy apparatus” means any apparatus, appliance, instrument 
    or material used or capable of use in wireless communication, and includes 
    any article determined by rule made under section 10 to be wireless 
    telegraphy apparatus, but does not include any such apparatus, appliance, 
    instrument or material commonly used for other electrical purposes, unless 
    it has been specially designed or adapted for wireless communication or 
    forms part of some apparatus, appliance, instrument or material specially so 
    designed or adapted, nor any article determined by rule made under section 
    10 not to be wireless telegraphy apparatus; 


    2[***]
 


    3[2A]   “wireless 
    transmitter” means any apparatus, appliance, instrument or material used or 
    capable of use for transmission or emission of wireless communication;]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>   
    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under section 10.
 
 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Prohibition of possession of wireless 
    telegraphy apparatus without license.—Save as provided by section 4, no 
    person shall possess wireless telegraphy apparatus except under and in 
    accordance with a license issued under this Act. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Licenses.—The telegraph authority 
    constituted under the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885), shall be the 
    authority competent to issue licenses to possess wireless telegraphy 
    apparatus under this Act, and may issue licenses in such manner, on such 
    conditions and subject to such payments as may be prescribed. 
  


 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Offence and penalty.—
<section><number>1</number> Whoever 
    possesses any 
1[wireless 
    telegraphy apparatus, other than a wireless transmitter,] in contravention 
    of the provisions of section 3 shall be punished, in the case of the first 
    offence, with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, and, in the case 
    of a second or subsequent offence, with fine which may extend to two hundred 
    and fifty rupees.
1[wireless 
    telegraphy apparatus, other than a wireless transmitter,] in contravention 
    of the provisions of section 3 shall be punished, in the case of the first 
    offence, with fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, and, in the case 
    of a second or subsequent offence, with fine which may extend to two hundred 
    and fifty rupees." 
 

2[(1A) 
    Whoever possesses any wireless transmitter in contravention of the 
    provisions of section 3 shall be punished with imprisonment which may extend 
    to three years, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
    with both.]2[(1A) 
    Whoever possesses any wireless transmitter in contravention of the 
    provisions of section 3 shall be punished with imprisonment which may extend 
    to three years, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
    with both.]" 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of this section a Court 
    may presume that a person possesses wireless telegraphy apparatus if such 
    apparatus is under his ostensible charge, or is located in any premises or 
    place over which he has effective control. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If in the trial of an offence under this 
    section the accused is convicted the Court shall decide whether any 
    apparatus in respect of which an offence has been committed should be 
    confiscated, and, if it so decides, may order confiscation accordingly.
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>

1[<number>7</number> 
    Power of search.—Any officer specially empowered2
    by the Central Government in this behalf may search 
    any building, vessel or place in which he has reason to believe that any 
    wireless telegraphy apparatus, in respect of which an offence punishable 
    under section 6 has been committed, is kept or concealed, and take 
    possession thereof.]1[7. 
    Power of search.—Any officer specially empowered2
    by the Central Government in this behalf may search 
    any building, vessel or place in which he has reason to believe that any 
    wireless telegraphy apparatus, in respect of which an offence punishable 
    under section 6 has been committed, is kept or concealed, and take 
    possession thereof.]" 
 
 
 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Apparatus confiscated or having no owner 
    to be property of Central Government.—All wireless telegraphy apparatus 
    confiscated under the provisions of sub-section (3) of section 6, and all 
    wireless telegraphy apparatus having no ostensible owner shall be the 
    property of the Central Government. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power of Court to direct payment of 
    fines to prescribed authority.—[Ceased to have effect by the A.O. 
    1937 and rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1940 (32 of 1940), sec. 2 
    and Sch. I]. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Power of Central Government to make 
    rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, make rules1
    for the purpose of carrying into 
    effect the provisions of this Act.3
    for the purpose of carrying into effect 
    the provisions of this Act." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and without prejudice to the 
    generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    determining that any article or class of article shall be or shall not be 
    wireless telegraphy apparatus for the purposes of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the 
    exemption of persons or classes of persons under section 4 from the 
    provisions of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the 
    manner of and the conditions governing the issue, renewal, suspension and 
    cancellation of licenses, the form of licenses and the payments to be made 
    for the issue and renewal of licenses;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the 
    maintenance of records containing details of the acquisition and disposal by 
    sale or otherwise of wireless telegraphy apparatus possessed by dealers in 
    wireless telegraphy apparatus;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   the 
    conditions governing the sale of wireless telegraphy apparatus by dealers in 
    and manufacturers of such apparatus. 


    2[***]
 

2[***] 4[***]" 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In making a rule under this section the 
    Central Government may direct that a breach of it shall be punishable with 
    fine which may extend to one hundred rupees. 
 

3[(4) 
    Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it 
    is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
4[in 
    two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], 
    both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
    agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
    effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
    so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.1[(4) 
    Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it 
    is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 
2[in 
    two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], 
    both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses 
    agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have 
    effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
    so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule." 
 
 
 
 







 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number> Saving of Indian Telegraph 
      Act, 1885.—Nothing in this Act contained shall authorise the doing of 
      anything prohibited under the Indian Telegraph Act, 1885 (13 of 1885), and 
      no license issued under this Act shall authorise any person to do anything 
      for the doing of which a license or permission under the Indian Telegraph 
      Act, 1885 (13 of 1885), is necessary. 
  
  
 
  </article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>