<act><tid>258943</tid>
<title>THE CRIMINAL LAW AMENDMENT ACT, <year>1961</year></title>

ACT NO. 23 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 17th May, <year>1961</year>.]

An Act to supplement the criminal law.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1597624</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1007543</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and extent. This Act may be called the  
Criminal Law Amendment Act, <year>1961</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1563965</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>496978</tid>
<number> 2</number> Questioning the territorial integrity or frontiers of India 
in a manner prejudicial to the interests of safety and security of 
India.
<section><tid>982044</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever by words either spoken or written, or by signs, or  
by visible representation or otherwise, questions the territorial 
integrity or frontiers of India in a manner which is, or is likely to 
be, prejudicial to the interests of the safety or security of India, 
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
three years, or with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>1615680</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Whoever publishes a map of India, which is not in conformity 
with the maps of India as published by the Survey of India, shall be 
punishable with imprisonment which may be extend to six months, or 
with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>583874</tid>
<number>3</number>No court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under 
sub- section (2), except on a complaint made by the Government.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1211562</tid>
<number> 3</number> Statements, etc., in a notified area prejudicial to 
maintenance of public order, etc., therein or to safety or security of 
India and regulation entry of persons in such area.
<section><tid>1781203</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central  
Government considers that in the interests of the safety or security 
of India or in the public interest, it is necessary or expedient so to 
do, it may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare any area 
adjoining the frontiers of India to be a notified area; and 
thereupon, for so long as the notification is in force, such area 
shall be a notified area for the purposes of this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1898840</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever makes, Publishes or circulates in any notified area 
any statement, rumour or report which is, or is likely to be, preju- 
dicial to the maintenance of public order or essential supplies or 
services in the said area or to the interests of the safety or 
security of India, shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to three years, or with fine, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>1337308</tid>
<number>3</number>On and after such day as may be specified in, and subject to 
any exemptions for which provision may be made by, a notification 
issued under sub- section (1), no person who was not immediately before 
the said day a resident in the area declared to be a notified area by 
the notification shall enter or attempt to enter that area or be 
therein except in accordance with the terms of a permit in writing 
granted to him by a person, not below the rank of a magistrate of the 
first class, specified in the said notification.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>756</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Renumbered and ins. by Act 9 of <year>1990</year>, S. 2.

Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli 
 (w. e. f. 1. 7. 65) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, S. 2 and Sch. I.

Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of 
<year>1962</year>, S. 3 and Sch.

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 
of <year>1963</year>, S. 3 and Sch.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>883070</tid>
<number>4</number>Any police officer, not below the rank of sub- inspector of 
police, may search any person entering or attempting to enter, or 
being in, or leaving, a notified area and any vehicle, vessel, animal 
or article brought in by such person, and may, for the purpose of the 
search, detain such person, vehicle, vessel, animal or article:
Provided that no woman shall be searched in pursuance of this 
sub- section except by a woman authorised in this behalf by the police 
officer.


</section>

<section><tid>847595</tid>
<number>5</number>If any person is in a notified area in contravention of the 
provisions of sub- section (3), then, without prejudice to any other 
proceedings which may be taken against him, he may be removed therefrom 
by or under the direction of any police officer on duty in the 
notified area, not below the rank of sub- inspector of police.

</section>

<section><tid>1606916</tid>
<number>6</number>If any person enters or attempts to enter a notified area or 
is therein in contravention of any of the provisions of sub- section 
 (3), he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to one year, or with fine, or with both.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>852691</tid>
<number> 4</number> Power to declare certain publications forfeited and to 
issue search warrants for the same.
<section><tid>1201958</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any newspaper or book as  
defined in the Press and Registration of Books Act, <year>1867</year> (25 of <year>1867</year>), 
or any other document, wherever printed, appears to the State 
Government to contain any matter the publication of which is 
punishable under section 2 or sub- section (2) of section 3, the State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, stating the 
grounds of its opinion, declare every copy of the issue of the 
newspaper containing such matter and every copy of such book or other 
document to be forfeited to the Government, and thereupon any police 
officer may seize the same wherever found and any magistrate may by 
warrant authorise any police officer not below the rank of sub- 
inspector to enter upon and search for the same in any premises where 
any copy of such issue or any copy of such book or other document may 
be or may be reasonably suspected to be.

</section>

<section><tid>1044508</tid>
<number>2</number>The powers conferred by sub- section (1) on the State Govern- 
ment may also be exercised by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>154811</tid>
<number>3</number>In sub- section (1)" document" includes also any painting, 
drawing or photograph, or other visible representation.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>313868</tid>
<number> 5</number> Application to High Court to set aside order of 
forfeiture.
<section><tid>505689</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person having any interest in any newspaper, book  
or other document in respect of which an order of forfeiture has been 
made under section 4 may, within two months from the date of such 
order, apply to the High Court to set aside such order on the round 
that the issue of the newspaper or the book or other

<pagefootnote><pagenum>757</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

document in respect of which the order was made did not contain any 
matter of such a nature as is referred to in sub- section (1) of 
section 4.


</section>

<section><tid>1098329</tid>
<number>2</number>The provisions of sections 99C to 99F of the Code of 
Criminal Procedure, <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>), shall apply in relation to an 
application under subsection (1) as they apply in relation to an 
application under section 99B of that Code and the reference in 
section 99D to seditious or other matter of such a nature as is 
referred to in sub- section (1) of section 99A of that Code shall be 
construed as a reference to any matter of such a nature as is referred 
to in sub- section (1) of section 4 of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>737983</tid>
<number>3</number>No order passed or action taken under section 4 shall be 
called in question in any court otherwise than in accordance with the 
provisions of this section.


</section>

</article>



 </act>