<act><tid>265110</tid>
<title>THE AGRICULTURAL PRODUCE CESS ACT, <year>1940</year></title>

ACT NO. 27 OF <year>1940</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 15th April, <year>1940</year>.]

An Act to make better financial provision for <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Indian Council of 
Agricultural Research].





<article><tid>1649268</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1393897</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Agricultural Produce Cess Act, <year>1940</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1893911</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>584179</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1405776</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>" Collector" means a Collector of Customs as defined 
in clause (8) of section 2 of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>; 
 (52 of <year>1962</year>.) and]

</section>

<section><tid>1301894</tid>
<number>b</number>" Council" means <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the Indian Council of Agricultural 
Research].



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1189098</tid>
<number> 3</number> Imposition of cess.
<section><tid>204485</tid>
<number>1</number>A customs duty at the rate of one- half  
of one per cent. ad valorem shall be levied on all articles included 
in the Schedule which are exported from <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> India]:
Provided that the said duty shall not be levied on articles 
proved to the satisfaction of the Collector not to have been produced 
in India.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>40</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Extended to Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>. 
Extended to the Union territory of Goa, Daman and Diu, vide 
Notfn. No. G. S. R. 504 (E), dated 21. 6. <year>1985</year>, Gaz. of India, Exty. 
pt. II sec. 3 (i). 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" the Imperial Council of 
Agricultural Research". 
3 The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
62 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1956</year>). 
4 Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1970</year>, s. 2, for cl. (a). 
5 Subs. by Act 62 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2 and Sch., for" the territories to 
which this Act extends".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>391489</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> notification in the 
Official Gazette, fix for the purposes of levying the said duty tariff 
values of any articles included in the Schedule, and may alter any 
tariff values for the time being in force.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>482519</tid>
<number>4</number>Power to exclude articles from Schedule. The Central 
Government may after previous consultation with the Council, by <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
notification in the Official Gazette, direct that any article 
specified in the Schedule shall cease to be subject to the duty 
imposed by section 3, and thereupon, so long as the notification 
remains in force, that article shall be deemed not to be included in 
the Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>202400</tid>
<number> 5</number> Refund of, and exemption from cess. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The Central Board of 
Excise and Customs constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue 
Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>.)] may make <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> rules providing, on such 
conditions as may be specified, in the rules, for--
<section><tid>1289988</tid>
<number>a</number>the refund of duty levied where articles are exported by 
land and subsequently imported into India, and

</section>

<section><tid>1438595</tid>
<number>b</number>the export by land, without payment of the duty of 
articles, which are subsequently to be imported into 
India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1178589</tid>
<number>5A</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Certain provisions of the Customes Act, <year>1962</year> to apply. The 
provisions of the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>.) and the rules and 
regulations made thereunder, including those relating to refunds and 
exemptions from duty, shall so far as may be, apply in relation to the 
levy and collection of customs duty on all articles included in the 
Schedule as they apply in relation to the levy and collection of duty 
payable to the Central Government under that Act.


</article>



<article><tid>561086</tid>
<number> 5B</number> Penalties.
<section><tid>759271</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever-- 

<subsection><tid>92347</tid>
<number>a</number>evades the payment of any customs duty under this Act, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>78418</tid>
<number>b</number>fails to furnish any information which it is his duty to 
furnish or furnishes information which is false in 
material particulars or which he does not believe to be 
true, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1771870</tid>
<number>c</number>obstructs the Collector or any other officer in the 
performance of his duties under this Act or any rules 
made thereunder,
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or 
with both.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>41</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For such notification, see Gazette of India, <year>1947</year>, Extraordinary, 
p. 611. 
2 For such notification, see Gazette of India, <year>1940</year>, Pt. I, p. 
1323. 
3 Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1970</year>, s. 3, for" The Central Board of 
Revenue". 
4 For such rules, see Gazette of India, <year>1940</year>, Pt. I, p. 565. 
5 Ins. by Act 40 of <year>1970</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1236408</tid>
<number>2</number>Any court trying an offence under this Act may direct that 
any article specified in the Schedule in respect of which it is 
satisfied that an offence punishable under this Act has been committed 
shall be forfeited to the Central Government and may also direct that 
all packages, coverings or receptacles in which such article is 
contained and every vessel or other conveyance used in carrying such 
article shall be forfeited to the Central Government.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>913589</tid>
<number> 6</number> Payment of cess to Council and expenditure of cess by Council.

<section><tid>130111</tid>
<number>1</number>The proceeds of the duty levied under this Act reduced by the cost  
of collection as determined by the Central Government shall be paid to 
the Council.

</section>

<section><tid>1862058</tid>
<number>2</number>The amount so due shall be paid by the Central Government to 
the Council at intervals of not more than six months.

</section>

<section><tid>1912217</tid>
<number>3</number>The expenditure of the money so paid to the Council shall be 
subject to such limitation as may be imposed by rules made in this 
behalf by the Central Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1113493</tid>
<number> 7</number> Standing Finance Committee.
<section><tid>383672</tid>
<number>1</number>The Council shall constitute a  
Standing Finance Committee, of which one member shall be chosen among 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the Members of Parliament] on the governing body of the Council, 
and one member shall be an officer appointed by the Central 
Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1936738</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1) the 
constitution, functions and procedure of the Standing Finance 
Committee shall be regulated in such manner as the Council may with 
the previous approval of the Central Government determine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>271644</tid>
<number>8</number>Reserve fund. The Council shall in accordance with the rules 
made in this behalf by the Central Government create and maintain a 
reserve fund.


</article>



<article><tid>18382</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.
<section><tid>1807592</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, after consultation with the Council, by notification 
in the Official Gazette, make <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> rules to carry out the purposes of 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1203635</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, the Central Government may make rules regulating the 
expenditure of the money paid to the Council under section 6 and 
providing for the creation, maintenance and management of the reserve 
fund referred to in section 8.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>42</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 40 of <year>1970</year>, s. 5, for" the representatives of the 
Central Legislature". 
2 For such rules see Gazette of India, <year>1940</year>, Pt. I, p. 1353.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>481903</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is 
in session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
of the session in which it is so laid or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]


</section>

</article>



 </act>