<act><tid>26828</tid>
<title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> THE STAGE- CARRIAGES ACT, <year>1861</year>]</title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1861</year> 
[ 7the July, <year>1861</year>.]
An Act for licensing and regulating Stage- Carriages.

Preamble.- WHEREAS it is expedient to licence and to regulate 
stage- carriages in the Provinces; It is enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1233265</tid>
<number>1</number>Definition of stage- carriage.-- Every carriage drawn by one or 
more <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> horses which shall ordinarily be used for the purpose of 
conveying passengers for hire to or from any place in the Stats, 
shall, without regard to the form or construction of such carriage, be 
deemed to be a stage- carriage within the meaning of this Act.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>1553877</tid>
<number>2</number>Carriages to be licensed.-- No carriage shall be used as a 
stage- carriage unless licensed by a <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Magistrate or by the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> 
Commissioner of Police of a Presidency- town.


</article>



<article><tid>1981</tid>
<number>3</number>Power to refuse license.-- The Magistrate or <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Commissioner 
of Police to whom the application for a license of a stage- carriage is 
made may refuse to license the same, if he shall be of opinion that 
such stage- carriage is unserviceable or is unsafe or unfit for public 
accommodation or use.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>236</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Indian Short Titles Act, <year>1897</year> (14 of  
  <year>1897</year>).

This Act, as amended by the Stage- Carriages Act (1861) Amendment 
Act, <year>1898</year> (1 of <year>1898</year>), has been declared to apply to all the States of 
India, but not so as to supersede or contravene provisions of local 
laws dealing with the same subject- see s. 22. For local laws, see the 
Bombay Public Conveyance Act, <year>1920</year> (Bom. 7 of <year>1920</year>), the Madras 
Hackney Carriage Act, <year>1911</year> (Mad. 5 of <year>1911</year>), and the Calcutta Hackney 
Carriage Act, <year>1919</year> (Ben. 1 of <year>1919</year>), cf. also the Hackney Carriage 
Act, <year>1879</year> (14 of <year>1879</year>).

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Scheduled Districts Act, <year>1874</year> (14 of <year>1874</year>), to be in force in the 
following Scheduled Districts, namely:-

The Districts of Hazaribagh, Lohardaga (now the Ranchi  
  District, see Calcutta Gazette, <year>1899</year>, Pt. I, p. 44) and Manbhum, 
and Pargana Dhalbhum and the Kolhan in the District of Singh- 
bhum...... See Gazette of India, <year>1881</year>, Pt. I, p. 504.

The Tarai of the Province of Agra.. Ditto <year>1876</year>, Pt. I, p. 595.

It has been declared, by notification under s. 3 (a) of the 
Sonthal Parganas Justice and Laws Regulation,

The Act has been amended in Himachal Pradesh by Himachal Pradesh 
Act 3 of <year>1974</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>All expressions and provisions in this Act applied to horses, 
also apply to all other animals employed in drawing stage- 
carriages, see section 21, infra.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Proviso to s. 1 which read:" Provided that this Act shall not 
apply to carriages not ordinarily used for journey of a greater 
distance than twenty miles" rep. by Act 1 of <year>1898</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>For definition of" Magistrate", see s. 21, infra.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>The word" Chief" rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


Particulars of license.-- If a Magistrate or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner of 
Police as aforesaid shall grant a license, the license shall set forth 
the number thereof, the name and residence of the proprietor of the 
stage- carriage, the place at which his head office is held, the 
largest number of passengers and the greatest weight of luggage to be 
carried in or on such carriage, the number of horses by which such 
carriage is to be drawn, and the name of the place at which such 
carriage is licensed.



</article>



<article><tid>80341</tid>
<number>4</number>Charge for and duration of license.-- <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> For every such 
license there shall be paid by the proprietor of the stage- carriage 
the sum of five rupees or such less sum as the State Government may 
fix, and such license shall be in force for one year from the date 
thereof.]
When a licensed stage- carriage is transferred to a new proprietor 
within the year, the name of such new proprietor shall, on application 
to that effect, be substituted in the license for the name of the 
former proprietor without any further payment for that year; and every 
person who appears by the license to be the proprietor, shall be 
deemed to be such proprietor for all the purposes of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>1624045</tid>
<number>5</number>Particulars to be painted on conspicuous part of carriage.-- On 
any stage- carriage being licensed, the proprietor thereof shall cause 
the number of the license and all the other particulars of the license 
to be distinctly painted in the English language and character upon a 
conspicuous part of such stage- carriage.


</article>



<article><tid>1654086</tid>
<number>6</number>Penalty for letting carriage without having particulars 
painted.-- The proprietor of any licensed stage- carriage who shall let 
such stage- carriage for hire without the particulars specified in 
section 3 being painted on such carriage in the manner directed in the 
last preceding section, shall be liable to a fine not exceeding one 
hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>297110</tid>
<number>7</number>Penalty for letting for hire unlicensed carriage.-- Whoever 
lets for hire any stage- carriage without the same being licensed as 
provided by this Act, shall be liable, on a first conviction, to a 
fine not exceeding one hundred rupees, and on any subsequent 
conviction, to a fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1116318</tid>
<number>8</number>Penalty for allowing carriage to be drawn by fewer animals or 
more passengers, etc., to be carried than provided by license.-- Any 
proprietor, or agent of a proprietor, or any driver of a licensed 
stage- carriage, who, knowingly permits such carriage to be drawn by a 
less number of harses or who knowingly permits a larger number of 
passengers, or a greater weight of luggage, to be carried by such 
stage- carriage than shall be provided by the license, shall be liable 
on a first conviction to a fine not exceeding one hundred rupees, and 
on any subsequent conviction, to a fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees.
In every case where such stage- carriage shall be proved to have 
been drawn by a less number of horses, or to have carried a larger 
number of passengers or a greater weight of luggage, than shall be 
provided by the license, the proprietor of such carriage shall be held 
to have knowingly permitted such offence, unless he shall prove that 
the offence was not committed with his connivance, and that he had 
taken every reasonable precaution and had made reasonable provision to 
prevent the commission of the offence.



</article>



<article><tid>1229614</tid>
<number>9</number>Penalty for ill- treating animals.-- Any person who shall 
cruelly beat, ill- treat, over- drive, abuse, torture or cause or 
procure to be cruelly beaten, ill- treated, overdrive, abused or 
tortured any horse employed in drawing or harnessed to any stage- 
carriage, or who shall harness to or drive in any stage- carriage any 
horse which from sickness, age, wounds or other cause is unfit to be 
driven in such stage- carriage, shall for every such offence be liable 
to a fine not exceeding one hundred rupees.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>237</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" Chief" rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1898</year>, s. 3, for the original paragraph.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>716537</tid>
<number>10</number>Revocation of license.-- Any Magistrate or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner 
of Police within the local limits of whose jurisdiction any stage- 
carriage shall ply, or who has granted the license of any stage- 
carriage, may cancel the license of such stage- carriage if it shall 
appear to him that such stage- carriage or any horse or any harness 
used with such carriage is unserviceable or unsafe or otherwise unfit 
for public accommodation or use.


</article>



<article><tid>588700</tid>
<number>11</number>Penalty for not conforming to provisions of section 5.-- In 
any station or place in which a Magistrate shall reside and be, any 
police- officer may, in any place within two miles of the office of 
such Magistrate, seize any stage- carriage with the horse harnessed 
thereto, if the full particulars of the license of such stage- carriage 
be not distinctly painted on such stage- carriage in the manner 
provided in section 5 of this Act.
Such carriage with the horse harnessed thereto shall be taken 
without delay by such police- officer before such Magistrate, who shall 
forthwith proceed to hear and determine the complaint of such police- 
officer; and, if thereupon any fine is imposed by such Magistrate and 
such fine is paid, such stage- carriage and horse shall be immediately 
released; and if such fine be not paid, such stage- carriage and horse 
may be detained for twenty days as security for the payment thereof; 
and if the fine be not sooner paid, they may be sold and the proceeds 
applied (so far as they extend) to the payment of the said fine, and 
all costs and charges incurred on account of the detention and sale; 
and the surplus (if any), when claimed, shall be paid to the 
proprietor of such carriage and horse; and if such surplus be not 
claimed within a further period of two months from such sale, the same 
shall be forfeited to the State.

If the proceeds of such sale do not fully pay the fine and costs 
and charges aforesaid, the balance may be recovered as hereinafter 
provided.



</article>



<article><tid>879821</tid>
<number>12</number>Penalty for misconduct on part of drivers.-- If any driver of 
any stage- carriage, or any other person having the care thereof, 
shall, through intoxication, neglect, or by wanton or furious driving, 
or by any other misconduct, endanger the safety of any passenger or 
other person, or shall injure or endanger the property of the 
proprietor of such stage- carriage or of any other person, every such 
person so offending shall be liable to a fine not exceeding one 
hundred rupees.


</article>



<article><tid>1519462</tid>
<number>13</number>Penalty when recoverable from proprietor.-- Whenever the 
driver of any stage- carriage or the owner of any horse employed in 
drawing any stage- carriage shall have committed any offence against 
this Act for the commission whereof any penalty is by this Act 
imposed, other than an offence specified in section 8, and such driver 
or owner shall not be known, or being known cannot be found, or if the 
penalty cannot be recovered from such driver or owner, the proprietor 
of such carriage shall be liable to every such penalty as if he had 
been the driver of such carriage or owner of such horse at the time 
when such offence was committed:
Proviso.-- Provided that if any such proprietor shall make out, to 
the satisfaction of the Magistrate before whom any complaint or 
information shall be heard, by sufficient evidence, that the offence 
was committed by such driver or owner without the privity or knowledge 
of such proprietor, and that no profit, advantage, or benefit, either 
directly or indirectly, has accrued or can accrue to such proprietor 
therefrom, and that he has used his endeavour to find out such driver 
or owner, and has done all that was in his power to recover the amount 
of the penalty from him, the Magistrate may discharge the proprietor 
from such penalty, and shall levy the same upon such driver or owner 
when found.



</article>



<article><tid>1555197</tid>
<number>14</number>Issue of summons.-- Whenever any charge is made before any 
Magistrate of any offence under this Act on which it is necessary to 
issue a summons to the proprietor of a stage- carriage, the Magistrate 
shall issue such summons directed to such proprietor or his nearest 
agent, and may transmit such summons by letter- post, which shall be 
deemed to be good service thereof.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>238</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" Chief" rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


The letter shall be registered at the post- office, and the cost 
of the registration shall be born by the Government in the first 
instance, but may be charged as costs in the case.

The summons shall allow a reasonable time, in reference to the 
distance to which the summons is sent, for the appearance of such 
proprietor or his agent as aforesaid.



</article>



<article><tid>1400496</tid>
<number>15</number>Adjudication of penalties.-- All penalties incurred under this 
Act shall be adjudged by a Magistrate or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner of Police 
as aforesaid, and all orders made under this Act by such Magistrate or 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner of Police shall be final.


</article>



<article><tid>1177040</tid>
<number>16</number>Recovery of penalties etc.-- All penalties imposed under this 
Act, or any balance of any fine, costs, or charges as mentioned in 
section 11 of this Act, may in case of non- payment or non- recovery 
thereof be levied by distress and sale of the movable property of the 
offender by warrant under the hand of the Magistrate who imposed the 
same.


</article>



<article><tid>1477005</tid>
<number>17</number>Offender may be apprehended and detained in custody until 
return of warrant of distress.-- In case any such penalties shall not 
be forthwith paid, such Magistrate may order the offender to be 
apprehended and detained in safe custody until the return can be 
conveniently made to such warrant of distress, unless the offender 
shall give security to the satisfaction of such Magistrate for his 
appearance at such place and time as shall be appointed for the return 
of the warrant of distress.


</article>



<article><tid>1241529</tid>
<number>18</number>Imprisonment of offender if distress not sufficient.-- If upon 
the return of such warrant it shall appear that no sufficient distress 
can be had whereon to levy such penalty, and the same shall not be 
forthwith paid, or in case it shall appear to the satisfaction of such 
Magistrate by the confession of the offender or otherwise that he has 
not sufficient goods and chattels whereupon such penalty could be 
levied if warrant of distress were issued, such Magistrate may, by 
warrant under his hand, commit the offender <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to prison, there to 
be imprisoned, according to the discretion of such officer, for any 
term not exceeding two calender months when the amount of penalty 
shall not exceed fifty rupees, and for any term not exceeding four 
calendar months when the amount shall not exceed one hundred rupees, 
and for any term not exceeding six calendar months in any other case, 
the commitment to be determinable in each of the cases aforesaid on 
payment of the amount.

</article>



<article><tid>1092146</tid>
<number>19</number>[ Recovery of penalty and costs from European British 
subjects.] Rep. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1286961</tid>
<number>20</number>Jurisdiction.-- On complaint made before any Magistrate of any 
offence committed under this Act, it shall not be necessary to prove 
that the offence was committed within the local limits of such 
Magistrate or other officer.


</article>



<article><tid>362071</tid>
<number> 20A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Power to make rules.--
<section><tid>746506</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes and objects of this Act in the territories under its 
administration or any part of the said territories.

</section>

<section><tid>1053783</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may-

<subsection><tid>1534771</tid>
<number>a</number>prescribe forms for licenses under this Act, the sums 
payable for the same and the conditions on which they may be 
granted, and the cases in which they may be revoked;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1793433</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for the inspection of stage- carriages, and of 
the animals employed in drawing them; and
<pagefootnote><pagenum>239</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word" Chief" rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" provided he is not a European British subject" omitted 
by the A. O. <year>1950</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Added by Act 1 of <year>1898</year>, s. 4


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>986890</tid>
<number>c</number>regulate the number and length of the stages for which 
animals may be driven in stage- carriages, and the manner in which 
they shall be harnessed and yoked.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>36093</tid>
<number>3</number>In making any rule under this section the State Government 
may direct that a breach thereof shall be punishable with fine which 
may extend to one hundred rupees.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1177260</tid>
<number>21</number>Interpretation- clause." Magistrate."-- The term" Magistrate" 
in this Act shall include all Magistrates and other persons exercising 
the powers of a Magistrate:
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

Act applicable to all animals used for drawing carriages.-- 2 
[ All expressions and provisions which in this Act are applied to 
horses shall also apply to all other animals employed in drawing any 
carriage ordinarily used for the purpose of conveying passengers for 
hire to or from any place in the States:]

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>1456175</tid>
<number>22</number><footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Extent of Act.-- This Act, as amended by subsequent 
Acts, extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States]; but it shall not apply to carriages ordinarily plying 
for hire within the limits of any municipality or cantonment or other 
place in which any law for the regulation of carriages is for the time 
being in force.


</article>



<article><tid>1649467</tid>
<number>23</number>Power to State Government to exempt.-- The State Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, exempt any carriages or 
class of carriages from all or any of the provisions of this Act.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>240</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The definition of" British India" omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1876</year>, s. 1, for the third sentence.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The definitions relating to" number" and" gender" rep. by Act 10 
of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ss, 22 and 23 added by Act 1 of <year>1898</year>, s. 5. The original s. 22 
regarding the commencement of this Act as originally passed had 
been rep. by Act 14 of <year>1870</year>, s. 1 and Sch., Part II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Sub. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



 </act>