<act><tid>269107</tid>
<title>THE FINANCE COMMISSION (MISCELLANEOUS PROVISIONS) ACT, <year>1951</year></title>

ACT NO. 33 OF <year>1951</year>
[ 16th May. <year>1951</year>.]

An Act to determine the qualifications requisite for appointment 
as members of the Finance Commission and the manner in which they 
shall be selected, and to prescribe their powers.

BE it enacted by Parliament as follows:--





<article><tid>1665284</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Finance Commission 
 (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, <year>1951</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1941999</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definition. In this Act," the Commission" means the Finance 
Commission constituted by the President pursuant to clause
<section><tid>1334028</tid>
<number>1</number>of  
article 280 of the Constitution.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>774445</tid>
<number> 3</number> Qualifications for appointment as, and the manner of selection 
of, members of the commission. The Chairman of the Commission shall be 
selected from among persons who have had experience in public affairs, 
and the four other members shall be selected from among persons who--
<section><tid>558992</tid>
<number>a</number>are, or have been, or are qualified to be appointed as 
Judges of a High Court; or

</section>

<section><tid>1278060</tid>
<number>b</number>have special knowledge of the finances and accounts of 
Government; or

</section>

<section><tid>1568053</tid>
<number>c</number>have had wide experience in financial matters and in 
administration; or

</section>

<section><tid>4504</tid>
<number>d</number>have special knowledge of economics.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>410991</tid>
<number>4</number>Personal interest to disqualify members. Before appointing a 
person to be a member of the Commission, the President shall satisfy 
himself that that person will have no such financial or other interest 
as is likely to affect prejudicially his functions as a member of the 
commission; and the President shall also satisfy himself from time to 
time with respect to every member of the Commission that he has no 
such interest and any person who is, or whom the President proposes to 
appoint to be, a member of the Commission shall, whenever required by 
the President so to do, furnish to him such information as the 
President considers necessary for the performance by him of his duties 
under this section.


</article>



<article><tid>1820769</tid>
<number> 5</number> Disqualifications for being a member of the Commission. A 
person shall be disqualified for being appointed as, or for being, a 
member of the Commission,--
<section><tid>1956606</tid>
<number>a</number>if he is of unsound mind;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>172</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1966103</tid>
<number>b</number>if he is an undischarged insolvent;

</section>

<section><tid>511078</tid>
<number>c</number>if he has been convicted of an offence involving moral 
turpitude;

</section>

<section><tid>1547016</tid>
<number>d</number>if he has such financial or other interest as is likely 
to affect prejudicially his functions as a member of 
the Commission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1483254</tid>
<number>6</number>Term of office of members and eligibility for reappointment. 
Every member of the Commission shall hold office for such period as 
may be specified in the order of the President appointing him, but 
shall be eligible for reappointment:
Provided that he may, by letter addressed to the President, 
resign his office.



</article>



<article><tid>1290757</tid>
<number> 7</number> Conditions of service and salaries and allowances of members.

<section><tid>267582</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>] The members of the Commission shall render whole- time or part-  
time service to the Commission as the President may in each case 
specify, and there shall be paid to the members of the Commission such 
fees or salaries and such allowances as the Central Government may, by 
rules made <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by notification in the Official Gazette,] in this behalf 
determine.

</section>

<section><tid>119298</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>729058</tid>
<number> 8</number> Procedure and powers of the Commission.
<section><tid>1709486</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commission  
shall determine their procedure and in the performance of their 
functions shall have all the powers of a civil court under the Code of 
Civil Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), while trying a suit in respect of 
the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>903557</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of witnesses;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1027916</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the production of any document;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>749777</tid>
<number>c</number>requisitioning any public record from any court or 
office.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1753835</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commission shall have power to require any person to 
furnish information on such points or matters as in the opinion of the 
Commission may be useful for, or relevant to, any matter under the 
consideration of the Commission <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> and any person so required shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2) of section 54 of 
the Indian Income- tax Act, <year>1922</year> (11 of <year>1922</year>), or in any other law for 
the time being in force, be deemed to be legally bound to furnish such 
information within the meaning of section 176 of the Indian Penal Code 
 (45 of <year>1860</year>)].

</section>

<section><tid>963333</tid>
<number>3</number>The Commission shall be deemed to be a civil court for the 
purposes of sections 480 and 482 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
 <year>1898</year> (5 of <year>1898</year>).
Explanation.-- For the purposes of enforcing the attendance of 
witnesses, the local limits of the Commission' s jurisdiction shall be 
the limits of the territory of India.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>173</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 7 renumbered as sub- section (1) thereof by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 
and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
2. Ins. by s. 2 and Sch., ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>). 
3. Added by Act 13 of <year>1955</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>