<act><title>The collection 
      of statistics act, 1953</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
      commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may 
      be called the Collection of Statistics Act, 1953.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except the 
      State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the 
      Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
      appoint.
  




  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
      requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>   “appropriate 
      Government” means—
 <subsection><number>i</number>   the Central 
      Government, in relation to the collection of statistics under a direction 
      issued by it under section 3, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   the State 
      Government, in relation to the collection of statistics under a direction 
      issued by it under that section;
 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number>   “commercial 
      concern” means a public limited company or a co-operative society or a 
      firm or any other person or body of persons engaged in trade or commerce, 
      and includes—
 <subsection><number>i</number>   a concern engaged 
      in banking or insurance;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   a financial 
      corporation;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>   a concern 
      engaged in shipping and navigation;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>   a concern engaged 
      in the business of brokers dealing in shares, stocks and securities and 
      commodities;
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>   a concern engaged 
      in the business of advertising consultants;
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number>   a light 
      railway;
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number>   a concern 
      engaged in road transport service;
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number>   a concern 
      engaged in air transport service;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number>   a rubber, tea, 
      coffee or cinchona plantation;
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number>   a concern engaged 
      in the business of forwarding and clearing agents;
 </subsection><subsection><number>xi</number>   any other concern 
      which, in the opinion of the Central Government, is a commercial concern 
      and is declared to be such by that Government by notification in the 
      Official Gazette, but does not include an industrial concern;
 </subsection></section><section><number>c</number>   “factory” means a 
      factory as defined in clause (m) of section 2 of the Factories Act, 1948 
      (LXIII of 1948);
 </section><section><number>d</number>   “industrial 
      concern” means a public limited company or a co-operative society or a 
      firm or any other person or body of persons engaged in the manufacture, 
      assembling, packing, preservation or processing of goods or in mining or 
      in the generation or distribution of electricity or any other form of 
      power;
 </section><section><number>e</number>   “owner”, in 
      relation to a commercial or an industrial concern, means the person who, 
      or the authority which has the ultimate control over the affairs of the 
      concern, and where the said affairs are entrusted to a manager, managing 
      director or managing agent, such manager, managing director or managing 
      agent shall be deemed to be the owner of the concern;
 </section><section><number>f</number>   “prescribed” means 
      prescribed by rules made under this Act or in any form laid down by such 
      rules.
  
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>3</number> Collection of statistics.—The appropriate Government may, by notification 
      in the Official Gazette, direct that statistics shall be collected 
      relating to any of the following matters, namely:—
 <section><number>a</number>   any matter 
      relating to any industry or class of industries;
 </section><section><number>b</number>   any matter 
      relating to any commercial or industrial concern or class of commercial or 
      industrial concerns, and in particular, any matter relating to 
      factories;
 </section><section><number>c</number>   any of the 
      following matters so far as they relate to welfare of labour and 
      conditions of labour, namely:—
 <subsection><number>i</number>   price of 
      commodities;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   
      attendance;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>   living 
      conditions including housing, water-supply and sanitation;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>   
      indebtedness;
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number>   rents of 
      dwelling-houses;
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number>   wages and other 
      earnings;
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number>   provident and 
      other funds provided for labour;
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number>   benefits and 
      amenities provided for labour;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number>   hours of 
      work;
 </subsection><subsection><number>x</number>   employment and 
      unemployment;
 </subsection><subsection><number>xi</number>   industrial and 
      labour disputes;
 </subsection></section><section><number>xii</number>   labour 
      turnover;
 </section><section><number>xiii</number>   trade 
      unions;
 and thereupon the provisions of 
      this Act shall apply in relation to those statistics:
 Provided that—
 </section><section><number>a</number>   nothing contained 
      in this section shall be deemed to authorise a State Government to issue 
      any direction under this Act with respect to the collection of statistics 
      relating to any matter falling under any of the entries specified in List 
      I in the Seventh Schedule to the Constitution; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>   where the Central 
      Government has issued any direction under this section for the collection 
      of statistics relating to any matter, no State Government shall, except 
      with the previous approval of the Central Government, issue any similar 
      direction for so long as the collection of statistics by the Central 
      Government remains to be completed; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>   where a State 
      Government has issued a direction under this section for the collection of 
      statistics relating to any matter, the Central Government shall not issue 
      any similar direction for so long as the collection of the statistics by 
      the State Government remains to be completed, except in cases where 
      statistics have to be collected with reference to two or more 
      States.
  
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>4</number> Appointment of statistics 
      authority.—The appropriate 
      Government may appoint an officer to be the statistics authority for the 
      purpose of collecting any statistics directed by it to be 
      collected.

  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>5</number> Power of statistics authority to call for 
      information or returns.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
      statistics authority may serve or cause to be served on the owner of an 
      industrial or commercial concern or on any other person a notice requiring 
      him to furnish such information or returns as may be prescribed relating 
      to any matter in respect of which statistics are to be 
      collected.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The form in which, and the person to whom, 
      or the authorities to which, such information or returns should be 
      furnished, the particulars which they should contain and the intervals 
      within which such information or returns should be furnished shall be such 
      as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The notice referred to in sub-section (1) 
      may be served by post.

  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number> Right to access to records or 
      documents.—The statistics 
      authority or any person authorised by him in writing in this behalf shall, 
      for the purposes of the collection of any statistics under this Act, have 
      access to any relevant record or document in the possession of any person 
      required to furnish any information or return under this Act and may enter 
      at any reasonable time any premises where he believes such record or 
      document to be and may inspect or take copies of relevant records or 
      documents or ask any question necessary for obtaining any information 
      required to be furnished under this Act.

  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>7</number> Restriction on the publication of information 
      and returns.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
      information, no individual return and no part of an individual return with 
      respect to any particular industrial or commercial concern, given for the 
      purposes of this Act, shall, without the previous consent in writing of 
      the owner for the time being of the industrial or commercial concern in 
      relation to which the information or return was given or made or his 
      authorised agent, be published in such manner as would enable any 
      particulars to be identified as referring to a particular 
      concern.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Except for the purposes of a prosecution 
      under this Act or under the Indian Penal Code (Act XLV of 1860), no person 
      who is not engaged in the collection of statistics under this Act shall be 
      permitted to see any information or individual return referred to in 
      sub-section (1).
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Penalties.—If any person—
 <section><number>a</number>   required to 
      furnish any information or return—
 <subsection><number>i</number>   wilfully refuses 
      or without lawful excuse neglects to furnish such information or return as 
      may be required under this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   wilfully 
      furnishes or causes to be furnished any information or return which he 
      knows to be false; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>   refuses to 
      answer or wilfully gives a false answer to any question necessary for 
      obtaining any information required to be furnished under this Act; 
      or
 </subsection></section><section><number>b</number>   impedes the right 
      of access to relevant records or documents or the right of entry conferred 
      by section 6,
 he shall for each such offence be 
      punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees and in the 
      case of a continuing offence to a further fine which may extend to two 
      hundred rupees for each day after the first during which the offence 
      continues.

  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> If the person guilty of an offence under 
      section 8 is a company, every person who at the time the offence was 
      committed was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the 
      conduct of the business of the company, as well as the company, shall be 
      deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
      against and punished accordingly:
 Provided that nothing contained in this 
      sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment provided 
      in this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
      knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission 
      of such offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
      sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a 
      company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the 
      consent or connivance of or is attributable to any neglect on the part of 
      any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such 
      director, manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be 
      guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
      punished accordingly.
 Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
      section,—
 <subsection><number>a</number>   “company” means 
      any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
      individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   “director” in 
      relation to a firm means a partner in the firm.
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Penalty for improper disclosure of 
      information or returns.—If any 
      person engaged in connection with the collection of statistics under this 
      Act wilfully discloses any information or the contents of any return given 
      or made under this Act otherwise than in the execution of his duties under 
      this Act or for the purposes of the prosecution of an offence under this 
      Act or under the Indian Penal Code (Act XLV of 1860), he shall be 
      punishable for such offence with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
      to six months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or 
      with both.

  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>11</number> Cognizance of offences.—No prosecution for an offence under section 8 
      shall be instituted except by or with the sanction of the statistics 
      authority and no prosecution for an offence under section 10 shall be 
      instituted except by or with the consent of the appropriate 
      Government.
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>12</number> Power of Central Government to give 
      directions.—The Central 
      Government may give directions to a State Government as to the carrying 
      into execution of this Act in the State.
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>13</number> Protection of action taken in good 
      faith.—No suit or other legal 
      proceeding shall lie against the appropriate Government, the statistics 
      authority, or any other person acting under the authority of the 
      appropriate Government or of the statistics authority in respect of 
      anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance 
      of this Act or of any rules or directions issued 
      thereunder.
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>14</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The appropriate Government may, subject to 
      the condition of previous publication, by notification in the Official 
      Gazette, make rules for the purpose of carrying out the purposes of this 
      Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Without prejudice to the generality of the 
      foregoing power, rules may be made under this section for all or any of 
      the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection><number>a</number>   the form and 
      manner in which the information and returns may be furnished, the 
      particulars which they should contain, the intervals within which and the 
      authority to which such information and returns may be 
      furnished;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   the manner in 
      which the right of access to documents and the right of entry conferred by 
      section 6 may be exercised; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   any other matter 
      which is to be or may be prescribed under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> Every rule made by the Central Government under this section 
      shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
      Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
      which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
      sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following 
      the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
      making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule 
      should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
      modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that 
      any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
      validity of anything previously done under that 
      rule.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every rule made by the State Government 
      under this section shall be laid, as soon as it is made, before the State 
      Legislature.]
  




  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>15</number> Repeal.—[Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, 
      1957 (36 of 1957), sec. 2 and Sch. I (w.e.f. 17-9-1957).]
  
  </article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Came into 
      force on 10-11-1956, vide Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. I, Sec. 1, 
      p. 1027, dated 10th November, 1956.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
         Subs. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 
      15-5-1986).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>