<act><title>


    The Civil Defence Act, 1968</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Civil Defence Act, 1968.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends 
    to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in a State or part thereof on such date1, 
    not being a date earlier than the date of the expiry of the Defence of India 
    Act, 1962 (51 of 1962), as the Central Government may, by notification, 
    appoint and different dates may be appointed for different States or 
    different parts thereof. 
 
 



 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In this Act, unless the context otherwise re­quires,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “civil defence” includes any measures, not amounting to actual combat, for affording protection to any person, property, place or thing in India or any part of the territory thereof against any hostile attack, whether from air, land, sea or other places, or, for depriving any such attack of the whole or part of its effect, whether such measures are taken before, during, at or after the time of such attack <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[or any measure taken for the purpose of disaster management, before, during, at, or after any disaster]; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> “Civil Defence Corps” means the Corps formed wholly or mainly to meet the needs of civil defence and includes an organisation deemed to be a Corps under the proviso to sub-section (1) of section 4; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> “hostile attack” means any attack by any person or body of persons, whether during any war, external aggression, internal disturbance or otherwise which endangers the security of any life, property, place or thing in India or any part of the terri­tory thereof; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> “notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> “personal service injury” has the meaning assigned to it in the Personal Injuries (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1962 (59 of 1962); 
 </section><section><number>f</number> “State Government”, in relation to a Union territory, means the Administrator of the Union territory; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>g</number> “disaster” means a disaster as defined in clause (d) of section 2 of the Disaster Management Act, 2005 (53 of 2005);] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>h</number> “disaster management” means the disaster management as defined in clause (e) of section 2 of the Disaster Management Act, 2005 (53 of 2005).] 
  
</section>



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Power to 
    make rules for civil defence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Gov­ernment may, for securing civil defence, by notification, 
    make rules providing for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    preventing the prosecution of any work 
    likely to prejudice civil defence; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    instruction of members of the public 
    regarding civil defence and their equipment for the purpose of such defence; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    provision, storage and maintenance of 
    commodities and things required for civil defence; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    prohibiting or regulating traffic, and 
    the use of vessels, buoys, lights and signals in ports and territorial, 
    tidal and inland waters; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    control of lights and sounds; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    protection of life and property by 
    taking fire prevention and other measures; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    securing of any buildings, premises or 
    other structures from being readily recognisable in the event of a hostile 
    attack; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    for the prevention of danger to life or 
    property, the demoli­tion, destruction or rendering useless, of any 
    building, premises or other structures or any other property; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    prohibiting or regulating the 
    possession, use or disposal of— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    explosives, inflammable substances, 
    corrosive and other dan­gerous substances or articles, arms and ammunition; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    vessels; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    wireless telegraphic apparatus; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    aircraft; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    photographic and signalling apparatus 
    and any means of record­ing information; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>    evacuation of areas and the removal of 
    property or animals there­from; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>    accommodation in any area of persons 
    evacuated from another area and the regulation of the conduct of evacuated 
    persons accommodated in such area; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>    billeting of evacuated persons or 
    persons authorised to perform functions under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>    salvage of damaged buildings, 
    structures and property and disposal of the dead; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>    seizure and custody or destruction of 
    injured, unclaimed or dangerous animals; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>    ensuring the safety of— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    ports, dockyards, lighthouses, 
    lightships, aerodromes and facilities associated with aerial navigation; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    railways, tramways, roads, bridges, 
    canals and all other means of transport by land or water; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    telegraphs, post offices, signalling 
    apparatus and all other means of communication; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    sources and systems of water supply, 
    works for the supply of water, gas or electricity and all other works for 
    public purpos­es; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    vessels, aircraft, transport vehicles 
    as defined in the Motor Vehicles Act, 1939 (4 of 1939), and rolling stocks 
    of railways and tramways; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>    warehouses and all other places used 
    or intended to be used for storage purposes; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>    mines, oilfields, factories or 
    industrial or commercial undertakings generally, or any mine, oilfield, 
    factory or indus­trial or commercial undertaking in particular; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>viii</number>    laboratories and institutions where 
    scientific or techno­logical research or training is conducted or imparted; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ix</number>    all works and structures being part 
    of, or connected with, anything earlier mentioned in this clause; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>x</number>    any other place or thing used or 
    intended to be used for the purposes of Government or a local authority or a 
    semi-Government or autonomous organisation, the protection of which is 
    considered necessary or expedient for securing civil defence; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>p</number>    control of any road or pathway, 
    waterway, ferry or bridge, river, canal or other source of water supply; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>q</number>    precautionary measures, which the 
    Government or any depart­ment thereof or any local authority, members of 
    police force, fire brigade and members of any other service or authority 
    employed primarily for purposes other than civil defence purposes should be 
    required to take within their respective jurisdictions or with respect to 
    any personnel employed by them: 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>r</number>    preventing or controlling any use of 
    uniforms, whether offi­cial or otherwise, or flags or official decorations 
    like medals, badges or other insignia or anything similar thereto, the 
    wearing of which is calculated to deceive or to prejudice civil defence; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>s</number>    precautions to be taken or action to be 
    taken by persons or authorities with a view to protecting or acquainting the 
    general public or any members thereof against the dangers involved in any 
    apprehended hostile attack; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>t</number>    requiring the owner or occupier of any 
    building, structure or premises to make or carry out such arrangements as 
    may be neces­sary for the purposes of detection and prevention of fire; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>u</number>    taking of specified measures for 
    dealing with outbreaks of fire; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>    directing that, subject to any 
    specified exemption, no person present in any specified area shall, between 
    such hours as may be specified, be out of doors, except under the authority 
    of a written permit granted by a specified authority or person; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>w</number>  (i)    prohibiting the printing and 
    publication of any newspa­per, news-sheet, book or other document containing 
    matters preju­dicial to civil defence; 
 <subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    demanding security from any press used 
    for the purpose of printing or publishing, and forfeiting the copies of, any 
    newspa­per, news-sheet, book or other document containing any of the matters 
    referred to in sub-clause (i); 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>x</number>    regulating the conduct of persons in 
    respect of areas the control of which is considered necessary or expedient, 
    the remov­al of persons from such areas; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>y</number>    requiring any person or class of 
    persons to comply with any scheme of civil defence; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>z</number>    any other provision which may be 
    necessary for the purposes of civil defence.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any rule 
    made under sub-section (1) may provide that orders with regard to the 
    matters specified therein may be made by the State Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any rule 
    made under sub-section (1) may provide that a con­travention thereof or any 
    order made thereunder shall be punish­able with fine which may extend to 
    five hundred rupees, and where the contravention is a continuing one, with a 
    further fine which may extend to fifty rupees for every day, after the 
    first, during which such contravention continues. 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>4</number> 
    Constitution of Civil Defence Corps.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may constitute, for any area within the State, a body 
    of persons to be called the Civil Defence Corps (hereinafter referred to as 
    the “Corps”) and may appoint a person, not being, in its opinion, below the 
    rank of a District Magistrate (to be known as the “Controller”) to command 
    such Corps: 
 
Provided that 
    if there is in existence in any area in a State, immediately before the 
    commencement of this Act in that area, an organisation which, in the opinion 
    of the State Government, may be entrusted with the functions of the Corps, 
    the State Govern­ment may, instead of constituting a separate Corps for such 
    area, call upon that organisation to take over or discharge the functions of 
    the Corps in that area, and thereupon such organisa­tion shall be deemed, 
    for the purpose of this Act, to be the Corps for that area. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State 
    Government may, for the purpose of co-ordinating the activities of the 
    Controllers within the State, appoint a Director of Civil Defence and every 
    Controller shall comply with the directions given by such Director. 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>5</number> 
    Appointment of members and officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Govern­ment may appoint as members of the Corps persons who are 
    fit and willing to serve as such and the Controller may appoint any member 
    so appointed to such office or command in the Corps, as such member is, in 
    the opinion of the Controller, fit to hold.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    person appointed to be a member of the Corps shall be given a certificate of 
    membership in such form as may be pre­scribed. 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>6</number> Dismissal 
    of members of Civil Defence Corps.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any member of the Corps fails or has failed, in the opinion of the 
    Controller, to discharge his duties as such member satisfactorily or is or 
    has been found guilty of any misconduct in the discharge of his duties as 
    such member, the Controller may, after an in­quiry in which such member of 
    the Corps has been given a reason­able opportunity of being heard in respect 
    of the charges against him, by an order, dismiss such member from the Corps. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    Controller is of opinion that the continued pres­ence of any member of the 
    Corps is undesirable, he may, without assigning any reason, summarily 
    dismiss such member from the Corps. 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Appeal.—A 
    member of the Corps who is dismissed from the Corps under section 6 may 
    prefer an appeal to the State Govern­ment within thirty days from the date 
    of such dismissal and that Government may, on such appeal, confirm, modify 
    or reverse the order made by the Controller or other authority. 
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>8</number> Functions 
    of members of Civil Defence Corps.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The members of the Corps shall perform such functions in relation to the 
    carrying out of measures for civil defence as may be assigned to them by 
    rules made under this Act or by any other law for the time being in force. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State 
    Government or the Controller may, by order, call out a member of the Corps 
    for training or for discharging such functions in relation to the carrying 
    out of measures for civil defence as may be specified in such order. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    such orders as the Central Government may make in this behalf, any member of 
    the Corps of any State may at any time be required, by order, to discharge 
    functions in relation to civil defence in any other State and shall while 
    discharging such functions, be deemed to be a member of the Corps of that 
    other State and be vested with the powers, functions and privileges and be 
    subject to the liabilities of a member of the Corps in that other State. 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power to 
    make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central 
    Government may, by notification, make regulations for carrying out the 
    purposes of this Chapter. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such regulations may— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    prescribe the functions of the members 
    of the Corps and regulate the manner in which they may be called out for 
    service; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    regulate the organisation, appointment, 
    conditions of service, discipline, accoutrement and clothing of members of 
    any or all of the Corps; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    prescribe the form of certificates of 
    membership of any or all of the Corps. 
 
 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article> <number>10</number> 
      Provisions of the Personal Injuries (Emergency Provisions) Act to apply to 
      injuries sustained by the members of the Corps.—The provisions of the Personal Injuries 
      (Emergency Provisions) Act, 1962 (59 of 1962), and of every scheme made 
      thereunder shall apply, so far as may be, to every personal service injury 
      sus­tained by any person appointed to be a member of the Corps as they 
      apply to personal service injury sustained by a civil defence volunteer, 
      subject to the modifications that— 
 <section><number>a</number>    any 
      reference to a civil defence volunteer under that Act or any scheme made 
      thereunder shall be construed as reference to a member of the Corps; and 
 </section><section><number>b</number>    any 
      reference therein to the period of emergency shall, in relation to a 
      member of the Corps, be construed as the period during which this Act is 
      in force. 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any member of 
    the Corps on being called out by an order under sub-section (2) of section 8 
    neglects or refuses without sufficient excuse to obey such order or to 
    discharge his functions as such member or to obey any lawful order or 
    direction given to him for the performance of his functions, he shall be 
    punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and where such 
    neglect or refusal is a continuing one, with a further fine which may extend 
    to fifty rupees for every day, after the first, during which such 
    contravention continues. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person neglects or fails without any reasonable excuse to obey any order 
    made or direction given to him under this Act or rules made thereunder, he 
    shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and 
    where such negligence or failure is a continuing one, with a further fine 
    which may extend to fifty rupees for every day, after the first, during 
    which such negligence or failure continues. 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>12</number> Effect of Act and rules, etc., 
      inconsistent with other enact­ments.—
<section><number>1</number> The provisions of this Act or any rules 
      made thereunder or any order made under this Act or any such rule shall 
      have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in 
      any enactment other than this Act or in any instru­ment having effect 
      by virtue of any enactment other than this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every appointment, order or rule made in 
      relation to civil defence before the commencement of this Act by or under 
      any law relating to civil defence shall, in so far as it is not 
      inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, continue to be in force 
      until it is rescinded or altered under this Act, and be deemed to have 
      been made under the corresponding provisions of this Act. 
 Explanation.—“Commencement of this Act”, in relation to any 
      provision or area, means the commencement of that provision or, as the 
      case may be, the commencement of this Act in that area. 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>13</number> Ordinary 
    avocations of life to be interfered with as little as possible.—Any 
    authority or person acting in pursuance of this Act shall interfere with the 
    ordinary avocations of life and the enjoyment of property as little as may 
    be consonant with the purpose of ensuring the public safety and civil 
    defence.
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Savings 
    as to orders.—
<section><number>1</number> No order made in 
    exercise of any power conferred by or under this Act shall be called in 
    question in any court. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    order purports to have been made and signed by any authority in exercise of 
    any power conferred by or under this Act, a court shall, within the meaning 
    of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872), presume that such order was so 
    made by that authority. 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>15</number> Act not to apply to measures taken for the 
      protection of the Armed Forces.— Nothing contained in this Act or any rule, 
      regu­lation or order made thereunder shall apply to the Armed Forces 
      of the Union or to any measures taken by any of the authorities in control 
      of the Armed Forces of the Union for the purpose of securing civil defence 
      or safety of such forces or for the pro­tection of any naval, military 
      or air force installations of stores.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Limitation of prosecutions.—No 
    prosecution for any offence punishable under this Act shall be instituted 
    against any person except by, or with the consent of, the Controller or any 
    person authorised by the Controller in this behalf. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
 <number>17</number> Power to 
    delegate.—The State Government 
    may, by notifica­tion, direct that—
 <section>
<number>a</number>    all or any of the powers which may be 
    exercised by it under this Act shall, in such circumstances and under such 
    conditions, if any, as may be specified in that notification, be exercised 
    also by such officer, not being, in the opinion of the State Government, 
    inferior in rank to that of a District Magistrate, as may be specified in 
    the said notification; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    all or any of the powers which may be 
    exercised by the Controller under this Act shall, in such circumstances and 
    under such conditions, if any, as may be specified in that notification, be 
    exercised also by such officer, not being, in the opinion of the State 
    Government, inferior in rank to that of a Sub-Divisional Magistrate, as may 
    be specified in the said notifica­tion. 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>18</number> Protection of action taken in good 
      faith.—
<section><number>1</number> No suit, prosecution 
      or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Government, the Director 
      or the Controller or any person, author­ised by the Government or the 
      Controller, for anything which is in good faith done or intended to be 
      done under this Act or any rules or orders made thereunder or any order 
      issued under any such 
      rule. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie 
      against the Government, the Director or the Controller or any person, 
      authorised by the Government or the Controller, for any damage caused or 
      likely to be caused by anything which is in good faith done or intended to 
      be done under this Act or any rule made thereunder or any order issued 
      under any such rule. 
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Authorised persons and members of Corps to be public serv­ants.—Any 
    person authorised by the Controller or the State Government under this Act 
    and every member of the Corps, while functioning as such, shall be deemed to 
    be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal 
    Code, (45 of 1860). 
 
 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Rules and regulations to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
    rule and every regulation made by the Central Government under this Act 
    shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
    Parliament while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which 
    may be comprised in one session or 

    1[in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the succes­sive sessions aforesaid] both Houses 
    agree in making any modifi­cation in the rule or regulation or both Houses 
    agree that the rule or regulation, as the case may be, should not be made, 
    the rule or regulations shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
    form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so, howev­er, that any such 
    modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule or regulation.
 

 
 
--------------------­­­­­
 <section>
     <number>1</number>   Subs. by Act 20 of 
    1983, sec. 2 and Sch., for certain words (w.e.f. 15-3-1984).
 
 
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by Act 3 of 2010, sec. 2(i) (w.e.f 21-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by Act 3 of 2010, sec. 2(ii) (w.e.f 21-1-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>