<act><tid>273666</tid>
<title>THE RAJASTHAN AND MADHYA PRADESH (TRANSFER OF TERRITORIES) ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 47 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 18th September, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to provide for the transfer of certain territories from the 
State of Rajasthan to the State of Madhya Pradesh and for matters 
connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1418392</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Rajasthan and Madhya 
Pradesh (Transfer of Territories) Act, <year>1959</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>195917</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>388974</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of October, <year>1959</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>1885212</tid>
<number>b</number>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and 
" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as 
in the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1920574</tid>
<number>c</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of a State, means a 
person who, immediately before the appointed day, is a 
member of that House;

</section>

<section><tid>399112</tid>
<number>d</number>" transferred territories" means the territories 
specified in the First Schedule and transferred from 
the State of Rajasthan to the State of Madhya Pradesh 
by section 3.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>378928</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer of territories from Rajasthan to Madhya Pradesh.
<section><tid>392124</tid>
<number>1</number> 
As from the appointed day, there shall be added to the State of Madhya 
Pradesh the territories specified in the First Schedule which shall 
thereupon cease to form part of the State of Rajasthan.

</section>

<section><tid>1479158</tid>
<number>2</number>The transferred territories shall be included in, and form 
part of, Bhanpura pargana of Mandsaur district in the State of Madhya 
Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>1762011</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall be deemed to affect the 
power of the State Government to alter after the appointed day the 
name, extent or boundaries of any district in the State of Madhya 
Pradesh.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>518</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1381865</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of the First Schedule to the Constitution. As from 
the appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under 
the heading" I. THE STATES",--
<section><tid>1942909</tid>
<number>a</number>in the entry against" 6. Madhya Pradesh", after the 
words and figures" States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>", 
the words, brackets and figures" and the First Schedule 
to the Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh (Transfer of  
  Territories) Act, <year>1959</year>" shall be inserted;

</section>

<section><tid>856737</tid>
<number>b</number>in the entry against" 11. Rajasthan", after the words 
and figures" States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>", the 
words, brackets and figures" but excluding the 
territories specified in the First Schedule to the 
Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh (Transfer of Territories) 
Act, <year>1959</year>" shall be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1516779</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendments of Delimitation Orders. The Delimitation of 
Parliamentary and Assembly Constituencies Order, <year>1956</year>, and the 
Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Madhya Pradesh) Order, <year>1957</year>, 
shall have effect subject to the modifications specified in the Second 
Schedule.


</article>



<article><tid>1316024</tid>
<number> 6</number> Provision as to sitting members.
<section><tid>699410</tid>
<number>1</number>The sitting members of  
the House of the People representing Mandsaur constituency in the 
State of Madhya Pradesh and Kotah constituency in the State of 
Rajasthan shall, notwithstanding the alteration in the extent of those 
constituencies by virtue of the provisions of this Act, continue to be 
members of the House of the People.

</section>

<section><tid>457079</tid>
<number>2</number>The sitting members of the Legislative Assemblies of Madhya 
Pradesh and Rajasthan representing Garoth constituency and begun 
constituency respectively shall, notwithstanding the alteration in the 
extent of those constituencies by virtue of the provisions of this 
Act, continue to be members of the said Assemblies.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>129957</tid>
<number> 7</number> Extension of jurisdiction of Madhya Pradesh High Court.
<section><tid>1127707</tid>
<number>1</number>As  
from the appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>1355828</tid>
<number>a</number>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Madhya Pradesh 
shall extend to the transferred territories; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>3456</tid>
<number>b</number>the High Court of Rajasthan shall have no jurisdiction 
in respect of the said territories.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>443744</tid>
<number>2</number>If, immediately before the appointed day, there is any 
proceeding relatable to the transferred territories pending in the 
High Court of Rajasthan, then, notwithstanding anything contained in 
sub- section (1), such proceeding shall be heard and disposed of by 
that High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1349107</tid>
<number>3</number>Any order made by the High Court of Rajasthan in any 
proceeding with respect to which that High Court exercises juris-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>519</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

diction by virtue of sub- section (2), shall, for all purposes, have 
effect, not only as an order of the High Court of Rajasthan, but also 
as an order made by the High Court of Madhya Pradesh.


</section>

<section><tid>1129723</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>615390</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High 
Court of Rajasthan until that Court has disposed of all 
issues between the parties, including any issues with 
respect to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings 
and shall include appeals, applications for leave to 
appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review, 
petitions for revision and petitions for writs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452023</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or Division Court 
thereof, and references to an order made by a Court or 
a Judge shall be construed as including references to a 
sentence, judgment or decree passed or made by that 
Court or Judge.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>761660</tid>
<number>8</number>Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred 
territories under existing Appropriation Acts. As from the appointed 
day, any Act passed by the Legislature of Madhya Pradesh before that 
day for the appropriation of any money out of the Consolidated Fund of 
the State to meet any expenditure in respect of any part of the 
financial year <year>1959</year>- 60 shall have effect also in relation to the 
transferred territories, and it shall be lawful for the State 
Government to spend any amount for those territories out of the amount 
authorised by such Act to be expended for any services in that State.


</article>



<article><tid>558068</tid>
<number> 9</number> Assets and liabilities.
<section><tid>827407</tid>
<number>1</number>All land and all stores, articles  
and other goods in the transferred territories belonging to the State 
of Rajasthan shall, as from the appointed day, pass to the State of 
Madhya Pradesh.
Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression" land" includes 
immovable property of every kind and any rights in or over such 
property and the expression" goods" does not include coins, bank notes 
and currency notes.


</section>

<section><tid>1839134</tid>
<number>2</number>All rights, liabilities and obligations, whether arising out 
of a contract or otherwise, of the State of Rajasthan in relation to 
the transferred territories shall, as from the appointed day, be the 
rights, liabilities and obligations, respectively, of the State of 
Madhya Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>553063</tid>
<number> 10</number> State Financial Corporations and State Electricity Boards. As 
from the appointed day,--
<section><tid>116725</tid>
<number>a</number>the Financial Corporations constituted under the State 
Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>), for the 
States of Rajasthan and Madhya Pradesh, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>520</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>603475</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Electricity Boards constituted under the 
Electricity (Supply) Act, <year>1948</year> (54 of <year>1948</year>), for the 
said States,
shall be deemed to have been constituted for those States with their 
areas as altered by the provisions of section 3.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>266471</tid>
<number>11</number>Extension of laws. All laws which immediately before the 
appointed day extend to, or are in force in, the Mandsaur district in 
the State of Madhya Pradesh but do not extend to, or are not in force 
in, the transferred territories shall, as from that day, extend to, or 
as the case may be, come into force in, the transferred territories; 
and all laws which, immediately before the appointed day, are in force 
in the transferred territories, but not in the Mandsaur district in 
the State of Madhya Pradesh, shall, on that day, cease to be in force 
in the transferred territories, except as respects things done or 
omitted to be done before that day.
Explanation.-- In this section" law" includes any enactment, 
ordinance, regulation, order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or 
other instrument having the force of law in the whole or in any part 
of Madhya Pradesh or Rajasthan.



</article>



<article><tid>795660</tid>
<number>12</number>Power to construe laws. Any court, tribunal or authority 
required or empowered to enforce any law extended to the transferred 
territories by section 11 may, for the purpose of facilitating its 
application in relation to the transferred territories, construe the 
law in such manner, without affecting the substance, as may be 
necessary or proper in regard to the matter before the court, tribunal 
or authority.


</article>



<article><tid>846120</tid>
<number>13</number>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed 
day, the State of Rajasthan is a party to any legal proceedings with 
respect to any property, rights or liabilities transferred to the 
State of Madhya Pradesh under this Act, that State shall be deemed to 
be substituted for the State of Rajasthan as a party to those 
proceedings, or added as a party thereto, as the case may be, and the 
proceedings may continue accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>1080703</tid>
<number> 14</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>1378425</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before any court (other than a  
  High Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that 
day falls within the State of Rajasthan shall, if it is a proceeding 
relating exclusively to any part of the transferred territories, stand 
transferred to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer 
in the State of Madhya Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>962181</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should 
stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>521</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

High Court of Rajasthan and the decision of that High Court shall be 
final.


</section>

<section><tid>353897</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section,--

<subsection><tid>925022</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1433919</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in 
Madhya Pradesh means--

<subsubsection><tid>1442823</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer 
in which, or before whom, the proceeding would 
have lain if the proceeding had been instituted 
after the appointed day, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>84203</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, 
authority or officer in that State as may be 
determined after the appointed day by the 
Government of Madhya Pradesh, or before the 
appointed day by the Government of Rajasthan, to 
be the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or 
officer.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1017636</tid>
<number>15</number>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.


</article>



<article><tid>1882390</tid>
<number>16</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act (including any difficulty  
in relation to the transition under section 11 from one law to another 
  law), the President may by order do anything not inconsistent with any 
such provision which appears to him to be necessary for the purpose of 
removing the difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>851925</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1681645</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1407933</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>522</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 5- <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



 </act>