<act><title>THE TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF INDIA (FORM OF ANNUAL STATEMENT OF ACCOUNTS AND RECORDS) RULES, 19991</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.</title>—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Form of Annual Statement of Accounts and Records) Rules, 1999.
 </section><section> <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions</title>.—In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section> <number>a</number> ‘Act’ means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 
    (24 of 1997);
 </section><section> <number>b</number> ‘Schedule’ means a Schedule appended to the Form;
 </section><section> <number>c</number> ‘Authority’ means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India;
 </section><section> <number>d</number> ‘Form’ means a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section> <number>e</number> All other words and expressions used in these rules but not defined, and defined in the Act shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Annual Statement of Accounts and other relevant records</title>.—At the end of a period of twelve months ending with 31st March of every year, the Authority shall prepare an Income and Expenditure Account and a Receipt and Payment Account for the period and a Balance-Sheet as at the last day of that period in the Forms specified below:
 
 <section> <number>a</number> Receipt and Payment account in Form A.
 </section><section> <number>b</number> Income and Expenditure Account in Form B.
 </section><section> <number>c</number> Balance Sheet in Form C.
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number></title> The Authority shall preserve the Balance Sheet, Income and Expenditure Account and Receipt and Payment Account prepared under rule 3 above for a minimum period of five years.


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Authorized Signatory</title>.—The Receipt and Payment Account, Income and Expenditure Account and the Balance Sheet mentioned in rule 3 above shall be signed by the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Advisor/Principal Advisor (Financial Analysis) and Internal Finance Advisor], Secretary, Member and Chairperson.



</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 233(E), dated 20th April, 2006 (w.e.f. 20-4-2006).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>