<act><tid>284174</tid>
<title>THE OIL AND NATURAL GAS COMMISSION (TRANSFER OF UNDERTAKING AND REPEAL) Act, <year>1993</year></title>

NO. 65 OF <year>1993</year> 
[ 4th S
An Act to provide for the transfer and vesting of the underta- 
king of the Oil and Natural Gas Commission to and in the Oil and 
Natu- 
ral Gas Corporation Limited, a company incorporated under the 
Companies 
, Act, <year>1956</year>, and for matters connected therewith or incidental 
thereto 
and also to repeal the Oil and Natural Gas Commission Act, <year>1959</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Forty- fourth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-




<article><tid>1702828</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>294426</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Oil and Natural Gas Commission (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) 
Act, <year>1993</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>201776</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 2nd day of 
July, <year>1993</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>365954</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>908915</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Govern- 
ment may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>1807228</tid>
<number>b</number>" Corporation" means the Oil and Natural Gas Corporation 
Limited, a company registered under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> 
 (1 of <year>1956</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>188193</tid>
<number>c</number>" Commission" means the Oil and Natural Gas Commission 
established under sub- section (1) of section 3 of the Oil and 
Natural Gas Commission Act, <year>1959</year> (43 of <year>1959</year>);

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>310264</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1255193</tid>
<number>3</number>Undertaking of Commission to vest in Corporation. On such 
date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint, the undertaking of the Commission shall stand 
transferred to, and vest in, the Corporation.

</article>



<article><tid>735821</tid>
<number> 4</number> General effect of vesting of undertaking in Corporation.

<section><tid>1273900</tid>
<number>1</number>On and from the appointed day, the entire capital of the  
Commission shall, by virtue of this Act, stand vested in the 
Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>1333269</tid>
<number>2</number>The undertaking of the Commission which is transferred to, 
and which vests in, the Coporation under section 3 shall be deemed to 
include all assets, rights, powers, authorities and privileges and all 
properties, movable and immovable, real and personal, corporeal or 
incorporeal, in possession or reservation, present or contingent of 
whatever nature and wheresoever situate including lands, buildings, 
works, workshops, vehicles, oil rigs, oil platforms, cash balances, 
deposits, foreign currencies, reserves, reserve funds or any other 
investments, securities, tenancies, leases and book debts and all 
other rights and interests arising out of such properties as were 
immediately before the appointed day in the ownership, possession or 
power of the Commission in relation to its undertaking, whether 
within or outside India, all books of account and registers, records 
and documents relating thereto and shall also be deemed to include all 
liabilities and obligations of whatever kind, within or outside India, 
of the Commission in relation to its undertaking subsisting 
immediately before the appointed day.

</section>

<section><tid>436896</tid>
<number>3</number>All contracts, deeds, bonds, guarantees, powers of attorney, 
other instruments and working arrangements subsisting immediately 
before the appointed day and affecting the Commission shall cease to 
have effect or to be enforceable against the Commission and shall be 
of as full force and effect against or in favour of the Corporation 
and enforceable as fully and effectually as if, instead of the 
Commission the Corporation had been named therein or had been a party 
thereto.

</section>

<section><tid>675542</tid>
<number>4</number>Any proceeding or cause of action pending or existing 
immediately before the appointed day by or against the Commission in 
relation to its undertaking may, as from the appointed day, be 
continued and enforced by, or against the Corporation as it might 
have been enforced by or against the Commission, if this Act had not 
been in force, and shall cease to be enforceable by or against the 
Commission.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1057384</tid>
<number>5</number>Licences, etc., to be deemed to have been granted to 
Corporation. With effect from the appointed day, all licences, leases, 
concessions, permits, quotas, benefits, privileges and exemptions 
granted to the Commission in connection with the affairs of the 
Commission under any law for the time being in force, shall be deemed 
to have been granted to the Corporation.

</article>



<article><tid>1434878</tid>
<number> 6</number> Tax exemption or benefit to continue to have effect.
<section><tid>1634168</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Where any exemption from, or any assessment with respect to, any tax 
has been granted or made or any benefit by way of set off or carry 
forward of any unabsorbed depreciation or investment allowance or 
other allowance or loss has been extended or is available to the Com- 
mission under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), such exemption, 
assessment or benefit shall continue to have effect, in relation to 
the Corporation.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 2. <year>1994</year>: Vide Notification No. G. S. R. 44 (E), dt. 28. 1. <year>1994</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>187827</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any payment made by the Commission is exempt from 
deduction of the tax at source under any provision of the Income- tax 
Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), the exemption from tax will continue to be 
available as if the provisions of the said Act made applicable to the 
Commission were operative in relation to the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>252221</tid>
<number>3</number>The transfer and vesting of the undertaking or any part 
thereof in terms of section 3 shall not be construed as a transfer 
within the meaning of the Income- Lax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of <year>1961</year>), for the 
purpose of capital gains.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1989260</tid>
<number>7</number>Guarantee to be operative. Any guarantee given for or in 
favour of the Commission with respect to any loan or lease finance or 
other assistance shall continue to be operative in relation to the 
Corporation.

</article>



<article><tid>904556</tid>
<number> 8</number> Provisions in respect of officers and other employees of 
Commission.
<section><tid>1620932</tid>
<number>1</number>Every officer or other employee of the Commission  
 (except a member or the chairman) serving in its employment 
immediately before the appointed day shall, in so far as such officer 
or other employee is employed in connection with the undertaking which 
has vested in the Corporation by virtue of this Act, become, as from 
the appointed day, an officer or, as the case may be, other employee 
of the Corporation and shall hold his office or service therein by 
the same tenure, at the same remuneration, upon the same terms and 
conditions with the same obligations and with the same rights and 
privileges as to leave, passage, insurance, superannuation scheme, 
provident fund, other funds, retirement, pension, gratuity and other 
benefits as he would have held under the Commission if its undertaking 
had not vested in the Corporation and shall continue to do so as an 
officer or other employee of the Corporation or until the expiry of a 
period of one year from the appointed day if such officer or other 
employee opts not to be the officer or other, employee of the 
Corporation within such period.

</section>

<section><tid>1747120</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an officer or other employee of the Commission opts 
under sub- section (1) not to be in the employment or service of the 
Corporation such officer or other employee shall be deemed to have 
resigned.

</section>

<section><tid>649977</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Industrial 
Disputes Act, <year>1947</year> (14 of <year>1947</year>) or in any other law for the time 
being in force, the transfer of the service of any officer or other 
employee of the Commission to the Corporation shall not entitle such 
officer or other employee to any compensation under this Act or under 
any other law for the time being in force and no such claim shall be 
entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>516020</tid>
<number>4</number>The officers and other employees who have retired before the 
appointed day from the service of the Commission and are entitled to 
any benefits, rights or privileges shall be entitled to receive the 
same benefits, rights or privileges from the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>490961</tid>
<number>5</number>The trusts of the provident fund, gratuity fund or the 
superannuation scheme of the Commission and any other bodies created 
for the welfare of officers or other employees shall continue to 
discharge their functions in the Corporation as was being done 
hitherto in the Commission and any tax exemptions granted to the 
provident fund, gratuity fund and the superannuation scheme or any 
other bodies created for the welfare of officers or other employees 
shall continue to be applied to the Corporation.

</section>

<section><tid>522314</tid>
<number>6</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act or in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>) or in any other law for the time 
being in force or in the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

regulations of the Commission, no member or chairman of the Commis- 
sion shall be entitled to any compensation against the Commission or 
the Corporation for the loss of office or for the premature 
termination of any contract of management entered into by him with the 
Commission.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1173368</tid>
<number> 9</number> Power of entry.
<section><tid>1061119</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of ascertaining the  
availability of any oil or natural gas, the Central Government may, on 
the request being made by the Corporation, authorise any officer or 
employee of the Corporation,' by general or special order,--

<subsection><tid>1471506</tid>
<number>a</number>to enter and inspect any land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1887653</tid>
<number>b</number>to survey and take measurements of such land;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>177681</tid>
<number>c</number>to dig holes or perform any other functions for 
the purposes of measuring or prospecting for the availability 
of oil and natural gas; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1268358</tid>
<number>d</number>to examine any document, book, register or record in 
the possession or power of any person having the control of 
or connected with any such land and place marks of 
identification thereon and take extracts from and make copies 
of any such document, book, register or record.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>327452</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person authorised by the Central Government under sub- 
section (1) shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning 
of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>752668</tid>
<number>3</number>The Corporation shall be liable to pay compensation for any 
loss or damage caused to the land caused by its officers or employees 
in performing the functions under sub- section (1) in such manner as may 
be prescribed to the occupier of the land.

</section>

<section><tid>1161787</tid>
<number>4</number>The amount of compensation payable under sub- section (3) 
shall be determined by the competent authority appointed by the 
Central Government in the manner prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1476962</tid>
<number> 10</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>799828</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out 
the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>98856</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for the amount, and the 
manner of paying compensation for any loss or damage caused to the 
land by the officers and employees of the Corporation under sub- 
sections (3) and (4) of section 9.

</section>

<section><tid>887909</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may 
be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>579449</tid>
<number> 11</number> Repeal of Act 48 of <year>1959</year>.
<section><tid>327491</tid>
<number>1</number>On the appointed day, the Oil  
and Natural Gas Commission Act, <year>1959</year> shall stand repealed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>189612</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, the Corporation shall, so far 
as may be, comply with the provisions of sections 22 and 23 of 
the said Act so repealed for any of the purposes related to the annual 
accounts of the Commission.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1097554</tid>
<number> 12</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1038738</tid>
<number>1</number>The Oil and Natural Gas Commission  
 (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Ordinance, <year>1993</year> (Ord. 28 of  
  <year>1993</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>693345</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding the repeal of the Oil and Natural Gas 
Commission (Transfer of Undertaking and Repeal) Ordinance, <year>1993</year> (Ord.  
  28 of <year>1993</year>) anything done or any action taken under the said 
Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the 
corresponding provision of this Act.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1702828</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>294426</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called  
the Public Records Act, <year>1993</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>201776</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>365954</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>908915</tid>
<number>a</number>" Board" means the Archival Advisory Board constituted under 
sub- section (1) of section 13;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> 1- 3- <year>1995</year>: Vide Notification No. S. O. 128 (E), dated 1- 3- <year>1995</year>.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1807228</tid>
<number>b</number>" Director General" means the Director General of 
Archives appointed by the Central Government and includes any 
officer authorised by that Government to perform the duties 
of the Director General;

</section>

<section><tid>188193</tid>
<number>c</number>" head of the Archives" means a person holding the 
charge of the Archives of the Union territory Administration;

</section>

<section><tid>310264</tid>
<number>d</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1928177</tid>
<number>e</number>" public records" includes-

<subsection><tid>1334000</tid>
<number>i</number>any document, manuscript and file;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>695920</tid>
<number>ii</number>any microfilm, microfiche and facsimile copy of a 
document;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>246638</tid>
<number>iii</number>any reproduction of image or images embodied in such 
microfilm (whether enlarged or not); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>857460</tid>
<number>iv</number>any other material produced by a computer or by any 
other device,
of any records creating agency;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 3- <year>1995</year>, Vide Notifn. No. S. O. 128E, dated 1- 3- <year>1995</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>383018</tid>
<number>f</number>records creating agency includes,-

<subsection><tid>1203483</tid>
<number>i</number>in relation to the Central Government, any ministry, 
department or office of that Government;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>48485</tid>
<number>ii</number>in relation to any statutory body or corporation wholly 
or substantially controlled or financed by the Central 
Government, or commission or any committee constituted by 
that Government, the offices of the said body, corporation, 
commission or committee;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>607874</tid>
<number>iii</number>in relation to a Union territory Administration, 
any department or office of that Administration;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1427149</tid>
<number>iv</number>in relation to any statutory body or corporation wholly 
or substantially controlled or financed by Union territory 
Administration or commission or any committee constituted by 
that Administration, the offices of the said body, 
corporation, commission or committee;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1440279</tid>
<number>g</number>" records officer" means the officer nominated by the 
records creating agency under sub- section (1) of section 5.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1255193</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power of the Central Government to coordinate, regulate and 
supervise operations connected with administration, management, etc., 
of public records.
<section><tid>623394</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government shall have the power to  
coordinate, regulate and supervise the operations connected with the 
administration, management, preservation, selection, disposal and 
retirement of public records under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>576784</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government in relation to the public records of 
the records creating agencies specified in sub- clauses (i) and (ii) of 
clause (f) of section 2 and the Union territory Administration in 
relation to the public records of the records creating agencies 
specified in sub- clauses (iii) and (iv) of the said clause, may, by 
order, authorise the Director General or the head of the Archives, as 
the case may be, subject to such conditions as may be specified in the 
o[[ rder, to carry out all or any of the following functions, namely:-

<subsection><tid>925131</tid>
<number>a</number>supervision, management and control of the Archives;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1363621</tid>
<number>b</number>acceptance for deposit of public records of permanent 
nature after such period as may be prescribed;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>102134</tid>
<number>c</number>custody, use and withdrawal of public records:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1648293</tid>
<number>d</number>arrangement, preservation and exhibition of public 
records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1759601</tid>
<number>e</number>preparation of inventories, indices, catalogues and 
other reference media of public records; 
[[[ 
 (f) analysing, developing, promoting and coordinating the 
standards, procedures and the techniques for improvement of 
the records management system;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1934894</tid>
<number>g</number>ensuring the maintenance, arrangement and security of 
public records in the SArchives and in the offices of the 
records creating agency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1157936</tid>
<number>h</number>promoting utilisation of available space and 
maintenance equipments for preserving public records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>947310</tid>
<number>i</number>tendering advice to records creating agencies on the 
compilation, classification and disposal of records and 
application of standards, procedures and techniques of 
records management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1575106</tid>
<number>j</number>survey and inspection of public records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>542376</tid>
<number>k</number>organising training programmes in various disciplines 
of Archives administration and records management; 
[ 
 (l) accepting records from any private source;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>440980</tid>
<number>m</number>regulating access to public records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>988484</tid>
<number>n</number>receiving records from defunct bodies and making 
arrangement for securing public records in the event of 
national emergency;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1031783</tid>
<number>o</number>receiving reports on records management and disposal 
practices from the records officer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>48568</tid>
<number>p</number>providing authenticated copies of, or extracts from, 
public records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1524666</tid>
<number>q</number>destroying or disposal of public records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>24570</tid>
<number>r</number>obtaining on lease or purchasing or accepting as gift 
any document of historical or national importance.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>735821</tid>
<number>4</number>Prohibition against taking of public records out of India. 
No person shall take or cause to be taken out of India any public re- 
cords without the prior approval of the Central Government:
Provided that no such prior approval shall be required if any 
public records are taken or sent out of India for any official purpose.


</article>



<article><tid>1057384</tid>
<number> 5</number> Records officer.
<section><tid>796963</tid>
<number>1</number>Every records creating agency shall  
nominate one of its records officer to discharge the functions under 
this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>961830</tid>
<number>2</number>Every records creating agency may set up such number of 
record rooms in such places as it deems fit and shall place each 
record room under the charge of a records officer.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1434878</tid>
<number> 6</number> Responsibilities of records officer.
<section><tid>1634168</tid>
<number>1</number>The records officer  
shall be responsible for-

<subsection><tid>1823404</tid>
<number>a</number>proper arrangement, maintenance and preservation of 
public records under his charge;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1234135</tid>
<number>b</number>periodical review of all public records and weeding out 
public records of euphemeral value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>923442</tid>
<number>c</number>appraisal of public records which are more than twenty- 
five years old in consultation with the National Archives of 
India or, as the case may be, the Archives of the Union 
territory with a view to retaining public records of 
permanent value;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1884959</tid>
<number>d</number>destruction of public records in such manner and 
subject to such conditions as may be prescribed under sub- 
section (1) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1824872</tid>
<number>e</number>compilation of a schedule of retention for public 
records in consultation with the National Archive of India 
or, as the case may be, the Archives of the Union territory;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1258142</tid>
<number>f</number>periodical review for downgrading of classified 
public records in such manner as may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>176693</tid>
<number>g</number>adoption of such standards, procedures and techniques 
as may be recommended from time to time by the National 
Archives of India for improvement of record management 
system and maintenance of security of public records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>273664</tid>
<number>h</number>compilation of annual indices of public records;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1857452</tid>
<number>i</number>compilation of organisational history and annual 
supplement thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>198200</tid>
<number>j</number>assisting the National Archives of India or, as the case 
may be, the Archives of the Union territory for public 
records management;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30945</tid>
<number>k</number>submission of annual report to the Director General or, 
as the case may be, head of the Archives in such manner as 
may be prescribed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>133350</tid>
<number>l</number>transferring of records of any defunct body to the 
National Archives of India or the Archives of the Union 
territory, as the case may be, for preservation.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>187827</tid>
<number>2</number>The records officer shall act under the direction of the 
Director General or, as the case may be, head of the Archives while 
discharging the responsibilities specified in sub- section (1);


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1989260</tid>
<number> 7</number> Records officer to take appropriate action in the event of 
unauthorised removal, destruction, etc., of public records in his 
custody.
<section><tid>642526</tid>
<number>1</number>The records officer shall, in the event of any  
unauthorised removal, destruction, defacement or alteration of any 
public records under his charge, forthwith take appropriate action for 
the recovery or restoration of such public records.

</section>

<section><tid>356454</tid>
<number>2</number>The records officer shall submit a report in writing to the 
Director General or as the case may be, the head of the Archives 
without any delay on any information about any unauthorised removal, 
destruction, defacement or alteration of any public records under his 
charge and about the action initiated by him and shall taken action 
as he may deem necessary subject to the directions, if any, given by 
the Director General or, as the case may be, head of the Archives.

</section>

<section><tid>885373</tid>
<number>3</number>The records officer may seek assistance from any government 
officer or any other person for the purpose of recovery or 
restoration of public records and such officer or person shall render 
all assistance to the records officers.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>904556</tid>
<number> 8</number> Destruction or disposal of public records.
<section><tid>1620932</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise provided in any law for the time being in force no public 
record shall be destroyed or otherwise disposed of except in such 
manner and subject to such conditions as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1747120</tid>
<number>2</number>No record created before the year <year>1892</year> shall be destroyed, 
except where, in the opinion of the Director General or, as the case 
may be, the head of the Archives, it is so defaced or is in such con- 
dition that it cannot be put to any archival use.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1173368</tid>
<number>9</number>Penalty for contraventions. Whoever contravenes any of the 
provisions of section 4 or section 8 shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years or with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees or with both.

</article>



<article><tid>1476962</tid>
<number>10</number>Public records bearing security classification. No public 
records bearing security classification shall be transferred to the 
National Archives of India or the Archives of the Union territory.

</article>



<article><tid>579449</tid>
<number> 11</number> Receipt of records from private sources.
<section><tid>327491</tid>
<number>1</number>The National  
Archives of India or the Archives of the Union territory may accept 
any record of historical or national importance from any private 
source by way of gift, purchase or otherwise.

</section>

<section><tid>189612</tid>
<number>2</number>The National Archives of India or, as the case may be, the 
Archives of any Union territory may, in such manner and subject to 
such conditions as may be prescribed, make any record referred to in 
sub- section (1) available to any bona fide research scholar.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1097554</tid>
<number> 12</number> Access to public records.
<section><tid>1038738</tid>
<number>1</number>All unclassified public  
record, as are more than thirty years old and are transferred to the 
National Archives of India or the Archives of the Union territory may 
be subject to such exceptions and restrictions as may be prescribed 
made available to any bona fide research scholar.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this such section, the period 
of thirty years shall be reckoned from the year of the opening of the 
public record.


</section>

<section><tid>693345</tid>
<number>2</number>Any records creating agency may grant to any person access 
to any public record in its custody in such manner and subject to 
such conditions as may be prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1192862</tid>
<number> 13</number> Archival Advisory Board.
<section><tid>1723859</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute an Archival Advisory 
Board for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1768685</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board shall consist of the following members, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1930787</tid>
<number>a</number>Secretary to the Government of India in the Ministry of 
Central Government dealing with culture (Chairman, ex  
  officio;)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1947244</tid>
<number>b</number>one officer not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the 
Government of India each from the Cabinet Secretariat, 
Ministry of Home Affairs, Ministry of Defence, Ministry of 
External Affairs, Ministry of Finance and Ministry of 
Personnel, Public Grievances and Pension (Members, ex  
  officio;)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>492159</tid>
<number>c</number>two representatives not below the rank of Joint 
Secretary in the Union territory Administrations to be 
nominated by the Central Government (Members);

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1995780</tid>
<number>d</number>three persons to be nominated by the Central 
Government for a period not exceeding three years, one being 
an Archivist and two being Professors in the Post- graduate 
Department of History in any recognised University. (Members)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1932716</tid>
<number>e</number>Director General (Member- Secretary,  
  ex officio).

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>678608</tid>
<number>3</number>The members nominated under clause (d) of sub- section (2) 
shall be paid such allowances as may be prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1522438</tid>
<number> 14</number> Functions of the Board. The Board shall perform the 
following functions, namely:-
<section><tid>891858</tid>
<number>a</number>advise the Central Government and Union territory 
Administrations on matters concerning the administration, 
management, conservation and use of public records;

</section>

<section><tid>628227</tid>
<number>b</number>lay down guidelines for training of Archivists;

</section>

<section><tid>1977692</tid>
<number>c</number>give directions for acquisition of records from private 
custody;

</section>

<section><tid>121119</tid>
<number>d</number>deal with such other matters as may be prescribed.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>801558</tid>
<number>15</number>Power of the Director General to lay down norms and 
standards for courses in archival science. The Director General shall 
have the power to lay down norms and standards for courses curricula, 
assessment and examinations relating to the training in archival 
science and other ancillary subjects.

</article>



<article><tid>606370</tid>
<number>16</number>Protection of action taken in good faith. No Suit, 
prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against any person in 
respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done 
in pursuance of this Act or the rules made thereunder.

</article>



<article><tid>1528784</tid>
<number> 17</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1339011</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1196553</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>835369</tid>
<number>a</number>the period after which public records of permanent 
nature may be accepted under clause (b) of sub- section (2) of 
section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1598461</tid>
<number>b</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
public records can be destroyed under clause (d) of sub- 
section (1) of section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>600685</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which periodical review of classified 
public records for downgrading shall be undertaken under 
clause (f) of sub- section (1) of section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1438972</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which the records officer will report to 
the Director General or the head of the Archives under clause 
 (k) of sub- section (1) of section 6;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>637743</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
public records may be destroyed or disposed of under sub- 
section (1) of section 8;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1865476</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
records of historical or national importance may be made 
available to research scholar under sub- section (2) of 
section 11;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>538499</tid>
<number>g</number>exceptions and restrictions subject to which public 
records may be made available to a research scholar under 
sub- section (1) of section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>548851</tid>
<number>h</number>the manner in which and the conditions subject to which 
any records creating agency may grant to any person access to 
public records in its custody under sub- section (2) of 
section 12;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1310151</tid>
<number>i</number>the allowances payable to members of the Board under 
sub- section (3) of section 13;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>827668</tid>
<number>j</number>the matters with respect to which the Board may perform 
its functions under clause (d) of section 14;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>314919</tid>
<number>k</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1955121</tid>
<number>18</number>Laying of rules before Parliament. Every rule made under 
this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period 
of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything pre- 
viously done under that rule.

</article>



 </act>