<act><tid>286852</tid>
<title>THE INDIAN FISHERIES ACT, <year>1897</year></title>

ACT NO. 4 OF <year>1897</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 4th February, <year>1897</year>.]

An Act to provide for certain matters relating to Fisheries <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>.

WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for certain matters relating 
to fisheries <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>;

It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>580955</tid>
<number> 1</number> Title and extent.
<section><tid>602280</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Indian  
Fisheries Act, <year>1897</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>984370</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the territories 
which, immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>, were comprised in 
Part B States] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>; <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>.
<footcitenum>5</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>727497</tid>
<number>2</number>Act to be read as supplemental to other Fisheries Laws. 
Subject to the provisions of sections 8 and 10 of the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> General 
Clauses Act, <year>1887</year> (1 of <year>1887</year>), this Act shall be read as supplemental 
to any other enactment <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> for the time being in force relating to 
fisheries in <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> the territories to which this Act extends] <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>.


</article>



<article><tid>1135968</tid>
<number> 3</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1927241</tid>
<number>1</number>" fish" includes shell- fish;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Extended to Goa, Daman and Diu with modifications, by Reg. 12 of <year>1962</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch. The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide 
Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi islands (w. e. f.  
  1- 101967): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch. Madhya Pradesh by the 
C. P. and Berar Fisheries Act, <year>1948</year> (C. P. and B. Act 8 of <year>1948</year>).

Repealed in its application to Ballery District by Mysore Act 14 of <year>1955</year>.

Amendmend in Andhra Pradesh by A. P. Act 5 of <year>1961</year>.

Repealed in Bombay area by Maharashtra Act 1 of <year>1961</year>.

Amendmend in Pondicherry by Pondy. Act 18 of <year>1965</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been rep. in Madhya Pradesh by the C. P. and Berar 
Fisheries Act, <year>1948</year> (C. P. and B. Act 8 of <year>1948</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" in the Provinces" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3. Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" Part B 
States". 
4. The words" except Burma" rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
5. The word" and" at the end of sub- section (2), and sub- section 
 (3), rep. by Act 10 of <year>1914</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II. 
6. See now ss. 4 and 26 of the General Clauses Act, <year>1897</year> (10 of  
  <year>1897</year>). 
7. For law relating to Fisheries in--

(1) Assam, see the Assam Land and Revenue Regulation, <year>1886</year> (1 of  
  <year>1886</year>), ss. 16 and 155; 
 (2) Bengal and Assam (Private Fisheries), see the Private 
Fisheries Protection Act, <year>1889</year> (Ben. 2 of <year>1889</year>); 
 (3) Nilgiris District, as to acclimatised fish, see the Nilgiris 
Game and Fish Preservation Act, <year>1879</year> (Mad. 2 of <year>1879</year>); 
 (4) Punjab, see the Punjab Fisheries Act, <year>1914</year> (Pun. 2 of <year>1914</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" a Part 
A State or a Part C State".



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>680132</tid>
<number>2</number>" fixed engine" means any net, cage, trap or other 
contrivance for taking fish, fixed in the soil or made 
stationary in any other way; and

</section>

<section><tid>1851412</tid>
<number>3</number>" private water" means water which is the exclusive 
property of any person or in which any person has for 
the time being an exclusive right of fishery whether as 
owner, lessee or in any other capacity.
Explanation.-- Water shall not cease to be" private 
water" within the meaning of this definition by reason 
only that other persons may have by custom a right of 
fishery therein.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>28604</tid>
<number> 4</number> Destruction of fish by explosives in inland waters and on 
coasts.
<section><tid>87431</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person uses any dynamite or other explosive  
substance in any water with intent thereby to catch or destroy any of 
the fish that may be therein, he shall be punishable with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to two months, or with fine which may 
extend to two hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>1258978</tid>
<number>2</number>In sub- section (1) the word" water" includes the sea within a 
distance of one marine league of the sea- coast; and an offence 
committed under that sub- section in such sea may be tried, punished 
and in all respects dealt with as if it had been committed on the land 
abutting on such coast.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1819546</tid>
<number> 5</number> Destruction of fish by poisoning of waters.
<section><tid>1528459</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person  
puts any poison, lime or noxious material into any water with intent 
thereby to catch or destroy any fish, he shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two months, or with fine 
which may extend to two hundred rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>72856</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, suspend the operation of this section in any specified area, 
and may in like manner modify or cancel any such notification.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1136850</tid>
<number> 6</number> Protection of fish in selected waters by rules of State 
Government.
<section><tid>148608</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may make rules <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> for the  
purposes hereinafter in this section mentioned, and may by 
notification in the Official Gazette apply all or any of such rules to 
such waters, not being private waters, as the State Government may 
specify in the said notification.

</section>

<section><tid>576074</tid>
<number>2</number>The State Government may also, by like notification, apply 
such rules or any of them to any private water with the consent in 
writing of the owner thereof and of all persons having for the time 
being any exclusive right of fishery therein.

</section>

<section><tid>36381</tid>
<number>3</number>Such rules may prohibit or regulate all or any of the 
following matters, that is to say:-

<subsection><tid>1401968</tid>
<number>a</number>the erection and use of fixed engines;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For rules under s. 6, see different local Rules and Orders.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1345826</tid>
<number>b</number>the construction of weirs; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1876731</tid>
<number>c</number>the dimension and kind of the nets to be used and the 
modes of using them.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1747213</tid>
<number>4</number>Such rules may also prohibit all fishing in any specified 
water for a period not exceeding two years.

</section>

<section><tid>356194</tid>
<number>5</number>In making any rule under this section the State Government 
may--

<subsection><tid>1297738</tid>
<number>a</number>Direct that a breach of it shall be punishable with 
fine which may extend to one hundred rupees, and, when 
the breach is a continuing breach, with a further fine 
which may extend to ten rupees for every day after the 
date of the first conviction during which the breach is 
proved to have been persisted in; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>510767</tid>
<number>b</number>provide for--

<subsubsection><tid>1558878</tid>
<number>i</number>the seizure, forfeiture and removal of 
fixed engines, erected or used, or nets used, in 
contravention of the rule, and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>875042</tid>
<number>ii</number>the forfeiture of any fish taken by 
means of any such fixed engine or net.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1836309</tid>
<number>6</number>The power to make rules under this section is subject to the 
condition that they shall be made after previous publication.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1394341</tid>
<number> 7</number> Arrest without warrant for offences under this Act.
<section><tid>1681324</tid>
<number>1</number>Any  
police- officer, or other person <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> specially empowered by the State 
Government in this behalf, either by name or as holding any office, 
for the time being, may, without an order from a Magistrate and 
without warrant, arrest any person committing in his view any offence 
punishable under section 4 or 5 or under any rule under section 6--

<subsection><tid>254327</tid>
<number>a</number>if the name and address of the person are unknown to 
him, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1326059</tid>
<number>b</number>if the person declines to give his name and address, or 
if there is reason to doubt the accuracy of the name 
and address if given.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>624935</tid>
<number>2</number>A person arrested under this section may be detained until 
his name and address have been correctly ascertained:
Provided that no person so arrested shall be detained longer than 
may be necessary for bringing him before a Magistrate, except under 
the order of a Magistrate for his detention.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For notification under this section vin Madras, see Fort St. 
George Gazette, <year>1903</year>, Pt. I, p. 19.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>