<act><title>THE TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
(SALARIES, ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND 
WHOLE-TIME MEMBERS) RULES, 20001</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement</title>.
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India (Salaries, Allowances and other 
Conditions of Service of Chairperson and Whole-time Members) Rules, 2000. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the 
Official Gazette. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions</title>.In these rules, unless the context otherwise 
requires,
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act, means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India Act, 1997 (24 of 
  1997);
 </section><section><number>b</number> Authority, means the Telecom Regulatory Authority of India 
  established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Act;
 </section><section><number>c</number> Chairperson, means the Chairperson of the Authority appointed under 
  sub-section (3) of section 3 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> Member, means a whole-time Member of the Authority appointed under 
  sub-section (3) of section 3 of the Act;
 </section><section><number>e</number> All other words and expressions used herein but not defined shall have 
  the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> (i) Salaries and allowances.</title>
 
 
 <section><number>a</number> The Chairperson shall be paid a salary of Rs. 30,000/- per month 
    (fixed).
 </section><section><number>b</number> The Member shall be paid a salary of Rs. 26,000/- per month 
    (fixed).
 </section><section><number>c</number> <title>Dearness Allowance and City Compensatory 
    Allowance</title>.The Chairperson and a Member shall be entitled to draw 
    dearness allowance and city compensatory allowance at the rate applicable to 
    a Group A officer of the Central Government drawing an equivalent 
  pay:</section>
 Provided that in case of appointment of a person as the Chairperson or a 
  Member who has retired from the service under Central Government or State 
  Government and who is in receipt of, or has received or has become entitled to 
  receive any retirement benefits by way of pension, gratuity, employers 
  contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund or other forms of retirement 
  benefits, the pay of such Chairperson or Member, shall be reduced by the gross 
  amount of pension or employers contribution to the Contributory Provident Fund 
  or any other form of retirement benefits, if any (except pension equivalent of 
  gratuity), drawn or to be drawn by him:
 Provided further that if a person who has retired from any service 
  including service under Central Government or State Government, Public Sector 
  Undertakings and/or Autonomous Bodies is appointed as the Chairperson or a 
  Member, he shall be entitled to receive dearness allowance at the same rate as 
  applicable to a Group A officer of the Central Government drawing an 
  equivalent pay, but he shall not be entitled to receive dearness relief on 
  pension during the period he holds office as such Chairperson or a Member. 

 <section><title><number>ii</number> Leave</title>.The Chairperson or a Member shall be entitled 
  to thirty days of earned leave for every year of service. The payment of leave 
  salary during leave shall be governed by rule 40 of the Central Civil Service 
  (Leave) Rules, 1972. The Chairperson or Member shall be entitled to encashment 
  of fifty percent of earned leave to his credit at any time. 
 </section><section><title><number>iii</number> Provident Fund</title>.The Chairperson and a Member shall 
  be entitled to subscribe to the Contributory Provident Fund which shall be 
  governed by the Contributory Provident Fund Rules, 1962. 
 </section><section><title><number>iv</number> Travelling Allowance and Daily Allowance.</title>The 
  Chairperson and a Member shall be entitled to travelling allowance and daily 
  allowance for transportation of personal effects while on tour or on transfer 
  (including the journey undertaken to join the Authority or on the expiry of 
  his term with the Authority to proceed to his home-town), at the same rates as 
  applicable to Group A officer of the Central Government drawing an 
  equivalent pay. 
 </section><section><title><number>v</number> Domestic official tours</title>.The Chairperson and a Member, 
  while on tour, shall be entitled to the facility of Government accommodation 
  in guest houses or inspection bungalows run by the Central Government, 
  wherever available, on payment of normal rent at outstations, as applicable to 
  Group A Officers of the Central Government drawing an equivalent pay.  In 
  case Government accommodation is not available while on domestic official 
  tour, the Chairperson and a Member shall be entitled to stay in India Tourism 
  Development Corporation hotels on a reimbursement basis and wherever India 
  Tourism Development Corporation hotels are not available, in other hotels on 
  reimbursement basis, re-imbursement in both cases being limited to lodging 
  charges only, and on a single room occupancy basis;
 </section><section><title><number>vi</number> Leave Travel Concession</title>.The Chairperson and a Member 
  shall be entitled to leave travel concession at the same rate as applicable to 
  Group A officers of the Central Government drawing an equivalent pay;
 </section><section><title><number>vii</number> Medical Facilities</title>.The Chairperson and a Member 
  shall be entitled to medical treatment and hospital facilities, as provided in 
  the Central Government Health Scheme and at places where the Central 
  Government Health Scheme is not in operation, the Chairperson and a Member 
  shall be entitled to facilities as provided in the Central Services (Medical 
  Attendance) Rules, 1944; 
 </section><section><title><number>viii</number> Official Visits Abroad</title>.The Chairperson and a 
  Member shall be entitled to undertake official visits abroad with the prior 
  approval of the Minister of the Government of India in-charge of the 
  Department of Telecommunications and after clearance from Ministry of External 
  Affairs on the points relating to political affairs. The daily allowance and 
  provision accommodation during the period of tour abroad shall be regulated in 
  accordance with the Government instructions as applicable to officers of equal 
  grade in the Government of India. Indian Missions abroad shall take care of 
  arrangements and extend facilities as applicable to Group A officers of the 
  Central Government drawing an equivalent pay;
 </section><section><title><number>ix</number></title> <title>Conveyance facility</title>.The Chairperson 
  and a Member shall be entitled to conveyance facilities at par with those 
  available to a Group A officer of the Central Government drawing an 
  equivalent pay;
 </section><section><title><number>x</number> Accommodation</title>.(a) The Chairperson is entitled to rent 
  free furnished residential accommodation at the rates specified by the Central 
  Government from time to time for this purpose or house rent allowance at the 
  rate of twelve-and-a-half percent of his pay in lieu thereof; and
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> a Member shall be entitled to residential accommodation as applicable 
    to Group A officers of the Central Government drawing an equivalent 
    pay.</subsection>
   On demitting office, the Chairperson and Member shall be 
  entitled to retention of residential accommodation for one month, on the same 
  terms and conditions. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Oath of Office and Secrecy.</title>Every person appointed to be 
the Chairperson and Member shall, before entering upon their office, make and 
subscribe an Oath of Office and Secrecy, in the FORMS I and II annexed to these 
rules. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Interpretation.</title>If any question arises relating to the 
interpretation of these rules the same shall be referred to the Central 
Government for its decision. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Residuary provision.</title>Matters relating to the terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairperson or a Member with respect to which no 
express provision has been made in these rules, shall be referred by the 
Authority to the Central Government for its decision, and the decision of the 
Central Government thereon shall be applicable to the Chairperson or Member, as 
the case may be. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Power to relax</title>.The Central Government shall have power 
to relax any provision of these rules in respect of Chairperson on any other 
Member. 

</article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

THE TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
      (SALARIES, ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND 
      WHOLE-TIME MEMBERS) RULES, 2000
 

 
 

FORM I
 

(See rule 4)
 

Form of Oath of Office for the Chairperson/Members of  
the 
      Telecom Regulatory Authority of India
 

 
 

I, 
      ................................., having been appointed as the 
      Chairperson/Member (cross out portion not applicable) solemnly 
      affirm and do swear in the name of God I will faithfully and 
      conscientiously discharge my duties as the Chairperson/Member  
      (cross out portion not applicable), of the Telecom Regulatory 
      Authority of India, to the best of my ability, knowledge and judgement, 
      without fear or favour, affection or ill-will. 
 

 
 

Dated: 
                                 
              
 

 
 

(Name of the 
      Chairperson/Member)
 

TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF 
      INDIA 
 

 
 
 

 </form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

THE TELECOM REGULATORY AUTHORITY OF INDIA 
      (SALARIES, ALLOWANCES AND OTHER CONDITIONS OF SERVICE OF CHAIRPERSON AND 
      WHOLE-TIME MEMBERS) RULES, 2000
 

 
 

FORM II
 

(See rule 4)
 

Form of Oath of Secrecy for the Chairperson/Members of  
the 
      Telecom Regulatory Authority of India
 

 
 

I, ...................., having 
      been appointed as the Chairperson/Member (cross out portion not 
      applicable) do solemnly affirm and swear in the name of God that I 
      will not directly or indirectly communicate or reveal to any person or 
      persons any matter which shall be brought under my consideration or shall 
      become known to me as the Chairperson/ Member  (cross out portion 
      not applicable), of the said Telecom Regulatory Authority of India, 
      except as may be required for the due discharge of my duties as the 
      Chairperson/Member (cross out portion not applicable).  
 

 
 

Dated:
 

(Name of the 
      Chairperson/Member)
 

                                
               TELECOM REGULATORY 
      AUTHORITY OF INDIA
 

 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>