<act><tid>289628</tid>
<title>THE SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF OFFICERS OF PARLIAMENT AND LEADERS 
OFOPPOSITION IN PARLIAMENT (SECOND AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2002</year></title>

ACT NO. 56 OF <year>2002</year>
[ 17th December, <year>2002</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Salaries and Allowances of Officers of 
Parliament Act, <year>1953</year> and the Salary and Allowances of Leaders of 
Opposition in Parliament Act, <year>1977</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- third Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>755129</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>714146</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Salaries and Allowances of Officers of Parliament and Leaders of 
Opposition in Parliament (Second Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>

</section>

<section><tid>1327404</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 17th day of 
September, <year>2001</year>.
CHAP

AMENDMENT TO THE SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF OFFICERS OF PARLIAMENTACT, <year>1953</year>

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENT TO THE SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF OFFICERS OF PARLIAMENT 
ACT, <year>1953</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1925290</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 6 of Act 20 of <year>1953</year>.- In section 6 of the 
Salaries and Allowances of Officers of Parliament Act, <year>1953</year>, for 
sub- section (1A), the following sub- section shall be substituted, 
namely:-
" (1A) On and from the commencement of the Salaries and Allowances of 
Officers of Parliament and Leaders of Opposition in Parliament (Second  
  Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, an officer of Parliament and his family, whether 
traveling together or separately, shall be ntitled to traveling 
allowance at the same rates and for the same number of return journeys 
as admissible to a Minister and his family under sub- section (1A) of 
section 6 of the Salaries and Allowances of Ministers Act, <year>1952</year> (58 of  
  <year>1952</year>).".

CHAP

AMENDMENT TO THE SALARY AND ALLOWANCES OF LEADERS OF OPPOSITION 
INPARLIAMENT ACT, <year>1977</year>

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENT TO THE SALARY AND ALLOWANCES OF LEADERS OF OPPOSITION IN 
PARLIAMENT ACT, <year>1977</year>



</article>



<article><tid>162058</tid>
<number>3</number>Amendment of section 5 of Act 33 of <year>1977</year>.- In section 5 of the 
Salary and Allowances of Leaders of Opposition in Parliament Act, 
<year>1977</year>, for sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (2) On and from the commencement of the Salaries and Allowances of 
Officers of Parliament and Leaders of Opposition in Parliament (Second  
  Amendment) Act, <year>2002</year>, a Leader of the Opposition and his family, 
whether traveling together or separately, shall be entitled to 
traveling allowance at the same rates and for the same number of 
return journeys as admissible to a Minister and his family under 
sub- section (1A) of section 6 of the Salaries and Allowances of 
Ministers Act, <year>1952</year> (58 of <year>1952</year>).".



SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>