<act><tid>292060</tid>
<title>THE COAL BEARING AREAS (ACQUISITION AND DEVELOPMENT) AMENDMENT 
ANDVALIDATION ACT, <year>1971</year></title>

ACT NO. 54 OF <year>1971</year>
[ 11th December, <year>1971</year>.

An Act further to amend the Coal Bearing Areas (Acquisition and  
  Development) Act, <year>1957</year>, and to validate certain acquisitions of land 
or rights in or over land under the said Act.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- second Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1481942</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Coal Bearing Areas 
 (Acquisition and Development) Amendment and Validation Act, <year>1971</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1316021</tid>
<number> 8</number> Validation of certain acquisitions.
<section><tid>482913</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding any  
judgment, decree or order of any court to the contrary,-

<subsection><tid>184807</tid>
<number>a</number>no acquisition of land or of rights in or over land 
made or purporting to have been made under the principal Act 
before the commencement of this Act, and no action taken or 
thing done (including any order made, agreement entered into  
  or notification published) in connection with such 
acquisition shall be- deemed to be invalid or ever to have 
become invalid merely on the ground-

<subsubsection><tid>524190</tid>
<number>i</number>that one or more competent authorities have performed 
the functions of competent authority under the principal Act 
in respect of the land covered by the same notification 
under sub- section (1) of section 7 of the principal Act;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1660648</tid>
<number>ii</number>that One or more reports have been made under sub- 
section (2) of section 8 of the principal Act, whether in 
respect of the entire land covered by the same notification 
under sub- section (1) of section 7 of the principal Act or 
rights in or over such land, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>122</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

in respect of different parcels of such land or of rights in 
or over such land;


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>691308</tid>
<number>iii</number>that one or more declarations have been made under 
section 9 of the principal Act in respect of different 
parcels of the land covered by the same notification under 
sub- section (1) of section 7 of the principal Act or in 
respect of rights in or over such land,

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1923722</tid>
<number>b</number>any acquisition in pursuance of any notification issued 
under sub- section (1) of section 7 of the principal Act 
before the commencement of this Act may be made after such 
commencement and no such acquisition and no action taken or 
thing done (including any order made, agreement entered into  
  or notification published) whether before or after such 
commencement, in connection with such acquisition shall be 
deemed to be invalid merely on the grounds referred to in 
clause (a) or any of them.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>165998</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (b) of sub- sec- 
tion (1), no declaration under section 9 of the principal Act in 
respect of any land, or rights in or over such land, which has been 
notified before the commencement of this Act, under sub- section (1) of 
section 7 of the principal Act, shall be made after the expiry of two 
years from the commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1030098</tid>
<number>3</number>Where acquisition of any particular land (not being acquisi-  
  tion of rights in or over such land) covered by a notification under 
sub- section (1) of section 7 of the principal Act, issued before the 
commencement of this Act, is or has been made in pursuance of any 
declaration under section 9 of the principal Act, whether made before 
or after such commencement, and such declaration is or has been made 
after the expiry of three years from the date of issue of such 
notification, there shall be paid simple interest, calculated at the 
rate of six per centum per annum on the market value of such land, as 
determined under sub- section (5) of section 13 of the principal Act, 
from the date of expiry of the said period of three years to the 
date of tender of payment of compensation payable for the acquisition 
of such land:
Provided that no such interest shall be payable for any period 
during which the proceedings for the acquisition of any land were held 
up an account of stay or injunction by order of a court:

Provided further that nothing in this sub- section shall apply to 
the acquisition of any land where. the amount of compensation has been 
paid to the persons interested before the commencement of this Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>123</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>