<act> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
India.
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall be deemed to have 
come into force on the 2nd day of October, 1997. 
</section></article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  “bumper draw of a lottery” means a special draw 
of lottery conducted on or during any festival or other special occasion wherein 
the prize money offered is greater than the prize money offered in the case of 
other ordinary draw of lotteries;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  “lottery” means a scheme, in whatever form and 
by whatever name called, for distribution of prizes by lot or chance to those 
persons participating in the chances of a prize by purchasing tickets;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made 
under this Act.
</section></article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>3</number> Prohibition of lotteries.—Save 
as otherwise provided in section 4, no State Government shall organise, conduct 
or promote any lottery.
</article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>4</number> Conditions subject to 
which lotteries may be organised etc.—A 
State Government may organise, conduct or promote a lottery, subject to 
the following conditions, namely:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  prizes shall not be offered on any pre-announced 
number or on the basis of a single digit;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  the State Government shall print the lottery 
tickets bearing the imprint and logo of the State in such manner that the 
authenticity of the lottery ticket is ensured;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  the State Government shall sell the tickets 
either itself or through distributors or selling agents;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  the proceeds of the sale of lottery tickets 
shall be credited into the public account of the State;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  the State Government itself shall conduct the 
draws of all the lotteries;
 </section><section>        <number>f</number>  the prize money unclaimed within such time as 
may be prescribed by the State Government or not otherwise distributed, shall 
become the property of that Government;
 </section><section> <number>g</number>  the place of draw shall be located within 
the State concerned; 
 </section><section>       <number>h</number> no lottery shall have more than one draw 
in a week;
 </section><section>        <number>i</number>  the draws of all kinds of lotteries shall be 
conducted between such period of the day as may be prescribed by the State 
Government;
 </section><section>        <number>j</number>  the number of bumper draws of a lottery shall 
not be more than six in a calendar year;
 </section><section> <number>k</number>  such other conditions as may be 
prescribed by the Central Government. 


</section></article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>5</number> Prohibition of sale of 
ticket in a State.—A State Government 
may, within the State, prohibit the sale of tickets of a lottery organised, 
conducted or promoted by every other State.


</article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>6</number> Prohibition of 
organisation etc., of lottery.—The 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, prohibit a 
lottery organised, conducted or promoted in contravention of the provisions of 
section 4 or where tickets of such lottery are sold in contravention of the 
provisions of section 5.
</article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>7</number> Penalty.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where a lottery is organised, conducted or promoted after the date on which this 
Act receives the assent of the President, in contravention of the provisions of 
this Act, by any Department of the State Government, the Head of the Department 
shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
two years or with fine or with both:
 Provided that nothing contained 
in this section shall render such Head of the Department liable to any 
punishment if he proves that the contravention was committed without his 
knowledge or that he exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of 
such contravention.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), where a contravention under this Act has been 
committed by a Department of Government and it is proved that the contravention 
has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any 
neglect on the part of, any officer, other than the Head of the Department, such 
officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that contravention and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If any person acts as an 
agent or promoter or trader in any lottery organised, conducted or promoted in 
contravention of the provisions of this Act or sells, distributes or purchases 
the ticket of such lottery, he shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to two years or with fine or with both.
</section></article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>8</number> Offences to be cognizable 
and non-bailable.—The offence under 
this Act shall be cognizable and non-bailable.
</article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>9</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person 
who at the time the offence was committed was incharge of, and was responsible 
to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 Provided that nothing contained 
in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment if he 
proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or that he had 
exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been 
committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with 
the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to, any neglect on the part of, 
any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, 
manager, secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the 
offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  “company” means any body corporate and includes 
a firm or other association of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  “director”, in relation to a firm, means a 
partner in the firm.


</subsection></section></article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>10</number> Power to give directions.—The 
Central Government may give directions to the State Government as to carrying 
into execution in the State of any of the provisions of this Act or of any rule 
or order made thereunder.
</article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>11</number> Power of Central 
Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to 
carry out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every rule made by the 
Central Government shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the 
session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule, or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, 
the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no 
effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that rule.
</section></article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>12</number> Power of State Government 
to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out 
the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for 
all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  time to be fixed for claiming prize money under 
clause (f) of section 4;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  period to be fixed for draws of all lotteries 
under clause (i) of section 4; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  any other matter which is required to be, or may 
be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made by the State 
Government under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, 
before each House of the State Legislature where it consists of two Houses, or 
where such Legislature consists of one House, before that House.
</section></article> 
 The Lotteries (Regulation) Act, 1998
  
 <article><number>13</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> The Lotteries (Regulation) 
Ordinance, 1998 (Ord. 6 of 1998), is hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance, shall be deemed to have been done or taken under 
the corresponding provisions of this Act.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>