<act><tid>302871</tid>
<title>THE SUGAR CESS ACT, <year>1982</year></title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>1982</year>
[ 19th March, <year>1982</year>.]

An Act to provide for the imposition of a cess on sugar for the 
development of sugar industry and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Thirty- third Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>210223</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>653351</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Sugar Cess Act, <year>1982</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>332260</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>571824</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>269555</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1676267</tid>
<number>a</number>" occupier", in relation to any sugar factory, means the 
person who has ultimate control over the affairs of the sugar 
factory or the owner of the sugar factory in case he is not the 
occupier;

</section>

<section><tid>1973951</tid>
<number>b</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1978961</tid>
<number>c</number>" sugar factory" means any premises (including the  
  precincts thereof) in any part of which sugar is manufactured by 
vacuum pan process;

</section>

<section><tid>223453</tid>
<number>d</number>" sugar" means any form of sugar including crushed sugar 
or sugar in crystalised or powder form, containing ninety per 
cent, or more of sucrose and produced by the vacuum pan process 
and includes raw sugar produced by the said process.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>223295</tid>
<number> 3</number> Imposition of cess.
<section><tid>542219</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and collected as  
a cess, for the purposes of the Sugar Development Fund Act, <year>1982</year>, a 
duty of excise on all sugar produced by any sugar factory in India, at 
such rate not exceeding <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fifteen rupees] per quintal of sugar, as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
specify from time to time:
Provided that until such rate is specified by the Central 
Government, the duty of excise shall be levied and collected at the 
rate of <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> fourteen rupees] per quintal of sugar.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>14</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 6- <year>1982</year>: vide notification No. G. S. R. <footcitenum>435</footcitenum> E], dated 29- 5- 
<year>1982</year>, Gazette of India, Extraordinary <year>1982</year>, Pt. II, Sec. 3 (i).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Substituted by Act 57 of <year>1982</year>, section 2 for ten rupees" (w. e. f.  
  1- 11- <year>1982</year>)"

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Substituted by s. 2, ibid for" five rupees,"" (w. e. f. 1- 11-  
  <year>1982</year>)"


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>302263</tid>
<number>2</number>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be in 
addition to the duty of excise leviable on sugar under the Central 
Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year>, (1 of <year>1944</year>.) or any other law for the time 
being in force.

</section>

<section><tid>152203</tid>
<number>3</number>The duty of excise levied under sub- section (1) shall be 
payable by the occupier of the sugar factory in which sugar is 
produced.

</section>

<section><tid>1159457</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of the Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year>, (1  
  of <year>1944</year>.) and the rules made thereunder, including those relating to 
refunds and exemptions from duty, shall, so far as may be, apply in 
relation to the levy and collection of the said duty of excise as they 
apply in relation to the levy and collection of the duty of excise on 
sugar under that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>648332</tid>
<number>4</number>Crediting proceeds of duty to Consolidated Fund of India. The 
proceeds of the duty of excise levied under section 3 shall be 
credited to the Consolidated Fund of India.


</article>



<article><tid>270774</tid>
<number>5</number>Power to call for reports and returns. The Central Government 
may require an occupier of a sugar factory to furnish, for the 
purposes of this Act, such statistical and other information in such 
form and within such period as may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1555693</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>906431</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1694997</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for the form in which and the 
period within which statistical and other information may be furnished 
under section 5.

</section>

<section><tid>1286864</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as 
may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is 
in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised 
in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>