<act> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Air Corporations (Transfer of Undertakings and 
Repeal) Act, 1994.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It shall be deemed to 
have come into force on the 29th day of January, 1994.
</section></article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  “appointed day” means such date 
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
under section 3;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “company” means “Indian Airlines 
Limited” or “Air India Limited” formed and registered under the Companies Act, 
1956 (1 of 1956);
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  “corporations” means “Indian 
Airlines” and “Air India” established under section 3 of the Air Corporations 
Act, 1953 (27 of 1953) and “corporation” means either of the corporations.
</section></article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Undertakings of 
corporations to vest in companies.—On 
such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, appoint, there shall be transferred to, and vest in,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  Indian Airlines Limited, the 
undertaking of Indian Airlines; and
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  Air India Limited, the 
undertaking of Air India.
</section></article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> General effect of 
vesting of undertakings in the companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The undertaking of a corporation which is transferred to, and which vests in, a 
company under section 3 shall be deemed to include all assets, rights, powers, 
authorities and privileges and all properties, movable and immovable, real or 
personal, corporeal or incorporeal, in possession or reservation, present or 
contingent, of whatever nature and wheresoever-situate, including lands, words, 
workshops, aircraft cash balances, capital reserves, reserve funds, 
investments, tenancies, leases and book debts and all other rights and 
interests arising out of such property as were immediately before the appointed 
day in the ownership, possession or power of that corporation in relation to 
its undertaking, whether within or outside India, all books of account and 
documents relating thereto and shall also be deemed to include all borrowings, 
liabilities and obligations of whatever kind then subsisting of that 
corporation in relation to its undertaking.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All contracts and 
working arrangements subsisting immediately before the appointed day and 
affecting a corporation shall, in so far as they relate to the undertaking of 
that corporation cease to have effect or to be enforceable against that 
corporation and shall be of as full force and effect against or in favour of 
the company in which the undertaking has vested by virtue of this Act and 
enforceable as fully and effectually as if, instead of the corporation, the 
company had been named therein or had been a party thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any proceeding or 
cause of action pending or existing immediately before the appointed day by or 
against a corporation in relation to its undertaking may, as from that day, be 
continued and enforced by or against the company in which it has vested by 
virtue of this Act, as it might have been enforced by or against that 
corporation if this Act had not been passed, and shall cease to be enforceable 
by or against that corporation.
</section></article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Licences etc., to be 
deemed to have been granted to companies.—With 
effect from the appointed day, all licences, permits, quotas and exemptions 
granted to a corporation in connection with the affairs and business of that 
corporation under any law for the time being in force, shall be deemed to have 
been granted to the company in which the undertaking of that corporation has 
vested.


</article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Tax exemption or 
benefit to continue to have effect.—Where 
any exemption from, or any assessment with respect to any tax has been granted 
or made or any benefit by way of set off or carry forward, as the case may be, 
of any unabsorbed depreciation or investment allowance or other allowance or 
loss has been extended or is available to a corporation under the Income-tax 
Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), such exemption, assessment or benefit shall 
continue to have effect in relation, to the company in which the undertaking of 
that corporation has vested.
 <section>
<number>2</number> Where any payment 
made by a corporation is exempt from deduction of the tax at source under any 
provision of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), the exemption from tax will 
continue to be available as if the provisions of the said Act made applicable 
to the corporation were operative in relation to the company in which the 
undertaking of that corporation has been vested.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The transfer and 
vesting of the undertaking or any part thereof in terms of section 3 shall not 
be construed as a transfer within the meaning of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 
of 1961), for the purposes of capital gains.
</section></article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Guarantee to be 
operative.—Any 
guarantee given for or in favour of a corporation with respect to any loan or 
lease finance shall continue to be operative in relation to the company in 
which the undertaking of that corporation has vested by virtue of this Act.


</article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Provisions in respect 
of officers and other employees of corporations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every officer or other employee of a corporation (except a Director of the 
Board, Chairman, Managing Director or any other person entitled to manage the 
whole or a substantial part of the business and affairs of the corporation) 
serving in its employment immediately before the appointed day shall, in so far 
as such officer or other employee is employed in connection with the 
undertaking which has vested in a company by virtue of this Act, become, as 
from the appointed day, an officer or other employee, as the case may be, of 
the company in which the undertaking has vested and shall hold his office or 
service therein by the same tenure, at the same remuneration, upon the same 
terms and conditions, with the same obligations and with the same rights and 
privileges as to leave, passage, insurance, superannuation scheme, provident 
fund, other funds retirement, pension, gratuity and other benefits as he would 
have held under that corporation if its undertaking had not vested in the 
company and shall continue to do so as an officer or other employee, as the 
case may be, of the company or until the expiry of a period of six months from 
the appointed day if such officer or other employee opts not to be the officer 
or other employee of the company, within such period.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an officer or 
other employee of a corporation opts under sub-section (1) not to be in the 
employment or service of the company in which the undertaking of that 
corporation has vested, such officer or other employee shall be deemed to have 
resigned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) or in any 
other law for the time being in force, the transfer of the services of any 
officer or other employee of a corporation to a company shall not entitle such 
officer or other employee to any compensation under this Act or under any other 
law for the time being in force and no such claim shall be entertained by any 
Court, tribunal or other authority;
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The officers and 
other employees who have retired before the appointed day from the service of a 
corporation and are entitled to any benefits, rights or privileges shall be 
entitled to receive the same benefits, rights or privileges from the company in 
which the undertaking of that corporation has vested.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The trusts of the 
Provident Fund or Pilots Group Insurance and Superannuation Scheme of the 
corporation and any other bodies created for the welfare of officers or 
employees would continue to discharge their functions in the company as was 
being done hitherto in the corporation. Tax exemption granted to Provident Fund 
or Pilots Group Insurance and Superannuation Scheme would continue to be 
applied to the company.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act or in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or in 
any other law for the time being in force or in the regulations of a 
corporation, no Director of the Board, Chairman, Managing Director or any other 
person entitled to manage the whole or a substantial part of the business and 
affairs of that corporation shall be entitled to any compensation against that 
corporation or against the company, as the case may be, for the loss of office 
or for the premature, termination of any contract of management entered into by 
him with that corporation.
</section></article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Power of Central 
Government to give directions.—The 
Central Government may give to a company directions as to the exercise and 
performance by that company of its functions, and that company shall be bound 
to give effect to any such directions.


</article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, not 
inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, remove the difficulty:
 
Provided that no such 
order shall be made after the expiry of a period of two years from the coming 
into force of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made 
under sub-section (1) shall be laid before each House of Parliament.
</section></article> 
 THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
  
 <article><number>11</number> Repeal of Act 27 of 1953 and 
cesser of corporations.—On the appointed day, the Air 
Corporations Act, 1953 shall stand repealed.
 <section><number>2</number> The corporations shall, with 
the repeal of the Air Corporations Act, 1953, cease to 
exist.</section></article> 
 
THE AIR CORPORATIONS (TRANSFER OF 
UNDERTAKINGS AND REPEAL) ACT, 1994
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Air Corporations (Transfer of Undertakings and Repeal) Ordinance, 1994 (Ord. 
4 of 1994) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such 
repeal of the Air Corporations (Transfer of Undertakings and Repeal) Ordinance, 
1994 (Ord. 4 of 1994), anything done or any action taken under the said 
Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or taken under the corresponding 
provisions of this Act.
 
 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>