<act><title>THE INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (PROCEDURE AND 
SAFEGUARDS FOR INTERCEPTION, MONITORING AND DECRYPTION OF INFORMATION) RULES, 
20091 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be 
called the Information Technology (Procedure and Safeguards for Interception, 
Monitoring and Decryption of Information) Rules, 2009. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Information Technology Act, 2000 (21 of 2000); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> communication means dissemination, transmission, carriage of 
  information or signal in some manner and include both a direct communication 
  and an indirect communication; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> communication link means the use of satellite, microwave, radio, 
  terrestrial line, wire, wireless or any other communication media to 
  inter-connect computer resource; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> competent authority means 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the Secretary in the Ministry of Home Affairs, in case of the Central 
    Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the Secretary in charge of the Home Department, in case of a State 
    Government or Union territory, as the case may be; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>e</number> computer resource means computer resource as defined in clause (k) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> decryption means the process of conversion of information in 
  non-intelligible form to an intelligible form via a mathematical formula, 
  code, password or algorithm or a combination thereof; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> decryption assistance means any assistance to 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> allow access, to the extent possible, to encrypted information; or 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> facilitate conversion of encrypted information into an intelligible 
    form; </subsection>
 </section><section><number>h</number> decryption direction means a direction issued under rule 3 in which a 
  decryption key holder is directed to 
 
 
 </section><section><number>i</number> disclose a decryption key; or 
 <subsection><number>ii</number> provide decryption assistance in respect of encrypted information; 
    
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> decryption key means any key, mathematical formula, code, 
      password, algorithm or any other data which is used to 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> allow access to encrypted information; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> facilitate the conversion of encrypted information into an 
        intelligible form; </subsection></section><section><number>j</number> decryption key holder means any person who deploys the decryption 
  mechanism and who is in possession of a decryption key for purposes of 
  subsequent decryption of encrypted information relating to direct or indirect 
  communications; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> information means information as defined in clause (v) of sub-section 
  (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>l</number> intercept with its grammatical variations and cognate expressions, 
  means the aural or other acquisition of the contents of any information 
  through the use of any means, including an interception device, so as to make 
  some or all of the contents of a information available to a person other than 
  the sender or recipient or intended recipient of that communication, and 
  includes 
 
 
 </section><section><number>a</number> monitoring of any such information by means of a monitoring device; 
    
 </section><section><number>b</number> viewing, examination or inspection of the contents of any direct or 
    indirect information; and 
 </section><section><number>c</number> diversion of any direct or indirect information from its intended 
    destination to any other destination; </section><section><number>m</number> interception device means any electronic, mechanical, 
  electro-mechanical, electro-magnetic, optical or other instrument, device, 
  equipment or apparatus which is used or can be used, whether by itself or in 
  combination with any other instrument, device, equipment or apparatus, to 
  intercept any information; and any reference to an interception device 
  includes, where applicable, a reference to a monitoring device; 
 </section><section><number>n</number> intermediary means an intermediary as defined in clause (w) of 
  sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </section><section><number>o</number> monitor with its grammatical variations and cognate expressions, 
  includes to view or to inspect or listen to or record information by means of 
  a monitoring device; 
 </section><section><number>p</number> monitoring device means any electronic, mechanical, 
  electro-mechanical, electro-magnetic, optical or other instrument, device, 
  equipment or apparatus which is used or can be used, whether by itself in 
  combination with any other instrument, device, equipment or apparatus, to view 
  or to inspect or to listen to or record any information; 
 </section><section><number>q</number> Review Committee means the Review Committee constituted under rule 
  419A of Indian Telegraph Rules, 1951. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Directions for interception or monitoring or decryption of any 
information. </title>No person shall carry out the interception or monitoring 
or decryption of any information generated, transmitted, received or stored in 
any computer resource under sub-section (2) of section 69 of the Act, except by 
an order issued by the competent authority: 
 Provided that in an unavoidable circumstances, such order may be issued by an 
officer, not below the rank of the Joint Secretary to the Government of India, 
who has been duly authorised by the competent authority: 
 Provided further that in a case of emergency 
 
 <section><number>i</number> in remote areas, where obtaining of prior directions for interception 
  or monitoring or decryption of information is not feasible; or 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> for operational reasons, where obtaining of prior directions for 
  interception or monitoring or decryption of any information generated, 
  transmitted, received or stored in any computer resource is not feasible, 
</section>
 the interception or monitoring or decryption of any information generated, 
transmitted, received or stored in any computer resource may be carried out with 
the prior approval of the Head or the second senior most officer of the security 
and law enforcement agency (hereinafter referred to as the said security agency) 
at the Central level and the officer authorised in this behalf, not below the 
rank of the Inspector General of Police or an officer of equivalent rank, at the 
State or Union territory level: 
 Provided also that the officer, who approved such interception or monitoring 
or decryption of information in case of emergency, shall inform in writing to 
the competent authority about the emergency and of such interception or 
monitoring or decryption within three working days and obtain the approval of 
the competent authority thereon within a period of seven working days and if the 
approval of competent authority is not obtained within the said period of seven 
working days, such interception or monitoring or decryption shall cease and the 
information shall not be intercepted or monitored or decrypted thereafter 
without the prior approval of the competent authority. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Issue of decryption direction by competent authority. 
</title>The competent authority may, under rule 3 give any decryption 
direction to the decryption key holder for decryption of any information 
involving a computer resource or part thereof. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Interception or monitoring or decryption of information by a State 
beyond its jurisdiction. </title>Notwithstanding anything contained in rule 3, 
if a State Government or Union territory Administration requires any 
interception or monitoring or decryption of information beyond its territorial 
jurisdiction, the Secretary in-charge of the Home Department in that State or 
Union territory, as the case may be, shall make a request to the Secretary in 
the Ministry of Home Affairs, Government of India for issuing direction to the 
appropriate authority for such interception or monitoring or decryption of 
information. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Contents of direction. </title>Any direction issued by the 
competent authority under rule 3 shall contain reasons for such direction and a 
copy of such direction shall be forwarded to the Review Committee within a 
period of seven working days. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Competent authority to consider alternative means in acquiring 
information. </title>The competent authority shall, before issuing any 
direction under rule 3, consider possibility of acquiring the necessary 
information by other means and the direction under rule 3 shall be issued only 
when it is not possible to acquire the information by any other reasonable 
means. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Direction of interception or monitoring or decryption of any 
specific information. </title>The direction of interception or monitoring or 
decryption of any information generated, transmitted, received or stored in any 
computer resource shall be of any information as is sent to or from any person 
or class of persons or relating to any particular subject whether such 
information or class of information are received with one or more computer 
resources, or being a computer resource likely to be used for the generation, 
transmission, receiving, storing of information from or to one particular person 
or one or many set of premises, as may be specified or described in the 
direction. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Direction to specify the name and designation of the officer to 
whom information to be disclosed </title>.Every directions under rule 3 shall 
specify the name and designation of the officer of the authorised agency to whom 
the intercepted or monitored or decrypted or stored information shall be 
disclosed and also specify that the use of intercepted or monitored or decrypted 
information shall be subject to the provisions of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 69 
of the said Act. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> Period within which direction shall remain in force. 
</title>The direction for interception or monitoring or decryption shall 
remain in force, unless revoked earlier, for a period not exceeding sixty days 
from the date of its issue and may be renewed from time-to-time for such period 
not exceeding the total period of one hundred and eighty days. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Authorised agency to designate nodal officer. </title>The 
agency authorised by the competent authority under rule 4 shall designate one or 
more nodal officer, not below the rank of Superintendent of Police or Additional 
Superintendent of Police or the officer of the equivalent rank, to authenticate 
and send the requisition conveying direction issued under rule 3 for 
interception or monitoring or decryption to the designated officers of the 
concerned intermediaries or person in-charge of computer resource: 
 Provided that an officer, not below the rank of Inspector of Police or 
officer of equivalent rank, shall deliver the requisition to the designated 
officer of the intermediary. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Intermediary to provide facilities, etc. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The 
officer issuing the requisition conveying direction issued under rule 3 for 
interception or monitoring or decryption of information shall also make a 
request in writing to the designated officers of intermediary or person 
in-charge of computer resources, to provide all facilities, co-operation and 
assistance for interception or monitoring or decryption mentioned in the 
directions. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> On the receipt of request under sub-rule (1), the designated officers of 
intermediary or person in-charge of computer resources, shall provide all 
facilities, co-operation and assistance for interception or monitoring or 
decryption of information mentioned in the direction. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any direction of decryption of information issued under rule 3 to 
intermediary shall be limited to the extent the information is encrypted by the 
intermediary or the intermediary has control over the decryption key. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> Intermediary to designate officers to receive and handle 
requisition. </title>Every intermediary or person in-charge of computer 
resource shall designate an officer to receive requisition, and another officer 
to handle such requisition, from the nodal officer for interception or 
monitoring or decryption of information generated, transmitted, received or 
stored in any computer resource. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Acknowledgement of instruction. </title>The designated officer 
of the intermediary or person in-charge of computer resources shall acknowledge 
the instructions received by him through letters or fax or e-mail signed with 
electronic signature to the nodal officer of the concerned agency within two 
hours on receipt of such intimation or direction for interception or monitoring 
or decryption of information. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Maintenance of records by designated officer. </title>The 
designated officer of intermediary or person in-charge of computer resource 
authorised to intercept or monitor or decrypt any information shall maintain 
proper records mentioning therein, the intercepted or monitored or decrypted 
information, the particulars of persons, computer resource, e-mail account, 
website address, etc., whose information has been intercepted or monitored or 
decrypted, the name and other particulars of the officer or the authority to 
whom the intercepted or monitored or decrypted information has been disclosed, 
the number of copies, including corresponding electronic records of the 
intercepted or monitored or decrypted information made and the mode or the 
method by which such copies, including corresponding electronic record are made, 
the date of destruction of the copies, including corresponding electronic record 
and the duration within which the directions remain in force. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> Decryption key holder to disclose decryption key or provide 
decryption assistance. </title>If a <title></title>decryption direction or a 
copy thereof is handed to the decryption key holder to whom the decryption 
direction is addressed by the nodal officer referred to in rule 12, the 
decryption key holder shall within the period mentioned in the decryption 
direction 
 
 <section><number>a</number> disclose the decryption key; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> provide the decryption assistance, specified in the decryption 
  direction to the concerned authorised person. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Submission of list of interception or monitoring or decryption of 
information. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The designated officers of the intermediary or person 
in-charge of computer resources shall forward in every fifteen days a list of 
interception or monitoring or decryption authorisations received by them during 
the preceding fortnight to the nodal officers of the agencies authorised under 
rule 4 for confirmation of the authenticity of such authorisations. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The list referred to in sub-rule (1) shall include details, such as the 
reference and date of orders of the concerned competent authority including any 
order issued under emergency cases, date and time of receipt of such order and 
the date and time of implementation of such order. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>19</number> Intermediary to ensure effective check in handling matter of 
interception or monitoring or decryption of information. </title>The 
intermediary or the person in-charge of the computer resource so directed under 
rule 3, shall provide technical assistance and the equipment including hardware, 
software, firmware, storage, interface and access to the equipment wherever 
requested by the agency authorised under rule 4 for performing interception or 
monitoring or decryption including for the purposes of 
 
 <section><number>i</number> the installation of equipment of the agency authorised under rule 4 for 
  the purposes of interception or monitoring or decryption or accessing stored 
  information in accordance with directions by the nodal officer; or 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> the maintenance, testing or use of such equipment; or 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> the removal of such equipment; or 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> the performance of any action required for accessing of stored 
  information under the direction issued by the competent authority under rule 
  3. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>20</number> Intermediary to ensure effective check in handling matter of 
interception or monitoring or decryption of information. </title>The 
intermediary or person  in-charge of computer resources shall put in place 
adequate and effective internal checks to ensure the unauthorised interception 
of information does not take place and extreme secrecy is maintained and utmost 
care and precaution shall be taken in the matter of interception or monitoring 
or decryption of information as it affects privacy of citizens and also that it 
is handled only by the designated officers of the intermediary and no other 
person of the intermediary or person in-charge of computer resources shall have 
access to such intercepted or monitored or decrypted information. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>21</number> Responsibility of intermediary. </title>The intermediary or 
person in-charge of computer resources shall be responsible for any action of 
their employees also and in case of violation pertaining to maintenance of 
secrecy and confidentiality of information or any unauthorised interception or 
monitoring or decryption of information, the intermediary or person in-charge of 
computer resources shall be liable for any action under the relevant provisions 
of the laws for the time being in force. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>22</number> Review of directions of competent authority. </title>The Review 
Committee shall meet at least once in two months and record its findings whether 
the directions issued under rule 3 are in accordance with the provisions of 
sub-section (2) of section 69 of the Act and where the Review Committee is of 
the opinion that the directions are not in accordance with the provisions 
referred to above, it may set aside the directions and issue order for 
destruction of the copies, including corresponding electronic record of the 
intercepted or monitored or decrypted information. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>23</number> Destruction of records of interception or monitoring or 
decryption of information. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every record, including electronic 
records pertaining to such directions for interception or monitoring or 
decryption of information and of intercepted or monitored or decrypted 
information shall be destroyed by the security agency in every six months except 
in a case where such information is required, or likely to be required for 
functional requirements. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Save as otherwise required for the purpose of any ongoing investigation, 
criminal complaint or legal proceedings, the intermediary or person in-charge of 
computer resources shall destroy records pertaining to directions for 
interception of information within a period of two months of discontinuance of 
the interception or monitoring or decryption of such information and in doing so 
they shall maintain extreme secrecy. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> Prohibition of interception or monitoring or decryption of 
information without authorisation. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Any person who intentionally or 
knowingly, without authorisation under rule 3 or rule 4, intercepts or attempts 
to intercept, or authorises or assists any other person to intercept or attempts 
to intercept any information in the course of its occurrence or transmission at 
any place within India, shall be proceeded against and punished accordingly 
under the relevant provisions of the laws for the time being in force. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any interception, monitoring or decryption of information in computer 
resource by the employee of an intermediary or person in-charge of computer 
resource or a person duly authorised by the intermediary, may be undertaken in 
course of his duty relating to the services provided by that intermediary, if 
such activities are reasonably necessary for the discharge his duties as per the 
prevailing industry practices, in connection with the following matters, 
namely: 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> installation of computer resource or any equipment to be used with 
  computer resource; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> operation or maintenance of computer resource; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> installation of any communication link or software either at the end 
  of the intermediary or subscriber, or installation of user account on the 
  computer resource of intermediary and testing of the same for its 
  functionality; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> accessing stored information from computer resource relating to the 
  installation, connection or maintenance of equipment, computer resource or a 
  communication link or code; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> accessing stored information from computer resource for the purpose of 
  
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> implementing information security practices in the computer resource; 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> determining any security breaches, computer contaminant or computer 
    virus; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> undertaking forensic of the concerned computer resource as a part of 
    investigation or internal audit; or (vi) accessing or analysing information 
    from a computer resource for the purpose of tracing a computer resource or 
    any person who has contravened, or is suspected of having contravened or 
    being likely to contravene, any provision of the Act that is likely to have 
    an adverse impact on the services provided by the intermediary. 
  </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The intermediary or the person in-charge of computer resource and its 
employees shall maintain strict secrecy and confidentiality of information while 
performing the actions specified under sub-rule (2). 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>25</number> Prohibition of disclosure of intercepted or monitored or 
decrypted information. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The contents of intercepted or monitored or 
stored or decrypted information shall not be used or disclosed by intermediary 
or any of its employees or person in-charge of computer resource to any person 
other than the intended recipient of the said information under rule 10. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The contents of intercepted or monitored or decrypted information shall 
not be used or disclosed by the agency authorised under rule 4 for any other 
purpose, except for investigation or sharing with other security agency for the 
purpose of investigation or in judicial proceedings before the competent court 
in India. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2), the contents of intercepted 
or monitored or decrypted information shall not be disclosed or reported in 
public by any means, without the prior order of the competent court in India . 

 </section><section><number>4</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-rule (2), strict confidentiality shall 
be maintained in respect of direction for interception, monitoring or decryption 
issued by concerned competent authority or the nodal officers. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Any intermediary or its employees or person in-charge of computer 
resource who contravenes provisions of these rules shall be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly under the relevant provisions of the Act for the time 
being in force. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> Whenever asked for by the concerned security agency at the Centre, the 
security agencies at the State and the Union territory level shall promptly 
share any information which they may have obtained following directions for 
interception or monitoring or decryption of any information generated, 
transmitted, received or stored in any computer resource under rule 3, with the 
security agency at the Centre. 

</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 27-10-2009.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>