<act><tid>309835</tid>
<title>THE INTER- STATE WATER DISPUTES ACT, <year>1956</year></title>

ACT NO. 33 OF <year>1956</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 28th August, <year>1956</year>.]

An Act to provide for the adjudication of disputes relating to 
waters of inter- State rivers and river valleys.

Be it enacted by Parliament in the Seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--





<article><tid>450544</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>977358</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Inter-  
State Water Disputes Act, <year>1956</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1790698</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1003392</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1233200</tid>
<number>a</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>848016</tid>
<number>b</number>" Tribunal" means a Water Disputes Tribunal constituted 
under section 4;

</section>

<section><tid>1483007</tid>
<number>c</number>" water dispute" means any dispute or difference between 
two or more State Governments with respect to--

<subsection><tid>1825037</tid>
<number>i</number>the use, distribution or control of the waters 
of, or in, any inter- State river or river valley; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1225148</tid>
<number>ii</number>the interpretation of the terms of any 
agreement relating to the use, distribution or control 
of such waters or the implementation of such agreement; 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1760749</tid>
<number>iii</number>the levy of any water rate in contravention 
of the prohibition contained in section 7.

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>734854</tid>
<number> 3</number> Complaints by State Governments as to water disputes. 
appears to the Government of any State that a water dispute with the 
Government of another State has arisen or is likely to arise by reason 
of the fact that the interests of the State, or of any of the 
inhabitants thereof, in the waters of an inter- State river or river 
valley have been, or are likely to be, affected prejudicially by--
<section><tid>1442749</tid>
<number>a</number>any executive action or legislation taken or passed, or 
proposed to be taken or passed, by the other State; or

</section>

<section><tid>765838</tid>
<number>b</number>the failure of the other State or any authority therein 
to exercise any of their powers with respect to the 
use, distribution or control of such waters; or
<pagefootnote><pagenum>294</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The Act has been extended to Dadra and Nagar Haveli by Reg. 6 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 1 and to Pondicherry by Reg. 7 of <year>1963</year>, s. 3 and 
Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>685120</tid>
<number>c</number>the failure of the other State to implement the terms of 
any agreement relating to the use, distribution or 
control of such waters,
the State Government may, in such form and manner as may be 
prescribed, request the Central Government to refer the water dispute 
to a Tribunal for adjudication.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>182653</tid>
<number> 4</number> Constitution of Tribunal.
<section><tid>1548808</tid>
<number>1</number>When any request under section 3  
is received from any State Government in respect of any water dispute 
and the Central Government is of opinion that the water dispute cannot 
be settled by negotiations, the Central Government shall, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, constitute a Water Disputes 
Tribunal for the adjudication of the water dispute.

</section>

<section><tid>785553</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The Tribunal shall consist of a Chairman and two other 
members nominated in this behalf by the Chief Justice of India from 
among persons who at the time of such nomination are Judges of the 
Supreme Court or of a High Court.]

</section>

<section><tid>537813</tid>
<number>3</number>The Tribunal may appoint two or more persons as assessors to 
advise it in the proceeding before it.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>191435</tid>
<number> 5</number> Adjudication of water disputes.
<section><tid>894378</tid>
<number>1</number>When a Tribunal has been  
constituted under section 4, the Central Government shall, subject to 
the prohibition contained in section 8, refer the water dispute and 
any matter appearing to be connected with, or relevant to, the water 
dispute to the Tribunal for adjudication.

</section>

<section><tid>1382627</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal shall investigate the matters referred to it and 
foward to the Central Government a report setting out the facts as 
found by it and giving its decision on the matters referred to it.

</section>

<section><tid>1778492</tid>
<number>3</number>If, upon consideration of the decision of the Tribunal, the 
Central Government or any State Government is of opinion that anything 
therein contained requires explanation or that guidance is needed upon 
any point not originally referred to the Tribunal, the Central 
Government or the State Government, as the case may be, may, within 
three months from the date of the decision, again refer the matter to 
the Tribunal for further consideration; and on such reference, the 
Tribunal may forward to the Central Government a further report giving 
such explanation or guidance as it deems fit and in such a case, the 
decision of the Tribunal shall be deemed to be modified accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>632861</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> If the members of the Tribunal differ in opinion on any 
point, the point shall be decided according to the opinion of the 
majority.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1553234</tid>
<number>5A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Filling of vacancies. If, for any reason a vacancy (other  
  than a temporary absence) occurs in the office of the Chairman or any 
other member of a Tribunal,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>295</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1968</year>, s. 2, for sub- section (2). 
2. Ins. by s. 3, ibid. 
3. Ins. by s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


such vacancy shall be filled by a person to be nominated in this 
behalf by the Chief Justice of India in accordance with the provisions 
of sub- section (2) of section 4, and the investigation of the matter 
referred to the Tribunal may be continued by the Tribunal after the 
vacancy is filled and from the stage at which the vacancy occurred.]



</article>



<article><tid>7809</tid>
<number>6</number>Publication of decision of Tribunal. The Central Government 
shall publish the decision of the Tribunal in the Official Gazette and 
the decision shall be final and binding on the parties to the dispute 
and shall be given effect to by them.


</article>



<article><tid>831869</tid>
<number> 6A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Power to make schemes to implement decision of Tribunal.

<section><tid>1132727</tid>
<number>1</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of section 6, the Central  
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, frame a 
scheme or schemes whereby provision may be made for all matters 
necessary to give effect to the decision of a Tribunal.

</section>

<section><tid>261711</tid>
<number>2</number>A scheme framed under sub- section (1) may provide for--

<subsection><tid>1608918</tid>
<number>a</number>the establishment of any authority (whether described as  
  such or as a committee or other body) for the implementation of 
the decision or directions of the Tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1175444</tid>
<number>b</number>the composition, jurisdiction, powers and functions of 
the authority, the term of office and other conditions of service 
of, the procedure to be followed by, and the manner of filling 
vacancies among, the members of the authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>886701</tid>
<number>c</number>the holding of a minimum number of meetings of the 
authority every year, the quorum for such meetings and the 
procedure thereat;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1156356</tid>
<number>d</number>the appointment of any standing, ad hoc or other 
committees by the authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1537600</tid>
<number>e</number>the employment of a Secretary and other staff by the 
authority, the pay and allowances and other conditions of service 
of such staff;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>879429</tid>
<number>f</number>the constitution of a fund by the authority, the amounts 
that may be credited to such fund and the expenses to which the 
fund may be applied;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>469212</tid>
<number>g</number>the form and the manner in which accounts shall be kept 
by the authority;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>858439</tid>
<number>h</number>the submission of an annual report by the authority of 
its activities;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>290646</tid>
<number>i</number>the decisions of the authority which shall be subject to 
review;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>78766</tid>
<number>j</number>the constitution of a committee for making such review 
and the procedure to be followed by such committee; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>619939</tid>
<number>k</number>any other matter which may be necessary or proper for 
the effective implementation of the decision or directions of the 
Tribunal.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>895272</tid>
<number>3</number>In making provision in any scheme framed under sub- section 
 (1) for the establishment of an authority for giving effect to the 
decision of a Tribunal, the Central Government may, having regard to 
the nature of the jurisdiction, powers and functions required to be 
vested in such authority in accordance with such decision and all 
other relevant circumstances, declare in the said scheme that such 
authority shall, under the name specified in the said scheme, have 
capacity to acquire, hold and dispose of property, enter into 
contracts, sue and be sued and do all such acts as may be necessary 
for the proper exercise and discharge of its jurisdiction, powers and 
functions.

</section>

<section><tid>213737</tid>
<number>4</number>A scheme may empower the authority to make, with the previous 
approval of the Central Government, regulations for giving effect to 
the purposes of the scheme.

</section>

<section><tid>384664</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, add to, amend, or vary, any scheme framed under sub- section 
 (1).

</section>

<section><tid>606416</tid>
<number>6</number>Every scheme framed under this section shall have effect 
notwithstanding anything contained in any law for the time being in 
force (other than this Act) or any instrument having effect by Virtue 
of any law other than this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>359367</tid>
<number>7</number>Every scheme and every regulation made under a scheme shall 
be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty days 
which may be comprised in one session or in two or more successive 
sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
Houses agree in making any modification in the scheme or the 
regulation or both Houses agree that the scheme or the regulation 
should not be made, the scheme or the regulation shall thereafter have 
effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
that scheme or regulation."]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1779366</tid>
<number> 7</number> Prohibition of levy of seigniorage, etc.
<section><tid>318106</tid>
<number>1</number>No State  
Government shall, by reason only of the fact that any works for the 
conservation, regulation or utilisation of water resources of an 
inter- State river have been constructed within the limits of the 
State, impose, or authorize the imposition of, any seigniorage or 
additional rate or fee (by whatever name called) in respect of the use 
of such water by any other State of the inhabitants thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>199188</tid>
<number>2</number>Any dispute or difference between two or more State 
Governments with respect to the levy of any water rate in 
contravention of the prohibition contained in sub- section (1) shall be 
deemed to be a water dispute.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>984798</tid>
<number>8</number>Bar of reference of certain disputes to Tribunal. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 3 or section 5, no 
reference shall be made to a Tribunal of any dispute that may arise 
regarding any matter which may be referred to arbitration under the 
River Boards Act, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <year>1956</year>] (49 of <year>1956</year>).


</article>



<article><tid>524338</tid>
<number> 9</number> Powers of Tribunal.
<section><tid>1048343</tid>
<number>1</number>The Tribunal shall have the same  
powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
Procedure, <year>1908</year> (5 of <year>1908</year>), in respect of the following matters, 
namely:--

<subsection><tid>1565883</tid>
<number>a</number>summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and 
examining him on oath;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>379345</tid>
<number>b</number>requiring the discovery and production of documents and 
material objects;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>753001</tid>
<number>c</number>issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or 
for local investigation;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1109632</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1597930</tid>
<number>2</number>The Tribunal may require any State Government to carry out, 
or permit to be carried out, such surveys and investigation as may be 
considered necessary for the adjudication of any water dispute pending 
before it.

</section>

<section><tid>1024028</tid>
<number>3</number>A decision of the Tribunal may contain directions as to the 
Government by which the expenses of the Tribunal and any costs 
incurred
<pagefootnote><pagenum>296</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 45 of <year>1980</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by Act 36 of <year>1957</year>, s. 3 and Sch, II, for" <year>1955</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


by any State Government in appearing before the Tribunal are to be 
paid, and may fix the amount of any expenses or costs to be so paid, 
and so far as it relates to expenses or costs, may be enforced as if 
it were an order made by the Supreme Court.


</section>

<section><tid>629831</tid>
<number>4</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Subject to the provisions of this Act and any rules that 
may be made thereunder], the Tribunal may, by order, regulate its 
practice and procedure.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>80501</tid>
<number>10</number>Allowances or fees for Chairman of Tribunal and assessors. 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> The Chairman and other members of a Tribunal] and the assessors 
shall be entitled to receive such remuneration, allowances or fees as 
may be prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>80709</tid>
<number>11</number>Bar of jurisdiction of Supreme Court and other courts. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law, neither the 
Supreme Court nor any other court shall have or exercise jurisdiction 
in respect of any water dispute which may be referred to a Tribunal 
under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>921102</tid>
<number>12</number>Dissolution of Tribunal. The Central Government shall 
dissolve the Tribunal after it has forwarded its report and as soon as 
the Central Government is satisfied that no further reference to the 
Tribunal in the matter would be necessary.


</article>



<article><tid>823743</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1020352</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government, after  
consultation with the State Governments, may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>767020</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>737681</tid>
<number>a</number>the form and manner in which a complaint as to any water 
dispute may be made by any State Government,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1368107</tid>
<number>b</number>the matters in respect of which a Tribunal may be vested 
with the powers of a civil court:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1724475</tid>
<number>c</number>the procedure to be followed by a Tribunal under this 
Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>990335</tid>
<number>d</number>the remuneration, allowances or fees payable to <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the 
Chairman and other members] of a Tribunal and 
assessors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1667742</tid>
<number>e</number>the terms and conditions of service of officers of the 
Tribunal;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>954781</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>296A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1968</year>, s. 5. for" Subject to any rules that may 
be made under this Act". 
2. Subs. by s. 6, ibid., for" The presiding officer of a Tribunal". 
3. Subs. by s. 7, ibid., for" the presiding officer".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>69083</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon 
as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament while it 
is in session for a total period of thirty days, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> which may be 
comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and 
if, before the expiry of the session immediately following the session 
or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that rule.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>800067</tid>
<number> 14</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Constitution of Ravi and Beas Waters Tribunal.
<section><tid>576568</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing provisions of this 
Act, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, constitute a Tribunal under this Act, to be known as the Ravi 
and Beas Waters Tribunal for the verification and adjudication of the 
matters referred to in paragraphs 9. 1 and 9. 2, respectively, of the 
Punjab Settlement.

</section>

<section><tid>509773</tid>
<number>2</number>When a Tribunal has been constituted under sub- section (1), 
the provisions of sub- sections (2) and (3) of section 4, sub- sections 
 (2), (3) and (4) of section 5 and sections 5A to 13 (both inclusive) 
of this Act relating to the constitution, jurisdiction, powers, 
authority and bar of jurisdiction shall, so far as may be, but subject 
to sub- section (3) hereof, apply to the constitution, jurisdiction, 
powers, authority and bar of jurisdiction in relation to the Tribunal 
constituted under sub- section (1).

</section>

<section><tid>1766103</tid>
<number>3</number>When a Tribunal has been constituted under sub- section (1), 
the Central Government alone may suo motu or at the request of the 
concerned State Government refer the matters specified in paragraphs 
9. 1 and 9. 2 of the Punjab Settlement to such Tribunal.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section," Punjab 
Settlement" means the Memorandum of Settlement signed at New Delhi on 
the 24th day of July, <year>1985</year>.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 35 of <year>1968</year>, s. 7, for sub- section (3). 
2. Subs. by Act 45 of <year>1980</year>, s. 3. 
3. Ins. by Act 20 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>