<act><title>THE
NATIONAL HOUSING BANK GENERAL REGULATIONS, 19881


</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These regulations may be called the National Housing Bank General Regulations,
1988.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the official
Gazette. 




</section></article> 

   


 <article>  

<number>2</number> Definitions.—In
these regulations, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or
context,—
 


 <section>
<number>a</number>
“Act” means the National Housing Bank Act, 1987 (53 of 1987); 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
“member” means a member of the Executive Committee constituted under
sub-section (1) of section 12 of the Act and includes a Member of any other
Committee constituted under sub-section (3) of that section. 
 

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>3</number>
Meetings of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Board shall ordinarily meet once a quarter in each year.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Meetings of the Board shall be convened by the Chairman, or in his absence, by
the Managing Director or in the absence of both, by any other director nominated
by the Chairman or the Managing Director, as the case may be, and shall be held
at Delhi or at such other place in India as may be directed by the Board.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Any five directors may, for the purpose of the consideration of the business to
be specified in their requisition, require the Chairman or the Managing Director
to convene a meeting of the Board and the Chairman or the Managing Director, as
the case may be, shall, on receipt of such requisition, convene a meeting of the
Board giving sufficient notice:
 


 Provided
that the date of the meeting so convened shall not be later than 21 days from
the date of the requisition.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Ordinarily, not less than one clear fortnight’s notice shall be given of each
meeting of the Board and such notice shall be sent to every director to his
registered address. Should it be necessary to convene an emergency meeting,
sufficient notice shall be given to every director who is at that time in India.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
No business other than that for which the meeting was convened shall be
discussed at a meeting of a Board, except with the consent of the person
presiding at the meeting.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
Five directors, of whom one shall be a director nominated under clause (d) or
clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 6 of the Act, shall form a quorum for
the transaction of business.
 


 </section><section><number>7</number>
A copy of the minutes of each meeting of the Board shall be signed by the person
presiding and circulated for the information of the directors as soon as
possible after the meeting and shall be signed by the person presiding at the
next succeeding meeting by way of confirmation.

</section></article> 

   


 <article><number>4</number>
Resolution without meeting of Board valid.—A
resolution in writing circulated to all the directors in India and approved and
signed by a majority of such directors who are then in India (of whom one shall
be the Chairman or a director nominated by the Reserve Bank) shall be valid and
effectual and shall be deemed to be the resolution passed by the Board on the
date on which it is approved and signed by the last signatory to the resolution:
 


 Provided
that if any dissenting director requires in writing that any resolution so
passed shall be placed before a meeting of the Board, the resolution shall not
be deemed to be valid and effectual as aforesaid, unless the same is passed at
such a meeting.

</article> 

  
 <article><number>5</number>
The Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Executive Committee of the National Housing Bank shall consist of the
Chairman, the Managing Director and not more than three directors of the Board
to be nominated by the Board of whom at least one shall be a director other than
the directors nominated under clause (d) and clause (e) of sub-section (1) of
section 6 of the Act.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Executive Committee shall have full powers to transact all the usual
business of the National Housing Bank except in such matters as are specifically
reserved to the Board by the Act or regulation 9 of these regulations.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Meetings of the Executive Committee shall be convened by the Chairman, or in his
absence, by the Managing Director or, in the absence of both by any other
Director nominated by the Chairman or the Managing Director, as the case may be,
and shall be held at New Delhi or at such other place as may be specified by the
person convening the meeting.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Any three of the directors referred to in sub-regulation (1) shall form a quorum
for the transaction of business by the Executive Committee.
 


 </section><section><number>5</number>
A resolution in writing and circulated to the members of the Executive Committee
referred to in sub-regulation (1) and approved by any three of them shall be
valid and effectual and shall be deemed to be the resolution passed by the
Executive Committee on the date on which it is signed by the last signatory to
the resolution.
 


 </section><section><number>6</number>
The provisions of the Act and save as otherwise provided herein, these
regulations shall apply to the meetings of the Executive Committee as if they
were meetings of the Board.

  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>6</number>
Other committees.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any committee (other than the Executive Committee) constituted under sub-section
(3) of section 12 of the Act shall, in 
exercise of the powers entrusted to it, be bound by such general or
special directions as the Board may give from time to time.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Meetings of such committee shall be called from time to time by the person
appointed as the convenor of the committee by the Board at Delhi or at such
other place in India as may be specified by him.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The quorum for the meeting of any such committee shall be one-third of its
strength (any fraction contained in that one third being rounded off as one) or
two members, whichever is higher.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
The provisions of the Act and save as otherwise provided herein, these
regulations shall apply to meetings of such a Committee as if they were meetings
of the Board.

  
</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>7</number>
Fees and allowances.—
<section><number>1</number>
Subject to the provisions of the proviso to sub-section (5) of section 7 of the
Act, every director shall be entitled to receive a fee of Rs. 200 for each
meeting of the Board which he attends.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Unless he is in receipt of any remuneration, including honorarium (other than
casual remuneration) from the National Housing Bank, every member shall be
entitled to receive a fee of Rs. 100 for each committee meeting which he
attends.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
In addition to such fees, directors and members shall be reimbursed their
travelling, halting and other expenses including accommodation on such scales as
may be fixed from time to time by the Reserve Bank of India.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>8</number>
Manner and form in which contracts binding on the National Housing Bank may be
executed.—
<section><number>1</number>
Contracts on behalf of the National Housing Bank may be made as follows:—
 


 Any
contract which, if made between private persons, would by law be required to be
in writing, signed by the parties to be charged therewith, may be made on behalf
of the National Housing Bank in writing signed by any person acting under its
authority, express or implied, and may in the same manner be varied or
discharged. 
 
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
All contracts made, according to the provisions of this regulation, shall be
valid and binding on the National Housing Bank.

</section></article> 

   


   


 <article><number>9</number>
Certain powers to be exercised by the Board only.—Save
as otherwise provided in the Act the following powers on behalf of the National
Housing Bank shall be exercised only by the Board, namely:—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
approval of the balance-sheets relating to the General Fund referred to
in sub-section (1) of section 37 of the Act; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>b</number>
approval of appropriation of profits and other usual and necessary
provisions relating to the said General Fund; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>c</number>
approval of write-off of losses/bad debts in excess of rupees one lakh. 
 

</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Accounts, receipts and documents of Bank by whom to be signed.—The
Chairman, the Managing Director or such of the Officers of the National Housing
Bank as are authorised in this behalf by the Board by notification in the
Gazette of India shall have power to execute, on hehalf of the National Housing
bank, lease deeds, transfers, conveyances, charges and all other deeds relating
to or affecting rights to or in immovable property, to endorse and transfer
promissory notes, stock receipts, stocks, debentures, shares, securities and
documents of title to goods standing in the name of or held in the name of or
held by the National Housing Bank, and to draw, accept and endorse bills of
exchange and other instruments in the current and authorised business of the
National Housing Bank and to sign all other accounts, receipts and documents
connected with or incidental to such business.

</article> 

  
 <article><number>11</number>
Plaints, etc., by whom to be signed.—Plaints,
written statements, affidavits and all other documents connected with legal
proceedings may be signed and verified on behalf of the National Housing Bank by
any officer empowered by or under regulation 10, to sign documents for and on
behalf of the National Housing Bank.

</article> 

  
 <article><number>12</number>
Issue of bonds.—
<section><number>1</number>
The bonds or debentures of the National Housing Bank shall be issued over the
signature of the Chairman or the Managing Director which may be printed,
engraved or lithographed or impressed by such other mechanical process as the
National Housing Bank may direct;
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
A signature so printed, engraved, lithographed or otherwise impressed shall be
as valid as if it had been inscribed in the proper handwriting of the signatory
himself.

  
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>13</number>
Common seal of the Bank.—The common
seal of the National Housing Bank shall be affixed to any instrument only in the
presence of at least three directors including the Chairman or the Managing
Director, who shall sign their names to the instrument in token of their
presence, and such signing shall be independent of the signing of any person who
may sign the instrument as a witness. Unless so signed as aforesaid, such
instrument shall be of no validity.

</article> 

  
 <article><number>14</number>
Annual statement of accounts.—The
annual accounts of National Housing Bank shall be prepared and set out in—
 


 <section><number>i</number>
a balance-sheet as on the 30th June of the year as specified in Form A
annexed hereto or as near thereto as circumstances admit; 
 
 


 </section><section><number>ii</number>
a profit and loss account for the year ended 30th June as specified in
Form B annexed hereto or as near thereto as circumstances admit. 
 
 


   


  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>