<act> 
 
The Cost Accounting Records  
(Bulk Drugs) Rules, 19741
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Cost Accounting Records (Bulk Drugs) Rules, 1974.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the 1st day of April, 1979.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The Cost Accounting Records  
(Bulk Drugs) Rules, 1974
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Application.—They 
shall apply to every company engaged in the production, processing or 
manufacturing of bulk drugs.
 
 
</article> 
 
The Cost Accounting Records  
(Bulk Drugs) Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  the expressions “bulk drug”, 
“essential bulk drug” and “formulation” shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in the Drugs (Prices Control) Order, 1970, as amended from time 
to time:
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  “intermediate” means any compound 
which is manufactured from primary or basic raw material and which is used in 
the production, processing or manufacture of any bulk drug.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Cost Accounting Records  
(Bulk Drugs) Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Maintenance of records.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every company to which these rules apply shall, in respect of each of its 
financial year commencing on or after the commencement of these rules, keep 
proper books of account containing inter alia the particulars specified 
in Schedules I and II annexed to these rules relating to the utilisation of 
materials, labour and other items of cost so far as they are applicable to the 
bulk drugs:
 
Provided that if the said 
company is manufacturing any products or engaged in other activities in addition 
to any of the bulk drugs, the particulars relating to the utilisation of 
materials, labour and other items of cost in so far as they are applicable to 
such other products or activities shall not be included in the cost of such bulk 
drug.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The books of account 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be kept in such a way as to make it possible 
to calculate the cost of production and cost of sale of each of the bulk drugs 
during a financial year (hereinafter referred to as the relevant period) from 
the particulars entered therein.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be the duty 
of every person referred to in sub­-section (6) and sub-section (7) of section 
209 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) to take all reasonable steps to 
secure compliance by the company with the provisions of sub-rules (1) and (2) in 
the same manner as they are liable to maintain financial accounts required under 
sub-section (1) of section 209 of the said Act.
 
 
</section></article> 
 
The Cost Accounting Records  
(Bulk Drugs) Rules, 1974
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Penalty.—If 
a company contravenes the provisions of Rule 4, the company and every officer 
thereof who is in default, including the persons referred to in sub-rule (3) of 
that rule, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees 
and, where the contravention is continuing one, with a further fine which may 
extend to fifty rupees for every day after the first during which contravention 
continues.
 
 
</article><form>
 


The Cost Accounting Records  

(Bulk Drugs) Rules, 1974
 


 
 


Schedule I
 


(See rule 4)
 


I. Production Materials
 


(a) Adequate records shall be maintained 
showing all receipts, issues and balances both in quantities and cost of each 
item of raw material and intermediate required and actually used for producing, 
processing or manufacturing any bulk drug. The basis on which the said 
quantities and costs have been calculated shall be clearly indicated in the cost 
records, or, if so desired by the company, in a separate manual of procedure, if 
any, maintained by the company or in foot notes or explanatory notes to the cost 
statements. The basis adopted shall be applied consistently. The cost shown in 
the records shall include all direct charges up to the works. Any wastage 
whether in storage, transit or for other reasons of these materials shall be 
shown separately and the method of dealing with such losses in costs shall also 
be disclosed in the costs records.
 


Adequate records showing the consumption of 
each item of raw material for production shall be maintained. If the quantity 
and cost of materials consumed are determined on any basis other than actuals 
the methods adopted shall be mentioned in the cost records. The overall 
reconciliation of such costs of materials with the actuals shall be made 
periodically and in any case at the end of the relevant period, explaining the 
reasons for variances. The method followed for adjusting the cost variances in 
determining the actual costs of the bulk drugs shall be clearly indicated in the 
cost records.
 


(b) Where basic raw materials or ingredients, 
such as Sorbitol for the manufacture of Vitamin “C” or for the bulk drugs, are 
manufactured by the company or by its holding company or its wholly owned 
subsidiary, adequate records showing the cost of production of such items shall 
be maintained in such details as may enable the company to fill up the 
particulars in Proforma ‘A’ of Schedule II or in any form as near thereto, as 
practicable. Where farm products are raised by the company for use in the 
manufacture of bulk drugs or phytochemical products, adequate records to 
disclose the cost of production of such products shall be maintained in a 
suitable form. Separate cost statements in respect of each such raw material 
ingredient/farm product shall be maintained by the company. The records of these 
materials shall be maintained in such details as may enable the company to 
determine the actual cost of production as well at the ultimate cost as the 
consuming point including all charges upon the works. The basis of pricing 
adopted by the holding company or subsidiary company for the supply of these raw 
materials to the subsidiary or holding company, as the case may be, shall be 
disclosed in the cost records.
 


(c) Adequate quantitative records for 
determining the net consumption of solvents like acetone alcohol material which 
are used for processing shall be maintained. The cost records shall clearly 
indicate absorption or loss in the process of solvents used for the production 
of each bulk drug in a scientific manner indicating in plant stocks and actual 
recovery of pure solvents arising out of production of each individual bulk 
drugs. Adequate records shall also be maintained showing the receipts, issue and 
balances, both in quantities and costs of process chemicals such as caustic 
soda, activated carbon and benzene.
 


(d) The records relating to consumption of 
production materials shall, as far as possible, be identified with the batch of 
production or the cost centres to which the materials are issued.
 


II. Consumable stores, small tools, machinery 
spares, etc.
 


(a) Adequate records shall be maintained to 
show all receipts, issues and balances both in quantity and cost of each item of 
consumable stores, lubricants arid items, spare parts and consumable tools 
required in connection with the manufacture of the bulk drug. The costs shall 
include all direct charges upto works, wherever specifically incurred. In the 
case of small tools, the costs of which are significant, the company may, if it 
so desires, maintain such records for the main group of such items.
 


(b) The cost of consumable stores, small 
tools and machinery spares consumed shall be charged to the relevant heads of 
account such as repairs to plant and machinery, repairs to buildings, 
maintenance of township and maintenance of vehicles. Items issued for capital 
works, such as additions to buildings, plant and machinery, shall be shown under 
the relevant capital heads. Any wastage in storage, transit or for other reasons 
shall be shown separately. The method of dealing with such losses in costs shall 
also be indicated in the cost records.
 


III. Power and Fuel
 


Adequate records shall be maintained in order 
to ascertain the cost of power and fuel. The cost of power and fuel consumed 
shall be determined on the basis of actual meter reading of consumption or 
calculated on a reasonable basis and applied consistently. Where power is 
generated by the company itself, separate records shall be maintained to show in 
detail the different items making up the cost of generation of power.
 


IV. Steam
 


Adequate records shall be maintained to 
ascertain the total quantity and cost of steam generated and the quantity and 
cost of steam consumed in the different process, departments or cost centres 
including that consumed for generation of power. The cost of steam so consumed 
shall be calculated on a reasonable basis and applied consistently.
 


V. Brine and chilled water
 


Adequate records shall be maintained to 
determine correctly the quantity and the cost of brine and chilled water 
utilised by the different production departments.
 


VI. Raw water, Soft water, Demineralised 
water, compressed air
 


Adequate records showing the cost of 
production and distri­bution of raw water, soft water, demineralised water, the 
compressed air shall be kept. The cost of these services shall be charged to the 
respective production departments and to the products on a reasonable basis.
 


VII. By-products
 


Adequate records shall be maintained showing 
the quantity of by-products derived and the basis adopted for their pricing for 
giving credit to the respective bulk drugs and intermediates. The basis so 
adopted for pricing the by-products shall be equitable and consistent. Records 
showing the expenses incurred on the recovery of the by­-products like operation 
of distillation columns and treating plant, shall be kept to ascertain correctly 
the ultimate cost of the by­-products in saleable form. Records showing the 
actual quantity sold and sales realisation of the by-products shall also be 
maintained.
 


VIII. Wages and salaries
 


(a) Proper and systemic records shall be 
maintained to show the attendance and the earning of workers and other 
operational staff indicating the departments or the work on which they are 
employed. Where payments to workers are made on piece-rate basis the records 
relating thereto shall be maintained so as to enable proper assessment of wages 
payable to such workers. Necessary records shall also be maintained in respect 
of all payments for overtime work and to casual labour. Where any incentive 
payments are made, whether in the shape of production bonus or other forms of 
incentive based on output achieved by the workers individually or collectively, 
proper records shall also be maintained for the assessment of such payments.
 


(b) The records shall further show the wages 
and salaries relating to various manufacturing and other departments or units or 
cost centres, being the amounts payable and allocated to the different 
departments or units or cost centres. Idle time of workers shall be recorded 
separately, indicating the reasons for such idle time and the method of its 
treatment in calculating the costs of products. Any wages and salaries incurred 
towards additions to plant, machinery, buildings or other fixed assets shall be 
allocated to the relevant capital heads in the accounts.
 


(c) If the wages or salaries are allocated to 
the departments or units or cost centres or products on any basis other than 
actuals, the reconciliation of such wages with actuals and method followed for 
adjusting the cost variances, if any, determining the actual cost of bulk drugs 
shall be indicated in the cost records.
 


IX. Service Department expenses
 


Expenses of service departments shall be 
apportioned to other service departments and the production departments on the 
basis of service rendered. Detailed records about the utilisation of the 
services by the different departments, cost centres and their absorption in 
product costs shall be maintained.
 


X. Multi-purpose vessels
 


When more than one manufacturing process is 
carried out in a particular or series of vessels, adequate records about the 
usage of such vessels for different products shall be kept. The cost of using 
such vessels shall be charged to the different products on an equitable basis 
such as equipment occupancy hours. Where composite machine hour rates are 
applied for absorption of wages, overheads and equipment usage, proper records 
relating to the utilisation of labour and multi-purpose vessels for different 
processes connected with the manufacture of different products shall be kept to 
enable determination of total machine hours and the amount chargeable to the 
respective bulk drugs or intermediates. The variances between the actuals and 
the amounts charged at pre-determined rates shall be adjusted for arriving at 
the actual cost of production at the end of the year.
 


XI. Workshop/Repairs and Maintenance Shop 
expenses
 


Adequate records showing the expenditure 
incurred in the workshop and in the repairs and maintenance shop shall be 
maintained. The records shall further indicate the basis of charging the 
expenditure incurred in these shops to the different departments or 
manufacturing units or cost centres. Expenditure on a major repair work from 
which benefit is likely to accrue for more than one financial year, shall be 
shown separately in the cost records, indicating the method of its treatment in 
determining the cost of bulk drugs. Expenditure on capital works shall be 
capitalised.
 


XII. Depreciation
 


(a) Adequate records shall be maintained 
showing the values and other particulars of fixed assets in respect of which 
depreciation is to be provided. The records shall inter alia indicate the 
cost of each item of assets, the date of its acquisition, and the rate of 
depreciation. In respect of those assets, the original cost of acquisition of 
which cannot be ascertained without unreasonable expenditure or delay the 
valuation as shown in the books on the first day of the financial year beginning 
on or after the commencement of these rules shall be taken as the opening 
balance.
 


(b) The basis on which depreciation is 
calculated and further allocated to the various departments, cost centres and to 
the products shall be clearly indicated in the records. Depreciation chargeable 
to the different departments, manufacturing units, or cost centres shall not be 
less than the amount of depreciation chargeable in accordance with the 
provisions of sub-section (2) of section 205 of the Companies Act, 1955 and 
shall relate to plant, machinery and other fixed assets unutilised in such 
department or units or cost centres. If in case the amount of depreciation 
charged in the cost records is higher than an amount of depreciation chargeable 
under the aforesaid provisions of the Companies Act, 1956, the amount so charged 
in excess shall be indicated clearly in the records. However, the cumulative 
depreciation charged against individual assets over a period of years shall not 
exceed the original cost of the respective assets. The method once adopted shall 
be applied consistently.
 


XIII. Overhead expenses
 


(a) Adequate records showing the details of 
the amounts comprising the overhead expenses including the break of head office 
expenses and the data relating to apportionment of overhead expenses to the 
various departments or manufacturing units or cost centres shall be maintained 
after reconciling all such expenses with the financial accounts. Overheads 
relating to works, administration, selling and distribution shall be recorded 
separately with details. In respect of capital jobs, appropriate share of 
overhead expenses shall be allocated to the capital heads.
 


Works overheads shall include among other 
items, indirect materials consumed and the relevant share of staff and labour 
welfare expenses. The detailed break-up of the items, constituting Head Office 
or common unit expenses and their allocation shall be maintained indicating the 
basis on which they are allocated to different activities or products of the 
company to enable determination of an equitable charge to the different bulk 
drugs and intermediates. The amount allocated to the different bulk drugs or 
intermediates shall be reasonable and appropriate. The method of apportioning 
overhead expenses to the various departments of manufacturing units or cost 
centres shall be clearly indicated in the cost records and applied consistently. 
Where the overhead expenses are recovered through the output of the various 
departments or manufacturing units or cost centres otherwise than actuals, the 
method of reconciling such expenses with the actuals for the relevant period, 
the variances, if any, and the method followed for adjusting the cost variances 
in determining the cost of bulk drugs shall be indicated in the cost records.
 


(b) Details of selling and distribution 
expenses and the share thereof applicable to the bulk drugs and as between 
different sizes of packs shall be maintained in such a manner so as to enable 
the relevant particulars to be furnished in Proforma ‘C’ of Schedule II. Selling 
and distribution expenses shall be charged only to the quantity of bulk drugs 
and intermediates sold, if applicable. The basis of appointment of these 
expenses to the bulk drugs and intermediates and others shall be indicated in 
the cost records and applied consistently.
 


Records showing the expenses incurred on 
export of bulk drugs, if any, shall be separately maintained so that the cost of 
sales within the country, and for exports can be correctly determined. The 
export expenses as well as the credits relating to drawbacks, sale of import 
entitlements etc. shall be shown in the relevant cost statements of drugs 
exported for arriving at the net cost.
 


XIV. Packing
 


Adequate records shall be maintained showing 
the cost of packing materials and wages and other expenses incurred in respect 
of different items packed. Where such expenses are not capable of being charged 
directly against individual items, the basis of apportioning the expenses shall 
be clearly indicated in the cost records and applied consistently. Detailed 
records of expenses incurred on export packing, if any, shall also be kept 
separately and exhibited in the relevant cost statements.
 


The records shall be kept in such a manner 
that the packing cost in respect of different types and sizes of packs are 
available separately.
 


XV. Research and Development expenses
 


Adequate records showing the details of 
expenses incurred by the company for the development of existing products or new 
products or processes, if any, shall be maintained separately. If the Research 
and Development Department is also engaged in the design and development of the 
plant facilities, the appropriate share thereof shall be capitalised. The method 
of charging search and development expenses to the cost of production shall be 
indicated in the relevant cost records and such expenses shall be charged to 
bulk drug and intermediates on a reasonable basis.
 


XVI. Transfer price for bulk drugs used for 
captive consumption
 


Adequate records showing the quantity of bulk 
drugs consumed for captive consumption by the formulation division of the 
company and the quantity sold to outside parties shall be maintained. The 
quantity transferred to formulations shall be valued at cost. A similar 
procedure shall be followed in respect of intermediates consumed for the 
manufacture of bulk drugs. However, the selling price as well as the notional 
price notified to the Central Government under paragraph 5 of the Drugs (Price 
Control) Order, 1970, shall be shown by way of foot notes in the relevant cost 
statements indicating the basis on which the notional price has been arrived at.
 


XVII. Cost statements
 


Cost statements showing separately the actual 
cost of production and marketing of the bulk drugs and such of the intermediates 
which are partially or fully utilised for the manufacture of bulk drugs by the 
company shown in Proforma ‘B’ and ‘C’ of Schedule II or in any form as near 
thereto, as practicable. Costs of bulk drugs and such of the above referred 
intermediates exported shall be exhibited in separate cost statements and the 
same excluded from the cost statements of these products sold in the internal 
market.
 


If a company follows a system of ascertaining 
costs on any basis other than actuals such as standard costing, the method 
adopted for arriving at the actual costs shown in the Proforma of Schedule II 
shall also be indicated in the cost records. Packing, selling and distribution 
expenses in respect of each size of packing shall also be maintained separately.
 


Proforma ‘B’ of Schedule II is meant to 
exhibit the final cost of each intermediate and bulk drug. Where, however, an 
intermediate or bulk drug passes through identifiable stages of process such as 
fermentationf crystallisation, 
extraction and purification as in the case of manufacture or antibiotics, cost 
records for such stages shall be maintained and reconciled with the data 
incorporated in Proforma ‘B’ of Schedule II.
 


XVIII. Work-in-progress and finished goods 
stock
 


The basis of arriving at the cost of 
work-in-progress and finished goods stock shall be indicated in the cost of 
records so as to reveal the cost elements that have been taken into account in 
such computations. The cost elements referred to shall be related to the items 
shown in the Schedule II. The method adopted shall be consistently followed. 
Records shall be maintained by the company in such details so as to enable it to 
fill up the particulars in Proforma ‘D’ of Schedule II.
 


XIX. Reconciliation of cost and financial 
accounts
 


The cost records shall be periodically 
reconciled with the financial books of accounts so as to ensure accuracy. 
Variations, if any, shall be clearly, indicated and explained. The period for 
which such reconciliation is effected shall not exceed the period of the 
financial year of the company. The reconciliation shall be done in such a manner 
that the profitability of the product under reference can be correctly adjudged 
and reconciled with the overall profits of the company from all its activities.
 


A statement showing the total expenses 
incurred by the company indicating the share applicable to bulk drugs shall be 
maintained in Proforma ‘E’ of Schedule II and reconciled with the financial 
accounts.
 


XX. Records for stock verification
 


Records of physical stock verification shall 
be maintained in respect of all materials including different solvents, raw 
materials, packing materials, consumable stores, small tools and machinery 
spares and other finished goods stock. Records of consumption and production 
shall also be reconciled with the excise returns. Any losses or surpluses 
arising out of such verification or losses in storage or in transit shall also 
be indicated separately stating the method of their treatment in cost records.
 


XXI. Statistical statements and other records
 


Statistical statements and other records 
shall be maintained in such details so as to enable the company to comply with 
the requirements of this Schedule and Schedule II and to enable the cost auditor 
to report to the Company Law Board on all the points referred to in the Cost 
Audit (Report) Rules, 1958, as amended from time to time. Data relating to 
batchwise production, standard and actual yields, operational efficiency of 
individual departments, solvent losses, number of fermentations carried out, 
equipment occupancy usage as well as details of major repairs and maintenance 
carried out shall be maintained. Such records as will enable to identify, as far 
as possible, the capital employed separately for the bulk drugs activity shall 
also be kept. The data shall also reveal fresh investments on fixed assets that 
have not contributed to the production during the year. The broad effect of 
under utilisation of capacity, if any, on the cost of production of the bulk 
drug, shall also be made available in the records.
 

 
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>