<act><tid>318197</tid>
<title>THE VACCINATION ACT, <year>1880</year></title>

ACT NO. 13 OF <year>1880</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 9th July, <year>1880</year>.]

An Act to give power to prohibit inoculation and to make the 
vaccination of children compulsory in certain Municipalities 
and Cantonments. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

Preamble. WHEREAS it is expedient to give power to prohibit 
certain municipalities and cantonments 2; It is hereby enacted as 
inoculation, and make the vaccination of children compulsory in 
follows:-





<article><tid>1309180</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title Application. This Act may be called the Vaccination Act, 
<year>1880</year>: and it shall apply only to such municipalities and cantonments <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 
situate in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Uttar Pradesh, (Application.) <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Punjab as it existed 
immediately before the 1st November, <year>1956</year>], the Central Provinces, 
Assam, Delhi, Ajmer] and Coorg as it may be extended to in manner 
hereinafter provided.


</article>



<article><tid>1100443</tid>
<number> 2</number> Interpretation- clause. In this Act unless there is something 
repugnant in the subject or context,-
<section><tid>1390694</tid>
<number>1</number>" Municipal Commissioners." the expression" Municipal 
Commissioners" means a body of Municipal Commissioners or a 
Municipal Committee constituted under the provisions of any 
enactment for the time being in force:

</section>

<section><tid>159989</tid>
<number>2</number>" parent" means the father of a legitimate child and the 
mother of an illegitimate child:

</section>

<section><tid>898771</tid>
<number>3</number>" guardian" includes any person who has accepted or 
assumed the care or custody of any child:

</section>

<section><tid>351104</tid>
<number>4</number>" unprotected child" means a child who has not been 
protected from small- pox by having had that disease either
<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act has been amended in its application to- 
Ajmer by Act 6 of <year>1945</year>;

C. P. by C. P. Acts 3 of <year>1915</year>, 6 of <year>1932</year> and 4 of <year>1933</year>; 
C. P. and Berar by C. P. and Berar Act 44 of <year>1947</year>; 
U. P. by U. P. Act 2 of <year>1907</year>.

This Act has been repealed in Coorg by Coorg Act 4 of <year>1950</year>; and 
in Punjab by Punjab Act 49 of <year>1953</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The long title and preamble have been amended in U. P. and C. 
P. so a to include other local areas.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>This provision has been amended in U. P. and C. P. so as to 
include other local areas.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The original words have been successively amended by the A. O. 
<year>1937</year> A. O. <year>1948</year> and A. O. <year>1950</year> to read as above.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by the Adaptation of Laws (No. 2) Order, <year>1956</year>, for" 
Punjab".

Extended to the whole of Madhya Pradesh by Madhya Pradesh Act 23 of 
<year>1958</year> (when notified.)

Rep. in Orissa by Orissa Act 13 of <year>1960</year> (w. e. f---).

An. in Himanchal Pradesh an H. P. Act 17 of <year>1969</year>.

Extended to Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1967</year>): vide Reg. 8 of <year>1965</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

Extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 
and Schedule.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


naturally or by inoculation, or by having been successfully 
vaccinated, and who has not been certified under this Act to 
be insusceptible to vaccination:


</section>

<section><tid>955179</tid>
<number>5</number>" inoculation" means any operation performed with the 
object of producing the disease of small- pox in any person by 
means of variolous matter:

</section>

<section><tid>1595510</tid>
<number>6</number>" vaccination- circle" means one of the parts into 
which a municipality or cantonment has been divided under 
this Act for the performance of vaccination:

</section>

<section><tid>582671</tid>
<number>7</number>" vaccinator" means any vaccinator appointed under 
this Act to perform the operation of vaccination, or any 
private person authorized <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in manner hereinafter 
provided to perform the same operation; and includes a" 
Superintendent of vaccination":

</section>

<section><tid>1605179</tid>
<number>8</number>" vaccination- season" means the period from time to 
time fixed by the State Government for any local area under 
its administration by notification in the Official Gazette, 
during which alone vaccination may be performed under this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1918686</tid>
<number>3</number>Extension of act of municipalities. A majority in number of the 
persons present at a meeting of the Municipal Commissioners specially 
convened in this behalf may apply to the State Government to extend 
this Act to the whole or any part of a municipality, and thereupon the 
State Government may, if it thinks fit, by notification published in 
the Official Gazette, declare its intention to extend this Act in the 
manner proposed.
Any inhabitant of such municipality or part thereof who objects 
to such extension may within six weeks from the date of such publica- 
tion, send his objection in writing to the Secretary to the State 
Government, and the State Government shall take such objection into 
consideration. When six weeks from the said publication have expired, 
the State Government, if no such objections have been sent as 
aforesaid, or (when such objections have been so sent) if in its 
opinion they are insufficient, may by like notification effect the 
proposed extension.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" by the L. G." omitted by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and 
Sch., Pt. 1.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>In the U, P. a new s. 3A has been inserted by U. P. Act 2 of 
<year>1907</year> providing for extension of the Act to other local areas. In the 
C. P. ss. 3A, 3B, 3C and 3D have been inserted for a similar purpose 
by C. P. Acts 3 of <year>1915</year>, 6 of <year>1932</year> and 4 of <year>1933</year> respectively.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>191986</tid>
<number>4</number>Extension to cantonments. The State Government may <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> by 
notification in the Official Gazette, extend this Act to the whole or 
any part of a military cantonment.


</article>



<article><tid>735245</tid>
<number>5</number>Power to withdraw local area form operation of Act. The State 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, withdraw any 
local area in a municipality <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> any local area in a 
cantonment, from the operation of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1772374</tid>
<number>6</number>Prohibition of inoculation. In any local area to which the 
provisions of this Act apply, inoculation shall be prohibited; and
Inoculated persons not to enter, without certificate, local area 
subject to Act. No person who has undergone inoculation shall enter such 
area before the lapse of forty days from the date of the operation, 
with out a certificate from a medical practitioner, of such class as 
the State Government may from time to time by written order authorize 
to grant such certificates, stating that such person is no longer 
likely to produce small- pox by contact or near approach.



</article>



<article><tid>965147</tid>
<number>7</number>Vaccination circles. Every local area to which this Act 
applies shall be a vaccination- circle, or shall in manner hereinafter 
provided be divided into a number of such circles;


</article>



<article><tid>1305230</tid>
<number>8</number>Private vaccinators. The <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Commissioner] may by written 
licence authorize private vaccinators to perform vaccination in any 
vaccination- circle, and may suspend or cancel any such licence.


</article>



<article><tid>1322880</tid>
<number>9</number>Unprotected children to be vaccinated. When any unprotected 
child, having attained the age of 6 months, has resided for a period 
of one month during the vaccination- season in any local area to which 
the provisions of this Act apply, and has not at the expiration of 
such period attained the age, if a boy, of fourteen years, and if a 
girl, of eight years, the parent or guardian of such child shall take 
it, or cause it to be taken, to a vaccinator to be vaccinated, or send 
for a vaccinator to vaccinate it.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" subject to the control of the G. G. in C." omitted 
by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. The words" subject to the 
control" were subs. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I, for" 
with the previous sanction".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>This provision has been amended in the U. P. and the C. P. so 
as to include other local areas.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year> s. 2 and Sch., Pt. 1, for" L. G.".





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1909403</tid>
<number>10</number>Inspection after vacination. The parent or guardian of every 
child which has been vaccinated under section nine shall, on the date 
of inspection stated in the memorandum, take the child, or cause it to 
be taken, to a vaccinator for inspection, or get it inspected at his 
own house by a vaccinator; and
such vaccinator shall then append to the memorandum a certificate 
stating that the child has been inspected and the result of such 
inspection.



</article>



<article><tid>1660259</tid>
<number>11</number>Procedure when vaccination is successful. When it 
is ascertained at the time of inspecting a child under section 
section ten that the vaccination has been successful, a certificate 
shall be delivered by the vaccinator to the parent or guardian of 
such child to that effect, and such child shall thereafter be deemed 
to be protected.


</article>



<article><tid>1192564</tid>
<number>12</number>Procedure when vaccination is unsuccessful. When it is 
ascertained as aforesaid that the vaccination has been unsuccessful, 
the parent or guardian shall, if the vaccinator so direct, cause the 
child to be forthwith again vaccinated and subsequently inspected in 
manner hereinbefore provided.


</article>



<article><tid>1442945</tid>
<number>13</number>Procedure when child is unfit for vaccination. A certificate 
granted under section nine showing the unfitness of a child for 
vaccination shall remain in force for the period stated therein, and 
on the termination of that period, or, if that period terminates after 
the vaccination- season is over, when the next vaccination season 
begins, the parent or guardian of such child shall take the child, or 
cause it to be taken, to a vaccinator to be vaccinated, or procure its 
vaccination at his own house by a vaccinator:


</article>



<article><tid>228845</tid>
<number>14</number>Certificates of insusceptibility of successful vaccination. If 
the Superintendent of vaccination is of opinion that a child which has 
been three times unsuccessfully vaccinated is insusceptible of 
successful vaccination, he shall deliver to the parent or guardian

<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

of such child a certificate under his hand to that effect; and the 
parent or guardian shall thenceforth not be required to cause the 
child to be vaccinated.



</article>



<article><tid>1836230</tid>
<number>15</number>What lymph to be used. The vaccination of a child shall 
ordinarily be performed with such lymph as may be prescribed by the 
rules to be made under this Act:
Provided that,

First, if animal- lymph is so prescribed and the parent or 
guardian of any child desires that such child shall be 
vaccinated with human lymph, it shall be so vaccinated; 
and

Second, if in any local area in which animal- lymph is 
procurable human lymph is so prescribed, and the parent 
or guardian of any child desires that such child should 
be vaccinated with animal- lymph, and tenders to the 
vaccinator the amount of such fee, not exceeding one 
rupee, as may be fixed by such rules in this behalf, 
such child shall be so vaccinated.



</article>



<article><tid>1437513</tid>
<number>16</number>No fee to be charged except by private vaccinator. No fee 
shall be charged by any vaccinator except a private vaccinator to the 
parent or guardian of any child for any of the duties imposed on such 
vaccinator by or under the provisions of this Act:
Provided that it shall be lawful for a vaccinator to accept a fee 
for vaccinating a child by request of the parent or guardian elsewhere 
than in the circle for which such vaccinator is appointed.



</article>



<article><tid>1006754</tid>
<number>17</number>Duties of Superintendent of vaccination. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> The 
Superintendent of vaccination, in addition to the 
other duties imposed on him by or under the provisions of this Act, 
shall ascertain whether all unprotected children, under the age of 
fourteen years if boys, and under the age of eight years if girls, 
within the local area under his superintendence have been vaccinated; 
and, if he has reason to believe that the parent or guardian of any 
such child is bound by the provisions hereinbefore contained to 
procure the vaccination of such child or to present it for 
inspection, and has omitted so to do, he shall personally go to the 
house of such parent or guardian, and there make enquiry, and shall, 
if the fact is proved, forthwith deliver to such parent or guardian, 
or cause to be affixed to his house, a notice requiring that the child 
be vaccinated, or (the case may be) that it be presented for 
inspection, at a time and place to be specified in such notice.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 17 has been amended in C. P. and Berar by C. P. and Berar Act 44 
of <year>1947</year>.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1692014</tid>
<number>18</number>Order by Magistrate when notice not complied with. If such 
notice is not complied with, the Superintendent of vaccination shall 
report the matter to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Magistrate of the District, or such 
Magistrate as the State Government or the Magistrate of the District 
may from time to time appoint in this behalf; and the Magistrate 
receiving such report shall summon the parent or guardian of the child 
and demand his explanation, and shall, if such explanation is not 
satisfactory, make an order in writing directing such parent or 
guardian to comply with the notice before a date specified in the 
order.
Procedure when order not obeyed. If on such date the order has 
not been obeyed, the Magistrate shall summon the parent or guardian 
before him, and unless just cause or excuse is shown, shall deal with 
the disobedience as an offence punishable under section twenty- two.

Magistrates to be non- officialls. The Magistrates appointed under 
this section shall, as far as is conveniently practicable, <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> not be 
paid servants of Government].



</article>



<article><tid>1765930</tid>
<number>19</number>Power to make rules for municipalities. When this Act has been 
applied to any municipality or any part thereof, the Municipal 
Commissioners may, from time to time, make rules consistent with this 
Act for the proper enforcement of this Act within the limits to which 
it applies. Such rules shall be made in the manner in which, under 
the law for the time being in force, the <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Municipal] Commissioners 
make rules or bye- laws for the regulation of other matters within the 
limits of the municipality, and shall, when confirmed by the 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Commissioner] and published in the Official Gazette, have the force 
of law:
Provided that the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Commissioner] may at any time rescind or 
modify any such rule. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>229134</tid>
<number>20</number>Power to make rules for cantonments. When this Act has been 
applied to any cantonment or any part thereof, the State Government 
may, from time to time, <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> make such rules.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Read District Magistrate, see the Code of Criminal Procedure, 
<year>1898</year> (Act 5 of <year>1898</year>), s. 3 (2).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for" be Natives of India, and not 
paid servants of the Crown". The last word subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, 
for" Govt.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I, ibid., for" L. G.".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>After this section a new s. 19A has been ins. in the U. P. and 
two new ss. 19A and 19B in the C. P. by U. P. Act 2 of <year>1907</year> and C. P. 
Acts 3 of <year>1915</year> and 6 of 1. 932, respectively.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>The words" subject to the control of the G. G, in C." omitted 
by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>511933</tid>
<number> 21</number> What rules under sections 19 and 20 may provide for. The rules 
to be made for any local area under section nineteen or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> twenty may, 
among other matters, provide for-
<section><tid>1013970</tid>
<number>a</number>the division of such local area into circles for the 
performance of vaccination;

</section>

<section><tid>610660</tid>
<number>b</number>the appointment of a place in each vaccination- circle 
as a public vaccine- station, and the posting of some distin- 
guishing mark in a conspicuous place near such station;

</section>

<section><tid>665484</tid>
<number>c</number>the qualifications to be required of public vaccinators 
and Superintendents of vaccination;

</section>

<section><tid>1243484</tid>
<number>d</number>the authority with which their appointment, suspension 
and dismissal shall rest;

</section>

<section><tid>224855</tid>
<number>e</number>the time of attendance of public vaccinators at the 
vaccine- stations, and their residence within the limits of the 
vaccination- circles;

</section>

<section><tid>606573</tid>
<number>f</number>the distinguishing mark or badge to be worn by them;

</section>

<section><tid>1899247</tid>
<number>g</number>the amount of fee chargeable by private vaccinators, 
and their guidance generally in the performance of their 
duties;

</section>

<section><tid>1818850</tid>
<number>h</number>the facilities to be afforded to people for procuring 
the vaccination of their children at their own houses;

</section>

<section><tid>1020284</tid>
<number>i</number>the grant and form of certificates of successful 
vaccination, of unfitness for vaccination or of 
insusceptibility of vaccination;

</section>

<section><tid>151415</tid>
<number>j</number>the nature of the lymph to be used and the supply of a 
sufficient quantity of such lymph;

</section>

<section><tid>1626601</tid>
<number>k</number>the fee to be paid for vaccination with animal- lymph 
under section fifteen;

</section>

<section><tid>464037</tid>
<number>l</number>the fee to be paid to a public vaccinator for 
vaccinating a child beyond the vaccination- circle at the 
request of the parent or guardian of the said child;

</section>

<section><tid>691368</tid>
<number>m</number>the preparation and keeping of registers showing-
the names of children born in such local area on or after 
the date of the application of this Act;

the names of unprotected children born in such local area 
previous to the application of this Act, and who are, at the 
time this Act is applied, under the age of fourteen years if 
boys, and of eight years if girls;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The word and letter" nineteen A" have been ins. at this place 
in the U. P. and the words and letters" nineteen A, nineteen B" have 
been ins. in the C. P., by U. P. Act 2 of <year>1907</year> and C. P. Acts 3 of 
<year>1915</year> and 6 of <year>1932</year>, respectively.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


the names of unprotected boys and girls respectively under 
those ages brought within such local area at any time after 
the application of this Act and who have resided there for a 
month;

the result of each vaccination or its postponement, and the 
delivery of certificates, if any;


</section>

<section><tid>455489</tid>
<number>n</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the assistance to be given by the Municipal 
Commissioners and municipal servants in the preparation of 
these registers, and in other matters; and

</section>

<section><tid>64689</tid>
<number>o</number>the preparation of vaccination- reports and returns.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>852869</tid>
<number> 22</number> Punishment of offences. Whoever commits any of the 
undermentioned offences (that is to say):-
<section><tid>1106220</tid>
<number>a</number>violates the provisions of section six,

</section>

<section><tid>1867055</tid>
<number>b</number>neglects without just excuse to obey an order made 
under section eighteen,

</section>

<section><tid>816008</tid>
<number>c</number>breaks any of the rules made under section nineteen <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> 
or twenty, or

</section>

<section><tid>991387</tid>
<number>d</number>neglects without just cause to obey an order made under 
section eighteen after having been previously convicted of so 
neglecting to obey a similar order made in respect of the 
same child,
shall be punished as follows (that is to say):-

in the case of the offence mentioned in clause (a), with 
simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to three 
months, or with fine which may extend to two hundred rupees, 
or with both;

in the case of the offences mentioned in clauses (b) and 
 (c), with fine which may extend to fifty rupees; and

in the case of the offence mentioned in clause (d), with 
simple imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, 
or with both.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>11</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This cl. has been amended in the C. P. by C. P. Act 6 of <year>1932</year>, 
so as to include members of District Boards Councils and the servants 
of those local bodies.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The word and letter" nineteen A" have been ins. at this place 
in the U. P. and the words and letters" nineteen A, nineteen B" have 
been ins. in the C. P. by U. P. Act 2 of <year>1907</year> and C. P. Acts 3 of 
<year>1915</year> and 6 of <year>1932</year>, respectively.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1766842</tid>
<number>23</number>Municipal funds to receive fees and meet expenditure. The 
amount of all fees <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> realized, and the amount of all expenditure 
incurred, under this Act in any municipality shall respectively be 
credited to and paid from the Municipal Fund. <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>12</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" and fines" omitted by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>This section has been amended in the U. P., the Punjab and the 
C. P. by U. P. Act 2 of <year>1907</year>, Punjab Acts 9 of <year>1925</year> and 2 of <year>1929</year>, and 
C. P. Act 6 of <year>1932</year>, respectively so as to include other local areas 
and funds.

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>