<act><title>The debts Recovery 
      Appellate Tribunal (Procedure for appointment as chairperson 
      of the Appellate Tribunal) Rules, 
      19981</title> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short 
      title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the 
      Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal (Procedure for Appointment as 
      <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Chairperson] of the Appellate Tribunal) Rules, 
      1998.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come 
      into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
Gazette.  
  




 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number> 
      Definitions.—In these rules, 
      unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section><number>a</number>    “Act” means the Recovery of 
      Debts Due to Banks and Financial Institutions Act, 1993 (51 to 1993);  
 </section><section><number>b</number>    “Appellate Tribunal” means the 
      Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal established under section 8 of the Act;  
 </section><section><number>c</number>    1[“Chairperson”] means a person appointed as 1[Chairperson] of an Appellate Tribunal under section 9 of the Act;  
 </section><section><number>d</number>    “Reserve Bank” means the Reserve 
      Bank of India constituted under section 3 of the Reserve Bank of India 
      Act, 1934 (2 of 1934);
 </section><section><number>e</number>    all other words and expressions 
      used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the 
      meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.  
  
  








 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number> Method of 
      appointment under section 9 of the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of appointment 
      to the post of a 1[Chairperson] , there shall be a 
      Selection Committee consisting of—
 <subsection><number>i</number>    the Chief Justice of India or a 
      Judge of the Supreme Court of India as nominated by the Chief Justice of 
      India;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    the Secretary to the Government 
      of India in the Ministry of Finance (Department of Economic 
      Affairs);
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    the Secretary to the 
      Government of India in the Ministry of Law and Justice;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>    the Governor, of the Reserve 
      Bank or the Deputy Governor of the Reserve Bank nominated by the Governor 
      of the Reserve Bank;
 2[(v)    the Secretary, in the absence of whom 
      Special Secretary, in the absence of both, the Additional Secretary, 
      Ministry of Finance, Department of Economic Affairs, Banking 
      Division.]
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Chief Justice 
      of India the Judge of the Supreme Court shall be the Chairman of the 
      Selection Committee.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any three members 
      of the Committee including the Chairman shall form a quorum for meeting of 
      the Committee.
 1[(4) The Selection Committee may 
      devise its own procedure including interview for selection and appointment 
      of Chairperson:
 Provided that the 
      procedure of interview shall not apply in case of a Judge of a High Court 
      nominated by the Chief Justice of such High Court.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Selection 
      Committee shall recommend persons for appointment of 
      Chairperson,—
 <subsection><number>i</number>    from amongst the persons from 
      the list of candidates prepared by the Ministry of Finance after inviting 
      necessary applications; and
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    from amongst the Judges of High 
      Court nominated by the Chief Justice of such High Courts.
 </subsection></section><section><number>6</number> The Central 
      Government shall on the basis of the recommendations of the Selection 
      Committee make a list of persons selected for appointment as 
      1[Chairperson] and the said list 
      shall be valid for a period of two years. The appointment of a 
      1[Chairperson] shall be made from 
      the list so prepared.
  






 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Medical 
      Fitness.—No 
      person shall be appointed as a 1[Chairperson] unless he is declared 
      medically fit by a Medical Board to be constituted by the Central 
      Government for the purpose unless he has already been declared fit by an 
      equivalent authority.  
  







 
</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> 
      Interpretation.—If any question 
      arises relating to the interpretation of these rules the same shall be 
      referred to the Central Government for its decision.  
  
  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number> 
      Saving.—Nothing in these rules 
      shall affect reservations, relaxation of age limit and other concessions 
      required to be provided for the Scheduled Castes, Scheduled Tribes, other 
      Backward Classes, ex-servicemen and other special categories of persons, 
      in accordance with the orders issued by the Central Government from time 
      to time in this regard.  
  
  
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Oaths of 
      office and secrecy.—Every person appointed to be 1[Chairperson] under section 9 of 
      the Act shall, before entering upon his office, make and subscribe an oath 
      of office and secrecy in the Forms annexed to these 
      rules.  
  








 
</article><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

The debts Recovery 
      Appellate Tribunal  
(Procedure for appointment as chairperson 
       
of the Appellate Tribunal) Rules, 
      1998
 

 
 

 
 

ANNEXURE
 

Form 
      I
 

(See rule 7)  
 

Form of oath of office for 
      1[Chairperson] of the 
       
Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal
 

 
 

“I,.................(Name of the 1[Chairperson]), having been appointed as 1[Chairperson] do solemnly affirm/do swear in the name of God that I 
      will faithfully and conscientiously discharge my duties as 1[Chairperson] to the best of my ability, knowledge and judgment, 
      without fear or favour, affection or ill will.  
 

Name of 
      the 1[Chairperson]
 

Debts Recovery 
      Appellate Tribunal
 

 
 

Form 
      II
 

(See rule 7)
 

Form 
      of oath of secrecy for 1[Chairperson] of the 
       
Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal
 

 
 

“I,.................(Name of the 1[Chairperson]), having been appointed as 1[Chairperson] do solemnly affirm/do swear in the name of God that I 
      will not directly or indirectly communicate or reveal to any person or 
      persons any matter which shall be brought under my consideration or shall 
      become known to me as 1[Chairperson] of said Debts Recovery Appellate Tribunal except as 
      may be required for the due discharge of my duties as the 1[Chairperson].
 

Name of 
      the 1[Chairperson]
 

Debts Recovery 
      Appellate Tribunal
 

 
 

 
 

-------------------------
 

     
      1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 645(E), dated 2nd August, 2000 (w.e.f. 
      2-8-2000).
 

-------------------------
 

  
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by 
      G.S.R. 645(E), dated 2nd August, 2000 (w.e.f. 2-8-2000).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 103(E), 
      dated 25th February, 2005, for “ (v) an special Additional Secretary to 
      the Government of India in the Ministry of Finance, Department of Economic 
      Affairs, (Banking Division) or an officer not below the rank of Joint 
      Secretary in the Banking Division nominated by the special Additional 
      Secretary in the Banking Division.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>