<act><title>

THE 
    CHILD MARRIAGE RESTRAINT ACT, 1929</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number>

Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Child Marriage Restraint Act, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[1929].
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[except the State of Jammu and 
    Kashmir]; and it applies also to all citizens of India without and beyond 
    India.]
 </section><section>
 <number>3</number> It shall 
    come into force on the 1st day of April, 1930.






  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—
 
 <section>
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[<number>a</number>   
      "child" means a person who, if a male, has not completed twenty-one years 
      of age, and if a female, has not completed eighteen years of age;]
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   "child marriage" means a marriage to 
      which either of the contracting parties is a child;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   "contracting party" to a marriage 
      means either of the parties whose marriage is <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[or 
      is about to be] thereby solemnised; and
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   "minor" means a person of either sex 
      who is under eighteen years of age.
</section>






  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Punishment for male adult below twenty-one years of age marrying a child.—Whoever, 
    being a male above eighteen years of age and below twenty-one, contracts a 
    child marriage <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[shall be punishable with simple imprisonment 
    which may extend to fifteen days, or with fine which may extend to one 
    thousand rupees, or with both].
 








  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Punishment for male adult above twenty-one years of age marrying a child.—Whoever, 
    being a male above twenty-one years of age, contracts a child marriage shall 
    be punishable with <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[simple imprisonment which may extend to 
    three months and shall also be liable to fine].





  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Punishment for solemnising a child marriage.—Whoever 
    performs, conducts or directs any child marriage shall be punishable with
    <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[simple imprisonment which may extend to three months and shall 
    also be liable to fine], unless he proves that he had reason to believe that 
    the marriage was not a child marriage.





  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Punishment for parent or guardian concerned in a child marriage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a minor contracts a child marriage, any person having charge of the 
    minor, whether as parent or guardian or in any other capacity, lawful or 
    unlawful, who does any act to promote the marriage or permits it to be 
    solemnised, or negligently fails to prevent it from being solemnised, shall 
    be punishable with <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[simple imprisonment which may extend to 
    three months and shall also be liable to fine]:
 
Provided that 
    no woman shall be punishable with imprisonment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of this section, it shall be presumed, unless and until the 
    contrary is proved, that where a minor has contracted a child marriage, the 
    person having charge of such minor has negligently failed to prevent the 
    marriage from being solemnised.





  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>7</number> 
    Offences to be cognizable for certain purposes.—The 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), shall apply to offences under 
    this Act as if they were cognizable offences—
 
 <section><number>a</number>   
      for the purpose of investigation of such offences; and
 </section><section><number>b</number>   
      for the purposes of matters other than (i) matters referred to in section 
      42 of that Code, and (ii) the arrest of a person without a warrant or 
      without an order of a Magistrate.]
</section>





  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number> 
      Jurisdiction under this Act.—Notwithstanding anything contained 
      in section 190 of the <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 
      (2 of 1974),] no court other than that of a <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[Metropolitan 
      Magistrate or a Judicial <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[Magistrate of the first class]] 
      shall take cognizance of, or try, any offence under this 
      Act.






  
 
  
  
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[<number>9</number> 
    Mode of taking cognizance of offences.—No court shall take cognizance of 
    any offence under this Act after the expiry of one year from the date on 
    which the offence is alleged to have been committed.]





  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> 
    Preliminary inquiries into offences.—Any 
    court, on receipt of a complaint of an offence of which it is authorised to 
    take cognizance, shall, unless it dismisses the complaint under section 203 
    of the <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974)] either 
    itself make an inquiry under section 202 of that Code or direct a Magistrate 
    subordinate to it to make such inquiry.]






  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Power to 
    take security from complainant.—[Repealed 
    by the Child Marriage Restraint (Amendment) Act, 1949 (41 of 1949) sec. 7.]
  

  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>12</number> 
    Power to issue injunction prohibiting marriage in contravention of this Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in this Act, the court 
    may, if satisfied from information laid before it through a complaint or 
    otherwise that a child marriage in contravention of this Act has been 
    arranged or is about to be solemnised, issue an injunction against any of 
    the persons mentioned in sections 3, 4, 5 and 6 of this Act prohibiting such 
    marriage.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    injunction under sub-section (1) shall be issued against any person unless 
    the court has previously given notice to such person, and has afforded him 
    an opportunity to show cause against the issue of the injunction.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The court 
    may either on its own motion or on the application of any person aggrieved 
    rescind or alter any order made under sub-section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where such 
    an application is received, the court shall afford the applicant an early 
    opportunity of appearing before it either in person or by pleader; and if 
    the court rejects the application wholly or in part, it shall record in 
    writing its reasons for so doing.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Whoever 
    knowing that an injunction has been issued against him under sub-section (1) 
    of this section disobeys such injunction shall be punished with imprisonment 
    of either description for a term which may extend to three months, or with 
    fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both:
 
Provided that 
    no woman shall be punishable with imprisonment.]



  

 
  
 

  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Subs. by Act 8 of 
    1930, sec. 2 and Sch. 1, for "1928".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>  Subs. by A.O. 
    1950, for the former sub-section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>  Subs. by Act 3 of 
    1951 sec. 3 and Sch., for "except Part B States".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>  Subs. by Act 2 of 
    1978, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 2-10-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>  Subs. by Act 19 of 
    1938, sec. 2.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>   
    Subs. by Act 41 of 1949, sec. 3 for "shall be punishable with fine which may 
    extend to one</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number>  Subs. by Act 41 of 1949, 
    sec. 4, for "simple imprisonment which may extend to one month, or with fine 
    which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both"</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number>   Subs. by Act 41 of 1949, 
    sec. 4, for "simple imprisonment which may extend to one month, or with fine 
    which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>   Subs. by Act 41 of 1949, 
    sec. 4, for "simple imprisonment which may extend to one month, or with fine 
    which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number>   Ins. by Act 2 of 1978, 
    sec. 3 (w.e.f. 2-10-1978).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number>   Subs. by Act 2 of 
      1978, sec. 4, for the words "Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number>   Subs. by Act 2 of 
      1978, sec. 4, for certain words.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. by Act 19 of 
      1938, sec. 3, for "District Magistrate".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. by Act 19 of 1938, 
    sec 4, for the original section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>   Subs. by Act 41 of 
    1949, sec. 6 for the original section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>   Subs. by Act 2 of 
    1978, sec. 5, for the words "Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898".</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number>   Ins. by Act 19 of 
    1938, sec. 6.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>