<act><title>THE INDUSTRIAL TRIBUNAL (CENTRAL PROCEDURE) 
RULES, 19541</title> 

  
 <article><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Industrial Tribunal 
(Central Procedure) Rules, 1954. 


</article> 

  
 <article><number>2</number> In these rules 
 
 <section><number>a</number>    the Act means the Industrial Disputes 
  Act, 1947 (14 of 1947); 
 </section><section><number>b</number>    Chairman means the Chairman of the 
  Tribunal; 
 </section><section><number>c</number>    member means a member of the 
  Tribunal; 
 </section><section><number>d</number>    section means a section of the Act; 
  
 </section><section><number>e</number>    Tribunal means the Industrial 
  Tribunal constituted under section 7 consisting of two or more members. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>3</number> In the case of a Tribunal where it consists of two 
or more members, the Chairman may sit alone or with one or more members to hear 
an application or complaint in writing under section 33 or section 33A, as the 
case may be, for inquiry and report to the Tribunal or entrust any such 
application or complaint to one or more members, as he deems fit, for such 
enquiry and report.



</article> 

  
 <article><number>4</number> The Chairman may withdraw any case or matters referred to 
one or more members, under rule 3 and transfer the same to himself or any other 
member or members. 



</article> 

  
 <article><number>5</number> The report under rule 3, where the enquiry is made by one or 
more members, shall be submitted to the Chairman and where the enquiry is by the 
Chairman sitting alone or with one or more members, the report shall be 
submitted to the Tribunal: 
 Provided that in all cases, the final order on such application 
or complaint shall be passed by the Tribunal after taking into consideration the 
report submitted to it by the Chairman sitting singly or with one or more 
members or by any other member or members. 



</article> 

  
 <article><number>6</number> The Tribunal shall, after considering the report submitted 
to the Chairman under rule 5 and making such further enquiry, if any, as it 
thinks fit, give its decision or award as the case may be. 



</article> 

  
 <article><number>7</number> For the purposes of making an enquiry under these rules the 
Chairman or member or members, as the case may be, shall have all the powers of 
the Tribunal under section 11 and the provisions of rules 14 to 21, 24, 30 and 
31 of the Industrial Disputes (Central) Rules, 1947, shall apply to such enquiry 
as if the Chairman or member or members by themselves constituted the Tribunal. 




</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. by S.R.O. 3534, dated 1st December, 1954.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>