<act><title>
the
Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 20031</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 2003.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official
Gazette. 
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions—In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 

 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Medical Termination of Pregnancy Act, 1971 (34 of
1971);
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Chief Medical Officer” means the Chief Medical Officer of a
District, by whatever name called;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Form” means a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“owner”, in relation to a place, means any person who is the
administrative head or otherwise responsible for the working or maintenance of a
hospital or place, by whatever name called, where the pregnancy may be
terminated under this Act.
 </section><section><number>e</number>
“Committee” means a committee constituted at the district level under
the proviso to clause (b) of section 4 read with rule 3.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Composition and tenure of District level Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> One member of the district level Committee shall be the Gynaecologist/Surgeon/Anesthetist
and other members from the local medical profession, non-governmental
organizations, and Panchayati Raj Institution of the district:  
 

 Provided
that one of the members of the Committee shall be a woman. 
 

 </section><section><number>2</number>
Tenure of the committee shall be
for two calendar years and the tenure of the non-Government members shall not be
more than two terms. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Experience and training under clause (d) of section 2.—For the purpose of
clause (d) of section (2), a registered medical practitioner shall have one or
more of the following experience or training in gynaecology and obstetrics,
namely:— 
 

 <section><number>a</number>
in the case of a medical practitioner, who was registered in a State
Medical Register immediately before the commencement of the Act, experience in
the practice of gynaecology and obstetrics for a period of not less than three
years; 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
in the case of a medical practitioner, who is registered in a State
Medical Register:— 
 

 <subsection><number>i</number>
if he has completed six months of house surgency in gynaecology and
obstetrics; or 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
unless the following facilities are provided therein, if he had
experience at any hospital for a period of not less than one year in the
practice of obstetrics and gynaecology; or 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>c</number>
if he has assisted a registered medical practitioner in the performance
of twenty-five cases of medical termination of pregnancy of which at least five
have been performed independently, in a hospital established or maintained, or a
training institute approved for this purpose by the Government. 
 

 <subsection><number>i</number>
This training would enable the Registered Medical Practitioner (RMP) to
do only Ist Trimester terminations (up to 12 weeks of gestation).  
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
For terminations up to twenty weeks the experience or training as
prescribed under sub-rules (a), (b) and (d) shall apply. 
 

 </subsection></section><section><number>d</number>
in case of a medical practitioner who has been registered in a State
Medical Register and who holds a post-graduate degree or diploma in gynaecology
and obstetrics, the experience or training gained during the course of such
degree or diploma. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Approval of a place.—
<section><number>1</number> No place shall be approved under clause (b) of
section 4,— 
 

 <subsection><number>i</number>
unless the Government is satisfied that termination of pregnancies may be
done therein under safe and hygienic conditions; and 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
unless the following facilities are provided therein, namely:— 
 

 in
case of first trimester, that is, up to 12 weeks of pregnancy:— 
 

 a
gynaecology examination/labour table, resuscitation and sterilization equipment,
drugs and parental fluid, back up facilities for treatment of shock and
facilities for transportation; and 
 

 in
case of second trimester, that is up to 20 weeks of pregnancy:— 
 

 <subsubsection><number>a</number>
an operation table and instruments for performing abdominal or
gynaecological surgery; 
 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number>
anaesthetic equipment, resuscitation equipment and sterilization
equipment; 
 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number>
drugs and parental fluids for emergency use, notified by Government of
India from time to time. 
 

 Explanation.—In
the case of termination of early pregnancy up to seven weeks using RU-486 with
Misoprostol, the same may be prescribed by a Registered Medical Practitioner (RMP)
as defined under clause (d) of section 2 of the Act and section 4 of MTP Rules,
at his clinic, provided such a Registered Medical Practitioner has access to a
place approved under Section 4 of the MTP Act, 1971 read with MTP (Amendment)
Act, 2002 and rule 5 of the MTP Rules. For the purpose of access, the RMP should
display a Certificate to this effect from the owner of the approved place. 
 

 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number>
Every application for the approval of a place shall be in Form A and shall be
addressed to the Chief Medical Officer of the District. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
On receipt of an application under sub-rule (2), the Chief Medical Officer of
the District may verify any information contained, in any such application or
inspect any such place with a view to satisfying himself that the facilities
referred to in sub-rule (1) are provided, and that termination of pregnancies
may be made under safe and hygienic conditions. 
 

 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every owner of the place which is inspected by the Chief Medical Officer of the
District shall afford all reasonable facilities for the inspection of the place. 
 

 </section><section><number>5</number>
The Chief Medical Officer of the District may, if he is satisfied after such
verification, enquiry or inspection, as may be considered necessary, that
termination of pregnancies may be done under safe and hygienic conditions, at
the place, recommend the approval of such place to the Committee. 
 

 </section><section><number>6</number>
The Committee may after considering the application and the recommendations of
the Chief Medical Officer of the District approve such place and issue a
certificate of approval in Form B. 
 

 </section><section><number>7</number>
The certificate of approval issued by the Committee shall be conspicuously
displaced at the place to be easily visible to persons visiting the place. 
 

 </section><section><number>8</number>
The place shall be inspected within 2 months of receiving the application and
certificate of approval may be issued within the next 2 months, or in case any
deficiency has been noted, within 2 months of the deficiency having been
rectified by the applicant. 
 

 </section><section><number>9</number>
On the commencement of these rules, a place approved in accordance with the
Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 1975 shall be deemed to have been
approved under these rules. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Inspection of a place.—
<section><number>1</number> A place approved under rule 5 may be inspected
by the Chief Medical Officer of the District, as often as may be necessary with
a view to verify whether termination of pregnancies is being done therein under
safe and hygienic conditions. 
 

 </section><section><number>2</number>
If the Chief Medical Officer has reason to believe that there has been death of,
or injury to, a pregnant woman at the place or that termination of pregnancies
is not being done at the place under safe and hygienic conditions, he may call
for any information or may seize any article, medicine, ampoule, admission
register or other document, maintained, kept or found at the place. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
The provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), relating to
seizure, so far as it may, apply to seizure made under sub-rule (2). 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Cancellation or suspension of certificate of approval.—
<section><number>1</number> If, after
inspection of any place approved under rule 5, the Chief Medical Officer of the
District is satisfied that the facilities specified in rule 5 are not being
properly maintained therein and the termination of pregnancy at such place
cannot be made under safe and hygienic conditions, he shall make a report of the
fact to the Committee giving the detail of the deficiencies or defects found at
the place and the committee may, if it is satisfied, suspend or cancel the
approval provided that the committee
shall give an opportunity of making representation to the owner of the place
before the certificate issued under rule 5 is cancelled. 
 

 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where a certificate issued under rule 5 is cancelled, the owner of the place may
make such additions or improvements in the place and thereafter, he may make an
application to the Committee for grant of approval under rule 5. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
In the event of suspension of a certificate of approval, the place shall not be
deemed to be an approved place during the suspension for the purposes of
termination of pregnancy from the date of communication of the order of such
suspension. 
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Review.—
<section><number>1</number> The owner of a place, who is aggrieved by an order made under
rule 7, may make .an application for review of the order to the Government
within a period of sixty days from the date of such order:
 Provided
that the Government may condone any delay in case it is satisfied that applicant
was prevented by sufficient cause to make application within time.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Government may, after giving the owner an opportunity of being heard,
confirm, modify or reverse the order.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Form of consent.—The consent referred to in sub-section (4) of section 3
shall be given in Form C.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Repeal and saving.—The Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 1975, are
hereby repealed except as respects things done or omitted to be done before such
repeal.
 


 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


the
Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 2003
 

 
 

 
 

 
 


FORM A
 


(See sub-rule (2) 
    of rule 5)
 



Form of application 
    for the approval of a place under  

    clause (b) of section 4
 

 
 


Category of approved 
    place:
 


A    Pregnancy can be 
    terminated upto 12 weeks
 


B    Pregnancy can be 
    terminated upto 20 weeks
 


1. Name of the place (in 
    capital letters)
 


2. Address in full
 


3. 
    Non-Governmental/Private/Nursing Home/Other Institutions
 


4. State, if the 
    following facilities are available at the place
 


Category A
 


(i)   Gynaecological 
    examination/labour table.
 


(ii)   Resuscitation 
    equipment.
 


(iii)  Sterilization 
    equipment.
 


(iv)  Facilities for 
    treatment of shock, including emergency drugs.
 


(v)   Facilities for 
    transportation, if required.
 


Category B
 


(ii)   An operation table 
    and instruments for performing abdominal or gynaecological surgery.
 


(iii)  Drugs and parental 
    fluid in sufficient supply for emergency cases.
 


(iv)  Anaesthetic 
    equipment, resuscitation equipment and sterilization equipment. 

 

 
 


Signature of the owner of 
    the place
 



    Place.................                                                                     
    
 


Date..................
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


the
Medical Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 2003
 

 
 

 
 



Form B
 


(See sub-rule (6) 
    of rule 5)
 



Certificate of 
    approval
 

 
 


The place described below 
    is hereby approved for the purpose of the Medical Termination of Pregnancy 
    Act, 1971 (34 of 1971).
 


AS READ WITHIN UPTO........................WEEKS
 


Name of the Place
 


Address and other 
    descriptions
 


Name of the owner
 



    Place.........................
 



    Date.........................
 

 
 


          To the 
    Government of 
    the....................................................................................................
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 
 

 
 
 

the Medical 
      Termination of Pregnancy Rules, 2003
 

 
 

 
 

FORM C
 

(See 
      rule 9)
 

 
 

I................................................... 
      daughter/wife of ........................... aged about 
      .................  
      years.............................................................................................................................................
 

(here state 
      the permanent address)
 

at present residing 
      at.................................................................................................................................
 

do hereby give my consent to 
      termination of my pregnancy 
      at.......................................................
 

.......................................................................................................................................................................
 

(State the 
      name of place where the pregnancy is to be terminated)
 

Place.........................                                                                                      
               
      Signature
 

Date.........................
 

 
 

(To be 
      filled in by guardian where the woman is a mentally ill person or 
      minor)
 

I..................................... 
      son/daughter/wife of ............................... aged about 
      ................................... years of 
      ...................................... 
      at present residing at (permanent address) 
      .............................................................. do hereby 
      give my consent to the termination of the pregnancy of my ward 
      .................................... who is a minor/lunatic 
      at...............................................................................................................................
 

(place of 
      termination of my pregnancy)
 

 
 

Place..........................                                                                                     
               
      Signature
 

Date..........................
 

 
 

 
 
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>