<act><title>THE
EMIGRATION RULES, 19831


</title> 

   


   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Emigration Rules, 1983.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
They shall come into force on the date2 of their publication in the Official
Gazette. 


   









</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Emigration Act, 1983 (31 
    of 1983);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Certificate” means a certificate issued 
    under Section 11 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Competent Authority’ means competent 
    authority notified by Central Government under Section 15 of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “demand” means the category wise, skill 
    wise number of workers required by the employer for being employed in his 
    establishment. This includes description of job-specifications and salary 
    offered;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “emigration number” means the number 
    assigned by the Protector of Emigrants to an emigrant at the time of 
    granting emigration clearance;  
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “Form” means a Form annexed to these 
    rules;  
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “permit” means a permit issued under 
    Chapter IV of the Act;  
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “remittable component” means a part of 
    the wages which the emigrant is entitled to remit to India;  
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “unauthorised emigrant” means any person 
    who has emigrated or intends to emigrate out of India for employment in 
    violation of the provision of the Act and the rules.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Dependent of an emigrant.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
    person who claims to be the dependent of an emigrant shall be required to 
    produce in support of his claim a certificate to this effect from the 
    District Magistrate or a revenue authority not below the rank of Tehsildar 
    of the place where the emigrant ordinarily resides or domiciles.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Determination of the purpose of visit of dependent shall be carried out with 
    reference to the nature of the visa, sponsorship certificate and such other 
    travel documents as may be considered necessary.   
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Emigrants conveyance.—Any 
    conveyance, especially chartered, for conveyance of emigrant or employed 
    generally for conveying emigrants exceeding two in number shall be deemed to 
    be emigrant conveyance.  
 
  


</article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<title><number>5</number> Recruiting agent representing the 
employer. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> An employer may authorise a recruiting agent in India, 
registered under the provisions of the Act, by a power of attorney executed in 
favour of the recruiting agent authorising that recruiting agent for the 
purposes of the recruitment of person on his behalf. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The power of attorney referred to under sub-rule (1) shall be valid for 
the period of the employment contract of the recruited worker even if the 
certificate of registration of such recruiting agent ceases to be valid before 
that period.] 









</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Inspection of an emigrant’s conveyance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Protector of Emigrants has reason to believe that a conveyance is an 
    emigrant’s conveyance he may inspect such conveyance with a view to 
    detecting the presence of unauthorised emigrants in the conveyance or for 
    obtaining such evidence as may be necessary for protecting the interests of 
    emigrants and he may, with such assistance, as he may think fit,—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   enter such conveyance at any time;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   require the production of registration 
    certificate of the conveyance, log book and list of passengers; and   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   take such other evidence and examine 
    any person as he may deem necessary.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Person 
    having the general management or control of the conveyance shall provide 
    such means as may be required by the Protector of Emigrants for inspection 
    under sub-rule (1).  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<title><number>7</number> Application for registration as recruiting 
agent. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any person intending to engage in India in the business of 
recruitment for an employer may make an application for registration under 
section 11 of the Act to the registering authority in Form I. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied with a 
fee of twenty-five thousand rupees payable by a bank draft issued in favour of 
the pay and Accounts, Officer, Ministry of Overseas India, Affaris, New Delhi 
and shall contain the following particulars and documents, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a copy of the applicant's bachelor's degree or two years diploma or 
  equivalent from a recognised university or institute 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> a copy of the balance sheet of the previous financial years or a 
  statement of account showing the assets and liabilities of the applicant, duly 
  verified by a chartered accountant having a certificate of practice under the 
  Chartered Accountant Act 1949 (38 -of 1949), showing the financial soundness 
  of the applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> a copy of the income tax returns for the last three consecutive 
  years; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> an affidavit in Form-II, executed by the applicant before a Magistrate 
  or Notary Public.] </subsection>












</section></article> 

  
 <article><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<title><number>8</number> Amount of security. </title>—The 
applicant, on being informed by the registering authority under sub-section (2) 
of section 11 of the Act, shall provide a bank guarantee of thirteen years' 
validity for an amount of twenty lakh rupees as security under sub-section (3) 
of that section.] 
  










 
 <section><number>i</number> up to 300 workers Rs. 3 lakh 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> 301 to 1000 workers Rs. 5 lakhs 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> 1001 and above Rs. 10 lakhs </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Validity of certificate. </title>—A certificate shall be valid 
<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[initially for a period of ten years and shall be renewed for a 
period of ten years]: 
 Provided that a certificate may be issued for a shorter period— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> if the person to whom it is issued so desires; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> if the registering authority, for reasons to be communicated in writing 
  to the applicant for the certificate, considers in any case that the 
  certificate, should be issued for a shorter period. </section>
  








</article> 

  
 [<title>9A Renewal of certificate. </title>—An application for 
renewal of certificate under section 13 may be made to the registering authority 
in Form IIA and shall be accompanied with a fee of twenty-five thousand rupees 
payable by a bank draft issued in favour of the Pay and Accounts Officer, 
Ministry of Overseas Indian Affairs, New Delhi.] 









 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> Terms and conditions of the certificate. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The 
registration certificate shall be subject to the following terms and conditions— 

 
 <subsection><number>i</number> This certificate shall be valid for a period specified in the 
  certificate: 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the certificate shall not be transferable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> the holder of the certificate shall conduct the business under his 
  own hand and seal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> a photocopy of registration certificate shall be displayed prominently 
  at a conspicuously place of business; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> the certificate shall be made available for inspection to the 
  emigration authorities, law enforcement authorities and employers; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> the certificate shall be produced on demand for satisfaction of the 
  bona fides of the recruiting agent, when such demand is made by an 
  emigrant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> the holder of the certificate shall conduct the business from the 
  place indicated in certificate. For opening a recruitment centre at a place 
  other than the place indicated in the certificate, the holder of the 
  certificate shall obtain the prior permission of the registering authority 
  <footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[or an officer specially authorised by the registering authority]; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> the holder of the certificate shall not employ sub-agents for the 
  purpose of conducting or carrying on his business, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ix</number> the holder of the certificate shall maintain the following records at 
  his place of business and shall make them available for inspection on demand 
  by Protector General of Emigrants or the Protector of Emigrants,— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>a</number> a register of receipt of charges from emigrants recruited, in the 
    form of an original acquittance roll containing the signature of each 
    emigrant from whom the charge has been received. Each such register shall be 
    with reference to a demand for recruitment. The register shall be maintained 
    as permanent records; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> a register and records of the amount and Pre-paid Ticket Advices 
    along with their photo copies received from the employers, identified demand 
    wise; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> a register containing details of expenses incurred on the recruitment 
    of emigrants demand wise supported by the documents; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> individual folders for each employer whose demands of labour, the 
    holder of the certificate has processed, proposes to process or is 
    processing; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>e</number> bio-data of each emigrant recruited by the holder of the certificate; 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>f</number> copies of employment contracts of each emigrant as authenticated by 
    the Protector of Emigrants; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>g</number> original demand letter, power of attorney and correspondence with the 
    employers; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>h</number> all documents relating to the recruitment of emigrants, including 
    office copies of all advertisements issued, letters of interview and 
    correspondence with the applicants, original award sheets leading to the 
    selection, names and addresses of persons involved in the selection process, 
    copies of letters of appointments, trade-testing particulars; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>i</number> a register of visas received from the employers, giving separate 
    account of block and individual visas; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>j</number> a register of claims for all compensation, (including for injury or 
    death) made by the emigrants or their dependents, recruited by the holder of 
    the certificate giving the name, address of the emigrant, emigration number, 
    country of employment, nature of compensation (including the details in 
    regard to the circumstances leading to the claim), address of the recipients 
    and the name and address of the employer, and the receipt in original in 
    token of having made the payment of compensation; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>k</number> such other records as may be required to be maintained by the 
    registering authority. 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>x</number> <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[the holder of certificate shall file a return every 
    month in Form IV to the Protector General of Emigrants or the Protector of 
    Emigrants specified by the Protector General in this behalf, by the 10th of 
    the succeeding month]; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>xi</number> Copy of each advertisement for recruitment of the emigrants shall be 
    endorsed to the Protector of Emigrants; 
 <subsubsection><number>xii</number> the holder of the certificate shall ensure that the employer 
    observes the terms and conditions of the contracts; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xiii</number> the holder of the certificate shall not charge any amount from the 
    emigrant towards the repatriation expenses. 
 <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[xiv) the holder of the certificate shall— 
 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>a</number> provide details of employment, including contract conditions, to 
      the intending emigrants before recruitment; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> endeavor to ensure proper reception of the emigrant by the employer 
      in the country of employment; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> endeavor to ensure that subsequent to the employment, the employer 
      shall not alter the terms of the employment contract; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> endeavor to ensure that the employer takes timely action for 
      renewal of documents authorising the stay of the emigrant in the country 
      of employment, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>e</number> facilitate amicable settlement of disputes between the employer and 
      the emigrant; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>f</number> issue receipt for the payments received from the emigrant; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>g</number> issue only such advertisements that are genuine and factually 
      correct and shall refrain from any inducement or misrepresentation in this 
      regard; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>h</number> file copies of all advertisements to the Protector General of 
      Emigrants immediately after their publication or release. </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>xv</number> The holder of the certificate shall maintain— 
 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>a</number> office premises of not less than fifty square meters of built up 
      area, having a waiting hall with the capacity of sitting for at least 
      thirty persons, a room for the purpose of conducting interview and an 
      office space equipped with furniture, photocopier, telephone with 
      Subscriber Trunk Dialing and International Subscriber Dialing facility, 
      fax, computer and other office amenities as may be specified by the 
      registering authority by order in writing; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number> work stations for the office personnel; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> internet facility, email accounts and a web portal containing 
      detailed information about the recruiting agent, the validity status of 
      the registration certificate, the services offered, the cost of services, 
      the mode of payment of service charges, the remedies available to 
      emigrants for redressal of grievances, vacancies available along with the 
      details of the jobs, the employers and the contract conditions and the 
      recruitments made in the past with such particular as the registering 
      authority may require by order in writing 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>d</number> adequate and duly trained staff 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>e</number> a signboard, to be displayed in front of the business premises or 
      so fixed that it is conspicuously visible to the public from outside the 
      office premises indicating the name and the registration number of the 
      recruiting agent, they years of registration and date of its expiry. 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>f</number> arrangements for skill testing for the trades for which he recruits 
      the intending emigrants.] </subsubsection></subsection>










</section><section><number>2</number> The Certificate shall be in Form V. </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Permits 
    for recruitment by employers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Application for permits. The application for issue of the permits for 
    recruitment by foreign employers shall be in Form VI.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    application for issue of permits for recruitment by Indian employers for 
    foreign jobs shall be in Form VII.  
 


    1[(3) The applications 
    under rules (1) and (2) above shall be accompanied by bank draft of rupees 
    two thousand payable in favour of the Pay and Accounts Officer, Ministry of 
    Labour (Main Secretariat), New Delhi, towards the application fee.]  
 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Conditions of permit. </title>—The permit shall be subject to 
the following conditions, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> The permit is not transferable. 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> The permit is valid for a period of <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[one year] from the 
  date of issue or the date of completion of the recruitment whichever is 
  earlier. 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> Workers recruited on the strength of this permit shall not be 
  repatriated on the ground that they do not possess the required skill. 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> The holder of the permit shall not obtain the assistance of recruiting 
  agent in any manner. 
 </section><section><number>v</number> The employment agreement with the worker shall be signed by the holder 
  of the permit. 
 </section><section><number>vi</number> The holder of the permit shall be under obligation to treat the 
  contract entered into with the worker as enforceable under the Labour Laws of 
  the country of employment. It shall be his responsibility to file the copies 
  of the contracts with the concerned authorities in the country of employment. 
  
 </section><section><number>vii</number> The holder of the permit shall not supply manpower recruited on the 
  strength of this permit to any other agency or concern. 
 </section><section><number>viii</number> The holder of the permit shall be responsible for the general 
  welfare and redressal of specific grievances of the workers recruited on the 
  strength of the permit during the period of contract. 
 </section><section><number>ix</number> The holder of the permit shall not extend the services of a worker 
  after the expiry of a contract without entering into a fresh contract or 
  without extending the existing contract. 
 </section><section><number>x</number> The holder of the permit shall notify to the Indian Mission in the 
  country of employment each case of death or disability of a worker within 48 
  hours of the occurrence of the event. Similarly information should be 
  communicated to the next of kin in India in case of disability/death within 48 
  hours. 
 </section><section><number>xi</number> The holder of the permit is prohibited from supplying manpower for a 
  work in another country to a country other than the country from which the 
  permit has been issued. 
 <subsection><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>xii</number> The holder of the Permit shall 
 
 </subsection><subsection><number>a</number> provide details of employment, including contract conditions, to the 
    intending emigrants before recruitment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> ensure proper reception of the emigrant in the country of employment 
    
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> ensure that subsequent to the employment, the employer shall not 
    alter the contract of employment 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> ensures timely action for renewal of documents authorising stay of 
    emigrant in the country of employment 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> not deprive the emigrant of the custody of his travel and employment 
    documents (f) ensure advertisement for the genuineness of employer's in 
    respect of recruitment before it is released and shall refrain any 
    inducement or misrepresentation in this regard; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> file copies of all advertisements for recruitment to the Protector 
    General of Emigrants immediately after their publication or release.] 
  </subsection></section>









</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Issue of permit. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of the application, the 
competent authority may verify the facts contained in the application and may 
make the following enquiries to ascertain that the terms and conditions of 
employment are not discriminatory or exploitative:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the basis on which the demand has been computed; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the principle on which skills have been classified; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> job contents of a post required to be filled; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> scope of future prospects in various categories of jobs; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> structure of supervisory control; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> grievances procedure followed; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> general reputation of the applicant and reports of specific misconduct, 
  if any. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> A permit issued under section 17 of the Act shall be in Form VIII and 
shall be valid for a period of <footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[one year] from the date of its issue 
or till the recruitment of the persons for whose recruitment such permit is 
issued is completed, whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>2A</number> The permit shall be issued only after applicant furnishes a 
bank guarantee of ten thousand rupees for every person intended to be recruited 
subject to a minimum of one lakh rupees and a maximum of twenty lakh rupees, 
valid for a period of one year over and above the duration of the employment 
contract.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> In case the employer is not able to complete the recruitment within 
<footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[one year], then he may make an application under section 18 of the 
Act for an extension of the period of validity of the permit, stating the 
reasons therein for not completing the recruitment within the prescribed period. 
The prescribed authority may extend the validity of the permit by such further 
period as it may think fit but not exceeding three months at a time. 










</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> 
      
<section><number>1</number> A foreign employer who has been granted a permit under sub-section (2) 
      of section 15 of the Act shall on arrival in India submit to the Protector 
      General of Emigrants a certified copy of the permit and thereafter may 
      proceed to make recruitments.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where the permit under sub-section (2) of 
      section 15 has been issued for recruitment of persons not more than two in 
      number and where such recruitment is being made on the basis of postal 
      communication or personal contact, a copy of the permit certified by the 
      Indian Mission in the country of employment can be filed by such person 
      himself.  
 
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15</number> Application for emigration clearance. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
application made under sub-section (2) of section 22 of the Act shall be made in 
Form IX by the applicant directly or through the recruiting agent if any or 
through the employer <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[including Indian employers permitted under 
rule 11(2)] concerned and shall be accompanied by,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> a true copy of the demand verified and authenticated by the Indian 
  Mission in the country of employment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> a true copy of the power of attorney given by the employer to the 
  recruiting agent verified and authenticated by the Indian Mission in the 
  country of employment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> a true copy of the agreement under sub-section (3) of section 22 of the 
  Act verified and authenticated by the Indian Mission in the country of 
  employment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> a statement setting out the particulars of matters prescribed under 
  sub-rule (2) not provided in the agreement; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> a statement of additional conditions, if any; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> a statement as to the provision by way of security for meeting the 
  expenses which may be incurred in case it becomes necessary to arrange for the 
  repatriation to India of the applicant. This statement shall be verified and 
  authenticated by the Recruiting Agent in case the applicant is recruited by 
  him; and 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[<number>g</number> a demand draft of <footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[rupees two hundred], drawn 
  in favour of the Protector General of Emigrants as fee for emigration 
  clearance.] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<number>h</number> an insurance policy providing insurance cover for the 
  intending emigrant for the period of employment contract.] </subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> An agreement under sub-section (3) of Section 22 shall 
provide for the following matters:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> period of employment/place of employment; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> wages and other conditions of service; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> free food or food allowance provision; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> free accommodation; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> provision in regard to disposal, or transportation to India , of dead 
  body of the emigrant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> working hours, overtime allowance, other working conditions, leave and 
  social security benefits as per local labour laws; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> to-and-fro air-passage at the employers' cost; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>viii</number> mode of settlement of disputes]; </subsection>













</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>15A</number> </title><footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[***]


 
 <title>“15A. </title> All applications from the persons, individually or through recruiting agents or through other permitted agents, who intend to go abroad on short term non-employment visit and requiring suspension of emigration check requirements for a limited period (emigration suspension) shall be accompanied by a demand draft of rupees one hundred drawn in favour of the Protector General of Emigrants as fee in respect of each applicant.”. 


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number> Emigration clearance under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 22 of the Act 
      shall be given 1[by making] an entry incorporating 
      grant of emigration clearance to an emigrant for the country of employment 
      for the period of contract and the attestation number of the Mission on 
      the demand should be made in the passport of the emigrant by the Protector 
      of Emigrants.  
  




 
</section></article> 

  
 [***]
  










 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> Form of appeal. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every appeal presented to the 
Central Government under Section 23 of the Act shall be in the form of a 
memorandum signed by the appellant. The memorandum shall be sent in triplicate 
and accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against and a demand draft of 
<footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[two thousand rupees] drawn in favour of the Union of India towards 
the fee for the appeal. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The memorandum— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> shall set forth concisely the grounds of objection to the order 
  appealed against and such ground shall be numbered consecutively; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> shall specify— 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> the address at which notices or other processes may be served on the 
    appellant; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the date on which the order appealed against was served on the 
    appellant. </subsubsection></subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Where the memorandum is presented after the expiry of the period of 
thirty days referred to in sub-section (2) of section 23, it shall be 
accompanied by a petition, in triplicate, duly verified and supported by the 
documents, if any, relied upon by the appellant, showing cause how the appellant 
had been prevented from preferring the appeal within the said period of thirty 
days. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any notice required to be served on the appellant shall be served on him 
in the manner prescribed in Rule 18, at the address for service specified in the 
memorandum. 








</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Procedure before the appellate authority.— 
    
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an appeal under Rule 18, the Appellate Authority shall 
    send a copy of the memorandum of appeal to the registering authority or the 
    competent authority or the Protector of Emigrants or the prescribed 
    authority against whose order the appeal has been presented.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Appellate Authority shall then issue notices to the appellant and the 
    registering authority or the competent authority or the Protector of 
    Emigrants or the prescribed authority, as the case may be, fixing a date for 
    hearing of the appeal.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the 
    date fixed for the hearing of the appeal, or any other day to which the 
    hearing of the appeal may be adjourned, the appellant as well as the 
    representative of the registering authority or the competent authority or 
    the Protector of Emigrants or the prescribed authority, as the case may be, 
    shall be heard.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where on 
    the date fixed, or any other day to which the hearing of the appeal may be 
    adjourned, the appellant fails to appear when the appeal is called on for 
    hearing, the Appellate Authority may decide the appeal on the basis of the 
    records of the case.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Contents of the order in appeal.—The 
    order of Appellate Authority shall be in writing and shall state briefly the 
    grounds for the decision and shall also be signed by the Appellate 
    Authority.  
 
  


</article> 

   


   


 <article><footcitenum>23</footcitenum>[<number>21</number>
Representation of party.—Any
person who has filed an appeal under section 23 of the Act, may appear himself
or appoint a pleader, advocate or any of the following to appear, plead and act
on his behalf before the Appellate Authority:
 


 <section>
<number>i</number> a partner, in case of a partnership firm; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> a Director, in case of a Limited Company registered under
Companies Act; 
 
 


 </section><section>
<number>iii</number> a practising advocate having vakalatnama executed by the owner,
partner or Managing Director, as the case may be; 
 
 


 </section><section>     
<number>iv</number>
a regular employee of the Limited Company or Firm who has been in direct
employment of the Company or Firm for at least a period of one year.]
   







</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Procedure for deciding emigrant status.—Where 
    a question arises before a Protector of Emigrants as to whether a person 
    intending to depart from India is or is not an emigrant shall be decided by 
    the Protector of Emigrants after holding an enquiry in the following 
    manner:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   he may require the presence of the 
    concerned person on an appointed day and time;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   he may also require the concerned person 
    to produce evidence relating to—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the present occupation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   his financial status and income;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   certificate of sponsorship from the 
    foreign country;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the source of financing of the journey;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   the source of receipt of foreign 
    exchange; and thereafter he shall pass speaking order and copy of the same 
    shall be provided to the person concerned and an endorsement to this effect 
    shall be made in the passport.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Forfeiture of security deposit.—Where 
    the competent authority or the registering authority has reason to believe 
    that it is expedient to forfeit the whole or any part of security furnished 
    by any person for being utilised for such purpose and in such manner as may 
    be specified in the order, he may, after giving a notice to this effect to 
    such person and thereafter giving him an opportunity to represent his case, 
    by order in writing, forfeit the whole or any part of the security.  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Authorities and officers to have certain power of civil courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Protector General of Emigrants, the registering authority, the competent 
    authority and every Protector of Emigrants shall, for the purpose of 
    discharging their functions under this Act, have the same powers as are 
    vested in a court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 while trying a 
    suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   summoning and enforcing the attendance 
    of witnesses;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   requiring any public record or copy 
    thereof, from any court or office;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   requisitioning any public record or copy 
    thereof from any court or office;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   receiving evidence on affidavits; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   issuing commissions for the examination 
    of witnesses or documents.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    proceeding before the Protector General of Emigrants, or the registering 
    authority or the competent authority or a Protector of Emigrants shall be a 
    judicial proceeding within the meaning of Sections 193 and 228 of the Indian 
    Penal Code and the Protector General of Emigrants, the registering 
    authority, the competent authority, and every Protector of Emigrants shall 
    be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of Section 195 and Chapter 
    XXVI of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973.  
 
  


</section></article> 

  
 [<title>25 Service Charges. </title>—No recruiting agent shall 
collect from the worker the charges more than the equivalent of his wages for 
forty five days as offered under the employment contract, subject to a maximum 
of twenty thousand rupees, in respect of services provided by it to that worker 
and the recruiting agent shall issue a receipt to that worker for the amount 
collected by it in this regard.] 








 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Service 
    of notice and orders.—A notice or 
    an order issued under these rules shall be served on any person in the 
    following manner, that is to say—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   by delivering or tendering the notice or 
    order to that person or his duly authorised agent; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   by sending a notice or order to him by 
    Registered Post with acknowledgment due to the address of his place or 
    residence or his last known place of residence or the place where he carries 
    out or last carried out business or personally works or last worked for 
    gain; or  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   if the notice or order cannot be served 
    under clause (a) or clause (b), by affixing it on the outer door or some 
    other conspicuous part of the premises in which that person resides or is 
    known to have last resided, or carries out or last carried out business or 
    personally works or last worked for gain and that written report thereof 
    should be witnessed by two persons.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>


    1[<number>26A</number> Withdrawal 
    of the Certificate of Registration of Recruiting Agent during Suspension.—Where 
    an order suspending the operation of the registration certificate of the 
    recruiting agent has been issued by registering authority, under sub-section 
    (2) of Section 14 of the Act, the certificate of that recruiting agent may 
    be withdrawn by the registering authority, for the period for which the 
    suspension of certificate has been ordered and for the periods of further 
    extensions of suspension of such certificate, if any.]  
 
 





 



</article><form>
 

THE EMIGRATION RULES, 19831
 

 
 

2[***]
 

-------
 

1  Vide S.O. 941(E), dated 30th December, 1983, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 30th 
December, 1983 and subsequently amended by: 
 

S.O. 665(E), dated 10th September, 1986 , G.S.R. 713(E), dated 
18th October, 2002 , 
 

G.S.R. 111(E), dated 24th February, 1987 , G.S.R. 143(E), dated 
26th February, 2004 , 
 

G.S.R. 375(E), dated 23rd March, 1989 , G.S.R. 773(E), dated 
25th November, 2004 , 
 

S.O. 111(E), dated 8th February, 1996 , G.S.R. 50(E), dated 6th 
February, 2006 , 
 

S.O. 159(E), dated 28th February, 1996 , S.O. 776(E), dated 
18th May, 2007 , 
 

S.O. 526(E), dated 22nd July, 1996, G.S.R. 658(E), dated 15th 
October, 2007. 
 

2. Form X omitted by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 
(w.e.f. 9-7-2009).</form><form>
 

THE EMIGRATION RULES, 19831
 

 
 

FORM VI 
 

FORM OF APPLICATION FOR A PERMIT FOR RECRUITMENT  
BY 
A FOREIGN EMPLOYER 
 

[ See rule 11(1)] 
 

1. Name of the employer. 
 

2. Status (Company/a partnership firm/sole proprietor). 
 

(in case of a company copy of the registration certificate and memorandum of 
articles and in case of a firm copy of the registration certificate and 
partnership deed shall be annexed to this application). 
 

3. Have the applicant obtained the permission of his Government to employ 
foreign workers? (attach photocopy of the permission). 
 

4. Has the applicant arranged to obtain employment visa for the proposed 
number of workers? Whether on block/individual basis ? 
 

5. How does the applicant propose to carry out the recruitment: 
 

6. What is present requirement ? (Attach detailed demand containing 
information about category of workers required, wages offered and a copy of 
specimen of the employment contract). 
 

7. Has the applicant earlier employed any Indian workers in his establishment 
? If so, give the total number. 
 

8. Are there any pending complaints from the Indian workers; if so details 
thereof. 
 

UNDERTAKING 
 

I undertake that in the event of the foregoing information being found to be 
incorrect or false in any respect, the permit shall be liable to be cancelled. 

 

Applicant 
 

Seal (Chamber of Commerce) 
 

Seal (Foreign Affairs) 
 

Seal (Indian Embassy) 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide S.O. 941(E), dated 30th December, 1983, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 30th 
December, 1983 and subsequently amended by: 
 

S.O. 665(E), dated 10th September, 1986 , G.S.R. 713(E), dated 
18th October, 2002 , 
 

G.S.R. 111(E), dated 24th February, 1987 , G.S.R. 143(E), dated 
26th February, 2004 , 
 

G.S.R. 375(E), dated 23rd March, 1989 , G.S.R. 773(E), dated 
25th November, 2004 , 
 

S.O. 111(E), dated 8th February, 1996 , G.S.R. 50(E), dated 6th 
February, 2006 , 
 

S.O. 159(E), dated 28th February, 1996 , S.O. 776(E), dated 18th 
May, 2007 , 
 

S.O. 526(E), dated 22nd July, 1996 , G.S.R. 658(E), dated 15th 
October, 2007 . </form><form>
 

THE EMIGRATION RULES, 19831
 

 
 

FORM VII 
 

FORM OF APPLICATION FOR A PERMIT FOR RECRUITMENT 

 

BY AN INDIAN PROJECT EXPORTER 
 

[ See rule 11(2)] 
 

1.  Name of the employer. 
 

2. Status (Company/a partnership firm/sole proprietor). 
 

(in case of a company copy of the registration certificate and memorandum of 
articles and in case of a firm copy of the registration certificate and 
partnership deed shall be annexed to this application). 
 

3. Has the applicant arranged to obtain employment visa for proposed number 
of workers? Whether on block/individual basis ? 
 

4. How does the applicant propose to carry out recruitment ? 
 

5. What is present requirement ? (attach detailed demand containing 
information about category of workers required, wages offered and a copy of the 
specimen of the employment contract). 
 

6. Name of the country for which workers are required. 
 

7. Name of the project undertaken in the foreign country and whether prime or 
sub-contract basis and details thereof. 
 

8. Total value and nature of contract (attach a copy of the contract with the 
foreign principal). 
 

9. Has the applicant obtained Reserve Bank of India/Screening Committee 
clearance ? (Photo copy to be attached). 
 

10. What will be the arrangement for payment of wages and remittances of 
 
wages ? 
 

11. If prime contractor, is the applicant employing a sub-contractor ? If so, 
give deatils. 
 

12. Does the applicant undertake to bear the liabilities of the 
sub-contractor towards workers in the event of the failure of the sub-contractor 
to discharge his liabilities ? 
 

13. What arrangements the applicant shall make for accommodating the workers 
in the foreign country ? 
 

14. Total number of Indian workers already employed by the applicant abroad. 
Date up to which their wages have been paid and date upto which arrangements for 
remittance of remittable components have been made. 
 

15. Is there any pending complaints from workers ? 
 

16. If so, give details and action being taken to settle the same. 
 

UNDERTAKING 
 

I undertake that in the event of the aforesaid information being found to be 
false or incorrect in any respect, the permit shall be liable to be cancelled. 

 

Applicant 
 

--------- 
 

1. Vide S.O. 941(E), dated 30th December, 1983, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 30th 
December, 1983 and subsequently amended by: 
 

S.O. 665(E), dated 10th September, 1986 , G.S.R. 713(E), dated 
18th October, 2002 , 
 

G.S.R. 111(E), dated 24th February, 1987 , G.S.R. 143(E), dated 
26th February, 2004 , 
 

G.S.R. 375(E), dated 23rd March, 1989 , G.S.R. 773(E), dated 
25th November, 2004 , 
 

S.O. 111(E), dated 8th February, 1996 , G.S.R. 50(E), dated 6th 
February, 2006 , 
 

S.O. 159(E), dated 28th February, 1996 , S.O. 776(E), dated 18th 
May, 2007 , 
 

S.O. 526(E), dated 22nd July, 1996 , G.S.R. 658(E), dated 15th 
October, 2007 . </form><form>
 

THE EMIGRATION RULES, 19831
 

FORM VIII 
 

FORM OF PERMIT GRANTED UNDER CHAPTER IV 
 

[ See rule 13 (2)] 
 

With reference to his application dated....................for grant of a 
permit under Chpater IV of the Act to recruit and employ..................number 
of persons M/s................... is hereby granted this permit effective from 
the date of issue of this permit subject to the following conditions:— 
 
 

(i) The permit is not transferable. 
 

(ii) The permit is valid for a period of 2[one year] from the 
  date of issue of the date of completion of the recruitment, whichever is 
  earlier. 
 

(iii) Workers recruited on the strength of this permit shall not be 
  repatriated on the ground that they do not possess the required skill. 
 

(iv) The holder of the permit shall not obtain the assistance of recruiting 
  agent in any manner. 
 

(v) The employment agreement with the worker shall be signed by the holder 
  of the permit. 
 

(vi) The holder of the permit shall be under obligation to treat the 
  contract entered into with the worker as enforceable under the labour laws of 
  the country of employment. It shall be his responsibility to file the copies 
  of the contracts with the concerned authorities in the country of employment. 
  
 

(vii) The holder of the permit shall not supply manpower recruited on the 
  strength of this permit to any other agency or concern. 
 

(viii) The holder of the permit shall be responsible for the general 
  welfare and redressal of specific grievances of the workers recruited on the 
  strength of the permit during the period of contract. 
 

(ix) The holder of the permit shall not extend the services of a worker 
  after the expiry of a contract without entering into a fresh contract or 
  without extending the existing contract. 
 

(x) The holder of the permit shall notify to the Indian Mission in the 
  country of employment each case of death or disability of a worker within 48 
  hours of the occurrence of the event. Similarly information should be 
  communicated to the next of kin in India in case of disability/death within 48 
  hours. 
 

(xi) The holder of the permit is prohibited from supplying manpower for a 
  work in another country to a country other than the country from which the 
  permit has been issued. 
 

3[(xii) The holder of the Permit shall— 
 
 

(a) provide details or employment, including contract conditions, to the 
    intending emigrants before recruitment; 
 

(b) ensure proper reception of the emigrant in the country of employment; 
    
 

(c) ensure that subsequent to the employment, the employer shall not 
    alter the contract of employment; 
 

(d) ensures timely action for renewal of documents authorsing stay of 
    emigrant in the country of employment; 
 

(e) not deprive the emigrant of the custody of his travel and employment 
    documents; 
 

(f) issue only such advertisements that are genuine and factually correct 
    and shall refrain from any inducement or misrepresentation in this regard; 
    
 

(g) file copies of all advertisements for recruitment to the Protector 
    General of Emigrants immediately after their publication or release.] 
  
 

-------
 

1  Vide S.O. 941(E), dated 30th December, 1983, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 30th 
December, 1983 and subsequently amended by: 
 

S.O. 665(E), dated 10th September, 1986 , G.S.R. 713(E), dated 
18th October, 2002 , 
 

G.S.R. 111(E), dated 24th February, 1987 , G.S.R. 143(E), dated 
26th February, 2004 , 
 

G.S.R. 375(E), dated 23rd March, 1989 , G.S.R. 773(E), dated 
25th November, 2004 , 
 

S.O. 111(E), dated 8th February, 1996 , G.S.R. 50(E), dated 6th 
February, 2006 , 
 

S.O. 159(E), dated 28th February, 1996 , S.O. 776(E), dated 
18th May, 2007 , 
 

S.O. 526(E), dated 22nd July, 1996, G.S.R. 658(E), dated 15th 
October, 2007. 
 

2. Subs. by G.S.R. 773(E), dated 25th November, 2004 , for “six 
months” (w.e.f. 25-11-2004 ). 
 

3. Ins. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 (w.e.f. 9-7-2009 
). </form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE EMIGRATION RULES, 1983
 

 
 


FORM IX
 


APPLICATION FOR EMIGRATION CLEARANCE
 


[See rule 15(1)]
 

 
 


          1.   Agent’s Registration Number 
                 To be filled in by Agent
 


          2.   Permission number and date
 
 


          1.   Applicant’s name 
                                       To be filled in by the Applicant
 


          2.   Age
 


          3.   Had been abroad before; Yes/No  
 


          4.   Sex; Male/Female  
 


          5.   State of domicile  
 


          6.   Passport number, date and place 
    of issue  
 


          7.   Rural/Urban  
 


          8.   Number of dependents  
 


          9.   Been employed during the last 
    12 months. Yes/No  
 


        10.   If yes, with Government or 
    private establishment  
 


        11.   Earning in India 
    (rupees........per month)  
 


        12.   Belonging to SC/ST, if yes, 
    whether SC/ST  
 
 


          1.   Job for which to be employed  
 


          2.   Country of employment  
 


          3.   Salary abroad (including food 
    allowance)  
 


          4.   Contract period (months)  
 


          5.   Free food; Yes/No  
 


          6.   Employer’s name   
 


Applicant  
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 , for rule (5) 
(w.e.f. 9-7-2009 ). Sub-rule (5), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July 2009 , for rule (7) 
(w.e.f. 9-7-2009 ). Rule (7), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 , for rule (8) 
(w.e.f. 9-7-2009 ). Rule (8), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 , for the words 
”initially for a period of five years and shall be renewed for a further period 
of fine years” (w.e.f. 9-7-2009 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Subs. by 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 for rule 9A (w.e.f. 
9-7-2009 ). Rule 9A before substitution stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 375(E), dated 23rd March, 1989 (w.e.f. 
23-3-1989 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 375(E), dated 23rd March, 1989 .</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 (w.e.f. 9-7-2009 
).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 773(E), dated 25th November, 2004 , for “six 
months” (w.e.f. 25-11-2004 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 (w.e.f. 9-7-2009 
).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 111(E), dated 24th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 
24-2-1987 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 (w.e.f. 9-7-2009 
).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 773(E), dated 25th November, 2004 , for “six 
months” (w.e.f. 25-11-2004 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 713(E), dated 18th October, 2002 (w.e.f. 
1-11-2002 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> Subs. by S.O. 159(E), dated 28th February, 1996 (w.e.f. 
28-2-1996 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 713(E), dated 18th October, 2002 (w.e.f. 
1-11-2002 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 (w.e.f. 9-7-2009 
).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 111(E), dated 24th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 
24-2-1987 ).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> Rule 15A omitted by G.S.R. 658(E), dated 15th October, 2007 (w.e.f. 15-10-2007). Earlier Rule 15A was inserted by G.S.R. 713(E), dated 18th October, 2002 (w.e.f. 1-11-2002). Rule 15A, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number>   Subs. by G.S.R. 111 (E), 
      dated 24th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 24-2-1987).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Rule 17 Omitted by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 
(w.e.f. 9-7-2009 ). Rule 17, before omission, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 for rupees two 
hundred (w.e.f. 9-7-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number>
Subs. by S.O. 776(E), dated 18th May, 2007, for rule 21 (w.e.f.
3-6-2007). Rule 21, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 511(E), dated 9th July, 2009 for rule 25 
(w.e.f. 9-7-2009). Rule (25) before substitution stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number>   Ins. by G.S.R. 111 
    (E), dated 24th February, 1987 (w.e.f. 24-2-1987).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>