<act><tid>337865</tid>
<title>THE COMPANIES (PROFITS) SURTAX ACT, <year>1964</year></title>

ACT NO. 7 OF <year>1964</year>
[ 2nd May, <year>1964</year>.]

An Act to impose a special tax on the profits of certain 
companies.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifteenth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>144352</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1187251</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Companies (Profits) Surtax Act, <year>1964</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>470400</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>832969</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1025442</tid>
<number>1</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" Advance surtax" means the surtax payable under 
section 7A;]

</section>

<section><tid>418695</tid>
<number>1A</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>] assessee" means a person by whom surtax or any other 
sum of money is payable under this Act and includes every 
person in respect of whom any proceeding under this Act has 
been taken for the assessment of his chargeable profits or 
, of the amount of refund due to him or of the chargeable 
profits of any other person in respect of which he is 
assessable or of the amount of refund due to such other 
person;

</section>

<section><tid>796221</tid>
<number>2</number>assessment" includes re- assessment;

</section>

<section><tid>499651</tid>
<number>3</number>" assessment year" means the period of twelve months 
commencing on the 1st day of April, every year;

</section>

<section><tid>1569420</tid>
<number>4</number>" Board" means the Central Board of Direct Taxes 
constituted under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>; 
 (54 of <year>1963</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>1162487</tid>
<number>5</number>" chargeable profits" means the total income of an 
assessee computed under the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year> (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>) for any previous year or years, as the case may be, and 
adjusted in accordance with the provisions of the First 
Schedule;

</section>

<section><tid>475116</tid>
<number>6</number>Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>; (43 of  
  <year>1961</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>1883965</tid>
<number>7</number>prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>482481</tid>
<number>7A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>" regular assessment" means an assessment made under 
section 6;"]

</section>

<section><tid>454144</tid>
<number>8</number>statutory deduction" means an amount equal to 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> fifteen per cent.] of the capital of the company as 
computed in accordance with the provisions of the Second 
Schedule, or an amount of two hundred thousand rupees, which- 
ever is greater:
Provided that where the previous year is longer or shorter 
than a period of twelve months, the aforesaid amount of


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1272</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1976</year>, S. 29 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Re- numbered and ins. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, S. 35 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Re- lettered by s. 35, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1981</year>)




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> fifteen per cent.] or, as the case may be, of two hundred 
thousand rupees shall be increased or decreased propor- 
tionately:

Provided further that where a company has different previous 
years in respect of its income, profits and gains, the 
aforesaid increase or decrease, as the case may be, shall be 
calculated with reference to the length of the previous year 
of the longest duration; and


</section>

<section><tid>223319</tid>
<number>9</number>all other words and expressions used herein but not 
defined and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1631072</tid>
<number> 3</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>
<section><tid>358388</tid>
<number>1</number>Tax authorities. The income- tax authorities specified  
in section 116 of the come- tax Act shall be the authorities for the 
purpose of this the Act and every such authority shall exercise the 
power and perform the functions of a tax authority under this Act in 
respect of any company, and for this purpose his jurisdiction under 
this Act shall be the same as he has under the Income- Tax Act by 
virtue of orders or directions issued under section 120 of that Act 
 (Including orders or directions assigning concurrent jurisdiction) or 
under any other provision of that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1537708</tid>
<number>2</number>The Board may, from time to time, issue such 
orders, instructions and directions to other tax authorities as it may 
deem fit for the proper administration of this Act, and such 
authorities and all other persons employed in the execution of this 
Act shall observe and follow such orders, instructions and directions 
of the Board:
Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be 
issued-


<subsection><tid>1398221</tid>
<number>a</number>so as to require any tax authority to make a particular 
assessment or to dispose of a particular case in a particular 
manner; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1888039</tid>
<number>b</number>so as to interfere with the discretion of the Commis- 
sioner (Appeals) in the exercise of his appellate 
functions."]



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>895762</tid>
<number>4</number>Charge of tax. Subject to the provisions contained in this Act, 
there shall be charged on every company for every assessment year 
commencing on and from the first day of April, <year>1964</year>, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> but before the 
first day of April, <year>1988</year>"] a tax (in- this Act referred to as the  
  surtax) in respect of so much of its chargeable profits of the 
previous year or previous years, as the case may be, as exceed the 
statutory deduction, at the rate or rates specified in the Third 
Schedule.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>1273</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 19 of <year>1970</year>, s. 39.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 36, for" and Income- tax' Officer" 
 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1967</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 36 ibid, for" same as that he has" (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1967</year>).



</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 66 of <year>1976</year>, S. 29 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1977</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, S. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 10. 7. <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 23 of <year>1986</year>, S. 47 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1988</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1988</year>, S. 188 (w. e. f 1. 4. <year>1988</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1691220</tid>
<number> 5</number> Return of chargeable profit.
<section><tid>1887129</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of every  
company whose chargeable profits assessable under this Act exceeded 
during the previous year the amount of. statutory deduction, its 
principal officer, or where in the case of a non- resident company any 
person has been treated as its agent under section 163 of the Income- 
tax Act, such person, shall furnish a return of the chargeable profits 
of the company during the previous year in the prescribed form and 
verified in the prescribed manner and setting forth such other 
particulars as may be prescribed, before the 30th day of September of 
the assessment year:
Provided that on an application made in this behalf, the Income- 
tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for the furnishing 
of the return.


</section>

<section><tid>594361</tid>
<number>2</number>In the case of any company which in the Income- tax Officer' s 
opinion is assessable under this Act, the Income- tax Officer may, 
before the end of the relevant assessment year, serve a notice upon 
its principal officer, or where in the case of a non- resident company 
any person has been treated as its agent under section 163 of the 
Income- tax Act, upon such person, requiring him to furnish within 
thirty days from the date of service of the notice a return of the 
chargeable profits of the company during the previous year in the 
prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner and setting 
forth such other particulars as may be prescribed:
Provided that on an application made in this behalf, the Income- 
tax Officer may, in his discretion, extend the date for the furnishing 
of the return.


</section>

<section><tid>1046795</tid>
<number>3</number>Any assessee who has not furnished a return during the time 
allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), or having furnished 
a return under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) discovers any 
omission or wrong statement therein, may furnish a return or a revised 
return, as the case may be, at any time before the assessment is made.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1595033</tid>
<number> 6</number> Assessment.
<section><tid>1203403</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of making an assessment under  
this Act, the Income- tax Officer may serve on any, person who has 
furnished a return under sub- section (1) of section 5 or upon whom a 
notice has been served under' sub- section (2) of section 5 (whether a  
  return has been furnished or not) a notice requiring him on a date 
therein to be specified, to produce or cause to be produced such 
accounts or documents or evidence as the Income- tax officer may 
require for the purposes of this Act and may from time to time serve 
further notices requiring the production of such further accounts or 
documents or other evidence as he may require.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1274</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>459785</tid>
<number>2</number>The Income- tax Officer, after considering such accounts, 
documents or evidence, if any, as he has obtained under subsection (1) 
and after taking into account any relevant material which he has 
gathered, shall, by an order in writing, assess the chargeable profits 
and the amount of the surtax payable on the basis of such assessment.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>956748</tid>
<number> 7</number> Provisional assessment.
<section><tid>190303</tid>
<number>1</number>The Income- tax Officer, before  
proceeding to make an assessment under section 6 (in this section  
  referred to as the regular assessment) may, at any time after the 
expiry of the period allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) 
of section 5 for the furnishing of the return and whether the return 
has or has not been furnished, proceed to make in a summary manner a 
provisional assessment of the chargeable profits and the amount of the 
surtax payable thereon.

</section>

<section><tid>1069658</tid>
<number>2</number>Before making such provisional assessment, the Income- tax 
Officer shall give notice in the prescribed form to the person on whom 
the provisional assessment is to be made of his intension to do so, 
and shall with the notice forward a statement of the amount of the 
proposed assessment, and the said person shall be entitled to deliver 
to the Income- tax Officer at any time within fourteen days of the 
service of the said notice a statement of his objections, if any, to 
the amount of the proposed assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>334325</tid>
<number>3</number>On expiry of the said fourteen days from the date of service 
of the notice referred to in sub- section (2), or earlier, if the 
assessee agrees to the proposed provisional assessment, the Income- tax 
Officer may, after taking into account the objections, if any, made 
under sub- section (2), make a provisional assessment, and shall 
furnish a copy of the order of the assessment to the assessee:
Provided that assent to the amount of the provisional assessment, 
or failure to make objection to it, shall in no way prejudice the 
assessee in relation to the regular assessment.


</section>

<section><tid>700008</tid>
<number>4</number>There shall be no right of appeal against a provisional 
assessment made under this section,

</section>

<section><tid>452798</tid>
<number>5</number>After a regular assessment has been made, any amount paid or 
deemed to have been paid towards the provisional assessment made under 
this section shall be deemed to have been paid towards the regular 
assessment; and where the amount paid or deemed to have been paid 
towards the provisional assessment exceeds the amount payable under 
the regular assessment, the excess shall be refunded to the assessee.

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1788635</tid>
<number> 7A</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Advance payment of surtax.
<section><tid>1151539</tid>
<number>1</number>In this section,- 

<subsection><tid>1919932</tid>
<number>a</number>" chargeable amount", in relation to any previous year, 
means so much of the chargeable profits of the previous year 
as exceed the statutory deduction;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1842862</tid>
<number>b</number>" current chargeable amount", in relation to the advance 
surtax payable by a company during any financial year, means 
the chargeable amount of the company of the, period which 
would be the previous year for the assessment year 
immediately following that financial year.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1824422</tid>
<number>2</number>Surtax shall be payable, in accordance' with the pro- 
visions of-- this section, in advance during the financial 
year in respect of the chargeable amount of the period which 
would be the previous year for the immediately following 
assessment year.

</section>

<section><tid>880140</tid>
<number>3</number>The amount of advance surtax payable by an assessee in 
the financial year shall be computed as follows:-

<subsection><tid>47074</tid>
<number>a</number>the chargeable amount of the latest previous year in 
respect of which the assessee has been assessed by way of 
regular assessment shall first be ascertained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>239342</tid>
<number>b</number>in a case where the chargeable amount of the latest 
previous year[ being a year later than the previous year 
referred to in clause (a) on the basis of which a 
provisional assessment has been made under section 7. exceeds 
the chargeable amount referred to in clause, (a), the, 
chargeable, amount referred to in clause (a) shall be sub- 
stituted by the chargeable amount on the basis of which such 
provisional assessment has been made;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1760134</tid>
<number>c</number>surtax shall be calculated on the chargeable amount 
referred to in clause (a) or, as the case may be, in clause 
 (b), at the rates specified in the Third Schedule.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>644334</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of this section, advance sur- 
tax shall be payable in three equal instalments on the 
following dates during the financial year, namely:-

<subsection><tid>747036</tid>
<number>a</number>the 15th day of June, the 15th day of September and the 
 15th day of December, in the case of an assessee
whose chargeable amount to the extent of 75 per cent. thereof 
or more is derived from a source or sources for which the 
previous year (relevant to the assessment year next following  
  the financial year aforesaid) ends on or before the 31st day 
of December;


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1151010</tid>
<number>b</number>the 15th day of September, the 15th day of December 
and the 15th day of March, in any other case.
Provided that where, in respect of any class of assessees, the 
Board has, in exercise of the powers conferred by the proviso to sub- 
section (1) of section 211 of the Income- tax Act, authorised the 
payment of the last instalment of advance tax on the 15th day of March 
during the financial year instead of on the 15th day of December, the 
last instalment of advance surtax in the case of such assessees shall 
also be payable on the 15th day of March during the financial year.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>920332</tid>
<number>5</number>Every company shall, in each financial year, on or before 
the date on which the first instalment, or where it has not previously 
been assessed by way of regular assessment under this Act, on or 
before the date on which the last instalment, of advance surtax is due 
in its case under sub- section (4), if it is likely to have any current 
chargeable amount, send to the Income- tax Officer,--

<subsection><tid>289218</tid>
<number>a</number>where it has been previously assessed by way of regular 
assessment under this Act, a statement of advance surtax 
payable by it computed in the manner laid down in sub- section 
 (3), or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>563541</tid>
<number>b</number>where it has not previously been assessed by way of 
regular assessment under this Act, an estimate of--

<subsubsection><tid>370101</tid>
<number>i</number>the current chargeable amount and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1433705</tid>
<number>ii</number>the advance surtax payable by it on the amount 
specified in (i) above calculated in the, manner laid 
down in sub- section (3),
and shall pay such amount of advance surtax,-


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>520899</tid>
<number>I</number>in a case falling under clause (a), as accords 
with the statement in equal instalments on the dates 
applicable in its case under sub- section (4); and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>710328</tid>
<number>II</number>in a case falling under clause (b), as accords 
with the estimate in equal instalments on such of the 
dates applicable in its case as have not expired, or in 
one sum if only the last of such dates has not expired.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1634855</tid>
<number>6</number>Where a company which is required to send a statement under 
clause (a) of sub- section (5) estimates on or before the date on which 
the first instalment of advance surtax is due in its case under sub- 
section (4) that, by reason of its current chargeable amount being 
likely to be less than the chargeable amount on which advance surtax 
is payable by it under subsection (5) or for any other reason, the 
amount of advance surtax computed in the manner laid down in sub- 
section (3) on the current chargeable amount would be less than the 
amount of advance surtax payable by it under sub- section (5), it may 
send to the Income- tax Officer, in lieu of such statement, an estimate 
of-

<subsection><tid>1416104</tid>
<number>i</number>the current chargeable amount, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>933121</tid>
<number>ii</number>the advance surtax payable by it on the current 
chargeable amount calculated in the manner laid down in sub- 
section (3),
and shall pay such amount of advance surtax as accords with its 
estimate in equal instalments on the dates applicable in its case 
under sub- section (4).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1570174</tid>
<number>7</number>Where a company which has sent a statement under clause (a) 
of subsection (5) estimates on or before the date on which the last 
instalment of advance surtax is due in its case that, by reason of its 
current chargeable amount being likely to be less than the chargeable 
amount on which advance surtax is payable by it under sub- section (5) 
or for any other reason, the amount of advance surtax computed in the 
manner laid down in sub- section (3) on the current chargeable amount 
would be less than the amount of advance surtax payable by it under- 
sub- section (5), it may, at its option, send to the Income- tax Officer 
an estimate of--

<subsection><tid>1357624</tid>
<number>i</number>the current chargeable amount, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>405277</tid>
<number>ii</number>the advance surtax payable by it on the current 
chargeable amount calculated in the manner laid down in sub- 
section (3),
and shall pay such amount of advance surtax as accords with its 
estimate in equal instalments on such of the dates applicable in its 
case under subsection (4) as have not expired, or in one sum if only 
the last of such dates has not expired.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1944422</tid>
<number>8</number>In the case of any company which is liable to pay advance 
surtax under subsection (5) or sub- section (6) or, as the case may be, 
sub- section (7), if, by reason of the current chargeable amount being 
likely to be greater than the chargeable amount on which the advance 
surtax so payable by it has been computed or for any other reason, the 
amount of advance surtax computed in the manner laid down in sub- 
section (3) on the current chargeable amount (which shall be estimated  
  by the company) exceeds the amount of advance surtax so payable by it 
by more than twenty per cent. of the latter amount, it shall, on or 
before the date on which the last instalment of advance surtax is 
payable by it, send to the Income- tax Officer an estimate of-

<subsection><tid>984242</tid>
<number>i</number>the current chargeable amount, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>811549</tid>
<number>ii</number>the advance surtax payable by it on the current 
chargeable amount calculated in the manner laid down in sub- 
section (3),
and shall pay such amount of advance surtax as accords with its 
estimate on such of the dates applicable in its case under sub- section 
 (4) as have not expired, by instalment-. which may be revised 
according to sub- section (9):

Provided that where in respect of any company the Commissioner 
has, in exercise of the powers conferred by the first proviso to sub- 
section (4) of section 209A, or the first proviso to sub- section (3A) 
of section 212, of the Income- tax Act, extended the date for 
furnishing the estimate referred to in the said sub- section (4) or, as 
the case may be, the said sub- section (3A) and the company has paid 
the advance surtax which it is liable to pay under sub- section (5) or 
sub- section (6) or, as the case may be, sub- section (7) on or before 
the date on which the last instalment of advance surtax is due in its 
case, the company shall pay, on or before the date as so extended, the 
amount by which the advance surtax already paid by It falls short of 
the advance surtax payable in accordance with its estimate.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1674977</tid>
<number>9</number>The company may send a revised estimate of the, advance 
surtax payable by it on or before any one of the dates specified in 
sub- section (4) and adjust any excess or deficiency in respect of any 
instalment already paid in a subsequent instalment or in subsequent 
instalments.

</section>

<section><tid>530308</tid>
<number>10</number>Every statement or estimate under this section shall be sent 
in the prescribed form and verified in the prescribed manner.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1093579</tid>
<number> 7C</number> Interest payable by assessee.
<section><tid>1000239</tid>
<number>1</number>Where, in any financial  
year, a company has paid advance surtax under section 7A on the basis 
of its own estimate (including revised estimate), and the advance 
surtax so paid is less than eighty- three, and one- third per cent of 
the assessed surtax, simple interest at the rate of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fifteen per 
cent.] per annum from the 1st day of April next following the 
said financial year up to the date of the regular assessment shall be 
payable by the company upon the amount by which the advance surtax so 
paid falls short of the assessed surtax,

</section>

<section><tid>779879</tid>
<number>2</number>Where, on making the regular assessment, the Income- tax 
Officer finds-

<subsection><tid>1818301</tid>
<number>a</number>that any such company as is referred to in clause (a) of 
sub- section (5) of section 7A has not sent the statement 
referred to in that clause or the estimate in lieu of such 
statement referred to in sub- section (6) of that section; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>644434</tid>
<number>b</number>that any such company as is referred to in clause (b) of 
sub- section (5) of section 7A has not sent the estimate 
referred to in that clause,
simple interest at the rate of[ fifteen per cent] 2 per annum from 
the 1st day of April next following the financial year, in which the 
advance surtax was. payable in accordance with the said sub- section 
 (5) or sub-, section (6) up to the date of the regular assessment shall 
be payable by the company upon the amount equal to the assessed 
surtax.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>742002</tid>
<number>3</number>Where, on making the regular assessment, the Income- tax 
Officer finds that any company which is required,- to send an estimate 
under sub- section (8) of section 7A has not sent the, estimate 
referred to therein, simple interest at the rate of[ fifteen per 
cent] 2 per annum from the 1st day of April next following the finan- 
cial year in which the advance surtax was payable in accordance with 
the' said sub- section (8) to the date of the regular assessment shall 
be payable by the company upon the amount by which the advance surtax 
paid by, it falls short of the assessed surtax.

</section>

<section><tid>463980</tid>
<number>4</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the foregoing sub- 
sections, where provisional assessment is made under section 7-

<subsection><tid>1709907</tid>
<number>i</number>interest shall be calculated in accordance with the 
provisions of sub- section (1) or subsection (2) or, as the 
case may be, sub- section (3) up to the date on which the 
surtax provisionally assessed is paid; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1355477</tid>
<number>ii</number>thereafter interest shall be calculated at the rate of 
[ fifteen per cent] 2 per annum on the amount by which the 
surtax provisionally assessed falls short of the assessed 
surtax.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1282981</tid>
<number>5</number>In such cases and under such circumstances as may be, 
prescribed, the Income- tax Officer may reduce or waive the interest 
payable by the company under this section.

</section>

<section><tid>1182020</tid>
<number>6</number>Where, as a result of an order under section 11, or section 
12, or section 13, or section 17, or section 18 read with section 260 
or section 262 of the Income- tax Act. the amount on which interest was 
payable under this section' has been reduced, the interest shall be 
reduced accordingly and the excess interest paid, if any, shall be 
refunded.

</section>

<section><tid>1310726</tid>
<number>7</number>In this section and section 9A," assessed surtax" mean.,; 
the surtax determined on the basis of the regular assessment without 
making any deduction therefrom.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1531998</tid>
<number>7D</number>Interest payable by assessee in case of underestimate, etc. 
where, on making the regular assessment, the Income- tax Officer finds 
that any company has under section 7A underestimated the advance 
surtax payable by it and thereby reduced the amount payable in either 
of the first two instalments, he may direct that the company shall pay 
simple interest at <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> fifteen per cent.] per annum for the period 
during which the payment was deficient, on the difference between the 
amount paid in each such instalment and the amount which should have 
been paid, having regard to the aggregate advance surtax actually paid 
during the year.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, any instalment due 
before the expiry of six months from the commencement of the previous 
year in respect of which it is to be paid shall be deemed to have 
become, due fifteen days after the expiry of the said six months."]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1275</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 36 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>subs. by Act 67 of <year>1984</year>, s. 77 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).








</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>515790</tid>
<number> 8</number> Profits escaping assessment. If-
<section><tid>766876</tid>
<number>a</number>the Income- tax Officer has reason to believe that by 
reason of the omission or failure on the part of the assessee 
to make a return under section 5 for any assessment year or 
to disclose fully and truly all material facts necessary for 
his assessment for any assessment year, chargeable profits 
for that year have escaped assessment or have been under- 
assessed or assessed at too low a rate or have been made the 
subject of excessive relief under this Act, or

</section>

<section><tid>1103788</tid>
<number>b</number>notwithstanding that there has been no omission or 
failure as mentioned in clause (a) on the part of the 
assessee, the Income- tax Officer has in consequence of 
information in his possession reason to believe that 
chargeable profits assessable for any assessment year have 
escaped assessment or have been under- assessed or assessed at 
too low a rate or have been the subject of excessive relief 
under this Act,
he may, in cases falling under clause (a) at any time, and in cases 
falling under clause (b) at any time within four years of the end of 
that assessment year, serve on the assessee a notice containing all or 
any of the requirements which may be included in a notice under 
section 5, and may proceed to assess or re- assess the amount charge- 
able to surtax, and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as may 
be, apply as if the notice were a notice issued under that section.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>347173</tid>
<number> 9</number> Penalties. If the Income- tax, Officer, in the course of any 
proceedings under this Act, is satisfied that any person has, without 
reasonable cause, failed to furnish' the return required under section 
5, or to produce or cause to be produced the accounts, documents or 
other evidence required by the Income- tax Officer under sub- section

<section><tid>441987</tid>
<number>1</number>of section 6, or has concealed the particulars of the chargeable  
profits or has furnished inaccurate particulars of such profits, he 
may direct that such person shall pay, by way of penalty, in addition 
to the amount of surtax payable, a sum not exceeding-

<subsection><tid>1406707</tid>
<number>a</number>where the person has failed to furnish the return 
required under section 5, the amount of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> surtax chargeable 
under the Provisions of this Act."];

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>806330</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, the amount of surtax which would 
have been avoided if the return made had been accepted as 
correct:
Provided that the Income- tax Officer shall not impose any penalty 
under this section without the previous authority of the Inspecting 
Assistant Commissioner.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>227206</tid>
<number> 9A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> False estimate of, or failure to pay, advance surtax.
<section><tid>1169946</tid>
<number>1</number> 
If the Income- tax Officer, in the course of any proceedings in 
connection with the regular assessment for any assessment year, is 
satisfied that any assessee-

<subsection><tid>1044364</tid>
<number>a</number>has furnished under clause (a) of sub- section (5) of 
section 7A a statement of advance surtax payable by him which 
he knew or had reason to believe to be untrue, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>787795</tid>
<number>b</number>has without reasonable cause failed to furnish a 
statement of the advance surtax payable by him in accordance 
with the provisions of clause (a) of sub- section (5) of 
section 7A,
he may direct that such assessee shall, in addition to the 
amount of surtax, if any, payable by him, pay by way of 
penalty a sum-,


<subsubsection><tid>275553</tid>
<number>i</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall not 
be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a 
half times the amount by which the surtax actually paid 
during the financial year immediately preceding the 
assessment year under the provisions of section 7A falls 
short of--

<subsubsubsection><tid>1620283</tid>
<number>1</number>eighty- three and one- third percent of the assessed 
surtax, or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>1198023</tid>
<number>2</number>the amount which would have been payable by way of advance 
surtax if the assessee had furnished a correct and complete 
statement in accordance with the provisions of clause (a) of 
sub- section (5) of section 7A,
whichever is less;


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1187529</tid>
<number>ii</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall not 
be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a 
half times of eighty- three and one- third per cent, of the 
assessed surtax.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1313343</tid>
<number>2</number>If the Income- tax Officer, in the course of any 
proceedings in connection with the regular assessment for any 
assessment year, is satisfied that any assessee-

<subsection><tid>451037</tid>
<number>a</number>has furnished under clause (b) of sub- section (5) or 
sub- section (6) or sub- section (7) or sub- section (9) of 
section 7A, an estimate of the advance surtax payable by him 
which he knew or had reason to believe to be untrue, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1092051</tid>
<number>b</number>has furnished under sub- section (8) of section 7A, an 
estimate of the advance surtax payable by him which he knew 
or had reason to believe to be untrue, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1824700</tid>
<number>c</number>has without reasonable cause failed to furnish an 
estimate of the advance surtax payable by him in accordance 
with the provisions of clause (b) of sub- section (5) of 
section 7A, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1256628</tid>
<number>d</number>has without reasonable cause failed to furnish an 
estimate of advance surtax payable by him in accordance with 
the provisions of sub- section (8) of section 7A,
he may direct that such assessee shall, in addition to the 
amount of surtax, if any, payable by him, pay by way of 
penalty a sum-


<subsubsection><tid>1723158</tid>
<number>i</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (a), shall not 
be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a 
half times the amount by which the surtax actually paid 
during the financial year immediately preceding the 
assessment year under the provisions of section 7A falls 
short of-

<subsubsubsection><tid>376080</tid>
<number>1</number>eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the assess- 
ed surtax, or

</subsubsubsection>

<subsubsubsection><tid>266496</tid>
<number>2</number>where a statement under clause (a) of sub- section 
 (5) of section 7A was furnished by the assessee, the 
amount payable under such statement,
whichever is less;


</subsubsubsection>

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>529032</tid>
<number>ii</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (b), shall not 
be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a 
half times the amount by which the surtax actually paid 
during the financial year immediately preceding the 
assessment year under the provisions of section 7A falls 
short of eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the assessed 
surtax;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1607628</tid>
<number>iii</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (c), shall not 
be less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a 
half times of eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the 
assessed surtax; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1393066</tid>
<number>iv</number>which, in the case referred to in clause (d), shall not be 
less than ten per cent. but shall not exceed one and a half times the 
amount of surtax payable in accordance with a statement under clause 
 (a) or an estimate under clause (b) of sub- section (5) of section 7A 
or an estimate in lieu of a statement under sub- section (6) of that 
section falls short of eighty- three and one- third per cent. of the 
assessed surtax.
Explanation.- Where the Commissioner has, in exercise of the 
powers conferred by the first proviso to sub- section (4) of section 
209A, or the first proviso to sub- section (3A) of section 212, of the 
Income- tax Act, extended the date for furnishing the estimate referred 
to in the said sub- section (4) or, as the case may be, the said sub- 
section (3A) and the date so extended falls beyond the financial year 
immediately preceding the assessment year, then, the amount of surtax 
paid by the assessee on or before the date so extended shall, for the 
purposes of clause (ii) of subsection (2) also be regarded is surtax 
actual paid during that financial year."]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1276</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 26 of <year>1974</year>, s. 20 (retrospectively).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 37 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>.)






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>451737</tid>
<number>10</number>Opportunity of being heard. No order imposing a penalty under 
section 9 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> or section 9A] shall be made unless the assessee has been 
given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</article>



<article><tid>1404671</tid>
<number> 11</number> Appeals to the Appellate Assistant Commissioner.
<section><tid>413434</tid>
<number>1</number>Any  
person objecting to the amount of surtax for which he is liable as 
assessed by the Income- tax Officer or denying his liability to be 
assessed under this Act, or objecting to any penalty or fine imposed 
by the Income- Tax Officer, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> or objecting to the interest levied by 
the Income- Tax Officer under section 7D,"] or to the amount allowed by 
the Income- tax Officer by way of any relief under any provisions of 
this Act, or to any refusal by the Income- tax officer to grant relief 
or to an order of rectification or amendment having the effect of 
enhancing the assessment or reducing the refund, or to an order 
refusing to allow the claim made by the assessee for a rectification 
under section 13 or amendment under section 14 may appeal to the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioners[ Appeals]]

</section>

<section><tid>379916</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be 
verified in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1340793</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal shall be presented within thirty days of the 
following date, that is to say-

<subsection><tid>1798700</tid>
<number>a</number>where the appeal relates to assessment or penalty or 
fine, the date of service of the notice of demand relating to 
the assessment or penalty or fine, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1563178</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, the date on which the intimation of 
the order sought to be appealed against is served:
Provided that the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioners[ Appeals] may admit an appeal 
after the expiration of the said period if he is satisfied that the 
appellant had sufficient cause for not presenting it within that 
period.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1906052</tid>
<number>4</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] shall hear and determine the 
appeal and, subject to the provisions of this Act, pass such orders as 
he thinks fit and such orders may include an order enhancing the 
assessment or penalty:
Provided that an order enhancing the assessment or penalty shall 
not be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a 
reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.


</section>

<section><tid>1725384</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure to be adopted in the hearing and determination 
of the appeals shall, with any necessary modification, be in 
accordance with the procedure applicable in relation to income- tax.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>962018</tid>
<number>11A</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Transfer of certain pending appeals. Every appeal under 
this Act which is pending immediately before the appointed day before 
an Appellate Assistant commissioner or a Commissioner and any matter 
arising Out of or connected with such appeal and which Is so pending 
shall stand transferred on that day to the Commissioner, (Appeals) and 
the Commissioner (Appeals) may Proceed with such appeal or matter 
from, the stage at which it was on that day:
Provided that the appellant may demand that before Proceeding 
further with the appeal or matter the previous Proceeding or any part 
thereof be reopened or that he be re- heard.

Explanation.- In this section," appointed day" means the date 
appointed under section 39 of the Finance (No. 2) Act, <year>1977</year>.]



</article>



<article><tid>1456982</tid>
<number> 12</number> Appeals to Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>942598</tid>
<number>1</number>any assessee aggrieved by  
an order passed by a Commissioner under section 16, or an order passed 
by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a Commissioner (Appeals)]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1277</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. and Ins. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V, (w. e. f. 10- 7-  
  <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 38 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 39, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

under any provision of this Act, may appeal to the Appellate Tribunal 
against such order.


</section>

<section><tid>1406384</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner may, if he objects to any order passed by 
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] under any provision of this Act, direct 
the Income- tax Officer to appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against the 
order.

</section>

<section><tid>220479</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) shall 
be filled within sixty days of the date on which the order sought to 
be appealed against is communicated to the assessee or to the Commis- 
sioner, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1369194</tid>
<number>4</number>The Income- tax Officer, or the assessee, as the case may be, 
on receipt of notice that an appeal against the order of the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] has been preferred under sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) by the other party may, notwithstanding that he may 
not have appealed against such order or any part thereof, within 
thirty days of the receipt of the notice, file, a memorandum of cross 
objections, verified in the prescribed manner, against any part of the 
order of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Commissioner Appeals] and such memorandum shall be 
disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal, as if it were an appeal 
presented within the time specified in sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>1683959</tid>
<number>5</number>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the 
filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the 
relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if 
it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it 
wit within that period.

</section>

<section><tid>1280381</tid>
<number>6</number>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the 
prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and, 
shall, except in the case of in appeal referred to in sub- section (2) 
or a memorandum of cross- objections referred to in sub- section (4). be 
accompanied by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a fee of <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> two hundred rupees].

</section>

<section><tid>119977</tid>
<number>7</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, in hearing and making 
an order on any appeal under this section. the Appellate Tribunal 
shall exercise the same powers and follow the same procedure as it 
exercises and follows hearing and making an order on any appeal under 
the Income- tax Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>571766</tid>
<number> 13</number> Rectification of mistakes.
<section><tid>1076844</tid>
<number>1</number>With a view to rectifying any  
mistake apparent from the record, the Commissioner, the Income- tax 
Officer, the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals] and the Appellate Tribunal may,  
its, own motion or on an application by the assessee in this behalf 
amend any order passed by him or it in any proceeding under this Act 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> within four years from the end of the financial year in which such 
order was passed."]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1278</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 72, for" a fee of one hundred 
rupees" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>.)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and sch. V (w. e. f. 10- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 40 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 67 of <year>1984</year>, s. 78 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>957183</tid>
<number>2</number>An amendment which has the effect of enhancing the assess- 
ment or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability of the 
assessee shall not be made under this section unless the authority 
concerned has given notice to the assessee of its intention so to do 
and has allowed the assessee a reasonable opportunity of being heard.

</section>

<section><tid>790108</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an amendment is made under this section, the order 
shall be passed in writing by the authority concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1863899</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, where any such 
amendment has the effect of reducing the assessment, the Income- tax 
Officer shall make any refund which may be due to such assessee.

</section>

<section><tid>114069</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the 
assessment or reducing the refund already made, the Income- tax Officer 
shall serve on the assessee a notice of demand in the prescribed form 
specifying the sum payable.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1839797</tid>
<number> 14</number> Other amendments. Where as a result of any order made under 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> section 154, 155, 250, 254, 260, 262, 263 or 264] of the Income- tax 
Act, it is necessary to recompute the chargeable profits determined in 
any assessment under this Act, the Income- tax Officer may proceed to 
recompute the chargeable profits, and determine the surtax payable or 
refundable on the basis of such recomputation and make the necessary 
amendment and the provisions of section 13 shall, so far as may be, 
apply thereto, the period of four years specified in sub- section
<section><tid>511484</tid>
<number>1</number> 
of that section being reckoned <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> from the end of the financial year 
in which the order under the aforesaid sections of the Income- tax Act 
was passed"]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>634910</tid>
<number>15</number>Surtax deductible in computing distributable income under 
Income- tax Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in clause (i) of 
section 109 of the Income- tax Act, in computing the distributable 
income of a company for the purposes of Chapter XID of that Act, the 
surtax payable by the company any for any assessment year shall be 
deductible from the total income of the company assessable for that 
assessment year.


</article>



<article><tid>1527871</tid>
<number> 16</number> Revision of orders prejudicial to revenue.
<section><tid>1142714</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Commissioner may call for and examine the record of any proceeding 
under this Act, and if he considers that any order passed therein by 
the Income- tax Officer Is erroneous in so far as it is prejudicial to 
the interests of the revenue, he, may, after giving the assessee an 
opportunity of being heard and after making or causing to be made such 
inquiry as he deems necessary, pass such order thereon as the 
circumstances of the case justify, including an order enhancing or 
modifying the assessment, or cancelling the assessment and directing a 
fresh assessment.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Explanation.-- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that, for the purposes of this sub- section, an order passed by the 
Income- Tax Officer shall include an order passed by the Inspecting 
Assistant Commissioner in exercise of the powers or in performance of 
the functions of an Income- tax Officer conferred on, or assigned to, 
him under clause (a) of sub- section (1) of section 125 or under sub- 
section (1) of section 125A of the Income- tax Act as applied by 
section 18 of this Act."]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1279</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 73, for" section 154 or section 
155" (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 67 of <year>1984</year>, s. 79 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 80, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>86385</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> No order shall be made under sub- section (1) after the 
expiry of two years from the end of the financial year in which the 
order sought to be revised was passed."]

</section>

<section><tid>1457174</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), an 
order in revision under this section may be passed at any time in the 
case of an order which has been passed in consequence of, or to give 
effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order of the 
Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the Supreme Court.
Explanation.- In computing the period of limitation for the pur- 
poses of sub- section (2), any period during which any proceeding under 
this section is stayed by an order or injunction of any court shall be 
excluded.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>979241</tid>
<number> 17</number> Revision of orders by Commissioner.
<section><tid>764061</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commissioner may,  
either of his own motion or on an application by the assessee for 
revision, call for the record of any proceeding under this Act which 
has been taken by an Income- tax Officer subordinate to him and may 
make such inquiry or cause such inquiry to be made and, subject to the 
provisions of this Act, may pass such order thereon, not being an 
order prejudicial to the assessee, as he thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>954415</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner shall not of his own motion revise any 
order under this section if the order has been made more than one year 
previously.

</section>

<section><tid>1918457</tid>
<number>3</number>In the case of an application for revision under this 
section by the assessee, the application shall be made within one 
year from the date on which the order in question was communicated to 
him or the date on which he otherwise came to know of it, whichever is 
earlier:
Provided that the Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the 
assessee was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application 
within, that period admit an application made after the expiry of that 
period.


</section>

<section><tid>619199</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall not revise any order under this 
section in the following cases-

<subsection><tid>1156768</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> where an appeal against the order lies to the Commissioner 
 (Appeals) but has not been made and the time within which such appeal 
may be made has not expired, or the assessee has not waived his right 
of appeal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1733160</tid>
<number>b</number>where the order has been made the subject of an appeal to 
the Commissioner (Appeals).]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1280</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted and subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and sch. V, (w. e. f.  
  10- 7- <year>1978</year>.)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 67 of <year>1984</year>, s. 80 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>199685</tid>
<number>5</number>Every application by an assessee for revision under this 
section shall be accompanied by a fee of twenty- five rupees.
Explanation 1.- An order by the Commissioner declining to inter- 
fere shall, for the purposes of this section be deemed not to be an 
order prejudicial to the assessee.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>715548</tid>
<number> 18</number> Application of provisions of Income- tax Act. The provisions of 
the following sections and Schedules of the Income- tax Act and the 
Income- tax (Certificate Proceedings) Rules, <year>1962</year>, as in force from 
time to time, shall apply with such modifications, if any, as may be 
prescribed, as if the said provisions and the rules referred to surtax 
instead of to income- tax <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>:--
<section><tid>544402</tid>
<number>44</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>] 18 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> 116, 117, 118, 119, 120, 129], 131, 132, 132A 
 <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>, 132 B] 133 to 136 (both inclusive)], 138, 140, 156, 160, 
161, 162, 163, 166, 167, 170, 173, 175, 176, 178, 179, <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> 218 
to 229] (both inclusive), 231, 232, 233, 237 to 242 (both  
  inclusive), 244, 245, 254 to 262 (both inclusive), 265, 266, 
268, 269, 281, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> 281B] 282, 284, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> 287, 288, 288A, 288B, 289 
to 293 (both inclusive)], the Second Schedule and the Third 
Schedule:
Provided that references in the said provisions and the rules to 
the" assessee" shall be construed as references to an assessee as 
defined in this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1215886</tid>
<number> 19</number> Income- tax papers to be available for the purpose of this Act.

<section><tid>1291276</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax be Act, all  
information contained in any statement or return made or furnished 
under the provisions of that Act or obtained or collected of for the 
purposes of that Act may be used for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1389740</tid>
<number>2</number>All information' contained in any statement or return made 
or furnished under the provisions of this Act or obtained or collected 
for the purposes of this Act may be used for the purposes of the 
Income- tax Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1281</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" and super- tax" omitted by Act 10 of <year>1965</year>, s. 74 
 (we. f. 1- 4- <year>1965</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by Act 20 of <year>1967</year>, s. 36, for" 287 to 293 (both  
  inclusive)" (w. e. f. 14- <year>1967</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 124 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1975</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Explanation 1 Omitted by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f.  
  10- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 41, for" 220 to 229" (w. e. f. 1- 4-  
  <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1988</year>, s. 189, for" 2 (43B) and (44)" (w. e. f. 1-  
  4- <year>1989</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 189 ibid., for" 118, 125, 125A, 129, 139, 130A (w. e.-  
  f. 1- 4- <year>1988</year>).







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1137093</tid>
<number>20</number>Failure to deliver returns, etc. If any person fails without 
reasonable cause to furnish in due time any return, under sub- section 
 (2) of section 5, or to produce, or cause to be produced, any accounts 
or documents, required to be produced under section 6, he shall be 
punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, and with 
a further fine which may extend to ten rupees for every day during 
which the default continues.


</article>



<article><tid>951687</tid>
<number>21</number>False statements. If a person makes in any return furnished 
under section 5, any statement which is false, and which he either 
knows or believes to be false, or does not believe to be true, he 
shall be punishable with simple imprisonment which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both.


</article>



<article><tid>462409</tid>
<number>22</number>Abatement of false returns, etc. If a person makes or induces 
in any manner another person to make and deliver any account, 
statement or declaration relating to chargeable profits liable to 
surtax which is false and which he either knows to be false or does 
not believe to be true, he shall be punishable with simple 
imprisonment which may extend to six months, or with fine which may 
extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>1401635</tid>
<number> 23</number> Institution of proceedings and composition of offences.
<section><tid>1552607</tid>
<number>1</number>A  
person shall not be proceeded against for an offence under section 20 
or section 21 or section 22 or under the Indian Penal Code except at 
the instance of the Commissioner. (45 of <year>1860</year>).

</section>

<section><tid>14369</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner may, either before or after the institution 
of proceedings, compound any offence punishable under section 20 or 
section 21 or section 22.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1840741</tid>
<number>24</number>Power to make exemption, etc., in relation to certain Union 
territories. If the Central Government considers it necessary or 
expedient so to do for avoiding any hardship or anomaly or removing an 
difficulty that may arise as a result of the application of this Act 
to the Union territories of Dadra and Nagar Haveli, Goa, Dam and Diu 
and Pondicherry, the Central Government may, by general or special 
order, made an exemption, reduction in rate or other modification in 
respect of surtax in favour of any class of assessees or in regard to 
the whole or any part of the chargeable profits of any class of 
assessees.


</article>



<article><tid>659045</tid>
<number> 24A</number> <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Agreement with foreign countries. The Central 
Government may enter into an agreement with the Government of any 
country outside India-
<section><tid>277048</tid>
<number>a</number>for the granting of relief in respect of chargeable 
profits on which have been paid both surtax under this Act 
and tax of a similar character or income- tax on such profits 
in that country, or

</section>

<section><tid>1463815</tid>
<number>b</number>for the avoidance of double taxation of chargeable 
profit under this Act and under any law relating to the 
taxation of income or profits in force in that country, or

</section>

<section><tid>1811837</tid>
<number>c</number>for exchange of information for the prevention of eva- 
sion or avoidance of surtax chargeable under this Act or the 
chargeable under the corresponding law in force in that 
country or investigation of cases of such evasion or 
avoidance, or

</section>

<section><tid>1781640</tid>
<number>d</number>for recovery of tax under this Act and under any law 
relating to the taxation of income or profits in force that 
country,
and may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make such provision 
as may be necessary for implementing the agreement."]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1282</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 15 of <year>1965</year>, s. 22.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1972</year>, s. 57 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1021867</tid>
<number> 24AA</number> <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Power to make exemption, etc., in relation to 
participation in the business of prospecting for, extraction, etc., of 
mineral oils.
<section><tid>866096</tid>
<number>1</number>If the Central Government is satisfied that it is  
necessary or expedient so to do in the public interest, it may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make in exemption, reduction in 
rate or other modification in respect of surtax in favour of any class 
of foreign companies specified in sub- section (2) or in regard to the 
whole or any part of the profits chargeable of such class of companies.
Explanation.- For the purposes, of this sub- section," foreign 
company" shall have the meaning assigned to it in clause (4) of 
section 80B of the Income- Tax Act.


</section>

<section><tid>386450</tid>
<number>2</number>The foreign companies referred to in sub- section (1) are the 
following, namely:-

<subsection><tid>89844</tid>
<number>a</number>foreign companies with whom the Central Government has 
entered into agreements for the association or participation 
of that Government or any person authorised by that 
Government in any business consisting of the prospecting for 
or extraction or production of mineral oils; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1950649</tid>
<number>b</number>foreign companies providing any services or facilities 
or supplying any ship, aircraft, machinery or plant (whether  
  by way of sale or hire) in connection with any business 
consisting of the prospecting for or extraction or production 
of mineral oils carried on by that Government or any person 
specified by that Government in this behalf by notification 
in the Official Gazette.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>120073</tid>
<number>3</number>Every notification issued under this section shall be laid 
before each House of Parliament,
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," mineral oil" 
includes petroleum and natural gas.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1031582</tid>
<number> 25</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>692093</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board may, subject to the control  
of the Central Government, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>904827</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>41240</tid>
<number>a</number>the form in which returns under section 5 may be 
furnished and the manner in which they may be verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>115509</tid>
<number>b</number>the form in which notice for making provisional 
assessment shall be given;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>283492</tid>
<number>c</number>the form in which appeals under section 11 or section 
 12 may be filed and the manner in which they shall be 
verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1944635</tid>
<number>cc</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the circumstances in which, the conditions subject to 
which and the manner in which,' the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] 
may permit an appellant to produce evidence which he did not 
produce or which he was- not allowed to Produce before the 
Income- tax Officer;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>696975</tid>
<number>d</number>the procedure to be followed on applications for 
rectification of mistakes and applications for refunds;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>536637</tid>
<number>dd</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the procedure to be followed in calculating interest 
payable by assessees or interest payable by the Government to 
assessees under this Act, including the rounding off the 
period for which such interest is to be calculated in cases 
where such period includes a fraction of a month, and 
specifying the circumstances in which and the extent to which 
petty amounts of interest payable by assessees may be 
ignored;]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1611045</tid>
<number>e</number>any other matter which by this Act is to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>38952</tid>
<number>2A</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> The power to make rules conferred by this section shall 
include the power to give retrospective effect, form a date not 
earlier than the date of commencement of this Act, to the rules or any 
of them and, unless the contrary is permitted (whether expressly  
  or by necessary implication), no retrospective effect shall be given 
to any rule so as to Prejudicially affect the interests of 
assessees."]

</section>

<section><tid>1923368</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall cause every rule made under this 
section to be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days, which may be comprised in one session <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or in two or 
more successive sessions] and if, before the expiry of the session 
 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid"] both Houses agree in

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1282A</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 42 of <year>1970</year>, s. 74 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1971</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1972</year>, s. 58 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1972</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 26 of <year>1974</year>, s. 21.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 41 of <year>1975</year>, s. 125 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1976</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 10- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 42 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1981</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule 
should not be made, that rule shall thereafter have effect only in 
such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so however 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to 
the validity of anything previously done under that rule.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1548276</tid>
<number>26</number>Saving. Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to any 
company Saving. which has no share capital.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1283</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</article>



 </act>