<act><tid>340758</tid>
<title>THE COTTON TRANSPORT ACT, <year>1923</year></title>

ACT NO. 3 OF <year>1923</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 23rd February, <year>1923</year>.]

An Act to provide for the restriction and control of the transport of 
cotton in certain circumstances.

WHEREAS it is expedient for the purpose of maintaining the 
quality and reputation of the cotton grown in certain areas <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to 
enable the restriction and control of the transport by rail and the 
import of cotton into those areas; It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1652480</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>941809</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Cotton  
Transport Act, <year>1923</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>116225</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1167509</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,--
<section><tid>1126884</tid>
<number>a</number>" certified copy," in relation to a licence, means a copy 
of the licence certified in the manner described in 
section 76 of the Indian Evidence Act, <year>1872</year> (1 of  
  <year>1872</year>), by the authority by which the licence was 
granted;

</section>

<section><tid>1596928</tid>
<number>b</number>" cotton" means every kind of unmanufactured cotton, that 
is to say, ginned and unginned cotton, cotton waste and 
cotton seed;

</section>

<section><tid>1304292</tid>
<number>c</number>" cotton waste" means droppings, strippings, fly and 
other waste products of a cotton- mill other than yarn 
waste;

</section>

<section><tid>1960950</tid>
<number>d</number>" licence" means a licence granted under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>547097</tid>
<number>e</number>" notified station" means a railway station specified in 
a notification under section 3;

</section>

<section><tid>240392</tid>
<number>f</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act; and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>6</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>This Act was partially extended to Berar by the Berar Laws Act, 
<year>1941</year> (4 of <year>1941</year>).

It was extended to Shahda, Nandurbar and Taloda Talukas of the 
West Khandesh District, the Dohad Taluka and the Jhalod Mahal of the 
Panch Mahal District of the State of Bombay by Schedule II of the 
Absorbed Areas (Laws) Act, <year>1954</year> (20 of <year>1954</year>).

The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>The words" in the Provinces" omitted by the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
3 Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1960</year>, s. 2, for sub- section (2).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>257515</tid>
<number>g</number>" protected area" means an area into which the import of 
cotton or of any kind of cotton has been prohibited 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> wholly or partly] by a notification under section 3.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1140890</tid>
<number> 3</number> Power to issue notification prohibiting import of cotton into 
protected area.
<section><tid>1467405</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, for the purpose of  
maintaining the quality or reputation of the cotton grown in any area 
in the State, by notification in the Official Gazette, prohibit the 
import of cotton or of any specified kind of cotton into that area 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by rail, road, river and sea, or by any one or more of such routes] 
save under, and in accordance with the conditions of, a licence:
Provided that no such notification shall be deemed to prohibit 
the import into any protected area of packages containing any kind of 
cotton and not exceeding ten pounds avoirdupois weight.


</section>

<section><tid>95843</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such notification may prohibit the delivery to, and the 
taking of delivery by, any person, at any specified railway station 
situated in the protected area, of any cotton, the import of which 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by rail] into that area is prohibited when such cotton has been 
consigned from a railway station not situated in that area, unless 
such person holds a licence for the import <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by rail] of the cotton 
into that area.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>535229</tid>
<number> 4</number> Refusal to carry unlicensed cotton.
<section><tid>43648</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding  
anything contained in the Indian Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>), or 
any other law for the time being in force, the station master of any 
railway station or any other railway servant responsible for the 
booking of goods or parcels at that station may refuse to receive for 
carriage at, or to forward or allow to be carried on the railway from, 
that station any cotton consigned to a notified station, being cotton 
of a kind of which the delivery at such notified station has been 
prohibited unless both stations are in the same protected area, or 
unless the consignor produces a certified copy of a licence for the 
import of the cotton <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> by rail] into the protected area in which such 
notified station is situated.

</section>

<section><tid>459150</tid>
<number>2</number>Every certified copy of a licence when so produced shall be 
attached to the invoice or way- bill, as the case may be, and shall 
accompany the consignment to its destination, and shall there be dealt 
with in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>343720</tid>
<number>3</number>Where by or under any law in force in the territories of any 
State in India the import <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> by rail] into any area, or the delivery
<pagefootnote><pagenum>7</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 34 of <year>1925</year>, s. 2. 
2 Ins. by s. 3, ibid. 
3 Ins. by s. 4, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


at any railway station, of cotton or of any kind of cotton has been 
prohibited, the Central Government may, by notification <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in the 
Official Gazette, declare that the provisions of sub- section (1) shall 
apply in respect of cotton consigned to any such station as if such 
area and such station were respectively a protected area and a 
notified station, and as if any licence granted under such law were a 
licence granted under this Act.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>235299</tid>
<number> 5</number> Procedure where cotton arrives at notified station.
<section><tid>1992893</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
any cotton, the import of which <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by rail] into any protected area 
has been prohibited, has been consigned to and arrives at a notified 
station in any such protected area, the station master or other 
railway servant responsible for the receipt and delivery to the 
consignee of goods or parcels, as the case may be, at that station 
shall, unless both the notified station and the railway station from 
which the cotton has been consigned are situated in the same protected 
area, refuse to deliver the cotton until he is satisfied that the 
consignee holds a licence for the import of the cotton <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by rail] 
into the protected area in which such notified station is situated; 
and, if he is not so satified, or if within fourteen days the 
consignee or some person acting on his behalf does not appear in order 
to take delivery, shall return the cotton to the railway station from 
which it was consigned, together with an intimation that delivery of 
the cotton has been refused or has not been taken, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>271735</tid>
<number>2</number>Any station master or other railway servant receiving any 
cotton returned under sub- section (1), or returned with a like 
intimation from a railway station specified in a notification under 
sub- section (3) of section 4, shall cause to be served on the 
consignor in any manner authorised by section 141 of the Indian 
Railways Act, <year>1890</year> (9 of <year>1890</year>), a notice stating that the cotton has 
been so returned and requiring the consignor to pay any rate, terminal 
or other charges due in respect of the carriage of the cotton to and 
from the railway station to which it was consigned, and such charges 
shall be deemed to be due from the consignor for all the purposes of 
section 55 of that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>576673</tid>
<number>6</number>Penalties. Any person who, in contravention of the provisions 
of this Act or of any notification or rule made hereunder, knowingly 
takes delivery of any cotton from a notified station or imports, or 
attempts to import, any cotton into a protected area, and any station 
master or other railway servant who, in contravention of the 
provisions of
<pagefootnote><pagenum>8</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>For such notifications see Gen. R. and O. Vol. V, p. 90; ibid., 
Supplementary Vol. II, p. 998; and ibid., Supplementary Vol. VI, p. 
457. 
2 Ins. by Act 34 of <year>1925</year>, s. 5.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


sub- section (1) of section 5, without reasonable excuse, the burden of 
proving which shall lie upon him, delivers any cotton to a consignee 
or other person, shall be liable to a fine not exceeding one thousand 
rupees, and upon any subsequent conviction to imprisonment which may 
extend to three months, or to fine which may extend to five thousand 
rupees, or to both.



</article>



<article><tid>1440127</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1840226</tid>
<number>1</number>The State Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to provide for any of 
the following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>933558</tid>
<number>a</number>the prevention of the import into a protected area by 
road, river or sea, save under and in accordance with 
the conditions of a licence, of cotton the import of 
which into that area has been prohibited <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> wholly or 
partly] by a notification under section 3;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1531585</tid>
<number>b</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the terms and conditions to be contained in licences, 
the authorities by which they may be granted and the 
fees which may be levied in respect thereof; and]

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1503033</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which licences and certified copies 
thereof shall be dealt with on and after the delivery 
of the cotton to which they relate.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>652026</tid>
<number>2</number>Any such rules may provide that any contravention thereof or 
of the conditions of any licence, not otherwise made punishable by 
this Act, shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five 
hundred rupees.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>237535</tid>
<number>8</number>Previous approval of State Legislature to issue of 
notifications and rules. No notification under section 3 or rule under 
section 7 shall be issued by the State Government <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>, unless it has 
been laid in draft before <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> the Legislative Assembly of the State], 
and has been approved by a Resolution <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> of that Assembly], either 
with or without modification or addition, but upon such approval being 
given the notification or rule, as the case may be, may be issued in 
the form in which it has been so approved:
<pagefootnote><pagenum>9</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 34 of <year>1925</year>, s. 6. 
2 Subs. by Act 22 of <year>1960</year>, s. 3, for cl. (b). 
3 The words" of any Part A State" omitted by the Adaptation of Laws 
 (No. 3) Order, <year>1956</year>. 
4 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" the Legislative Council of the 
Province". 
5 Subs., ibid., for" of the Legislative Council".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Provided that if the State Legislature has two <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Houses], the 
notification must be laid in draft before, and be approved by 
Resolutions of, both <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Houses], either without modifications or 
additions, or with modifications or additions approved by both 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Houses].]



</article>



<article><tid>1207521</tid>
<number>9</number>Protection for acts done under Act. No suit or other legal 
proceeding shall be instituted against any person in respect of 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done under this 
Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>10</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>. 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" Chambers".

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>