<act><tid>355318</tid>
<title>THE PUBLIC WAKFS (EXTENSION OF LIMITATION) ACT, <year>1959</year></title>

ACT NO. 29 OF <year>1959</year>
[ 1st September, <year>1959</year>.]

An Act to extend the period of limitation in certain cases for suits 
to recover possession of immovable property forming part of Public 
Wakfs.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Tenth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>224879</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>504975</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Public  
Wakfs (Extension of Limitation) Act, <year>1959</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1906962</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu 
and Kashmir.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>554231</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," public wakf" means the permanent 
dedication by a person professing Islam of any immovable property for 
any purpose recognised by Muslim law as a public purpose of a pious, 
religious or charitable nature.


</article>



<article><tid>1697202</tid>
<number>3</number>Extension of period of limitation in certain cases for suits 
to recover possession of immovable property forming part of public 
wakfs. Where a person entitled to institute a suit of the description 
referred to in article 142 or article 144 of the First Schedule to the 
Indian Limitation Act, <year>1908</year>, (9 of <year>1908</year>.) for possession of any 
immovable property forming part of a public wakf or any interest 
therein has been dispossessed, or has discontinued the possession, at 
any time after the 14th day of August, <year>1947</year>, and before the 7th day of 
May, <year>1954</year>, or, as the case may be, the possession of the defendant in 
such a suit has become adverse to such person at any time during the 
said period, then, notwithstanding anything contained in the said Act, 
the period of limitation in respect of such a suit shall extend up to 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> the 31st day of December, <year>1970</year>].


</article>



<article><tid>430201</tid>
<number> 4</number> Repeal and saving.
<section><tid>1729013</tid>
<number>1</number>The Public Wakfs (Extension of   
  Limitation) Ordinance, <year>1959</year> (2 of <year>1959</year>.), is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1451558</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under this Act as if this Act had commenced on the 20th day of 
July, <year>1959</year>.
Amended in Haryana by Haryana Act 22 of <year>1971</year>. 
Amended in Kerala by Kerala Act 8 of <year>1971</year>. 
Amended in Andhra Pradesh by A. P. Act, 9 of <year>1972</year>. 
Amended in West Bengal by W. B. Act 33 of <year>1972</year>. 
Amended in Tamil Nadu By T. N. Act 19 of <year>1972</year>. 
Amended in Orissa by Orissa Act 22 of <year>1972</year>. 12 of <year>1975</year>. 
Amended in Mysore by Mysore, Act 11 of <year>1973</year>. 46 of <year>1976</year>. 
Amended in Punjab by Punjab Act 41 of <year>1973</year>. 24 of <year>1976</year>. 
Amended in Delhi by Act 9 of <year>1974</year>. 
Amended in Madhya Pradesh by M. P. Act 29 of <year>1975</year>. 28 of <year>1976</year>. 
Amended in Himachal Pradesh by H. P. Act 16 of <year>1974</year> and 38 of <year>1976</year>. 
Amended in Himachal Pradesh by H. P. Act 13 of <year>1978</year>. 
Amended in Andhra Pradesh by A. P. Act 15 of <year>1978</year>. 
Amended in its application to Delhi by Acts 9 of <year>1972</year>, 9 of <year>1974</year> 12 of 
 <year>1978</year> and 39 <year>1982</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>subs. by Act 9 of <year>1969</year>, s, 2, for" the 31st day of December, 
<year>1968</year>".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>