<act><title>

the 
    delimitation act, 2002</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—This 
    Act may be called the Delimitation Act, 2002.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>  “article” means an 
    article of the Constitution; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  “associate member” 
    means a member nominated under section 5;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>  “Commission” means the 
    Delimitation Commission constituted under section 3; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>  “Election Commission“ 
    means the Election Commission referred to in article 324;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>  “member” means a 
    member of the Commission and includes the Chairperson; and; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>  “State” includes a 
    Union territory having a Legislative Assembly but does not include the State 
    of Jammu and Kashmir.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of Delimitation Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    As soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, the Central Government 
    shall constitute a Commission to be called the Delimitation Commission which 
    shall consist of three members as follows:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  one members, who shall 
    be a person who is or has been a Judge of the Supreme Court, to be appointed 
    by the Central Government who shall be the Chairperson of the Commission;
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  the Chief Election 
    Commissioner or an Election Commissioner nominated by the Chief Election 
    Commissioner, ex officio: 
 
      Provided that after 
    the nomination of an Election Commissioner as a member under this clause, no 
    further nomination under this clause shall be made except to fill the casual 
    vacancy of such member under section 6; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  the State Election 
    Commissioner of concerned State, ex officio. 
 
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of clause (c), the State Election Commissioner of concerned 
    State,—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  in respect of the 
    duties of the Commission relating to a State (other than the States of 
    Meghalaya, Mizoram and Nagaland), means the State Election Commissioner 
    appointed by the Governor of that State under clause (1) of Article 243K; 
    and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>  in respect of the 
    duties of the Commission relating to the State of Meghalaya or the State of 
    Mizoram or the State of Nagaland, as the case may be, means a person nominated 
    by the Governor of that State for such purposes.] 
  
  






 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Duties of the Commission.—The 
    readjustment made, on the basis of the census figures as ascertained at the 
    census held in the year 1971 by the Delimitation Commission constituted 
    under section 3 of the Delimitation Act, 1972 (76 of 1972) of the allocation 
    of seats in the House of the People to the several States and the total 
    number of seats in the Legislative Assembly of each State shall be deemed to 
    be the readjustment made by the Commission for the purposes of this Act.
 <section>
<number>2</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (1) and any other law for the time 
    being in force, the Commission shall readjust the division of each State 
    into territorial constituencies for the purpose of elections to the House of 
    the People and to the State Legislative Assembly on the basis of the census 
    figures as ascertained at the census held in the year <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[2001]:
 
Provided 
    that where on such readjustment only one seat is allocated in the House of 
    the People to a State, the whole of that State shall form one territorial 
    constituency for the purpose of elections to the House of the People from 
    that State.
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Associate members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commission shall associate with itself for the purpose of assisting it 
    in its duties in respect of each State, ten persons five of whom shall be 
    members of the House of the People representing that State and five shall be 
    members of the Legislative Assembly of that State:
 
Provided 
    that where the number of the members of the House of the People representing 
    any State is five or less, then, all such members shall be the associate 
    members for that State and in the latter case the total number of associate 
    members shall be less than ten by such number as by which the total number 
    of members of the House of the People representing that State is less than 
    five.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    persons to be so associated from each State shall be nominated, in the case 
    of members of the House of the People, by the Speaker of that House, and in 
    the case of members of a Legislative Assembly, by the Speaker of that 
    Assembly, having due regard to the composition of the House or, as the case 
    may be, of the Assembly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    first nominations to be made under sub-section (2)—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  shall be made by the 
    Speakers of the several Legislative Assemblies within one month, and by the 
    Speaker of the House of the People within two months, of the commencement of 
    this Act, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  shall be communicated 
    to the Chief Election Commissioner, and where the nominations are made by 
    the Speaker of a Legislative Assembly, also to the Speaker of the House of 
    the People. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> None 
    of the associate members shall have a right to vote or to sign any decision 
    of the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Commission shall have power to call upon—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  the Registrar-General 
    and Census Commissioner, India or his nominee; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  the Surveyor General 
    of India or his nominee; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  any other officer of 
    the Central Government or State Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  any expert in 
    geographical information system; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>  any other person, 
 
whose expertise and 
    knowledge are considered necessary by the Commission to provide assistance 
    to it in addition to the assistance provided by the persons referred to in 
    sub-section (1) and the officers and persons so called upon shall be duty 
    bound to assist the Commission.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Secretary to the Election Commission shall be the ex officio 
    Secretary of the Commission and shall discharge his functions with the 
    assistance of the employees of the Election Commission under the supervision 
    of the Chairperson of the Commission.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Casual vacancies.—If 
    the office of the Chairperson or of a member or of an associate member falls 
    vacant owing to his death or resignation, it shall be filled as soon as may 
    be practicable by the Central Government or the Speaker concerned under and 
    in accordance with the provisions of section 3 or, as the case may be, of 
    section 5.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Procedure and powers of the Commission.—
<section><number>1</number> The Commission shall determine its own procedure 
    and shall, in the performance of its functions, have all the powers of a 
    civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while 
    trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  summoning and 
    enforcing the attendance of witnesses; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  requiring the 
    production of any document; and 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  requisitioning any 
    public record from any court or office. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission shall have power to require any person to furnish any information 
    on such points or matters as in the opinion of the Commission may be useful 
    for, or relevant to, any matter under the consideration of the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Commission may authorise any of its members to exercise any of the powers 
    conferred on it by clauses (a) to (c) of sub-section (1) and sub-section 
    (2), and any order made or act done in exercise of any of those powers by 
    the member authorised by the Commission in that behalf shall be deemed to be 
    the order or act, as the case may be, of the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If 
    there is a difference of opinion among the members, the opinion of the 
    majority shall prevail, and acts and orders of the Commission shall be 
    expressed in terms of the views of the majority.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    Commission as well as any group of associate members shall have power to act 
    notwithstanding the temporary absence of a member or associate member or the 
    existence of a vacancy in the Commission or in that or any other group of 
    associate members; and no act or proceeding of the Commission or of any 
    group of associate members shall be invalid or called in question on the 
    ground merely of such temporary absence or of the existence of such vacancy.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Commission shall be deemed to be a civil court for the purposes of sections 
    345 and 346 of the Code of Criminal Procedure,  1973 (2 of 1974).
 

    Explanation.—For 
    the purposes of enforcing the attendance of witnesses, the local limits of 
    the jurisdiction of the Commission shall be the limits of the territory of 
    India.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Readjustment of number of seats.—The Commission shall, having regard to the provisions of 
    articles 81, 170, 330 and 332 and also, in relation to the Union 
    territories, except National Capital Territory of Delhi, sections 3 and 39 
    of the Government of Union Territories Act, 1963 (20 of 1963) and in 
    relation to the National Capital Territory of Delhi sub-clause (b) of clause 
    (2) of article 239AA, by order, determine,—
 <section>
<number>a</number>  on the basis of the 
    census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 1971 and 
    subject to the provisions of section 4, the number of seats in the House of 
    the People to be allocated to each State and determine on the basis of the 
    census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[2001] 
    the number of seats, if any, to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and for 
    the Scheduled Tribes of the State; and 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>  on the basis of the 
    census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year 1971 and 
    subject to the provisions of section 4, the total number of seats to be 
    assigned to the Legislative Assembly of each State and determine on he basis 
    of the census figures as ascertained at the census held in the year
    1[2001] the number 
    seats, if any, to be reserved for the Scheduled Castes and for the Scheduled 
    Tribes of the State: 
 
Provided 
    that the total number of seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of any 
    State under clause (b) shall be an integral multiple of the number of seats 
    in the House of the People allocated to that State under clause (a).
  
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Delimitation of constituencies.—
<section><number>1</number> The Commission shall, in the manner herein provided, then 
    distribute the seats in the House of the People allocated to each State and 
    the seats assigned to the Legislative Assembly of each State as readjusted 
    on the basis of 1971 census to single-member territorial constituencies and 
    delimit them on the basis of the census figures as ascertained, at the 
    census held in the year 1[2001], 
    having regard to the provisions of the Constitution,  the provisions of the 
    Acts specified in section 8 and also to the following provisions, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  all constituencies 
    shall, as far as practicable, be geographically compact areas, and in 
    delimiting them regard shall be had to physical features, existing 
    boundaries of administrative units, facilities of communication and public 
    convenience; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  every assembly 
    constituency shall be so delimited as to fall wholly within one 
    parliamentary constituency; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  constituencies in 
    which seats are reserved for the Scheduled Castes shall be distributed in 
    different parts of the State and located, as far as practicable, in those 
    areas where the proportion of their population to the total is comparatively 
    large; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  constituencies in 
    which seats are reserved for the Scheduled Tribes shall, as far as 
    practicable, be located in areas where the proportion of their population to 
    the total is the largest. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission shall—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  publish its proposals 
    for the delimitation of constituencies, together with the dissenting 
    proposals, if any, of any associate member who desires publication thereof, 
    in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazettes of all the States 
    concerned and also in such other manner as it thinks fit;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  specify a date on or 
    after which the proposals shall be further considered by it; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>  consider all 
    objections and suggestions which may have been received by it before the 
    date so specified, and for the purpose of such consideration, hold one or 
    more public sittings at such place or places in each State as it thinks fit; 
    and  

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>  thereafter by one or 
    more orders determine—
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  the delimitation of 
    parliamentary constituencies, and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>  the delimitation of 
    assembly constituencies, 
 
of each State.
  
  





 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Publication of orders and their date of operation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commission shall cause each of its orders made under section 8 or 
    section 9 to be published in the Gazette of India and in the Official 
    Gazettes of the States concerned and simultaneously cause such orders to be 
    published at last in two vernacular newspapers and publicize on radio, 
    television and other possible media available to the public and after such 
    publication in the Official Gazettes of the States Concerned, every District 
    Election Officer shall cause to be affixed, the Gazette version of such 
    orders relating to the area under his jurisdiction, on a conspicuous part of 
    his office for public notice. —(1) 
    The Commission shall cause each of its orders made under section 8 or 
    section 9 to be published in the Gazette of India and in the Official 
    Gazettes of the States concerned and simultaneously cause such orders to be 
    published at last in two vernacular newspapers and publicize on radio, 
    television and other possible media available to the public and after such 
    publication in the Official Gazettes of the States Concerned, every District 
    Election Officer shall cause to be affixed, the Gazette version of such 
    orders relating to the area under his jurisdiction, on a conspicuous part of 
    his office for public notice." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon 
    publication in the Gazette of India, every such order shall have the force 
    of law and shall not be called in question in any court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> As 
    soon as may be after such publication, every such order shall be laid before 
    the House of the People and the Legislative Assemblies of the States 
    concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (5), the readjustment of 
    representation of the several territorial constituencies in the House of the 
    People or in the Legislative Assembly of a State and the delimitation of 
    those constituencies provided for in any such order shall apply in relation 
    to every election to the House or to the Assembly, as the case may be, held 
    after the publication in the Gazette of India of that order and shall so 
    apply in supersession of the provisions relating to such representation and 
    delimitation contained in any other law for the time being in force or any 
    order or notification issued under such law in so far as such representation 
    and delimitation are inconsistent with the provision of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Nothing in this section shall affect the representation in the House of the 
    People or in the Legislative Assembly of a State until the dissolution of 
    the House or of the Assembly, as the case may be, existing on the date of 
    publication in the Gazette of India of the final order or orders of the 
    Commission relating to the delimitation of parliamentary constituencies or, 
    as the case may be, of the assembly constituencies of that State and any 
    bye-election to fill any vacancy in such House or in any such Assembly shall 
    be held on the basis of the provisions of the laws and orders superseded by 
    sub-section (4) as if the said provisions had not been superseded.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Commission shall endeavour to complete and publish each of its orders 
    referred to in sub-section (1) in the manner provided in that sub-section, 
    within two years of the constitution of the Commission under section 3.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Power to maintain delimitation orders up-to-date.—
<section><number>1</number> The Election Commission may, from time to time, 
    by notification in the Gazette of India and in the Official Gazette of the 
    State concerned—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>  correct any printing 
    mistake in any of the orders made by the Commission under section 9 or any 
    error arising therein from an inadvertent slip or omission; and 

 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>  where the boundaries 
    or name of any district or any territorial division mentioned in any of the 
    said orders are or is altered, make such amendments as appear to it to be 
    necessary or expedient for bringing the orders up-to-date, so however, that 
    the boundaries or areas or extent of any constituency shall not be changed 
    by any such notification. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    notification under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    issued, before the House of the People and the Legislative Assembly of the 
    State concerned.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Repeal.—The 
    Delimitation Act, 1972 (76 of 1972) is hereby repealed.

 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>  Subs. by Act 3 of 
    2004, sec. 2, for Explanation (w.e.f. 31-10-2003). Explnation, 
    before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    2004, sec. 3, for “1991” (w.e.f. 31-10-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>   Subs. by Act 3 of 
    2004, sec. 4, for “1991” (w.e.f. 31-10-2003).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number>             
    Subs. by Act 3 of 2004, sec. 5, for “1991” (w.e.f. 31-10-2003).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>