<act><tid>358252</tid>
<title>THE DADRA AND NAGAR HAVELI ACT, <year>1961</year></title>

ACT NO. 35 OF <year>1961</year>
[ 2nd September, <year>1961</year>.]

An Act to make provision for the representation of the Union territory 
of Dadra and Nagar Haveli in Parliament and for the adminis- 
tration of that Union territory and for matters connected 
therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twelfth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:--





<article><tid>445254</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1953792</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Dadra and Nagar Haveli Act, <year>1961</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>63683</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of the Union territory of Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli.

</section>

<section><tid>619010</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 11th day of 
August, <year>1961</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1993928</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1225294</tid>
<number>a</number>" Administrator" means the Administrator of the Union 
territory of Dadra and Nagar Haveli appointed by the 
President under article 239 of the Constitution;

</section>

<section><tid>431654</tid>
<number>b</number>" appointed day" means the eleventh day of August, <year>1961</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>976726</tid>
<number>c</number>" Dadra and Nagar Haveli" means the Union territory of 
Dadra and Nagar Haveli;

</section>

<section><tid>277943</tid>
<number>d</number>" Varishta Panchayat" means the Varishta Panchayat as in 
existence immediately before the appointed day <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>56523</tid>
<number> 3</number> Representation in the House of the People.
<section><tid>72817</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be  
allotted one seat to the Union territory of Dadra and Nagar Haveli in 
the House of the People.

</section>

<section><tid>1765632</tid>
<number>2</number>In the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>),--

<subsection><tid>1224</tid>
<number>a</number>in section 4, in sub- section (1), after the words" to 
the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi Islands". the words 
", to Dadra and Nagar Haveli" shall be inserted:

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>114803</tid>
<number>b</number>in the First Schedule,--

<subsubsection><tid>1572947</tid>
<number>i</number>after entry 21, the following entry shall 
be inserted, namely:--
" 22. Dadra and Nagar Haveli.......... 1";


</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>693794</tid>
<number>ii</number>entries 22 and 23 shall be re- numbered 
as entries 23 and 24 respectively.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>664</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" and as reconstituted from time to time in accordance 
with law" were inserted at the end of cl. (d) of section 2, by Reg. 3 
of <year>1965</year>, s. 69 (w. e. f. 2- 10- <year>1965</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>473272</tid>
<number>3</number>In the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>), 
in section 4, after the words" to the Laccadive, Minicoy and Amindivi 
Islands", the words", to Dadra and Nagar Haveli" shall be inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1314609</tid>
<number> 4</number> Varishta Panchayat.
<section><tid>1487134</tid>
<number>1</number>Until other provision is made by law,  
as from the commencement of this Act the Varishta Panchayat shall have 
the right to discuss and make recommendations to the Administrator 
on,--

<subsection><tid>1171808</tid>
<number>a</number>matters of administration involving general policy and 
schemes of development;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1943802</tid>
<number>b</number>any other matter referred to it by the Administrator.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1954153</tid>
<number>2</number>The functions of the Varishta Panchayat referred to in this 
section will be advisory only but due regard shall be given to such 
advice by the Administrator in reaching decisions on the matter in 
relation to which the advice is given.

</section>

<section><tid>1353276</tid>
<number>3</number>No act or proceeding of the Varishta Panchayat shall be 
invalid by reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its 
members or any defect in the constitution thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>231970</tid>
<number>4</number>Every member of the Varishta Panchayat shall before entering 
upon his duties under this Act make and subscribe before the 
Administrator an oath or affirmation in the following form, namely:--
" I, A. B., a member of the Varishta Panchayat of the Union 
territory of Dadra and Nagar Haveli, do swear in the name of God 
solemnly affirm that I will bear true faith and allegiance to the 
Constitution of India as by law established and that I will faithfully 
discharge the duty upon which I am about to enter.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1692174</tid>
<number>5</number>Other functionaries. Without prejudice to the powers of the 
Central Government to appoint from time to time such officers and 
authorities as may be necessary for the administration of Dadra and 
Nagar Haveli, all judges, magistrates and other officers and 
authorities who immediately before the appointed day were exercising 
lawful functions in Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli or any part thereof 
shall, until other provision is made by law, continue to exercise in 
connection with the administration of Dadra and Nagar Haveli their 
respective functions in the same manner and to the same extent as 
before the appointed day.


</article>



<article><tid>1615663</tid>
<number>6</number>Property and assets. It is hereby declared that all property 
and assets which immediately before the appointed day vested in the 
Varishta Panchayat or the Administrator of Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli 
shall, as from that day, west in the Union.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>665</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>80097</tid>
<number>7</number>Rights an obligations. All rights, liabilities and obligations 
of the Varishta Panchayat or the Administrator of Free Dadra and Nagar 
Haveli in relation to Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli shall, as from the 
appointed day, be the rights, liabilities and obligations of the 
Central Government.


</article>



<article><tid>550467</tid>
<number>8</number>Continuance of existing laws. Save as otherwise provided in 
this Act all laws in force in Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli immediately 
before the appointed day shall continue to be in force until repealed 
or amended by Parliament or other competent authority.


</article>



<article><tid>821555</tid>
<number>9</number>Continuance of existing taxes. All taxes, duties, cesses or 
fees which, immediately before the appointed day, were being lawfully 
levied in Free Dadra and Nagar Haveli or any part thereof shall 
continue to be levied and to be applied to the same purposes, until 
other provision is made by Parliament or other competent authority.


</article>



<article><tid>184645</tid>
<number>10</number>Power to extend enactments to Dadra and Nagar Haveli. The 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
extend with such restrictions or modifications as it thinks fit, to 
Dadra and Nagar Haveli any enactment which is in force in a State at 
the date of the notification.


</article>



<article><tid>565357</tid>
<number>11</number>Extension of the jurisdiction of Bombay High Court to Dadra 
and Nagar Haveli. As from such date <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, 
by notification in the Official Gazette, specify the jurisdiction of 
the High Court at Bombay shall extend to Dadra and Nagar Haveli.


</article>



<article><tid>180655</tid>
<number>12</number>Powers of courts and other authorities for purposes of 
facilitating the application of laws. For the purpose of facilitating 
the application of any law in Dadra and Nagar Haveli, any court or 
other authority may construe any such law with such alterations not 
affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper to adapt it to 
the matter before the court or other authority.


</article>



<article><tid>504093</tid>
<number> 13</number> Power to remove difficulties.
<section><tid>198956</tid>
<number>1</number>If any difficulty arises in  
giving effect to the provisions of this Act or in connection with the 
administration of Dadra and Nagar Haveli, the Central Government may, 
by order, make such further provision as appears to it to be necessary 
or expedient for removing the difficulty.

</section>

<section><tid>1348529</tid>
<number>2</number>Any order under sub- section (1) may be made so as to be 
retrospective to any date not earlier than the appointed day.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>548141</tid>
<number> 14</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>953766</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>666</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1- 7- <year>1965</year>: Vide Notifn No. S. O. <year>1957</year> (E), dt. 15- 6- <year>1965</year>, Gaz, of 
India, Pt. II, sec. 3 (ii), p. 579.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>1023242</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1868288</tid>
<number>a</number>the manner in which casual vacancies in the Varishta 
Panchayat may be filled;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>799128</tid>
<number>b</number>the meetings of the Varishta Panchayat, the conduct of 
business and the procedure to be followed at such 
meetings;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>863808</tid>
<number>c</number>any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>217198</tid>
<number>3</number>Every rule made under this Act shall be laid as soon as may 
be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid"] both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>667</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch, (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>