<act><tid>359185</tid>
<title>THE STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURESACT, <year>1976</year></title>

ACT NO. 60 OF <year>1976</year>
[ 8th April, <year>1976</year>.]

An Act to establish standards of weights and measures, to regulate 
inter- State trade or commerce in weights, measures and other goods 
which are sold or distributed by weight, measure or number, and to 
provide for matters connected therewith or incidental thereto.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- seventh Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-

PART

PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO EVERY PART

PART I

PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO EVERY PART





<article><tid>1967895</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1223415</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Standards of Weights and Measures Act, <year>1976</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1095041</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.

</section>

<section><tid>363605</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central 
Government may, by notification, appoint, and different dates may be 
appointed for different-

<subsection><tid>1130227</tid>
<number>a</number>provisions of this Act,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>16645</tid>
<number>b</number>areas,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>355</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 7. <year>1987</year>: Vide Notification No. G. S. R. 617 (E), dated 1. 7. <year>1987</year> 
 (in respect of sections 4 to 27 (both inclusive), 30, clause (a) and  
 (c) of s. 31, 32 to 38 (both inclusive), 40 to 47 (both inclusive), 
sub- sections (1) and (3) of section 48, 49 to 53 (both inclusive), 
55 to 62 (both inclusive), 64, 65, 68, 75, 79, to 82 (both inclusive), 
  84 and 85.).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Sections 4 to 27, 30, 51, and 53 of the Act came into force 
in the State of Sikkim on 4. 4. <year>1985</year> vide Notifn. No. G. S. R. 344 (E), 
dated 4. 4. <year>1985</year>, Gaz. of India, Exty., Pt. II sec. 3 (i).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number> 1. 4. <year>1980</year>: Vide Notifn. No. G. S. R. 193 (E), dt. 1. 4. <year>1980</year>, (in  
  respect of Sections 76 and 77).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number> 26. 9. <year>1977</year>: Vide Notifn. No. G. S. R. 620 (E), dt. 26. 9. <year>1977</year> (in  
respect of ss. 1, 2, 3, 28, 29, 31 (b), 39, 48 (2), 54, 63, 67, 59 to 
74, 78 and 83.



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>356</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1471180</tid>
<number>c</number>classes of undertakings,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>500876</tid>
<number>d</number>classes of goods,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1156931</tid>
<number>e</number>classes of weights and measures, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>995945</tid>
<number>f</number>classes of users of weights and measures,
and any reference in any such provision to the commencement of this 
Act shall be construed as a reference to the coming into force of that 
provision in such areas, or in respect of such classes of 
undertakings, goods, weights and measures or users of weights and 
measures in relation to which this Act has been brought into force:

Provided that the provisions of this Act (including the standards  
  established by or under this Act) shall come into force in the State 
of Sikkim on such date, not being later than five years from the 
passing of this Act, as the Central Government may, by notification, 
appoint, and different dates may be appointed for different provisions 
of this Act or for different art- as or for different classes of 
undertakings or for different classes of goods, or for different 
classes of weights and measures or for different classes of users of 
weights and measures.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>249575</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>254534</tid>
<number>a</number>" calibration" means all the operations which are 
necessary for the purpose of determining the values of the 
errors of a weight or measure and, if necessary, to determine 
the other metrological properties of such weight or measure, 
and includes the actual fixing of the positions of the gauge- 
marks or scale- marks of a weight or measure or in some cases, 
of certain principal marks only, in relation to the 
corresponding values of the quantity to be measured.
Explanation.- Calibration may also be carried out with a view 
to permitting the use of a weight or measure as a standard;


</section>

<section><tid>448116</tid>
<number>b</number>" commodity in packaged form" means commodity packaged, 
whether in any bottle, tin, wrapper or otherwise, in units 
suitable for sale, whether wholesale or retail;

</section>

<section><tid>1153112</tid>
<number>c</number>" dealer", in relation to any weight or measure, means a 
person who, or a firm or a Hindu undivided family which, 
carries on, directly or otherwise, the business of buying, 
selling, supplying or distributing any such weight or measure 
of whether for cash. or for deferred payment or for 
commission, remuneration or other valuable consideration, and 
includes-

<subsection><tid>1711677</tid>
<number>i</number>a commission agent who carries on such business on 
behalf of any principal,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1876618</tid>
<number>ii</number>an importer who sells, supplies, distributes or 
otherwise delivers any weight or measure to any user, 
manufacturer, repairer, consumer or any other person,
but does not include a manufacturer who sells, supplies, 
distributes or otherwise delivers any weight or measure to 
' any person or category of persons referred to in this 
clause.

Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that a manufacturer, who sells, supplies, distributes or 
otherwise delivers any weight or measure to any person other 
than a dealer, shall be deemed to, be a dealer;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>301141</tid>
<number>d</number>" Director" means the Director of Legal Metrology 
appointed under section 28;

</section>

<section><tid>1098912</tid>
<number>e</number>" export" with its grammatical variations and cognate 
expressions, means taking out of India to a place outside 
India;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>357</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1862487</tid>
<number>f</number>" false package" means any package which does not conform 
to the provisions of this Act or any rule or order made 
thereunder in relation to such package;

</section>

<section><tid>1721342</tid>
<number>g</number>" false weight or measure" means any weight or measure 
which does not conform to the standards established by or 
under this Act in relation to that weight or measure;

</section>

<section><tid>973205</tid>
<number>h</number>" General. Conference on Weights and Measures" means 
the Conference General des Poids et Mesures established under 
the Convention du Metre:

</section>

<section><tid>222070</tid>
<number>i</number>" import", with its grammatical variations and cognate 
pressions, means bringing into India from a place outside 
India.

<subsection><tid>1228436</tid>
<number>J</number>" International Bureau of Weights and Measures" means 
Bureau International des Poids et Mesures, established under 
Convention du Metre, at Sevres in France;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>955949</tid>
<number>k</number>" International Organisation of Legal Metrology" means 
the Organisation Internationale de Metrologie Legale 
established under the Convention Instituant Une Organisation 
Internationale de MetroIogie Legale;

</section>

<section><tid>208093</tid>
<number>l</number>" international prototype of the kilogram" means the 
prototype sanctioned by the First General Conference on 
Weights and Measures held in Paris in <year>1889</year>, and deposited at 
the International Bureau of Weights and Measures;

</section>

<section><tid>1851839</tid>
<number>m</number>" inter- State trade or commerce", in relation to any 
weight or measure or other goods which are bought, sold, 
supplied, distributed or delivered by weight, measure or 
number, means the purchase, sale, supply, distribution or 
delivery which-

<subsection><tid>1075474</tid>
<number>i</number>occasions the movement of such weight, measure or 
other goods from one State to another, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>218731</tid>
<number>ii</number>is effected by a transfer of documents of title to 
such weight, measure or other goods during its movement 
from one State to another.
Explanation I.- Where any such weight or measure is, or other 
goods are, delivered to a carrier or other bailee for 
transmission, the movement of such weight, measure or other 
goods shall, for the purposes of sub- clause (ii), be deemed 
to commence at the time of such delivery and terminate at the 
time when delivery is taken from such carrier or bailee.

Explanation II.- Where the movement of any such weight, mea- 
sure or other goods commences and terminates in the same 
State, it shall not be deemed to be a movement of such 
weight, measure or other goods from one State to another 
merely by reason of the fact that In the course of such 
movement it passes through the territory of any other State;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1632972</tid>
<number>n</number>" label" means any written, marked, stamped, printed, or 
graphic matter affixed to, or appearing upon, any 
commodity or package containing any commodity;

</section>

<section><tid>475786</tid>
<number>o</number>" manufacturer", in relation to any weight or measure, 
means person who, or a firm or a Hindu undivided family 
which,-

<subsection><tid>692205</tid>
<number>i</number>makes or manufactures such weight or measure,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1818648</tid>
<number>ii</number>makes or manufactures one or more parts, and 
acquires the other parts, of such weight or measure and, 
after assembling those parts, claims the end product to 
be a weight or measure manufactured by himself or 
itself, as the case may be,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>358</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1145742</tid>
<number>iii</number>does not make or manufacture any part of such 
weight or measure but assembles parts thereof made or 
manufactured by others and claims the end product to be 
a weight or measure manufactured by himself or itself, 
as the case may be,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>405567</tid>
<number>iv</number>puts, or causes to be put, his own mark on any 
complete weight or measure made or manufactured by any 
other person and claims such product to be a weight or 
measure made or manufactured by himself or itself, as 
the case may be.
Explanation.- Where any manufacturer despatches any weight or 
measure or any part thereof to any branch office maintained 
by or it, such branch office shall not be, deemed to be a 
manufacturer evenb though the parts so despatched to it are 
assembled at such ranch office;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>980844</tid>
<number>p</number>" notification" means a notification published in the 
Official Gazette;

</section>

<section><tid>1571607</tid>
<number>q</number>" Person" includes--

<subsection><tid>462963</tid>
<number>i</number>every department or office,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1723402</tid>
<number>ii</number>every Organisation established or constituted by 
Government,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>332742</tid>
<number>iii</number>every local authority within the territory of 
India,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>312209</tid>
<number>iv</number>every co- operative society,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>233493</tid>
<number>v</number>every other society registered under the Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1860</year>; (21 of <year>1860</year>.)

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1988416</tid>
<number>r</number>" premises" includes-

<subsection><tid>790551</tid>
<number>i</number>a place where any business, industry, production 
or trade is carried on by a person, whether by himself 
or through an agent, by whatever name called,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>509826</tid>
<number>ii</number>a warehouse, godown or other place where any 
weight, measure or other goods are stored or exhibited,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1362179</tid>
<number>iii</number>a place where any books of account or other 
documents pertaining to any trade or 
transaction are 
kept,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1025394</tid>
<number>iv</number>a dwelling house, if any part thereof is used for 
the purpose of carrying on any business, industry, 
production or trade.
Explanation.-- Place" includes a vehicle or vessel or any 
other mobile device, with the help of which any trade or 
business is carried on, and also includes any measuring 
instrument mounted on a vehicle, vessel or other mobile 
device;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1102399</tid>
<number>s</number>" prescribed" means, prescribed by rules made under this 
Act and" prescribed authority" means such authority as may be 
specified by such rules;

</section>

<section><tid>910423</tid>
<number>t</number>" reference standard" means the set of standard weight o 
measure which is made or manufactured by or on behalf of the 
Central Government for the verification of any secondary 
standard;

</section>

<section><tid>1891381</tid>
<number>u</number>" repairer" includes a person who adjusts, cleans, 
lubricate or paints any weight or measure or renders any 
other service to such weight or measure to ensure that such 
weight or. measure con. forms to the standards established by 
or under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>236554</tid>
<number>v</number>" sale", with its grammatical variations and cognate 
expressions, means transfer of property in any weight, 
measure or other

<pagefootnote><pagenum>359</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

goods by one person to another for cash or for deferred 
payment or for any Other valuable consideration, and includes 
a transfer of any weight, measure or other goods on the hire- 
purchase system or any other system of payment by 
instalments, but does not include a mortgage or hypothecation 
of, or a charge or pledge on, such weight, measure or other 
goods;


</section>

<section><tid>760706</tid>
<number>w</number>" seal" means a device or process by which a stamp is 
made, and includes any wire or other accessory which is used 
for ensuring the integrity of any stamp;

</section>

<section><tid>748839</tid>
<number>x</number>" secondary standard" means the set of standard weight 
or measure which is made or manufactured by or on behalf of 
the Central or State Government for the verification of any 
work standard;

</section>

<section><tid>2670</tid>
<number>y</number>" stamp" means a mark, which is made on, or in relation 
to, any weight or measure with a view to-

<subsection><tid>1167540</tid>
<number>i</number>certifying that such weight or measure conforms to 
the standard specified by or under this Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>477596</tid>
<number>ii</number>indicating that any mark which was previously made 
thereon certifying that such weight or measure conforms 
to the standards specified by or under this Act, has 
been obliterated.
Explanation.- A stamp may be made by impressing, casting, en- 
graving, etching, branding or any other process;


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>205948</tid>
<number>z</number>" transaction" means-

<subsection><tid>1727906</tid>
<number>i</number>any contract, whether for sale, purchase, exchange 
or any other purpose, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>255230</tid>
<number>ii</number>any assessment of royalty, toll, duty or other 
dues, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1080462</tid>
<number>iii</number>the assessment of any work done, wages due or 
services rendered;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1593470</tid>
<number>za</number>" unverified weight or measure" means a weight or measure 
which, being required to be verified and stamped under this 
Act, has not been so verified and stamped;

</section>

<section><tid>15561</tid>
<number>zb</number>" verification", with its grammatical variations and 
cognate expressions, includes, in relation to any weight or 
measure, the process of comparing, checking, testing or 
adjusting such weight or measure with a view to ensuring that 
such weight or measure conforms to the standards established 
by or under this Act, and also includes re- verification and 
calibration;

</section>

<section><tid>755747</tid>
<number>zc</number>" weighing or measuring instrument" means any object, 
instrument, apparatus or device, or any combination thereof, 
which is, or is intended to be, used, exclusively or 
additionally, for the purpose of making any weighment or 
measurement, and includes any appliance, accessory or part 
associated with any such object, instrument, apparatus or 
device;

</section>

<section><tid>1382532</tid>
<number>zd</number>" weight or measure" means a weight or measure specified 
by or under this Act, and includes a weighing or measuring 
instrument;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>360</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1818407</tid>
<number>ze</number>" working standard" means the set of standard weight or 
measure which is made or manufactured by or on behalf of 
Government for the verification of any standard weight or 
measure, other than a national prototype or national 
reference or secondary standard.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1872507</tid>
<number>3</number>Provisions of this Act to override the provisions of any other 
law. The provisions of this Act shall have effect, notwithstanding 
anything inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment other than 
this Act or in any instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment 
other than this Act.
PART

ESTABLISHMENT OF STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES

PART II

ESTABLISHMENT OF STANDARDS OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES

CHAP

Standard units

CHAPTER I

Standard units



</article>



<article><tid>1907210</tid>
<number> 4</number> Units of weight or measure to be based on metric system.
<section><tid>810390</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every unit of weight or measure shall be based on the units of the 
metric system.

</section>

<section><tid>836703</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purposes of sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>195284</tid>
<number>a</number>the international system of units as recommended by the 
General Conference on Weights and Measures, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>502964</tid>
<number>b</number>such additional units as may be recommended by the 
International Organisation of Legal Metrology,
shall be the units of the metric system.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1024299</tid>
<number> 5</number> Base unit of length.
<section><tid>982677</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of length shall be the  
metre.

</section>

<section><tid>1635080</tid>
<number>2</number>The" metre" is the length equal to 1650 763. 73 wave lengths 
in vacuum of the radiation corresponding to the transition between the 
levels 2p- 10 and 5d- 5 of the krypton- 86 atom.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>880502</tid>
<number> 6</number> Base unit of mass.
<section><tid>1348780</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of mass shall be the  
kilogram.

</section>

<section><tid>1324992</tid>
<number>2</number>The" kilogram" is the unit of mass; it is equal to the mass 
of the international prototype of the kilogram.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1905331</tid>
<number> 7</number> Base unit of time.
<section><tid>686322</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of time shall be the  
second.

</section>

<section><tid>1867534</tid>
<number>2</number>The" second" is the duration of 9 192 631 770 periods of the 
radiation corresponding to the transition between the two hyperfine 
levels of the ground state of the caesium- 133 atom.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>293411</tid>
<number> 8</number> Base unit of electric current.
<section><tid>1650456</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of electric  
current shall be the ampere.

</section>

<section><tid>9005</tid>
<number>2</number>The" ampere" is that constant current which if maintained in 
two, straight parallel conductors of infinite length, of negligible 
circular cross- section, and placed one metre apart in vacuum, would 
produce between these conductors a force equal to 2 x 10' newton per 
metre of length.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1645363</tid>
<number> 9</number> Base unit of thermodynamic temperature.
<section><tid>172528</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of  
thermodynamic temperature shall be the kelvin.

</section>

<section><tid>1213785</tid>
<number>2</number>The" kelvin" is the fraction 1 273- 16 of the thermodynamic 
temperature of the triple point of water.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>361</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>535312</tid>
<number>3</number>The kelvin shall also be used for expressing the interval or 
difference of temperature.

</section>

<section><tid>1945372</tid>
<number>4</number>Zero degree Celsius corresponds to 273. 15 kelvin.

</section>

<section><tid>1110935</tid>
<number>5</number>The degree Celsius may also be used for expressing the 
interval or difference of temperature, unit degree Celsius being equal 
to unit kelvin.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1728775</tid>
<number> 10</number> Base unit of luminous intensity.
<section><tid>1065409</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of  
luminous intensity shall be the candela.

</section>

<section><tid>303428</tid>
<number>2</number>The" candela" is the luminous intensity, in the 
perpendicular direction, of a surface of 1 600, 000 square metre of a 
black body at the temperature of freezing platinum under a pressure of 
 101 325 newtons per square metre.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1398319</tid>
<number> 11</number> Base unit of amount of substance.
<section><tid>292705</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of amount  
of substance shall be the mole.

</section>

<section><tid>1814860</tid>
<number>2</number>The" mole is the amount of substance of a system which 
contains as many elementary entities as there are atoms in 0. 012 
kilogram of carbon 12.

</section>

<section><tid>1666300</tid>
<number>3</number>When the mole is used, the elementary entities shall 
invariably be' specified and may be atoms, molecules, ions, electrons, 
other particle, or specified groups of such particles.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1278682</tid>
<number> 12</number> Supplementary, derived, special and other units of weight or 
measure their symbols, definitions, etc.
<section><tid>202967</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government  
may, by rules made in this behalf, specify, in relation to the base 
units of weight or measure, such supplementary, derived, or other 
units or standard symbols or definitions as the General Conference on 
Weights and Measures or the International Organisation of Legal 
Metrology may recommend.
Explanation.-" Derived unit" means a unit which is derived from 
the base, or supplementary, units, or both.


</section>

<section><tid>1458330</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government may, by rules made in this behalf, 
specify, such multiples and sub- multiples of, and physical constants, 
and ratios or coefficients in relation to, units of weight or measure 
as the General Conference on Weights and Measures or the International 
Organisation of Legal Metrology may recommend.

</section>

<section><tid>911317</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government may, by notification, declare, for 
such period as it may consider necessary such special units of weight 
or measure as the General Conference on Weights and Measures or the 
International Organisation of Legal Metrology may recommend.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>738898</tid>
<number> 13</number> Base unit of numeration.
<section><tid>907101</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of numeration  
shall be the unit of the International form of Indian numerals.

</section>

<section><tid>162187</tid>
<number>2</number>Every numeration shall be made in accordance with the 
decimal system.

</section>

<section><tid>1851022</tid>
<number>3</number>The decimal multiples and sub- multiples of the numerals 
shall be of such denominations and be written in such manner as the 
Central
 115 Law-- 46


<pagefootnote><pagenum>362</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Government may, after previous publication, specify by rules made in 
this behalf:

Provided that no such rule shall be made before the expiry of six 
months from the date on which the draft of the proposed rules was 
first published in the Official Gazette.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>334594</tid>
<number> 14</number> Standard unit of weight or measure.
<section><tid>434895</tid>
<number>1</number>The base unit of mass  
specified in section 6 and base' units of measures specified in 
section 5 and sections 7 to 11 (both inclusive) and the supplementary 
and other units specified by rules made under section 12, shall be the 
standard units of weight or measure, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1058743</tid>
<number>2</number>The units of numeration specified by or under section 13 
shall be the standard units of numeration.
CHAP

Physical representation of standard units

CHAPTER II

Physical representation of standard units




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>890398</tid>
<number> 15</number> National prototypes.
<section><tid>1486134</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of deriving the  
value of the kilogram, the Central Government shall cause to be 
prepared a national prototype of the kilogram and shall cause its 
accuracy to be certified by the International Bureau of Weights and 
Measures in terms of the international prototype of the kilogram and 
shall deposit the same in such custody and at such place as that 
Government may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>572730</tid>
<number>2</number>For tile purpose of deriving the value of the metre, the 
Central Government may cause to be prepared a national prototype of 
the metre and, where such prototype is caused to be made, shall also 
cause its accuracy to be certified by the International Bureau of 
Weights and Measures and deposit the same in such custody and at such 
place as that Government may think fit.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1337801</tid>
<number> 16</number> National standards.
<section><tid>1229685</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purpose of deriving the  
value of the base units, other than the base unit of mass, the Central 
Government shall' cause to be prepared such objects or equipments, or 
both, as may be necessary for the purpose and shall cause the accuracy 
of such objects or equipments, or both, to, be certified by the 
International Bureau of Weights and Measures at such periodical 
intervals as may be prescribed, and, shall, after such certification, 
deposit such objects or equipments, or' both, in such custody and at 
such place as that Government may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1190507</tid>
<number>2</number>For the purpose of deriving the value of the supplementary 
and other units specified under section 12, the Central Government 
shall cause to be prepared such objects or equipments, or both as may 
be necessary for the purpose and shall cause the accuracy of such 
objects or equipments, or both, to be certified at such periodical 
intervals and by, such authority as may be prescribed, and, shall 
after certification, deposit such objects or equipments, or both, in 
such custody and at such place as that Government may think fit,



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>296786</tid>
<number>17</number>National prototype and national standard how to be kept. 
Every national prototype specified in section 15 and every object or 
equipment, or both, referred to in section 16, shall be kept in such 
manner and under such conditions as may be prescribed.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>363</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1556067</tid>
<number> 18</number> Reference, secondary and working standards.
<section><tid>642381</tid>
<number>1</number>Every- 

<subsection><tid>1348098</tid>
<number>a</number>reference Standard,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>813480</tid>
<number>b</number>secondary standard, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>966866</tid>
<number>c</number>working standard,
shall conform to the standards established by or under this Act and be 
verified and authenticated at such periodical intervals and in such 
manner as may be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>561932</tid>
<number>2</number>Every reference standard, every secondary standard and every 
working standard shall be kept in such manner and under such condi- 
tions as may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>581273</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power of Central Government to prescribe physical 
characteristics, etc., of weights and measures.
<section><tid>1024963</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall, in relation to any weight or measure, prescribe the 
physical characteristics, configuration, constructional details, 
materials, equipment, performance, tolerances, methods or procedures 
of tests in accordance with the recommendations made by the 
International Organisation of Legal Metrology:
Provided that where no such recommendation has been made, the 
Central Government shall prescribe such physical characteristics, con- 
figuration, constructional details, materials, equipment, performance, 
tolerances, methods or procedures of tests in relation to any weight 
or measure as it may think fit.


</section>

<section><tid>229348</tid>
<number>2</number>Where it is not reasonably practicable to give effect to any 
recommendation made by the International Organisation of Legal Metro- 
logy, the Central Government may make such changes of a minor nature 
in the recommendation of the International Organisation of Legal 
Metrology as may appear to it to be necessary.
CHAP

Standard Weights, and measures

CHAPTER III

Standard Weights, and measures




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1045184</tid>
<number> 20</number> Standard weight or measure.
<section><tid>1281209</tid>
<number>1</number>Any weight or measure which  
conforms to the standard unit of such weight or measure and also 
conforms to such of, the provisions of sections 15 to 19 (both  
  inclusive) as are applicable to it shall be the standard weight or 
measure.

</section>

<section><tid>1000702</tid>
<number>2</number>Any numeral which conforms to the provisions of section 13 
shall be the standard numeral.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>364942</tid>
<number>21</number>Use of non- standard weight or measure prohibited. No weight, 
measure or numeral, other than the standard weight, measure or 
numeral, shall be used as a standard weight, measure or numeral.


</article>



<article><tid>1437960</tid>
<number>22</number>Manufacture of non- standard weight or measure prohibited. No 
weight or measure shall be made or manufactured unless It conforms to 
the standards of weight or measure established by or under this Act:
Provided that the Central Government may permit the malting or 
manufacturing of any weight or measure which does not conform to the 
standards established by or under this Act, if such weight or measure 
is made or manufactured exclusively for the purpose of any scientific 
investigation or research or for export and is made or manufactured 
under such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>364</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>520471</tid>
<number>23</number>Prohibition with regard to inscriptions, etc. No weight, 
measure or other goods shall bear thereon, any inscription or 
indication of weight, measure or number except in accordance with the 
standard unit of such weight, measure or numeration established by or 
under this Act:
Provided that in relation to any weight, measure or other goods 
which are manufactured for scientific investigation or research or for 
export, inscription or indication thereon of any weight, measure or 
number may also be made in accordance with any other system of weight, 
measure or numeration if such inscription or Indication Is demanded by 
the person by whom such scientific investigation or research is to be 
made or by the person to whom the export Is to be made.

CHAP

Custody and verification of standard equipments

CHAPTER IV

Custody and verification of standard equipments



</article>



<article><tid>389616</tid>
<number> 24</number> Supply, etc., of reference standards.
<section><tid>555388</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government shall cause to be prepared, for the purposes of this Act, 
as many sets of reference standards as it may think necessary and 
shall supply to each State Government as many sets of reference 
standards as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>1234935</tid>
<number>2</number>The Central Government shall keep in its custody, for the 
purposes of this Act, such number of reference standards as may be 
necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1922102</tid>
<number>3</number>Every reference standard referred to in sub- section (2) 
shall be kept at such place and in such custody as may be prescribed 
and no such reference standard shall be deemed to be a reference 
standard and shall be used as such unless it has been verified and 
authenticated in accordance with the rules made under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1638511</tid>
<number>25</number>Preparation and custody of secondary or or working standards. 
The Central Government shall cause to be prepared, for the Purposes of 
this Act, as many sets of secondary standard or working standard as it 
may think necessary and shall keep such sets of secondary standard or 
working standard at such place and in such custody as may be 
prescribed.


</article>



<article><tid>1831799</tid>
<number> 26</number> Verification, stamping, etc., of secondary or working 
standards.
<section><tid>1969556</tid>
<number>1</number>Every secondary standard referred to in section 25  
shall be verified with the reference standard by such authority as may 
be prescribed and shall, if found on such verification to conform to 
the standards established by or under this Act, be stamped by that 
authority.

</section>

<section><tid>526042</tid>
<number>2</number>Every working standard referred to in section 25 shall be 
verified with the secondary standard which has been stamped in 
accordance with the provisions of sub- section (1), by such authority 
as may be prescribed and shall, If found on such verification to 
conform to the standards established by or under this Act, be stamped 
by that authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1839552</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any secondary standard or working standard is stamped 
in accordance with the provisions of sub- section (1) or sub- section 
 (2). as the case may be,. a certificate shall' be separately given 
showing the date on which such weight or measure was stamped.

</section>

<section><tid>607277</tid>
<number>4</number>Ever,, secondary standard or working standard which is not 
verified and stamped in accordance with the provisions of sub- section 
 (1) or sub- section (2), as the case may be, shall not be deemed to be 
a secondary standard or working standard and shall not be used as 
such.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>365</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>705550</tid>
<number>27</number>Secondary or working standard which may be stamped. Where the 
Central Government is of opinion that by reason of the size or nature 
of any secondary standard or working standard referred to in section 
25, it is not desirable or practicable to put a stamp thereon, it may 
direct that instead of putting a stamp on such secondary standard or 
working standard, a certificate may be issued to the effect that such 
secondary standard or working standard conforms to the standards 
established by or under this Act and every secondary standard or 
working standard so certified shall be deemed to have been duly 
stamped under this Act on the date on which such certificate was 
issued.
PART

APPOINTMENT AND POWERS OF DIRECTOR AND OTHER STAFF

PART III

APPOINTMENT AND POWERS OF DIRECTOR AND OTHER STAFF



</article>



<article><tid>893548</tid>
<number> 28</number> Appointment of Director and other staff.
<section><tid>81655</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central  
Government may, by notification, appoint a Director of Legal Metrology 
and as many Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Directors and other 
officers and staff as may be necessary for exercising the powers and 
efficiently discharging the duties conferred or imposed on them by or 
under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1814006</tid>
<number>2</number>Every Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Director and 
other officer, appointed under sub- section (1), shall exercise such 
powers, and discharge such functions of the Director as the Central 
Government may, by notification, authorise in this behalf.

</section>

<section><tid>105719</tid>
<number>3</number>The Director may, by general or special order, define the 
local limits within which each Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant 
Director or other officer, appointed under sub- section (1), shall 
exercise his powers and discharge the duties conferred or imposed on 
him by or under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>813917</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, every Additional, 
Joint, Deputy or Assistant Director and every other officer, appointed 
under sub- section (1), shall exercise his powers and discharge the 
duties of his office under the general superintendence, direction and 
control of the Director and shall exercise those powers and discharge 
those duties in the same manner and with the same effect as if they 
had been conferred or imposed on him directly by this Act and not by 
way of authorisation.

</section>

<section><tid>266344</tid>
<number>5</number>The Director and every Additional, Joint, Deputy and 
Assistant Director and every other officer authorised to perform any 
duty by or under this Act shall be deemed to be a public servant 
within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code. (45 of  
  <year>1860</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1166860</tid>
<number>6</number>No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie 
against the Director, Additional, Joint, Deputy or Assistant Director 
or any other officer authorised to perform any duty by or under this 
Act in respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to 
be done under this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>1752862</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Government may, with the consent of the State 
Government and subject to such conditions, limitations and 
restrictions as it nay specify in this behalf, delegate such of the 
powers of the Director under this Act as it may think fit to the 
person for the time being

<pagefootnote><pagenum>366</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

holding the office of the Controller of Legal Metrology, in the State, 
and such Controller may, if he is of opinion that it is necessary or 
expedient in the public interest so to do, delegate such of the powers 
delegated to him as he may think fit to any officer subordinate to 
him, not being an officer below the rank of an Inspector, and where 
any such delegation of powers is made by such Controller, the person 
to whom such powers are delegated shall exercise those powers in the 
same manner and with the same effect as if they had been conferred on 
him directly by this Act and not by way of delegation.


</section>

<section><tid>1732929</tid>
<number>8</number>Where any delegation of powers is made under sub- section 
 (7), the powers so delegated shall be exercised under the general 
superintendence, direction and guidance of the Director.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>568679</tid>
<number> 29</number> Power of inspection, etc.
<section><tid>1487645</tid>
<number>1</number>The Director, or any person  
authorised to exercise the powers or discharge the functions of the 
Director, may, if he has any reason to believe. whether from any 
information given to him by any person and taken down in writing or 
from personal knowledge or otherwise, that any weight or measure or 
other goods in relation to which any interState trade or commerce has 
taken place or is intended to take place and in respect of which an 
offence punishable under this Act appears to have been, or is likely 
to be, committed are either kept or concealed in any premises or are 
in the course of transportation from one State to another,-

<subsection><tid>676903</tid>
<number>a</number>enter at any reasonable time into any such premises and 
search for and inspect any weight, measure or other goods in 
relation to which inter- State trade or commerce has taken 
place. or is intended to take place, and any record, register 
or other document relating thereto;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>452177</tid>
<number>b</number>seize any weight, measure or other goods and any 
record, register or other document or article which he has 
reason to believe may furnish evidence indicating that an 
offence punishable under this Act has been or is likely to 
be, committed in the course. of, or in relation to, any 
inter- State trade or commerce.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1473127</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any goods seized under sub- section (1) are subject to 
speedy or natural decay, the Director or the authorised person may 
dispose of such mods in such manner as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>266643</tid>
<number>3</number>Every search or seizure made under this section shall be 
carried out in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Criminal 
' Procedure, <year>1973</year>, (2 of <year>1974</year>.) relating to searches and seizures made 
under that Code.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1499034</tid>
<number>30</number>Forfeiture. Every false or unverified weight or measure, and 
every, false package. used in the course of, or in relation tn. any 
inter- State trade or commerce and seized under section 29, shall be 
liable to be forfeited to the Central Government:,
Provided that such unverified weight or measure shall not be 
forfeited to Government if the person from whom such weight or measure 
was seized gets the same verified and stamped within such time as may 
be prescribed.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>367</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

INTER- STATE TRADE OR COMMERCE IN WEIGHT, MEASURE OR OTHER GOODS

PART IV

INTER- STATE TRADE OR COMMERCE IN WEIGHT, MEASURE OR OTHER GOODS

CHAP

Applicability of this Part

CHAPTER I

Applicability of this Part



</article>



<article><tid>799874</tid>
<number> 31</number> Part IV to apply to inter- State trade or commerce only. The 
provisions of this Part shall apply to-
<section><tid>1368171</tid>
<number>a</number>every weight or measure which is, or is intended' to 
be",-

<subsection><tid>1924732</tid>
<number>i</number>made or manufactured for the purpose of inter- 
State trade or commerce,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>654925</tid>
<number>ii</number>used, sold, distributed, delivered or otherwise 
transferred in the course of inter- State. trade or 
commerce;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1682426</tid>
<number>b</number>goods which are, or are intended to be, sold, 
distributed delivered or otherwise transferred by weight, 
measure or number the course of inter- State trade or 
commerce;

</section>

<section><tid>430242</tid>
<number>c</number>every service which is rendered by Wright, measure or 
number in relation to, or in the course of, inter- State trade 
or commerce.
CHAP

General

CHAPTER II

General




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1074119</tid>
<number> 32</number> Use of weights only or measures only in certain cases.
<section><tid>669639</tid>
<number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by rules made in this behalf, direct that 
in respect of the class of goods or undertakings or users specified 
therein, no transaction. dealing or contract shall be made or had 
except by such weight, measure or number as may be specified in the 
said rules.

</section>

<section><tid>441847</tid>
<number>2</number>Any rule made under sub- section (1) shall take effect in such 
area, from such future date and subject to such conditions, if any, as 
may be specified therein.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>352846</tid>
<number> 33</number> Prohibition of quotations, etc., otherwise than in terms of 
standard units of weights, measures or numeration. No person shall, in 
relation to any goods, thing or service to which this Part applies,-
<section><tid>1167211</tid>
<number>a</number>quote, or make announcement of, whether by word 
of mouth or otherwise, any price or charge, or

</section>

<section><tid>1671603</tid>
<number>b</number>issue or exhibit any price list, invoice, cash memo or 
other document, or

</section>

<section><tid>1455820</tid>
<number>c</number>prepare or publish any advertisement, poster or other 
document, or

</section>

<section><tid>1228525</tid>
<number>d</number>indicate the contents of any package either on itself 
or on any label, carton or other thing, or

</section>

<section><tid>526675</tid>
<number>e</number>indicate the contents on any container, or

</section>

<section><tid>75107</tid>
<number>f</number>express any quantity or dimension,
otherwise than in accordance with the standard unit of weight, measure 
or numeration.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>368</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>236052</tid>
<number>34</number>Any custom, usage, etc., contrary to standard weight, measure 
or numeration to be void. Any custom, usage, practice or method of 
whatever nature which permits a person to demand, receive, or cause to 
be demanded or received, any quantity of article, thing or service (to  
  which this Part applies) in excess of, or less than, the quantity 
specified by weight; measure or number in the contract or other 
agreement in relation to the said article, thing or service, shall be 
void.


</article>



<article><tid>172732</tid>
<number> 35</number> Manufactures, etc., to maintain records and registers.
<section><tid>1703126</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Every person who-

<subsection><tid>273539</tid>
<number>a</number>makes, manufactures, sells, distributes or otherwise 
disposes of any weight or measure or other goods which are 
sold, delivered or distributed by weight, measure or number, 
or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>921053</tid>
<number>b</number>repairs any weight or measure,
to which this Part applies, shall maintain such records and registers 
as may be prescribed and if required so to do by the Director, shall 
produce such records and registers before the Director or such other 
officer as the Director may authorise in this behalf, for inspection.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>890198</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), if 
the Director is of opinion that having regard to the nature or volume 
of the business carried on by any maker, manufacturer, dealer or 
repairer, it is necessary so to do, he may, by order exempt such 
maker, manufacturer, dealer or repairer from the operation of that 
sub- section.
CHAP

Approval of models

CHAPTER III

Approval of models




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1762748</tid>
<number> 36</number> Approval of models.
<section><tid>1600726</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as otherwise provided in this  
section, this Chapter shall not apply to-

<subsection><tid>90218</tid>
<number>a</number>any weight or measure which, being subject to 
verification and stamping under the State law as in force 
immediately before the commencement of this Act, is in use at 
such commencement;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>597116</tid>
<number>b</number>any cast Iron, brass, bullion, or carat weight or any 
beamscale, except those specified by rules made in this 
behalf;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>294755</tid>
<number>c</number>length measures (not being measuring tapes) ordinarily 
used in retail trade for measuring textiles or timber;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>97046</tid>
<number>d</number>capacity measures, not exceeding twenty litres in 
capacity, which are ordinarily used in retail trade for 
measuring kerosene, milk or potable liquors;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1189403</tid>
<number>e</number>any weighing or measuring instrument or device which is 
made or manufactured exclusively for domestic use:
Provided that such instrument or device is not intended for 
the use of any member of the medical profession in the course 
of such profession.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>659984</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any officer of the Central or State Government charged 
with the duty of implementing the law relating to weights and measures 
has any reason to believe that the model of any weight or measure 
referred to in sub- section (1) requires a test by the prescribed 
authority, he may acquire one such weight or measure from the market 
and forward it to the prescribed authority for, test, the fees for 
which shall be payable by the Government employing the officer by whom 
such weight or measure has been forwarded for test.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>369</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1458731</tid>
<number>3</number>Every person shall, before making or manufacturing any 
weight or measure to which this Part applies, submit for approval of 
the prescribed authority, such number of models, drawings and other 
information relating to such weight or measure as may be prescribed:
Provided that in relation to any weight or measure, to which this 
Part applies, which has already been made or manufactured, or which Is 
in the process of being made or manufactured, at the commencement of 
this Part, models of such weight or measure shall be submitted to the 
prescribed authority from out of the weights or measures which have 
already been, or which are in the process of being, made or 
manufactured:

Provided further that in the case of a weight or measure the 
model whereof cannot be submitted, whether by reason of its nature or 
otherwise, it shall be sufficient if the drawings and other prescribed 
information about the weight or measure is submitted to the prescribed 
authority and thereupon that authority shall test the models of such 
weight or measure at the place where it is made or manufactured or at 
such other place as may be specified by the Director:

Provided also that the prescribed authority may, if it is 
satisfied that the model of any weight or measure which has been 
approved in a country outside India conforms to the standards 
established by or under this Act, approve such model without any test 
or, after such test as it may deem fit.


</section>

<section><tid>1943730</tid>
<number>4</number>The prescribed authority shall levy and collect such fees 
for the testing of any model, submitted under this section for 
approval, as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1059740</tid>
<number>5</number>The prescribed authority shall test the models submitted to 
it with a view to-

<subsection><tid>1430311</tid>
<number>a</number>ascertaining whether such models conform to the standards 
established be or under this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1984057</tid>
<number>b</number>finding out the ability of such models to maintain 
accuracy over periods of sustained use; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>711777</tid>
<number>c</number>determining the performance of such models under such 
varied conditions as may be prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1225985</tid>
<number>6</number>The prescribed authority shall submit to the Central 
Government a detailed report on the performance of the model submitted 
to it together worth its recommendations with regard to the 
desirability or otherwise of issuing a certificate of approval in 
respect of that model.

</section>

<section><tid>1322538</tid>
<number>7</number>The Central Government may, if it is satisfied after 
considering the report submitted to it by the prescribed authority 
that thee aforesaid model is in conformity with the provisions of this 
Act or any rule made thereunder and is likely to maintain accuracy 
over periods of sustained use and to render accurate service under 
varied conditions, issue a certificate of approval in respect of that 
model.

</section>

<section><tid>105226</tid>
<number>8</number>Every certificate of approval of a model shall be published 
In the Official Gazette and shall also be published in such other 
manner as the Central Government may thin fit,
 115 Law- 47


<pagefootnote><pagenum>370</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>692363</tid>
<number>9</number>The Central Government may, if it is satisfied that the 
product made or manufactured in accordance with the model which was 
approved by it has failed to render the expected performance or to 
conform to the standards established by or under this Act, revoke the 
certificate of approval issued by it under sub- section (7):
Provided that no such revocation shall be made except after 
giving the manufacturer of such weight or measure a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard:

Provided further that where the Central Government is satisfied 
that as a result of the alteration made by the manufacturer in the 
model of the weight or measure, such model has become fit for 
approval, it may vacate the order of revocation of the certificate of 
approval issued by It.


</section>

<section><tid>1994560</tid>
<number>10</number>If for any reason any material of the approved model of a 
weight or measure to which this Part applies becomes non- available In 
India, the manufacturer may continue the manufacture of such weight or 
measure with such substitute materials as may be, in his opinion, most 
suitable for the manufacture of such weight or measure but where the 
manufacturer does so, he shall send such substitute materials to the 
prescribed authority for test.

</section>

<section><tid>1904633</tid>
<number>11</number>If the prescribed authority is of openion that the 
substitute material referred to in sub- section (10) is not suitable 
and that there is available in India any other material which is more 
suitable, that authority shall intimate its findings to the Central 
Government and also to the manufacturer, and thereupon the 
manufacturer shall not manufacture the weight or measure with any 
material other than the material recommended by the prescribed 
authority, until the material which was originally approved by the 
prescribed authority becomes available in India:
Provided that where, in the opinion of the prescribed authority, 
the Substitute material referred to in sub- section (10) is not 
suitable and no other suitable material is also available in India, 
the approval in relation to the model shall stand suspended until a 
suitable material becomes available in India.


</section>

<section><tid>218034</tid>
<number>12</number>Where the model of any weight or measure to Which this Part 
applies has been approved, the models of different denominations of 
such weight or measure shall not require any approval if such 
denominations are manufactured in accordance with the same principles 
according to which, and the same materials with which, the approved 
model has been manufactured.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1840791</tid>
<number> 37</number> Licence to manufacture weights or measures when to be issued.

<section><tid>1515456</tid>
<number>1</number>Before issuing a licence to make or manufacture any weight or  
measure to which this Part applies, the State Government shall satisfy 
Itself that a certificate of approval of the model of such weight or 
measure has been granted by the Central Government under section 36.

</section>

<section><tid>1730937</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any certificate of approval of any model has been 
revoked by the Central Government, the licence issued by the State 
Government for the making or manufacturing of any weight or measure in 
accordance with such model shall stand suspended:
Provided that such suspension shall stand vacated if such model 
subsequently approved by the Central Government.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>371</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>649491</tid>
<number>38</number>Weight or measure to contain number of the approved model, 
etc. Every weight or measure to which this Part applies and for which 
a model has been approved shall bear thereon, in such manner as may be 
prescribed, the number of the approved model and the number of the 
certificate by or under which such model was approved:
Provided that where the Central Government is of opinion that 
inclusion of any such particulars on any weight or measure is not 
possible by reason of its size or nature, that Government may exempt 
the inclusion of such particulars on such weight or measure.

CHAP

Commodities in packaged form intended to be sold or distributed in the 
course of inter- State trade or commerce

CHAPTER IV

Commodities in packaged form intended to be sold or distributed in the 
course of inter- State trade or commerce



</article>



<article><tid>1349597</tid>
<number> 39</number> Quantities and origin of commodities in packaged form to be 
declared.
<section><tid>1644155</tid>
<number>1</number>No person shall- 
 (a) make, manufacture, pack, sell, or cause to be packed or 
sold; or


<subsection><tid>1953026</tid>
<number>b</number>distribute, deliver, or cause to be distributed or 
delivered; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1595829</tid>
<number>c</number>offer, expose or possess for sale,
any commodity, in packaged form to which this Part applies unless such 
package bears thereon or on a label securely attached thereto a 
definite, plain and conspicuous declaration, made in the prescribed 
manner, of-


<subsubsection><tid>52023</tid>
<number>i</number>the identity of the commodity in the package;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1607042</tid>
<number>ii</number>the net quantity, in terms of the standard unit of 
weight or measure, of the commodity in the package;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>296990</tid>
<number>iii</number>where the commodity is packaged or sold by number, the 
accurate number of the commodity contained in the package;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1740046</tid>
<number>iv</number>the unit sale price of the commodity in the package; 
and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>656670</tid>
<number>v</number>the sale price of the package.
Explanation.- In this sub- section, the expression" unit sale 
price" means the price according to such unit of weight, measure or 
number as may be prescribed.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>220816</tid>
<number>2</number>Every package to which this Part applies shall bear thereon 
the name of the manufacturer and also of the packer or distributor.

</section>

<section><tid>82550</tid>
<number>3</number>Where the package of a commodity to which this Part applies 
or the label thereon bears a representation as to the number of 
servings, of the commodity contained therein, such package or label 
shall also bear a statement as to the net quantity (in terms of  
  weight, measure or number) of each such serving.

</section>

<section><tid>1803534</tid>
<number>4</number>The statement on a package or label as to the net weight, 
measure or number of the contents thereof shall not include any 
expression which tends to qualify such weight, measure or number:
Provided that the Central Government may, by rules, specify the 
commodities, the weight or measure of which is likely to increase or 
decrease beyond the prescribed tolerance limits by reason of climatic 
variations; and it shall be lawful for the manufacturer or packer of 
the commodity so specified to qualify the statement as to the net 
content of such commodity by the use of the words" when packed".

Explanation.- The words" when packed" shall not be used in any 
case except a case to which the proviso to sub- section (4) applies.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>372</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>721081</tid>
<number>5</number>Where the Central Government has reason to believe 
that. there is undue proliferation of weight, measure or number, in 
which any commodity is, or reasonably comparable commodities are, 
being- packed for sale, distribution or delivery and such undue 
proliferation impairs in the opinion of that Government, the 
reasonable ability of the consumer to make a comparative assessment of 
the prices after considering the net quantity or number of such 
commodity, that Government may direct the manufacturers and also the 
packers or distributors to sell, distribute or deliver such commodity 
in such standard quantities or number as' may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>503434</tid>
<number>6</number>Whenever the retail price of a commodity in packaged form to 
which this Chapter applies is stated in any advertisement. there shall 
be included in the advertisement, a conspicuous declaration as to the 
net quantity or number of the commodity contained in the package. and, 
retail unit sale price thereof.

</section>

<section><tid>641042</tid>
<number>7</number>No person shall sell, distribute or deliver for sale a 
package containing a commodity which is filled less than the, 
prescribed capacity of such package except where it is proved by such 
person that the package was so filled with a view to-

<subsection><tid>1281250</tid>
<number>a</number>giving protection to the contents of such package, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>513269</tid>
<number>b</number>meeting the requirements of machines used for 
enclosings the contents of such package.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>542030</tid>
<number>8</number>The Central Government may, by rules, specify such' 
reasonable variations in the net contents of the commodity in a 
package as may be caused by the method of packing or the ordinary 
exposure Which may be undergone by such commodity after it has been 
introduced in trade or commerce.

</section>

<section><tid>1074534</tid>
<number>9</number>The Central Government may, by rules, specify, the classes 
of commodities or packages in relation to which all or any of the 
provision of this section shall not apply or shall apply with, such 
exceptions or modifications as may be specified therein.
CHAP

Verification and stamping of weights and measures sent from one Stateto another

CHAPTER V

Verification and stamping of weights and measures sent from one State 
to another




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>580121</tid>
<number> 40</number> Definitions. In this Chapter, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>458863</tid>
<number>a</number>" Controller" means the person appointed, as suck by, 
the State, Government under the State law;

</section>

<section><tid>1875723</tid>
<number>b</number>" Inspector" means the person appointed as such by the 
State Government under the State law;

</section>

<section><tid>1314597</tid>
<number>c</number>" local Inspector" means an Inspector, Within the, 
local, limits of whose jurisdiction any weight or measure is 
made, manufactured, received, delivered or kept for sale or 
use;

</section>

<section><tid>641143</tid>
<number>d</number>" State law" means the law enacted, by the Legislature 
of a State, and for the time being in force in that State, 
with regard to the, enforcement of the standards of weight or 
measure established by or under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1978439</tid>
<number>e</number>" transferee, State" means the State in which any weight 
or measure is delivered or received for sale or use therein 
from any other State;

</section>

<section><tid>323807</tid>
<number>f</number>" transferor State" means the State from which any weight 
or measure made or manufactured therein, or kept therein, for 
sale or use, is sent to, or delivered in any other State.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>373</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>580296</tid>
<number> 41</number> Verification and stamping of weights and measures sent from 
one State to another.
<section><tid>900063</tid>
<number>1</number>Where any weight or measure, sent from a  
transferor State for delivery, sale or use in a transferee State, is 
such that-

<subsection><tid>647577</tid>
<number>a</number>it is not required to be dismantled before its despatch 
to th transferee State and is not likely to lose its accuracy 
by reason of such despatch, it shall be known, for the 
purposes of this Chapter, as a weight or measure of the first 
category;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1404817</tid>
<number>b</number>it is required to be dismantled before its despatch to 
the transferee State and re- assembled and installed for use 
in the transferee State, it shall be known, for the purposes 
of this Chapter, as a weight or measure of the second 
category.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1686697</tid>
<number>2</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (1), the Central 
Government may specify, by rules made in this behalf, the classes of 
weights or measures which would, fall in the first category or the 
second category, and may, from time to time, if the circumstances so 
require, alter the category in which any class of weight or measure 
has been specified.

</section>

<section><tid>536629</tid>
<number>3</number>Weight or measure of the first category shall, before it is 
despatched to any transferee State, be produced before the local 
Inspector in the transferor State and if such Inspector is, after 
verification of such Weight or measure, satisfied that such weight or 
measure conforms to the standards established by or under this Act, 
stamp the same with such special seal as may be specified by rules 
made under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1310691</tid>
<number>4</number>A weight or measure of the second category shall not be 
verified and stamped in, the transferor State but shall be verified 
and stamped, after its re- assembly and installation for use, by the 
local Inspector in the transferee State.

</section>

<section><tid>95538</tid>
<number>5</number>The fees for the verification and stamping of every weight 
or measure of-

<subsection><tid>1409250</tid>
<number>a</number>the first category shall be levied and collected by the 
transferor State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1075652</tid>
<number>b</number>the second category shall be levied and collected by 
the transferee State,
in accordance with such scales as may be specified by rules made under 
this Act.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>71842</tid>
<number>6</number>A weight or measure, whether of the first or second 
category, shall not require periodical re- verification if it is 
exclusively intended for domestic use and is not used by any member of 
the medical profession in the course of such profession.

</section>

<section><tid>502499</tid>
<number>7</number>No weight or measure, whether of the first or of the second 
category, shall be verified and stamped unless fees for such 
verification and stamping have been paid in accordance with the scales 
specified under sub- section (5).



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>811424</tid>
<number> 42</number> Weight or measure of the first category to be presumed to be 
correct throughout the territory of India.
<section><tid>1005111</tid>
<number>1</number>Every weight or  
measure of the first category which is stamped with, the special seal 
referred to in sub- section (3) of section, 41 shall be presumed to be 
correct throughout the territory of India and shall not be required, 
until its re- verification in the transferee State becomes due by 
efflux of time, to be verified or stamped in the transferee State:
Provided that where the local Inspector in the transferee State 
has any reason to believe that any weight or measure of the first 
category has lost its accuracy in transit or has, for any other 
reason, ceased to conform to the standards of weight or measure 
established by or under this Act, he may, for reasons to be recorded 
by him in within and


<pagefootnote><pagenum>374</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

communicated to the Controller of the transferor State, through the 
Controller of the transferee State,-


<subsection><tid>151706</tid>
<number>a</number>verify such weight or measure; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>784540</tid>
<number>b</number>if, on verification, such weight or measure is found to be 
Inaccurate,-

<subsubsection><tid>252245</tid>
<number>i</number>cause such adjustment as is necessary to be made 
as so as to make it conform to the standards established 
by or under this Act, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>841108</tid>
<number>ii</number>where he is of opinion that such adjustment is not 
possible, reject it and obliterate the stamp thereon:
Provided further that where any verification, adjustment or 
obliteration is made in exercise of the powers conferred by the 
foregoing proviso, no fee shall be charged for such verification, 
adjustment or obliteration.


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>156744</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the time when the re- verification of a weight 
or measure of the first category shall become due in the transferee 
State, the period during which such weight or measure remains unsold 
or undistributed in the transferee State, shall be excluded.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1158954</tid>
<number>43</number>Weight or measure of the first category not to be sold or 
used in any State unless it is stamped in the transferor State. No 
weight or measure of the first category shall be used, sold, 
purchased, delivered or otherwise transferred in any transferee State 
unless such weight or measure bears thereon the stamp made' with the 
special seal referred to in sub- section (3) of section 41.


</article>



<article><tid>1719279</tid>
<number> 44</number> Weights or measures of the second category received from 
transferor State to be produced before the local Inspector of the 
transferee State.
<section><tid>543909</tid>
<number>1</number>Every person in a transferee State who receives  
or delivers for sale or use therein any weight or measure of the 
second category shall, after its re- assembly and installation for use, 
have such, weight or measure verified and stamped by the local 
Inspector in the transferee State.

</section>

<section><tid>1476548</tid>
<number>2</number>The local Inspector in the transferee State shall verify 
every weight or measure of the second category and shall if he is 
satisfied that such weight or measure conforms to the standards 
established by or under this Act, stamp the same with the seal 
prescribed by or under the State law In force in the transferee State.

</section>

<section><tid>1586969</tid>
<number>3</number>For the avoidance of doubt, it is hereby declared that where 
any weight or measure of the second category is delivered or received 
in a State from any other State, not for the purpose of sale or use 
therein but for the transmission of such weight or measure to any 
other State, then, such other State shall be deemed, for the purposes 
of this Chapter, to be the transferee State in relation to such weight 
or measure and the provisions of sub- section (1) and sub- section (2) 
shall apply accordingly.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>375</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>56263</tid>
<number>45</number>Procedure when any weight or measure is transferred from a 
transferee State to another State. Where any weight or measure, which 
being in use in a transfer State, is sent to, or delivered in, any 
other State for sale or use in such other State, then, such other 
State shall also be deemed to be the transferee State in relation to 
such weight or measure and the provisions this Chapter shall, so far 
as may be, apply to the weight or measure to, or delivered in, such 
other State.


</article>



<article><tid>844921</tid>
<number> 46</number> Manufacturers, etc., who send any weight or measure to any 
other State to submit return to the Controller. Every manufacturer, 
dealer or other person in a transferor State who sends to, or delivers 
in, any transferee State any weight or measure whether of the first or 
of the second category, shall-
<section><tid>564787</tid>
<number>a</number>submit such periodical returns as may be prescribed, to 
the Controller of the transferor State with regard to such 
despatch, deli very or transfer and specify in such returns 
the particulars of the weight or measure which has been sent 
to, or delivered in, the transferee State;

</section>

<section><tid>784444</tid>
<number>b</number>specify in such periodical returns the particulars of the 
person to whom such weight or measure has been sent, or 
delivered in the transferee State; and

</section>

<section><tid>168412</tid>
<number>c</number>forward a copy of such periodical returns to the 
Controller of the transferee State.
PART

IMPORT AND EXPORT OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES

PART V

IMPORT AND EXPORT OF WEIGHTS AND MEASURES

CHAP

Registration of exporters and importers

CHAPTER I

Registration of exporters and importers




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1319567</tid>
<number> 47</number> Persons exporting or importing any weight or measure to get 
themselves registered.
<section><tid>1885078</tid>
<number>1</number>No dealer or manufacturer shall export or  
Import any weight or measure unless he is registered under this 
section as such exporter or importer, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>1024359</tid>
<number>2</number>Every person who intends to commence or continue business 
as an exporter or importer of any weight or measure shall make, within 
such time from the commencement of this Act as may be prescribed, an 
application for the inclusion of his name in the register to be 
maintained for the purpose.

</section>

<section><tid>731032</tid>
<number>3</number>The application referred to in sub- section (2) shall be made 
to the Director and every such application shall be made in such form, 
In such manner and on payment of such fees, not exceeding ten rupees, 
as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>828640</tid>
<number>4</number>On receipt of an application referred to in sub- section (2), 
the Director shall, if he is satisfied after such inquiry as he may 
think fit, that it is expedient in the public interest so to do, 
include the name of the applicant in the register referred to in sub- 
section (2) and issue to the applicant a certificate to the effect 
that his name has been so included and send a copy of the said 
certificate to the Controller of Legal Metrology in the State in which 
such exporter or importer is carrying on his business.

</section>

<section><tid>693076</tid>
<number>5</number>A certificate granted under sub- section (4) shall be valid 
for the period specified therein and may be renewed, from time to 
time, for such further period as may be prescribed,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>376</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

CHAP

Export and import of weights, measures and commoditiesin packaged form

CHAPTER II

Export and import of weights, measures and commodities 
in packaged form




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>717615</tid>
<number> 48</number> Conditions under which export of non- standard weights and 
measures and other goods may be made.
<section><tid>151810</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to such conditions,  
limitations and restrictions as may be prescribed, the Central 
Government may allow the export of any weight or measure which has 
been made or manufactured exclusively for export with the previous 
permission of that Government notwithstanding that such weight or 
measure does not conform to the standards established by or under this 
Act.

</section>

<section><tid>215478</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any commodity in packaged form Is exported and the 
person to whom such export is to be made so requires, the exporter 
may, in addition to specifying the net contents of such package In 
terms of the standards unit of weight or measure established by or 
under this Act, also specify the weight or the net contents thereof In 
terms of such units of weight or measure as may be specified by the 
person to whom such commodity is to be exported.

</section>

<section><tid>1845235</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained elsewhere in this Act, in 
relation to any goods which are exported-

<subsection><tid>1874255</tid>
<number>a</number>quotation of any price;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1891289</tid>
<number>b</number>Issue a any price list, invoke or cash memo;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>169422</tid>
<number>c</number>indication of the weight or measure or number of net 
contents of any package on any label, carton or other thing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1105845</tid>
<number>d</number>expression of any dimension,
may be made in accordance with any other system of weight, measure or 
numeration if the person to whom the export is to be made so requires.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>251377</tid>
<number> 49</number> Non- metric weight or measure not to be imported.
<section><tid>589913</tid>
<number>1</number>Save as  
otherwise provided in sub- section (2) no weight or measure, whether 
singly or as a part or component of any machine or machinery, shall be 
imported unless it conforms to the standards of weight or measure 
established by or under this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>427771</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any commodity, machinery or tiny part or component of 
any machinery is imported from a country in which the metric, system 
of weight or measure is not in force, or in which such system being in 
force, such commodity, machinery, part or component of any machinery 
has not been, made or manufactured in accordance with such system, the 
importer shall, before making such import, make an endeavour to 
obtain, on such commodity, machinery, part or component, and also on 
the drawings thereof, the weight or measurement thereof expressed in 
terms of the standard unit of weight or measure established by or 
under this Act:
Provided that where any weight or measure has not been expressed 
in terms of the standard unit of weight or measure established by or 
under this Act, on any commodity, machinery, part or component or on 
any drawings thereof the importer shall, within six months from the 
date of import, get the weight or measure thereof expressed on such 
commodity, machinery, part or component and On the drawings thereof in 
terms of the standard unit of weight or measure established by or 
under this Act.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>377</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

PART

OFFENCES AND THEIR TRIAL

PART VI

OFFENCES AND THEIR TRIAL




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1222583</tid>
<number>50</number>Penalty for use of non- standard weights or measures. Whoever 
uses any weight or measure or makes any numeration otherwise than in 
accordance with the standards of weight or measure or the standards of 
numeration, as the case may be, established by or under this Act, 
shall be punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six 
months, or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with 
both, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for 
a term which may extend to two years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>419099</tid>
<number>51</number>Penalty for contravention of section 18. Whoever tampers 
with, or alters, in any way, any reference standard, secondary 
standard, or working standard except where such alteration is made for 
the correction of any error noticed therein on verification, shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, 
or with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, or with both.


</article>



<article><tid>723162</tid>
<number>52</number>Penalty for contravention of section 22. Except Where any 
weight or measure is made or manufactured, with the permission of the 
Central Government, exclusively for export, every person who makes or 
manufactures any weight or measure which does not conform to the 
standards of weight or measure establish by or under this Act, shall, 
where such offence is not punishable under any other law relating to 
weights and measures for the time being in force, be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or with fine 
which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both, and, for the 
second or subsequent offence with imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to three years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1106979</tid>
<number>53</number>Penalty for contravention of section 23. Except where any 
weight or measure is made or manufactured, with the permission of the 
Central Government, exclusively for export, every person who makes or 
manufactures any weight or measure which bears thereon any inscription 
of weight, measure or number Which does not conform to the standards 
of weight or measure or numeration established by or under this Act, 
shall, where such offence is not punishable under any other law 
relating to weights and measures for the time being in force, be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to one year, or 
with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with both, and, 
for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to three years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1120097</tid>
<number>54</number>Penalty for contravention of section 29. Whoever obstructs 
the Director or any person authorised to exercise the powers or 
discharge the functions of the Director (hereafter, in this Part,  
  referred to as the" authorised officer") in the exercise of his powers 
or discharge of his functions as such Director or authorised officer, 
or with intent to prevent or deter the Director or such authorised 
officer from exercising his powers or discharging his functions, or in 
consequence of any thing done or attempted to be done by the Director 
or such authorised officer in the lawful exercise of his powers or 
discharge of his functions as such, shall be punished with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years, and, for the 
second or subsequent offence, with Imprisonment for a term which may 
extend to five years.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>378</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>40888</tid>
<number>55</number>Penalty for contravention of section 32. Whoever in the 
course of any inter- State trade or commerce, makes any transaction, 
deal or contract in contravention of the provisions of section 32 
shall be punished with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, 
and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to one year and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>738568</tid>
<number>56</number>Penalty for contravention of section 33. Whoever, in the 
course of any inter- State trade or commerce, contravenes the 
provisions of section 33 shall be punished with fine which may extend 
to two thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and also 
with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1968591</tid>
<number> 57</number> Penalty for contravention of section 34. Whoever, in the 
course of any inter- State trade or commerce,--
<section><tid>1728327</tid>
<number>i</number>sells, delivers, or causes to be sold or delivered, to 
the purchaser any quantity or number of any article or thing, 
less than the quantity or number contracted for or paid for; 
or

</section>

<section><tid>203400</tid>
<number>ii</number>renders any service by weight, measure or number, less 
than the service contracted for or paid for; or

</section>

<section><tid>174158</tid>
<number>iii</number>demands, or causes to be demanded, or receives, or 
causes to be received, while buying any article or thing, any 
quantity or number of goods in excess of the quantity or 
number contracted for, or paid for; or

</section>

<section><tid>1907893</tid>
<number>iv</number>obtains any service in excess of the service contracted 
for or paid for,
shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, 
and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to five years and also with fine.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1321453</tid>
<number>58</number>Penalty for contravention of section 35. Whoever, being 
required by or under this Act so to do, without any reasonable excuse, 
omits or fails to maintain any record or register, or being required 
by the Director or the authorised officers to produce any record or 
register for his- inspection, omits or fails, without any reasonable 
excuse, so to do, shall be punished with fine which may extend to one 
thousand rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with 
imprisonment for i term which may extend to six months and also with 
fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1535175</tid>
<number>59</number>Penalty for contravention of section 36. Whoever, being 
required by section 36 to submit the model of any weight or measure 
for approval, omits, or fails, without any reasonable excuse, so to 
do, shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand 
rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to five years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>881369</tid>
<number> 60</number> Penalty for manufacture of weights or measures unless 
approval of model is in force.
<section><tid>1591512</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever makes or manufactures any  
weight or measure which is, or is intended to be, sold, distributed, 
delivered or' otherwise transferred in the course of inter- State trade 
or commerce, shall,; unless a certificate of approval of the model of 
such weight or measure granted under section 36 is in force, be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to two years 
and shall also be liable to fine, and, for the second or subsequent 
offence, with Imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years 
and also with fine.

</section>

<section><tid>471026</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever, without any reasonable excuse, manufactures any 
weight or measure in accordance with an approved model with any

<pagefootnote><pagenum>379</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

material other than the material approved or recommended by the 
prescribed authority, shall be punished with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to five years and also with fine.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>60493</tid>
<number>61</number>Penalty for contravention of section 38. Whoever makes or 
manufactures any weight or measure without, complying with the 
requirements of section 38 shall be punished wit fine which may extend 
to five thousand rupees, and, for the second subsequent offence, with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend five years and also with 
fine.


</article>



<article><tid>290156</tid>
<number>62</number>Penalty for sale, etc, of unverified weights or measures 
in the course of inter- State trade or commerce. Whoever, in the 
course of inter- State trade or commerce, sells, distributes, delivers 
or otherwise transfers any weight or measure which does not conform to 
the standards of weight or measure established by or under this Act or 
which has not been duly verified under any other law relating to' 
weights and measures for the time being in force, shall be punished 
with fine which may extend to ten thousand rupees, and, for the second 
or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
to seven years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1427531</tid>
<number>63</number>Penalty for contravention of section 39. Whoever, in the 
course of inter- State trade or commerce, sells, distributes, delivers; 
or otherwise transfers, or causes to be sold, distributed, delivered 
or otherwise transferred any commodity in a packaged form which does 
not conform to the provisions of this Act or any rule made thereunder, 
shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand rupees, 
and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to five years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>393869</tid>
<number>64</number>Penalty for contravention of section 47. Whoever exports or 
imports any weight or measure without being registered under this Act 
shall be punished with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, 
and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to six months and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1197953</tid>
<number>65</number>Penalty for contravention of section 48. Every person who 
exports any weight or measure or commodity in packaged form which does 
not conform to the standards of weight or measure established by or 
under this Act shall, except where such export has been made with the 
previous approval of the Central Government, be punished with fine- 
which may extend to five thousand rupees, and, for the second or 
subsequent offence with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
five years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>165542</tid>
<number>66</number>Penalty for contravention of section 49. Whoever 
contravenes, without any reasonable excuse, the provisions of section 
49, shall be punished with fine which may extend to five thousand 
rupees, and, for the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment 
for a term which may extend to five years and also with fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1445989</tid>
<number>67</number>Penalty where no specific penalty is provided. Whoever 
contravenes any provisions of this Act for the, contravention of which 
no punishment has been separately provided in any of the provisions of 
this Act, shall be punished with fine which may extend to two thousand 
rupees.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>380</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</article>



<article><tid>1643665</tid>
<number> 68</number> Presumption to be made in certain cases.
<section><tid>449121</tid>
<number>1</number>If any person,  
in the course of inter- State trade or commerce, uses, or causes to be 
used, sells, distributes, delivers or otherwise transfers, or causes 
to be sold, distributed, delivered or otherwise transferred, any false 
or unverified weight or measure, it shall be presumed, until the 
contrary is proved, that he had done so with the knowledge that the 
weight or measure was a false or unverified weight or measure.

</section>

<section><tid>60373</tid>
<number>2</number>If any person makes or manufactures or has in his 
possession, custody or control any false or, unverified weight or 
measure in such circumstances as to indicate that such weight or 
measure is likely to be used in the course of inter- State trade or 
commerce, it shall be presumed, until the contrary is proved, that 
such false or unverified weight or measure was made, manufactured, 
possessed, held or controlled by such person with the knowledge that 
the same would be, or is intended to be, used in- the course of inter- 
State trade or commerce.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>855644</tid>
<number>69</number>Presumption to be made in certain cases. Whoever personates, 
in any way, the Director, or any authorised officer, shall be punished 
with imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years.


</article>



<article><tid>1496023</tid>
<number> 70</number> Penalty for giving false information or false returns.
<section><tid>640724</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Whoever gives information to the Director or the authorised officer 
which he may require or ask for in the course of his duty and which 
such person either knows or has reason to believe to be false shall be 
punished with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, 
or with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees, or with both.

</section>

<section><tid>998388</tid>
<number>2</number>Whoever, being required by or under this Act so to do, 
submits a return which is false in material particulars, shall be 
punished with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, and, for 
the second or subsequent offence, with imprisonment for a term which 
may extend to one year and also with fine.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>609163</tid>
<number> 71</number> Vexatious actions.
<section><tid>1070198</tid>
<number>1</number>An authorised officer who knows that  
there are no reasonable grounds for so doing, and yet-

<subsection><tid>1746139</tid>
<number>a</number>searches, or causes to be searched, any house, 
conveyance or place; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>790731</tid>
<number>b</number>searches any person; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1988682</tid>
<number>c</number>seizes any weight, measure or other movable property,
shall, for every such offence, be punished with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to 
two thousand rupees, or with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1480476</tid>
<number>2</number>If a local Inspector, as defined in section 40,--

<subsection><tid>815035</tid>
<number>a</number>without any reasonable cause verifies any weight or 
measure of first category, within the meaning of section 41,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>712502</tid>
<number>b</number>without any reasonable cause obliterates any stamp on 
any such weight or measure,
in contravention of the provisions of the first proviso to section 42, 
he shall, for every such offence be punished with imprisonment for a 
term which may extend to one year, or with fine which may extend to 
two thousand rupees, or with both.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>381</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1727506</tid>
<number> 72</number> Cognizance of offences, etc. Notwithstanding anything 
contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, <year>1973</year>, (2 of <year>1974</year>.)
<section><tid>1140359</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> no court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable 
under this Act except upon a complaint, in writing, made by-

<subsection><tid>99872</tid>
<number>i</number>the Director;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1884611</tid>
<number>ii</number>any other authorised officer;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1100536</tid>
<number>iii</number>any person aggrieved; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1005437</tid>
<number>iv</number>a recognised consumer association whether the person 
aggrieved is a member of such association or not.
Explanation.- For the purposes' of this clause" recognised 
consumer association" means, a voluntary consumer association 
registered under the Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1of 1956.) or any 
other law for the time being in force:


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>986787</tid>
<number>b</number>no court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate 
or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall try any 
offence under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>484154</tid>
<number>c</number>an offence punishable under section 50, section 52, 
section 53, section 56, section 58, section 60, section 61, 
section 63, section 64, section 65 or section 66, may be 
tried summarily by a Magistrate and no sentence of 
imprisonment for a term exceeding one year shall be passed In 
the case of any conviction for an offence which is summarily 
tried under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>18948</tid>
<number> 73</number> Compunding of offences.
<section><tid>1366889</tid>
<number>1</number>Any offence punishable under  
section 50. section 55, section 56, section 57, section 58, section 
59, section 60, section 63, section 64, section 65, section 66 or 
section 67 may, either before or after the institution of the 
prosecution, be compounded by the Director or such other officer as 
may be specially authorised by him in this behalf, on payment for 
credit to the Government of such sum as the Director or such other 
officer may specify:
Provided that such sum shall not, in any case, exceed the maximum 
amount of the fine which may be imposed under this Act for the offence 
so compounded.


</section>

<section><tid>1331340</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall apply to a person who 
commits the same or similar offence within a period of three years 
from the date on which the first offence, committed by him, was 
compounded.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this sub- section, any second or 
subsequent offence committed after the expiry of a period of three 
years from the date on which the offence was previously compounded, 
shall be deemed to be a first offence.


</section>

<section><tid>1534477</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an offence has been compounded under sub- section (1), 
no proceeding or further proceeding, as the case may be, shall be 
taken against the offender in respect of the offence so compounded, 
and the offender, if in custody, shall be discharged forthwith.

</section>

<section><tid>1375462</tid>
<number>4</number>No offence under this Act shall be compounded except as 
provided by this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>823624</tid>
<number> 74</number> Offences by companies and power of court to publish name, 
place of business etc, of companies convicted.
<section><tid>1956608</tid>
<number>1</number>If an offence under  
this Act is committed by a company, every person who, at the time the 
offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible to the 
company for the conduct of the business of the company as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be 
liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to punishment if he proves that the offence was 
committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>382</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 75 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1. 7. <year>1987</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1407774</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), where 
an offence under this Act has been committed by a company and it is 
proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or conni- 
vance of, or is attributable to the neglect on the part of, any 
director, manager, secretary or other officer, such director, manager, 
secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of that 
offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1072993</tid>
<number>3</number>Where any company is convicted under this Act for contraven- 
tion of any of the provisions thereof, it shall be competent for the 
court convicting the company to cause the name and place of business 
of the company, nature of the contravention, the fact that the company 
has been so convicted and such other particulars as the court may 
consider to be appropriate in the circumstances of the case, to be 
published at the expense of the company in such newspapers or in such 
other manner as the court may direct.

</section>

<section><tid>200854</tid>
<number>4</number>No publication under sub- section (3) shall be made until the 
period for preferring an appeal against the orders of the court has 
expired without any appeal having been preferred, or such an appeal, 
having been preferred, has been disposed of.

</section>

<section><tid>1117967</tid>
<number>5</number>The expenses of any publication under sub- section (3) shall 
be recoverable from the company as if it were a fine imposed by the 
court.
Explanation.-- For the purposes of this section-


<subsection><tid>1376274</tid>
<number>a</number>" company" means any body corporate and includes a, firm 
or other association of individuals; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1364981</tid>
<number>b</number>" director", in relation to a firm, means a partner, in 
the firm.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1768222</tid>
<number>75</number>Provisions of Indian Penal Code not to apply to any 
offence punishable under this Act. The provisions of the Indian Penal 
Code, (45 of <year>1860</year>.) in so far as such provisions relate to offences 
with regard to weights and measures, shall not apply to any offence 
which is punishable under this Act.
PART

TRAINING INSTITUTE

PART VII

TRAINING INSTITUTE



</article>



<article><tid>1666662</tid>
<number> 76</number> Establishment of a training Institute and provisions for 
training thereat.
<section><tid>1400774</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be established by the Central  
Government, at such place as it may think fit, an Institute to be 
known as the" Indian Institute of Legal Metrology" (hereafter referred  
  to as the" Institute") for imparting training in legal metrology and 
other allied branches of knowledge.

</section>

<section><tid>246457</tid>
<number>2</number>The management and control of the Institute, which shall 
vest in the Central Government, shall be carried on in accordance with 
such regulations as may be made by the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1736980</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Government shall provide the Institute with such 
teaching staff and other employees, and with such equipments and other 
facilities as it may think fit to enable the Institute to function 
effectively as an institution for imparting adequate training in legal 
metrology and other allied branches of knowledge.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>383</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1662822</tid>
<number>4</number>The courses and curricula for training at the Institute and 
period for: which the- training may be imparted thereat for each course 
shall be such as may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1542835</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government shall prescribe the minimum qualifi- 
cations which a person shall possess in order to be eligible for 
admission to the Institute for receiving training thereat and 
different, qualifications may be prescribed for different courses of 
training imparted at the Institute,

</section>

<section><tid>1937330</tid>
<number>6</number>The Central Government and every State Government may de- 
pute, in. such batches as may be convenient to the Institute employees 
of, or above, the rank of an Inspector for receiving training at the 
Institute and the Central Government may also arrange for the 
training, at the Institute, of such other persons as it may think fit.

</section>

<section><tid>56451</tid>
<number>7</number>The Institute may,--

<subsection><tid>1441178</tid>
<number>a</number>carry out such researches in legal metrology and other 
allied branches of knowledge as may be entrusted to it by the 
Central Government, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>886849</tid>
<number>b</number>hold such seminars, meetings or other gatherings as it 
may think fit.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>710247</tid>
<number>77</number>Training at other places. Where the Central Government is of 
opinion that in addition to the training imparted at the Institute, it 
is necessary to impart to an employee; not below the rank of an 
Inspector, further specialised training which is not provided for at 
the Institute, it may send such employee to such other place, 
authority or institution as it may think fit for receiving such 
specialised training.
PART

MISCELLANEOUS PART VIII 
MISCELLANEOUS



</article>



<article><tid>575065</tid>
<number>78</number>Survey and statistics. The Central Government shall make, or 
cause to be Made, such surveys and collect, or cause to be collected, 
such statistics as it may consider necessary with a view to 
ascertaining the extent to which any standard of weight, measure or 
numeration established by or under this Act has been implemented in 
any area or in relation to a every class of undertakings, users or 
goods and it shall be the duty of every person using weight or measure 
or making any numeration to render such assistance as the person 
making such survey or collecting such statistics may require.


</article>



<article><tid>846341</tid>
<number> 79</number> Conversion of non- metric weights and measures into 
standard units or weights or measures.
<section><tid>1677004</tid>
<number>1</number>The value expressed in  
terms of any unit of weight or measure other than in terms of the 
standard units of weight or measure may be converted into the value 
expressed in terms of a standard unit of weight or measure at the rate 
specified in the Schedule.

</section>

<section><tid>102192</tid>
<number>2</number>All references in any enactment or in any notification, rule 
or order made under any enactment, or in any contract, deed or other 
instrument, for the time being in force, to a value expressed in terms 
of any unit of weight, measure or numeration other than that of a 
standard unit of weight, measure or numeration shall be construed as 
references to that value expressed in terms of standard units of 
weight, measure or numeration, as the case may be, converted at the 
rates specified in the Schedule.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>384</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1555795</tid>
<number> 80</number> Non- metric weight or weight or measure not to be mentioned 
in any documents, etc., or to form the basis of any contract after 
the commencement of this Act.
<section><tid>1665989</tid>
<number>1</number>No unit of weight, measure or  
numeration shall, after the commencement of this Act, be stated in any 
enactment, notification, rule, order, contract, deed or other 
instrument in terms of any unit of weight, measure or numeration other 
than that of a standard unit of weight, measure or numeration.

</section>

<section><tid>294229</tid>
<number>2</number>On and from the commencement of this Act, no weight, measure 
or number other than the standard weight, measure or number shall be 
used in, or form the basis of, any contract or other agreement in 
relation to any inter- State or international trade or commerce:
Provided that in relation to any goods which are exported the 
weight, measure or number of such goods may be indicated thereon, or 
in any contract, in addition to the standard units of weight, measure 
or numeration, in accordance with any other system of weight, measure 
or numeration if the person to whom the export is to be made so 
requires.


</section>

<section><tid>767995</tid>
<number>3</number>Any contract or other agreement in contravention of the 
provisions of sub- section (2) shall be void.

</section>

<section><tid>1368260</tid>
<number>4</number>No written record of the results of any measurement shall be 
maintained in any unit other than the standard unit of weight, measure 
or numeration established by or under this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1467391</tid>
<number> 81</number> Appeals.
<section><tid>317670</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the provisions of sub- section (2),  
any person aggrieved by an order made under section 30 or section 36 
may prefer an appeal against such order to the Director, or where the 
order, has been made by the Director, to the Central Government.

</section>

<section><tid>1283786</tid>
<number>2</number>Every such appeal shall be preferred within sixty days from 
the date on which the impugned order was made:
Provided that the appellate authority may, if it is satisfied 
that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from preferring 
the appeal within the said period of sixty days, permit the appellant 
to prefer the appeal within a further period of sixty days.


</section>

<section><tid>624777</tid>
<number>3</number>On receipt of any such appeal, the appellate authority 
shall, after giving the parties to the appeal a reasonable opportunity 
of being heard and after making such inquiry as it deems proper, make 
such order, as it may think fit, confirming, modifying or reversing 
the order appealed against or may send back the case with such 
direction as it may think fit for a fresh order after taking 
additional evidence, if necessary.

</section>

<section><tid>1183748</tid>
<number>4</number>Every appeal shall be preferred on payment of such fee, as 
may be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>492303</tid>
<number>5</number>The Central Government may, on its own motion or otherwise, 
call for and examine the record of any proceeding (including a pro-  
  ceeding in appeal) in which any decision or order has been made, for 
the purpose of satisfying itself as to the correctness, legality or 
propriety of such decision or order and may pass such order thereon as 
it may think fit:
Provided that no decision or order shall be varied under this 
subsection so as to prejudicially affect any person unless such person 
has been given a reasonable opportunity of showing cause against the 
proposed action.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>385</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>293440</tid>
<number> 82</number> Levy of fees.
<section><tid>272945</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central; Government may, by rules made  
under section 83, specify such fees, not exceeding--

<subsection><tid>12630</tid>
<number>a</number>five thousand rupees, for the approval of the model of 
any weight or measure intended to be made or manufactured for 
sale, purchase, distribution or delivery in the course of any 
inter- State trade or commerce;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1007469</tid>
<number>b</number>one thousand, rupees, for the verification and stamping 
of a weight or measure of the first category within the 
meaning of section 41;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1447974</tid>
<number>c</number>five thousand rupees, for the verification and stamping of 
a weight or measure of the second category, within the 
meaning of section 41;-

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1148745</tid>
<number>d</number>one rupee for every 100 words or less, for the grant of 
copies' of nature; any document, not, being a document of a 
confidential

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>186606</tid>
<number>e</number>ten rupees, for the registration of exporters or 
importers of weights and measures;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1668383</tid>
<number>f</number>twenty- five rupees for any appeal preferred under this 
Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1881092</tid>
<number>2</number>No approval, verification or stamping shall be, made, copy 
granted, registration made or appeal entertained unless the fee 
prescribed therefor under sub- section (1) has been paid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>761486</tid>
<number> 83</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>580006</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification, make, rules for carrying out the provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>941418</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such. rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>109141</tid>
<number>a</number>supplementary, derived, special or other units of, 
weight or measure, standard symbols or definitions, as 
recommended by the General Conference on Weights and Measures 
or the International Organisation of Legal Metrology;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>344802</tid>
<number>b</number>multiples and sub- multiples of, and physical constants, 
ratios or coefficients in relation to units of weight or 
measure, as recommended by the General Conference on, Weights 
and Measures or the International Organisation of Legal 
Metrology;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>880429</tid>
<number>c</number>denominations of decimal multiples and sub- multiples of 
numerals and the manner in which they shall be written;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1750118</tid>
<number>d</number>periodical intervals at which the accuracy of the objects 
or equipments referred to in sub- section (1) or sub- section 
 (2) of section 16 shall be certified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>257469</tid>
<number>e</number>the manner in which and the conditions under which 
every national prototype, referred to in section 15, and 
every object or equipment referred to in section 16, shall be 
kept;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>422910</tid>
<number>f</number>the manner in which and the conditions under which 
every reference standard, secondary standard or working 
standard shall be kept;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>386</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>797344</tid>
<number>g</number>the place at which, the authority by which, the manner 
in which and the periodical intervals at which, every 
reference standard, secondary standard and working standard 
shall be verified and authenticated;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1290276</tid>
<number>h</number>the custody in which every reference standard, 
secondary standard or working standard shall be kept;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1257920</tid>
<number>i</number>the physical characteristics, configuration, 
constructional details, materials, equipment, performance, 
tolerances methods or procedures of tests, in relation to 
weights or measures;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1938707</tid>
<number>j</number>the conditions, limitations and restrictions under 
which nonstandard weights or measures may be manufactured for 
export or may be exported;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1630144</tid>
<number>k</number>the manner of disposal of any commodity which is sub- 
ject to speedy or natural decay;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>892810</tid>
<number>l</number>class of goods or undertakings in relation to which, or 
class of users in relation to whom, no transaction, dealing 
or contract shall be made or had except by specified weight, 
measure or number;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1760009</tid>
<number>m</number>registers and records to be maintained by persons 
referred to in section 35;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1290710</tid>
<number>n</number>the authority to whom models are to be submitted for 
approval;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>114570</tid>
<number>o</number>the number of models, drawings and other information 
which are to be submitted for the approval of the model;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1363540</tid>
<number>p</number>the conditions under which the performance of any model 
is to be tested;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1133282</tid>
<number>q</number>the manner in which the number of model and certificate 
shall be inscribed on every weight or measure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>895830</tid>
<number>r</number>the manner of declaration of the contents of a package 
and specification of the unit of weight, measure or number 
in accordance with which the retail sale price shall be 
declared on the package;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1348721</tid>
<number>s</number>the standard quantities or number in which commodities 
way be packed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>691470</tid>
<number>t</number>the capacity up to which a package shall be filled;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1484322</tid>
<number>u</number>the reasonable variations in the net contents of a 
packaged commodity which may be caused by the method of 
packing or ordinary exposure;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>532957</tid>
<number>v</number>the classes of weights or measures which would fall in 
the first category or the second category;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1795213</tid>
<number>w</number>the special seal by which weights or measures of the 
first category shall be stamped;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1687574</tid>
<number>x</number>periodical returns to be submitted by every 
manufacturer dealer or other person in a transferor State;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1067323</tid>
<number>y</number>the form and manner in which, and the time within 
which, applications for inclusion of a name in the register 
of exporters and Importers of weights and measures shall be 
made;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>387</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1162236</tid>
<number>z</number>the period for which certificate of registration of an 
exporter or importer of weights or measures may be renewed;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1183768</tid>
<number>za</number>the courses and curricula for, and the period of, 
training at the Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1629022</tid>
<number>zb</number>the minimum qualifications for admission to the 
Institute;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>854286</tid>
<number>zc</number>the scales in accordance with which fees may be collec- 
ted under section 82;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1435875</tid>
<number>zd</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>547692</tid>
<number>3</number>In making any rule under this section, the Central 
Government may provide that a breach thereof shall be punishable with 
fine which may extend to two thousand rupees.

</section>

<section><tid>959878</tid>
<number>4</number>Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for, a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised In one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1635098</tid>
<number> 84</number> Continuance of certain weights and measures during 
transitional period.
<section><tid>1176196</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding that this Act has come into  
force in respect of any area or class of goods or undertakings or 
class of weights and measures or users of weights and measures in the 
State of Sikkim, the Central Government way, by notification, permit 
the continuance of the use, after such commencement, in respect of 
that area or class of goods or undertakings,' or for classes of users 
of weights and measures, of such weights and measures in addition to 
the standard weights or measures, and for such period, not exceeding 
five years, as may be specified in the notification.

</section>

<section><tid>207098</tid>
<number>2</number>Nothing in sub- section (1) shall be deemed to empower the 
Central Government to Issue any notification in respect of any weight 
or measure which was not in use in the State of Sikkim immediately 
before the commencement of this Act.



</section>

</article>



 </act>