<act><title>
THE
RAILWAY PROPERTY (UNLAWFUL POSSESSION) ACT, 1966</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Railway Property (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1966.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 


   







  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definition.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 


 <section>
 <number>a</number>
 “Force” means
the Railway Protection Force constituted under section 3 of the Railway
Protection Force Act, 1957 (23 of 1957); 
 

 </section><section>
 <number>b</number>
 “member of the
Force” means a person appointed to the Force, other than a superior officer; 
 

 </section><section> <number>c</number>
 “officer of the
Force” means an officer of and above the rank of Assistant Sub-Inspector
appointed to the Force and includes a superior officer; 
 

 </section><section>
 <number>d</number>
 “railway
property” includes any goods, money or valuable security or animal, belonging
to, or in the charge or possession of, a railway administration; 
 

 </section><section>
 <number>e</number>
 “superior
officer” means any of the officers appointed under Section 4 of the Railway
Protection Force Act, 1957 (23 of 1957), and includes any other officer
appointed by the Central Government as a superior officer of the force; 
 

 </section><section> <number>f</number>
 words
and expressions used but not defined in this Act and defined in the Indian
Railway Act, 1890 (9 of 1890), shall have the meanings respectively assigned to
them under that Act. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Penalty for unlawful possession of railway property.—Whoever
is found, or is proved to have been, in possession of any railway property
reasonably suspected of having been stolen or unlawful obtained shall, unless he
proves that the railway property came into his possession lawfully, be
punishable—
 


 <section><number>a</number>
 for the first offence, with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, or with fine, or with
both and in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be mentioned in the
judgment of the Court, such imprisonment shall not be less than one year and
such fine shall not be less than one thousand rupees; 
 

 </section><section><number>b</number>
 for the second or a subsequent
offence, with imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years and also
with fine and in the absence of special and adequate reasons to be mentioned in
the judgment of the Court, such imprisonment shall not be less than two years
and such fine shall not be less than two thousand rupees. 
 


  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Punishment for connivance at offences.—Any
owner or occupier of land or building, or any agent of such owner or occupier
incharge of the management of that land or building, who wilfully connives at an
offence against the provisions of this Act, shall be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to five years, or with both.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Offences under the Act not to be 
      cognizable.—Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code 
      of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)<footcitenum>2</footcitenum> an offence under this Act shall not be 
      cognizable.  
    




  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Power to arrest without warrant.—Any
superior officer or member of the Force may, without an order from a Magistrate
and without a warrant, arrest any person who has been concerned in an offence
punishable uner this Act or against whom a reasonable suspicion exists of his
having been so concerned.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Disposal of persons arrested.—Every
person arrested for an offence punishable under this Act shall, if the arrest
was made by a person other than an officer of the Force, be forwarded without
delay to the nearest officer of the Force.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>8</number>
Inquiry how to be made against arrested persons.—
<section><number>1</number>
When any person is arrested by an officer of the Force for an offence punishable
under this Act or is forwarded to him under Section 7, he shall proceed to
inquire into the charge against such person.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
For this purpose the officer of the Force may exercise the same powers and shall
be subject to the same provisions as the officer incharge of a police station
may exercise and is subject to under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of
1898), when investigating a cognizable case:
 


 Provided
that—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
 if the officer of the Force is
of opinion that there is sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of suspicion
against the accused person, he shall either admit him to bail to appear before a
Magistrate having jurisdiction in the case, or forward him in custody to such
Magistrate; 
 

 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
 if it appears to the officer
of the Force that there is no sufficient evidence or reasonable ground of
suspicion against the accused person, he shall release the accused person, on
his executing a bond, with or without sureties as the officer of the Force may
direct, to appear, if and when so required before the Magistrate having
jurisdiction, and shall make a full report of all the particulars of the case to
his official superior. 
 


  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Power to summon persons to give evidence and produce documents.—
<section><number>1</number>
An officer of the Force shall have power to summon any person whose attendance
he considers necessary either to give evidence or to produce a document, or any
other thing in any inquiry which such officer in making for any of the purposes
of this Act.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
A summons to produce documents or other things may be for the production of
certain specified documents or things or for the production of all documents or
things of a certain description in the possession or under the control of the
person summoned.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
All persons, so summoned, shall be bound to attend either in person or by an
authorized agent as such officer may direct; and all persons so summoned shall
be bound to state the truth upon any subject respecting which they are examined
or make statements and to produce such documents and other things as may be
required:
 


 Provided
that the exemptions under sections 132 and 133 of the Code of Civil Procedure,
1908 (5 of 1908), shall be applicable to requisitions for attendance under this
section.
 


 </section><section><number>4</number>
Every such inquiry as aforesaid shall be deemed to be a “judicial
proceeding” within the meaning of sections 193 and 228 of the Indian Penal
Code (45 of 1860).
 



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Issue of search warrant.—
<section><number>1</number>
If an officer of the Force has reason to believe that any place is used for the
deposit or sale of railway property which has been stolen or unlawfully
obtained, he shall make an application to the Magistrate, having jurisdiction
over the area in which that place is situate, for issue of a search warrant.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Magistrate to whom an application is made under sub-section (1), may, after
such inquiry as he thinks necessary, by his warrant authorise any officer of the
Force—
 


 <subsection><number>a</number>
to enter with such assistance as may be required, such place;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
to search the same in the manner specified in the warrant;
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
to take possession of any railway property therein found which he reasonably
suspects to be stolen or unlawfully obtained; and
 


 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
to convey such railway property before a Magistrate, or to guard the same on the
spot until the offender is taken before a Magistrate, or otherwise to dispose
thereof in some place of safety.
 



  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Searches and arrests how to be made.—All
searches and arrests made under this Act shall be carried out in accordance with
the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898)<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>,
relating respectively to searches and arrests made under that Code.
  
  





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Officers required to assist.—All
officers of Government and all village officers are hereby empowered and
required to assist the superior officers and members of the force in the
enforcement of this Act.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Power of courts to order forfeiture of vehicles, etc.—Any
court trying an offence punishable under this Act may order the forfeiture to
Government of any property in respect of which the court is satisfied that an
offence under this Act has been committed and may also order the forfeiture of
any receptacles, packages or coverings in which such property is contained and
the animals, vehicles, or other conveyances used in carrying the property.
 



  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Act to override other laws.—The provisions of this Act shall 
      have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in 
      any other law for the time being in force.
 
  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number>
Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number>
The Railway Stores (Unlawful Possession) Act, 1955 (51 of 1955) is hereby
repealed.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
Nothing contained in this Act shall apply to offences punishable under the Act
hereby repealed and such offences may be investigated and tried as if this Act
had not been passed.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
The mention of particular matters in sub-section (2) shall not be held to
prejudice or affect the general application of section 6 of the General Act,
1857 (10 of 1897), with regard to the effect of repeals.
 



  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
1st April, 1968, vide S.O. 1225, dated 1-4-1968, Gazette of India,
Extra., 1968, Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), p. 413.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> See now the Code of 
      Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number>
See now the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>