<act><title>

    THE PROVINCIAL INSOLVENCY ACT, 1920</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act 
    may be called the Provincial Insolvency Act, 1920. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to 

    1[the whole of India 
    except 

    2[the territories 
    which, immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B 
    States] and] the Scheduled Districts.3
 
 
State Amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 1, for sub-section (2), substitute the following sub-section:—
 
           “(2) It extends to the whole State of Andhra Pradesh except the Scheduled 
      Areas”.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]
 
Madhya Pradesh.—In 
      section 1, in sub-section (2), after the words “Part B States” add the 
      words “other than the Madhya Bharat and Sironj regions of the State of 
      Madhya Pradesh”.
 
[Vide Madhya Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1958, sec. 3 and Sch., Part A, item 18.]
 <subsection>
<number>Mysore</number>—In section 1, 
      in sub-section (2), after the words “except the territories which 
      immediately before the 1st November, 1956, were comprised in Part B 
      States”, add the words “other than the territories specified in clause (a) 
      and clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 7 of the States 
      Reorganisation Act, 1956 (Central Act 37 of 1956)”.
 
[Vide Mysore Act 7 of 
      1963, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 2-12-1963).]
</subsection>
 

 
 

 












 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, 
    unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    “creditor” includes a decree-holder, 
    “debt” includes a judgment-debt, and “debtor” includes a judgment-debtor; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    “District Court” means the 
    Principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction in any area outside the local 
    limits for the time being of the Presidency-towns 
1[***]
    
1[***] 
    " 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    “property” includes any property over 
    which or the profits of which any person has a disposing power which he may 
    exercise for his own benefit; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    “secured creditor” means a person 
    holding a mortgage, charge or lien on the property of the debtor or any part 
    thereof as a security for a debt due to him from the debtor; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    “transfer of property” includes a 
    transfer of any interest in property and the creation of any charge upon 
    property. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and 
    expressions used in this Act and defined in the Code of Civil Procedure, 
    1908 (5 of 1908), and not hereinbefore defined shall have the same meanings 
    as those respectively attributed to them by the said Code. 
 
 

      State Amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 2, for clause (b) substitute the following clause, namely:—
 
         “(b) “District Court” 
      means the principal Civil Court of original jurisdiction and includes the 
      City Civil Court of Hyderabad”.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 2,—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>   omit the 
      word ‘and’ occurring in clause (e); and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>   after 
      clause (e), insert the following:—
 
         “(ee) the 
      State Government in relation to the Union Territory of Goa, Daman and Diu 
      means the administrator thereof; and”.
 
[Vide Goa, Daman and 
      Diu Act 1 of 1968, sec. 3.]
  
 
COMMENTS
 
‘Property’: 
      Meaning of
 
      “property” means the personal 
      property of an insolvent, which he can dispose of whenever he wants; 
      Vraj Kuwar Bai v. Kunjbiharilal Krishna Chandra, AIR 1971 MP 
      109. 
 
      The trust property held by an 
      insolvent is not his property; Banarsi Das v. Bhagat Ram, 
      AIR 1934 Lah 683. 
 
‘Debtor’: 
      Meaning of
 
      A ‘debtor’ is a person against 
      whom the creditor had filed an insolvency application; P.S. Ramaswami 
      Iyer v. Subramanian Chettiar, AIR 1938 Mad 267. 
 
‘Debt’: 
      Means
 
      The term ‘debt’ means an 
      amount payable in regard to money demand, recoverable by action; Bharat 
      National Bank Ltd. v. Bishan Lal, AIR 1932 Lah 212. 
 
Movable 
      Property
 
      The right of the partner to 
      file a suit for accounts of dissolved partnership is a movable property;
      Thawerdas Jethanand v. Seth Vishindas Nihalchand, AIR 1925 
      Sind 72.
</subsection>
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Insolvency jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    District Courts shall be the Courts having jurisdiction under this Act: 
 
Provided that 
    the State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, invest 
    any Court subordinate to a District Court with jurisdiction in any class of 
    cases, and any Court so invested shall within the local limits of its 
    jurisdiction have concurrent jurisdiction with the District Court under this 
    Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of this Act, a Court of Small Causes shall be deemed to be 
    subordinate to the District Court. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 3, after sub-section (2) add the following sub-section, namely:—
 
         “(3) In the 
      cities of Hyderabad and Secunderabad, the State Government may, by 
      notification in the Andhra Pradesh Gazette, invest the Chief Judge and the 
      Additional Judges of the City Small Causes Court and the Additional Judges 
      of the City Civil Court with jurisdiction in any class of cases.”
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 5 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]
 

 
COMMENTS
 
Power of 
      Civil Judge
 
A Civil Judge has the powers 
      of the District Judge under this section, although the Court of the Civil 
      Judge is subordinate to that of the District Judge; Kewal Singh v.
      Ram Chander, AIR 1990 All 99. 
 
Power of 
      District Judge
 
If the amount of debt is more 
      than Rs. 5,000 the insolvency proceedings should be conducted by the 
      District Judge and not by Deputy Commissioner; Rup Chand Panna Lal 
      v. Subedar M.A. Huq, AIR 1939 Pat 73. 
 
Jurisdiction 
      of District Court
 
Under section 3, District 
      Court has the jurisdiction to deal with insolvency petition. Even the High 
      Court has the jurisdiction to deal with such cases; Harkishan Lal 
      v. Peoples Bank of Northern India Ltd., AIR 1936 Lah 608. 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Power of 
    Court to decide all questions arising in insolvency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, the Court shall have full power to 
    decide all questions whether of title or priority, or of any nature 
    whatsoever, and whether involving matters of law or of fact, which may arise 
    in any case of insolvency coming within the cognizance of the Court, or 
    which the Court may deem it expedient or necessary to decide for the purpose 
    of doing complete justice or making a complete distribution of property in 
    any such case. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this Act and notwithstanding anything contained in any 
    other law for the time being in force, every such decision shall be final 
    and binding for all purposes as between, on the one hand, the debtor and the 
    debtor’s estate and, on the other hand, all claimants against him or it and 
    all persons claiming through or under them or any of them. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    Court does not deem it expedient or necessary to decide any question of the 
    nature referred to in sub-section (1), but has reason to believe that the 
    debtor has a saleable interest in any property, the Court may without 
    further inquiry sell such interest in such manner and subject to such 
    conditions as it may think fit. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> General 
    powers of Courts.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this Act, the Court, in regard to proceedings under this 
    Act, shall have the same powers and shall follow the same procedure as it 
    has and follows in the exercise of original civil jurisdiction. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject as 
    aforesaid, High Courts and District Courts, in regard to proceedings under 
    this Act in Courts subordinate to them, shall have the same powers and shall 
    follow the same procedure as they respectively have and follow in regard to 
    civil suits. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      the Act, for the words “High Court” (whether in singular or plural), 
      wherever they occur, substitute the words “Judicial Commissioner”.
 
[Vide Goa, Daman and 
      Diu Act 1 of 1968, sec. 3(2).]
 

 
COMMENTS
 
Power of 
      Civil Court
 
Under section 5, the 
      Insolvency Court being a Civil Court has the powers to grant an 
      injunction; Ramnad District Central Cooperative Bank v. Official 
      Receiver of Ramnad, AIR 1954 Mad 12. 

  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Acts of insolvency.—1[
<section><number>1</number>] 
    A debtor commits an act of insolvency in each of the following cases, 
    namely:——1[(1)] 
    A debtor commits an act of insolvency in each of the following cases, 
    namely\:—" 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if, in 
2[India] 
    or elsewhere, he makes a transfer of all or substantially all his property 
    to a third person for the benefit of his creditors generally;
2[India] 
    or elsewhere, he makes a transfer of all or substantially all his property 
    to a third person for the benefit of his creditors generally;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if, in 
2[India] 
    or elsewhere, he makes a transfer of his property or of any part thereof 
    with intent to defeat or delay his creditors;
2[India] 
    or elsewhere, he makes a transfer of his property or of any part thereof 
    with intent to defeat or delay his creditors;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    if in 
2[India] 
    or elsewhere, he makes any transfer of his property, or of any part thereof, 
    which would, under this or any other enactment for the time being in force, 
    be void as a fraudulent preference if he were adjudged an insolvent;
2[India] 
    or elsewhere, he makes any transfer of his property, or of any part thereof, 
    which would, under this or any other enactment for the time being in force, 
    be void as a fraudulent preference if he were adjudged an insolvent;" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    if with intent to defeat or delay his 
    creditors,—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    he departs or remains out of
    3[the 
    territories to which this Act extends];
3[the 
    territories to which this Act extends];" 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    he departs from his dwelling-house or 
    usual place of business or otherwise absents himself; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    he secludes himself so as to deprive 
    his creditors of the means of communicating with him; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    if any of his property has been sold in 
    execution of the decree of any Court for the payment of money; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    if he petitions to be adjudged an 
    insolvent under the provisions of this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    if he gives notice to any of his 
    creditors that he has suspended, or that he is about to suspend, payment of 
    his debts; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    if he is imprisoned in execution 
    of the decree of any Court for the payment of money.1 tc 
    " (h) if he is imprisoned in execution of the decree of any Court for the 
    payment of money.1" 
 


    5[(2) Without 
    prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1), a debtor commits an act of 
    insolvency if a creditor, who has obtained a decree or order against him for 
    the payment of money (being a decree or order which has become final and the 
    execution whereof has not been stayed), has served on him a notice 
    (hereafter in this section referred to as the insolvency notice) as provided 
    in sub-section (3) and the debtor does not comply with that notice within 
    the period specified therein: 
 
Provided that 
    where a debtor makes an application under sub-section (5) for setting aside 
    an insolvency notice— 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>a</number>    in a case where such application is 
    allowed by the District Court, he shall not be deemed to have committed an 
    act of insolvency under this sub-section; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    in a case where such application is 
    rejected by the District Court, he shall be deemed to have committed an act 
    of insolvency under this sub-section on the date of rejection of the 
    application or the expiry of the period specified in the insolvency notice 
    for its compliance, whichever is later: 
 
Provided 
    further that no insolvency notice shall be served on a debtor residing, 
    whether permanently or temporarily, outside India, unless the creditor 
    obtained the leave of the District Court therefor. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> An 
    insolvency notice under sub-section (2) shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    be in the prescribed form; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    be served in the prescribed manner; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    specify the amount due under the decree 
    or order and require the debtor to pay the same or to furnish security for 
    the payment of such amount to the satisfaction of the creditor or his agent; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    specify for its compliance a period of 
    not less than one month after its service on the debtor or, if it is to be 
    served on a debtor residing, whether permanently or temporarily, outside 
    India, such period (being not less than one month) as may be specified by 
    the order of the District Court granting leave for the service of such 
    notice; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    state the consequences of 
    non-compliance with the notice. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> No 
    insolvency notice shall be deemed to be invalid by reason only that the sum 
    specified therein as the amount due under the decree or order exceeds the 
    amount actually due, unless the debtor, within the period specified in the 
    insolvency notice for its compliance, gives notice to the creditor that the 
    sum specified in the insolvency notice does not correctly represent the 
    amount due under the decree or order: 
 
Provided that 
    if the debtor does not give any such notice as aforesaid, he shall be deemed 
    to have complied with the insolvency notice if, within the period specified 
    therein for its compliance, he takes such steps as would have constituted a 
    compliance with the insolvency notice had the actual amount due been 
    correctly specified therein. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any person 
    served with an insolvency notice may, within the period specified therein 
    for its compliance, apply to the District Court to set aside the insolvency 
    notice on any of the following grounds, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that he has a counter-claim or set-off 
    against the creditor which is equal to or is in excess of the amount due 
    under the decree or order and which he could not, under any law for the time 
    being in force, prefer in the suit or proceeding in which the decree or 
    order was passed; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that he is entitled to have the decree 
    or order set aside under any law providing for the relief of indebtedness 
    and that— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    he has made an application before the 
    competent authority under such law for the setting aside of the decree or 
    order; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the time allowed for the making of 
    such application has not expired; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the decree or order is not 
    executable under the provisions of any law referred to in clause (b) on the 
    date of application. 
 

    Explanation.—For the purposes of 
    this section the act of an agent may be the act of the principal. 
 
 

State Amendments
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 6, in sub-section,—
 <subsubsection>
      <number>1</number>   in clause (g) at 
      the end delete the word “or” and add same at the end of clause (h);
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>2</number>   after the clause 
      (h) insert the following clause, namely:—
 <subsubsubsection>
      <number>i</number>   if after 
      a creditor has served an insolvency notice on him in respect of a decree 
      or an order for the payment of any amount due to such creditor, the 
      execution of which is not stayed, he does not, within the period specified 
      in the notice (which shall be not less than one month) comply with the 
      requirements of the notice:
 
      Provided that the debtor shall not be deemed to have committed an act of 
      insolvency for not complying with the requirements of the notice, if he 
      has a counter-claim or set-off which equals or exceeds the decretal amount 
      or amount ordered to be paid by him and which he could not lawfully set up 
      in the suit or proceedings in which the decree or order was made against 
      him.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
      <number>ii</number>   
      Insolvency notice.—(1) An insolvency notice under this Act shall be in 
      the prescribed form and shall be served in the prescribed manner. 

 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
      
      <number>2</number> The said notice shall require the debtor to pay the amount due under 
      the decree or order or to furnish security for the payment of such amount 
      to the satisfaction of the creditor or his agent and shall also state the 
      consequences of non-compliance with the notice.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>3</number> The 
      insolvency notice shall not be invalidated by reason only that the sum 
      shown therein as the amount due to the creditor exceeds the amount 
      actually due, unless the debtor, within the time allowed for payment, 
      gives notice to the creditor that he disputes the validity of the 
      insolvency notice on the ground of such mis-statement; but where the 
      debtor does not give a decree as aforesaid he shall be deemed to have 
      complied with the insolvency notice if within the time allowed, he takes 
      steps as would have constituted a compliance with the notice had the 
      actual amount due been correctly shown therein”.
 
[Vide Goa, Daman and 
      Diu Act 1 of 1968, sec. 3(4).]
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In its 
      application to the Bombay and Saurashtra areas of the State, amendments 
      are the same as in Maharashtra.—
 
[Vide Act 11 of 1960, 
      sec. 87 and Gujarat AL (8th Am.) O., 1961 (w.r.e.f. 1-5-1960).]
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In its 
      application to the Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra.—(1) In section 
      6, for clause (i) as inserted by Bombay Act 25 of 1939, substitute the 
      following, namely:—
 
      “(i) if, 
      after a creditor has served an insolvency notice on him under this Act in 
      respect of a decree or an order for the payment of any amount due to such 
      creditor, the execution of which is not stayed, he does not, within the 
      period specified in the notice which shall not be less than one month 
      either comply with the requirements of the notice or satisfy the Court 
      that he has a counter-claim or set-off which equals or exceeds the decretal amount or the amount ordered to be paid by him and which he could 
      not lawfully set up in the suit or proceeding in which the decree or order 
      was made against him.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 68 of 
      1948, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 19-6-1939), Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87 
      (w.e.f. 1-5-1960).]
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>2</number> after section 6, insert 
      the following section, namely:—
 
      “6A.
      Insolvency notice.—(1) An insolvency notice under this Act shall be in 
      the prescribed from and shall be served in the prescribed manner. It shall 
      require the debtor to pay the amount due under the decree or order, or to 
      furnish security for the payment of such amount to the satisfaction of the 
      creditor or his agent, or to satisfy the Court that he has a counter-claim 
      or set-off which equals or exceeds the decretal amount or the amount 
      ordered to be paid by him and which he could not lawfully set up in the 
      suit or proceeding in which the decree or order made against him and shall 
      state the consequences of non-compliance with the notice.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
      <number>2</number> Such 
      notice shall not be invalidated by reason only that the sum specified in 
      the notice as the amount due exceeds the amount actually due, unless the 
      debtor within the time allowed for payment gives notice to the creditor 
      that he disputes the validity of the notice on the ground of such mis-statements; 
      but if the debtor does not give such notice, he shall be deemed to have 
      complied with the insolvency notice if within the time allowed he takes 
      such steps as would have constituted a compliance with the notice had the 
      actual amount due been correctly specified therein.” 
 
[Vide Bombay Act 15 of 
      1939, sec. 3(b) (w.e.f. 19-6-1939) as amended by 68 of 1948, sec. 2 (w.r.e.f. 
      19-6-1939); Act 11 of 1960, sec. 87.] 
 <subsubsubsection>
<number>Mysore</number>—In sections 6 
      and 6A, clause (i) in the same as in Maharashtra.
 
[Vide Mysore Act 7 of 
      1963, sec. 5(1) (w.e.f. 2-12-1963).]
  
 
COMMENTS
 

      Applicability
 
Section 6(1)(b) of the Act is 
      applicable only when the debtor transfers his property with the intention 
      to defeat or delay all the creditors; V. Sanjeevi Reddy v.
      K. Ellappa Reddy, AIR 1967 AP 243. 
 
Assignment 
      of property
 
If a trade assigns all his 
      property except on some substantial contemporaneous payment in future that 
      is an act of bankruptcy, and is void against the creditors and assignee 
      simply because nothing is left with which carry on his business; whereas 
      if he receives substantial assistance something is left to carry on the 
      business; Khoo Kwat Siew v. Wooi Taife Hwat; (1892) 19 IA 
      15. 
 
Burden of 
      proof
 
The burden to show the 
      fraudulent nature of transaction is on the petitioner; Official 
      Receiver v. P.L.K.M.R.M. Chettiyar Firm, AIR 1931 PC 75. 
 
Conduct of 
      an agent: Liability
 
A man cannot commit any act of 
      bankruptcy by an act of his agent which he has not authorised, and of 
      which act he had no cognisance. Of course in a sense very act of an agent 
      must have the authority of the principal in order to affect him; Kastur 
      Chand v. Dhanpat Singh, (1896) 22 IA 62. 
 
An order of adjudication can 
      be made against a firm if there was an act of insolvency by an agent of 
      the firm which was such as must necessarily be imputed to the firm. The 
      Explanation to section 6 of the Act says “for the purpose of this section 
      the act of the agent may be the act of the principal”. The Explanation 
      does not lay down that an act of insolvency of the agent shall be 
      attributed to the principal but that it may be treated as the act  of the 
      principal but that it may be treated as the act of the principal; Firm  
      Mukund Lal v.  Purushottam Singh, AIR 1968 SC 1182. 
 
Ingredients
 
Under section 6(1)(d), the 
      main ingredient is the intention to defeat or delay the creditors in order 
      to constitute an act of insolvency. Where a debtor makes an attempt to 
      disentitle the creditor to enjoy the fruits of decree, it does not 
      constitute an act of insolvency; Maung Nyun Tin v. Saw EU Hoke, 
      AIR 1935 Rang 281. 
 
Limitation
 
The adjudication petition 
      should be made within a period of three months from the date when the 
      property was sold and not when the sale was confirmed; Kanai Lal Nandy 
      v. Tinkari De, AIR 1933 Cal 564. 
 
Position of 
      firm
 
A firm is not a different 
      person. An order which is passed against the firm is said to have been 
      passed against its individual partners; Mohammad Umar v. 
      Official Receiver, Rawalpindi, AIR 1929 Lah 447. 
 
Sale of 
      property
 
The sale of the property of 
      the insolvent would constitute an act of insolvency even though the sale 
      was later on set aside under section 6(1)(e); Gulabchand v. 
      Durga Bank Ltd., AIR 1954 Nag 286. 
 
Scope
 
This section talks about the 
      acts of insolvency but does not state at what particular time the act of 
      insolvency is committed and this is a question of fact which is to be 
      decided by the Court only after considering an evidence; Laxman Dhondu 
      Badgujar v. D.M. Paranjape, AIR 1958 Bom 164. 
 
The Provincial Insolvency Act 
      lays down in section 6 what acts are to be regarded as acts of insolvency. 
      It is a long list. Some are voluntary acts of the insolvent and some 
      others are involuntary. The involuntary acts are of a kind by which a 
      creditor is able to compel a debtor to disclose his insolvent condition 
      even if the insolvent is careful enough not to commit a voluntary act of 
      insolvency. One such act is that insolvent has been imprisoned in 
      execution of a decree of any Court for payment of money and another is 
      that any of his property has been sold in execution of a decree of any 
      Court for payment of money; Y. Malludora v. P. Seetharathnam; 
      AIR 1966 SC 918. 
 
Transfer of 
      property
 
Where the debtor transferred 
      his properties—residential house, car and lorry—in favour of some of his 
      creditors and other persons on the same day, it was held that debtor 
      wanted to defraud or delay payment to other creditors and the same was 
      covered under section 6(b) of the Act; K. Venkataramanasetty v. 
      Malali Venkataramanaiya Setty, AIR 1984 Karn 102. 
 
If a debtor transfers his 
      assets, it is not an act of insolvency; Pirthi v. Budh Singh, 
      AIR 1982 All 179. 
 
When act of 
      insolvency starts
 
The act of insolvency starts 
      from the date when the debtor is arrested and imprisoned and continues 
      till he continues to be in prison; Karam v. Jhanda Mal, AIR 
      1931 Lah 112. 
 
Under section 6(1)(f), an act 
      of insolvency is committed when the debtor files the adjudication 
      application, no matter if the same is rejected. When a new petition is 
      filed after the rejection of the first one, a new act of insolvency is 
      committed; Jamal Din v. Bishambar Dayal, AIR 1929 Lah 72. 
 
When person 
      adjudged insolvent
 
A person can be adjudged as an 
      insolvent only if he commits one of the acts mentioned in section 6. Where 
      the person admits that he owes money to the creditor and he is not able to 
      pay the same, then he cannot be adjudged as an insolvent; Veerayya 
      Chetty v. Doraiswamy Reddiar, AIR 1928 Mad 393.
 
 
</subsubsubsection></subsubsection>
 
 
 
 










 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Petition 
    and adjudication.—Subject to the 
    conditions specified in this Act, if a debtor commits an act of insolvency, 
    an insolvency petition may be presented either by a creditor or by the 
    debtor, and the Court may on such petition make an order (hereinafter called 
    an order of adjudication) adjudging him an insolvent. 
 

    Explanation.—The presentation of 
    a petition by the debtor shall be deemed an act of insolvency within the 
    meaning of this section, and on such petition the Court may make an order of 
    adjudication. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Exemption of corporation, etc., from insolvency proceedings.—No 
    insolvency petition shall be presented against any corporation or against 
    any association or company registered under any enactment for the time being 
    in force. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Conditions on which creditor may petition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A creditor shall not be entitled to present an insolvency petition against a 
    debtor unless— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the debt owing by the debtor to the 
    creditor, or, if two or more creditors join in the petition, the aggregate 
    amount of debts owing to such creditors, amounts to five hundred rupees, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the debt is a liquidated sum payable 
    either immediately or at some certain future time, and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the act of insolvency on which the 
    petition is grounded has occurred within three months before the 
    presentation of the petition: 
 


    1[Provided that where 
    the said period of three months referred to in clause (c) expires on a day 
    when the Court is closed, the insolvency petition may be presented on the 
    day on which the Court re-opens.] 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If the 
    petitioning creditor is a secured creditor, he shall in his petition either 
    state that he is willing to relinquish his security for the benefit of the 
    creditors in the event of the debtor being adjudged insolvent, or give an 
    estimate of the value of the security. In the latter case, he may be 
    admitted as a petitioning creditor to the extent of the balance of the debt 
    due to him after deducting the value so estimated in the same way as if he 
    were an unsecured creditor. 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Conditions on which debtor may petition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A debtor shall not be entitled to present an insolvency petition, unless he 
    is unable to pay his debts and— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> his debts amount to five hundred rupees; 
    or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> he is under arrest or imprisonment in 
    execution of the decree of any Court for the payment of money; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> an order of attachment in execution of 
    such a decree has been made, and is subsisting, against his property.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    debtor in respect of whom an order of adjudication 

    1[whether made under 
    the Presidency-towns Insolvency Act, 1909 (3 of 1909), or under this Act has 
    been annulled, owing to his failure to apply, or to prosecute an application 
    for his discharge, shall not be entitled to present an insolvency petition 
    without the leave of the Court by which the order of adjudication was 
    annulled. Such Court shall not grant leave unless it is satisfied either 
    that the debtor was prevented by any reasonable cause from presenting or 
    prosecuting his application, as the case may be, or that the petition is 
    founded on facts substantially different from those contained in the 
    petition on which the order of adjudication was made.] 
 
 

State Amendments
 
Himachal Pradesh.—Same 
      as in Punjab.
 
[Vide Himachal Pradesh 
      Act 31 of 1976, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 1-4-1979).]
 
Madhya Pradesh.—In 
      section 10, in sub-section (1), in clause (a), for the words “five hundred 
      rupees”, substitute the words “two hundred rupees”.
 
[Vide C.P. Act 2 of 
      1936, sec. 2 read with M.P. Act 23 of 1958, sec. 3(1).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In 
      section 10, in sub-section (1), insert after clause (a) the following 
      clause namely:—
 
      “(aa) his debts amount 
      to two hundred and fifty rupees, and he satisfies the Court that he is 
      entitled to summary administration of his estate under section 74 of this 
      Act; or”
 
[Vide Punjab Act 7 of 
      1934, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 19-4-1935) read with 30 of 1958, sec. 4(1); Act 31 of 
      1966, sec. 88.]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Adjudication 
      as a matter of right
 
If all the conditions of the 
      section are satisfied, then the debtor is entitled to the order of 
      adjudication as a matter of right and the same cannot be refused by the 
      Court; K.R.K. Krishnappa Chettiar v. V.V.R. Kasiviswanathan, 
      AIR 1966 Mad 331. 
 
Burden to 
      prove
 
The burden to prove that all 
      the conditions of section 10 are satisfied is on the debtor; Siya Ram 
      v. Bohra Kishori Lal, AIR 1933 All 841. 
 
Debt: 
      Meaning of
 
Under section 10, there is no 
      need for more than one debt. The word “debt” means and includes a ‘single 
      debt’; S. Damodaran Pillai v. K. Nanthedu Bava, AIR 1992 Ker 
      212. 
 
Res 
      Judicata
 
If the first petition is 
      dismissed because the evidence could not be produced, the principle of 
      res judicata will not apply to it; Hasan Din v. Kirpa Ram, 
      AIR 1928 Lah 374. 
 
Second order
 
If a person has been declared 
      as an insolvent, he cannot apply for a second order of adjudication until 
      he has been discharged from the first order or the order has been 
      annulled; Ram Das v. Sultan Husain Khan, AIR 1929 Oudh 149. 
 
What debtor 
      has to prove
 
Under section 10, debtor must 
      prove that he is not able to pay his debts, in order to be adjudicated as 
      an insolvent; Bonagiri Yellalu v. Nagulavaram Chenchu Subbaiah, 
      AIR 1972 AP 221. 

 
 
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Court 
    to which petition shall be presented.—Every 
    insolvency petition shall be presented to a Court having jurisdiction under 
    this Act in any local area in which the debtor ordinarily resides or carries 
    on business, or personally works for gain, or if he has been arrested or 
    imprisoned, where he is in custody: 
 
Provided that 
    no objection as to the place of presentment shall be allowed by any Court in 
    the exercise of appellate or revisional jurisdiction unless such objection 
    was taken in the Court by which the petition was heard at the earliest 
    possible opportunity, and unless there has been a consequent failure of 
    justice. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Verification of petition.—Every 
    insolvency petition shall be in writing and shall be signed and verified in 
    the manner prescribed by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), for 
    signing and verifying plaints. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Contents of petition.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
    insolvency petition presented by a debtor shall contain the following 
    particulars, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a statement that the debtor is unable 
    to pay his debts; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the place where he ordinarily resides 
    or carries on business or personally works for gain, or, if he has been 
    arrested or imprisoned, the place where he is in custody; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the Court (if any) by whose order he 
    has been arrested or imprisoned, or by which an order has been made for the 
    attachment of his property, together with particulars of the decree in 
    respect of which any such order has been made; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the amount and particulars of all 
    pecuniary claims against him, together with the names and residences of his 
    creditors so far as they are known to, or can by the exercise of reasonable 
    care and diligence be ascertained by him; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    the amount and particulars of all his 
    property, together with— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    a specification of the value of all 
    such property not consisting of money; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    the place or places at which any such 
    property is to be found; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    a declaration of his willingness to 
    place at the disposal of the Court all such property save in so far as it 
    includes such particulars (not being his books of account) as are exempted 
    by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), or by any other enactment 
    for the time being in force from liability to attachment and sale in 
    execution of decree; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    a statement whether the debtor has on 
    any previous occasion filed a petition to be adjudged an insolvent, and 
    (where such a petition has been filed)— 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    if such petition has been dismissed, 
    the reasons for such dismissal, or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    if the debtor has been adjudged an 
    insolvent, concise particulars of the insolvency, including a statement 
    whether any previous adjudication has been annulled and, if so, the grounds 
    therefor. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    insolvency petition presented by a creditor or creditors shall set forth the 
    particulars regarding the debtor specified in clause (b) of sub-section (1), 
    and shall also specify— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the act of insolvency committed by such 
    debtor, together with the date of its commission; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the amount and particulars of his or 
    their pecuniary claim, or claims against such debtor. 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Withdrawal of petitions.—No 
    petition, whether presented by a debtor or by a creditor, shall be withdrawn 
    without the leave of the Court. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Consolidation of petitions.—Where 
    two or more insolvency petitions are presented against the same debtor, or 
    where separate petitions are presented against joint debtors, the Court may 
    consolidate the proceedings of any of them, on such terms as the Court 
    thinks fit. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Power 
    to change carriage of proceedings.—Where 
    the petitioner does not proceed with due diligence on his petition, the 
    Court may substitute as petitioner any other creditor to whom the debtor may 
    be indebted in the amount required by this Act in the case of a petitioning 
    creditor. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Continuance of proceedings on death of debtor.—If 
    a debtor by or against whom an insolvency petition has been presented dies, 
    the proceedings in the matter shall, unless the Court otherwise orders, be 
    continued so far as may be necessary for the realization and distribution of 
    the property of the debtor. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Procedure for admission of petition.—The 
    procedure laid down in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), with 
    respect to the admission of plaints, shall, so far as it is applicable, be 
    followed in the case of insolvency petitions. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Procedure on admission of petition.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an insolvency petition is admitted, the Court shall make an order 
    fixing a date for hearing the petition. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notice of 
    the order under sub-section (1) shall be given to creditors in such manner 
    as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    debtor is not the petitioner, notice of the order under sub-section (1) 
    shall be served on him in the manner provided for the service of summons. 
 
 
 
  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Appointment of interim receiver.—The 
    Court when making an order admitting the petition may, and where the debtor 
    is the petitioner ordinarily shall, appoint an interim receiver of the 
    property of the debtor or of any part thereof and may direct him to take 
    immediate possession thereof or of any part thereof, and the interim 
    receiver shall thereupon have such of the powers conferable on a receiver 
    appointed under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), as the Court 
    may direct. If an interim receiver is not so appointed, the Court may make 
    such appointment at any subsequent time before adjudication, and the 
    provisions of 

    1[this section] shall 
    apply accordingly.—The 
    Court when making an order admitting the petition may, and where the debtor 
    is the petitioner ordinarily shall, appoint an interim receiver of the 
    property of the debtor or of any part thereof and may direct him to take 
    immediate possession thereof or of any part thereof, and the interim 
    receiver shall thereupon have such of the powers conferable on a receiver 
    appointed under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), as the Court 
    may direct. If an interim receiver is not so appointed, the Court may make 
    such appointment at any subsequent time before adjudication, and the 
    provisions of 

    1[this section] shall 
    apply accordingly." 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Uttar Pradesh.—For 
      section 20, substitute the following section namely:—
 
      “20. The Court when 
      making an order admitting the petition may, and where the debtor is a 
      petitioner, shall, appoint an interim receiver of the property of the 
      debtor and may direct such receiver to take immediate possession thereof, 
      and the interim receiver shall thereupon have such of the powers 
      conferrable on a receiver appointed under the Code of Civil Procedure, 
      1908, as the Court may direct.
 
      Where in any case an 
      interim receiver is not appointed at the time of admitting the petition, 
      the Court may make such appointment at any subsequent time before 
      adjudication and the provisions of this section shall apply accordingly.
 
 
      Explanation.—The order appointing an interim receiver may in cases 
      where the debtor is not the petitioner be in respect of either the whole 
      or a part only of the debtor’s property.”
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 
      24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).] 
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Purpose of 
      appointment
 
After admitting the insolvency 
      petition, the Court shall appoint an interim receiver to take the 
      possession of the debtor’s property. Thus, the Court gets the possession 
      of the insolvent’s property in order to protect the property from being 
      wasted or being taken out of its reach; Vadamony v. Palai 
      Central Bank Ltd., AIR 1953 Travancore 266. 
 
Right of 
      interim receiver
 
Where the property is not of 
      the debtor’s firm, the interim receiver will have no right over such 
      property under section 20; Gulab Chand v. Lachuman Sah, AIR 
      1955 Pat 413. 
 
scope
 
Section 20 of the Act empowers 
      the court to appoint an interim receiver of the property of the debtor as 
      soon as an order is made admitting the petition. For the preservation of 
      the insolvent’s property, the court may direct such interim receiver to 
      take immediate possession of the whole or any part thereof. A duty is 
      therefore cast on  the interim receiver to see that the property of the 
      debtor is not lost and for that purpose he must act quickly. As it is not 
      possible for him except on the application of the debtor to know all the 
      details of the insolvent’s property, he may take the help of the creditors 
      to ascertain what they are; Hans Raj v. Rattan Chand, AIR 
      1967 SC 178. 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Interim 
    proceedings against debtor.—At 
    the time of making an order admitting the petition or at any subsequent time 
    before adjudication the Court may either of its own motion or on the 
    application of any creditor make one or more of the following orders, 
    namely:— 
 <section>
<number>1</number>    order the debtor to give reasonable 
    security for his appearance until final orders are made upon the petition, 
    and direct, that in default of giving such security, he shall be detained in 
    the civil prison; 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>    order the attachment by actual seizure 
    of the whole or any part of the property in the possession or under the 
    control of the debtor, other than such particulars (not being his books of 
    account) as are exempted by the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), 
    or by any other enactment for the time being in force from liability to 
    attachment and sale in execution of a decree; 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>    order a warrant to issue with or 
    without bail for the arrest of the debtor, and direct either that he be 
    detained in the civil prison until the disposal of the petition, or that he 
    be released on such terms as to security as may be reasonable and necessary: 
 
Provided that 
    an order under clause (2) or clause (3) shall not be made unless the Court 
    is satisfied that the debtor, with intent to defeat or delay his creditors 
    or to avoid any process of the Court,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    has absconded or has departed from the 
    local limits of the jurisdiction of the Court, or is about to abscond or to 
    depart from such limits, or is remaining outside them, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    has failed to disclose or has 
    concealed, destroyed, transferred or removed from such limits, or is about 
    to conceal, destroy, transfer or remove from such limits, any documents 
    likely to be of use to his creditors in the course of the hearing, or any 
    part of his property other than such particulars as aforesaid. 
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Duties 
    of debtors.—The debtor shall, on 
    the making of an order admitting the petition, produce all books of account, 
    and shall at any time thereafter give such inventories of his property, and 
    such lists of his creditors and debtors and of the debts due to and from 
    them, respectively, submit to such examination in respect of his property or 
    his creditors, attend at such times before the Court or receiver, execute 
    such instruments, and generally do all such acts and things in relation to 
    his property as may be required by the Court or receiver, or as may be 
    prescribed. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Release 
    of debtor.—
<section><number>1</number> At the time of 
    making an order admitting the petition or at any subsequent time before 
    adjudication, the Court may, if the debtor is under arrest or imprisonment 
    in execution of the decree of any Court for the payment of money, order his 
    release on such terms as to security as may be reasonable and necessary. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court 
    may at any time order any person who has been released under this section to 
    be re-arrested and re-committed to the custody from which he was released. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At the 
    time of making any order under this section, the Court shall record in 
    writing its reasons therefor. 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Procedure at hearing.—
<section><number>1</number> On the 
    day fixed for the hearing of the petition, or on any subsequent day to which 
    the hearing may be adjourned, the Court shall require proof of the following 
    matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the creditor or the debtor, as the 
    case may be, is entitled to present the petition: 
 
Provided that, where the debtor is the 
    petitioner, he shall, for the purpose of proving his inability to pay his 
    debts, be required to furnish only such proof as to satisfy the Court that 
    there are prima facie grounds for believing the same and the Court, 
    if and when so satisfied, shall not be bound to hear any further evidence 
    thereon; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the debtor, if he does not appear 
    on a petition presented by a creditor, has been served with notice of the 
    order admitting the petition; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the debtor has committed the act 
    of insolvency alleged against him. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court 
    shall also examine the debtor, if he is present, as to his conduct, dealings 
    and property in the presence of such creditors as appear at the hearing, and 
    the creditors shall have the right to question the debtor thereon. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court 
    shall, if sufficient cause is shown, grant time to the debtor or to any 
    creditor to produce any evidence which appears to it to be necessary for the 
    proper disposal of the petition. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A 
    memorandum of the substance of the examination of the debtor and of any 
    other oral evidence given shall be made by the Judge, and shall form part of 
    the record of the case. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 24, in sub-section (2), after the words “as to his conduct, 
      dealings and property”, insert the words “and his means for the repayment 
      of the debts”.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965 sec. 6 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).] 
  
 
COMMENTS
 

      Applicability
 
Where the debtor is ready to 
      be examined, only then section 24(2) is applicable; Fasihullah v.
      State of Uttar Pradesh, AIR 1986 All 129. 
 
Power of 
      insolvency court
 
Under section 28 the 
      Insolvency Court is empowered to hold an enquiry, if the petition is filed 
      by the creditor or debtor. When the petition is presented under section 9, 
      the Court is entitled to look into this fact that whether the application 
      moved by the creditor or debtor is maintainable under section 24. Thus, 
      under section 24(1), the Court will first try to trace the debtor-creditor 
      relationship and then see the amount of debt and acts of insolvency; 
      Lakhi Prasad Choudhary v. Mohammad Matin, AIR 1978 Pat 312. 
 
Scope
 
Proviso to section 24(1)(a) 
      talks about the procedure for hearing. It does not absolve the debtor from 
      the duty to prove his inability as far as payment of debts is concerned. 
      There is no conflict between section 10(1) and section 24(1)(a); 
      Bonagiri Yellalu v. Nagulavaram Chenchu Subbaiah, AIR 1972 AP 
      221.
 
When act of 
      debtor does not amount to insolvency
 
If a debtor is temporarily 
      absent from his place of business or convenient place and does not intend 
      to defeat or delay creditors, it does not constitute an act of insolvency;
      Ratchaganadan v. Kishindas Shamadasunder, AIR 1967 Mad 279.


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Dismissal of petition.—
<section><number>1</number> In the 
    case of a petition presented by a creditor, where the Court is not satisfied 
    with the proof of his right to present the petition or of the service on the 
    debtor of notice of the order admitting the petition, or of the alleged act 
    of insolvency, or is satisfied by the debtor that he is able to pay his 
    debts, or that for any other sufficient cause no order ought to be made, the 
    Court shall dismiss the petition. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the 
    case of a petition presented by a debtor, the Court shall dismiss the 
    petition if it is not satisfied of his right to present the petition. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Award 
    of compensation.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a 
    petition presented by a creditor is dismissed under sub-section (1) of 
    section 25, and the Court is satisfied that the petition was frivolous or 
    vexatious, the Court may, on the application of the debtor, award against 
    such creditor such amount, not exceeding one thousand rupees, as it deems a 
    reasonable compensation to the debtor for the expense or injury occasioned 
    to him by the petition and the proceedings thereon, and such amount may be 
    realised as if it were a fine. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An award 
    under this section shall bar any suit for compensation in respect of such 
    petition and the proceedings thereon. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Order 
    of adjudication.—
<section><number>1</number> If the Court 
    does not dismiss the petition, it shall make an order of adjudication, and 
    shall specify in such order the period within which the debtor shall apply 
    for his discharge. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court 
    may, if sufficient cause is shown, extend the period within which the debtor 
    shall apply for his discharge, and in that case shall publish notice of the 
    order in such manner as it thinks fit. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Effect 
    of an order of adjudication.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On the making of an order of adjudication, the insolvent shall aid to the 
    utmost of his power in the realisation of his property and the distribution 
    of the proceeds among his creditors. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the 
    making of an order of adjudication, the whole of the property of the 
    insolvent shall vest in the Court or in a receiver as hereinafter provided, 
    and shall become divisible among the creditors, and thereafter, except as 
    provided by this Act, no creditor to whom the insolvent is indebted in 
    respect of any debt provable under this Act shall during the pendency of the 
    insolvency proceedings have any remedy against the property of the insolvent 
    in respect of the debt, or commence any suit or other legal proceeding, 
    except with the leave of the Court and on such terms as the Court may 
    impose. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> For the 
    purposes of sub-section (2), all goods being at the date of the presentation 
    of the petition on which the order is made, in the possession, order or 
    disposition of the insolvent in his trade or business, by the consent and 
    permission of the true owner, under such circumstances that he is the 
    reputed owner thereof, shall be deemed to be the property of the insolvent. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All 
    property which is acquired by or devolves on the insolvent after the date of 
    an order of adjudication and before his discharge shall forthwith vest in 
    the Court or receiver, and the provisions of sub-section (2) shall apply in 
    respect thereof. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    property of the insolvent for the purposes of this section shall not include 
    any property (not being books of account) which is exempted by the Code of 
    Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), or by any other enactment for the time 
    being in force from liability to attachment and sale in execution of a 
    decree. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Nothing in 
    this section shall affect the power of any secured creditor to realise or 
    otherwise deal with his security, in the same manner as he would have been 
    entitled to realise or deal with it if this section had not been passed. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> An order 
    of adjudication shall relate back to, and take effect from the date of the 
    presentation of the petition on which it is made. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>


    1[<number>28A</number> Insolvent’s 
    property to comprise certain capacity.—The property of the insolvent 
    shall comprise and shall always be deemed to have comprised also the 
    capacity to exercise and to take proceedings for exercising all such powers 
    in or over or in respect of property as might have been exercised by the 
    insolvent for his own benefit at the commencement of his insolvency or 
    before his discharge: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall affect any sale, mortgage or other transfer of 
    the property of the insolvent by a Court or receiver or the Collector acting 
    under section 60 made before the commencement of the Provincial Insolvency 
    (Amendment) Act, 1948 (25 of 1948), which has been the subject of a final 
    decision by a competent Court: 
 
Provided 
    further that the property of the insolvent shall not be deemed by reason of 
    anything contained in this section to comprise his capacity referred to in 
    this section in respect of any such sale, mortgage or other transfer of 
    property made in the State of Madras after the 26th day of July, 1942, and 
    before the commencement of the Provincial Insolvency (Amendment) Act, 1948 
    (25 of 1948)]. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Tamil Nadu.—After 
      section 28A, insert the following section, namely:—
 
      “28B. 
      Section 28A to apply to the merged territory of Pudukottai from 1st April, 
      1949 with certain modification.—Section 28A, shall, with effect on and 
      from the 1st day of April, 1949, be deemed to have applied to the merged 
      territory of Pudukottai, subject to the following modifications, namely:—
 <section>
      <number>i</number>   in the 
      first and second provisos, for the words, brackets and figures before the 
      commencement of the Provincial Insolvency (Amendment) Act, 1948, the words 
      and figures ’before the 7th day of May 1947’ shall be substituted;
 </section><section>
      <number>ii</number>   in the 
      second Proviso, for the figures, letters and words ’28th day of July 
      1942’, the figures, letters and words ‘29th day of August 1944’ shall be 
      substituted”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Act 8 
      of 1953, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 27-5-1953).]
  
 
COMMENTS
 
Power of 
      Official Receiver
 
In a case, where the father in 
      a joint Hindu Family is adjudicated as an insolvent, the Official Receiver 
      will have the control over the entire joint family property and he is also 
      entitled to collect rents etc. in order to clarify the debts which are not 
      incurred for illegal purposes; Official Receiver v. P.L. 
      Devarajan Chettiar, AIR 1949 Mad 216. 
 
Property 
      used by insolvent
 
Under section 28A if the 
      father is adjudged as an insolvent, he can use his property which vests in 
      the Official Receiver, to clear his debts. He can use joint family 
      property for this, provided his debts are not incurred for illegal 
      purposes; Nageswaraswami v. Viswasundara Rao, AIR 1953 SC 
      370. 
</section>
 

 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>


    1[<number>28A</number> Insolvent’s 
    property to comprise certain capacity.—The property of the insolvent 
    shall comprise and shall always be deemed to have comprised also the 
    capacity to exercise and to take proceedings for exercising all such powers 
    in or over or in respect of property as might have been exercised by the 
    insolvent for his own benefit at the commencement of his insolvency or 
    before his discharge: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall affect any sale, mortgage or other transfer of 
    the property of the insolvent by a Court or receiver or the Collector acting 
    under section 60 made before the commencement of the Provincial Insolvency 
    (Amendment) Act, 1948 (25 of 1948), which has been the subject of a final 
    decision by a competent Court: 
 
Provided 
    further that the property of the insolvent shall not be deemed by reason of 
    anything contained in this section to comprise his capacity referred to in 
    this section in respect of any such sale, mortgage or other transfer of 
    property made in the State of Madras after the 26th day of July, 1942, and 
    before the commencement of the Provincial Insolvency (Amendment) Act, 1948 
    (25 of 1948)]. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Tamil Nadu.—After 
      section 28A, insert the following section, namely:—
 
      “28B. 
      Section 28A to apply to the merged territory of Pudukottai from 1st April, 
      1949 with certain modification.—Section 28A, shall, with effect on and 
      from the 1st day of April, 1949, be deemed to have applied to the merged 
      territory of Pudukottai, subject to the following modifications, namely:—
 <section>
      <number>i</number>   in the 
      first and second provisos, for the words, brackets and figures before the 
      commencement of the Provincial Insolvency (Amendment) Act, 1948, the words 
      and figures ’before the 7th day of May 1947’ shall be substituted;
 </section><section>
      <number>ii</number>   in the 
      second Proviso, for the figures, letters and words ’28th day of July 
      1942’, the figures, letters and words ‘29th day of August 1944’ shall be 
      substituted”.
 
[Vide Tamil Nadu Act 8 
      of 1953, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 27-5-1953).]
  
 
COMMENTS
 
Power of 
      Official Receiver
 
In a case, where the father in 
      a joint Hindu Family is adjudicated as an insolvent, the Official Receiver 
      will have the control over the entire joint family property and he is also 
      entitled to collect rents etc. in order to clarify the debts which are not 
      incurred for illegal purposes; Official Receiver v. P.L. 
      Devarajan Chettiar, AIR 1949 Mad 216. 
 
Property 
      used by insolvent
 
Under section 28A if the 
      father is adjudged as an insolvent, he can use his property which vests in 
      the Official Receiver, to clear his debts. He can use joint family 
      property for this, provided his debts are not incurred for illegal 
      purposes; Nageswaraswami v. Viswasundara Rao, AIR 1953 SC 
      370. 
</section>
 

 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Stay of 
    pending proceedings.—Any Court in 
    which a suit or other proceeding is pending against a debtor shall, on proof 
    that an order of adjudication has been made against him under this Act, 
    either stay the proceedings, or allow it to continue on such terms as such 
    Court may impose. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Publication of order of adjudication.—Notice 
    of an order of adjudication stating the name, address and description of the 
    insolvent, the date of the adjudication, the period within which the debtor 
    shall apply for his discharge, and the Court by which the adjudication is 
    made, shall be published in the Official Gazette and in such other manner as 
    may be prescribed. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Protection order.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    insolvent in respect of whom an order of adjudication has been made may 
    apply to the Court for protection and the Court may on such application make 
    an order for the protection of the insolvent from arrest or detention.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    protection order may apply either to all the debts of the debtor, or to any 
    of them as the Court may think proper, and may commence and take effect at 
    and for such time as the Court may direct, and may be revoked or renewed as 
    the Court may think fit. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    protection order shall protect the insolvent from being arrested or detained 
    in prison for any debt to which such order applies, and any insolvent 
    arrested or detained contrary to the terms of such an order shall be 
    entitled to his release: 
 
Provided that 
    no such order shall operate to prejudice the rights of any creditor in the 
    event of such order being revoked or the adjudication annulled. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any 
    creditor shall be entitled to appear and oppose the grant of a protection 
    order. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 31,—in sub-section (2),—
 <subsection>
      <number>i</number>   for the 
      words “revoked or renewed”, substitute the words “revoked, modified or 
      renewed”;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>ii</number>   Insert 
      the following proviso, namely:—
 
      “Provided that a 
      protection order shall not apply to any debt referred to in sub-section 
      (1) of section 44”.
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>iii</number>   In 
      sub-section (3), in the proviso, for the word “revoked” substitute the 
      words “revoked or modified”.
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 
      53 of 1976 sec. 2 (w.e.f. 10-12-1976).] 
  
 
COMMENTS
 
Protection 
      order: When made
 
Where the debt has been 
      incurred after the adjudication order, then under section 31 protection 
      order can be made; S. Smith v. Dunichand, AIR 1933 Lah 261. 
 
When the adjudication order 
      has been passed, only then the order for protection can be made; Mariam 
      Bibi v. A.E. Motala, AIR 1932 Rang 51. 
 
When 
      protection order not made
 
If there is no protection 
      order and if no adjudication had taken place, the creditor can move an 
      application for the debtor’s arrest; Hari Ram v. Sri Krishan Ram, 
      AIR 1927 All 418. 
</subsection>

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Power 
    to arrest after adjudication.—At 
    any time after an order of adjudication has been made, the Court may, if it 
    has reason to believe on the application of any creditor or the receiver, 
    that the debtor has absconded or departed from the local limits of its 
    jurisdiction with intent to avoid any obligation which has been, or might 
    be, imposed on him by or under this Act, order a warrant to issue for his 
    arrest, and on his appearing or being brought before it, may, if satisfied 
    that he was absconding or had departed with such intent, order his release 
    on such terms as to security as may be reasonable or necessary, or if such 
    security is not furnished, direct that he shall be detained in the civil 
    prison for a period which may extend to three months. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Schedule of creditors.—
<section><number>1</number> When 
    an order of adjudication has been made under this Act, all persons alleging 
    themselves to be creditors of the insolvent in respect of debts provable 
    under this Act shall tender proof of their respective debts by producing 
    evidence of the amount and particulars thereof, and the Court shall, by 
    order, determine the persons who have proved themselves to be creditors of 
    the insolvent in respect of such debts, and the amount of such debts, 
    respectively, and shall frame a schedule of such persons and debts: 
 
Provided that, 
    if, in the opinion of the Court, the value of any debt is incapable of being 
    fairly estimated, the Court may make an order to that effect, and thereupon 
    the debts shall not be included in the schedule. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of 
    every such schedule shall be pasted in the Court-house. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any 
    creditor of the insolvent may, at any time before the discharge of the 
    insolvent, tender proof of his debt and apply to the Court for an order 
    directing his name to be entered in the schedule as a creditor in respect of 
    any debt provable under this Act, and not entered in the schedule, and the 
    Court, after causing notice to be served on the 

    1[receiver] and the 
    other creditors who have proved their debts, and hearing their objections 
    (if any), shall comply with or reject the application. 
 
 
 
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Debts 
    provable under the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> Debts 
    which have been excluded from the schedule on the ground that their value is 
    incapable of being fairly estimated and demands in the nature of 
    unliquidated damages arising otherwise than by reason of a contract or a 
    breach of trust shall not be provable under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as 
    provided by sub-section (1), all debts and liabilities, present or future, 
    certain or contingent, to which the debtor is subject when he is adjudged an 
    insolvent, or to which he may become subject before his discharge by reason 
    of any obligation incurred before the date of such adjudication, shall be 
    deemed to be debts provable under this Act. 
 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Power to annul adjudication of insolvency.—Where, 
    in the opinion of the Court, a debtor ought not to have been adjudged 
    insolvent or where it is proved to the satisfaction of the Court that the 
    debts of the insolvent have been paid in full, the Court shall, on the 
    application of the debtor, or of any other person interested, by order in 
    writing, annul the adjudication 

    1[and the Court may, 
    of its own motion or on an application made by the receiver or any creditor, 
    annul any adjudication made on the petition of a debtor who was, by reason 
    of the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 10, not entitled to present 
    such petition.]—Where, 
    in the opinion of the Court, a debtor ought not to have been adjudged 
    insolvent or where it is proved to the satisfaction of the Court that the 
    debts of the insolvent have been paid in full, the Court shall, on the 
    application of the debtor, or of any other person interested, by order in 
    writing, annul the adjudication 

    1[and the Court may, 
    of its own motion or on an application made by the receiver or any creditor, 
    annul any adjudication made on the petition of a debtor who was, by reason 
    of the provisions of sub-section (2) of section 10, not entitled to present 
    such petition.]" 
 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Power 
    to cancel one of the concurrent orders of adjudication.—If, 
    in any case in which an order of adjudication has been made, it shall be 
    proved to the Court by which such order was made that insolvency proceedings 
    are pending in another Court against the same debtor, and that the property 
    of the debtor can be more conveniently distributed by such other Court, the 
    Court may annul the adjudication or stay all proceedings thereon. 
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Proceedings on annulment.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where an adjudication is annulled, all sales and dispositions of property 
    and payments duly made, and all acts therefore done, by the Court or 
    receiver, shall be valid; but, subject as aforesaid, the property of the 
    debtor, who was adjudged insolvent, shall vest in such person as the Court 
    may appoint, or, in default of any such appointment, shall revert to the 
    debtor to the extent of his right or interest therein on such conditions (if 
    any) as the Court may, by order in writing, declare. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notice of 
    every order annulling an adjudication shall be published in the Official 
    Gazette and in such other manner as may be prescribed. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>38</number> 
    Compositions and schemes of arrangement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a debtor, after the making of an order of adjudication, submits a 
    proposal for a composition in satisfaction of his debts, or a proposal for a 
    scheme of arrangement of his affairs, the Court shall fix a date for the 
    consideration of the proposal, and shall issue a notice to all creditors in 
    such manner as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, on the 
    consideration of the proposal, a majority in number and three-fourths in 
    value of all the creditors whose debts are proved and who are present in 
    person or by pleader, resolve to accept the proposal, the same shall be 
    deemed to be duly accepted by the creditors. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The debtor 
    may at the meeting amend the terms of his proposal if the amendment is, in 
    the opinion of the Court, calculated to benefit the general body of 
    creditors. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the 
    Court is of opinion, after hearing the report of the receiver, if a receiver 
    has been appointed, and after considering any objections which may be made 
    by or on behalf of any creditor, that the terms of the proposal are not 
    reasonable or are not calculated to benefit the general body of creditors, 
    the Court shall refuse to approve the proposal. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If any 
    facts are proved on proof of which the Court would be required either to 
    refuse, suspend or attach conditions to the debtor’s discharge, the Court 
    shall refuse to approve the proposal unless it provides reasonable security 
    for payment of not less than six annas in the rupee on all the unsecured 
    debts provable against the debtor’s estate. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> No 
    composition or scheme shall be approved by the Court which does not provide 
    for the payment in priority to other debts of all debts directed to be so 
    paid in the distribution of the property of an insolvent. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In any 
    other case the Court may either approve or refuse to approve the proposal. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>39</number> 
    Order of approval.—If 
    the Court approves the proposal, the terms shall be embodied in an order of 
    the Court, and 

    1[***] the order of 
    adjudication shall be annulled, and the provisions of section 37 shall 
    apply, and the composition or scheme shall be binding on all the creditors
    

    2[so far as relates to 
    any debt due to them from the debtor and provable under this Act].—If 
    the Court approves the proposal, the terms shall be embodied in an order of 
    the Court, and 

    1[***] the order of 
    adjudication shall be annulled, and the provisions of section 37 shall 
    apply, and the composition or scheme shall be binding on all the creditors
    

    2[so far as relates to 
    any debt due to them from the debtor and provable under this Act]." 
 
 







 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Power 
    to re-adjudge debtor insolvent.—If 
    default is made in the payment of any instalment due in pursuance of the 
    composition or scheme, or if it appears to the Court that the composition or 
    scheme cannot proceed without injustice or undue delay, or that the approval 
    of the Court was obtained by fraud, the Court may, if it thinks fit, 
    re-adjudge the debtor insolvent and annul the composition or scheme but 
    without prejudice to the validity of any transfer or payment duly made or of 
    anything duly done under or in pursuance of the composition or scheme. When 
    a debtor is re-adjudged insolvent under this section, all debts provable in 
    other respects which have been contracted before the date of such 
    re-adjudication shall be provable in the insolvency. 
 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>41</number> 
    Discharge.—
<section><number>1</number> A debtor may, at 
    any time after the order of adjudication and shall, within the period 
    specified by the Court, apply to the Court for an order of discharge, and 
    the Court shall fix a day, notice whereof shall be given in such manner as 
    may be prescribed, for hearing such application, and any objections which 
    may be made thereto. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this section, the Court may, after considering the 
    objections of any creditor and, where a receiver has been appointed, the 
    report of the receiver— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    grant or refuse an absolute order of 
    discharge; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    suspend the operation of the order for 
    a specified time; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    grant an order of discharge subject to 
    any conditions with respect to any earnings or income which may afterwards 
    become due to the insolvent, or with respect to his after-acquired property. 
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Cases 
    in which Court must refuse an absolute discharge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Court shall refuse to grant an absolute order of discharge under section 
    41 on proof of any of the following facts, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    that the insolvent’s assets are not of 
    a value equal to eight annas in the rupee on the amount of his unsecured 
    liabilities, unless he satisfies the Court that the fact that the assets are 
    not of a value equal to eight annas in the rupee on the amount of his 
    unsecured liabilities has arisen from circumstances for which he cannot 
    justly be held responsible; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    that the insolvent has omitted to keep 
    such books of account as are usual and proper in the business carried on by 
    him and as sufficiently disclose his business transactions and financial 
    position within the three years immediately preceding his insolvency; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    that the insolvent has continued to 
    trade after knowing himself to be insolvent; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    that the insolvent has contracted any 
    debt provable under this Act without having at the time of contracting it 
    any reasonable or probable ground of expectation (the burden of proving 
    which shall lie on him) that he would be able to pay it; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    that the insolvent has failed to 
    account satisfactorily for any loss of assets or for any deficiency of 
    assets to meet his liabilities; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    that the insolvent has brought on, or 
    contributed to, his insolvency by rash and hazardous speculations, or by 
    unjustifiable extravagance in living, or by gambling, or by culpable neglect 
    of his business affairs; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    that the insolvent has, within three 
    months preceding the date of the presentation of the petition, when unable 
    to pay his debts as they become due, given an undue preference to any of his 
    creditors; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    that the insolvent has on any previous 
    occasion been adjudged an insolvent or made a composition or arrangement 
    with his creditors; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    that the insolvent has concealed or 
    removed his property or any part thereof, or has been guilty of any other 
    fraud or fraudulent breach of trust. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the 
    purposes of this section, the report of the receiver shall be deemed to be 
    evidence; and the Court may presume the correctness of any statement 
    contained therein. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The powers 
    of suspending, and of attaching conditions to, an insolvent’s discharge may 
    be exercised concurrently. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 42, in sub-section (1), in clause (a), for the words “eight annas 
      in the rupee” in both the places where they occur, substitute the words 
      “fifty paise in the rupee”.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 7 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]
 
COMMENTS 
 
Report of 
      Official Receiver
 
Where the Official Receiver’s 
      report is in favour of the discharge of the insolvent, it is for the 
      creditors to prove that the report is contrary to the existing facts; 
      Tara Singh v. Sarmukh Singh, AIR 1933 Lah 812. 
 
Scope
 
Section 42 covers the transfer 
      made by a person fraudulently, before he is adjudged as an insolvent and 
      if such transfers are made within the prescribed period, then the 
      discharge order can be refused. Thus, if the creditors point towards these 
      fraudulent transfers, the onus to prove the same will be on them; Abdul 
      Sattar v. Dinajpur Trading and Banking Co., AIR 1939 Cal 490. 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>43</number> 
    Adjudication to be annulled on failure to apply for discharge.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the debtor does not appear on the day fixed for hearing his application 
    for discharge or on such subsequent day as the Court may direct, or if the 
    debtor does not apply for an order of discharge within the period specified 
    by the Court, 

    1[the Court may annul 
    the order of adjudication or make such other order as it may think fit, and 
    if the adjudication is so annulled, the provisions of section 37 shall 
    apply].—(1) 
    If the debtor does not appear on the day fixed for hearing his application 
    for discharge or on such subsequent day as the Court may direct, or if the 
    debtor does not apply for an order of discharge within the period specified 
    by the Court, 

    1[the Court may annul 
    the order of adjudication or make such other order as it may think fit, and 
    if the adjudication is so annulled, the provisions of section 37 shall 
    apply]." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    debtor has been released from custody under the provisions of this Act and 
    the order of adjudication is annulled under sub-section (1), the Court may, 
    if it thinks fit, re-commit the debtor to his former custody, and the 
    officer-in-charge of the prison to whose custody such debtor is so 
    re-committed, shall receive such debtor into his custody according to such 
    re-commitment, and thereupon all processes which were in force against the 
    person of such debtor at the time of such release as aforesaid shall be 
    deemed to be still in force against him as if no order of adjudication had 
    been made. 
 
 
 
 

 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Effect 
    of order of discharge.—
<section><number>1</number> An 
    order of discharge shall not release the insolvent from— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    any debt due to the Government; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    any debt or liability incurred by means 
    of any fraud or fraudulent breach of trust to which he was a party; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    any debt or liability in respect of 
    which he has obtained forbearance by any fraud to which he was a party; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    any liability under an order for 
    maintenance made under section 488 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 
    (5 of 1898).1 tc 
    " (d) any liability under an order for maintenance made under section 488 of 
    the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 of 1898).1" 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as 
    otherwise provided by sub-section (1), an order of discharge shall release 
    the insolvent from all debts provable under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An order 
    of discharge shall not release any person who, at the date of the 
    presentation of the petition, was a partner or co-trustee with the 
    insolvent, or was jointly bound or had made any joint contract with him or 
    any person who was surety for him. 
 
 
State Amendment
 

Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 44, in sub-section (1), in clause (d), substitute the following 
      clauses, namely:—
 
    “(d)   any liability under 
      any assessment for maintenance or under any decree or order for 
      maintenance passed under any law for the time being in force; or
 <subsection>
      <number>e</number>   any debt or 
      liability the amount due in respect of which is recoverable from him as 
      arrears of land revenue under the Uttar Pradesh Public Moneys (Recovery of 
      Dues) Act, 1972 or under any other law for the time being in force”.
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 
      53 of 1976, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 10-12-1976).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Discharge 
      Co-debtor
 
A co-debtor will not be 
      discharged if a debtor is discharged for the same debt; Parasurama 
      Mudaliar v. B. Ramanathan, AIR 1981 Mad 33. 
 
Liability of 
      surety
 
Under section 44(3), surety is 
      liable even after the insolvent is discharged from liability; Thakar 
      Dass v. Phagwa, AIR 1936 Pesh 150. 
 
Property not 
      to be revested
 
The property is not reverted 
      once the discharge order is passed; Khem Chand v. Heman Das, 
      AIR 1937 Sind 306. 
 
Provable 
      debt
 
Only provable debts can be 
      penalised under section 44(2). Provable debts should not be in existence 
      after the order of discharge has been made and before the said order is 
      made. It should be there when the adjudication order was made; Kathu 
      v. A.I.Q. Raja Jang, AIR 1949 Lah 167. 
 
Receiver
 
The receiver does not become
      functus officio, if an order of discharge is made under section 
      44(2); Jubilee Bank v. Santimoyee Debi, AIR 1950 Cal 487. 
 
When court 
      can sell property of insolvent
 
The Insolvency Court can sell 
      the property of the insolvent even after the discharge order. The property 
      can be sold on creditor’s application; Suka v. Ram Chandra 
      Shankar Mohar, AIR 1937 Nag 171. 
 
When surety 
      cannot recover the amount
 
A surety cannot recover the 
      amount paid by him to the creditor, towards the satisfaction of debts of 
      the insolvent, once the insolvent is discharged from all the liabilities;
      Nalliya Goundan v. Marappa Goundan, AIR 1942 Mad 745.
</subsection>
 
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>45</number> Debt 
    payable at a future time.—A 
    creditor may prove for a debt not payable when the debtor is adjudged an 
    insolvent as if it were payable presently, and may receive dividends equally 
    with the other creditors, deducting therefrom only a rebate of interest at 
    the rate of six per centum per annum computed from the declaration of a 
    dividend to the time when the debt would have become payable, according to 
    the terms on which it was contracted. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>46</number> Mutual 
    dealings and set-off.—Where there 
    have been mutual dealings between an insolvent and a creditor proving or 
    claiming to prove a debt under this Act, an account shall be taken of what 
    is due from the one party to the other in respect of such mutual dealings, 
    and the sum due from the one party shall be set off against any sum due from 
    the other party, and the balance of the account, and no more, shall be 
    claimed or paid on either side respectively.
 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Secured 
    creditors.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a secured 
    creditor realizes his security, he may prove for the balance due to him, 
    after deducting the net amount realized. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    secured creditor relinquishes his security for the general benefit of the 
    creditors, he may prove for his whole debt. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where a 
    secured creditor does not either realize or relinquish his security, he 
    shall, before being entitled to have his debt entered in the schedule, state 
    in his proof the particulars of his security, and the value at which he 
    assesses it, and shall be entitled to receive a dividend only in respect of 
    the balance due to him after deducting the value so assessed. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a 
    security is so valued, the Court may at any time before realisation redeem 
    it on payment to the creditor of the assessed value. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where a 
    creditor, after having valued his security, subsequently realises it, the 
    net amount realised shall be substituted for the amount of any valuation 
    previously made by the creditor, and shall be treated in all respects as an 
    amended valuation made by the creditor. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where a 
    secured creditor does not comply with the provisions of this section, he 
    shall be excluded from all shares in any dividend. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
    Interest.—
<section><number>1</number> On any debt or sum 
    certain whereon interest is not reserved or agreed for, and which is overdue 
    when the debtor is adjudged an insolvent, and which is provable under this 
    Act, the creditor may pray for interest at a rate not exceeding six per 
    centum per annum— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    if the debt or sum is payable by virtue 
    of a written instrument at a certain time, from the time when such debt or 
    sum was payable to the date of such adjudication; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    if the debt or sum is payable 
    otherwise, from the time when a demand in writing has been made giving the 
    debtor notice that interest will be claimed from the date of the demand 
    until the time of payment to the date of such adjudication. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a 
    debt which has been proved under this Act includes interest or any pecuniary 
    consideration in lieu of interest, the interest or consideration shall, for 
    the purposes of dividend, be calculated at a rate not exceeding six per 
    centum per annum, without prejudice to the right of a creditor to receive 
    out of the debtor’s estate any higher rate of interest to which he may be 
    entitled after all the debts proved have been paid in full. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Mode of 
    proof.—
<section><number>1</number> A debt may be proved 
    under this Act by delivering, or sending by post in a registered letter, to 
    the Court an affidavit verifying the debt. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    affidavit shall contain or refer to a statement of account showing the 
    particulars of the debt, and shall specify the vouchers (if any) by which 
    the same can be substantiated. The Court may at any time call for the 
    production of the vouchers. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
    Disallowance and reduction of entries in schedule.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the receiver thinks that a debt has been improperly entered in the 
    schedule, the Court may, on the application of the receiver and after notice 
    to the creditor, and such inquiry (if any) as the Court thinks necessary, 
    expunge such entry or reduce the amount of the debt. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court 
    may also, after like inquiry, expunge an entry or reduce the amount of a 
    debt upon the application of a creditor where no receiver has been 
    appointed, or where the receiver declines to interfere in the matter or, in 
    the case of a composition or scheme, upon the application of the debtor. 
 
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>51</number> 
    Restriction of rights of creditor under execution.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where execution of a decree has been issued against the property of a 
    debtor, no person shall be entitled to the benefit of the execution against 
    the receiver except in respect of assets realised in the course of the 
    execution by sale or otherwise before the date of the admission of the 
    petition. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in 
    this section shall affect the rights of a secured creditor in respect of the 
    property against which the decree is executed. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A person 
    who in good faith purchases the property of a debtor under a sale in 
    execution shall in all cases acquire a good title to it against the 
    receiver. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Duties 
    of Courts executing decree as to property taken in execution.—Where 
    execution of a decree has been issued against any property of a debtor which 
    is saleable in execution and before the sale thereof notice is given to the 
    Court executing the decree that an insolvency petition by or against the 
    debtor has been admitted, the Court shall, on application, direct the 
    property, if in the possession of the Court, to be delivered to the 
    receiver, but the costs of the suit in which the decree was made and of the 
    execution shall be a first charge on the property so delivered, and the 
    receiver may sell the property or an adequate part thereof for the purpose 
    of satisfying the charge. 
 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>53</number> 
    Avoidance of voluntary transfer.—Any 
    transfer of property not being a transfer made before and in consideration 
    of marriage or made in favour of a purchaser or encumbrancer in good faith 
    and for valuable consideration shall, if the transferor is adjudged 
    insolvent 

    1[on a petition 
    presented] within two years after the date of the transfer, be voidable as 
    against the receiver and may be annulled by the Court.—Any 
    transfer of property not being a transfer made before and in consideration 
    of marriage or made in favour of a purchaser or encumbrancer in good faith 
    and for valuable consideration shall, if the transferor is adjudged 
    insolvent 

    1[on a petition 
    presented] within two years after the date of the transfer, be voidable as 
    against the receiver and may be annulled by the Court." 
 
 

 






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
    Avoidance of preference in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every transfer of property, every payment made, every obligation incurred, 
    and every judicial proceeding taken or suffered by any person unable to pay 
    his debts as they become due from his own money in favour of any creditor, 
    with a view of giving that creditor a preference over the other creditors, 
    shall, if such person is adjudged insolvent on a petition presented within 
    three months after the date thereof, be deemed fraudulent and void as 
    against the receiver, and shall be annulled by the Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> This 
    section shall not affect the rights of any person who in good faith and for 
    valuable consideration has acquired a title through or under a creditor of 
    the insolvent. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>


    1[<number>54A</number> By whom 
    petitions for annulment may be made.—A petition for the annulment of any 
    transfer under section 53, or of any transfer, payment, obligation or 
    judicial proceeding under section 54, may be made by the receiver or, with 
    the leave of the Court, by any creditor who has proved his debt and who 
    satisfies the Court that the receiver has been requested and has refused to 
    make such petition.] 
 
 

 





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>55</number> 
    Protection of bona fide transactions.—Subject 
    to the foregoing provisions of this Act with respect to the effect of 
    insolvency on an execution, and with respect to the avoidance of certain 
    transfers and preferences, nothing in this Act shall invalidate in the case 
    of an insolvency— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    any payment by the insolvent to any of 
    his creditors; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any payment or delivery to the 
    insolvent; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    any transfer by the insolvent for 
    valuable consideration; or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    any contract or dealing by or with the 
    insolvent for valuable consideration: 
 
Provided that 
    any such transaction takes place before the date of the order of 
    adjudication, and that such person with whom such transaction takes place 
    has not at the time notice of the presentation of any insolvency petition by 
    or against the debtor. 
 
  
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
    Appointment of receiver.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Court may, at the time of the order of adjudication, or at any time 
    afterwards, appoint a receiver for the property of the insolvent, and such 
    property shall thereupon vest in such receiver. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    such conditions as may be prescribed, the Court may— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    require the receiver to give such 
    security as it thinks fit duly to account for what he shall receive in 
    respect of the property; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    by general or special order, fix the 
    amount to be paid as remuneration for the services of the receiver out of 
    the assets of the insolvent. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the 
    Court appoints a receiver, it may remove the person in whose possession or 
    custody any such property as aforesaid, is from the possession or custody 
    thereof : 
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall be deemed to authorize the Court to remove 
    from the possession or custody of property any person whom the insolvent has 
    not a present right so to remove. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a 
    receiver appointed under this section— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    fails to submit his accounts at such 
    periods and in such forms as the Court directs, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    fails to pay the balance due from him 
    thereon as the Court directs, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    occasions loss to the property by his 
    wilful default or gross negligence, 
 
the Court may direct his property to be 
    attached and sold, and may apply the proceeds to make good any balance found 
    to be due from him or any loss so occasioned by him.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    provisions of this section shall apply, so far as may be, to interim 
    receivers appointed under section 20. 
 
 

State Amendment
 <subsection>
Gujarat.—In section 56, 
      after sub-section (3), insert as the following sub-sections, namely:—
 
      “(3A) The Court may 
      grant a warrant to an officer of the Court or any Police Officer above the 
      rank of a constable to seize any part of the property of the insolvent in 
      the custody or possession of the insolvent or of any other person, and 
      with a view to such seizure to break open any house, building or room of 
      the insolvent where the insolvent is supposed to be or any building or 
      receptacle of the insolvent where any of his property is supposed to be.
 </subsection>
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section><section>
      <number>3B</number> Where the Court is 
      satisfied that there is reason to believe that the property of the 
      insolvent is concealed in a house or place not belonging to him, the Court 
      may, if it thinks fit, grant a search warrant to any such officer as 
      aforesaid who may execute it according to its tenor”.
 
[Vide Gujarat Act 20 of 
      1987, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 20-4-1987).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 

      Applicability
 
Section 56 is applicable to 
      “interim receiver” also and he has some rights and liabilities as a 
      receiver; Subramania v. Dharapuram Janopakara Nidhi Ltd., 
      AIR 1928 Mad 454. 
 
Section 56 is not applicable 
      to the cases where the insolvent’s title over the property is in question. 
      This section is applicable, where the insolvent has a right to remove the 
      property from other person’s possession; Chittammal v. 
      Ponnuswamy Naicker, AIR 1926 Mad 263. 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>57</number> Power 
    to appoint Official Receivers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may appoint such persons as it thinks fit (to be called 
    “Official Receivers”) to be receivers under this Act within such local 
    limits as it may prescribe. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any 
    Official Receiver has been so appointed for the local limits of the 
    jurisdiction of any Court having jurisdiction under this Act, he shall be 
    the receiver for the purpose of every order appointing a receiver or an 
    interim receiver issued by any such Court, unless the Court for special 
    reasons otherwise directs. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any sum 
    payable under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 56 in respect of the 
    services of an Official Receiver shall be credited to such fund as the State 
    Government may direct. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every 
    Official Receiver shall receive such remuneration out of the said fund or 
    otherwise as the State Government may fix in this behalf, and no 
    remuneration whatever beyond that so fixed shall be received by the Official 
    Receiver as such. 
 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>58</number> Powers 
    of Court if no receiver appointed.—Where 
    no receiver is appointed, the Court shall have all the rights of, and may 
    exercise all the powers conferred on, a receiver under this Act. 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>59</number> Duties 
    and powers of receiver.—Subject 
    to the provisions of this Act, the receiver shall, with all convenient 
    speed, realize the property of the debtor and distribute dividends among the 
    creditors entitled thereto, and for that purpose may— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    sell all or any part of the property of 
    the insolvent; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    give receipts for any money received by 
    him; and may, by leave of the Court, do all or any of the following things, 
    namely; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    carry on the business of the insolvent 
    so far as may be necessary for the beneficial winding up of the same; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    institute, defend or continue any suit 
    or other legal proceeding relating to the property of the insolvent; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    employ a pleader or other agent to take 
    any proceedings or do any business which may be sanctioned by the Court; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    accept as the consideration for the 
    sale of any property of the insolvent a sum of money payable at a future 
    time subject to such stipulations as to security and otherwise as the Court 
    thinks fit; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    mortgage or pledge any part of the 
    property of the insolvent for the purpose of raising money for the payment 
    of his debts; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    refer any dispute to arbitration, and 
    compromise all debts, claims and liabilities, on such terms as may be agreed 
    upon; and 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>    divide in its existing form amongst the 
    creditors, according to its estimated value, any property which, from its 
    peculiar nature or other special circumstances, cannot readily or 
    advantageously be sold. 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>


    1[<number>59A</number> Power to 
    require information regarding insolvent’s property.—
<section><number>1</number> The Court, if 
    specially empowered in this behalf by an order of the State Government, or 
    any officer of the Court so empowered by a like order, may, on the 
    application of the receiver or any creditor who has proved his debt, at any 
    time after an order of adjudication has been made, summon before it in the 
    prescribed manner any person known or suspected to have in his possession 
    any property belonging to the insolvent, or supposed to be indebted to the 
    insolvent, or any person whom the Court or such officer, as the case may be, 
    may deem capable of giving information respecting the insolvent or his 
    dealings or property, and the Court or such officer may require any such 
    person to produce any documents in his custody or power relating to the 
    insolvent or to his dealings or property. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person so summoned, after having been tendered a reasonable sum, refuses to 
    come before the Court or such officer at the time appointed, or refuses to 
    produce any such document, having no lawful impediment made known to and 
    allowed by the Court or such officer, the Court or such officer may, by 
    warrant, cause him to be apprehended and brought up for examination. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court 
    or such officer may examine any person so brought before it or him 
    concerning the insolvent, his dealings or property, and such person may be 
    represented by a legal practitioner.] 
 
 

State Amendments
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 59A after sub-section (3) add the following sub-sections, namely,—
 
                   “(4) If on 
      his examination any such person admits that he is indebted to the 
      insolvent, the Court or such officer may, on the application of the 
      receiver, order him to pay to the receiver at such time and in such manner 
      as to the Court or to such officer seems expedient, the amount in which he 
      is indebted, or any part thereof, either in full discharge of the whole 
      amount or not, as the Court or the officer, as the case may be, thinks fit 
      with or without costs of the examination.
 
 

 







 



</section><section>
                   <number>5</number> If on 
      his examination such person admits that he has in his possession any 
      property belonging to the insolvent, the Court or such officer may, on the 
      application of the receiver, order him to deliver to the receiver that 
      property or any part thereof, at such time, in such manner and on such 
      term as to the Court or to the officer, as the case may be, may seems 
      just.
 </section><section>
                   <number>6</number> Orders 
      made under sub-sections (4) and (5) shall be executed in the same manner 
      as decrees for the payment of money, or for the delivery of property, 
      under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 respectively.
 </section><section>
                   <number>7</number> Any 
      person making any payment or delivery in pursuance of an order made under 
      sub-section (4) or sub-section (5) shall by such payment or delivery be 
      discharged from all liability whatsoever in respect of such debt or 
      property.”
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 
      24 of 1954 sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Who can be 
      witness
 
Under section 59A, a 
      pardnashin lady can be called as a witness if the Court suspects her 
      to be in possession of the insolvent’s property; In re: Bilasroy 
      Serowgee, AIR 1929 Cal 528. 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>


    1[<number>59A</number> Power to 
    require information regarding insolvent’s property.—
<section><number>1</number> The Court, if 
    specially empowered in this behalf by an order of the State Government, or 
    any officer of the Court so empowered by a like order, may, on the 
    application of the receiver or any creditor who has proved his debt, at any 
    time after an order of adjudication has been made, summon before it in the 
    prescribed manner any person known or suspected to have in his possession 
    any property belonging to the insolvent, or supposed to be indebted to the 
    insolvent, or any person whom the Court or such officer, as the case may be, 
    may deem capable of giving information respecting the insolvent or his 
    dealings or property, and the Court or such officer may require any such 
    person to produce any documents in his custody or power relating to the 
    insolvent or to his dealings or property. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any 
    person so summoned, after having been tendered a reasonable sum, refuses to 
    come before the Court or such officer at the time appointed, or refuses to 
    produce any such document, having no lawful impediment made known to and 
    allowed by the Court or such officer, the Court or such officer may, by 
    warrant, cause him to be apprehended and brought up for examination. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court 
    or such officer may examine any person so brought before it or him 
    concerning the insolvent, his dealings or property, and such person may be 
    represented by a legal practitioner.] 
 
 

State Amendments
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 59A after sub-section (3) add the following sub-sections, namely,—
 
                   “(4) If on 
      his examination any such person admits that he is indebted to the 
      insolvent, the Court or such officer may, on the application of the 
      receiver, order him to pay to the receiver at such time and in such manner 
      as to the Court or to such officer seems expedient, the amount in which he 
      is indebted, or any part thereof, either in full discharge of the whole 
      amount or not, as the Court or the officer, as the case may be, thinks fit 
      with or without costs of the examination.
 
 

 







 



</section><section>
                   <number>5</number> If on 
      his examination such person admits that he has in his possession any 
      property belonging to the insolvent, the Court or such officer may, on the 
      application of the receiver, order him to deliver to the receiver that 
      property or any part thereof, at such time, in such manner and on such 
      term as to the Court or to the officer, as the case may be, may seems 
      just.
 </section><section>
                   <number>6</number> Orders 
      made under sub-sections (4) and (5) shall be executed in the same manner 
      as decrees for the payment of money, or for the delivery of property, 
      under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 respectively.
 </section><section>
                   <number>7</number> Any 
      person making any payment or delivery in pursuance of an order made under 
      sub-section (4) or sub-section (5) shall by such payment or delivery be 
      discharged from all liability whatsoever in respect of such debt or 
      property.”
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 
      24 of 1954 sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Who can be 
      witness
 
Under section 59A, a 
      pardnashin lady can be called as a witness if the Court suspects her 
      to be in possession of the insolvent’s property; In re: Bilasroy 
      Serowgee, AIR 1929 Cal 528. 
</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>60</number> Special 
    provisions in regard to immovable property.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In any local area in which a declaration has been made under section 68 of 
    the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), and is in force, no sale of 
    immovable property paying revenue to the Government or held or let for 
    agricultural purposes shall be made by the receiver; but, after the other 
    property of the insolvent has been realised, the Court shall ascertain— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the amount required to satisfy the 
    debts proved under this Act after deducting the monies already received;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the immovable property of the insolvent 
    remaining unsold; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the encumbrances (if any) existing 
    thereon; 
 
and shall forward a statement to the Collector 
    containing the particulars aforesaid; and thereupon the Collector shall 
    proceed to raise the amount so required by the exercise of such of the 
    powers conferred on him by paragraphs 2 to 10 of the Third Schedule to the 
    said Code as he thinks fit, and subject to the provisions of those 
    paragraphs so far as they are applicable, and shall hold at the disposal of 
    the Court all sums that may come to his hands by the exercise of such 
    powers.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Nothing in this Act shall be deemed to affect any provisions of any 
    enactment for the time being in force prohibiting or restricting the 
    execution of decrees or orders against immovable property; and any such 
    provision shall be deemed to apply to the enforcement of an order of 
    adjudication made under this Act as if it were such a decree or order. 
 
 

state amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 60, omit sub-section (1).
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 8 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]
 <subsection>
Delhi.—Same as in 
      Punjab.
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
      section 60, after sub-section (2), insert the following sub-section, 
      namely:—
 
      “(3) In 
      particular and without prejudice to the generality of sub-section (2), 
      when the whole or any part of the estate of the insolvent consists of land 
      as defined in Punjab Tenancy Act, 1987, or Himachal Pradesh Abolition of 
      Big Landed Estates and Land Reforms Act, 1954, as the case may be, no such 
      land shall be temporarily alienated by the Receiver, but after the other 
      property of the insolvent has been realised, the Court shall proceed in 
      the manner provided in sub-section (1), and the Collector shall thereupon 
      proceed to raise the amount required by means of a temporary alienation in 
      such form and for such period as may be legally permissible and as he 
      thinks fit; and shall hold at the disposal of the Court all sums which may 
      thereby come to his hands:
 
      Provided that such 
      portion of the land shall be exempted from alienation as in the opinion of 
      the Collector, having regard to the income of the judgment-debtor from all 
      sources except such income as is dependent on the will of other person, is 
      sufficient to provide for the maintenance of the insolvent and the members 
      of his family who are dependent on him, and such portion shall be deemed 
      not to form part of the estate administration.
 
[Vide H.P. 
      Act 31 of 1969, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 6-2-1969).]
 
Note: Punjab Act 3 of 
      1939, as in force in areas transferred from Punjab to H.P. under Act 31 of 
      1966, is repealed by this Act.
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In 
      section 60, after sub-section (2) add the following sub-section, namely:—
 
      “(3) In 
      particular, and without prejudice to the generality of sub-section (2), 
      when the whole or any part of the estate of an insolvent consists of land 
      as defined in the Punjab Tenancy Act, 1887, no such land shall be 
      temporarily alienated by the receiver, but after the other property of the 
      insolvent has been realised the Court shall proceed in the manner provided 
      in sub-section (1), and the Collector shall thereupon proceed to raise the 
      amount required by means of a temporary alienation in such form and for 
      such and for such period as may be legally permissible and as he thinks 
      fit; and shall hold at the disposal of the Court all sums which may 
      thereby come to his hands:
 
      Provided that such 
      portions of the land shall be exempted from alienation as in the opinion 
      of the Collector, having regard to the income of the judgment-debtor from 
      all sources except such income as is dependent on the will of another 
      person, is sufficient to provide for the maintenance of the insolvent and 
      the members of his family who are dependent on him, and such portion shall 
      be deemed not to form part of the estate under administration.”
 
[Vide Punjab Act 3 of 
      1939, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 20-4-1939) read with 30 of 1958, sec. 4(1) (w.e.f. 
      7-11-1958); Act 31 of 1966, sec. 88.]
  
 
COMMENTS
 
Scope
 
Sections 60(1) and (2) are 
      independent of each other. Sub-section (1) relates to the immovable 
      property and sub-section (2) is wider in scope and applies to the 
      immovable property of whatever description against which execution is 
      prohibited or restricted by statute; Dhani Ram v. District 
      Official Receiver, AIR 1943 Lah 19. 
 
Void sale
 
If section 60 is violated and 
      a property is sold after the insolvent is granted conditional discharge, 
      then the sale is null and void and the property will revert back to the 
      Official Receiver; Sahu Tota Ram v. Bhagwant Singh, AIR 1957 
      All 262. 
</subsection>
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
    Priority of debts.—
<section><number>1</number> In the 
    distribution of the property of the insolvent, there shall be paid in 
    priority to all other debts— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    all debts due to the Government or to 
    any local authority; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    all salary or wages, not exceeding 
    twenty rupees in all, of any clerk, servant or labourer in respect of 
    services rendered to the insolvent during four months before the date of the 
    presentation of the petition. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The debts 
    specified in sub-section (1) shall rank equally between themselves, and 
    shall be paid in full, unless the property of the insolvent is insufficient 
    to meet them, in which case they shall abate in equal proportions between 
    themselves. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    the retention of such sums as may be necessary for the expenses of 
    administration or otherwise, the debts specified in sub-section (1) shall be 
    discharged forthwith in so far as the property of the insolvent is 
    sufficient to meet them. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the 
    case of partners, the partnership property shall be applicable in the first 
    instance in payment of the partnership debts, and the separate property of 
    each partner shall be applicable in the first instance in payment of his 
    separate debts. Where there is a surplus of the separate property of the 
    partners, it shall be dealt with as part of the partnership property; and 
    where there is a surplus of the partnership property, it shall be dealt with 
    as part of the respective separate property in proportion to the rights and 
    interests of each partner in the partnership property. 
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of this Act, all debts entered in the schedule shall be paid 
    rateably according to the amounts of such debts respectively and without any 
    preference. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where 
    there is any surplus after payment of the foregoing debts, it shall be 
    applied in payment of interest from the date on which the debtor is adjudged 
    an insolvent at the rate of six per centum per annum on all debts entered in 
    the schedule. 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
    Calculation of dividends.—
<section><number>1</number> In 
    the calculation of dividends, the receiver shall retain in his hands 
    sufficient assets to meet— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    debts provable under this Act and 
    appearing, from the insolvent’s statements or otherwise, to be due to 
    persons resident in places so distant that in the ordinary course of 
    communication they have not had sufficient time to tender their proofs;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    debts provable under this Act, the 
    subject of claims not yet determined;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    disputed proof or claims; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the expenses necessary for the 
    administration of the estate or otherwise.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the provisions of sub-section (1), all money in hand shall be distributed as 
    dividends.
 
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>63</number> Right 
    of creditor who has not proved debt before declaration of a dividend.—Any 
    creditor who has not proved his debt before the declaration of any dividend 
    or dividends shall be entitled to be paid, out of any money for the time 
    being in the hands of the receiver, any dividend or dividends which he may 
    have failed to receive before that money is applied to the payment of any 
    future dividend or dividends; but he shall not be entitled to disturb the 
    distribution of any dividend declared before his debt was proved by reason 
    that he has not participated therein. 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>64</number> Final 
    dividend.—When the receiver has 
    realized all the property of the insolvent or so much thereof as can, in the 
    opinion of the Court, be realised without needlessly protracting the 
    receivership, he shall declare a final dividend; but before so doing, he 
    shall give notice in manner prescribed to the persons whose claims to be 
    creditors have been notified but not proved, that if they do not prove their 
    claim within the time limited by the notice, he will proceed to make a final 
    dividend without regard to their claims. After the expiration of the time so 
    limited, or if the Court, on application by any such claimant, grants him 
    further time for establishing his claim, then on the expiration of such 
    further time, the property of the insolvent shall be divided among the 
    creditors entered in the schedule without regard to the claims of any other 
    persons. 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>65</number> No suit 
    for dividend.—No suit for a 
    dividend shall lie against the receiver; but where the receiver refuses to 
    pay any dividend, the Court may, on the application of any creditor who is 
    entered in the schedule, order him to pay it, and also to pay out of his own 
    money interest thereon for the time that it is withheld, and the costs of 
    the application. 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
    Management by and allowance to insolvent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Court may appoint the insolvent himself to superintend the management of 
    the property of the insolvent or of any part thereof or to carry on the 
    trade (if any) of the insolvent for the benefit of the creditors, and in any 
    other respect to aid in administering the property in such manner and on 
    such terms as the Court may direct. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Court 
    may, from time to time, make such allowance as it may think just to the 
    insolvent out of his property for the support of himself and his family, or 
    in consideration of his services if he is engaged in winding-up his estate, 
    but any such allowance may, at any time, be varied or determined by the 
    Court. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 66, in sub-section (2), for the words “in consideration of his 
      services if he is engaged in winding up his estate”, substitute the words 
      “in consideration of the services which he may have rendered by order of 
      the Court”.
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 9 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Power of 
      court
 
The insolvent can ask for the 
      expenses for celebrating his daughter’s marriage but he cannot claim the 
      same as a matter of right under section 66(2). The Court has full 
      discretion to dispose of this application; Appa Rao v. 
      Ramamurthi, AIR 1940 Mad 675. 
 
The Court can allow the 
      insolvent to look after his property, so that he (insolvent) can maintain 
      himself and his family. His family members cannot ask for separate 
      maintenance; Murad v. Official Receiver, Insolvency 
      Estate, Sargodha, AIR 1935 Lah 952. 

 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Right 
    of insolvent to surplus.—The 
    insolvent shall be entitled to any surplus remaining after payment in full 
    of his creditors with interest as provided by this Act and of the expenses 
    of the proceedings taken thereunder. 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>


    1[<number>67A</number> Committee of 
    inspection.—
<section><number>1</number> The Court may, if it thinks fit, authorise the creditors 
    who have proved their debts to appoint a committee of inspection for the 
    purpose of superintending the administration of the insolvent’s property by 
    the receiver. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    persons appointed to a committee of inspection shall be creditors who have 
    proved their debts or persons holding general powers of attorney from such 
    creditors. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    committee of inspection shall have such powers of control over the 
    proceedings of the receiver as may be prescribed.]
 
 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>68</number> Appeals 
    to Court against receiver.—If the 
    insolvent or any of the creditors or any other person is aggrieved by any 
    act or decision of the receiver, he may apply to the Court, and the Court 
    may confirm, reverse or modify the act or decision complained of, and make 
    such order as it thinks just: 
 
Provided that 
    no application under this section shall be entertained after the expiration 
    of twenty-one days from the date of the act or decision complained of. 
 
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Offence 
    by debtors.—If a debtor, whether 
    before or after the making of an order of adjudication,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    wilfully fails to 
    perform the duties imposed on him by section 22 or to deliver up possession 
    of any part of his property which is divisible among his creditors under 
    this Act, and which is for the time being in his possession or under his 
    control to the Court or to any person authorized by the Court to take 
    possession of it, or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    fraudulently with intent 
    to conceal the state of his affairs or to defeat the objects of this Act,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    has destroyed or 
    otherwise wilfully prevented or purposely withheld the production of any 
    document relating to such of his affairs as are subject to investigation 
    under this Act, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    has kept or caused to 
    be kept false books, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>    has made false entries 
    in or withheld entries from or wilfully altered or falsified any document 
    relating to such of his affairs as are subject to investigation under this 
    Act, or 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>c</number>    fraudulently with intent 
    to diminish the sum to be divided among his creditors or to give an undue 
    preference to any of his creditors,— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>    has discharged or 
    concealed any debt due to or from him, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>    has made away with, 
    charged, mortgaged or concealed any part of his property of any kind 
    whatsoever, 
 
he shall be punishable on conviction
    1[***] 
    with imprisonment which may extend to one year.
 









 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>


    1[<number>70</number> Procedure on 
    charge under section 69.—Where the Court is satisfied, after such 
    preliminary inquiry, if any, as it thinks necessary, that there is ground 
    for inquiring into any offence referred to in section 69, and appearing to 
    have been committed by the insolvent, the Court may record a finding to that 
    effect and make a complaint of the offence in writing to a Magistrate of the 
    first class having jurisdiction, and such Magistrate shall deal with such 
    complaint in the manner laid down in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1898 (5 
    of 1898)2.] 
 
 

 










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>71</number> 
    Criminal liability after discharge or composition.—Where 
    an insolvent has been guilty of any of the offences specified in section 69, 
    he shall not be exempt from being proceeded against therefor by reason that 
    he has obtained his discharge or that a composition or scheme of arrangement 
    has been accepted or approved. 
 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
    Undischarged insolvent obtaining credit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An undischarged insolvent obtaining credit to the extent of fifty rupees or 
    upward from any person without informing such person that he is an 
    undischarged insolvent shall, on conviction by a Magistrate, be punishable 
    with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months, or with fine, 
    or with both. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the 
    Court has reason to believe that an undischarged insolvent has committed the 
    offence referred to in sub-section (1), the Court, after making any 
    preliminary inquiry that may be necessary, may send the case for trial to 
    the nearest Magistrate of the first class, and may send the accused in 
    custody or take sufficient security for his appearance before such 
    Magistrate; and may bind over any person to appear and give evidence on such 
    trial. 
 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
    Disqualifications of insolvent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a debtor is adjudged or re-adjudged insolvent under this Act, he 
    shall, subject to the provisions of this section, be disqualified from— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    being appointed or acting as a 
    Magistrate; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    being elected to any office of any 
    local authority where the appointment to such office is by election or 
    holding or exercising any such office to which no salary is attached; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    being elected or sitting or voting as 
    member of any local authority. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    disqualifications which an insolvent is subject to, under this section shall 
    be removed, and shall cease if— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the order of adjudication is annulled 
    under section 35, or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    he obtains from the Court an order of 
    discharge, whether absolute or conditional, with a certificate that his 
    insolvency was caused by misfortune without any misconduct on his part. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Court 
    may grant or refuse such certificate as it thinks fit, but any order of 
    refusal shall be subject to appeal. 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>74</number> Summary 
    administration.—When a petition 
    is presented by or against a debtor, if the Court is satisfied by affidavit 
    or otherwise that the property of the debtor is not likely to exceed in 
    value of five hundred rupees, the Court may make an order that the debtor’s 
    estate be administered in a summary manner, and thereupon the provisions of 
    this Act shall be subject to the following modifications, namely:— 
 <section>
<number>i</number>    unless the Court otherwise directs, no 
    notice required under this Act shall be published in the Official Gazette; 
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    on the admission of a petition by a 
    debtor, the property of the debtor shall vest in the Court as a receiver; 
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    at the hearing of the petition, the 
    Court shall inquire into the debts and assets of the debtor and determine 
    the same by order in writing, and it shall not be necessary to frame a 
    schedule under the provisions of section 33; 
 </section><section>
<number>iv</number>    the property of the debtor shall be 
    realised with all reasonable despatch and thereafter, when practicable, 
    distributed in a single dividend; 
 </section><section>
<number>v</number>    the debtor shall apply for his 
    discharge within six months from the date of adjudication; and 
 </section><section>
<number>vi</number>    such other modifications as may be 
    prescribed with the view of saving expense and simplifying procedure: 
 
Provided that 
    the Court may at any time direct that the ordinary procedure provided for in 
    this Act shall be followed in regard to the debtor’s estate, and thereafter 
    the Act shall have effect accordingly. 
 
 

State Amendments
 
Himachal Pradesh.—In 
      section 74, for the words, “five hundred rupees” substitute the words “two 
      thousand rupees”.
 
[Vide Himachal Pradesh 
      Act 31 of 1976, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 1-4-1979).]
 
Punjab: Haryana: Chandigarh.—In 
      section 74, for the words, “five hundred rupees” substitute the words “two 
      thousand rupees”.
 
[Vide Punjab Act 7 of 
      1934, sec. 4 (w.e.f. 19-4-1935): Act 31 of 1996, sec. 88.]
 
Uttar Pradesh.—In 
      section 74, for the words, “five hundred rupees” substitute the words “one 
      thousand rupees”.
 
[Vide Uttar Pradesh Act 
      24 of 1954, sec. 2 and Sch. (w.e.f. 30-11-1954).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Scope
 
Under section 74(ii) the 
      property of the debtor vests with the Court as a receiver in case of an 
      insolvency petition in a summary administration. If the property is sold 
      by another Court, the property can be retained by the purchaser, if he 
      purchases the same in good faith. Creditors can distribute the sale 
      proceeds amongst themselves; Srirangamma v. Narayanamma, AIR 
      1956 AP 243. 
 
Summery 
      proceedings
 
Creditors do not have to prove 
      their debts in case of summary proceedings. The Court has to see the 
      creditors’ claim and make a schedule and do the distribution of the 
      insolvent’s assets; K.V. Muthu v. R.S. Mani, AIR 1956 Mad 
      580. 

 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>75</number> 
    Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> The debtor, any 
    creditor, the receiver or any other person aggrieved by a decision come to 
    or an order made in the exercise of insolvency jurisdiction by a Court 
    subordinate to a District Court, may appeal to the District Court, and the 
    order of the District Court upon such appeal shall be final: 
 
Provided that 
    the High Court, for the purposes of satisfying itself that an order made in 
    any appeal decided by the District Court was according to law, may call for 
    the case and pass such order with respect thereto as it thinks fit: 
 
Provided 
    further, that any such person aggrieved by a decision of the District Court 
    on appeal from a decision of a subordinate Court under section 4 may appeal 
    to the High Court on any of the grounds mentioned in sub-section (1) of 
    section 100 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908). 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any such 
    person aggrieved by any such decision or order of a District Court as is 
    specified in Schedule I, come to or made otherwise than in appeal from an 
    order made by a Subordinate Court, may appeal to the High Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any such 
    person aggrieved by any other order made by a District Court otherwise than 
    in appeal from an order made by a subordinate Court may appeal to the High 
    Court by leave of the District Court or of the High Court. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    periods of limitation for appeals to the District Court and to the High 
    Court under this section shall be thirty days and ninety days, respectively. 
 
 

State Amendments
 
Andhra Pradesh.—In 
      section 75, after sub-section (3), insert the following sub-section, 
      namely:—
 
             “(3A) Any such 
      person aggrieved by any such decision or order may appeal—
 <subsection>
               <number>i</number>   to the 
      Chief Judge, City Small Causes Court, where such decision or order is made 
      by an additional Judge of that Court;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>ii</number>   to the 
      High Court where such decision or order is made by the Chief Judge of the 
      City Small Cause Court.”
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 10 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 75, for the words ‘High Court’ (whether in singular or plural) 
      wherever occurring, substitute the words “Judicial Commissioner’s Court”.
 
[Vide Goa, Daman and 
      Diu Act 1 of 1968, sec. 3(2).]
  
 
COMMENTS 
 
Appeal 
      against the order
 
Where with the permission of 
      the Court, bank filed a suit against the insolvent, appeal can be made 
      against its order under section 75; State Bank of India v. Madan 
      Lal Mehta, 43 (1991) DLT 358. 
 
Where the transfer made by the 
      insolvent was held to be fraudulent one by the Insolvency Court, the 
      transferee can file an appeal as he is the “aggrieved person/ party”; 
      Hiralal v. Firm S.S.G. Bangle Merchants, AIR 1961 MP 15. 
</subsection>
  
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>76</number> Costs.—The 
    costs of any proceedings under this Act, including the costs of maintaining 
    a debtor in the civil prison, shall, subject to any rules made under this 
    Act, be in the discretion of the Court in which the proceeding is held. 
 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>77</number> Courts 
    to be auxiliary to each other.—All 
    Courts having jurisdiction in insolvency and the Officers of such Courts, 
    respectively, shall severally act in aid of and be auxiliary to each other 
    in all matters of insolvency, and an order of a Court seeking aid, with a 
    request to another of the said Courts shall be deemed sufficient to enable 
    the latter Court to exercise, in regard to the matters directed by the 
    order, such jurisdiction as either of such Courts could exercise in regard 
    to similar matters within their respective jurisdictions. 
 
 
  
 
 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>78</number> 
    Limitation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The provisions of sections 5 and 12 of the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 
    1908)1, 
    shall apply to appeals and applications under this Act, and for the purpose 
    of the said section 12, a decision under section 4 shall be deemed to be a 
    decree.—(1) 
    The provisions of sections 5 and 12 of the Indian Limitation Act, 1908 (9 of 
    1908)1, 
    shall apply to appeals and applications under this Act, and for the purpose 
    of the said section 12, a decision under section 4 shall be deemed to be a 
    decree." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where an 
    order of adjudication has been annulled under this Act, in computing the 
    period of limitation prescribed for any suit or application for the 
    execution of a decree or (other than a suit or application in respect of 
    which the leave of the Court was obtained under sub-section (2) of section 
    28) which might have been brought or made but for the making of an order of 
    adjudication under this Act, the period from the date of the order of 
    adjudication to the date of the order of annulment shall be excluded: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing in this section shall apply to a suit or application in respect of a 
    debt provable but not proved under this Act. 
 
 

 








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
    Power to make rules.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The High Court may, with the previous sanction of the State Government, make 
    rules for carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.]—1[(1) 
    The High Court may, with the previous sanction of the State Government, make 
    rules for carrying into effect the provisions of this Act.]" 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide— 
 

2[(a) 
       the form of the insolvency notice under clause (a), and the manner in 
    which such notice may be served under clause (b), of sub-section (3) of 
    section 6;] 
    2[(a) the form of the insolvency notice under clause 
    (a), and the manner in which such notice may be served under clause (b), of 
    sub-section (3) of section 6;]" 
 

3[(aa)]    
    for the appointment and remuneration of receivers (other than Official 
    Receivers), the audit of the accounts of all receivers and the costs of such 
    audit,  
    3[(aa)] for the appointment and remuneration of 
    receivers (other than Official Receivers), the audit of the accounts of all 
    receivers and the costs of such audit, " 
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    for meetings of creditors, 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    for the procedure to be followed 
    where the debtor is a firm, 
4[***]
4[***]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    for the procedure to be followed 
    in the case of estates to be administered in a summary manner, 
5[and]
    
5[and] 
    " 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    for any matter which is to be or may be 
    prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> All 
    rules made under this section shall be published 

    6[***] in the Official 
    Gazette, 

    7[***] and shall, on 
    such publication, have effect as if enacted in this Act. 
 
 

State Amendments
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—In 
      section 79, in sub-section (2), in clause (d),4.—
 <subsection>
              <number>a</number>   omit the 
      word ‘and’ occurring at the end; and
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>b</number>   after 
      clause (d) insert the following clause, namely:—
 
                     “(dd) the 
      form of the insolvency notice and the manner in which it may be served, 
      and”.
 
[Vide Goa, Daman and 
      Diu Act 1 of 1968, sec. 3 (5).]
 <subsubsection>
<number>Gujarat</number>—In its 
      application to the Bombay and Saurashtra areas of the State of Gujarat, 
      same as in Maharashtra.
 
[Vide Act 11 of 1960, 
      sec. 87 and Gujarat AL (8th Am.) O., 1961.]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>Karnataka</number>—Same as in 
      Maharashtra.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>Maharashtra</number>—In its 
      application to the Bombay area of the State of Maharashtra, in section 79, 
      in sub-section (2) after clause (a) insert the following clause, namely:—
 
             “(aa) the form of 
      insolvency notice and the manner in which it may be served.”
 
[Vide Bombay Act 15 of 
      1939, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 19-6-1939).]
</subsubsection></subsection>
 

 















 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>80</number> 
    Delegation of powers to Official Receivers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The High Court, with the like sanction, may from time to time direct that, 
    in any matters in respect of which jurisdiction is given to the Court by 
    this Act, the Official Receiver shall, subject to the directions of the 
    Court, have all or any of the following powers, namely:— 
 

1[***] 1[***]" 
 <subsection>
<number>b</number>    to frame Schedules and to admit or 
    reject proofs of creditors; 
 

2[***] 2[***]" 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    to make interim orders in any case of 
    urgency; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    to hear and determine any unopposed or
    ex-parte application. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to 
    the appeal to the Court provided for by section 68, any order made or act 
    done by the Official Receiver in the exercise of the said powers shall be 
    deemed the order or act of the Court. 
 
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>81</number> 
    Power of State Government to bar application of certain provisions to 
    certain Courts.—Any 
    State Government 

    1[***] may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, declare that any of the provisions of 
    this Act specified in Schedule II shall not apply to insolvency proceedings, 
    in any Court or Courts having jurisdiction under this Act in any part of the 
    territories administered by such State Government.—Any 
    State Government 

    3[***] may, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, declare that any of the provisions of 
    this Act specified in Schedule II shall not apply to insolvency proceedings, 
    in any Court or Courts having jurisdiction under this Act in any part of the 
    territories administered by such State Government." 
 
 










 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>82</number> 
    Savings.—Nothing in this Act 
    shall— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    affect the Presidency-towns 
    Insolvency Act, 1909 (3 of 1909) 
1[***] 
    or
4[***] 
    or" 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    apply to cases to which Chapter IV of 
    the Dekkhan Agriculturists Relief Act, 1879 (7 of 1879), is applicable.
 
 

State Amendment
 
Andhra Pradesh.—For 
      section 82, substitute the following section, namely:—
 
      “82. 
      Savings.—Nothing in this Act shall apply to cases to which the Andhra 
      Pradesh (Telangana Area) Agricultural Debtors’ Relief Act, 1956 (16 of 
      1956), is applicable.”
 
[Vide Andhra Pradesh 
      Act 23 of 1965, sec. 11 (w.e.f. 1-6-1966).]

 
 










 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
 
  
 <article>
<number>83</number> 
    Repeals.—1[***]—5[***]" 
 <section>
<number>2</number> Where in 
    any enactment or instrument in force at the date of the commencement of this 
    Act, reference is made to Chapter XX (Of Insolvent Judgement-Debtors) of the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1877 (10 of 1877), or of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1882 (14 of 1882), or to any section of either of those Chapters, 
    such reference shall, so far as may be practicable, be construed as applying 
    to this Act or to the corresponding section thereof. 
 
 

State Amendment
 
Goa, Daman and Diu.—Omit 
      section 83.
 
[Vide Goa, Daman and 
      Diu Act 1 of 1968, sec. 3.]

 

 








 



</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PROVINCIAL INSOLVENCY ACT, 1920
 


 
 


SCHEDULE I
 



[See section 
    75(2)]
 



Decisions and Orders from which an appeal 
    lies to the High Court  

    under section 75(2)
 
 
  

 
  
 Section
 Nature of decision or 
        order

 
  

 
  
 24
 Decision of questions of 
        title, priority, etc., arising in insolvency.

 
  
 25
 Order of dismissing a 
        petition.

 
  
 26
 Order awarding 
        compensation.

 
  
 27
 Order of adjudication.

 
  
 33
 Orders regarding entries 
        in the Schedule.

 
  
 35
 Order annulling 
        adjudication.

 
  
 37
 Order declaring the 
        conditions on which the debtor’s property shall revert to him on 
        annulment of adjudication.

 
  
 41
 Order on application for 
        discharge.

 
  
 50
 Order disallowing or 
        reducing entries in the Schedule.

 
  
 53
 Order annulling a 
        voluntary transfer.

 
  
 54
 Decision that a transfer 
        of property is a reference in favour of the creditor.

 
  
  
 1[***]

 
  


 

 
 

 
 



    ---------------------------------
 


   1. The entry 
    relating to section 69 rep. by Act 12 of 1927, sec. 2 and Sch.
 



    ---------------------------------
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PROVINCIAL INSOLVENCY ACT, 1920
 


 
 


 
 


SCHEDULE II
 



(See section 81)
 



Provisions of the Act application of which 
    may be barred  

    by State Governments
 
 
  

 
  
 Provision of the Act
 Subject

 
  

 
  
 Section
  

 
  
 26
 Award of compensation.

 
  
 28, sub-section (3)
 Reputed Property of an 
        insolvent.

 
  
 34
 Debts provable under the 
        Act.

 
  
 38
  

 
  
 39
 Compositions and schemes 
        of arrangements.

 
  
 40
  

 
  
 42, sub-section (1) and 
        (2)
 Obligation to refuse 
        absolute discharge.

 
  
 45
  

 
  
 46
  

 
  
 47
  

 
  
 48
 Method of proof of debt.

 
  
 49
  

 
  
 50
  

 
  
 51
  

 
  
 52
  

 
  
 53
 Effect of insolvency on 
        antecedent transactions.

 
  
 54
  

 
  
 55
  

 
  
 61 [except clause (a) of 
        sub-section (1) and sub-section (4)
 Priority of debts

 
  
 62
  

 
  
 63
 Dividends

 
  
 64
  

 
  
 65
  

 
  
 66
 Management by an allowance 
        to insolvent.  

 
  
 72
 Penalty for obtaining of 
        credit by undischarged insolvent.

 
  


 

 
 


 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE PROVINCIAL INSOLVENCY ACT, 1920
 


 
 



 


 
 


SCHEDULE III
 


Enactments repealed.—[Rep. by the Repealing 
    Act, 1927 (12 of 1927), sec. 2 and Sch].
 


 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>