<act><title>


The Employment of Manual Scavengers and 
    Construction of Dry Latrines (Prohibition) 
    (Central) Rules, 19971</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Employment of Manual Scavengers and Construction of 
    Dry Latrines (Prohibition) (Central) Rules, 1997.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “Act” means the Employment of Manual 
    Scavengers and Construction of Dry Latrines (Prohibition) Act, 1993 (46 of 
    1993);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “Committee” means a committee 
    constituted under sub‑section (1) of section 13;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Member” means a member of the Committee 
    and includes its Chairper­son and the Member‑Secretary;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “section” means a section of the Act.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Composition of the Project Committee.—The 
    Project Committee which may be constituted by the Central Government under 
    clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub‑section (1) of section 13 shall consist of the following 
    persons, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Adviser, Central Public Health 
    Environmental                    Chairperson
 
      Engineering Organisation, Department of
 
      Urban Development.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   A representative of Ministry of Urban 
    Affairs                   Member
 
      and Employment (Department of Urban
 
      Development) not below the rank of a 
    Deputy
 
      Secretary to the Government of India.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>  An officer of the Ministry of Welfare 
    not                         Member
 
      below the rank of a Deputy Secretary to 
    the
 
      Government of India to be nominated by 
    the
 
      Secretary to the Government in that 
    Ministry.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>  An officer of the National 
    Environmental                         Member
 
       Engineering Research Institute, Nagpur 
    not
 
       below the rank of a Deputy Director, to 
    be
 
       nominated by the Director of that 
    Institute.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   An officer of the HUDCO not lower in 
    rank                       Member
 
       than an Executive Director/Chief 
    (Projects) to
 
       be 
    nominated by the Chairman and Managing
 
       Director 
    of HUDCO.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   Deputy 
    Adviser in‑charge of Low Cost                              Member
    
 

           Sanitation in the Central Public 
    Health                            Secretary.
 

           Environmental Engineering Organisation,
 

           Department of Urban Development.
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Composition of the Monitoring Committee.—The 
    Monitoring Committee which may be constituted by the Central Government 
    under clause (b) of sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 13 shall consist of the 
    following persons, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Adviser, Central Public Health 
    Environmental                    Chairperson
 
      Engineering Organisation, Department of
 
      Urban Development.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   A representative of the Ministry of 
    Urban                        Member
 
      Affairs and Employment (Department of 
    Urban
 
      Development), not below the rank of a 
    Deputy
 
      Secretary to the Government of India.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>  An officer of the Ministry of Welfare 
    not                          Member
 
      below the rank of a Deputy Secretary to 
    the
 
      Government of India to be nominated by 
    the
 
      Secretary to the Government in that 
    Ministry.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>  An officer of the National 
    Environmental                          Member
 
       Engineering Research Institute, Nagpur 
    not
 
       below the rank of a Deputy Director, to 
    be
 
       nominated by the Director of that 
    Institute.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   An officer of the HUDCO not lower in 
    rank                        Member
 
       than an Executive Director/Chief 
    (Projects) to
 
       be nominated by the Chairman and 
    Managing
 
       Director of HUDCO.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   Deputy Adviser in‑charge of Low 
    Cost                              Member
 
       Sanitation in the Central Public 
    Health                             Secretary.
 
       Environmental Engineering Organisation,
 
       Department of Urban Development.
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Functions 
    and powers of the Project Committee.—The 
    Project Commit­tee shall—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   conduct technical assessment of the 
    schemes formulated by the State Governments and Union Territory 
    Administrations with a view to assess­ing the economic viability of such 
    schemes and recommend such modi­fications as would result in cost reduction 
    and greater coverage, taking into account the topography, customs of the 
    inhabitants, availability of materials and other related aspects.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   submit the report prepared by it to the 
    Central Government in the Department of Urban Development by the 30th June 
    and the 31st December every year, the first report starting from 1997.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Functions 
    and powers of the Monitoring Committee.—The 
    Monitoring Committee shall—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   review periodically the progress of 
    schemes for conversion of dry latrines into water‑seal latrines and prepare 
    a status report indicating the States and Union Territories where special 
    efforts are needed to implement the Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   submit the report prepared by it to the 
    Central Government in the Department of Urban Development by the 30th June 
    and 31st December every year, the first report starting from 1997.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Terms and 
    conditions of appointment of members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The term of appointment of a member of a committee other than its 
    Chairperson and the Member‑Secretary, shall be for a period of three years.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A Member, 
    other than the Chairperson and the Member‑Secretary of a Committee may be 
    re-appointed to the Committee subject to condition that the aggregate of his 
    term of appointment at no time shall exceed six years.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    travelling allowance and daily allowance of the members for attending the 
    meetings of a committee and for tours in connection with the work of the 
    Committee shall be regulated by the rules as applicable to them in their 
    parent office represented by them and such expenses shall be borne by such 
    parent office.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Meetings 
    of a Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> A committee 
    shall meet as often as may be necessary to transact its business:  
 
Provided that 
    not more than three months shall elapse between two successive meetings.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    meetings of the Committee shall ordinarily be held in 
Delhi.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    representative of the States and Union Territories whose schemes are to be 
    reviewed by the Committee shall be invited to attend and participate in the 
    meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Chairperson of the concerned committee shall preside at all meetings. In the 
    absence of the Chairperson, the members present shall elect one amongst them 
    to preside at the meeting.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Notice of 
    meetings and list of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Member‑Secretary of the Committee shall draw up and circulate to the 
    Members of the Committee the agenda items and brief notes on such agenda 
    items at least ten days before the scheduled date of the meeting.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice 
    shall state the place, date and time of the meeting and specify the business 
    proposed to be transacted thereat.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No business 
    which is not on the agenda shall be considered at the meeting without the 
    permission of the Chairperson or in his absence the other presiding member, 
    as the case may be.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Quorum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At every meeting of a Committee, one third of its members shall form a 
    quorum.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If at any 
    meeting a quorum is not present, the Chairperson or the presiding member, as 
    the case may be, shall, after waiting for thirty minutes, adjourn the 
    meeting for such hour on the same day or the following day or some other day 
    as he may think fit and the notice of such adjournment shall be given to the 
    members present as well as affixed on the Notice Board of the committee and 
    the business which was to have been brought before the original meeting, had 
    there been a quorum, shall be brought before the adjourned meeting and may 
    be disposed of irrespective of the quorum.  
  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Minutes 
    of the meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> Immediately 
    after each meeting of a committee, the Member‑Secretary shall draw up the 
    minutes of the meeting and submit the same to the Chairperson or the other 
    presiding member as the case may be, for his approval for taking further 
    necessary action. The minutes so approved shall be circulated to the members 
    of the committee for inviting comments, if any.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The minutes 
    circulated under sub‑rule (1) shall be placed before the committee for 
    confirmation and shall be subject to such modification, if any, as the 
    committee may deem fit to be made therein, and the minutes so approved shall 
    be signed by the Chairperson or in his absence, the presiding member, as the 
    case may be and be entered in a book to be kept for that purpose.  
  
  
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>