<act><title>
THE
ILLEGALLY ACQUIRED PROPERTY (RECEIPT, MANAGEMENT AND
DISPOSAL) RULES, 19891</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
These rules may be called the Illegally Acquired Property (Receipt, Management
and Disposal) Rules, 1989.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their
publication in the Official Gazette.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In these rules, unless
the context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
“Act” means the Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Act, 1985
(61 of 1985);
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“Administrator” means any officer appointed by the Central Government
under sub-section (1) of section 68G of the Act;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“Form” means form annexed to these rules;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“Fund” means the National Fund for Control of Drug Abuse, constituted
under sub-section (1) of section 7A of the Act;
 </section><section><number>e</number>
“godown” means a godown for storage of property received under
sub-section (2) of section 68G of the Act.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Assistance to the Administrators.—The
Central Government may provide from time to time such members of staff and other
persons as it thinks fit to assist the Administrator in exercise of his powers
and performance of duties under these rules.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Designation of godowns.—
<section><number>1</number> The
Administrator shall designate as many godowns as may be necessary for the
storage of property mentioned in the orders made under sub-section (1) of
section 68F or sub-section (3) of section 68-I of the Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The Administrator shall select godowns referred to in sub-rule (1), keeping in
view the security of the premises, storage capacity, nature of property and
other relevant factors.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Each designated godown shall have a godown keeper and a
godown-in-charge to assist the Administrator.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Proper accounting of properties.—The
Administrator shall, at the time of receiving the properties, ensure proper
identification of such property with reference to its particulars mentioned in
the order made under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 68F or sub-section (3) of
section 68-I of the Act, as the case may be.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Godown register.—The Administrator
shall cause a register in Form I for recording entries in respect of property
other than the properties referred to in
rule 7 to be maintained.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>7</number>
Godown register for valuables.—The
Administrator shall cause a register in Form II for recording entries in respect
of property, namely, gold and gold jewellery, diamonds (including rough and
uncut diamonds), precious and semi-precious stones other than diamond and wrist
watches (hereinafter called ‘valuables’) to be maintained. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article> <number>8</number>
Storage of property.—
<section><number>1</number> The Administrator shall ensure that the packages
containing valuables are kept in the godown in an iron safe and vault, under
double lock system, one key remaining with the godown-keeper and the other to be
retained by the godown-in-charge. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Where, for any valid reasons, it is found that the packages containing valuables
may not be kept in godown, such packages shall be kept in lockers obtained
exclusively for this purpose, either with any branch of the Reserve Bank of
India or of any nationalized bank. 
 


 </section><section><number>4</number> The packages referred to in sub-rules (1) and (2) shall
be stored systematically casewise, serialwise, yearwise and with proper
identification marks to facilitate re-check and inspection.
 


  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>9</number>
Management of land and building.—The
Administrator may authorise any officer referred to in section 68T of the Act to
take possession of vacant land or building in respect of which—
 <section><number>i</number>
an order of seizure of freezing of such land or building has been made
under sub-section (1) of section 68F of the Act; or 
 

 </section><section><number>ii</number>
an order for forfeiture of such land or building has been made under
sub-section (1) of section 80-I of the Act. 
 

  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>10</number>
Occupation of land or building.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where any property in the nature of land or building is in possession of a
lessee or a tenant and against such property and order under sub-section (1) of
section 68F of the Act has been made, the Administrator may allow the lease or
tenant to continue in occupation of such land or building in accordance with
such terms and conditions which existed on the date of passing an order under
sub-section (1) of section 68F of the Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The income derived from such property shall be kept with the Administrator until
such time the competent authority declares the property forfeited under
sub-section (3) of section 68-I.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
Where any property is declared not liable to be forfeited under the Act, the
Administrator shall, within reasonable time, return to the person such property
and the income derived therefrom after deducting such expenses if any, which
were incurred on the maintenance and management of the property.
 


  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>11</number>
Record of land or building.—The
Administrator shall maintain a record of land or building in Form III.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>12</number>
Storage of property other than valuables.—
<section><number>1</number>
Movable property other than valuables shall be stored in almirahs and racks.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Each almirah and rack shall have a stock-card indicating the case number and
full description of the property.
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>13</number>
Placement of stock-cards.—The godown-in-charge
shall ensure that the racks or almirahs or any other thing used for storage of
property, display stock-cards indicating the case number and full description of
the property stored.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number>
Opening and re-sealing of the packages.—
<section><number>1</number>
Where any package is to be opened for any reason, the same shall be opened in
the presence of the owner and the concerned godown-in-charge after obtaining the
order of the Administrator.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The packages shall be re-sealed immediately after the purpose, for which such
packages were opened, is fulfilled in the presence of the owner and the
concerned godown-in-charge.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
At the time of re-sealing, the owner, and the concerned godown-in-charge, shall
affix their seals.
 



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>15</number>
Maintenance of seized/confiscated conveyances.—Conveyances,
such as aircrafts, vessels, motor vehicles and any other mode of conveyance
shall be properly maintained by the godown-in-charge. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>16</number>
Disposal of livestocks, perishables, etc.—Subject
to the sale proceeds being credited to the Fund under section 7A of the Act, the
Administrator shall dispose of the livestock and property which is perishable in
nature or prone to decay in the manner as he deems fit.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>17</number>
Disposal of valuables.—Subject to
the sale proceeds being credited to the Fund under section 7A of the Act, the
Administrator shall dispose of the valuables mentioned below in the following
manners, namely:—
 <section><number>1</number>
Gold, gold jewellery, silver and silver jewellery.—The
valuables, namely, gold, gold jewellery, silver and silver jewellery shall be
deposited in the Government of India Mints which shall credit the value of such
property to the Central Government. 
 

 </section><section><number>2</number>
Diamonds.—Rough and uncut diamonds shall be sold either by
auction or tender to import licence holders against debit of their licences. Cut
and polished diamonds shall be sold by auction or tender with the specific
condition that such diamonds shall be exported. 
 

 </section><section><number>3</number>
Precious and semi-precious stones other than diamonds.—(i) Rough
and uncut precious and semi-precious stones other than diamonds shall be sold by
auction or tender to holders of import licences against debit of their licences
in the internal market.
 <subsection><number>ii</number>
Cut and polished precious and semi-precious stones, other than diamonds, shall
be sold internally, by auction or by tender.

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number>
Disposal of currency.—
<section><number>1</number> Indian and
Foreign currency shall be deposited with the Reserve Bank of India or any
Nationalised Bank. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
The amount so deposited shall be credited to the Fund constituted under this
Act.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>19</number>
Disposal of the property.—Property
other than those mentioned in rules 16 to 18 shall be disposed of by public
auction.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number>
Disposal of land or building.—Subject
to the relevant provisions of any law relating to the acquisition or disposal of
immovable property and also subject to the sale proceeds being credited to the
Fund under section 7A of the Act, land or building shall be disposed of by
tender or by public auction. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number>
Disposal of conveyances.—Conveyances,
such as aircrafts, vessels, vehicles and other mode conveyance shall be sold by
public auction of or by tender.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>22</number>
Furnishing reports and returns.—The
Administrator shall furnish a quarterly statement to the Narcotics Control
Bureau indicating the value of the property received and disposed of and the
closing balance of all properties kept in the godowns and banks.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>23</number>
Periodical Reports.—The godown-in-charge
shall submit, every month, a report to the Administrator of the property
received or disposed of during the period. 
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>24</number>
Periodical inspection.—The
Administrator with a view to ensuring safety, security, proper accounting and
management of all properties in the godowns, conduct physical inspection and
verification with the help of such officers as he thinks fit.
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>25</number>
Record of receipt and disposal.—The
Administrator shall maintain a record of receipt and disposal of all properties
received and disposed of under these rules. He shall also maintain an account of
all income received and expenditure incurred on receipt, management and disposal
of such property.
  

 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE
ILLEGALLY ACQUIRED PROPERTY (RECEIPT, MANAGEMENT AND
DISPOSAL) RULES, 1989
 

 
 

 
 


Form
I
 


(See
rule 6)
 


Godown
Register
 

 
 

1.
Godown entry Sl. No. 
 

 

2.
Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Crime No.
 

3.
Description of property in the sealed packages/containers.
 

4.
No. of packages/containers.
 

5.
Quantity (package/containerwise). 
 

 

6.
Name(s) and address(es) of accused. 
 

 

7.
Name with official designation and address of seizing/depositing officer. 
 

 

8.
Facsimile of the seal put on the packages/containers by the seizing
officer/depositing officer. 
 

 

9.
Date and time of deposit. 
 

 

10.
Particulars of exit and re-entry for exhibiting to competent
authority/Tribunal. 
 

 

11. Date and time of removal for disposal. 
 

 

12.
Disposal particulars. 
 

 

13.
Certificate of disposal including price payment particulars and credit to
the Fund. 
 

 

14.
Remarks of the Inspecting Officer(s).  
 

 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE
ILLEGALLY ACQUIRED PROPERTY (RECEIPT, MANAGEMENT AND
DISPOSAL) RULES, 1989
 

 
 

 
 


Form
II
 


(See
rule 7)
 


Godown
Register for valuable*
 

 
 

1.
Godown entry Sl. No. 
 

 

2.
Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances Crime No. 
 

 

3.
Description of the valuables in packages/containers. 
 

 

4.
No of packages/containers (itemwise). 
 

 

5.
Condition of seal at the time of entry. 
 

 

6.
Quantity (package/containerwise). 
 

 

7.
Name(s) and address(es) of accused. 
 

 

8.
Name with official designation and address of seizing/depositing officer.
 

9.
Facsimile of the seal put on the packages/containers by the
seizing/depositing officer.
 

10.
Date and time of deposit. 
 

 

11.
Particulars of exit and re-entry for exhibiting to competent
authority/Tribunal.
 

12.
Date and time of removal for disposal. 
 

 

13.
Disposal particulars. 
 

 

14.
Certificate of disposal including price payment particulars and credit to
the National Fund for Control of Drug Abuse.
 

15.
Remarks of the Inspecting Officer(s).
 

 
 

*Valuables
will include: (1) Precious and semi-precious stones; (2) Gold and articles of
gold; (3) Jewellery; (4) Silver and articles of silver; and (5) Watches.

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 


THE
ILLEGALLY ACQUIRED PROPERTY (RECEIPT,
MANAGEMENT AND
DISPOSAL) RULES, 1989
 

 
 

 
 


Form
III
 


(See
rule 11)
 


Record
for Land and Building

 

 
 
 
 
 


Sl. 



 
 


Crime
      No.
        



 
 


Particulars
      of the Last Owner 



 
 


Location 



 
 


Description
      as per municipal revenue Records 



 
 


Area
      (in case of land) 



 
 


Value 



 
 


Annual
      Income 



 
 


Remarks 




 
 
 


1 



 
 


2 



 
 


3 



 
 


4 



 
 


5 



 
 


6 



 
 


7 



 
 


8 



 
 


9 




 
 
 


  


 


  



 
 


  



 
 


  



 
 


  



 
 


  



 
 


  



 
 


  



 
 


  



 
 


  






 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>