<act><title>


The Disaster Management (Term of Office and
Conditions 
of Service of Members of 
the National
Authority and 
Payment of Allowances to
Members of 
Advisory 
Committee) Rules, 20061</title> 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Disaster Management (Term of Office and Conditions 
of Service of Members of the National Authority and Payment of Allowances to 
Members of Advisory Committee) Rules, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 
 
 



</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Disaster Management Act, 2005 (53 of 2005);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “advisory 
committee” means the advisory committee constituted by the National Authority 
under sub-section (1) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  “member” means 
a member of the National Authority nominated by the Chairperson of the National 
Authority under clause (b) of sub-section (2) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  “section” 
means a section of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  
“Vice-Chairperson” means the Vice-Chairperson designated by the Chairperson of 
the National Authority under sub-section (3) of section 3.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions 
used herein and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Pay and service 
conditions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person nominated as a member of the National Authority shall exercise his 
option to choose either,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  Pay (less 
pension in the case of a retired officer), dearness allowance, accommodation, 
medical facilities, travelling allowance, leave travel concession as admissible 
to a Secretary to the Government of India and leave as admissible to a 
Government servant under the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  pay, daily 
allowance as admissible to a Union Minister of State and pension (without 
dearness relief in the case of retired officer), accommodation, medical 
facilities, travelling allowance as admissible to a Union Minister of State in 
accordance with the provision of the Ministers (Allowances, Medical Treatment 
and Other Privileges) Rules, 1957, made under the Salaries and Allowances of 
Ministers Act, 1952 (58 of 1952), and leave as admissible to a temporary 
Government servant under the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972, but 
without the facility of leave travel concession:
 
              Provided 
that the option once exercised shall be final.
 </subsection></section><section>
 <number>2</number> A member of the 
National Authority, who is designated as the Vice-Chairperson of the National 
Authority under sub-section (3) of section 3, shall be entitled to pay and daily 
allowance, as admissible to a Union Minister, who is a member of the Cabinet, 
and pension (without dearness relief) and in the case of member who is a retired 
officer, accommodation, medical facilities and travelling allowance as 
admissible to a Union Cabinet Minister in accordance with the provisions of the 
Ministers (Allowances, Medical Treatment and Other Privileges) Rules, 1957, made 
under the Salaries and Allowances of Ministers Act, 1952 (58 of 1952).
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Disqualifications.—No 
person shall be a member of the National Authority, who—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  is, or at any 
time has been, adjudged insolvent; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  is declared to 
be of unsound mind by a competent court; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  becomes 
incapable of acting as a member; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  is, or has 
been convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, 
involves moral turpitude;
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  is, or has 
been removed or dismissed from the service of the Government or a body corporate 
owned or controlled by the Government.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Resignation.—Any 
member of the National Authority may resign from the office of member of the 
National Authority by giving a notice in writing under his hand to that effect 
to the Chairperson of the National Authority and such resignation shall take 
effect from the date on which such notice is accepted by the Chairperson of the 
National Authority.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Vacancies.—Where 
a vacancy occurs in the office of a member of the National Authority by reason 
of resignation, disqualification, death or otherwise, the vacancy may be filled 
by fresh nomination.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Allowances to be 
paid to a member of the Advisory Committee constituted by the National 
Authority.—A 
member of the Advisory Committee constituted under sub­-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 7 
shall be paid such travelling allowances, room rent, daily allowances and 
conveyance allowance as are admissible to a member of the High Power Committee 
as specified in Appendix 2 to Supplementary Rule 190.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>