<act><tid>432589</tid>
<title>THE KHADI AND VILLAGE INDUSTRIES COMMISSION (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2006</year></title>

NO. 10 OF <year>2006</year>
[ 22nd March, <year>2006</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Khadi and Village Industries Commission 
Act, <year>1956</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- seventh Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-





<article><tid>623144</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1452497</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Khadi  
and Village Industries Commission (Amendment) Act, <year>2006</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1195492</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1025053</tid>
<number> 2</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the Khadi and Village 
Industries Commission Act, <year>1956</year> (61 of <year>1956</year>)  (hereinafter referred to  
  as the principal Act),-
<section><tid>176832</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (ff), for the words" ten thousand", the words" twenty 
thousand" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>249410</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (h), in sub- clause (i),-

<subsection><tid>16647</tid>
<number>A</number>for the words" fifteen thousand rupees", the words" one lakh 
rupees" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>441854</tid>
<number>B</number>after the proviso, the following proviso shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' Provided further that in the case of any industry located in a hilly 
area, the provisions of this sub- clause shall have effect as if for 
the words" one lakh rupees", the words" one lakh and fifty thousand 
rupees" had been substituted.'. 
3.

Amendment of section 4.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>442251</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 4.- In section 4 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1284841</tid>
<number>a</number>after sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (1A) Save as otherwise provided under this Act and the rules made 
thereunder, the exercise of all powers and discharge of all functions 
under this Act, including general superintendence, direction and 
management of day- to- day affairs of the Commission, shall vest in the 
Commission.";


</section>

<section><tid>650778</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>311794</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words" having specialised knowledge and 
experience of khadi and village industries", the words" having 
specialised knowledge and not less than ten years of experience of 
khadi or village industries" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1000576</tid>
<number>ii</number>for clause (b), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>650778</tid>
<number>b</number>four non- official members of whom each member shall be from the 
following disciplines, namely:-

<subsection><tid>311794</tid>
<number>i</number>one member having expert knowledge and experience in Science and 
Technology;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1000576</tid>
<number>ii</number>one member having expert knowledge and experience in Marketing;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>958458</tid>
<number>iii</number>one member having expert knowledge and experience in Rural 
Development; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1361736</tid>
<number>iv</number>one member having expert knowledge and experience in Technical 
Education and Training;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>958458</tid>
<number>iii</number>after clause (b), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ba) the Chairman of the State Bank of India constituted under sub- 
section (1) of section 3 of the State Bank of India Act, <year>1955</year> (23 of  
  <year>1955</year>) or an officer not below the rank of the Deputy Managing 
Director as may be nominated by the Chairman of the State Bank of 
India- ex- officio;";


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1361736</tid>
<number>iv</number>for clauses (c) and (d), the following clauses shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (c) a Chief Executive Officer, ex- officio; and


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>968653</tid>
<number>d</number>a Financial Adviser, who shall also be the Chief Accounts 
Officer of the Commission, ex- officio.";

<subsection><tid>1071191</tid>
<number>v</number>after clause (d), the proviso shall be omitted.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>380535</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 5.- In section 5 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>580855</tid>
<number>a</number>for sub- section (1), the following sub- sections shall be 
substituted, namely:-
" (1) Subject to the provisions contained in sub- section (1A) of 
section 4, the Chief Executive Officer, appointed under clause (c) of 
sub- section (2) of section 4, shall exercise such powers and 
discharge such functions in respect of general superintendence over 
the affairs of the Commission and its day- to- day management, as may 
be prescribed.


<subsection><tid>1761263</tid>
<number>1A</number>Without prejudice to the powers and functions referred to in 
sub- section (1), the Chief Executive Officer shall exercise such 
powers and discharge such functions under the general 
superintendence, direction and management of the Commission.".

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>777805</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2), for the words" shall be responsible", the 
words" shall, in addition to exercise of the powers and discharge of 
the functions referred to in sub- section (1), be responsible" shall 
be substituted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>551545</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 5A.- In section 5A of the principal Act, for 
the words, brackets, letter and figures" appointed under clause (c) 
of sub- section (2) of section 4 shall be in charge of all financial 
matters of the Commission including its budget, accounts and audit", 
the words, brackets, letter and figures" appointed under clause (d) 
of sub- section (2) of section 4 shall be in charge of such financial 
matters of the Commission including its budget, accounts and audit, 
as may be prescribed" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1483451</tid>
<number> 6</number> Amendment of section 10.- Section 10 of the principal Act, shall be 
numbered as sub- section
<section><tid>1430215</tid>
<number>1</number>thereof and,- 

<subsection><tid>851138</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1) as so numbered, for the words" Khadi and 
Village Industries Board'', the words'' National Khadi and Village 
Industries Board'' shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>974363</tid>
<number>b</number>after sub- section (1) as so numbered, the following sub- sections 
shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2) The Board shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), 
meet at such times and places and observe such rules of procedure 
in regard to the transaction of business at its meetings including 
the quorum at meetings as may be prescribed.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>30256</tid>
<number>3</number>The Board shall meet at least twice in a year.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1277446</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 12.- In section 12 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (3), for the words" votes of the members present", the 
words and brackets" votes of the members (including ex- officio  
  members) present" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>1460967</tid>
<number> 8</number> Insertion of new section 12A.- After section 12 of the principal 
Act, the following section shall be inserted, namely:-
" 12A. Zonal Committee.- (1) The Commission shall constitute for each 
of the six geographical zones, referred to in clause (a) of sub- 
section (2) of section 4, a Zonal Committee, which shall consist of 
the following, namely:-

<section><tid>1101309</tid>
<number>a</number>the non- official member representing the zone, referred to in 
clause (a) of sub- section (2) of section 4, who shall be the Chairman 
of the Zonal Committee constituted for respective zones;

</section>

<section><tid>1471154</tid>
<number>b</number>one representative of each of the State Khadi and Village 
Industries Boards of the States or, as the case may be, the 
Government of each State in the zone, to be notified by the Central 
Government in consultation with the State Government concerned- 
member;

</section>

<section><tid>777971</tid>
<number>c</number>the Zonal Deputy Chief Executive Officer of the Commission, who 
shall be the convener of the Zonal Committee- member;

</section>

<section><tid>1598410</tid>
<number>d</number>the State Directors in charge of the Commission' s Directorates 
for the States in the zone- member;

</section>

<section><tid>569414</tid>
<number>e</number>a Zonal or Regional manager of one of the lead banks operating in 
the zone- member; and

</section>

<section><tid>44347</tid>
<number>f</number>one representative of an institution of repute, working for at 
least ten years in the khadi or village industries sector and having 
a good record of performance, from each State in the zone, to be 
notified by the Central Government- member. 
 (2) The Zonal Committee shall meet at such times and places and 
shall, subject to the provisions of sub- section (3), observe such 
rules of procedure in regard to the transaction of business at its 
meetings (including the quorum at the meetings) as may be provided by 
regulations made by the Commission under this Act:
Provided that the Committee shall meet at least once in every three 
months.


<subsection><tid>1954863</tid>
<number>3</number>The Chairman of the Zonal Committee or, in his absence, any 
member chosen by the members present from among themselves, shall 
preside at a meeting of the Committee.

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>195819</tid>
<number>4</number>The Zonal Committee shall generally function as a forum for 
consultation and, accordingly, inter alia,-

<subsubsection><tid>707334</tid>
<number>a</number>act as a conduit for the dissemination of information relating to 
the programmes and schemes of the Commission for the development of 
khadi and village industries in the zone;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1773372</tid>
<number>b</number>monitor, from time to time, the implementation of the programmes 
and schemes referred to in clause (a);

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>689850</tid>
<number>c</number>provide feedback to the Commission on the problems and 
difficulties envisaged and suggestions made by banks, voluntary 
agencies, artisans and others engaged in the operation of programmes 
and schemes referred to inclause (a).".



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1386015</tid>
<number>9</number>Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, for the words" for a term of five years", the words 
" at the pleasure of the Central Government which shall not exceed 
continuous period of five years" shall be substituted;


</article>



<article><tid>1618333</tid>
<number> 10</number> Amendment of section 15.- In section 15 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>882336</tid>
<number>a</number>in sub- section (1), for the words" plan, promote, organise", the 
words" plan, promote, facilitate, organise" shall be substituted;

</section>

<section><tid>1694055</tid>
<number>b</number>in sub- section (2),-

<subsection><tid>1800540</tid>
<number>i</number>in clause (a), for the words" plan and organise", the words" plan 
and organise, directly or through specified agencies" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>873283</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (b),- 
 (A) for the words" build up", the words" build up, directly or 
through specified agencies," shall be substituted;

<subsubsection><tid>734383</tid>
<number>B</number>for the words" supply them", the words" supply them or arrange 
supply of the raw materials and implements" shall be substituted;

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>913990</tid>
<number>iii</number>in clause (g), for the words" provide financial assistance", 
the words" provide financial assistance, directly or through 
specified agencies," shall be substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>30252</tid>
<number>iv</number>in clause (h), for the words" undertake experiments", the words 
" undertake, directly or through specified agencies, experiments," 
shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1588318</tid>
<number>c</number>after sub- section (2), the following Explanation shall be 
inserted at the end, namely:-
' Explanation.- For the purposes of clauses (a), (b), (g) and (h) of 
sub- section (2), the expression" specified agencies" means the 
agencies which the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, specify in this behalf.'.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>226237</tid>
<number>11</number>Amendment of section 19A.- In section 19A of the principal Act, in 
sub- section 1, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:-
" Provided that the Chief Executive Officer and Financial Adviser 
shall be ex- officio members of the Standing Finance Committee in 
respect of each of the three separate funds referred to in sub- 
section (1) of section 18.".



</article>



<article><tid>1545871</tid>
<number>12</number>Amendment of section 25.- In section 25 of the principal Act, 
after sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be inserted at 
the end, namely:-
" (3) Any time after the issue of the notification under sub- section 
 (1), the Central Government may re- establish the Commission in 
accordance with the provisions of section 4 and on and from the date 
of the re- establishment of the Commission, the properties and funds 
which had previously vested in the Central Government under clause 
 (a) of sub- section (2) shall stand vested in the Commission so re- 
established.".


</article>



<article><tid>271262</tid>
<number> 13</number> Amendment of section 26.- In section 26 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), after clause (a), the following clauses shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (aa) the powers to be exercised and functions to be discharged by 
the Chief Executive Officer under sub- section (1) of section 5;

<section><tid>890864</tid>
<number>ab</number>the financial matters in respect of which the Financial Adviser 
shall be in charge under section 5A;

</section>

<section><tid>1508350</tid>
<number>ac</number>the transaction of business at the meetings of the Board under 
sub- section (2) of section 10;".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1216684</tid>
<number> 14</number> Amendment of section 27.- In section 27 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2),-
<section><tid>990190</tid>
<number>i</number>after clause (b), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
" (ba) the transaction of business at the meetings of the Zonal 
Committee under sub- section (2) of section 12A;";


</section>

<section><tid>265938</tid>
<number>ii</number>in clause (c), the words" the Chief Executive Officer or" shall 
be omitted.
----

T. K. VISWANATHAN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.





</section>

</article>



 </act>