<act><title>THE
ACTUARIES ACT, 2006 

</title> 

   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Actuaries Act, 2006.
 


 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India.
 


 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
 


 Provided
that different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and
any reference in any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be
construed as a reference to the commencement of that provision. 


   




</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “Actuary” means a person skilled in determining the present effects of future contingent events or in finance modelling and risk analysis in different areas of insurance, or calculating the value of life interests and insurance risks, or designing and pricing of policies, working out the benefits, recommending rates relating to insurance business, annuities, insurance and pension rates on the basis of empirically based tables and includes a statistician engaged in such technology, taxation, employees' benefits and such other risk management and investments and who is a fellow member of the Institute, and the expression “actuarial science” shall be construed accordingly; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “Actuarial Society” means the Actuarial Society of India registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860) and the Bombay Public Trusts Act, 1950 (Bombay Act No. XXXIX of 1950); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “appointed day” means the date on which the Institute is constituted under sub-section (1) of section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “Authority” means the Appellate Authority referred to in section 32; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “Board” means the Quality Review Board constituted under sub-section (1) of section 43; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “Council” means the Council of the Institute as referred to in  
  section 12; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “fellow” means a fellow member of the Institute; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> “Institute” means the Institute of Actuaries of India constituted under section 3; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> “member” means an individual whose name appears in the register of members maintained by the Institute; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> “President” means President of the Council; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> “register” means the register of members maintained by the Institute under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> “specified” means specified by regulations made under this Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> “Tribunal” means a Tribunal established under sub-section (1) of section 16; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> “Vice-President” means Vice-President of the Council; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> “year” means the period commencing on the 1st day of April of any year and ending on the 31st day of March of the succeeding year. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Save as otherwise provided in this Act, a member of the Institute shall be deemed “to be in practice” when individually or in partnership with Actuaries in practice as a member or an employee of a company, he, whether or not in consideration or remuneration received or to be received,— 
 <subsection><number>i</number> engages himself in actuarial profession; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> offers to perform or performs services involving the application of actuarial techniques in the fields of insurance, pension, investment, finance and management; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> renders such other services as, in the opinion of the Council, are or may be rendered by an actuary in practice; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> is in employment of a person engaged in one or more of the activities mentioned in clauses (i), (ii) and (iii) above, 
 and the words “to be in practice” with their grammatical variations and cognate expressions shall be construed accordingly. 
 <subsubsection><number>Explanations</number> —For the purpose of this sub-section, the expression “company” includes a public financial institution as defined in section 4A of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956). 
</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Incorporation of 
Institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, appoint, all persons whose names are entered in the register 
of the Actuarial Society at the commencement of this Act and all persons who may 
thereafter have their names entered in the register to be maintained under this 
Act, so long as they continue to have their names borne on the register, are 
hereby constituted a body corporate by the name of the Institute of Actuaries of 
India and all such persons shall be known as members of the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Institute shall 
have perpetual succession and a common seal and shall have power to acquire, 
hold and dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and shall by its name 
sue or be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The head office of the 
Institute shall be situated at such place as may be decided by the Central 
Government.


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Transfer of assets, liabilities, 
etc., of Actuarial Society. </title>—On the appointed day,— 

 
 <section><number>a</number> all the assets and liabilities of the Actuarial Society 
  shall stand transferred to, and vested in, the Institute; 
 Explanation. —The assets of the Actuarial Society 
  shall be deemed to include all rights and powers and all properties, whether 
  movable or immovable, including, in particular, cash balances, deposits and 
  all other interests and rights in, or arising out of, such properties as may 
  be in the possession of the said Society and all books of accounts and other 
  documents relating to the same; and liabilities shall be deemed to include all 
  debts, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> without prejudice to the provisions of clause (a), all 
  debts, obligations and liabilities incurred, all contracts entered into and 
  all matters and things engaged to be done by, with or for the Actuarial 
  Society immediately before that day, for or in connection with the purpose of 
  the said Society, shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into or 
  engaged to be done by, with or for, the Institute; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> all sums of money due to the Actuarial Society immediately 
  before that day shall be deemed to be due to the Institute; and 
 </section><section><number>d</number> all suits and other legal proceedings instituted or which 
  could have been instituted by or against the Actuarial Society immediately 
  before that day may be continued or may be instituted by or against the 
  Institute. </section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Objects of 
Institute.—The 
objects of the Institute shall be—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  to promote, 
uphold and develop the standards of professional education, training, knowledge, 
practice and conduct amongst Actuaries;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  to promote the 
status of the Actuarial profession;
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  to regulate 
the practice by the members of the profession of Actuary;
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  to promote, in 
the public interest, knowledge and research in all matters relevant to Actuarial 
science and its application; and
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  to do all such 
other things as may be incidental or conducive to the above objects or any of 
them.


</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Entry of names in 
register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any of the following persons shall be entitled to have his name entered in the 
register, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  any person who 
immediately before the appointed day was an associate or a fellow (including an 
honorary fellow) of the Actuarial Society;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  any person who 
has passed the examination conducted by the Actuarial Society and has completed 
training either as specified by the said Society or as specified by the Council, 
except any such person who is not a permanent resident of India;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  any person who 
has passed such examination and completed such training, as may be specified for 
membership of the Institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  any person who 
has passed such other examination and completed such other training outside 
India as is specified as being equivalent to the examination and training 
specified under this Act for membership of the Institute:
 
Provided that in the case 
of any person belonging to any of the classes mentioned in this sub-section who 
is not permanently residing in India, the Central Government or the Council may 
impose such further conditions as it may deem necessary or expedient in the 
public interest.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every person mentioned 
in clause (a) of sub-section (1) may have his name entered in the register 
without the payment of any entrance fee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every person belonging 
to any of the classes mentioned in clauses (b), (c) and (d) of sub-section (1) 
shall have his name entered in the register on an application being made and 
granted in the specified manner and on payment of such fees, as may be 
specified.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Council shall take 
such steps as may be necessary for the purpose of having the names of all 
persons belonging to the class mentioned in clause (a) of sub-section (1) 
entered in the register before the appointed day.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this section, the Council may confer on any person 
honorary fellow membership, if the Council is of the opinion that such person 
has made a significant contribution to the profession of Actuary and thereupon 
the Council shall enter the name of such person in the register but such person 
shall not have any voting rights in any election or meetings of the Institute 
and shall not also be required to pay any fee to the Institute.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Associates and 
fellows.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The members of the Institute shall be divided into two classes designated 
respectively as associates and fellows.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person other than 
a person to whom the provisions of sub-section (3) apply, shall, on his name 
being entered in the register, be deemed to have become an associate and as long 
as his name remains so entered, shall be entitled to use the letters “AIAI” 
after his name to indicate that he is an associate.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person who was a 
fellow of the Actuarial Society and who is entitled to have his name entered in 
the register under clause (a) of sub-section (1) of section 6 shall be entered 
in the register as a fellow.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person whose name 
is entered in the register as fellow shall, so long as his name remains so 
entered, be entitled to use the letters “FIAI” after his name to indicate that 
he is a fellow.


</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Honorary, affiliate 
and student members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may choose, in such manner as may be specified, any person of 
eminence in matters relating to and of interest to the profession of Actuary as 
an honorary member of the Institute provided that he is not practicing as an 
Actuary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person, who is a 
fellow member, or is a holder of membership considered equivalent to the fellow 
membership of the Institute, of any other institution similar to the Institute, 
whether within or outside India, may be admitted as an affiliate member for such 
period, and on such terms and conditions as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any person who enrolls 
himself for examination of the Institute, and possesses such academic 
qualifications as may be specified, may be admitted as a student member of the 
Institute on such terms and conditions as may be specified.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An honorary member or 
an affiliate member or a student member shall have no right to vote on any 
matter or resolution in any meeting of the Institute.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>9</number> Certificate of 
practice.—
<section><number>1</number> No 
member of the Institute shall be entitled to practice, unless he fulfils the 
qualifications as may to specified and obtains from the Council a certificate of 
practice.
 </section><section><number>2</number> A member who desires to be 
entitled to practice shall make an application in such form and pay such annual 
fee for certificate of practice as may be specified and such fee shall be 
payable on or before the first day of April in each year.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The certificate of practice 
obtained under sub-section (1) may be cancelled by the Council under such 
circumstances as may be specified.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Members to be known as 
Actuaries.—Every 
member of the Institute in practice shall, and any other member may, use the 
designation of an Actuary and no member using such designation shall use any 
other description whether in addition thereto or in substitution 
therefor:
 Provided that nothing contained in 
this section shall be deemed to prohibit any such member from adding any other 
description or letters to his name, if entitled thereto, to indicate membership 
of such other Institute, whether in India or elsewhere, as may be recognised in 
this behalf by the Council, or any other qualification that he may possess, or 
to prohibit a firm, all the partners of which are members of the Institute and 
in practice, from being known by its firm name as 
Actuaries.</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Disqualifications.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in section 6, a person shall not be entitled to have his name 
entered in, or borne on, the register if he—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  has not 
attained the age of twenty-one years at the time of his application for the 
entry of his name in the register; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  is of unsound 
mind and stands so adjudged by a competent court; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  is an 
undischarged insolvent; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  being a 
discharged insolvent, has not obtained from the court a certificate stating that 
his insolvency was caused by misfortune and without any misconduct on his part; 
or
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  has been 
convicted by a competent court whether within or outside India, of an offence 
involving moral turpitude and punishable with imprisonment or of an offence, not 
of a technical nature, committed by him in his professional capacity unless in 
respect of the offence committed he has either been granted a pardon or, on an 
application made by him in this behalf, the Central Government has, by an order 
in writing, removed the disqualification; or
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  has been 
removed from the membership of the Institute on being found on inquiry to have 
been guilty of a professional or other misconduct:
 
Provided that a person who 
has been removed from the membership for a specified period shall not be 
entitled to have his name entered in the Register until the expiry of such 
period.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Composition of 
Council of Institute.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be a Council of the Institute for the management of the affairs of 
the Institute and for discharging the functions assigned to it by or under this 
Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Council shall be 
composed of the following persons, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  a minimum of 
nine and not more than twelve persons from amongst fellow members to be elected 
by the fellow and the associate members of the Institute in such manner as may 
be prescribed:
 
                 Provided 
that a fellow of the Institute, who has been found guilty of any professional or 
other misconduct and whose name is removed from the Register or has been awarded 
penalty of fine, shall not be eligible to contest election,—
 <subsubsection>
             <number>i</number>  in case 
of misconduct falling under the Schedule of this Act [except Part IV(B)], for a 
period of three years; or
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  in case 
of misconduct falling under Part IV(B) of the Schedule of this Act, for a period 
of six years,
 
              after the 
completion of the period of removal of name of the fellow from the Register or 
the payment of fine is made, as the case may be; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number> (i)  an 
officer not below the rank of Joint Secretary to the Government of India, to be 
nominated by the Central Government to represent the Ministry of Finance;
 <subsubsection>
            <number>ii</number>  one 
person from the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority constituted under 
the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 (41 of 1999) 
nominated by the Central Government; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
            <number>iii</number>  not 
more than two persons having knowledge in the field of life insurance, general 
insurance, finance, economics, law, accountancy or any other discipline which in 
the opinion of the Central Government, would be useful to the Council, to be 
nominated in such manner as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that till such 
time as the Council is constituted under this Act, the Executive Committee of 
the Actuarial Society shall discharge all the functions and shall have all the 
powers of the Council.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No person holding a 
post under the Central Government or a State Government, as the case may be, 
shall be eligible for election to the Council under clause (a) of sub-section 
(2).
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> One-third of the 
members of the Council referred to in clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall retire 
as soon as may be on the expiration of every second year by rotation but shall 
be eligible for re-election.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Any person nominated 
under clause (b) of sub-section (2) shall hold office for a period of six years 
from the date of his nomination unless he is removed earlier by the Central 
Government and shall be eligible for re-nomination.
 
Provided that he shall be 
given an opportunity of being heard before such removal.


</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Annual general 
meetings.—The 
Council shall every year hold an annual general meeting of the Institute to 
elect its members under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) of section 12, or to 
discuss any matter which it deems fit, and not more than fifteen months shall 
elapse between the date of one annual general meeting of the Institute and that 
of the next:
 
Provided that from the 
appointed day the Institute may hold its first annual general meeting within a 
period of not more than eighteen months and if such general meeting is held 
within that period, it shall not be necessary for the Institute to hold any 
general meeting in that year:
 
Provided further that the 
Central Government may, for sufficient reasons, extend the time within which any 
general meeting shall be held.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Re-election to 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), a member of the Council elected 
under clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) of section 12 shall be eligible for 
re-election but not for more than two consecutive terms.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A member of the 
Council, who is or has been elected, as the President under sub-section (1) of 
section 17, shall not be eligible for election or nomination as a member of the 
Council.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Settlement of 
disputes regarding election.—In 
case of any dispute regarding any election under clause 
<section><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) 
of section 12, the aggrieved person may make an application within thirty days 
from the date of the declaration of the result of the election to the Council 
which shall forward the same forthwith to the Central Government.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Establishment of 
Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of any application under section 15, the Central Government shall, by 
notification, establish a Tribunal consisting of a Presiding Officer and two 
other Members to decide such dispute and the decision of such Tribunal shall be 
final.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A person shall not be 
qualified for appointment,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  as a Presiding 
Officer of the Tribunal unless he has been a member of the Indian Legal Service 
and has held a post in Grade I of the service for at least three years;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  as a Member 
unless he has been a member of the Council for at least one full term and who is 
not a sitting Member of the Council or who has not been a candidate in the 
election under dispute; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  as a Member 
unless he holds the post of a Joint Secretary to the Government of India or any 
other post under the Central Government carrying a scale of pay which is not 
less than that of a Joint Secretary to the Government of India.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The terms and 
conditions of service of the Presiding Officer and Members of the Tribunal, 
their place of meetings, remuneration and allowances shall be such as may be 
prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The expenses of the 
Tribunal shall be borne by the Council.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> President, 
Vice-President and Honorary Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall, at its first meeting, elect three of its members from amongst 
persons referred to in clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of sub-section (2) of section 12, to be 
respectively the President, Vice-President and Honorary Secretary thereof, and 
as often as the office of the President, Vice-President and Honorary Secretary 
falls vacant, the Council shall choose one of the member in the same manner:
 
Provided that the 
Chairperson of the Council of the Actuarial Society shall continue to hold such 
office as President after the commencement of this Act, until such time as a 
President is elected under the provisions of this sub-section.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The President shall be 
the Chief Executive Officer of the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The President, the 
Vice-President or the Honorary Secretary shall hold office for a period of two 
years from the date on which he is chosen provided that he continues to be a 
member of the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The President and the 
Vice-President shall, notwithstanding the expiration of his term, continue to 
hold office until his successor enters upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In the event of 
occurrence of any vacancy in the office of the President, the Vice-President 
shall act as the President until a new President is elected in accordance with 
the provisions of this section to fill such vacancy and enters upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> When the President is 
unable to discharge his functions owing to absence, illness or any other cause, 
the Vice-President shall discharge his functions until the President resumes his 
duties.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Resignation from 
membership and filling up of casual vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any member of the Council may at any time resign his membership by writing under 
his hand addressed to the President, and the seat of such member shall become 
vacant when such resignation is accepted and notified by the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A member of the 
Council, other than a member nominated under clause (b) of sub­-section (2) of 
section 12 shall be deemed to have vacated his seat if he is declared by the 
Council to have been absent without sufficient reason from three consecutive 
meetings of the Council, or of any of the Committees constituted by the Council, 
and of which he is a member or he has been found guilty of any professional or 
other misconduct and awarded penalty of fine or if his name is, for any cause, 
removed from the register under the provisions of sections 24 and 30.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A casual vacancy in 
the office of a member of the Council shall be filled by fresh election or by 
nomination by the Central Government, as the case may be, and the person elected 
or nominated to fill the vacancy shall hold office only for the remainder of the 
term for which the member in whose place he was elected or nominated would have 
held that office:
 
Provided that no election 
shall be held to fill a casual vacancy occurring within one year prior to the 
date of the expiration of the term of such member.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No act done by the 
Council shall be called in question on the ground merely of the existence of any 
vacancy in, or defect in the constitution of the Council.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Functions of 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The duty of carrying out the functions under the provisions of this Act shall be 
vested in the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, the functions of the 
Council shall include—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the holding of 
examination of the candidates for enrolment and specifying fees therefor;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the specifying 
of qualifications for entry in the register;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the 
recognition of foreign qualifications and training for the purposes of 
enrolment;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the granting 
of or refusal to grant the certificate of practice under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the 
maintenance and publication of a register of persons qualified to practice as 
Actuaries;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the levy and 
collection of fees from members, students, examinees and other persons;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  the removal of 
names from the register and the restoration to the register of names which have 
been removed;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  the regulation 
and maintenance of the status and standard of professional qualifications of 
members of the Institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  to issue 
guidelines for the observance of the members, including the student members;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  to receive 
gifts, grants, donations or benefactions from the Central or State Governments 
and to receive bequests, donations and transfer of movable or immovable 
properties from testators, donors or transferors, as the case may be;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  co-operating 
with educational or other institutions in any part of the world having objects 
wholly or partly similar to those of the Institute by exchange of members and 
generally in such manner as may be conducive to achievement of their common 
objects;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  instituting 
and awarding fellowships, scholarships, prizes and medals;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  giving gifts, 
grants, donations or benefactions to other institutions or bodies having objects 
similar to those of the Institute;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>n</number>  the carrying 
out, by granting financial assistance to persons other than members of the 
Council, or in any other manner, of research in the actuarial science;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>o</number>  the 
maintenance of a library and publication of books, journals and periodicals 
relating to actuarial science;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>p</number>  the exercise 
of disciplinary powers conferred by this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>q</number>  establishing 
such regional council or councils as may be decided from time to time and fixing 
their headquarters; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>r</number>  doing all 
such things as may be necessary, incidental or conducive to the attainment of 
all or any of the objects of the Institute.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Staff, remuneration 
and allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the efficient performance of its functions, the Council may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  appoint an 
Executive Director, a Treasurer and such other officers and employees as it 
deems necessary and fix their salaries, fees, allowances and other conditions of 
service; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  fix the 
allowances of the President, the Vice-President, the Honorary Secretary and 
other members of the Council and its Committees,
 
in such manner as may be 
specified.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Executive Director 
of the Council shall be entitled to participate in the meetings of the Council 
but shall not be entitled to vote thereat.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Committees of 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may constitute such committees from amongst its members, and co-opt 
therein persons who are not members of the Institute, as it deems necessary for 
the purpose of carrying out the provisions of this Act:
 
Provided that the number 
of co-opted members shall not exceed one-third of the total membership of the 
committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every committee 
constituted under this section shall elect its own Chairman: 
 
Provided that—
 <subsection>
        <number>i</number>  where the 
President is a member of such committee, he shall be the Chairman of such 
committee, and in his absence, the Vice-President, if he is a member of such 
committee, shall be its Chairman; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>ii</number>  where the 
President is not a member of such committee but the Vice-President is a member, 
he shall be its Chairman.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The committees shall 
exercise such functions and be subject to such conditions as may be specified.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Finances of 
Council.—
<section><number>1</number> 
There shall be established a fund under the management and control of the 
Council into which shall be paid all moneys (including donations and grants) 
received by the Council and out of which shall be met all expenses and 
liabilities incurred by the Council.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Council may invest 
any money for the time being standing to the credit of the fund in any security 
as it may deem prudent consistent with the considerations of security of such 
investments and maximum returns thereon.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this sub-section, the expression “securities” shall have the 
meaning assigned to it in section 2 of the Securities Contracts (Regulation) 
Act, 1956 (42 of 1956), as amended from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Council shall keep 
proper accounts of the fund distinguishing capital account from revenue account.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The annual accounts of 
the Institute shall be subject to audit by a Chartered Accountant in practice 
within the meaning of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) to be 
appointed annually by the Council:
 
Provided that no member of 
the Council who is a Chartered Accountant or a person who is in partnership with 
such member shall be eligible for appointment as an auditor under this 
sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> As soon as may be 
practicable at the end of each year, but not later than the 30th day of 
September of the year next following, the Council shall cause to be published in 
the Gazette of India, a copy of the audited accounts and the report of the 
Council for that year and copies of the said accounts and report shall be 
forwarded to the Central Government and to all the members of the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Council may borrow 
from a scheduled bank, as defined in the Reserve Bank of India Act, 1934 (2 of 
1934), or from any public financial institution—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  any money 
required for meeting its liabilities on capital account on the security of the 
fund or on the security of any other asset, for the time being belonging to it; 
or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  for the 
purpose of meeting current liabilities, pending the receipt of income, by way of 
temporary loan or overdraft.
 
Explanation.—The 
expression “public financial institution” means a financial institution 
specified in section 4A of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall maintain in the specified manner a register of the members of 
the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The register shall 
include the following particulars about every member of the Institute, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  his full name, 
date of birth, domicile, residential and professional addresses;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the date on 
which his name is entered in the register;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  his 
qualifications;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  whether he 
holds a certificate of practice; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  any other 
particulars which may be specified.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Council shall 
cause to be published in such manner as may be specified a list of members as on 
the 1st day of April each year, and shall, if requested to do so by any such 
member, send him a copy of such list, on payment of such amount as may be 
specified.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every member of the 
Institute shall, on his name being entered in the register, pay such annual 
membership fee as may be specified by the Council.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Removal of name 
from Register.—The 
Council may, by order, remove from the register the name of any member of the 
Institute—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  who is dead; 
or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  from whom a 
request has been received to that effect; or
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  who has not 
paid any specified fee required to be paid by him; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  who is found 
to have been subject to, at the time when his name was entered in the register, 
or who at any time thereafter has become subject to, any of the 
disqualifications mentioned in section 11; or
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number>  who for any 
other reason has ceased to be entitled to have his name borne on the register.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Re-entry in 
register.—The 
Council may re-enter the name of a member, whose name has been removed from the 
register for reasons mentioned in clauses (b), (c), (d) and (e) of section 24, 
by an order, and on paying such fees, and after satisfying such conditions and 
requirement as may be specified.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Disciplinary 
Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall constitute a Disciplinary Committee consisting of the 
President or the Vice-President of the Council as the Presiding Officer and two 
members of the Council elected by the Council and two members to be nominated by 
the Central Government from amongst the persons of eminence having experience in 
the field of law, education, economics, business, finance, accountancy or public 
administration:
 
Provided that the Council 
may constitute more regional Disciplinary Committees as and when it deems fit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Disciplinary 
Committee in making the inquiry under the provisions of this Act shall follow 
such procedure and submit the report to the Council within such time as may be 
prescribed.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Appointment of 
Prosecution Director.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may, by notification, appoint a Prosecution Director and such other 
employees to assist the Disciplinary Committee in making inquiries in respect of 
any information or complaint received by the Council under the provisions of 
this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In order to make 
inquiries under the provisions of this Act, the Prosecution Director shall 
follow such procedure as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Authority, Council, 
Disciplinary Committee and Prosecution Director to have powers of civil court.—For 
the purposes of an inquiry under the provisions of this Act, the Authority, the 
Disciplinary Committee and the Prosecution Director shall have the same powers 
as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
1908), in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  summoning and 
enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on oath;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  the discovery 
and production of any document; and
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  receiving 
evidence on affidavit.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>29</number> Action by Council on 
Disciplinary Committee’s report.—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of a report from 
the Disciplinary Committee, if the Council is satisfied that the member of the 
Institute is guilty of any professional or other misconduct, it shall record its 
findings accordingly and shall proceed in accordance with the provisions of 
section 30.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In case the Council is not 
satisfied with the report of the Disciplinary Committee and is of the opinion 
that it requires further inquiry, it may refer the report again to the 
Disciplinary Committee for such further inquiry as may be directed through an 
order of the Council.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the Council disagrees with 
the findings of the Disciplinary Committee, it may direct the Prosecution 
Director or itself make an appeal to the Authority.</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Member to be 
afforded opportunity of being heard.—Where 
the Council is of the opinion that a member is guilty of a professional or other 
misconduct mentioned in the Schedule, it shall afford to the member a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard before making any order against him and may 
thereafter take any one or more of the following actions, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  reprimand the 
member; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  remove the 
name of the member from the register permanently or for such period, as it 
thinks fit.
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  impose such 
fine as it may think fit, which may extend to five lakh rupees.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section, “member of the Institute” includes a person who 
was a member of the Institute on the date of the alleged misconduct although he 
has ceased to be a member of the Institute at the time of the inquiry.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Professional or 
other misconduct defined.—For 
the purpose of this Act, the expression “professional misconduct” shall be 
deemed to include any act or omission provided in the Schedule, but nothing in 
this section shall be construed to limit or abridge in any way the power 
conferred or duty cast on the Disciplinary Committee or the Prosecution Director 
to inquire into the conduct of any member of the Institute under any other 
circumstances.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Constitution of 
Appellate Authority.—The 
Appellate Authority constituted under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 22A of the 
Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949), shall be deemed to be the 
Appellate Authority for the purposes of this Act subject to the modification 
that for clause (b) of said sub-section (1), the following clause had been 
substituted, namely:—
 
            “(b) the 
Central Government shall, by notification, appoint two part-time Members from 
amongst the persons who have been members of the Council of the Institute of 
Actuaries for at least one full term and who is not a sitting member of the 
council;”.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Term of office of 
Members of Authority.—A 
person appointed as a Member shall hold office for a term of three years from 
the date on which he enters upon his office or until he attains the age of 
sixty-seven years, whichever is earlier.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Allowances, 
conditions of service of members and procedure etc., of Authority.—The 
provisions of section 22C, section 22D and section 22F of the Chartered 
Accountants Act, 1949 (38 of 1949) shall apply to the Authority in relation to 
allowances and terms and conditions of service of its Chairperson and members, 
and in discharge of its functions under this Act as they apply to it in the 
discharge of its functions under the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Officers and other 
staff of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council shall make available to the Authority such officers and other staff 
members as may be necessary for the efficient performance of the functions of 
the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The salaries and 
allowances and conditions of service of the officers and other staff members of 
the Authority shall be such as may be specified.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Appeal to 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any member of the Institute aggrieved by any order of the Council imposing on 
him any of the penalties referred to in section 30, may, within ninety days of 
the date on which the order is communicated to him, prefer an appeal to the 
Authority:
 
Provided that the 
Authority may entertain any such appeal after the expiry of the said period of 
ninety days, if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing 
the appeal in time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority may, 
after calling for the records of any case, revise any order made by the Council 
under section 30 and may—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  confirm, 
modify or set aside the order;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  impose any 
penalty or set aside, reduce or enhance the penalty imposed by the order;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  remit the case 
to the Disciplinary Committee for such further inquiry as the Authority 
considers proper in the circumstances of the case; or
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  pass such 
other order as the Authority thinks fit:
 
Provided that the 
Authority shall give an opportunity of being heard to the parties concerned 
before passing any order.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Penalty for falsely 
claiming to be a member, etc.—Subject 
to the provisions of section 10, any person who,—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  not being a 
member of the Institute,—
 <subsection>
             <number>i</number>  
represents that he is a member of the Institute in any of the manners mentioned 
in section 7; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>ii</number>  uses the 
designation “Actuary”; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>iii</number>  uses 
the letters “AIAI” or “FIAI” after his name; or
 </subsection><subsection>
           <number>iv</number>  practises 
the profession of an Actuary; or
 </subsection></section><section>
       <number>b</number>  being a member 
of the Institute, but not having a certificate of practice, represents that he 
is in practice, or practises as an Actuary,
 
shall be punishable on 
first conviction with fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, and on any 
subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to one year, or with 
fine which may extend to two lakh rupees, or with both.


</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>38</number> Penalty for using name of 
Institution, awarding degrees of actuarial science, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as otherwise provided in 
this Act, no person shall—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  use a name or a common seal which is identical with the name or the 
common seal of the Institute or so nearly resembles it so as to deceive or as is 
likely to deceive the public; or
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  award any degree, diploma or certificate or bestow any designation 
which indicates or purports to indicate the position or attainment of any 
qualification or competence in actuaryship similar to that of a member of the 
Institute; or
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>c</number>  seek to regulate in any manner whatsoever the profession of 
Actuaries.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Any person contravening the 
provisions of sub-section (1) shall, without prejudice to any other proceedings, 
which may be taken against him, be punishable with fine, which may extend on 
first conviction to fifty thousand rupees and on any subsequent conviction with 
imprisonment which may extend to one year, or, with fine which may extend to one 
lakh rupees, or with both.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing contained in this 
section shall apply to any University or other institution established by law or 
to any body affiliated to the Institute.</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>39</number> Companies not to engage in 
actuarial practice.—
<section><number>1</number> No company, whether incorporated in India or 
elsewhere, shall practice as Actuaries.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any company contravening the 
provisions of sub-section (1) shall be punishable on first conviction with fine 
which may extend to ten thousand rupees, and on any subsequent conviction with 
fine which may extend to twenty-five thousand rupees.</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Unqualified person 
not to sign documents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No person other than a fellow member of the Institute shall sign any document on 
behalf of an Actuary in practice or a firm of such Actuaries in his or its 
professional capacity.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person 
contravening the provisions of sub-section (1) shall, without prejudice to any 
other proceedings which may be taken against him, be punishable on first 
conviction with fine which may extend to fifty thousand rupees, and on any 
subsequent conviction with imprisonment which may extend to one year, or with 
fine which may extend to one lakh rupees, or with both.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Offences by 
companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If the person committing an offence under this Act is a company, the company as 
well as every person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the 
conduct of its business at the time of the commission of the offence shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against 
and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing 
contained in this sub-section shall render any such person liable to any 
punishment if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or 
that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been 
committed by a company and it is proved that the offence has been committed with 
the consent or connivance of, or that the commission of the offence is 
attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or 
other officer of the company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer 
shall also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “company” 
means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association of 
individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “director”, in 
relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Sanction to 
prosecute.—No 
person shall be prosecuted under this Act except on a complaint made by or under 
the order of the Council or of the Central Government.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>43</number>
Establishment of Quality Review Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government shall, 
by notification, constitute a Quality Review Board consisting of a Chairperson 
and not more than four Members:
 
Provided that in case the 
Board is constituted with two Members, one each shall be nominated by the 
Council and the Central Government, respectively.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson and 
Members of the Board shall be appointed from amongst the persons of eminence 
having experience in the field of law, education, economics, business, finance, 
accountancy or public administration.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Two Members of the 
Board shall be nominated by the Council and other two Members shall be nominated 
by the Central Government.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Functions of Board.—The 
Board shall perform the following functions, namely:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  to fix 
standards for the services provided by the members of the Institute;
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  to review the 
quality of services provided by the members of the Institute including actuarial 
audit services; and
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number>  to guide the 
members of the Institute to improve the quality of services and adherence to the 
various statutory and other regulatory requirements.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>45</number> Procedure of Board.—The 
Board shall follow in its meeting and in discharging its functions such 
procedure as may be prescribed.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>46</number> Terms and 
conditions of Chairman and Members of Board.—The 
terms and conditions of service of the Chairperson and the Members of the Board, 
their place of meetings, remuneration and allowances shall be such as may be 
prescribed.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Expenditure of 
Board.—The 
expenditure of the Board shall be borne by the Council.
</article> 

  
 <article><number>48</number> Dissolution of Actuarial 
Society of India.—On the appointed day,—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  the Society known as the Actuarial Society of India registered under 
the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860) and the Bombay Public Trusts 
Act, 1950 (Bombay Act XXXIX of 1950) shall stand dissolved and thereafter no 
person shall make, assert or take any claims or demands or proceedings against 
the dissolved society or against any officer thereof in his capacity as such 
officer except in so far as may be necessary, for enforcing the provisions of 
this Act;
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  the right of every member to, or in respect of, the dissolved society 
shall be extinguished, and thereafter no member of the society shall make, 
assert or take any claims or demands or proceedings in respect of that society 
except as provided in this Act.</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Provisions 
respecting employees of dissolved society.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every person employed in the dissolved society and continuing in its employment 
immediately before the commencement of this Act shall, as from such 
commencement, become an employee of the Institute, shall hold his office or 
service therein by the same tenure and upon the same terms and conditions and 
with the same rights and privileges as to retirement benefits as he would have 
held the same under the dissolved society if this Act had not been passed, and 
shall, continue to do so unless and until his employment in the Institute is 
terminated or until his remuneration, terms and conditions of employment are 
duly altered by the Institute.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in the Industrial Disputes Act, 1947 (14 of 1947) or in any 
other law for the time being in force, the transfer of the services of any 
employee of the dissolved society to the Institute shall not entitle any such 
employee to any compensation under that Act or other law, and no such claims 
shall be entertained by any court, tribunal or other authority.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>50</number> Maintenance of more than one 
offices by Actuary.—
<section><number>1</number> Where an Actuary in practice 
or a firm of such Actuaries has more than one offices within or outside India, 
each one of such offices shall be in the separate charge of a fellow member of 
the Institute:
 Provided that the Council may in 
suitable cases exempt any Actuary in practice or firm of such Actuaries from the 
operation of this sub-section.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every Actuary in practice or a 
firm of such Actuaries maintaining more than one office shall send to the 
Council a list of offices and the person in charge thereof and shall keep the 
Council informed of any changes in relation thereto.</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Reciprocity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any country, notified by the Central Government in this behalf in the 
Official Gazette, prevents persons of Indian domicile from becoming members of 
any institution similar to the Institute or from practicing the profession of 
Actuaries or subjects them to unfair discrimination in that country, no subject 
of any such country shall be entitled to become a member of the Institute or 
practice the profession of Actuaries in India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Subject to the 
provisions of sub-section (1), the Council may specify the conditions, if any, 
subject to which foreign qualifications relating to actuarial science shall be 
recognised for the purposes of entry in the register.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Power of Central 
Government to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purposes of this Act, the Central Government may, from time to time, 
give to the Council such general or special directions as it thinks fit, and the 
Council shall, in the discharge of its functions under this Act, comply with 
such directions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If, in the opinion of 
the Central Government, the Council has persistently made default in giving 
effect to the directions issued under sub-section (1), it may, after giving an 
opportunity of being heard to the Council, by notification, dissolve the 
Council, whereafter a new Council shall be constituted in accordance with the 
provisions of this Act with effect from such date as may be decided by the 
Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Central 
Government has issued a notification under sub-section (2) dissolving the 
Council, it may, pending the constitution of a new Council in accordance with 
the provisions of this Act, authorise any person or body of persons to take over 
the management of the affairs of the Council and to exercise such functions as 
may be mentioned in the notification.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>53</number> Protection of action taken in 
good faith.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or the Council or the Disciplinary Committee or the Tribunal or the 
Authority or the Board or the Prosecution Director or any officer of that 
Government, Council, Committee, Tribunal, Authority or Board, for anything which 
is in good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule, 
regulation, notification, direction or order made 
thereunder.</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>54</number> Members, etc., to 
be public servants.—The 
Chairperson, Presiding Officer, Members and other officers and employees of the 
Authority, Tribunal and Board, and the Prosecution Director shall be deemed to 
be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 
of 1860).
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>55</number> Power of Central 
Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the manner of 
election and nomination in respect of members to the Council under sub-section 
(2) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the terms and 
conditions of service of the Presiding Officers and Members of the Tribunal, 
place of meeting, remuneration and allowances to be paid to them under 
sub-section (3) of section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the procedure 
of inquiry and submission of report by the Disciplinary Committee under 
sub-section (2) of section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the procedure 
of inquiry by the Prosecution Director under sub-section (2) of section 27;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  any act or 
omission which may be determined as professional misconduct under section 31;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the procedure 
to be followed by the Board in its meetings and discharging its functions under 
section 45; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  terms and 
conditions of service of the Chairman and Members of the Board under section 46.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>56</number> Power to make 
regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Council may, with the previous approval of the Central Government and 
subject to the previous publication, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
make regulations to carry out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  the 
examination and training for the purposes of clauses (b), (c) and (d) of 
sub-section (1) of section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  the manner of 
making an application under sub-section (3) of section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  the fees 
payable under sub-section (3) of section 6, sub-section (2) of section 9, clause 
(a) of sub-section (2) of section 19, sub-section (4) of section 23;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  the manner in 
which the honorary member may be chosen under sub­-section (1) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  the terms and 
conditions on which an affiliate member may be admitted under sub-section (2) of 
section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number>  the academic 
qualifications for admission of a student member under sub-section (3) of 
section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number>  qualifications 
required for a certificate of practice under sub- section (1) and the form in 
which an application may be made under sub-section (2) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number>  the 
transaction of business by the Council for the discharge of its functions 
mentioned in sub-section (2) of section 19;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number>  terms and 
conditions of the services under sub-section (1) of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>j</number>  the functions 
and conditions of the committees under sub-section (3) of section 21;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>k</number>  the manner in 
which the register of the members of the Institute and other particulars to be 
maintained under sub-sections (1) and (2) of section 23;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>l</number>  the manner in 
which the annual list of members of the Institute may be published under 
sub-section (3) of section 23;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  the conditions 
and requirements and payment of fee for re-entry in the register under section 
25;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>n</number>  salaries and 
allowances and conditions of service of the officers and other staff members of 
the Authority under sub-section (2) of section 35;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>o</number>  the conditions 
subject to which foreign qualifications may be recognised under sub-section (2) 
of section 51; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>p</number>  any other 
matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed under this Act.
</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>57</number> Power of Central 
Government to issue directions for making or amending regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where the Central Government considers it expedient so to do, it may, by order 
in writing, direct the Council to make any regulations or to amend or revoke any 
regulations already made within such period as it may specify in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Council fails 
or neglects to comply with such order within the specified period, the Central 
Government may itself make the regulations or amend or revoke the regulations 
made by the Council.
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>58</number> Laying of rules and 
regulations.—Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall, thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation.
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>59</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order, published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may appear to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no such 
order shall be made under this section after the expiry of a period of two years 
from the commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament.
</section></article><form>
 




The Actuaries Act, 2006
 

 
 




The Schedule
 


(See section 31)
 



Part 1
 




Professional misconduct in relation to members  

of the Institute in practice
 


An Actuary in practice 
shall be deemed to be guilty of professional misconduct, if he—
 


        (1)  allows any 
person to practice in his name as an actuary unless such person is also an 
actuary in practice and is in partnership with or employed by himself; or
 


        (2)  pays by way of 
remuneration to an employee, pays or allows or agrees to pay or allow, directly 
or indirectly, any share, commission or brokerage in the fees or profits of his 
professional business, to any person other than a member of the Institute or a 
partner or a retired partner or the legal representative of a deceased partner; 
or
 


        (3)  enters into 
partnership with any person other than an Actuary in practice or a person 
resident outside India who but for his residence abroad would be entitled to be 
admitted as a member under clause (c) of sub-section (1) of section 6 or whose 
qualifications are recognised by the Central Government or the Council for the 
purpose of permitting such partnership, provided the Actuary shares in the fees 
or profits of the business of the partnership both within and outside of India; 
or
 


        (4)  secures either 
through the services of a person who is not an employee of such Actuary or who 
is not qualified to be his partner or by means which are not open to an Actuary, 
any professional business; or
 


        (5)  accepts an 
assignment as Actuary previously held by another Actuary without first 
communicating with him in writing; or
 


        (6)  charges or 
offers to charge, accepts or offers to accept in respect of any professional 
employment fees which are based on a percentage of profit or which are 
contingent upon the findings or results of such employment, except as permitted 
under any regulation made under this Act; or
 


        (7)  engages in any 
business or occupation other than the profession of Actuaries unless permitted 
by the Council so to engage:
 


                  Provided 
that nothing contained herein shall disentitle an Actuary from being a director 
of a company; or
 


        (8)  accepts a 
position as an actuary previously held by some other Actuary in practice in such 
conditions as to constitute undercutting; or
 


        (9)  allows a 
person not being a member of the Institute in practice, or a member not being 
his partner to sign on his behalf or on behalf of his firm, any valuation report 
or financial statement; or
 


      (10)  discloses 
information acquired in the course of his professional engagement to any person 
other than his client so engaging him, without the consent of such client, or 
otherwise than as required by any law for the lime being in force; or
 


      (11)  certifies or 
submits in his name, or in the name of his firm, a valuation report or a 
financial statement unless the examination of such statement and the related 
records has been made by him or by a partner or an employee in his firm or by 
another Actuary in practice; or
 


      (12)  expresses his 
opinion or valuation reports or financial statements of any business or any 
enterprise in which he, his firm, or a partner in his firm has a substantial 
interest, unless he has disclosed the interest also in his report; or
 


      (13)  fails to 
disclose a material fact known to him in a valuation report or a financial 
statement, but disclosures of which is necessary to make the valuation report or 
the financial statement not misleading where he is concerned with such valuation 
report or the financial statement in a professional capacity; or
 


      (14)  fails to report 
a material misstatement known to him to appear in a valuation report or 
financial statement with which he is concerned in a professional capacity; or
 


      (15)  is grossly 
negligent in the conduct of his professional duties; or
 


      (16)  fails to obtain 
sufficient information to warrant the formation of an opinion in regard to any 
matter contained in any valuation report or financial statement prepared by him 
or on his behalf; or
 


      (17)  fails to invite 
attention to any material departure from the generally accepted procedure or 
professional work applicable to the circumstances, in any valuation report or 
financial statement prepared by him or on his behalf.
 



Part II
 




Professional misconduct in relation to the  

members of the Institute in service
 


A member of the Institute 
(other than a member in practice) shall be deemed to be guilty of professional 
misconduct, if he being an employee of any company, firm or person,—
 


        (1)  pays or allows 
or agrees to pay directly or indirectly to any person any share in the 
emoluments of the employment undertaken by him; or
 


        (2)  accepts or 
agrees to accept any part of fees, profits or gains by way of commission or 
gratification; or
 


        (3)  discloses 
confidential information acquired in the course of his employment except as and 
when required by law or except as permitted by his employer.
 



Part III
 




Professional misconduct in relation to members  

of the Institute generally
 


A member of the Institute, 
whether in practice or not, shall be deemed to be guilty of professional 
misconduct, if he—
 


        (1)  includes in 
any statement, return or form to be submitted to the Council any particulars 
knowing them to be false; or
 


        (2)  not being a 
fellow member of the Institute acts himself as a fellow member of the Institute; 
or
 


        (3)  does not 
supply the information called for or does not comply with the requirements asked 
for by the Council or any of its Committees; or
 


        (4)  contravenes 
any of the provisions of this Act or the regulations made thereunder or any 
guidelines issued by the Council under clause (1) of sub-section (2) of section 
19; or
 


        (5)  is guilty of 
such other act or omission as may be specified by the Council.
 



Part IV
 




Other misconduct in relation to member of  

the Institute generally
 


A member of the Institute, 
whether in practice or not, shall be deemed to be guilty of other misconduct, 
if—
 


       (A) (1) he is held 
guilty by any civil or criminal court for an offence which is punishable with 
imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months;
 


             (2) in the 
opinion of the Council, he brings disrepute to the profession or the Institute 
as result of his action whether or not related to his professional work;
 


        (B)  he is held 
guilty by any civil or criminal court for an offence which is punishable with 
imprisonment for a term exceeding six months.
 


 
 


—————
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Came
into force on 10th November, 2006, vide S.O. 1912(E), dated 8th November,
2006.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>