<act><tid>454464</tid>
<title>THE BENGAL, BIHAR AND ORISSA AND ASSAM LAWS ACT, <year>1912</year></title>

ACT NO. 7 OF <year>1912</year> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
[ 26th March, <year>1912</year>.]

An Act to make certain provisions regarding the application of the law 
in force in the Presidency of Fort William in Bengal, the Province of 
Bihar and Orissa and the Province of Assam.

WHEREAS a Governor and an Executive Council have been appointed 
for the Presidency of Fort William in Bengal;

AND WHEREAS, by Proclamation <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> published under Notification No. 
290, dated the twenty- second day of March, <year>1912</year>, the Governor- General 
in Council, with the sanction of His Majesty, has been pleased to 
declare and appoint that, on and from the first day of April, <year>1912</year>, 
the territory mentioned in Schedule A shall be and continue subject to 
the said Presidency of Fort William in Bengal;

AND WHEREAS, by Proclamation <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> published under Notification No. 
289, dated the twenty- second day of March, <year>1912</year>, the Governor- General, 
with the sanction of His Majesty, has been pleased to constitute the 
territory mentioned in Schedule B to be, for the purposes of the 
Indian Councils Act, <year>1861</year>, <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> (24 and 25 Vict., c. 67.) a Province to 
which the provisions of that Act touching the making of Laws and 
Regulations for the peace and good government of the Presidencies of 
Fort St. George and Bombay shall be applicable, and to direct that the 
said Province shall be called the Province of Bihar and Orissa, and 
further to appoint a Lieutenant- Governor of that Province;

AND WHEREAS, by Proclamation <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> published under Notification No. 
291, dated the twenty- second day of March, <year>1912</year>, the Governor- General 
in Council, with the sanction and approbation of the Secretary of 
State for India, has been pleased to take under his immediate 
authority and management the territory mentioned in Schedule C, which 
was formerly included within the Province of Eastern Bengal and Assam, 
and to form the same into a Chief Commissionership, to be called the 
Chief Commissionership of Assam, and further to appoint a Chief 
Commissioner therefor;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to make certain provisions regarding 
the application of the law in force in the territories affected by the 
said Proclamations;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>84</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the territories 
specified in the Schedule to the Malkharoda and Gaontia Villages Laws 
Act, <year>1923</year> (22 of <year>1923</year>), shall not be deemed to be included within the 
Province of Bihar and Orissa, see s. 2 of the latter Act. 
2. See the Gazette of India, Extraordinary, of the 22nd March, <year>1912</year>. 
3. Rep. and re- enacted by the Government of India Act, <year>1915</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1375341</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1807404</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Bengal, Bihar and Orissa and Assam Laws Act, <year>1912</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>588102</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on the first day of April, <year>1912</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1995402</tid>
<number>2</number>Saving of territorial application of enactments. The 
Proclamations referred to in the preamble shall not be deemed to have 
effected any change in the territorial application of any enactment, 
notwithstanding that such enactment may be expressed to apply or 
extend to the territotries for the time being under a particular 
administration.


</article>



<article><tid>278904</tid>
<number>3</number>Construction of certain references in enactments in force in 
territory mentioned in Schedules A, B and C. All enactments made by 
any authority in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], and all notifications, orders, schemes, 
rules, forms and by- laws issued, made or prescribed under such 
enactments, which, immediately before the commencement of this Act, 
were in force in, or prescribed for, any of the territory mentioned in 
Schedule A, Schedule B or Schedule C, shall, in their application to 
that territory, be construed as if references therein to the 
authorities, territory or Gazettes mentioned in column 1 of Schedule D 
were references to the authorities, territory or Gazettes respectively 
mentioned or referred to opposite thereto in column 2 of that 
Schedule.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>1824062</tid>
<number>4</number>[ Constitution of Board of Revenue in Bihar and Orissa.] Rep. 
by the Bihar and Orissa Board of Revenue Act, <year>1913</year> (B, and O. Act I of  
  <year>1913</year>), s. 7 and Sch. I.


</article>



<article><tid>1753381</tid>
<number> 5</number> Powers of Courts and State Governments for facilitating 
application of enactments. For the purpose of facilitating the 
application to the territory, or any part thereof, mentioned in 
Schedule A, Schedule B or Schedule C of any enactment passed before 
the Commencement of this Act, or of any notification, order, scheme, 
rule, form or by- law made under any such enactment,--
<section><tid>1978493</tid>
<number>a</number>any court may, subject to the other provisions of this 
Act, construe the enactment, notification, order, 
scheme, rule, form or by- law with such alterations, not 
affecting the substance, as may be necessary or proper 
to adapt it to the matter before the Court; and

</section>

<section><tid>1623004</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Government may, by notification in the 
Official Gazette, direct by what officer any authority 
or power shall be exercisable; and any such 
notification shall have effect as if enacted in this 
Act.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>85</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the States". 
2. The proviso to s. 3 rep. by Act 38 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>102330</tid>
<number>6</number>Pending proceedings. Nothing in this Act shall affect any 
proceeding which, at the commencement thereof, is pending in or in 
respect of any of the territory mentioned in Schedule A, Schedule B or 
Schedule C; and every such proceeding shall be continued as if this 
Act had not been passed.
 7 an

Amendments of Acts. Repeal.

 7 and 8.[ Amendments of Acts. Repeal.] Rep. by the Repealing Act, 
 <year>1938</year> (1 of <year>1938</year>), s. 2 and Sch.



</article>



<article><tid>1121553</tid>
<number>9</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Application to adaptations and modifications made under 
Article 372 or 372A of the Constitution. References in this Act, by 
whatever form of words, to Indian laws in force immediately before the 
commencement of this Act shall, after the commencement of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> the 
Constitution], be construed as references to those laws as adapted and 
modified under <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Article 372 <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> or 372A] of the Constitution].]

</article>



 </act>