<act><tid>463150</tid>
<title>THE ELECTION LAWS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2003</year></title>

ACT NO. 24 OF <year>2003</year>
[ 22nd March, <year>2003</year>.]

An Act further to amend the Representation of the People Act, <year>1951</year> and 
the Indian Penal Code.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- fourth Year of the Republic 
of India as follows:-

CHAP

PRELIMINARY

CHAPTER I

PRELIMINARY





<article><tid>93952</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.-
<section><tid>1951933</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Election Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>2003</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>494019</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on such date as the Central Government 
may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
CHAP

AMENDMENT TO THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PROPLE ACT, <year>1951</year>

CHAPTER II

AMENDMENT TO THE REPRESENTATION OF THE PEOPLE ACT, <year>1951</year>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>223060</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of section 59.- In the Representation of the People Act, 
 <year>1951</year> (43 of <year>1951</year>)  (hereafter in this Chapter referred to as the  
  principal Act), in section 59, for the words", and no votes shall be 
received by proxy", the words" and, save as expressl provided by this 
Act, no votes shall be received by proxy" shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>460193</tid>
<number> 3</number> Substitution of new section for section 60.- For section 60 of the 
principal Act, the following section shall be substituted, namely:-
" 60. Special procedure for voting by certain classes of 
persons.- Without prejudice to the generality of the provisions 
contained in section 59, provision may be made, by rules made under 
this Act, for enabling-

<section><tid>1978910</tid>
<number>a</number>any of the persons as is referred to in clause (a) or clause (b) 
of sub- section (8) of section 20 of the Representation of the People 
Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of <year>1950</year>)  (hereafter in this section referred to as the  
  1950-Act) to give his vote either in person or y postal ballot or by 
proxy, and not in any other manner, at an election in a constituency 
where poll is taken;

</section>

<section><tid>1089613</tid>
<number>b</number>any of the following persons to give his vote either in person or 
by postal ballot, and not in any other manner, at an election in a 
constituency where a poll is taken, namely:-

<subsection><tid>1432409</tid>
<number>i</number>any person as is referred to in clause (c) or clause (d) of 
sub- section (8) of section 20 of the 1950-Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>105346</tid>
<number>ii</number>the wife of any such person to whom the provisions of sub- section 
 (3) of section 20 of the 1950-Act apply and such wife being ordinarily 
residing with that person in terms of sub- section (6) of that section;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1916286</tid>
<number>c</number>any person belonging to a class of persons notified by the 
Election Commission in consultation with the Government to give his 
vote by postal ballot and not in any other manner, at an election in a 
constituency where a poll is taken subject to the fu filment of such 
requirements as may be specified in those rules;

</section>

<section><tid>758617</tid>
<number>d</number>any person subjected to preventive detention under any law for the 
time being in force to give his vote by postal ballot, and not in any 
other manner, at an election in a constituency where a poll is taken, 
subject to the fulfilment of such requireme ts as may be specified in 
those rules.".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1703121</tid>
<number>4</number>Amendment of section 62.- In section 62 of the principal Act, after 
sub- section (5), the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (6) Nothing contained in sub- sections (3) and (4) shall apply to a 
person who has been authorised to vote as proxy for an elector under 
this Act in so far as he votes as a proxy for such elector.".

CHAP

AMENDMENT TO THE INDIAN PENAL CODE

CHAPTER III

AMENDMENT TO THE INDIAN PENAL CODE



</article>



<article><tid>1004668</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 171D.- In section 171D of the Indian Penal 
Code (43 of <year>1860</year>), the following proviso shall be inserted at the end, 
namely:-
" Provided that nothing in this section shall apply to a person who has 
been authorised to vote as proxy for an elector under any law for the 
time being in force in so far as he votes as a proxy for such 
elector.".

SUBHASH C. JAIN,

Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>