<act><title>
THE 
    INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT BANK OF INDIA 
    GENERAL REGULATIONS, 19941</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These Regulation may be called the Industrial Development Bank of India 
    General Regulations, 1994.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date on their publication in the 
    Official Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
    these regulations, unless the context otherwise requires,—  
 <section>


    <number>a</number>    “the Act” means the Industrial Development Bank of India Act, 1964 
    (18 of 1964);  
 </section><section>


    <number>b</number>    “Form” means a form appended to these regulations;  
 </section><section>


    <number>c</number>    “member” means a Member of the Executive Committee constituted under 
    sub-section (1) of section 7 of the Act, or, as the case may be, any other 
    Committee constituted under sub-section (3) of section 7 of the Act;  
 </section><section>


    <number>d</number>    “register” means the register of shareholders kept in one or more 
    books of the Development Bank and includes the register of shareholders kept 
    in computer floppies or diskettes under section 13B of the Act;  
 </section><section>


    <number>e</number>    words and expressions used and not defined in these regulations but 
    defined in the Act shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in 
    the Act.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>3</number> Meetings of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Meetings of the Board shall be convened by the Chairman or, in his absence, 
    by the Managing Director or in the absence of both, by the whole time 
    Director.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Any three Directors may require the Chairman or in his absence, the 
    Managing Director or in the absence of both, the whole-time Director to 
    convene a meeting of the Board at any time and he shall forthwith convene a 
    meeting accordingly.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Meetings of the Board shall be held at the head office of the 
    Development Bank, or at such other place in India as may be specified in the 
    notice convening the meeting.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> Not less than fifteen days notice shall ordinarily be given of each 
    meeting of the Board and such notice shall be sent to every Director at his 
    usual address in India. Should it be found necessary to convene an emergency 
    meeting, sufficient notice shall be given to every Director to enable him to 
    attend.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> No business other than that for which the meeting was convened shall be 
    discussed at a meeting of the Board, except with the consent of the person 
    presiding at the meeting and a majority of the Directors present, unless one 
    clear week’s notice has been given of the same in writing to the Chairman or 
    the Managing Director.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> Quorum for the transaction of business at a meeting of the Board shall 
    be one-third of the total number of persons for the time being constituting 
    the Board (any fraction contained in that one-third being rounded off as 
    one).  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> A resolution in writing circulated to all the Directors at their usual 
    addresses in India and approved and signed by a majority of such Directors 
    who are then in India one of whom shall be the Chairman or the Managing 
    Director, shall be valid and effectual and shall be deemed to be the 
    resolution passed by the Board on the date on which it is concurred and 
    signed by the last signatory to the resolution:  
 


    Provided that if any dissenting Director requires in writing that any 
    resolution so passed shall be placed before a meeting of the Board, the 
    resolution shall not be deemed to be valid and effectual as aforesaid, 
    unless the same is passed at such meeting.  
 </section><section>


    <number>8</number> A copy of the proceedings of each meeting of the Board shall be 
    circulated as soon as possible thereafter for the information of the 
    Directors and shall be signed by the person presiding at that or the next 
    succeeding meeting.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>4</number> Powers of the Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Executive Committee shall have full powers to transact all the usual 
    business of the Development Bank except in such matters as are specifically 
    reserved to the Board under the Act or any regulations made thereunder.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> In the exercise of its powers, the Executive Committee shall be bound by 
    such general or special directions as the Board may give from time to time.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>5</number> Meetings of the Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Meetings of the Executive Committee may be convened from time to time at the 
    head office of the Development Bank, or at such other place in India as may 
    be specified in the notice convening the meetings, so however that at least 
    one meeting shall be convened in each calendar month. Sufficient notice 
    shall be given for such meetings.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Quorum for the transaction of business at a meeting of the Executive 
    Committee shall be one-third of the total strength of the Executive 
    Committee (any fraction contained in that one-third being rounded off as 
    one).  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Save as otherwise provided in this regulation, the provisions of the Act 
    and, of these regulations shall apply to meetings of the Executive Committee 
    as if they were meetings of the Board.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>6</number> No Director or 
      Member to deal with matters with which he is personally 
      concerned.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
      Director of the Board and every Member of the Executive Committee who is 
      in any way whether directly or indirectly, concerned or interested in a 
      contract or arrangement or proposed contract or arrangement entered into 
      or to be entered into, by or on behalf of the Development Bank shall 
      disclose the nature of his concern or interest at a meeting of the Board 
      or the Executive Committee, as the case may be:  
 Provided that it 
      shall not be necessary for a Director or Member to disclose his concern or 
      interest in any such contract or arrangement proposed to be entered into 
      with a company or a foreign company within the meaning of the Companies 
      Act, 1956, where the concern or interest consists only in his holding 
      either singly or together with any other Director or Directors of the 
      Board or any other Member or Members of the Executive Committee, in the 
      aggregate not more than two per cent. of the paid-up share capital in such 
      company.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> (a) In the 
      case of a proposed contract or arrangement, the disclosure required to be 
      made by a Director of the Board or Member of the Executive Committee under 
      sub-regulation (1) shall be made at the meeting of the Board or the 
      Executive Committee, as the case may be, at which the question of entering 
      into contract or arrangement is first taken into consideration, or if the 
      Director or Member, was not, at the date of that meeting concerned or 
      interested in the proposed contract or arrangement, at the first meeting 
      of the Board or the Executive Committee, as the case may be, held after he 
      becomes so concerned or interested.  
 <subsection><number>b</number> In the case 
      of any other contract or arrangement, the required disclosure shall be 
      made at the first meeting of the Board or the Executive Committee, as the 
      case may be, held after the Director or Member becomes concerned or 
      interested in the contract or arrangement.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> (a) For the 
      purpose of sub-regulations (1) and (2) a general notice given by a 
      Director or a Member, to the Board or to the Executive Committee, as the 
      case may be, to the effect that he is a Director or a Member of a 
      specified body corporate or is a Member of a specified firm and is to be 
      regarded as concerned or interested in any contract or arrangement which 
      may after the date of the notice, be entered into with that body corporate 
      or firm, shall be deemed to be a sufficient disclosure of concern or 
      interest in relation to any contract or arrangement so made.  
 <subsection><number>b</number> A Director or 
      a Member giving a general notice to the Board or Executive Committee under 
      clause (a) shall as soon as possible, give notice of any change in the 
      particulars contained therein.  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> No such 
      general notice (no notice of any change therein) be of effect unless 
      either it is given at a meeting of the Board or the Executive Committee, 
      as the case may be, or the Director or Member concerned, takes reasonable 
      steps to secure that it is brought upon and read at the first meeting of 
      the Board or the Executive Committee, as the case may be, after it is 
      given.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> No Director 
      of the Board and no Member of the Executive Committee, shall, as a 
      Director or member, as the case may be, take any part in the discussion 
      of, or vote on any contract or arrangement entered into or to be entered 
      into by or on behalf of the Development Bank, if he is in any way, whether 
      directly or indirectly, concerned or interested in such contract or 
      arrangement, nor shall his presence count for the purpose of forming a 
      quorum at the time of such discussion or vote; and if he does vote, his 
      vote shall be void:  
 Provided that 
      nothing herein contained shall apply to any contract or arrangement 
      entered into or to be entered into with a public company within the 
      meaning of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or a private company 
      within the meaning of that Act, which is a subsidiary of any such public 
      company in which the interest of the Director consists solely—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>    
      in his being—  
 <subsubsection><number>a</number>    
      a Director of such company; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number>    
      the holder of not more than shares of such number of value therein as is 
      requisite to qualify him for appointment as a Director thereof, he having 
      been nominated as such Director by the Development Bank; or  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    
      in his being a Member holding not more than two per cent. of the paid-up 
      share capital of such company.  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>7</number> Ad hoc Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any Committee constituted under sub-section (3) of section 7 of the Act 
    shall, in the exercise of the powers entrusted to it, be bound by such 
    general or special directions as the Board or the Executive Committee may 
    give from time to time.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Meetings of any such Committee may be convened from time to time at the 
    head office of the Development Bank, or at such other place in India as may 
    be specified in the notice convening the meetings. Sufficient notice shall 
    be given for such meetings.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The quorum for the meeting of any such Committee shall be one-third of 
    its strength (any fraction contained in that one-third being rounded off as 
    one).  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> The provisions of regulation 6 shall apply to every Member and to 
    meetings of any such committee in the same manner as that regulation applies 
    to every Member and to meetings of the Executive Committee:  
 


    Provided that if any such Member has given any notice under regulation 6 to 
    the Board or the Executive Committee, it shall not be necessary for him to 
    further disclose his concern or interest in pursuance of this sub-regulation.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Fees and 
      allowances of Directors and Members of the Executive Committee and other 
      Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
      the proviso to section 8 of the Act—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>    
      Every Director shall be entitled to receive a fee of rupees two hundred 
      and fifty only for every meeting of the Board which he 
      attends;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    
      Every Member of the Executive Committee shall be entitled to receive a fee 
      of rupees two hundred and fifty only for every meeting of the Executive 
      Committee which he attends;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    
      Every Member of any Committee constituted under sub-section (3) of section 
      7 of the Act shall, unless he is in receipt of any remuneration, including 
      honorarium other than casual remuneration from the Development Bank be 
      entitled to receive a fee of rupees two hundred and fifty only for each 
      meeting of such Committee, which he attends.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In addition 
      to such fee, Directors and Members shall be reimbursed their travelling 
      expenses on such scales as they are entitled to in the respective 
      institutions in which they hold office and in any other case, on such 
      scales as are applicable to the highest Group ‘A’ Officer of the Central 
      Government.  
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>8</number> Fees and 
      allowances of Directors and Members of the Executive Committee and other 
      Committees.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
      the proviso to section 8 of the Act—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>    
      Every Director shall be entitled to receive a fee of rupees two hundred 
      and fifty only for every meeting of the Board which he 
      attends;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>    
      Every Member of the Executive Committee shall be entitled to receive a fee 
      of rupees two hundred and fifty only for every meeting of the Executive 
      Committee which he attends;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>    
      Every Member of any Committee constituted under sub-section (3) of section 
      7 of the Act shall, unless he is in receipt of any remuneration, including 
      honorarium other than casual remuneration from the Development Bank be 
      entitled to receive a fee of rupees two hundred and fifty only for each 
      meeting of such Committee, which he attends.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> In addition 
      to such fee, Directors and Members shall be reimbursed their travelling 
      expenses on such scales as they are entitled to in the respective 
      institutions in which they hold office and in any other case, on such 
      scales as are applicable to the highest Group ‘A’ Officer of the Central 
      Government.  
  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>9</number> Manner and 
      form in which contracts binding on the Development Bank may be 
      executed.—
<section><number>1</number> Contracts on 
      behalf of the Development Bank shall be made in writing signed by any 
      person acting under its authority, express or implied, and may in the same 
      manner be varied or discharged.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> All contracts 
      made according to the provisions of this regulation shall be valid and 
      binding on the Development Bank.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>10</number> Accounts, 
      receipts and documents of the Development Bank by whom to be 
      signed.—The Managing 
      Director, the whole-time Director, the Executive Directors, the General 
      Managers, the Joint General Managers, the Deputy General Managers, the 
      Secretary and Chief Accountant and such Officers of the Development Bank 
      as the Board may authorise in this behalf by notification in the Official 
      Gazette, to such extent and subject to such limitations, if any, as the 
      Board may specify or impose in so authorising are hereby severally 
      empowered for and on behalf of the Development Bank to endorse and 
      transfer promissory notes, stock-receipts, stocks, debentures, shares, 
      securities and documents of title to goods, standing in the name of or 
      held in the name of or held by the Development Bank, and to draw, accept 
      and endorse bills of exchange and other instruments in the current and 
      authorised business of the Development Bank and to sign all other 
      accounts, receipts and documents connected with such business.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>11</number> Plaints, etc., by whom to be signed.—Plaints, 
    written statements, affidavits and all other documents connected with legal 
    proceedings may be signed and verified on behalf of the Development Bank by 
    any Officer empowered by or under the regulation 10 to sign documents for 
    and on behalf of the Development Bank.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 THE INDUSTRIAL DEVELOPMENT BANK OF INDIA 
    GENERAL REGULATIONS, 1994

  
 <article><title>12</title>. <title>Issue of bonds :- </title>
<section><number>1</number> The bonds or debentures of the Bank shall be issued under the signatures of the chairman or managing director and such signature may be printed, engraved or lithographed or impressed by such other mechanical process as the Board may be direct. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A signature so printed, engraved, lithographed or otherwise impressed shall be as valid as a signature in the proper handwriting of the signatory himself. 

</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>13</number> Common seal.—The 
    Common Seal of the Development Bank shall not be affixed to any instrument 
    except in pursuance of a resolution of the Board or of the Executive 
    Committee, as the case may be, and in the presence of at least three 
    Directors including the Chairman or the Managing Director or the whole-time 
    Director who shall sign their names to the instrument in token of their 
    presence, and such signing shall be independent of the signing of any person 
    who may sign the instrument as a witness. Unless so signed as aforesaid such 
    instrument shall be of no validity. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>14</number> Balance-sheet and profit and loss account.—The 
    Development Bank shall prepare the balance-sheet as at 31st March of every 
    year, and a profit and loss account for the year ending on that date, in the 
    forms specified in Schedule I and Schedule II to these regulations.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>15</number> Share to be movable property.—The 
    shares of the Development Bank shall be movable property.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>16</number> Control over shares and registers.—Subject 
    to the provisions of the Act and these regulations, and such directions as 
    the Board may give from time to time, the register kept at the head office 
    shall be maintained by and be under the control of the Board and the 
    decision of the Board as to whether or not a person is entitled to be 
    registered as a shareholder in respect of any share shall be final. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>17</number> Parties who may not be registered as shareholders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Except as otherwise provided by these regulations, no minor or person who 
    has been found by a court of competent jurisdiction to be of unsound mind 
    shall be entitled to be registered as a shareholder.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> In case of firms, shares shall be registered in the names of the 
    individual partners and no firm, as such, shall be entitled to be registered 
    as a shareholder.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>18</number> Particulars to be entered in the register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In addition to the particulars specified in section 13B of the Act, the 
    following particulars shall be entered in the register, namely:—
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    the manner in which each shareholder acquired his share or shares, 
    and except in the case of allotment of shares to the Central Government, the 
    name of the previous holder and the folio on which the share was last 
    entered;
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    whether the shareholder is the Central Government or belongs to a 
    category of shareholder other than the Central Government; and
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    when any person ceases to be a shareholder, the name of the person in 
    whose favour the share or shares are transferred.
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> A separate ledger shall be maintained in respect of (a) the equity 
    shares held by the Central Government and persons other than the Central 
    Government; and (b) preference shares held by the Central Government.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> In the case of joint holders of any share, their names and other 
    particulars required by sub-regulation (1) shall be grouped under the name 
    of the first of such joint holders.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> A shareholder resident outside India shall furnish to the Development 
    Bank an address in India, and such address shall be entered in the register 
    and be deemed to be his registered address for the purposes of the Act and 
    these regulations.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>19</number> Exercise of rights of joint holders.—If 
    any share stands in the name of two or more persons, the person first named 
    in the register shall, as regards voting, receipt of dividends, service of 
    notices and all or any other matters connected with the Development Bank 
    except the transfer of shares, be deemed to be the sole holder thereof. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>20</number> Inspection of the register.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The register shall, except when closed under regulation 21, be open to 
    inspection of any shareholder, free of charge, at the place where it is 
    maintained during business hours subject to such reasonable restrictions as 
    the Development Bank may impose, so however, that not less than two hours in 
    each working day shall be allowed for inspection.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A shareholder shall not have the right himself to make a copy of any 
    entry in the register, but may, except when the register is closed, require 
    a copy of the register or any part thereof.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-regulation (2), any office of 
    the Central Government authorised in this behalf by it, shall have the right 
    to make a copy of any entry in the register or require a copy of the 
    register or any part thereof.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>21</number> Closing of the register.—The 
    Development Bank may, after giving not less than seven days’ previous notice 
    by advertisement in at least two newspapers circulating in India, close the 
    register of shareholders for any period or periods not exceeding in the 
    aggregate forty-five days in each year, but not exceeding thirty days at any 
    one time.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>22</number> Share certificates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every share certificate shall be issued in such form as may be specified by 
    the Board. Each share certificate shall bear a distinctive number and denote 
    the number of shares in respect of which it is issued. Every share 
    certificate shall bear the name of the shareholder to whom it is issued.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every share certificate shall be signed on behalf of the Development 
    Bank by two persons duly authorised in this behalf by the Board and such 
    signature may be printed, engraved, lithographed or impressed by such other 
    mechanical process as the Board may direct.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> A signature so printed, engraved, lithographed or otherwise impressed 
    shall be as valid as a signature in the proper handwriting of the signatory 
    himself.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>23</number> Issue of share certificates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    While issuing certificates to any shareholder, it shall be competent for the 
    Development Bank to issue the certificates on the basis of one certificate 
    for each fifty shares or multiples thereof registered in his name on any one 
    occasion and one additional share certificate for the number of shares in 
    excess thereof but less than fifty.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If the number of shares to be registered is less than fifty, one 
    certificate shall be issued for all the shares.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> In the case of shares held jointly by several persons, delivery of the 
    relative certificate or certificates to one of such joint-holders shall be 
    sufficient delivery to all and receipt signed by any one of the 
    joint-holders shall effectually bind all the joint-holders.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>24</number> Renewal of share certificates.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If a worn out or defaced share certificate is produced, the Board may order 
    the same to be cancelled, and have a new certificate issued in lieu thereof.  
 


    (2 If any share certificate is alleged to be lost or destroyed, then upon 
    production of such evidence of the loss or destruction thereof as the Board 
    may consider satisfactory and upon such indemnity with or without security 
    as the Board may require, and on payment to the Development Bank of its 
    costs, charges and expenses of and incidental to the matter, a new 
    certificate in lieu thereof shall be given to the person entitled to such 
    lost or destroyed certificate.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>25</number> Transfer of shares.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every transfer of the shares of the Development Bank shall be in writing and 
    in Form A.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The instrument of transfer of any share shall be submitted to the Board 
    and shall be signed by the transferor and the transferee and the transferor 
    shall be deemed to remain the holder of such shares until the name of the 
    transferee is entered in the register.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Upon receipt by the Board of an instrument of transfer with a request to 
    register the transfer, the Board shall, unless it refuses to register the 
    transfer under section 13D of the Act, cause the transfer to be registered.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>26</number> Power to suspend transfers.—The 
    Board may suspend the registration of transfer during any period in which 
    the register is closed.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>27</number> Transmission 
      of shares in the event of death, insolvency, etc., of a 
      shareholder.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
      executors or administrators of a deceased shareholder in respect of a 
      share, or the holder of a succession certificate issued under Part X of 
      the Indian Succession Act, 1925, in respect of such share, or a person in 
      whose favour a valid instrument of transfer of such share was executed by 
      such person and by the deceased shareholder during the latter’s life-time 
      shall be the only person who may be recognised by the Development Bank as 
      having any title to such share.  
 </section><section><number>2</number> In the case 
      of the shares registered in the names of two or more shareholders, the 
      survivor or survivors and on the death of the last survivor, his executors 
      or administrators or any person who is the holder of a succession 
      certificate in respect of such survivor’s interest in the share or a 
      person in whose favour a valid instrument of transfer of the share was 
      executed by such person and such last survivor during the latter’s 
      life-time, shall be the only person who may be recognised by the 
      Development Bank as having any title to such share.  
 </section><section><number>3</number> The 
      Development Bank shall not be bound to recognise such executors or 
      administrators unless they shall have obtained probate or letters of 
      administration or other legal representation, as the case may be, from a 
      court of competent jurisdiction:  
 Provided, 
      however, that in a case where the Board in its discretion thinks fit, it 
      shall be lawful for the Board to dispense with the production of a 
      succession certificate, letters of administration or such other legal 
      representation upon such terms as to indemnity or otherwise as it may 
      think fit.  
 </section><section><number>4</number> Any such 
      person becoming entitled to a share in consequence of death of a 
      shareholder and any person becoming entitled to a share in consequence of 
      the insolvency, bankruptcy or liquidation of a shareholder shall upon 
      production of such evidence, as the Board may require, have the 
      right—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>    
      to be registered as a shareholder in respect of such share; or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>    
      to make such transfer of such share as the person from whom he derives 
      title could have made.  
 
  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>28</number> Calls on shares.—The 
    Board may, from time to time, make such calls as it thinks fit upon the 
    shareholders in respect of all moneys remaining unpaid on the shares held by 
    them, and not by the conditions of allotment thereof made payable at fixed 
    times, and each shareholder shall pay the amount of every call so made on 
    him to the person and at the time and place appointed by the Board. A call 
    may be made payable by instalments.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>29</number> Calls to date from resolution.—A 
    call shall be deemed to have been made at the time when the resolution of 
    the Board authorising such call was passed and may be made payable by the 
    shareholder on the register on such date or at the discretion of the Board 
    on such subsequent date as may be fixed by the Board.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>30</number> Notice of call.—A 
    notice of not less than thirty days of every call shall be given specifying 
    the time of payment provided that before the time for payment of such call 
    the Board may by notice in writing to the shareholders revoke the same. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>31</number> Extension of time for payment of call.—The 
    Board may, from time to time and at its discretion, extend the time fixed 
    for the payment of any call as to all or any of the shareholders having 
    regard to distance of their residence or some other sufficient cause, but no 
    shareholders shall be entitled to such extension as a matter of right. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>32</number> Liabilities of joint-holders.—The 
    joint-holders of a share shall be jointly and severally liable to pay all 
    calls in respect thereof. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>33</number> Amount 
      payable at fixed time or by instalments as calls.—If by the terms 
      of issue of any share or otherwise any amount is payable at any fixed time 
      or by instalments at fixed time, every such amount or instalment shall be 
      payable as if it were a call duly made by the Board and of which due 
      notice had been given and all the provisions herein contained in respect 
      of calls shall relate to such amount or instalment accordingly. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>34</number> When interest on call or instalment payable.—If 
    the sum payable in respect of any call or instalment is not paid on or 
    before the day appointed for payment thereof, the holder for the time being 
    or allottee of the share in respect of which a call shall have been made, or 
    the instalment shall be due, shall pay interest on such sum at such rate as 
    the Board may fix, from time to time, from the day appointed for the payment 
    thereof to the time of actual payment, but the Board may waive payment of 
    such interest wholly or in part.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>35</number> Non-payment of calls by shareholder.—No 
    shareholder shall be entitled to receive any dividend or to exercise any 
    privilege as a shareholder until he shall have paid all calls for the time 
    being due and payable on every share held by him, whether singly or jointly 
    with any person, together with interest and expenses, if any. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>36</number> If call or 
      instalment not paid, notice must be given.—If any 
      shareholder fails to pay the whole or any part of any call or instalment 
      or any money due in respect of any shares either by way of principal or 
      interest on or before the day appointed for the payment of the same, the 
      Board may at any time thereafter during such time as the call or 
      instalment or any part thereof or other moneys remain unpaid or a judgment 
      or decree in respect thereof remains unsatisfied in whole or in part serve 
      a notice on such shareholder or on the person (if any) entitled to the 
      share by transmission, requiring him to pay such call or instalment or 
      such part thereof or other moneys as remains unpaid together with any 
      interest that may have accrued and all expenses (legal or otherwise) that 
      may have been paid or incurred by the Development Bank by reason of such 
      non-payment.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>37</number> Form of notice.—The 
    notice shall name a day not being less than fourteen days from the date of 
    the notice and the place or places on and at which such call or instalment 
    or such part or other moneys and such interest and expenses as aforesaid are 
    to be paid. The notice shall also state that in the event of non-payment on 
    or before the time and at the place appointed, the share in respect of which 
    the call was made or instalment is payable will be liable to be forfeited. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>38</number> In default of payment shares to be forfeited.—If 
    the requirements of any such notice as aforesaid are not complied with, any 
    of the shares in respect of which such notice has been given may, at any 
    time thereafter before payment of all calls or instalments, interest and 
    expenses or the money due in respect thereof, be forfeited by a resolution 
    of the Board to that effect. Such forfeiture shall include all dividends 
    declared in respect of the forfeited shares and not actually paid before the 
    forfeiture. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>39</number> Entry of forfeiture in the register.—When 
    any share has been forfeited under regulation 38, an entry of the forfeiture 
    with the date thereof shall be made in the register. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>40</number> Forfeited 
      shares to be property of the Development Bank and may be 
      sold.—Any share so 
      forfeited shall be deemed to be the property of the Development Bank and 
      may be sold, re-allotted or otherwise disposed of, either to the original 
      holder thereof or to any other person upon such terms and in such manner 
      as the Board may decide.
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>41</number> Power to annul forfeiture.—The 
    Board may, at any time, before any share so forfeited under regulation 38 
    shall have been sold, re-allotted or otherwise disposed of, annul the 
    forfeiture thereof upon such conditions as it may think fit. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><number>42</number> Shareholder 
      liable to pay money owing at the time of forfeiture and 
      interest.—Any shareholder 
      whose shares have been forfeited shall, notwithstanding the forfeiture, be 
      liable to pay and shall forthwith pay to the Development Bank all calls, 
      instalments, interest, expenses and other moneys owing upon or in respect 
      of such shares at the time of the forfeiture with interest thereon from 
      the time of forfeiture until payment at such rate as may be specified by 
      the Board and the Board may enforce the payment of the whole or a portion 
      thereof. 
  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>43</number> Partial payment not to preclude forfeiture.—Neither 
    a judgment nor a decree in favour of the Development Bank for calls or other 
    moneys due in respect of any shares nor any payment or satisfaction 
    thereunder nor the receipt by the Development Bank of a portion of any money 
    which shall be due from any shareholder from time to time in respect of any 
    shares either by way of principal or interest nor any indulgence granted by 
    the Development Bank in respect of payment of any money shall preclude the 
    forfeiture of such shares under these regulations. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>44</number> Application of forfeiture provisions.—The 
    provisions of these regulations as to the forfeiture shall apply in the case 
    of non-payment of any sum which by terms of issue of a share become payable 
    at a fixed time, as if the same had been payable by virtue of a call duly 
    made.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>45</number> Development Bank’s lien on shares.—The 
    Development Bank, in the case of partly paid-up shares, shall have a first 
    and paramount lien for all moneys called or payable at a fixed time in 
    respect of such shares. Any such lien shall extend to all dividends from 
    time to time declared in respect of such shares. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>46</number> Enforcing lien by sale of shares.—The 
    Board may, for the purpose of enforcing lien referred to in regulation 45 
    sell the shares subject thereto in such manner as it thinks fit, but no sale 
    shall be made unless any sum in respect of which the lien exists is 
    presently payable nor until notice in writing of the intention to sell shall 
    have been served on such shareholder or person, if any, entitled for 
    transmission to the shares and default shall have been made by him in 
    payment of the sum presently payable for seven days after such notice. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>47</number> Application of proceeds of sale of shares.—The 
    net proceeds of any sale of shares under regulation 46 after deduction of 
    costs of such sale, shall be applied in or towards the satisfaction of the 
    debt or liability in respect whereof the lien exists so far as the same is 
    presently payable and the residue, if any, paid to the shareholders or the 
    person, if any, entitled by transmission to the shares so sold.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>48</number> Certificate of forfeiture.—A 
    certificate in writing under the hand of any Director, or any other Officer 
    of the Development Bank duly authorised in this behalf, that the call in 
    respect of a share was made and that the forfeiture of the share was made by 
    a resolution of the Board to that effect, shall be conclusive evidence of 
    the fact stated therein as against all persons entitled to such shares. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>49</number> Title of purchaser and allottee of forfeited shares.—The 
    Development Bank may receive the consideration, if any, given for the share 
    on any sale, re-allotment or other disposition thereof and the person to 
    whom such share is sold, re-allotted or disposed of may be registered as the 
    holder of the share and shall not be bound to see to the application of the 
    consideration, if any, nor shall his title to the share be affected by any 
    irregularity or invalidity in the proceedings in reference to the 
    forfeiture, sale, re-allotment or other disposal of the share and the remedy 
    of any person aggrieved by the sale shall be in damages only and against the 
    Development Bank exclusively. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>50</number> Service of a notice or document to shareholders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development bank may serve a service or a document on any shareholder 
    either personally, or by post at his registered address or if he has no 
    registered address in India, at the address, if any, within India supplied 
    by him to the Development Bank for the giving of notice to him. 
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Where a document or a notice is sent by post, the service of such 
    document or notice shall be deemed to be effected by properly addressing, 
    prepaying and posting a letter containing the document or notice:  
 


    Provided that where a shareholder has intimated to the Development Bank in 
    advance that documents should be sent to him under a certificate of posting 
    or by registered post, with or without acknowledgement due, and has 
    deposited with the Development Bank a sum sufficient to defray the expenses 
    of doing so, service of the document or notice shall not be deemed to be 
    effected unless it is sent in the manner intimated by the shareholder, and 
    unless the contrary is proved, such service shall be deemed to have been 
    effected in the case of a notice of a meeting at the expiration of 
    forty-eight hours after the letter containing the same is posted, and in any 
    other case, at the time at which the letter would have been delivered in the 
    ordinary course of post.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> A notice or a document advertised in a newspaper widely circulated in 
    India shall be deemed to be duly served on the day on which the 
    advertisement appears, on every shareholder of the Development Bank who has 
    no registered address in India and has not supplied to the Development Bank 
    an address within India for giving of notices to him.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> A notice or document may be served by the Development Bank on the 
    joint-holder of a share by serving it on the joint-holder named first in the 
    register in respect of the share.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> A notice or a document may be served by the Development Bank on the 
    persons entitled to a share upon death or in consequence of the insolvency 
    of a shareholder by sending it through post in a prepaid letter addressed to 
    them by name, or by the title of representatives of the deceased, or 
    assignees of the insolvent, or by any like description, at the address, if 
    any, in India supplied for the purpose by the persons claiming to be so 
    entitled, or until such an address has been so supplied, by serving the 
    document in any manner in which it might have been served if the death or 
    insolvency had not occurred.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>51</number> Notice convening a general meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A notice convening a general meeting of the shareholders signed by the 
    Chairman or the Managing Director or the whole-time Director of the 
    Development Bank shall be published at least twenty-one clear days before 
    the meeting in not less than two daily newspapers having wide circulation in 
    India. 
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Every such notice shall state the time, date and place of such meeting, 
    and also the business that shall be transacted at that meeting.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>52</number> Extraordinary general meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairman or in his absence the Managing Director or in his absence the 
    whole-time Director of the Development Bank shall convene an extraordinary 
    general meeting of shareholders if so directed by the Board, or if a 
    requisition for such a meeting has been received either from the Central 
    Government or from other shareholders holding shares, carrying in the 
    aggregate not less than twenty per cent. of the total voting rights of all 
    the shareholders.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The regulation referred to in sub-regulation (1) shall state the purpose 
    for which the extraordinary general meeting is required to be convened, but 
    may consist of several documents in like form each signed by one or more of 
    the requisitionists.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Where two or more persons hold any shares jointly, a requisition or a 
    notice calling a meeting, signed by one or some of them shall, for the 
    purposes of this regulation have the same force and effect as if it had been 
    signed by all of them.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> The time, date and place of the extraordinary general meeting shall be 
    decided by the Board:  
 


    Provided that the extraordinary general meeting convened on the requisition 
    by the Central Government or other shareholders shall be convened not later 
    than three months of the receipt of the requisition.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> If the Chairman or the Managing Director or the whole-time Director, as 
    the case may be, does not convene a meeting as required by sub-regulation 
    (1), within the period stipulated in the proviso to sub-regulation (4), the 
    meeting may be called by the requisitionists themselves within the next 
    three months:  
 


    Provided that nothing in this sub-regulation shall be deemed to prevent a 
    meeting duly commenced before the expiry of the period of three months 
    aforesaid, from adjourning to some day after the expiry of that period.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> A meeting called under sub-regulation (5) by the requisitionists shall 
    be called in the same manner, as nearly as possible, as that in which the 
    other general meetings are called.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> Any reasonable expenses incurred by the requisitionists in calling a 
    meeting under sub-regulation (5) shall be reimbursed to the requisitionists 
    by the Development Bank.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>53</number> Business at general meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No business other than that specified in section 13H of the Act shall be 
    transacted at the annual general meeting except with the consent of the 
    Chairman of the meeting.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Except with the consent of the Chairman of the meeting, no business 
    shall be transacted or discussed at any extraordinary general meeting, 
    except the business for which the meeting has been convened.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>54</number> Quorum of general meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No business shall be transacted at any meeting of the shareholders whether 
    it is the annual general meeting or an extraordinary general meeting unless 
    a quorum of at least five shareholders consisting a duly authorised 
    representative of the Central Government and four other shareholders 
    entitled to vote at such meeting in person or by proxy or by duly authorised 
    representatives are present at the commencement of such business.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> If within half an hour after the time appointed for the holding of a 
    meeting, a quorum be not present, in the case of a meeting called by the 
    requisition of shareholders other than the Central Government, the meeting 
    shall stand dissolved.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> In any other case, the meeting shall stand adjourned to the same day in 
    the next week, at the same time and place or to such other day and such 
    other time and place as the Chairman of the meeting may determine. If at the 
    adjourned meeting a quorum is not present within half an hour from the time 
    appointed for holding the meeting, the shareholders who are present in 
    person or by proxy or by duly authorised representative at such adjourned 
    meeting shall be quorum and may transact the business for which the meeting 
    was called:  
 


    Provided that no annual general meeting shall be adjourned to a date later 
    than the date within which such annual general meeting shall be held in 
    terms of section 13F of the Act and if adjournment of the meeting to the 
    same day in the following week would have this effect, the annual general 
    meeting shall not be adjourned but the business of the meeting shall be 
    commenced within one hour from the time appointed for the meeting if the 
    quorum is present or immediately after the expiry of one hour from that time 
    and those shareholders who are present in person or by proxy or by duly 
    authorised representative at such time shall form the quorum.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>55</number> Chairman at general meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairman or in his absence, the Managing Director or in this absence, 
    the whole-time Director or in his absence, such one of the Directors as may 
    be generally or in relation to a particular meeting be authorised by the 
    Chairman in this behalf shall be the Chairman of the meeting and if the 
    Chairman or the Managing Director or the whole-time Director or any other 
    Director authorised in this behalf is not present, the meeting may elect any 
    other Director present to be the Chairman of the meeting.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The Chairman of the general meeting shall regulate the procedure at all 
    general meetings and in particular shall have power to decide the order in 
    which shareholders may address the meeting, to fix a time-limit for 
    speeches, to apply the closure, when in his opinion, any matter has been 
    sufficiently discussed, and to adjourn the meeting.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>56</number> Persons entitled to attend general meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    All Directors and all shareholders of the Development Bank shall, subject to 
    the provisions of sub-regulation (2) be entitled to attend a general 
    meeting.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A shareholder (not being the Central Government) or a Director, 
    attending a general meeting shall for the purpose of identification and to 
    determine his voting rights, be required to sign and deliver to the 
    Development Bank a form containing the particulars relating to—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    his full name and numbers of his shares;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    the distinctive numbers of his shares;  
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    whether he is entitled to vote and the number of votes to which he is 
    entitled in person or by proxy or as a duly authorised representative.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>57</number> Voting at general meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    At any general meeting, a resolution put to the vote of the meeting shall, 
    unless a poll is demanded, be decided on a show of hands.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Save as otherwise provided in the Act, every matter submitted to a 
    general meeting shall be decided by a majority of votes.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Unless a poll is demanded under sub-regulation (1), a declaration by the 
    Chairman of the meeting that a resolution on show of hands has or has not 
    been carried, either unanimously or by a particular majority, and an entry 
    to that effect in the books containing the minutes of the proceedings, shall 
    be a conclusive evidence of the fact, without proof of the number or 
    proportion of the votes cast in favour of or against such resolution. 
 
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> Before or on the declaration of the result of the voting on any 
    resolution on a show of hands a poll may be ordered to be taken by the 
    Chairman of the meeting of his own motion, and shall be ordered to taken by 
    him on a demand made in that behalf by any shareholder be shareholders 
    present in person or by proxy and holding shares in the Development Bank 
    which confer a power to vote on the resolution not being less than one-fifth 
    of the total voting power in respect of the resolution.  
 </section><section>


    <number>5</number> The demand for a poll may be withdrawn at any time by the person or 
    persons who made the demand.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> A poll demanded on a question of adjournment or election of Chairman of 
    the meeting shall be taken forthwith.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> A poll demanded on any other question shall be taken at such time not 
    being later than forty-eight hours from the time when the demand was made, 
    as the Chairman of the meeting may direct.  
 </section><section>


    <number>8</number> The decision of the Chairman of the meeting as to the qualification of 
    any person to vote, and also in the case of poll, as to the number of votes 
    any person is competent to exercise shall be final.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>58</number> Minutes of general meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Development Bank shall cause the minutes of all proceedings to be 
    maintained in the books kept for the purpose which may be in the form of 
    binders containing loose leaves.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> Any such minutes, if purporting to be signed by the Chairman of the 
    meeting at which the proceedings were held, or by the Chairman of the next 
    succeeding meeting, shall be evidence of the proceedings concluded thereat.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> Until the contrary is proved every general meeting in respect of the 
    proceedings whereof minutes have been so made shall be deemed to have been 
    duly called and held, and all proceedings held thereat to have been duly 
    held.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>59</number> Determination of voting rights.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions contained in section 13G of the Act—  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    upon a show of hands, every shareholder entitled to vote and present 
    in person or by attorney or proxy shall have one vote; and   
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    upon a poll, every shareholder, who being an individual is present in 
    person or by attorney or by proxy or being the Central Government or a body 
    corporate, is present through a representative, shall have a voting right in 
    proportion to his or its share of the paid-up equity capital of the 
    Development Bank.  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> Shareholder of the Development Bank entitled to attend and vote at a 
    general meeting shall be entitled to appoint another person (whether a 
    shareholder or not) as his proxy to attend and vote instead of himself; but 
    a proxy so appointed shall not have any right to speak at the meeting.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> A person appointed as proxy shall be entitled to vote only upon a poll.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>60</number> Voting by duly authorised representative.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A shareholder being the Central Government or a body corporate may authorise 
    any of its officials or any other person to act as its representative at any 
    general meeting of the shareholders and the person so authorised (referred 
    to as a “duly authorised representative” in these regulations) shall be 
    entitled to exercise the same rights including the right to vote by proxy 
    and powers on behalf of the Central Government or such body corporate as if 
    he were an individual shareholder of the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> No person shall attend or vote at any meeting of shareholders of the 
    Development Bank as the duly authorised representative of a body corporate 
    unless a copy of the resolution appointing him as a duly authorised 
    representative certified to be a true copy by the Chairman of the meeting at 
    which it was passed shall have been deposited at the head office of the 
    Development Bank not less than four clear days before the date fixed for the 
    meeting.  
 


    Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this regulation, a body corporate shall also include a 
    society registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), 
    or any other law for the time being in force providing for registration of 
    societies.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>61</number> Proxies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No instrument of proxy shall be valid unless in the case of an individual 
    shareholder, it is signed by him or by his attorney duly authorised in 
    writing, or in the case of joint-holders, it is signed by the shareholder 
    first named in the register or his attorney duly authorised in writing or in 
    the case of the body corporate it is executed under its common seal, if any, 
    or signed by its attorney duly authorised in writing:  
 


    Provided that an instrument of proxy shall be sufficiently signed by any 
    shareholder, who for any reason is unable to write his name, if his 
    thumb-impression is affixed thereto and attested by a Judge, Magistrate, 
    Registrar or Sub-Registrar of Assurances or other Government Gazetted 
    Officer or an Officer of a Nationalised Bank or the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> No proxy shall be valid unless it is duly stamped and a copy thereof 
    deposited at the head office of the Development Bank not less than four 
    clear days before the date fixed for the meeting, together with the power of 
    attorney or other authority (if any) under which it is signed or a copy of 
    that power or authority certified by a Notary Public or a Magistrate unless 
    such a power of attorney or the other authority is previously deposited and 
    registered with the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> No instrument of proxy shall be valid unless it is in Form B.  
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> An instrument of proxy deposited with the Development Bank shall be 
    irrevocable unless:  
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    on or before the last date of deposit of proxy, there shall have been 
    deposited at the head office of the Development Bank a notice in writing 
    under the hand or common seal of the grantor specifically stating—  
 <subsubsection>


    <number>i</number>    the name of the person in whose favour the instrument was granted; 
    and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>


    <number>ii</number>    that such instrument is revoked; and   
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    the same is deemed to be invalid under sub-regulation (6).  
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>5</number> In the case of an instrument or proxy granted in favour of two grantees 
    in the alternative, it shall not be necessary to mention in the notice of 
    revocation the name of the second or alternative grantee provided that the 
    notice is otherwise sufficient to identify beyond doubt the instrument of 
    proxy which it is intended to revoke.  
 </section><section>


    <number>6</number> If two or more instruments of proxy in respect of the same shares are 
    deposited and if on or before the last day for deposit of proxies all but 
    one of such instruments of proxy has not been duly revoked in accordance 
    with the procedure laid down in sub-regulation (4) all such instruments of 
    proxy shall be deemed to be invalid.  
 </section><section>


    <number>7</number> The due revocation of an instrument of proxy shall in no way prohibit 
    the deposit of another valid instrument of proxy within the time specified 
    in sub-regulation (2).  
 </section><section>


    <number>8</number> The grantor of an instrument of proxy which has become irrevocable under 
    this regulation shall not be entitled to vote in person at the meeting to 
    which such instrument relates.  
 </section><section>


    <number>9</number> No person shall be appointed as duly authorised representative or a 
    proxy who is an Officer or an Employee of the Development Bank.  
 </section><section>


    <number>10</number> Nothing contained in this regulation shall apply to the Central 
    Government and the Central Government may appoint such person as it thinks 
    fit to act as its representative at any general meeting of the Development 
    Bank. A person so appointed shall for the purpose of the meeting be deemed 
    to be the shareholder of the Development Bank and shall exercise the same 
    rights and powers as the Central Government shall be entitled to exercise at 
    the meeting.  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>62</number> Directors to be elected at general meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A Director to be elected under clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 6 of 
    the Act shall be elected by the shareholders in the annual general meting of 
    the Development Bank.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> The number of Directors to be elected and the particular vacancies in 
    respect of which the election is to be held shall be specified in the notice 
    convening the annual general meeting.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>63</number> Nomination of candidates for election.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No candidate for election as a Director shall be validly nominated unless—
 <subsection>


    <number>a</number>    he is on the last date for receipt of nomination, not disqualified to 
    be a Director under sub-section (1) of section 6B of the Act;
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>b</number>    the nomination is in writing signed by at least two shareholders 
    entitled to elect Directors under clause (e) of sub-section (1) of section 6 
    of the Act or by their duly constituted attorney, provided that a nomination 
    by a shareholder who is a body corporate may be made by a resolution of the 
    Directors of the said body corporate and where it is so made, a copy of the 
    resolution certified to be a true copy by the Chairman of the meeting at 
    which it was passed shall be dispatched to the head office of the 
    Development Bank and such copy shall be deemed to be a nomination on behalf 
    of such body corporate;
 </subsection><subsection>


    <number>c</number>    the nomination shall accompany or contain a declaration signed by the 
    candidate before a Judge, Magistrate, Registrar or Sub-Registrar of 
    Assurances or other Gazetted Officer or an Officer of a Nationalised Bank or 
    Development Bank, that he accepts the nomination and is willing to stand for 
    election, and that he is not disqualified for election under section 6B of 
    the Act.
 </subsection></section><section>


    <number>2</number> No nomination shall be valid unless it is complete in all respects and 
    received in the head office of the Development Bank on a working day not 
    less than fourteen clear days before the date fixed for the meeting.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>64</number> Scrutiny of nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Nominations shall be scrutinised on the first working day following the date 
    fixed for receipt of the nominations and in case any nomination is not found 
    to be valid, the same shall be rejected after recording the reason therefor, 
    if there is only one valid nomination for any particular vacancy to be 
    filled by election, the candidate so nominated shall be deemed to be elected 
    forthwith and his name and address shall be published as so elected. In such 
    an event there shall not be any election at the meeting convened for the 
    purpose and if the meeting had been called solely for the purpose of the 
    aforesaid election, it shall stand cancelled.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> A Director elected to fill an existing vacancy shall be deemed to have 
    assumed office from the date following that on which he is, or is deemed to 
    be elected.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>65</number> Election disputes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any doubt or dispute shall arise as to the qualification or 
    disqualification of a person deemed, or declared to be elected, or as to the 
    validity of the election of a Director, any person interested, being a 
    candidate or shareholder entitled to vote at such election, may, within 
    seven days of the date of the declaration of the result of such election, 
    give intimation in writing thereof to the Chairman of the Development Bank 
    and shall in the said intimation give full particulars of the grounds upon 
    which he doubts or disputes the validity of the election.
 </section><section>


    <number>2</number> On receipt of an intimation under sub-regulation (1), the Chairman of 
    the Development Bank shall forthwith refer such doubt or dispute for the 
    decision of a Committee consisting of himself and any two of Directors 
    nominated under clauses (c) and (d) of sub-section (1) of section 6 of the 
    Act.  
 </section><section>


    <number>3</number> The Committee referred to in sub-regulation (2) shall make such enquiry 
    as it deems necessary and if it finds that the election was a valid 
    election, it shall confirm the declared result of the election, or, if it 
    finds that the election was not a valid election, it shall, within 30 days 
    of the commencement of the enquiry, make such order and give such directions 
    including the holding of a fresh election as shall in the circumstances 
    appear just to the Committee.
 </section><section>


    <number>4</number> An order and direction of such Committee in pursuance of this regulation 
    shall be conclusive.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>


    <number>66</number> Removal of Director.—A 
    Director sought to be removed under sub-section (4B) of section 6 of the 
    Act, shall be given an opportunity to make representation, in writing 
    against such removal to the Development Bank (not exceeding a reasonable 
    length) and such representation, if the Director so requests, shall be 
    circulated among the shareholders other than the Central Government or 
    alternatively, if the Director so requests, be published in any newspaper 
    circulated in India and if such circulation or publication of representation 
    is not possible for want of time, the same shall be read out at the meeting.
 


 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>