<act><tid>476269</tid>
<title>THE DELHI LAWS ACT, <year>1912</year></title>

ACT NO. 13 OF <year>1912</year>
[ 18th September, <year>1912</year>.]

An Act to provide for the application of the law in force in the 
Province of Delhi and for the extension of the enactments thereto.

WHEREAS by Proclamation <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> published in Notification No. 911, 
dated the seventeenth day of September, <year>1912</year>, the Governor- General in 
Council, with the sanction and approbation of the Secretary of State 
for India, has been pleased to take under his immediate authority and 
management the territory mentioned in Schedule A, which was formerly 
included within the Province of the Punjab, and to provide for the 
administration thereof by a Chief Commissioner as a separate Province 
to be known as the Province of Delhi;

AND WHEREAS it is expedient to provide for the application of the 
law in force in the said territory, and for the extension of other 
enactments thereto; It is hereby enacted as follows:--





<article><tid>1003447</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and commencement.
<section><tid>1628972</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Delhi Laws Act, <year>1912</year>; and

</section>

<section><tid>638967</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall come into force on the first day of October, <year>1912</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>789287</tid>
<number>2</number>Saving of territorial application of enactments. The 
Proclamation referred to in the preamble shall not be deemed to have 
effected any change in the territorial application of any enactment 
notwithstanding that such enactment may be expressed to apply or 
extend to the territories for the time being under any particular 
administration.


</article>



<article><tid>1532014</tid>
<number>3</number>Construction of certain enactments in force in the territories 
mentioned in Schedule A. All enactments made by any authority in 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> India] and all notifications, orders, schemes, rules, forms and by- 
laws issued, made or prescribed under such enactments which 
immediately before the commencement of this Act were in force in, or 
prescribed for, any of the territory mentioned in Schedule A, shall in 
their application to that territory be construed as if references 
therein to the authorities, or gazette mentioned in cloumn I of 
Schedule B were references to the authorities, or gazette respectively 
mentioned or referred to opposite there to in column 2 of that 
Schedule.
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>235968</tid>
<number> 4</number> Powers of Courts and State Government for purposes of 
facilitating application of enactments. For the purpose of 
facilitating the application to the territory mentioned in Schedule A 
or any part thereof of any enactment passed
<pagefootnote><pagenum>92</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>See Gazette of India, <year>1912</year>, Extraordinary, p. 17. 
2. Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" the Provinces". 
3. Proviso to s. 3 rep. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


before the commencement of this Act or of any notification, order, 
scheme, rule, form or by- law issued, made or prescribed under any such 
enactment--

<section><tid>280929</tid>
<number>1</number>any Court may, subject to the other provisions of this 
Act, construe the enactment, notification, order, 
scheme, rule, form or by- law with such alterations not 
affecting the substance as may be necessary or proper 
to adapt it to the matter before the Court, and

</section>

<section><tid>538702</tid>
<number>2</number>the State Government may, subject to the other 
provisions of this Act, by notification in the Official 
Gazette direct by what officer any power or duty shall 
be exercised or discharged, and any such notification 
shall have effect as if enacted in this Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>710884</tid>
<number> 5</number> Vesting of powers of separate officers in single officer.
<section><tid>1227795</tid>
<number>1</number> 
A notification issued under section 4, sub- section (2), may direct 
that any powers or duties vested in separate officers may be 
consolidated and vested in, and discharge by, a single officer.

</section>

<section><tid>912448</tid>
<number>2</number>Where by such a notification appellate powers are 
consolidated and vested in a single officer, the period of limitation 
for the consolidated appeal shall be the longest period provided in 
the case of an appeal to any of the officers whose powers are so 
consolidated.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1378012</tid>
<number>6</number>Pending proceedings. Nothing in this Act shall affect any 
proceeding which at the commencement thereof is pending in respect of 
any of the territory mentioned in Schedule A, and every such 
proceeding shall be continued as if this Act had not been passed:
Provided that all proceedings which at the commencement of this 
Act are pending before the Commissioner of the Division or any other 
authority within the territory mentioned in Schedule A shall be 
transferred to, and disposed of by, such authorities in the State of 
Delhi as the State Government may, by notification in the Official 
Gazette, direct.



</article>



<article><tid>230117</tid>
<number>7</number>[ Power to extend enactments in force in other Provinces with 
modifications and restrictions.] Rep. by the Part C States (Laws) Act, 
 <year>1950</year> (30 of <year>1950</year>), s. 4.

</article>



 </act>