<act><title>


The Employers’ 
    Liability Act, 1938</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title and extent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Employers’ Liability Act, 1938. —(1) 
    This Act may be called the Employers’ Liability Act, 1938." 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India 

    1[***].
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,— —In 
    this Act, unless there is anything repugnant in the subject or context,—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “workman” means any person who has 
    entered into, or works under a contract of, service or apprenticeship with 
    an employer whether by way of manual labour, clerical work or otherwise, and 
    whether the contract is expressed or implied, oral or in writing; and
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “employer” includes any body of persons 
    whether incorporated or not, any managing agent of an employer, and the 
    legal representatives of a deceased employer, and, where the services of a 
    workman are temporarily lent or let on hire to another person by the person 
    with whom the workman has entered into a contract of service or 
    apprenticeship, means such other person while the workman is working for 
    him.

 
    


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Defence of common employment barred in certain cases.—Where 
    personal injury is caused to a workman— —Where 
    personal injury is caused to a workman—" 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   by reason of the omission of the 
    employer to maintain in good and safe condition any way, works, machinery or 
    plant connected with or used in his trade or business, or by reason of any 
    like omission on the part of any person in the service of the employer who 
    has been entrusted by the employer with the duty of seeing that such way, 
    works, machinery or plant are in good and safe condition; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   by reason of the negligence of any 
    person in the service of the employer who has any superintendence entrusted 
    to him, whilst in the exercise of such superintendence; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   by reason of the negligence of any 
    person in the service of the employer to whose orders or directions the 
    workman at the time of the injury was bound to conform and did conform, 
    where the injury resulted from his having so conformed; or
 </section><section>
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>d</number>   by reason of the act or 
    omission of any person in the service of the employer done or made—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   in the normal performance of the duties 
    of that person; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   in obedience to any rule or bye-law of 
    the employer (not being a rule or bye-law which is required by or under any 
    law for the time being in force to be approved) by any authority and which 
    has been so approved; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   in obedience to particular 
    instructions given by any other person to whom the employer has delegated 
    authority in that behalf;]
 
a suit for damages in respect of the injury 
    instituted by the workman or by any person entitled in case of his death 
    shall not fail by reason only of the fact that the workman was at the time 
    of the injury a workman of, or in the service of, or engaged in the work of, 
    the employer.
  
  





 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> Contracting out.—Any 
      provision contained in a contract of service or  apprenticeship, or 
      in an agreement collateral thereto, shall be void in-so-far as it would 
      have the effect of excluding or limiting any liability of the employer in 
      respect of personal injuries caused to the person employed or apprenticed 
      by the negligence of persons in common employment with 
      him.] 
  
  




 
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Risk not to be deemed to have been assumed without full knowledge.—In 
    any such suit for damages, the workman shall not be deemed to have 
    undertaken any risk attaching to the employment unless the employer proves 
    that the risk was fully explained to and understood by the workman and the 
    workman voluntarily undertook the same. —In 
    any such suit for damages, the workman shall not be deemed to have 
    undertaken any risk attaching to the employment unless the employer proves 
    that the risk was fully explained to and understood by the workman and the 
    workman voluntarily undertook the same." 

 
    


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 

 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Saving.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall affect the validity of any decree or order of a Civil 
    Court passed before the commencement of this Act in any such suit for 
    damages. —Nothing 
    in this Act shall affect the validity of any decree or order of a Civil 
    Court passed before the commencement of this Act in any such suit for 
    damages." 
  
 
    


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> 
 
Subs. by Act 5 of 1951, sec. 2, 
    for clause (d) (w.e.f. 28-2-1951).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> 
 Ins. by Act 5 of 1951, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
      28-2-1951).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>