<act><title>


the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights 
and full participation) Rules, 19961</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, 
Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Rules, 1996.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
 THE PERSONS WITH DISABILITIES (EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES, PROTECTION OF RIGHTS AND FULL PARTICIPATION) RULES, 1996
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “Act” means the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “certificate” or “disability certificate” means a certificate issued in pursuance of clause (t) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “multiple disabilities” means a combination of two or more disabilities as defined in clause (i) of section 2 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “Form” means a form appended to these rules. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Words and expressions defined in the Act but not defined in these rules, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.] 




 
 <subsection><number>a</number> “Act” means the Persons with Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, 1995 (1 of 1996); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> “Chairperson” means a Chairperson appointed under the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> “Vice-Chairperson” means a Vice-Chairperson appointed under the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> “Member” means a Member appointed under the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> “Member-Secretary” means a Member-Secretary appointed under the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> “Special Employment Exchange” means Special Employment Exchange, Special cell in normal Employment Exchange and such Employment Exchanges which are notified Special Employment Ex­changes by notification in the Official Gazette; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> “Year” means the financial year commencing on the first day of April.'. 
</subsection>

</section></article> 
 
 THE PERSONS WITH DISABILITIES (EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES, PROTECTION OF RIGHTS AND FULL PARTICIPATION) RULES, 1996
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>3</number> Application for issue of disability certificate. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> A person with disability desirous of getting a certificate in his favour shall submit an application in  
  Form I, and the application shall be accompanied by— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> proof of residence, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> two recent passport size photographs. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application shall be submitted to— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> a medical authority competent to issue such a certificate in the district of the applicant's residence as mentioned in the proof of residence submitted by him with the application, or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the concerned medical authority in a government hospital where he may be undergoing or may have undergone treatment in connection with his disability: 
</subsection>
 Provided that where a person with disability is a minor or suffering from mental retardation or any other disability which renders him unfit or unable to make such an application himself, the application on his behalf may be made by his legal guardian. ] 








</section></article> 
 
 THE PERSONS WITH DISABILITIES (EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES, PROTECTION OF RIGHTS AND FULL PARTICIPATION) RULES, 1996
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>4</number> Issue of disability certificate. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> On receipt of an application under 
  rule 3, the medical authority shall, after satisfying himself that the applicant is a person with disability as defined in sub-clause (t) of section 2 of the Act, issue a disability certificate in his favour in Form II, Form III or Form IV as applicable. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The certificate shall be issued as far as possible, within a week from the date of receipt of the application by the medical authority, but in any case, not later than one month from such date. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The medical authority shall, after due examination,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> give a permanent disability certificate in cases where there are no chances of variation, over time, in the degree of disability, and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> shall indicate the period of validity in the certificate, in cases where there is any chance of variation, over time, in the degree of disability. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> If an applicant is found ineligible for issue of disability certificate, the medical authority shall explain to him the reasons for rejection of his application, and shall also convey the reasons to him in writing. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> A copy of every disability certificate issued under these rules by a medical authority other than the Chief Medical Officer shall be simultaneously sent by such medical authority to the Chief Medical Officer of the District.] 







 
 


</section><section><number>2</number> The State Government may constitute a Medical Board consisting of at least three members out of which at least one shall be a specialist in the particular field for assessing locomotor/Visual including low vision/hearing and speech disability, mental retardation and leprosy cured, as the case may be. 
</section></article> 
 
 THE PERSONS WITH DISABILITIES (EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES, PROTECTION OF RIGHTS AND FULL PARTICIPATION) RULES, 1996
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>5</number> Review of a decision regarding issue of, or refusal to issue, a disability certificate </title>.—
<section><number>1</number> Any applicant for a disability certificate, who is aggrieved by the nature of a certificate issued to him, or by refusal to issue such a certificate in his favour, as the case may be, may represent against such a decision to the medical authority as specified for the purpose by the appropriate Government: 
 Provided that where a person with disability is a minor or suffering from mental retardation or any other disability which renders him unfit or unable to make such an application himself, the application on his behalf may be made by his legal guardian. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application for review shall be accompanied by a copy of the certificate or letter of rejection being appealed against. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> On receipt of an application for review, the medical authority shall, after giving the appellant an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders on it as it may deem appropriate. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> An application for review shall, as far as possible, be disposed of within a fortnight from the date of its receipt, but in any case, not later than one month from such date.] 






 
 


</section><section><number>2</number> The Medical Board shall indicate the period of validity in the certificate, in cases where there is any chance of variation in the degree of disability. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> No refusal of Disability Certificate shall be made unless an opportunity is given to the applicant of being heard. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> On representation by the applicant, the Medical Board may review its decision having regard to all the facts and circumstances of the case and pass such order in the matter as it thinks fit. 
</section></article> 
 
 THE PERSONS WITH DISABILITIES (EQUAL OPPORTUNITIES, PROTECTION OF RIGHTS AND FULL PARTICIPATION) RULES, 1996
  
 <article><title><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[</title> <title><number>6</number> Certificate issued under rule 4 to be generally valid for all purposes. </title>—A certificate issued under rule 4 shall render a person eligible to apply for facilities, concessions and benefits admissible under schemes of the Government and of Non-Governmental Organizations funded by the Government, subject to such conditions as may be specified in relevant schemes or instructions of Government, etc., as the case may be. <title>]</title>








</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Nomination of State 
Government representatives by rotation.—The 
Central Government shall nominate four members—three from the State and one from 
the Union territories under clause (k) of sub-section (2) of section 3 of the 
Act, by rotation, in such a manner so as to cover all the four regions of the 
country, every year.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Membership Roll.—The 
Member-Secretary shall keep a record of names of Members and their addresses.
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Change of Address.—If 
a Member changes his address, he shall notify his new address to the 
Member-Secretary, who shall thereu­pon enter his new address, in the official 
records (but if he fails to notify his new address, the address in the official 
records shall for all purposes be treated as his correct address).
 
 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Daily and 
Travelling Allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Non-official members of the Central Co-ordination Committee, resident in Delhi, 
shall be paid an allowance of rupees seventy five per day for each day of the 
actual meetings of the Central Co-ordination Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Non-official members 
of the Central Co-ordination Committee, not resident in Delhi shall be paid 
daily and travelling allowances for each day of the actual meetings at the 
highest rates admissi­ble to a Grade I Officer of the Central Government:
 
Provided that in case of a 
Member of Parliament who is also a Member of the Central Co-ordination 
Committee, the said daily and travelling allowances shall be paid at the rates 
admissible to him as Member of Parliament, when the Parliament is not in session 
and on production of a certificate by the Member that he has not drawn any such 
allowance for the same journey and halts from any other Government source.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An official member of 
the Central Co-ordination Committee shall be paid daily and travelling 
allowances, at the rates admissible under the relevant rules of the respective 
Government under whom he is serving on production of a certificate by him that 
he has not drawn any such allowance for the same journey and halts from any 
other Government source.
 
 
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Notice of Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The meetings of the Central Co-ordination Committee shall ordinarily be held in 
New Delhi on such dates as may be fixed by the Chairperson:
 
Provided that it shall 
meet at least once in every six months.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson shall, 
upon the written request of not less than ten members of the Central 
Co-ordination Committee, call a special meeting of the Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Fifteen clear days’ 
notice of an ordinary meeting and five clear days’ notice of a special meeting 
specifying the time and the place at which such meeting is to be held and the 
business to be transacted thereat, shall be given by Member-Secretary to the 
members.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notice of a meeting 
may be given to the members by delivering the same by messenger or sending it by 
registered post to his last known place of residence or business or in such 
other manner as the Chairperson may, in the circumstances of the case think fit.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No member shall be 
entitled to bring forward for the consideration of the meeting any matter of 
which he has not given ten clear days’ notice to the Member-Secretary, unless 
the Chairpersons in his discretion, permits him to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> (a) The Central 
Co-ordination Committee may adjourn its meetings from day to day or to any 
particular day.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where a meeting of the 
Central Co-ordination Committee is adjourned from day to day, notice of such 
adjourned meeting shall be given to the members available at the place where the 
meeting which is adjourned if held by messenger and it shall not be necessary to 
give notice of the adjourned meeting to other members.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Where a meeting of the 
Central Co-ordination Committee is adjourned not from day to day but from the 
day on which the meet­ing is to be held to another date, notice of such meeting 
shall be given to all the members as provided in sub-rule (4) of this rule.
 
 
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Presiding Officer.—The 
Chairperson shall preside at every meeting of the Board and in his absence, the 
Vice-Chairperson shall preside, but when both the Chairperson and the 
Vice-Chairperson are absent from any meeting, the members present shall elect 
one of the members to preside at the meeting.
 
 
</article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Quorum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  One-third of the total members shall form the quorum for any meeting.
 

  1[(2) (a) If a 
  meeting of the Central Coordination Committee cannot be held for want of 
  quorum then, the meeting shall stand adjourned to the same day in the next 
  week, at the same time and place, and if that day is a public holiday, to the 
  next succeeding date which is not public holiday and at the same time and 
  place.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Notice of the 
  adjourned meeting shall be given to all the Members.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No quorum shall be 
  necessary for the adjourned meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No matter which had 
  not been on the agenda of the ordinary or the special meeting, in the case may 
  be, shall be discussed at adjourned meeting.
 
2[***]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> (b) Where a meeting 
  of the Central Government Committee is ad­journed under sub-rule (2) above for 
  want of quorum not to be the following date with sufficient gap, notice of 
  such adjourned meeting shall be given to all the members as provided in 
  sub-rule (4) of rule 11.
 
 
 
—————
 </section><section>
<number>1</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
  1376(E), dated 14th September, 2005, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 21-9-2005).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  Sub-rule 5(a) omitted 
  by S.O. 1376(E), dated 14th September, 2005 (w.e.f. 21-9-2005).
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Minutes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  Record shall be kept of the names of members who attend the meeting and of the 
  proceedings at the meeting in a book to be maintained for that purpose by the 
  Member-Secretary,
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The minutes of the 
  previous meeting shall be read at the beginning of the every succeeding 
  meeting, and shall be confirmed and signed by the presiding officer at such 
  meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The proceedings 
  shall be open to inspection by any member at the office of the 
  Member-Secretary during office hours.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Maintaining order 
  at meeting.—The 
  presiding officer shall maintain order at the meeting.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 the 
  persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  and 
  full participation) Rules, 1996
  
 <article><number>16</number> Business to be transacted at 
  meeting.—Except 
  with the permission of the presiding officer, no business which is not entered 
  in the agenda or of which notice has not been given by a member under sub-rule 
  (5) of Rule 11, shall be transacted at any meeting.
  </article> 
 
 the 
  persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  and 
  full participation) Rules, 1996
  
 <article><number>17</number> 
<section><number>1</number> At any meeting business 
  shall be transacted in the order in which it is entered in the agenda, unless 
  otherwise resolved in the meeting with the permission of the presiding 
  officer.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Either at the beginning of 
  the meeting or after the conclusion of the debate on a motion during the 
  meeting, the presiding officer or a member may suggest a change in the order 
  of business as entered in the agenda and if the Chairperson agrees, such a 
  change shall take place.
  </section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Decision by 
  majority.—All 
  questions considered at a meeting of the Committee shall be decided by a 
  majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of 
  equality of votes, the Chairperson or in the absence of the Chairperson, the 
  Vice-Chairperson or in the absence of both the Chairperson and the 
  Vice-Chairperson, the member presiding at the meeting, as the case may be, 
  shall have a second or casting vote.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> No proceeding to 
  be invalid due to vacancy or any defect.—No 
  proceeding of the Central Co-ordination Committee shall be invalid by reasons 
  of existence of any vacancy in or any defect in the con­stitution of the 
  Committee.
 



</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 



 <article>
<number>20</number> Nomination of 
  State Government representatives by rotation.—The 
  Central Government shall nominate four members—three from the States and one 
  from the Union territories under clause (h) of sub-section (2) of section 9 of 
  the Act, by rotation in such a manner so as to cover all the four regions of 
  the country, every year.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Daily and 
  Travelling Allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  Non-official members of the Central Executive Committee, resident in Delhi, 
  shall be paid an allowance of rupees seventy-five per day for each day of the 
  actual meetings of the Central Co-ordination Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Non-official members 
  of the Central Executive Committee, not resident in Delhi shall be paid daily 
  and travelling allowances for each day of the actual meetings at the higher 
  rates admissible to a Grade I Officer of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Official members of 
  the Central Executive Committee shall be paid daily and travelling allowances, 
  at the rates admissible under the relevant rules of the respective Government 
  under whom he is serving on production of a certificate by him that he has not 
  drawn any such allowance for the same journey and halts from any other 
  Government source.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Notice of 
  Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  The meetings of the Central Executive Committee shall ordinarily be held in 
  New Delhi on such dates as may be fixed by the Chairperson:
 
Provided that it shall 
  meet at least once in every three months.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson 
  shall, upon the written request of not less than ten members of the Central 
  Executive Committee, call a special meeting of the Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Fifteen clear days 
  ‘notice of an ordinary meeting and five clear days’ notice of a special 
  meeting specifying the time and the place at which such meeting is to be held 
  and the business to be transacted thereat, shall be given by the 
  Member-Secretary to the members.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notice of a meeting 
  may be given to the members by delivering the same by messenger or sending it 
  by registered post to his last known place of residence or business or in such 
  other manner as the Chairperson, may, in the circumstances of the case, thinks 
  fit.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No member shall be 
  entitled to bring forward for the considera­tion of the meeting any matter of 
  which he has not given ten clear days’ notice to the Member-Secretary unless 
  the Chairperson, in his discretion, permits him to do so.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> (a) The Central 
  Executive Committee may adjourn its meetings from day to day or to any 
  particular day.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Where a meeting of 
  the Central Executive Committee is adjourned from day today, notice of such 
  adjourned meeting shall be given to the members available at the place where 
  the meeting which is adjourned if held, by messenger and it shall not be 
  necessary to give notice of the adjourned meeting to other members.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Where a meeting of 
  the Central Executive Committee is adjourned not from day to day but from the 
  day on which the meeting is to be held to another date, notice of such meeting 
  shall be given to all the members as provided in sub-rule (4) of this rule.
 
 
</subsection></section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Presiding 
  Officer.—The 
  Chairperson shall preside at every meeting of the Board and in his absence, 
  the members present shall elect one of the members to preside at that meeting.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Quorum.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  One-third of the total members shall form the quorum for any meetings.
 

  1[(2) (a) If a 
  meeting of the Central Executive Committee cannot be held for want of quorum 
  then, the meeting shall stand adjourned to the same day in the next week, at 
  the same time and place, and if that day is a public holiday, to the next 
  succeeding date which is not public holiday and at the same time and place.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Notice of the 
  adjourned meeting shall be given to all the Members.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No quorum shall be 
  necessary for the adjourned meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No matter which had 
  not been on the agenda of the ordinary or the special meeting, as the case may 
  be, shall be discussed at adjourned meeting.
 

  2[***]
 
5 (b) Where a meeting of 
  the Central Executive Committee is adjourned under sub-rule (2) above for want 
  of quorum not to the following date with sufficient gap, notice of such 
  adjourned meeting shall be given to all the members as provided in sub-rule 
  (4) of Rule 22.
 
 
 
—————
 </section><section>
<number>1</number>  Subs. by S.O. 
  1376(E), dated 14th September, 2005, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 21-9-2005).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number>  Sub-rule 5(a) omitted 
  by S.O. 1376(E), dated 14th September, 2005 (w.e.f. 21-9-2005).
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Minutes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  Record shall be kept of the names of members who attend the meeting and of the 
  proceedings at the meeting in a book to be maintained for that purpose by the 
  Member-Secretary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The minutes of the 
  previous meeting shall be read at the beginning of the every succeeding 
  meeting, and shall be confirmed and signed by the presiding officer at such 
  meeting. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The proceedings 
  shall be open to inspection by any member at the office of the 
  Member-Secretary during office hours.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Maintaining order 
  at meeting.—The 
  presiding officer shall maintain order at the meeting.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 the 
  persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  and 
  full participation) Rules, 1996
  
 <article><number>27</number> Business to be transacted at 
  meeting.—Except 
  with the permission of the presiding officer, no business which is not entered 
  in the agenda or of which notice has not been given by a member under sub-rule 
  (5) of Rule 22, shall be transacted at any meeting.
  </article> 
 
 the 
  persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  and 
  full participation) Rules, 1996
  
 <article><number>28</number> 
<section><number>1</number> At any meeting business 
  shall be transacted in the order in which it is entered in the 
  agenda.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Either at the beginning of 
  the meeting or after the conclusion of the debate on a motion during the 
  meeting, the presiding officer or a member may suggest a change in the order 
  of business as entered in the agenda and the Chairperson agrees, such a change 
  shall take place.
  </section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Decision by 
  majority.—All 
  questions considered at a meeting of the Committee shall be decided by a 
  majority of votes of the members present and voting and in the event of 
  equality of votes, the Chairperson, or in the absence of Chairperson, the 
  member presiding at the meeting, as the case may be, shall have a second or 
  casting vote.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> No proceeding to 
  be invalid due to vacancy or any defect.—No 
  proceeding of the Central Executive Committee shall be invalid by reasons of 
  existence of any vacancy in or any defect in the constitution of the 
  Committee.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Manner and 
  purpose of association of persons with Central Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  The Central Executive Committee may invite any person to participate in the 
  deliberations of its meetings, whose assistance or advice, is considered 
  useful in performing any of its function, under the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the person 
  associated with the Central Executive Committee under sub-rule (1) happens to 
  be a non-official resident in Delhi, he shall be entitled to get an allowance 
  of rupees seventy-five per day for each day of actual meeting of the Committee 
  in which he is so associated.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If such a person is 
  not resident in Delhi, he shall be paid daily and travelling allowances for 
  each day of the actual meet­ing at the highest rates admissible to a Grade I 
  Officer of the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If such person is a 
  Government servant, or an employee in a Government undertaking, he shall be 
  entitled to travelling and daily allowances at the rates admissible under the 
  relevant rules applicable to him on production of a certificate by him that he 
  has not drawn any such allowance for the same journey and halts from any other 
  Government source.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Fee for the 
  associated person.—Notwithstanding 
  anything in Rule 31, the Central Executive Committee may pay the person 
  associated with the Committee, with the prior approval of the Central 
  Government, such fees as the Central Government may determine depending on the 
  nature of work assigned and the qualifications and experience of the 
  associated person.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> Tours by 
  associated person.—The 
  associated person may, with the prior approval of the Chairperson undertake 
  tours within the country for the performance of the duties entrusted to him by 
  the Central Executive Committee and in respect of such tours he shall be 
  entitled to travelling and daily allowances at the rates admissible to a Grade 
  I Officer of the Central Government.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> Associated person 
  not be disclose any information.—The 
  associated person shall not disclose any information either given by the 
  Central Executive Committee or obtained during the perfor­mance of the duties 
  assigned to him either from the Central Executive Committee otherwise, to any 
  person other than the Central Executive Committee without the written 
  permission of the Chairperson of the Committee.
 
 
</article>
 

  
 <article><title><number>35</number> Duties and functions of the associated person— </title>The associat­ed person shall discharge such duties and perform such functions as are assigned to him by the Central Executive Committee. 
  
</article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 



 <article>
<number>36</number> Computation of 
  vacancies.—For 
  the purpose of computation of vacancies for persons with disabilities in Group 
  A, B, C, and D posts, the manner of computation of vacancies shall be such as 
  may be determined by the Government by instructions or orders in this regard.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> Notification of 
  vacancies to the Special Employment Exchanges.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  The following vacancies shall be notified to the Special Employment Exchanges, 
  namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  Vacancies in 
  posts of a technical and scientific nature carrying a basic pay of Rs. 1400 or 
  more per month occurring in establishments in respect of which the Central 
  Government is the appropriate Government under the Act, and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  Vacancies 
  which an employer may desire to be circulated to the Special Employment 
  Exchanges outside the State or Union territory in which the establishment is 
  situated, shall be notified to such Special Employment Exchanges as may be 
  specified by the Central Government by notification in the Official Gazette, 
  in this behalf. A copy of the notification of vacancies shall be sent to the 
  Vocational Rehabilitation Centre for Handicapped concerned.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Vacancies other than 
  those specified in sub-rule (1) shall be notified to the local Special 
  Employment Exchange concerned. A copy of the notification of vacancies shall 
  also be sent to the Vocational Rehabilitation Centre for Handicapped 
  concerned.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>38</number> Form and manner 
  of notification of vacancies.—The 
  vacancies shall be notified in writing to the Special Employment Exchange 
  concerned, and the following particulars shall to furnished in respect of each 
  type of vacancy, namely:—
 <section>
         <number>1</number>  Name and 
  address of the employer.
 </section><section>
         <number>2</number>  Telephone 
  number of the employer, if any.
 </section><section>
         <number>3</number>  Nature of 
  vacancy—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  Type of 
  workers required (Designation)
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number> (i)  
  Description of duties;
 <subsubsection>
                 <number>ii</number>  
  Physical requirements (i.e., job involves visual accuracy, frequent 
  movement/walking, continuous long hours sitting, etc.)
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
            <number>c</number>  
  Qualifications required—
 <subsubsection>
                  <number>i</number>  
  Essential,
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
                 <number>ii</number>  
  Desirable
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
            <number>d</number>  
  Age-limits, if any
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>e</number>  Whether 
  women are eligible
 </subsection></section><section>
         <number>4</number>  Number of 
  vacancies—
 
Reserved for physically 
  handicapped persons
 

 
Orthopedically                                     
  Visually                          Hearing
 

  Handicapped                                    Handicapped                    
  Impairment
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  Regular
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number>  
  Temporary.
 </subsection></section><section>
         <number>5</number>  Pay and 
  allowances.
 </section><section>
         <number>6</number>  Place of 
  work (Name of town/village and district in which it is situated.)
 </section><section>
         <number>7</number>  Probable 
  date by which the vacancy will be filled.
 </section><section>
         <number>8</number>  Particulars 
  regarding interview/test of applicants—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  Date of 
  interview/test
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number>  Time of 
  interview/test
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>c</number>  Place 
  of interview/test
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>d</number>  
  Designation and address of the person to whom applicants should report.
 </subsection></section><section>
         <number>9</number>  Any other 
  relevant information—
 
             The 
  vacancies shall be re-notified in writing to the concerned Special Employment 
  Exchange if there is any change in the par­ticulars already furnished to the 
  Special Employment Exchange and Vocational Rehabilitation Centre for 
  Handicapped under this rule.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Time-limit for 
  the notification of vacancies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  Vacancies, required to be notified to the local Special Employment Exchange, 
  shall be notified at least thirty days before the date on which applicants 
  will be interviewed or tested where interviews or tests are held, or the date 
  on which vacancies are intended to be filled, if no interviews or tests are 
  held.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Vacancies required 
  to be notified to the Special Employment Exchange notified under sub-rule (1) 
  of Rule 37 shall be notified at least three weeks before the date on which 
  applicants will be interviewed or tested where interviews or tests are held, 
  or the date on which vacancies are intended to be filled, if no inter­views or 
  tests are held.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An employer shall 
  furnish to the concerned Special Employment Exchange, the results of selection 
  within fifteen days from the date of selection.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> Submission of 
  returns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  An employer shall furnish to the local Special Employment Exchange quarterly 
  returns in Form DPER I and biennial returns in Form DPER II as may be amended 
  from time to time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Quarterly returns 
  shall be furnished within thirty days of the due dates, namely, 31st March, 
  30th June, 30th September and 31st December.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Biennial returns 
  shall be furnished within thirty days of the due date as notified in the 
  Official Gazette.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Form in which 
  record to be kept by an employer.—An 
  employer shall maintain the record of employees with disabilities in Form DPER 
  III, as may be amended from time to time.
 



</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 



 <article>
<number>42</number> Procedure to be 
  followed by Chief Commissioner.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  A com­plaint containing the following particulars shall be presented by the 
  complainant in person or by his agent to the Chief Commis­sioner for Persons 
  with Disabilities or be sent by registered post addressed to the Chief 
  Commissioner:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  The name, 
  description and the address of the complainant;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  The name, 
  description and the address of the opposite party or parties, as the case may 
  be, so far as they can be ascertained;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  The facts 
  relating to complaint and when and where it arose;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  Documents in 
  support of the allegations contained in the complaint;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  The relief 
  which the complainant claims.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief 
  Commissioner on receipt of a complaint shall refer a copy of the complaint to 
  the opposite party/parties mentioned in the complaint directing him to give 
  his version of the case within a period of thirty days or such extended period 
  not ex­ceeding fifteen days as may be granted by the Chief Commissioner.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On the date of 
  hearing or any other date to which hearing could be adjourned, it shall be 
  obligatory on the parties or their agents to appear before the Chief 
  Commissioner.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the 
  complainant or his agent fails to appear before the Chief Commissioner on such 
  days, the Chief Commissioner may in his discretion either dismiss the 
  complaint on default or decide it on merits.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the opposite 
  party or his agent fails to appear on the date of hearing the Chief 
  Commissioner may take such necessary action under section 63 of the Act as he 
  deems fit for summoning and enforcing the attendance of the opposite party.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Chief 
  Commissioner may dispose of the complaint ex parte, if necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Chief 
  Commissioner may on such terms as he deems fit and at any stage of the 
  proceedings, adjourn the hearing of the complaint.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The complaint shall 
  be decided, as far as possible, within a period of three months from the date 
  of notice received by the opposite party.
 
 
</section></article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>43</number> Qualification for appointment of Chief Commissioner. </title>—In order to be eligible for the appointment as Chief Commissioner, a person must satisfy the following conditions, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> he should have special knowledge or practical experience in respect of matters relating to rehabilitation of persons with disabilities; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> he should not have attained the age of sixty years on the 1st January of the year in which the last date for receipt of applications, as specified in the advertisement issued under sub-rule (1) of rule 43A, falls; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> if he is in service under the Central Government or a State Government, he shall seek retirement from such service before his appointment to the post; and 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> he must possess the following educational qualification and experience, namely 
</section>
 <section><number>A</number> Educational qualifications,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Essential: Graduate from a recognised university. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Desirable: Recognised degree/diploma in Social Work/Law/Management/Human Rights/Rehabilitation/Education of Disabled Persons. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>B</number> Experience.—Should have at least twenty-five years experience in one or more of the following types of organizations at specified levels:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> In a Group ‘A'-level post in Central/State Government/Public Sector Undertaking/Semi-Government or Autonomous Bodies dealing with disability related matters and/or social sector (health/education/poverty alleviation/women and child development); or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> A senior level functionary in a registered national or international level voluntary organisation working in the field of disability/social development; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Senior Executive position in a leading private sector organisation, involved in social work and in charge of handling social development activities of the organization: 
</subsection>
 Provided that out of the total twenty-five years experience mentioned above, at least three years of experience in the recent past should have been in the field of empowerment of persons with disabilities. ] 



</section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>43</number> Qualification for appointment of Chief Commissioner. </title>—In order to be eligible for the appointment as Chief Commissioner, a person must satisfy the following conditions, namely:— 
 
 <section><number>i</number> he should have special knowledge or practical experience in respect of matters relating to rehabilitation of persons with disabilities; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> he should not have attained the age of sixty years on the 1st January of the year in which the last date for receipt of applications, as specified in the advertisement issued under sub-rule (1) of rule 43A, falls; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> if he is in service under the Central Government or a State Government, he shall seek retirement from such service before his appointment to the post; and 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> he must possess the following educational qualification and experience, namely 
</section>
 <section><number>A</number> Educational qualifications,— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Essential: Graduate from a recognised university. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Desirable: Recognised degree/diploma in Social Work/Law/Management/Human Rights/Rehabilitation/Education of Disabled Persons. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>B</number> Experience.—Should have at least twenty-five years experience in one or more of the following types of organizations at specified levels:— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> In a Group ‘A'-level post in Central/State Government/Public Sector Undertaking/Semi-Government or Autonomous Bodies dealing with disability related matters and/or social sector (health/education/poverty alleviation/women and child development); or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> A senior level functionary in a registered national or international level voluntary organisation working in the field of disability/social development; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Senior Executive position in a leading private sector organisation, involved in social work and in charge of handling social development activities of the organization: 
</subsection>
 Provided that out of the total twenty-five years experience mentioned above, at least three years of experience in the recent past should have been in the field of empowerment of persons with disabilities. ] 



</section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>43A</number> Mode of appointment of the Chief Commissioner. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> About six months before the post of Chief Commissioner is due to fall vacant, an advertisement shall be published in at least two national level dailies each in English and Hindi inviting applications for the post from eligible candidates fulfilling the criteria mentioned in rule 43. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A Search-cum-Selection Committee shall be constituted to recommend a panel of three suitable candidates for the post of the Chief Commissioner. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Composition of the Committee will be governed by relevant instructions issued by the Department of Personnel and Training from time-to-time. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The panel recommended by the Committee may consist of persons from amongst those who have applied in response to the- advertisement mentioned in sub-rule (1) above, as well as other eligible persons whom the Committee may consider suitable. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Central Government shall appoint one of the candidates recommended by the Search-cum-Selection Committee as the Chief Commissioner. ] 


</section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>43B</number> Term of the Chief Commissioner. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Chief Commissioner shall be appointed on full-time basis for a period of three years from the date on which he assumes office, or till he attains the age of sixty-five years, whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> A person may serve as Chief Commissioner for a maximum of two terms, subject to the upper age limit of sixty-five years. ] 


</section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>43C</number> Salary and allowances of the Chief Commissioner. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The salary and allowances of the Chief Commissioner shall be the salary and allowances as admissible to a Secretary to the Government of India. 
(2) Where a Chief Commissioner, being a retired Government Servant or a retired employee of any institution or autonomous body funded by the Government, is in receipt of pension in respect of such previous service, the salary admissible to him under these rules shall be reduced by the amount of the pension, and if he had received in lieu of a portion of the pension, the commuted value thereof, by the amount of such commuted portion of the pension.
] 


</section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>43D</number> Other terms and conditions of service of the Chief Commissioner. </title>— 

<section><number>1</number> <title>Leave </title>—The Chief Commissioner shall be entitled to such leave as is admissible to Government servants under the Central Civil Service (Leave) Rules, 1972. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> <title>Leave Travel Concession </title>—The Chief Commissioner shall be entitled to such Leave Travel Concession as is admissible to Group ‘A' officers under Central Civil Service (LTC) Rules, 1988. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> <title>Medical Benefits </title>—The Chief Commissioner shall be entitled to such medical benefits as is admissible to Group ‘A' officers under the Central Government Health Scheme (CGHS). ] 


</section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>43E</number> Resignation and removal. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Chief Commissioner may, by notice in writing, under his hand, addressed to the Central Government, resign his post. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Central Government shall remove a person from the office of the Chief Commissioner, if he— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> becomes an undischarged insolvent; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> engages during his term of office in any paid employment or activity outside the duties of his office; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> gets convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence which in the opinion of the Central Government involves moral turpitude; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> is in the opinion of the Central Government, unfit to continue in office by reason of infirmity of mind or body or serious default in the performance of his functions as laid down in the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> without obtaining leave of absence from the Central Government, remains absent from duty for a consecutive period of 15 days or  
    more; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> has, in the opinion of the Central Government, so abused the position of the Chief Commissioner as to render his continuance in office detrimental to the interest of persons with disability: 
 Provided that no person shall be removed under this rule except after following the procedure, mutatis mutandis , prescribed for removal of a Group ‘A' employee of the Central Government. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government may suspend a Chief Commissioner, in respect of whom proceedings for removal have been commenced in accordance with sub-  
  rule (2), pending conclusion of such proceedings. ] 


</section></article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996 
 


 <article><title><footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[<number>43F</number> Residuary provision. </title>—Conditions of service of a Chief Commissioner in respect of which no express provision has been made in these rules shall be determined by the rules and orders for the time being applicable to a Secretary to the Government of India.] 


</article> 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights and 
  full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> Submission of 
  Report to Central Government.—The 
  Chief Commissioner shall submit to the Central Government on the 
  implementation of the Act at the interval of six months in such a manner that 
  at least two reports are sent in one financial year.
 
 
</article>
 
 
 


  the persons with disabilities (equal opportunities, protection of rights  
  and full participation) Rules, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> Submission of 
  annual report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
  The Chief Commissioner shall as soon as possible after the end of the 
  financial year but not later than the 30th day of September in the next year 
  ensuing, prepare and submit to the Central Government an annual report giving 
  a complete account of his activities during the said financial year.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, the 
  annual report referred to in sub-rule (1) shall contain information in respect 
  of each of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  Names of 
  officers, staff of the Board and a chart showing the organizational set-up;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  The 
  functions which the Chief Commissioner has been empowered under sections 58 
  and 59 of the Act and the highlights of the performance in this regard;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  The main 
  recommendations made by the Chief Commissioner;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  Progress 
  made in the implementation of the Act Statewise;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  Any other 
  matter deemed appropriate for inclusion by the Chief Commissioner or specified 
  by the Central Government from time to time.
  
  
</subsection></section></article>

<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for section 2 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> rule 3  subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010). Chapter II, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> rule 4  subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010). Chapter II, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> rule 5  subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010). Chapter II, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> rule 6  subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010). Chapter II, before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010). Rule 43, before substitution stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010). Rule 43, before substitution stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 2(E), dated 30th December, 2009, for rule 43 (w.e.f. 1-1-2010).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>