<act> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Notaries Act, 1952.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India 

1[***].
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date2 as 
the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
 
 




</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 

1[***]
 <section>
       <number>b</number> “instrument” includes every 
document by which any right or liability is, or purports to be, created, 
transferred, modified, limited, extended, suspended, extinguished or recorded;
 

        2[(c)  “legal practitioner” 
means an advocate entered in any roll under the provisions of the Advocates Act, 
1961 (25 1961);]
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number>  “notary” means a person appointed 
as such under this Act:
 
                 Provided that for a period 
of two years from the commencement of this Act it shall include also a person 
who, before such commencement was appointed a notary public 

3[under] the Negotiable Instruments 
Act, 1881 [XXVI of 1881], 

4[***] and is, immediately before such 
commencement, in practice in 

5[any part of India:
 
                 Provided further that in 
relation to the State of Jammu and Kashmir the said period of two years shall be 
computed from the date on which this Act comes into force in that State;]
 </section><section>
       <number>e</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by 
rules made under this Act;
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number> “Register” means a Register of 
Notaries maintained by the Government under section 4;
 

        6[(g)  “State Government”, in 
relation to a Union territory means the administrator thereof.]
 
 








</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Power to appoint 
notaries.—The 
Central Government, for the whole or any part of India, and any State 
Government, for the whole or any part of the State, may appoint as notaries any 
legal practitioners or other persons who possess such qualifications as may be 
prescribed.



</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Registers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government and every State Government shall maintain, in such form 
as may be prescribed, a Register of the notaries appointed by that Government 
and entitled to practise as such under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such Register 
shall include the following particulars about the notary whose name is entered 
therein, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> his full name, date of birth, 
residential and professional address;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the date on which his name is 
entered in the Register;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> his qualifications; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> any other particulars which may be 
prescribed.
 
State Amendment
 
Gujarat:
 
After section 4 insert the following new 
section:—
 
            “4A.—Special provision 
regarding registered Notaries of Gujarat.—(1) Notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act, the State Government of Gujarat shall prepare in the form 
prescribed for a Register required to be maintained under section 4, a Register 
of Notaries for the State of Gujarat as hereinafter provided.
 </subsection></section><section>
            <number>2</number> The State Government of 
Gujarat shall, by an order published in the Official Gazette, enter in the 
Register the names of notaries and all particulars relating thereto appearing in 
the Register maintained immediately before the 1st May, 1960 by the State 
Government of Bombay (hereinafter referred to as ‘the Bombay Register’) after 
excluding from such names, the name of any notary whose professional address as 
recorded in the Bombay Register falls outside the State of Gujarat.
 </section><section>
            <number>3</number> Before making any Order under 
sub-section (2), the State government of Gujarat 
shall make such inquiry as a deems necessary, and give an opportunity to the 
person whose name is proposed to be excluded from the Register, to make his 
representation, if any.
 </section><section>
            <number>4</number> On preparation of the 
Register as aforesaid,—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number> the Register as so prepared 
shall, for all purposes of this Act, be deemed to be the Register maintained for 
the State of Gujarat;
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number> all persons whose names have 
been entered in the Register shall, for the residue of the period for which they 
were appointed by the State Government of Bombay, be deemed to have been 
appointed by the State Government of Gujarat, and accordingly, the certificate 
of practice issued to them under section 5 shall be deemed to have been amended 
so as to restrict their area os practice to the State of Gujarat.”—Notaries Act 
(Gujarat Adaptation) Order, 1961, published in Guj. Govt. Gaz., 27-4-1961, Pt. 
IVA, p. 43.
 


</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Entry of names in the 
Register and issue or renewal of certificates of practice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every notary who intends to practise as such 

1[may], on payment 
to the Government appointing him of the prescribed fee, if any, be entitled—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> to have his name entered in the 
Register maintained by that Government under section 4; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> to a certificate authorising him 
to practise for a period of 

2[five years] from the date on which 
the certificate is issued to him.
 

3[(2) The 
Government appointing the notary, may, on receipt of an application and the 
prescribed fee, renew the certificate of practice of any notary for a period of 
five years at a time.]
 
State Amendment
 
Section 5A:
 
Maharashtra:
 
After section 5, insert the following:—
 
            “5A. Special provision 
regarding Register of Notaries for the State of Maharashtra.—(1) 
Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the State Government of 
Maharashtra may, by order published in the Official Gazette, amend the Register, 
maintained before the 1st day of May 1960 by the State Government of Bombay, by 
deleting therefrom the name of any notary whose professional address as recorded 
in the Register, falls outside the State of Maharashtra:
 
            Provided that, before passing any 
order as aforesaid, the State Government of Maharashtra shall make such inquiry 
as it deems necessary, and give an opportunity to the person concerned to make 
his representation, if any.
 </subsection></section><section>
            <number>2</number> After the amendment of the 
Register as aforesaid,—
 <subsection>
             <number>a</number> the Register as so amended 
shall, for all purposes of this Act, be deemed to be the Register for the State 
of Maharashtra; and
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>b</number> all persons whose names 
remain thereon shall (for the residue of the period for which they were 
appointed by the State Government of Bombay) be deemed to have been appointed by 
the State Government of Maharashtra and accordingly, the certificates of 
practice issued to them under section 5 shall be amended so as to restrict their 
area of practice to the State of Maharashtra.”—The Central Acts on State and 
Concurrent Subjects (Maharashtra Adaptation) Order, 1960 (w.r.e.f. 1-5-1960).









</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Annual publication of 
lists of notaries.—The 
Central Government and every State Government shall, during the month of January 
each year, publish in the Official Gazette a list of notaries appointed by that 
Government and in practice at the beginning of that year together with such 
details pertaining to them as may be prescribed.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Seal of notaries.—Every 
notary shall have and use, as occasion may arise, a seal of such form and design 
as may be prescribed.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Functions of notaries.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notary may do all or any of the following acts by virtue of his office; 
namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> verify, authenticate, certify or 
attest the execution of any instrument;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> present any promissory note, 
hundi or bill of exchange for acceptance or payment or demand better 
security;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number> note or protest the dishonour by 
non-acceptance or non-payment of any promissory note, hundi or bill of 
exchange or protest for better security or prepare acts of honour under the 
Negotiable Instruments Act, 1881 (XXVI of 1881), or serve notice of such note or 
protest;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> note and draw up ship’s protest, 
boat’s protest or protest relating to demurrage and other commercial matters;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number> administer oath to, or take 
affidavit from, any person;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number> prepare bottomry and respondentia 
bonds, charter parties and other mercantile documents;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number> prepare, attest or authenticate 
any instrument intended to take effect in any country or place outside India in 
such form and language as may conform to the law of the place where such deed is 
entitled to operate;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number> translate, and verify the 
translation of, any document from, one language into another;
 

     1[(ha)  act as a Commissioner to 
record evidence in any civil or criminal trial if so directed by any court or 
authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
      <number>hb</number>  act as an arbitrator, mediator or 
conciliator, if so required;]
 <subsubsection>
        <number>i</number> any other act which may be 
prescribed.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No act specified in 
sub-section (1) shall be deemed to be a notarial act except when it is done by a 
notary under his signature and official seal.







</section></article> 
 THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
  
 <article><number>9</number> Bar of practice without 
certificate.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions 
of this section, no person shall practise as a notary or do any notarial act 
under the official seal of a notary unless he holds a certificate of practice in 
force issued to him under section 5:
 Provided that nothing in this 
sub-section shall apply to the presentation of any promissory note, hundi 
or bill of exchange for acceptance or payment by the clerk of a notary acting on 
behalf of such notary.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
sub-section (1) shall, until the expiry of two years from the commencement of 
this Act, apply to any such person as is referred to in the proviso to clause 
(d) of section 2:
 1[Provided that in relation to 
the State of Jammu and Kashmir the said period of two years shall be computed 
from the date on which this Act comes into force in that State.]
  


</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Removal of names from 
Register.—The 
Government appointing any notary may, by order, remove from the Register 
maintained by it under section 4 the name of the notary if he—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> makes a request to that effect; or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> has not paid any prescribed fee 
required to be paid by him; or 
 </section><section>
       <number>c</number> is an undischarged insolvent; or
 </section><section>
       <number>d</number> has been found, upon inquiry in 
the prescribed manner, to be guilty of such professional or other misconduct as, 
in the opinion of the Government, renders him unfit to practise as a notary;


1[or]
 

        1[(e)  is convicted by any 
court for an offence involving moral turpitude; or
 </section><section>
        <number>f</number>  does not get his certificate of 
practice renewed.]






</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Construction of 
references to notaries public in other laws.—Any 
reference to a notary public in any other law shall be construed as a reference 
to a notary entitled to practise under this Act.
 
 
</article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Penalty for falsely 
representing to be a notary, etc.—Any 
person who—
 <section>
       <number>a</number> falsely represents that he is a 
notary without being appointed as such, or
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number> practises as a notary or does any 
notarial act in contravention of section 9, shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to 

1[one year], or with fine, or with 
both.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Cognizance of offence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No court shall take cognizance of any offence committed by a notary in the 
exercise or purported exercise of his functions under this Act save upon 
complaint in writing made by an officer authorised by the Central Government or 
a State Government by general or special order in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No magistrate other 
than a presidency magistrate or a magistrate of the first class shall try an 
offence punishable under this Act.
 


</section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the
official Gazette, make rules to 
carry out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number> the qualifications of a notary, 
the form and manner in which applications for appointment as a notary may be 
made and the disposal of such applications;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number> the certificates, testimonials or 
proofs as to character, integrity, ability and competence which any person 
applying for appointment as a notary may be required to furnish;
 

        1[(c)  the fees payable for 
appointment as a notary and for the issue and renewal of a certificate of 
practice, area of practice or enlargement of area of practice and exemption 
whether wholly or in part, from such fees in specified classes of cases;]
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number> the fees payable to a notary for 
doing any notarial act;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number> the form of Registers and the 
particulars to be entered therein;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>f</number> the form and design of the seal 
of a notary;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>g</number> the manner in which inquiries into 
allegations of professional or other misconduct of notaries may be made;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>h</number> the acts which a notary may do in 
addition to those specified in section 8 and the manner in which a notary may 
perform his functions;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>i</number> any other matter which has to be, 
or may be, prescribed.
 

2[(3) Every rule 
made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.]
 
 




</subsection></section></article> 
 
THE NOTARIES ACT, 1952
 
 
 <article>
 <number>16</number> Amendment of Act XXVI 
of 1881.—[Rep. 
by the Repealing and Amending Act, 1957 (36 of 1957), sec. 2 and Sch.I.]
 
 
  
</article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>