<act><title>

THE 


    CHARITABLE ENDOWMENT ACT, 1890</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Title, extent and 
    commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Charitable Endowments Act, 1890.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It 
    extends to the whole of India, <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[except 
    the State of Jammu and Kashmir], <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[***]; and
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force on the first day of October, 1890.




  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definition.—In 
    this Act “charitable purpose” includes relief of the poor, education, 
    medical relief and the advancement of any other object of general public 
    utility, but does not include a purpose which relates exclusively to 
    religious teaching or worship. 
  
  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Appointment and 
    incorporation of treasurer of Charitable Endowments.—<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may appoint an officer of the Government by the name 
    of his office to be treasurer of Charitable Endowments for India, and the 
    Government of any State may appoint an officer of the Government by the name 
    of his office to be tresurer of Charitable Endowments for the State.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such treasurer shall, 
    for the purposes of taking, holding and transferring movable or immovable 
    property under the authority of this Act, be a corporation sole by the name 
    of the treasurer of Charitable Endowments for <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[India or, as the 
    case may be, the State], and, as such treasurer, shall have perpetual 
    succession and a corporate seal, and may sue and be sued in his corporate 
    name.
  

 
 
The Central Government 
      as well as State Governments have been empowered to appoint an officer of 
      the Government by the name of his office to be treasurer of Charitable 
      Endowments for India and for the States respectively and such treasurer 
      shall, for the purposes of taking, holding and transferring movable or 
      immovable property be a corporation sole by the name of the treasurer. It 
      shall have perpetual successor and a corporate seal and may sue and be 
      sued in his corporate name.
 






  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>3A</number> 
    Definition of “appropriate Government”, etc.—In 
    the subsequent provisions of this Act “ the appropriate Government” means, 
    as respects a charitable endowment, the objects of which do not extend 
    beyond a single State and are not objects to which the executive authority 
    of the Central Government extends, the Government of the State, and as 
    respects any other charitable endowment the Central Government.]



  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Orders vesting property 
    in treasurer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where any property is held or is to be applied in trust for charitable 
    purpose, the 

    1[appropriate 
    Government], if it thinks fit, may, on application made as hereinafter 
    mentioned, and subject to the other provisions of this section, order, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, that the property be vested in the 
    treasurer of Charitable Endowments on such terms as to the application of 
    the property or the income thereof as may be agreed on between the 
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[ appropriate 
    Government] and the person or persons making the application, and the 
    property shall thereupon so vest accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When any property has 
    vested under this section in a treasurer of Charitable Endowments, he is 
    entitled to all documents of title relating thereto.
 
<footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[***]
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An order under this 
    section vesting property in a treasurer of Charitable Endowments shall not 
    require or be deemed to require him to administer the property, or impose or 
    be deemed to impose upon him the duty of a trustee with respect to the 
    administration thereof. 
 


 
 
The appropriate 
      Government has been empowered to vest any property in the treasurer of 
      charitable Endowment on an application made by any person. Such vesting is 
      done by a notification in the Official Gazette. After vesting of any 
      property in the treasurer he becomes entitled to all documents of title 
      relating thereto.
 






  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Schemes for administration of property vested in the treasurer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On application made as hereinafter mentioned, and with the concurrence of 
    the person or persons making the application, the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[appropriate 
    Government] if it thinks fit, may settle a scheme for the administration of 
    any property which has been or is to be vested in the treasurer of 
    Charitable Endowments, and may in such scheme appoint, by name or office, a 
    person or persons, not being or including such treasurer, to administer the 
    property.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On 
    application made as hereinafter mentioned, and with the concurrence of the 
    person or persons making the application, the 

    1[appropriate 
    Government] may, if it thinks fit, modify any scheme settled under this 
    section or substitute another scheme in its stead.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A 
    scheme settled, modified or substituted under this section shall, subject to 
    the other provisions of this section come into operation on a day to be 
    appointed by the 

    1[appropriate 
    Government] in this behalf, and shall remain in force so long as the 
    property to which it relates continues to be vested in the treasurer of 
    Charitable Endowments or until it has been modified or another such scheme 
    has been substituted in its stead.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Such a scheme, when it comes into operation, shall supersede any decree or 
    direction relating to the subject-matter thereof insofar as such decree or 
    direction is in any way repugnant thereto, and its validity shall not be 
    questioned in any court, nor shall any court give, in contravention of the 
    provisions of the scheme or in any way contrary or in addition thereto, a 
    decree or direction regarding the administration of the property to which 
    the scheme relates:
 <footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[Provided 
    that nothing in this sub-section shall be construed as precluding a court 
    from inquiring whether the Government by which a scheme was made was the 
    appropriate Government.]
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> In 
    the settlement of such a scheme effect shall be given to the wishes of the 
    author of the trust so far as they can be ascertained, and, in the opinion 
    of the <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[appropriate Government], effect can reasonably be given 
    to them.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> 
    Where a scheme has been settled under this section for the administration of 
    property not already vested in the treasurer of Charitable Endowments, it 
    shall not come into operation until the property has become so vested.<footcitenum>10</footcitenum>
 










  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Mode of applying for vesting orders and schemes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The application referred to in the two last foregoing sections must be 
    made,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   If the 
      property is already held in trust for a charitable purpose, then by the 
      person acting in the administration of the trust, or, where there are more 
      persons than one so acting, then by those persons or a majority of them; 
      and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   If the 
      property is to be applied in trust for such a purpose then by the person 
      or persons proposing so to apply it.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    For the purposes of this section the executor or administrator of a deceased 
    trustee of property held in trust for a charitable purpose shall be deemed 
    to be a person acting in the administration of the trust<footcitenum>11</footcitenum>.
 








  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Exercise by Governor General in Council of Powers of Local Government.—[Omitted 
    by the A.O. 1937].
 
 
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Bare trusteeship of treasurer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of this Act, a treasurer of Charitable Endowments 
    shall not, as such treasurer, act in the administration of any trust whereof 
    any of the property is for the time being vested in him under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Such treasurer shall keep a separate account of each property for the time 
    being so vested insofar as the property consists of securities for money, 
    and shall apply the property or the income thereof in accordance with the 
    provision made in that behalf in the vesting order under section 4 or in the 
    scheme, if any, under section 5, or in both those documents.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In 
    the case of any property so vested other than securities for money, such 
    treasurer shall, subject to any special order which he may receive from the 
    authority by whose order the property became vested in him, permit the 
    persons acting in the administration of the trust to have the possession, 
    management and control of the property and the application of the income 
    thereof, as if the property had been vested in them.
 

 
 
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Annual publication of list of properties vested in treasurer.—A 
    treasurer of Charitable Endowments shall cause to be published annually in 
    the Official Gazette, at such time as the <footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[appropriate 
    Government] may direct, a list of all properties for the time being vested 
    in him under this Act and an abstract of all accounts kept by him under 
    section 2 of the last foregoing section.







  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Limitation of functions and powers of treasurer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A treasurer of Charitable Endowments shall always be a sole trustee, and 
    shall not, as such treasurer, take or hold any property otherwise than under 
    the provisions of this Act, or, subject to those provisions, transfer any 
    property vested in him except in obedience to a decree divesting him of the 
    property, or in compliance with a direction in that behalf issuing from the 
    authority by whose order the property became vested in him.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Such a direction may require the treasurer to sell or otherwise dispose of 
    any property vested in him, and, with the sanction of the authority issuing 
    the direction, to invest the proceeds of the sale or other disposal of the 
    property in any such security for money as is <footcitenum>13</footcitenum>[specified in the 
    direction], or in the purchase of immovable property.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    When a treasurer of Charitable Endowments is divested, by a direction of
    <footcitenum>14</footcitenum>[the appropriate Government] under this section, of any 
    property, it shall vest in the person or persons acting in the 
    administration thereof and be held by him or them on the same trusts as 
    those on which it was held by such treasurer. 
 









  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Provision for continuance of office of treasurer in certain contingencies.—If 
    the office held by an officer of the Government who has been appointed to be 
    treasurer of Charitable Endowments is abolished or its name is changed, the
    <footcitenum>15</footcitenum>[appropriate Government] may appoint the same or another office 
    of the Government by the name of his office to be such treasurer, and 
    thereupon the holder of the latter office shall be deemed for the purposes 
    of this Act to be the successor in office of the holder of the former 
    office.







  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<footcitenum>16</footcitenum>[<number>12</number>Transfer 
    of property from one treasurer to another.—If 
    by reason of any alteration of areas or by reason of the appointment of a 
    treasurer of Charitable Endowments for India or for any State for which such 
    a treasurer has not previously been appointed or for any other reason it 
    appears to the Central Government that any property vested in a treasurer of 
    Charitable Endowments should be vested in another such treasurer, that 
    Government may direct that the property shall be so vested and thereupon it 
    shall vest in that other treasurer and his successors as fully and 
    effectually for the purposes of this Act as if it had been originally vested 
    in him under this Act.]







  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
[<number>13</number> 
    Power to make rules.—<footcitenum>17</footcitenum>[<footcitenum>18</footcitenum>[
<section><number>1</number>]] The <footcitenum>19</footcitenum>[appropriate Government] 
    may 

    4[by notification in 
    the official Gazette] may make rules consistent with this Act for—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
      prescribing the fees to be paid to the Government in respect of any 
      property vested under this Act in a treasurer of Charitable Endowments;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
      regulating the cases and the mode in which schemes or any modification 
      thereof are to be published before they are settled or made under section 
      5;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
      prescribing the forms in which accounts are to be kept by treasurers of 
      Charitable Endowments and the mode in which such accounts are to be 
      audited; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
      generally carrying into effect the purposes of this Act.]
</subsection>
 </section><section><footcitenum>20</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> 
    Every rule made by the State Government under this Act shall be laid, as 
    soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act shall be laid, as 
    soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it 
    is in session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
    one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry 
    of the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both 
    Houses agree that the Rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter 
    have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may 
    be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without 
    prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.]










  

 
  
 

  


</section></article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Indemnity to Government and treasurer.—No 
    suit shall be instituted against the Government in respect of anything done 
    or purporting to be done under this Act, or in respect of any alleged 
    neglect or omission to perform any duty devolving on the Government under 
    this Act, or in respect of the exercise of, or the failure to exercise, any 
    power conferred by this Act on the Government, nor shall any suit be 
    instituted against a treasurer of Charitable Endowments except for divesting 
    him of property on the ground of its not being subject to a trust for a 
    charitable purpose, or for making him chargeable with or accountable for the 
    loss or misapplication of any property vested in him, or the income thereof, 
    where the loss or misapplication has been occasioned by or through his 
    wilful neglect or default.
 








  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 

 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Saving with respect to Advocate General and Official Trustee.—Nothing 
    in this Act shall be construed to impair the operation <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[of any 
    enactment] for the time being in force, respecting the authority of an 
    Advocate General <footcitenum>22</footcitenum>[***] to act with respect to any charity <footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[or 
    of the Official Trustees Act, 1913] respecting the vesting of property in 
    trust for a charitable purpose in an Official Trustee.








  

 
  
 

  


</article> 
  
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number>
    General Controlling Authority of Governor General in Council.—[Rep. 
    by the Devolution Act, 1920 (38 of 1920), sec. 2 and Sch. I.Pt. I.] 

 
 
 
 

  

 
  
 

  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Subs. 
    by Act 3 of 1951, sec. 3 and Sch., for “except Part B States”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   The 
    words “inclusive of British Baluchistan” omitted by the A.O. by 1948.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> 
 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for the 
    original sub-section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> 
 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937, for “the 
    territories subject to the Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> 
 
Ins. by the A.O. 1937</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> 
 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for 
    “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> 
 
Sub-section (3) omitted, by the 
    A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> 
 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for 
    “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> 
 
Ins. by the  A.O. 1937.tc " 2. 
    Ins. by the  A.O. 1937."</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> 
 
A proviso to sec. 5, applicable 
    only to Bengal, has been added by the Bengal Wakf Act,  1934 (Ben. 13 of 
    1934), sec. 79.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> 
 
A new sub-section (3), 
    application only to Bengal, has been  added by the Bengal Wakf Act, 
    1934 (Ben. 13 of 1934), sec. 80.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> 
 
Subs. by  the A.O. 1937, 
    for “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>   Subs. 
    by  the A.O. 1937, for “mentioned in section 4, sub-section (3), 
    clause (a), (b), (c), (d), or (e)”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>   Subs. 
    by the A.O. 1937 for “the Local Government or the Governor General in 
    Council”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number> 
 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for 
    “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number> 
 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for  
    the original section.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> 
 
Sub-section (1) omitted by the 
    A.O. 1937.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number> 
 
Sub-section (2) renumbered as 
    sub-section(1) by Act 56 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 25-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number> 
 
Subs. by the A.O. 1937 for 
    “Local Government”.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> 
 
Ins. by Act 56 of 1982, sec. 2 (w.e.f. 
    25-10-1982).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> 
 
Subs. by Act 58 of 1960, sec. 3 
    and Second Sch., for certain words (w.e.f. 26-12-1960).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number> 
 
The words “at a Presidency” 
    omitted by Act 58 of 1960, sec. 3 Second Sch. (w.e.f. 26-12-1960).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>