<act><tid>49618</tid>
<title>THE REHABILITATION COUNCIL OF INDIA (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>2000</year></title>

ACT NO. 38 OF <year>2000</year>
[ 4th September, <year>2000</year>.]

An Act to amend the Rehabilitation Council of India Act, <year>1992</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Fifty- first Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:-





<article><tid>587716</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title.- This Act may be called the Rehabilitation Council of 
India (Amendment) Act, <year>2000</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1863222</tid>
<number>2</number>Amendment of long title.- In the Rehabilitation Council of India 
Act, <year>1992</year> (34 of <year>1992</year>)  (hereinafter referred to as the principal Act), 
in the long title for the words" the training of rehabilitation 
professionals and", the words" and monitoring the t aining of 
rehabilitation professionals and personnel, promoting research in 
rehabilitation and special education," shall be substituted.


</article>



<article><tid>912499</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of section 2.- In section 2 of the principal Act,-
<section><tid>1203287</tid>
<number>1</number>in sub- section (1),-

<subsection><tid>1558847</tid>
<number>i</number>for clause (c), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:-
' (c)" handicapped" means a person suffering from any disability 
referred to in clause (i) of section 2 of the Persons With 
Disabilities (Equal Opportunities, Protection of Rights and Full  
  Participation) Act, <year>1995</year> (1 of <year>1996</year>);';


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>8533</tid>
<number>ii</number>clauses (d) and (e) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1069344</tid>
<number>iii</number>after clause (m), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:-
' (ma)" rehabilitation" refers to a process aimed at enabling persons 
with disabilities to reach and maintain their optimal physical, 
sensory, intellectual, psychiatric or social functional levels;';


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1254179</tid>
<number>iv</number>clause (o) shall be omitted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>203411</tid>
<number>2</number>after sub- section (1), the following sub- section shall be 
inserted, namely:-
" (1A) Words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but 
defined in the Persons With Disabilities (Equal Opportunities,  
  Protection of Rights and Full Participation) Act, <year>1995</year> (1 of <year>1996</year>) 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in th t Act.".




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1254282</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of section 3.- In section 3 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (3), for clauses (a) and (b), the following clauses shall 
be substituted, namely:-
" (a) a Chairperson, from amongst the persons having experience in 
administration with professional qualification in the field of 
rehabilitation, disabilities, and special education, to be appointed 
by the Central Government;

<section><tid>1828111</tid>
<number>b</number>such number of members not exceeding seven, as may be nominated by 
the Central Government, to represent the Ministries of the Central 
Government dealing with matters relating to persons with 
disabilities;".



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1329113</tid>
<number>5</number>Amendment of section 13.- In section 13 of the principal Act, after 
sub- section (2), the following sub- section shall be inserted, namely:-
" (2A) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), any 
person being a doctor or a paramedic in the field of physical medicine 
and rehabilitation, orthopaedics, ear, nose or throat (ENT), 
ophthalmology or psychiatry, employed or working in any h spital or 
establishment owned or controlled by the Central Government or a State 
Government or any other body funded by the Central or a State 
Government and notified by the Central Government, may discharge the 
functions referred to in clauses (a) to (d) of that sub- section.".



</article>



<article><tid>229359</tid>
<number>6</number>Amendment of section 19.- In section 19 of the principal Act, the 
following provisos shall be inserted at the end, namely:-
" Provided that the Council shall register vocational instructors and 
other personnel working in the vocational rehabilitation centres under 
the Ministry of Labour on recommendation of that Ministry and 
recognise the vocational rehabilitation centres as m npower 
development centres:

Provided further that the Council shall register personnel working in 
national institutes and apex institutions on disability under the 
Ministry of Social Justice and Empowerment on recommendation of that 
Ministry and recognise the national institutes a d apex institutions 
on disability as manpower development centres.".



</article>



<article><tid>8511</tid>
<number>7</number>Amendment of section 22.- In section 22 of the principal Act, in 
sub- section (2), for the words" period of thirty days", at both the 
places where they occur, the words" period of sixty days" shall be 
substituted.
SUBHASH C. JAIN, 
Secy. to the Govt. of India.


</article>



 </act>