<act><tid>498208</tid>
<title>THE PRODUCE CESS ACT, <year>1966</year></title>

ACT NO. 15 OF <year>1966</year>
[ 21st May, <year>1966</year>.]

An Act to provide for the imposition of cess on certain produce for 
the improvement and development of the methods of cultivation and 
marketing of such produce and for matters connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Seventeenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>1969878</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>878386</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the Produce  
Cess Act, <year>1966</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1044672</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>242347</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1949341</tid>
<number>a</number>" Collector" means the officer appointed by the Central 
Government to perform in any specified area the duties 
of a Collector under the provisions of this Act and the 
rules made thereunder, and includes any officer 
subordinate to that officer whom he may, by order in 
writing, authorise to perform his duties under those 
provisions;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1744871</tid>
<number>c</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>" customs airport"," customs port" and" customs 
station" have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in the Customs Act, <year>1962</year>] (52 of <year>1962</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>949226</tid>
<number>d</number>" Indian Council of Agricultural Research" means the body 
registered in that name under the Societies 
Registration Act, <year>1860</year> (21 of <year>1860</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>154094</tid>
<number>e</number>" lac" includes any form of manufactured or 
unmanufactured lac other than refuse lac;

</section>

<section><tid>1258312</tid>
<number>f</number>" managing agent" has the meaning assigned to it in the 
Companies Act, <year>1956</year> (1 of <year>1956</year>);
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>278</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2. 
2. Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1966</year>, s. 2, for cl. (c)  (retrospectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


</section>

<section><tid>1360460</tid>
<number>j</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act;

</section>

<section><tid>288913</tid>
<number>k</number>" produce" means any goods specified in the First 
Schedule <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1080849</tid>
<number> 3</number> Imposition of cess.
<section><tid>1870237</tid>
<number>1</number>There shall be levied and collected as  
a cess, for the purposes of this Act, on every produce specified in 
column 2 of the First Schedule, which is exported from any <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> customs 
station to any place] beyond the limits of India, a duty of customs at 
such rate, not exceeding the rate specified in the corresponding entry 
in column 3 thereof, as the Central Government may, by notification in 
the Official Gazette, specify:
Provided that until such rate is specified by the Central 
Government, the duty of customs shall be levied and collected at the 
rate specified in the corresponding entry in column 4 of the said 
Schedule.

<footcitenum>4</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>279</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 30 of <year>1983</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1984</year>). 
2. Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 2 
3. Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1966</year>, s. 3, for" customs port to any port" 
 (retrospectively). 
4. Omitted by s. 3, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>180586</tid>
<number>4</number>Persons who shall be liable to pay duty. Every duty of customs 
leviable under this Act on any produce shall be payable by the person 
by whom such produce is exported from India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> xxx


</article>



<article><tid>388883</tid>
<number> 5</number> Application of proceeds of cess.
<section><tid>816665</tid>
<number>1</number>An amount equivalent to  
the proceeds of the duty levied and collected under this Act, reduced 
by the cost of collection as determined by the Central Government, 
together with any moneys received by the Central Government for the 
purposes of this Act, shall, after due appropriation made by 
Parliament by law, be utilized by the Central Government to meet the 
expenditure incurred in connection with measures which, in the opinion 
of that Government, are necessary or expedient to promote the 
improvement, development and marketing of produce.

</section>

<section><tid>959667</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
provisions of sub- section (1), the proceeds of the duty levied and 
collected under this Act may be utilized by the Central Government for 
all or any of the following purposes, namely:--

<subsection><tid>1102818</tid>
<number>a</number>undertaking, assisting or encouraging, agricultural, 
industrial, technological and economic research, 
including research on the utilization of the products 
obtained from any produce;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1976220</tid>
<number>b</number>supplying technical advice to cultivators, growers and 
millers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>276022</tid>
<number>c</number>encouraging the adoption of improved methods of 
cultivation and storage of crops;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1821427</tid>
<number>d</number>producing, testing and distributing improved varieties 
of crops or assisting such work;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>65724</tid>
<number>e</number>assisting in the control of insects and other pests and 
diseases of the crops, both in the field and in 
storage;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>419409</tid>
<number>f</number>promoting the improvement of the marketing of produce 
and the products obtained therefrom in India and abroad 
including the setting up and adoption of grade 
standards for the produce and the products obtained 
therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1477793</tid>
<number>g</number>collecting statistics from cultivators, growers, dealers 
and occupiers of mills on all relevant matters and 
promoting improvement in the forecasting of crops and 
the preparation of all relevant statistics relating to 
the crops and the products obtained therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1491001</tid>
<number>h</number>maintaining, and assisting in the maintenance of, such 
institutes, farms and stations as the Central 
Government may consider necessary;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>280</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1442653</tid>
<number>i</number>advising and providing assistance on all matters 
connected with the improvement of the cultivation of 
crops (including advising on the best and most suitable  
  varieties of the crops to be cultivated) and the 
improvement of the industries using the crops and the 
products obtained therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>441383</tid>
<number>j</number>promoting and encouraging the co- operative movement in 
any connected industry;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>932522</tid>
<number>k</number>adopting such measures as may be practicable for 
ensuring remunerative returns to the growers;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1855829</tid>
<number>l</number>organising the establishment of cultivators', growers', 
millers' and consumers' organisations;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1985530</tid>
<number>m</number>aiding and encouraging the establishment of exhibitions 
for demonstrating the uses of the produce and the 
products obtained therefrom;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1055199</tid>
<number>n</number>adopting any other measures which the Central Government 
may deem to be necessary or advisable to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1772738</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section," crops" means crops or plants from which any 
produce is obtained[ and" produce" includes cotton.] <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>3</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>282</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 5. 
2. Omitted by Act 30 of <year>1983</year>, s. 7 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1984</year>). 
3. Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>875596</tid>
<number> 11</number> Collection of cess on any produce specified in First 
Schedule.
<section><tid>369601</tid>
<number>1</number>The Collector shall in respect of any produce specified  
in the First Schedule which is exported by sea <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or air] assess and 
collect the duty of customs at the customs port <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> or customs airport] 
of export.

</section>

<section><tid>994028</tid>
<number>2</number>Where any produce specified in the First Schedule is exported 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by land or inland water], the duty of customs leviable under this 
Act on such produce shall be assessed and collected by such authority 
and in such manner as may be prescribed, and, until so prescribed, 
such duty of customs shall be levied and collected in accordance with 
the law in force immediately before the commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>890833</tid>
<number>3</number>The Central Board of Excise and Customs constituted under the 
Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year> (54 of <year>1963</year>), may, be rules, 
specify the conditions and restrictions subject to which--

<subsection><tid>1577737</tid>
<number>a</number>refund may be made of the duty of customs levied on any 
produce specified in the First Schedule which is 
exported <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by land or inland water], where such 
produce is subsequently imported into India,

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1517690</tid>
<number>b</number>export may be made <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by land or inland water], without 
payment of any duty of customs, of any produce 
specified in the First Schedule which is intended to be 
brought back to India.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>283</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 49 of <year>1966</year>, s. 4 (retrospectively). 
2. Subs. by s. 4, ibid., for" by land" (retrospectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1081644</tid>
<number> 12</number> Recovery of sums due to Government. Where any duty of customs 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> demanded from any persons or any penalty payable by any person 
under this Act is not paid--
<section><tid>838420</tid>
<number>a</number>the Collector may deduct the amount so payable from any 
money owing to such person which may be under the 
control of the Collector or any other officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1267681</tid>
<number>b</number>the Collector may recover the amount so payable by 
detaining and selling any goods belonging to such 
person which are under the control of the Collector or 
any other officer; or

</section>

<section><tid>1759362</tid>
<number>c</number>if the amount cannot be recovered from such person in 
the manner provided in clause (a) or clause (b), the 
Collector may prepare a certificate signed by him 
specifying the amount due from such person and send it 
to the Collector of the district in which such person 
owns any property or resides or carries on his business 
and the said Collector shall, on receipt of such 
certificate, proceed to recover from the said person 
the amount specified therein as if it were an arrear of 
land revenue.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>

<pagefootnote><pagenum>284</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 6. 
2. Omitted by s. 3, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1329595</tid>
<number> 15</number> Provisions of certain Acts to apply.
<section><tid>1672171</tid>
<number>1</number>The provisions of  
the Customs Act, <year>1962</year> (52 of <year>1962</year>), and the rules and regulations 
made thereunder, including those relating to refunds and exemptions 
from duty, shall, so far as may be, apply in relation to the levy and 
collection of duties of customs on any produce specified in the First 
Schedule as they apply in relation to the levy and collection of duty 
payable to the Central Government under that Act.
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>121820</tid>
<number> 16</number> Offences.
<section><tid>467282</tid>
<number>1</number>Whoever-- 

<subsection><tid>1110459</tid>
<number>a</number>evades the payment of any duty of customs <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> payable 
under this Act, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>130370</tid>
<number>b</number>fails to furnish any return or information which it is 
his duty to furnish under this Act or furnishes a 
return or information which is false in material 
particulars or which he does not believe to be true, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>274578</tid>
<number>c</number>obstructs the Collector or any other officer in the 
performance of his duties under this Act or any rules 
made thereunder.
shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to 
six months, or with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees, or 
with both.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>446084</tid>
<number>2</number>Any court trying an offence under this Act may direct that 
any produce in respect of which it is satisfied that an offence 
punishable under this Act has been committed shall be forfeited to 
Government and may also direct that all packages, coverings or 
receptacles in which such produce is contained and every animal, 
vehicle, vessel or other conveyance used in carrying such produce 
shall be forfeited to Government.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1768478</tid>
<number>17</number>Limitation of prosecution. No prosecution for any offence 
punishable under this Act shall be instituted against any person 
except by, or with the consent of, the Collector.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>285</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 3. 
2. Omitted by s. 7, ibid.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>101566</tid>
<number>18</number>Composition of offences. Any offence punishable under this 
Act may, either before or after the institution of the prosecution, be 
compounded by the Collector or any other officer authorised by him in 
this behalf on payment to the Central Government, for the purposes of 
this Act, of such sum as the Collector or such officer, as the case 
may be, thinks fit.


</article>



<article><tid>1403400</tid>
<number> 19</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.
<section><tid>815396</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
Government or any person authorized by the Central Government for 
anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
pursuance of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>516303</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Central Government or any person authorized by the Central Government 
for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of any of the 
provisions of this Act or any rule or order made thereunder.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1538125</tid>
<number> 20</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>1701843</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>722369</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely--
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>


<subsection><tid>1152975</tid>
<number>e</number>the authority by which and the manner in which the 
duties of customs leviable under this Act shall be 
collected on any produce specified in the First 
Schedule which is exported <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> by land or inland water]; 
and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>367814</tid>
<number>f</number>any other matter which is required to be, or may be, 
prescribed.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1300125</tid>
<number>21</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Central Government 
may, be order, make such directions, not
<pagefootnote><pagenum>286</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 8. 
2. Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1966</year>, s. 5, for" by land" (retrospectively).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as appear to it to be 
necessary or expedient for the removal of the difficulty:

Provided that no such directions shall be made after the expiry 
of a period of three years from the date of commencement of this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>670202</tid>
<number>22</number>Rules of be laid before Parliament. Every rule made under 
this Act shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> two or 
more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session] or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under the rule.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>287</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1987</year>, s. 9.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>