<act><title>THE COMMISSIONS FOR PROTECTION OF CHILD RIGHTS ACT, 2005 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title, extend and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called the Commissions for Protection of Child Rights Act, 2005. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir . 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint. 


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.-In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,-
 
 
 
 
"Chairperson" means the Chairperson of the 
        Commission or of the State Commission, as the case may be;
 
 
"child rights" includes the children's 
        rights adopted in the United Nations convention on the Rights of the 
        Child on the 20th November, 1989 and ratified by the Government of India 
        on the 11th December, 1992;
 
 
"Commission" means the National Commission 
        for Protection of Child Rights constituted under section 3;
 
 
"Member" means a Member of the Commission 
        or of the State Commission, as the case may be, and includes the 
        Chairperson;
 
 
"notification" means a notification 
        published in the Official Gazette;
 
 
"prescribed" means prescribed by rules 
        made under this Act;
 
 
"State Commission" means State Commission 
        for Protection of Child Rights constituted under section 
        17.             





  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Constitution of National Commission for Protection of Child Rights.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, by notification, constitute a body to be known 
    as the National Commission for Protection of Child Rights to exercise the 
    powers conferred on, and to perform the functions assigned to it under this 
    Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission shall consist of the following Members, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    a Chairperson who, is a person of 
    eminence and has done outstanding work for promoting the welfare of 
    children; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    six Members, out of which at least two 
    shall be women, from the following fields, to be appointed by the Central 
    Government from amongst persons of eminence, ability, integrity, standing 
    and experience in,-
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  education;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>  child health, care, welfare or 
    child development;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>  juvenile justice or care of neglected 
    or marginalized children or children with disabilities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>  elimination of child labour or children 
    in distress; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>  child psychology or sociology; and
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>  laws relating to children.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    office of the Commission shall be at Delhi.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Appointment of Chairperson and Members.-The 
    Central Government shall, by notification, appoint the Chairperson and other 
    Members:
 
Provided 
    that the Chairperson shall be appointed on the recommendation of a three 
    member Selection Committee constituted by the Central Government under the 
    Chairmanship of the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Minister in-charge of the Ministry or the 
    Department of Women and Child 
    Development.]
  






  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Term of office and conditions of service of Chairperson and Members.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson and every Member shall hold office as such for a term of 
    three years from the date on which he assumes office:
 
Provided 
    that no Chairperson or a Member shall hold the office for more than two 
    terms:
 
Provided 
    further that no Chairperson or any other Member shall hold office as such 
    after he has attained-
 <subsection>
              <number>a</number>    in the case of the 
    Chairperson, the age of sixty-five years; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>b</number>    in the case of a Member, 
    the age of sixty years.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson or a Member may, by writing under his hand addressed to the 
    Central Government, resign his office at any time.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Salary and allowances of Chairperson and Members.-The 
    salary and allowances payable to, and other terms and conditions of service 
    of, the Chairperson and Members, shall be such as may be prescribed by the 
    Central Government:
 
Provided 
    that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Chairperson or a Member, as the case may be, shall be varied 
    to his disadvantage after his appointment.
  




  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Removal from office.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the provisions of sub-section (2), the Chairperson may be removed 
    from his office by an order of the Central Government on the ground of 
    proved misbehaviour or incapacity.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), the Central 
    Government may by order remove from office the Chairperson or any other 
    Member, if the Chairperson or, as the case may be, such other Member,-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    is adjudged an insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    engages during his term of office in 
    any paid employment outside the duties of his office; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    refuses to act or becomes incapable of 
    acting; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    is of unsound mind and stands so 
    declared by a competent court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    has so abused his office as to render 
    his continuance in office detrimental to the public interest; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    is convicted and sentenced to 
    imprisonment for an offence which in the opinion of the Central Government 
    involves moral turpitude; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    is, without obtaining leave of 
    absence from the Commission, absent from three consecutive meetings of the 
    Commission.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number>
No person shall be removed under this section until that person has been 
    given an opportunity of being heard in the matter.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Vacation of office by Chairperson or Member.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    If the Chairperson or, as the case may be, a Member,-
 <subsection>
              <number>a</number>    becomes subject to any of 
    the disqualifications mentioned in section 7; or
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>b</number>    tenders his resignation 
    under sub-section (2) of section 5,
 
his seat shall thereupon become vacant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If a 
    casual vacancy occurs in the office of the Chairperson or a Member, whether 
    by reason of his death, resignation or otherwise, such vacancy shall be 
    filled within a period of ninety days by making afresh appointment in 
    accordance with the provisions of section 4 and the person so appointed 
    shall hold office for the remainder of the term of office for which the 
    Chairperson, or a Member, as the case may be, in whose place he is so 
    appointed would have held that office.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate proceedings of Commission.-No 
    act or proceeding of the Commission shall be invalid merely by reason of-
 <section>
<number>a</number>    any vacancy in, or any defect in the 
    constitution of, the Commission; or
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    any defect in the appointment of a 
    person as the Chairperson or a Member; or
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    any irregularity in the 
    procedure of the Commission not affecting the merits of the case.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Procedure for transaction of business.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commission shall meet regularly at its office at such time as the 
    Chairperson thinks fit, but three months shall not intervene between its 
    last and the next meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All 
    decisions at a meeting shall be taken by majority:
 
Provided 
    that in the case of equality of votes, the Chairperson, or in his absence 
    the person presiding, shall have and exercise a second or casting vote.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If 
    for any reason, the Chairperson, is unable to attend the meeting of the 
    Commission, any Member chosen by the Members present from amongst themselves 
    at the meeting, shall preside.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Commission shall observe such rules of procedure in the transaction of its 
    business at a meeting, including the quorum at such meeting, as may be 
    prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> All 
    orders and decisions of the Commission shall be authenticated by the 
    Member-Secretary or any other officer of the Commission duly authorised by 
    Member-Secretary in this behalf.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Member-Secretary, officers and other employees of Commission.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, by notification, appoint an officer not below 
    the rank of the Joint Secretary or the Additional Secretary to the 
    Government of India as a Member-Secretary of the Commission and shall make 
    available to the Commission such other officers and employees as may be 
    necessary for the efficient performance of its functions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Member-Secretary shall be responsible for the proper administration of the 
    affairs of the Commission and its day-to-day management and shall exercise 
    and discharge such other powers and perform such other duties as may be 
    prescribed by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    salary and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Member-Secretary, other officers and employees, appointed for 
    the purpose of the Commission shall be such as may be prescribed by the 
    Central Government.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Salaries and allowances to be paid out of grants.-The 
    salaries and allowances payable to the Chairperson and Members and the 
    administrative expenses, including salaries, allowances and pensions payable 
    to the Member-Secretary, other officers and employees referred to in section 
    11, shall be paid out of the grants referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of 
    section 27.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Functions of Commission.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commission shall perform all or any of the following functions, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> examine and review the safeguards provided 
    by or under any law for the time being in force for the protection of child 
    rights and recommend measures for their effective implementation;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> present to the Central Government, 
    annually and at such other intervals, as the Commission may deem fit, 
    reports upon the working of those safeguards;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> inquire into violation of child rights and 
    recommend initiation of proceedings in such cases;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> examine all factors that inhibit the 
    enjoyment of rights of children affected by terrorism, communal violence, 
    riots, natural disaster, domestic violence, HIV/AIDS, trafficking, 
    maltreatment, torture and exploitation, pornography and prostitution and 
    recommend appropriate remedial measures;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> look into the matters relating to children 
    in need of special care and protection including children in distress, 
    marginalized and disadvantaged children, children in conflict with law, 
    juveniles, children without family and children of prisoners and recommend 
    appropriate remedial measures;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> study treaties and other international 
    instruments and undertake periodical review of existing policies, programmes 
    and other activities on child rights and make recommendations for their 
    effective implementation in the best interest of children;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> undertake and promote research in the 
    field of child rights;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> spread child rights literacy among various 
    sections of the society and promote awareness of the safeguards available 
    for protection of these rights through publications, the media, seminars and 
    other available means;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> inspect or cause to be inspected any 
    juvenile custodial home, or any other place of residence or institution 
    meant for children, under the control of the Central Government or any State 
    Government or any other authority, including any institution run by a social 
    organisation; where children are detained or lodged for the purpose of 
    treatment, reformation or protection and take up with these authorities for 
    remedial action, if found necessary;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> inquire into complaints and take suo 
    motu notice of matters relating to,- 
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>  deprivation and violation of child 
    rights;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number> non-implementation of laws providing for 
    protection and development of children;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number> non-compliance of policy decisions, 
    guidelines or instructions aimed at mitigating hardships to and ensuring 
    welfare of the children and to provide relief to such children,
 
or take up the issues arising out of such 
    matters with appropriate authorities; and
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number> such other functions as it may consider 
    necessary for the promotion of child rights and any other matter incidental 
    to the above functions.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    commission shall not inquire into any matter which is pending before a State 
    Commission or any other Commission duly constituted under any law for the 
    time being in force.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Powers relating to inquiries.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commission shall, while inquiring into any matter referred to in clause 
    (j) of sub-section (1) of section 13 have all the powers of a civil court 
    trying a suit under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) and, in 
    particular, in respect of the following matters, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    summoning and enforcing the attendance 
    of any person and examining him on oath;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    discovery and production of any 
    document;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    receiving evidence on affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    requisitioning any public record or 
    copy thereof from any court or office; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    issuing commissions for the examination 
    of witnesses or documents.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission shall have the power to forward any case to a Magistrate having 
    jurisdiction to try the same and the Magistrate to whom any such case is 
    forwarded shall proceed to hear the complaint against the accused as if the 
    case has been forwarded to him under section 346 of the Code of Criminal 
    Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Steps after inquiry.-The 
    Commission may take any of the following steps upon the completion of an 
    inquiry held under this Act, namely:-
 <section>
<number>i</number>    where the inquiry discloses, the 
    Commission of violation of child rights of a serious nature or contravention 
    of provisions of any law for the time being in force, it may recommend to 
    the concerned Government or authority the initiation of proceedings for 
    prosecution or such other action as the Commission may deem fit against the 
    concerned person or persons;
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>    approach the Supreme Court or the High 
    Court concerned for such directions, orders or writs as that Court may deem 
    necessary;
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>    recommend to the concerned Government 
    or authority for the grant of such interim relief to the victim or the 
    members of his family as the Commission may consider necessary.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    Annual and special reports of Commission.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commission shall submit an annual report to the Central Government and 
    to the State Government concerned and may at any time submit special reports 
    on any matter which, in its opinion, is of such urgency or importance that 
    it should not be deferred till submission of the annual report.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government and the State Government concerned, as the case may be, 
    shall cause the annual and special reports of the Commission to be laid 
    before each House of Parliament or the State Legislature respectively, as 
    the case may be, along with a memorandum of action taken or proposed to be 
    taken on the recommendations of the Commission and the reasons for 
    non-acceptance of the recommendations, if any, within a period of one year 
    from the date of receipt of such report.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    annual report shall be prepared in such form, manner and contain such 
    details as may be prescribed by the Central Government.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Constitution of State Commission for Protection of Child Rights.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    A State Government may constitute a body to be known as the.........(name of 
    the State) Commission for Protection of Child Rights to exercise the powers 
    conferred upon, and to perform the functions assigned to, a State Commission 
    under this Chapter.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Commission shall consist of the following Members, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> a Chairperson who is a person of eminence 
    and has done outstanding work for promoting the welfare of children; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> six Members, out of which at least two 
    shall be women, from the following fields, to be appointed by the State 
    Government from amongst persons of eminence, ability, integrity, standing 
    and experience in,-
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>    education;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>    child health, care, welfare or 
    child development;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>    juvenile justice or care of neglected 
    or marginalized children or children with disabilities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>    elimination of child labour or 
    children in distress; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>    child psychology or sociology; and
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>    laws relating to children.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    headquarter of the State Commission shall be at such place as the State 
    Government may, by notification, specify.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Appointment of Chairperson and other Members.-The 
    State Government shall, by notification, appoint the Chairperson and other 
    Members:
 
Provided 
    that the Chairperson shall be appointed on the recommendation of a three 
    Member Selection Committee constituted by the State Government under the 
    Chairmanship of the Minister in-charge of the Department dealing with 
    children.
  



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Term of office and conditions of service of Chairperson and Members.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chairperson and every Member shall hold office as such for a term of 
    three years from the date on which he assumes office:
 
Provided 
    that no Chairperson or a Member shall hold the office for more than two 
    terms:
 
Provided 
    further that no Chairperson or any other Member shall hold office as such 
    after he has attained-
 <subsection>
              <number>a</number>    in the case of 
    Chairperson, the age of sixty-five years; and
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>b</number>    in the case of a Member, 
    the age of sixty years.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Chairperson or a Member may, by writing under his hand addressed to the 
    State Government, resign his office at any time.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Salary and allowances of Chairperson and Members.-The 
    salaries and allowances payable to, and other terms and conditions of 
    service of, the Chairperson and Members shall be such as may be prescribed 
    by the State Government:
 
Provided 
    that neither the salary and allowances nor the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Chairperson or a Member, as the case may be, shall be varied 
    to his disadvantage after his appointment.
  




  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Secretary, officers and other employees of the State Commission.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall, by notification, appoint an officer not below 
    the rank of the Secretary to the State Government as the Secretary of the 
    State Commission and shall make available to the State Commission such other 
    officers and employees as may be necessary for the efficient performance of 
    its functions.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Secretary shall be responsible for the proper administration of the affairs 
    of the State Commission and its day-to-day management and shall exercise and 
    discharge such other powers and perform such other duties as may be 
    prescribed by the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    salary and allowances payable to, and the other terms and conditions of 
    service of the Secretary, other officers and employees, appointed for the 
    purpose of the State Commission shall be such as may be prescribed by the 
    State Government.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> 
    Salaries and allowances to be paid out of grants.-The 
    salaries and allowances payable to the Chairperson and Members and the 
    administrative expenses, including salaries, allowances and pensions payable 
    to the Secretary, other officers and employees referred to in section 21, 
    shall be paid out of the grants referred to in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 
    28.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Annual and special reports of State Commission.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Commission shall submit an annual report to the State Government 
    and may at any time submit special reports on any matter which, in its 
    opinion, is of such urgency or importance that it should not be deferred 
    till submission of the annual report.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Government shall cause all the reports referred to in sub-section (1) 
    to be laid before each House of State Legislature, where it consists of two 
    Houses, or where such Legislature consist of one House, before that House 
    along with a memorandum explaining the action taken or proposed to be taken 
    on the recommendations relating to the State and the reasons for the 
    non-acceptance, if any, of any of such recommendations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    annual report shall be prepared in such form, manner and contain such 
    details as may be prescribed by the State Government.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Application of certain provisions relating to National Commission for 
    Protection of Child Rights to State Commissions.-The 
    provisions of sections 7, 8, 9, 10, sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 13 and 
    sections 14 and 15 shall apply to a State Commission and shall have effect, 
    subject to the following modifications, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    references to "Commission" shall be 
    construed as references to "State Commission";
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    references to "Central Government" 
    shall be construed as references to "State Government"; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    references to "Member-Secretary" shall 
    be construed as references to "Secretary".
  




  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Children's Courts.-For 
    the purpose of providing speedy trial of offences against children or of 
    violation of child rights, the State Government may, with the concurrence of 
    the Chief Justice of the High Court, by notification, specify at least a 
    court in the State or specify, for each district, a Court of Session to be a 
    Children's Court to try the said offences:
 
Provided 
    that nothing in this section shall apply if-
 <section>
              <number>a</number>    a Court of Session is 
    already specified as a special court; or 
 </section><section>
              <number>b</number>    a special court is 
    already constituted,
 
for such offences under any other law for the 
    time being in force.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Special Public Prosecutor.-For 
    every Children's Court, the State Government shall, by notification, specify 
    a Public Prosecutor or appoint an advocate who has been in practice as an 
    advocate for not less than seven years, as a Special Public Prosecutor for 
    the purpose of conducting cases in that Court.
  



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> 
    Grants by Central Government.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government shall, after due appropriation made by Parliament by 
    law in this behalf, pay to the Commission by way of grants such sums of 
    money as the Central Government may think fit for being utilised for the 
    purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Commission may spend such sums of money as it thinks fit for performing the 
    functions under this Act, and such sums shall be treated as expenditure 
    payable out of the grants referred to in sub-section (1).
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Grants by State Governments.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall, after due appropriation made by Legislature by 
    law in this behalf, pay to the State Commission by way of grants such sums 
    of money as the State Government may think fit for being utilised for the 
    purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    State Commission may spend such sums of money as it thinks fit for 
    performing the functions under Chapter III of this Act, and such sums shall 
    be treated as expenditure payable out of the grants referred to in 
    sub-section (1).
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>29</number> 
    Accounts and audit of Commission.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Commission shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
    prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by 
    the Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the Commission shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General at such intervals as may be specified by him and any 
    expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
    Commission to the Comptroller and Auditor-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General and any person appointed by him in 
    connection with the audit of the accounts of the Commission under this Act 
    shall, have the same rights and privileges and the authority in connection 
    with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor-General generally has in 
    connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in particular, shall 
    have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected 
    vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of 
    the Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number>
The accounts of the Commission as certified by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General or any other person appointed by him in this behalf, 
    together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the 
    Central Government by the Commission and the Central Government shall cause 
    the audit report to be laid, as soon as may be after it is received, before 
    each House of Parliament.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Accounts and audit of State Commission.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Commission shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant 
    records and prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be 
    prescribed by the State Government in consultation with the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General of India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    accounts of the State Commission shall be audited by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General at such intervals as may be specified by him and any 
    expenditure incurred in connection with such audit shall be payable by the 
    State Commission to the Comptroller and Auditor-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Comptroller and Auditor-General and any person appointed by him in 
    connection with the audit of the accounts of the State Commission under this 
    Act shall, have the same rights and privileges and the authority in 
    connection with such audit as the Comptroller and Auditor-General generally 
    has in connection with the audit of Government accounts and, in particular, 
    shall have the right to demand the production of books, accounts, connected 
    vouchers and other documents and papers and to inspect any of the offices of 
    the State Commission.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    accounts of the State Commission as certified by the Comptroller and 
    Auditor-General or any other person appointed by him in this behalf, 
    together with the audit report thereon shall be forwarded annually to the 
    State Government by the State Commission and the State Government shall 
    cause the audit report to be laid, as soon as may be after it is received, 
    before the State Legislature.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>31</number> 
    Protection of action taken in good faith.-No 
    suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Central 
    Government, the State Government, the Commission, the State Commission, or 
    any Member thereof or any person acting under the direction either of the 
    Central Government, State Government, Commission or the State Commission, in 
    respect of anything which is in good faith done or intended to be done in 
    pursuance of this Act or of any rules made thereunder or in respect of the 
    publication by or under the authority of the Central Government, State 
    Government, Commission, or the State Commission of any report or paper.
  



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> 
    Chairperson, Members and other officers to be public servant.-Every 
    Member of the Commission, State Commission and every officer appointed in 
    the Commission or the State Commission to exercise functions under this Act 
    shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 of 
    the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
  




  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> 
    Directions by Central Government.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    In the discharge of its functions under this Act, the Commission shall be 
    guided by such directions on questions of policy relating to national 
    purposes, as may be given to it by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If 
    any dispute arises between the Central Government and the Commission as to 
    whether a question is or is not a question of policy relating to national 
    purposes, the decision of the Central Government thereon shall be final.
 




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> 
    Returns or information.-The 
    Commission shall furnish to the Central Government such returns or other 
    information with respect to its activities as the Central Government may, 
    from time to time, require.



  


</article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
    Power of Central Government to make rules.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
    provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    terms and conditions of service of the 
    Chairperson and Members of the Commission and their salaries and allowances 
    under section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the procedure to be followed by the 
    Commission in the transaction of its business at a meeting under sub-section 
    (4) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the powers and duties which may be 
    exercised and performed by the Member-Secretary of the Commission under 
    sub-section (2) of  
    section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the salary and allowances and other 
    terms and conditions of service of officers and other employees of the 
    Commission under sub-section (3) of section 11; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    form of the statement of accounts and 
    other records to be prepared by the Commission under sub-section (1) of 
    section 29.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
    made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
    more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
    immediately following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both 
    Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree 
    that the rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only 
    in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
    that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
    validity of anything previously done under that rule.
  



  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> 
    Power of State Government to make rules.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
    provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:-
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    terms and conditions of service of the 
    Chairperson and Members of the State Commission and their salaries and 
    allowances under  
    section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    the procedure to be followed by the 
    State Commission in the transaction of its business at a meeting under 
    sub-section (4) of section 10 read with section 24;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    the powers and duties which may be 
    exercised and performed by the Secretary of the State Commission 
    under sub-section (2) of section 21; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    the salary and allowances and other 
    terms and conditions of service of officers and other employees of the State 
    Commission under sub-section (3) of section 21; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    form of the statement of accounts and 
    other records to be prepared by the State Commission under sub-section (1) 
    of section 30.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made by the State Government under this section shall be laid, as 
    soon as may be after it is made before each House of the State Legislature 
    where it consists of two Houses, or where such State Legislature consists of 
    one House, before that House.
  




  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> 
    Power to remove difficulties.-
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may 
    appear to be necessary for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided 
    that no order shall be made under this section after the expiry of the 
    period of two years from the date of commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every order made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
    it is made, before each House of Parliament.
  



  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 15th February, 2007, vide S.O. 229(E), dated 15-2-2007.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number>   Subs. by Act 4 
    of 2007, sec. 2, for the words "Minister-in-charge of the Ministry of Human 
    Resource Development" (w.e.f. 29-12-2006).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>