<act><tid>506831</tid>
<title>THE ANTI- CORRUPTION LAWS (AMENDMENT) ACT, <year>1967</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1967</year>
[ 25th June, <year>1967</year>.]

An Act further to amend the anti- corruption laws.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Eighteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>970419</tid>
<number> 1</number> 
<section><tid>1060406</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title and commencement. This Act may be called the  
Anti- Corruption Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>1967</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>189171</tid>
<number>2</number>It shall be deemed to have come into force on the 5th day 
of May, <year>1967</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>487595</tid>
<number> 2</number> 
<section><tid>704272</tid>
<number>1</number>Amendment of anti- corruption law in relation to  
certain pending trials. Notwithstanding-

<subsection><tid>1935616</tid>
<number>a</number>the substitution of new provisions for sub- section (3) 
of section 5 of the Prevention of Corruption Act, <year>1947</year> (2 of  
  <year>1947</year>). (hereinafter referred to as the 1947-Act) by section 
6 (2)  (c) of the Anti- Corruption Laws (Amendment) Act, <year>1964</year> (40  
  of <year>1964</year>). (hereinafter referred to as the 1964-Act); and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>852496</tid>
<number>b</number>any judgment or order of any court,
the said sub- section (3) as it stood immediately before the com- 
mencement of the 1964-Act, shall apply and shall be deemed always to 
have applied to and in relation to trials of offences punishable under 
sub- section (2) of section 5 of the 1947-Act pending before any court 
immediately before such commencement as if no such new provisions had 
been substituted for the said sub- section (3).


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>513614</tid>
<number>2</number>The accused person in any trial to and in relation to which 
sub- section (1) applies may, at the earliest opportunity available to 
him after the commencement of this Act, demand that the trial of the 
offence should proceed from the stage at which it was immediately 
before the commencement of the 1964-Act and on any such demand being 
made the court shall proceed with the trial from that stage.

</section>

<section><tid>1098380</tid>
<number>3</number>For the removal of doubt it is hereby provided that any 
court-

<subsection><tid>106166</tid>
<number>i</number>before which an appeal or application for revision 
against any judgment, order or sentence passed or made in any 
trial to which sub- section (1) applies is pending immediately 
before the commencement of this Act, or

<pagefootnote><pagenum>760</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1388078</tid>
<number>ii</number>before which an appeal or application for revision 
against any judgment, order or sentence passed or made before 
the commencement of this Act in any such trial, is filed 
after such commencement,
shall remand the case for trial in conformity with the provisions of 
this section.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1086111</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>1351755</tid>
<number>1</number>Repeal and saving. The Anti- Corruption Laws (Amendment)  
Ordinance, <year>1967</year> (3 of <year>1967</year>) is hereby repealed.

</section>

<section><tid>1952682</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or any action 
taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done or 
taken under this Act.


</section>

</article>



 </act>