<act><title>THE PROTECTION OF PLANT VARIETIES AND FARMERS 
RIGHTS (CRITERIA FOR DISTINCTIVENESS, UNIFORMITY AND STABILITY FOR REGISTRATION) 
REGULATIONS, 20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number>Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> These Regulations may 
be called the Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers Rights (Criteria for 
Distinctiveness, Uniformity and Stability for Registration) Regulations, 2009. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date of their publication 
in the Official Gazette. 
 ______________
 </section></article><article><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 452(E), dated 29th June, 2009, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3
<section><number>i</number>, dated 30th June, 2009. 
 <subsection><number>3</number> Came into force on 30-6-2009 . 
  
  </subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number>Definitions. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In these regulations, unless the context 
otherwise requires, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "Act" means the Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers' Rights Act, 
  2001; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "Journal" means the Plant Variety Journal of India; </subsection>(2) 
All other words and expressions used in these regulations and not defined, but 
defined in the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
Act. 
 ______________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 452(E), dated 29th June, 2009, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 30th June, 2009. 
  
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> </title>The Protection of Plant Varieties and Farmers Rights 
Authority shall, develop and publish in the Journal guidelines for the 
distinctiveness, uniformity and stability test for each crop 
 ______________
 <section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 452(E), dated 29th June, 2009, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 30th June, 2009. 
  
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Criteria of Distinctiveness, Uniformity and Stability for 
registration of variety about which there is Common Knowledge. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The 
criteria for distinctiveness, uniformity and stability for registration of a 
variety about which there is a common knowledge shall be determined by 
conducting a field test for one season at two locations for the purpose of 
confirming the distinctiveness, uniformity and stability following the 
descriptors and plot size as may be specified in the Journal. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person who applies for registration under clause (b) of Section 14 of 
the Act shall submit half the quantity of seeds as divided into five equal 
numbers of packets for the purpose of field test and also for storing in the 
National Gene Bank and the seed supply procedures shall be such as may be 
specified in the Journal. 
 ______________
 </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 452(E), dated 29th June, 2009, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 30th June, 2009. 
  
  </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number>Criteria of Distinctiveness, Uniformity and Stability for 
registration of farmers' variety. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Any person who applies for 
registration under clause (c) of Section 14 of the Act shall submit half the 
quantity of seeds as divided into five equal numbers of packets for the purpose 
of field test and also for storing in the National Gene Bank and the seed supply 
procedures shall be such as may be specified in the Journal. 
 
 
 ______________
 </section><section><number>2</number> Wherever the distinctiveness of the variety is required to be verified, 
  field test will be conducted for distinctiveness, uniformity and stability in 
  the test Centres. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The farmers' variety along with example variety and any other similar 
  variety shall be evaluated in the paired row test. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The length of the row and plant population shall be such as may be 
  specified in the Journal. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> It shall be a replicated trial and will be conducted for one season at 
  two locations for the limited purpose of confirming the distinctiveness, 
  following the descriptors such as may be specified in the Journal. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The uniformity levels for Farmers' variety for the respective species 
  shall not exceed double the number of off-types such as may be specified in 
  the Journal. 
 Provided that the number of permitted off-types for each crop shall be 
  developed and published in the Journal. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> If the variety meets the uniformity criteria, it shall be deemed to 
  have met the stability criteria. </section><section><number>1</number> Vide G.S.R. 452(E), dated 29th June, 2009, published 
in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 30th June, 2009. 
  
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>