<act><title>


The Insurance Regulatory and development 
Authority Act, 1999 </title> 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent 
and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 
1999.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the 
whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into 
force on such date,1
as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint:
 
Provided that different 
dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act and any reference in 
any such provision to the commencement of this Act shall be construed as a 
reference to the coming into force of that provision.
 
 



</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  “appointed 
day” means the date on which the Authority is established under sub-section (1) 
of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  “Authority” 
means the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority established under 
sub-section (1) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  “Chairperson” 
means the Chairperson of the Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  “Fund” means 
the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Fund constituted under 
sub-section (1) of section 16;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  “Interim 
Insurance Regulatory Authority” means the Insurance Regulatory Authority set up 
by the Central Government through Resolution No. 17(2)/94-Ins.-V, dated the 23rd 
January, 1996;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  
“intermediary or insurance intermediary” includes insurance brokers, 
re-insurance brokers, insurance consultants, surveyors and loss assessors;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  “member” 
means a whole-time or a part-time member of the Authority and includes the 
Chairperson;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  
“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  “prescribed” 
means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  
“regulations” means the regulations made by the Authority.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions 
used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 
1938) or the Life Insurance Corporation Act, 1956 (31 of 1956) or the General 
Insurance Business (Nationalisation) Act, 1972 (57 of 1972) shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Establishment and 
incorporation of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
With effect from such date as the Central Government may, by notification, 
appoint, there shall be established, for the purposes of this Act, an Authority 
to be called “the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority shall be 
a body corporate by the name aforesaid having perpetual succession and a common 
seal with power, subject to the provisions of this Act, to acquire, hold and 
dispose of property, both movable and immovable, and to contract and shall, by 
the said name, sue or be sued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The head office of the 
Authority shall be at such place as the Central Government may decide from time 
to time.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Authority may 
establish offices at other places in India.


</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Composition of 
Authority.—The 
Authority shall consist of the following members, namely:—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  a 
Chairperson;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  not more than 
five whole-time members;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  not more than 
four part-time members,
 
to be appointed by the 
Central Government from amongst persons of ability, integrity and standing who 
have knowledge or experience in life insurance, general insurance, actuarial 
science, finance, economics, law, accountancy, administration or any other 
discipline which would, in the opinion of the Central Government, be useful to 
the Authority:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government shall, while appointing the Chairperson and the whole-time members, 
ensure that at least one person each is a person having knowledge or experience 
in life insurance, general insurance or actuarial science, respectively.


</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>5</number> Tenure of office of 
Chairperson and other members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson and every other whole-time member shall hold office for a term 
of five years from the date on which he enters upon his office and shall be 
eligible for reappointment:
 
Provided that no person 
shall hold office as a Chairperson after he has attained the age of sixty-five 
years:
 
Provided further that no 
person shall hold office as a whole-time member after he has attained the age of 
sixty-two years.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A part-time member 
shall hold office for a term not exceeding five years from the date on which he 
enters upon his office.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in sub-section (1) or sub-section (2), a member may—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  relinquish 
his office by giving in writing to the Central Government notice of not less 
than three months; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  be removed 
from his office in accordance with the provisions of section 6.


</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>6</number> Removal from office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may remove from office any member who—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  is, or at any 
time has been, adjudged as an insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  has become 
physically or mentally incapable of acting as a member; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  has been 
convicted of any offence which, in the opinion of the Central Government, 
involves moral turpitude; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  has acquired 
such financial or other interest as is likely to affect prejudicially his 
functions as a member; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  has so abused 
his position as to render his continuation in office detrimental to the public 
interest.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No such member shall 
be removed under clause (d) or clause (e) of sub-section (l) unless he has been 
given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter.


</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>7</number> Salary and 
allowances of Chairperson and members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The salary and allowances payable to, and other terms and conditions of service 
of, the members other than part-time members shall be such as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The part-time members 
shall receive such allowances as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The salary, allowances 
and other conditions of service of a member shall not be varied to his 
disadvantage after appointment.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>8</number> Bar on future 
employment of members.—The 
Chairperson and the whole-time members shall not, for a period of two years from 
the date on which they cease to hold office as such, except with the previous 
approval of the Central Government, accept—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  any 
employment either under the Central Government or under any State Government; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  any 
appointment in any company in the insurance sector.


</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>9</number> Administrative 
powers of Chairperson.—The 
Chairperson shall have the powers of general superintendence and direction in 
respect of all administrative matters of the Authority.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>10</number> Meetings of 
Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall meet at such time and places and shall observe such rules 
and procedures in regard to transaction of business at its meetings (including 
quorum at such meetings) as may be determined by regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson, or if 
for any reason he is unable to attend a meeting of the Authority, any other 
member chosen by the members present from amongst themselves at the meeting, 
shall preside at the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All questions which 
come up before any meeting of the Authority shall be decided by a majority of 
votes by the members present and voting, and in the event of an equality of 
votes, the Chairperson, or in his absence, the person presiding shall have a 
second or casting vote.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Authority may make 
regulations for the transaction of business at its meetings.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>11</number> Vacancies, etc., 
not to invalidate proceedings of Authority.—No 
act or proceeding of the Authority shall be invalid merely by reason of—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  any vacancy 
in, or any defect in the constitution of, the Authority; or
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  any defect in 
the appointment of a person acting as a member of the Authority; or
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  any 
irregularity in the procedure of the Authority not affecting the merits of the 
case.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>12</number> Officers and 
employees of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority may appoint officers and such other employees as it considers 
necessary for the efficient discharge of its functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The terms and other 
conditions of service of officers and other employees of the Authority appointed 
under sub-section (1) shall be governed by regulations made under this Act.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>13</number> Transfer of assets, 
liabilities, etc., of Interim Insurance Regulatory  Authority.—On 
the appointed day,—
 <section>
        <number>a</number>  all the 
assets and liabilities of the Interim Insurance Regulatory Authority shall stand 
transferred to, and vested in, the Authority;
 
              
               Explanation.—The 
assets of the Interim Insurance Regulatory Authority shall be deemed to include 
all rights and powers, and all properties, whether movable or immovable, 
including, in particular, cash balances, deposits and all other interests and 
rights in, or arising out of, such properties as may be in the possession of the 
Interim Insurance Regulatory Authority and all books of account and other 
documents relating to the same; and liabilities shall be deemed to include all 
debts, liabilities and obligations of whatever kind;
 </section><section>
        <number>b</number>  without 
prejudice to the provisions of clause (a), all debts, obligations and 
liabilities incurred, all contracts entered into and all matters and things 
engaged to be done by, with or for the Interim Insurance Regulatory Authority 
immediately before that day, for or in connection with the purpose of the said 
Regulatory Authority, shall be deemed to have been incurred, entered into or 
engaged to be done by, with or for, the Authority;
 </section><section>
        <number>c</number>  all sums of 
money due to the Interim Insurance Regulatory Authority immediately before that 
day shall be deemed to be due to the Authority; and
 </section><section>
        <number>d</number>  all suits and 
other legal proceedings instituted or which could have been instituted by or 
against the Interim Insurance Regulatory Authority immediately before that day 
may be continued or may be instituted by or against the Authority.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>14</number> Duties, powers and 
functions of Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this Act and any other law for the time being in 
force, the Authority shall have the duty to regulate, promote and ensure orderly 
growth of the insurance business and re-insurance business.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
the generality of the provisions contained in sub-section (1), the powers and 
functions of the Authority shall include,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  issue to the 
applicant a certificate of registration, renew, modify, withdraw, suspend or 
cancel such registration;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  protection of 
the interests of the policy-holders in matters concerning assigning of policy, 
nomination by policy-holders, insurable interest, settlement of insurance claim, 
surrender value of policy, and other terms and conditions of contracts of 
insurance;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  specifying 
requisite qualifications, code of conduct and practical training for 
intermediary or insurance intermediaries and agents;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  specifying 
the code of conduct for surveyors and loss assessors;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  promoting 
efficiency in the conduct of insurance business;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  promoting 
and regulating professional organisations connected with the insurance and 
re-insurance business;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  levying fees 
and other charges for carrying out the purposes of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>h</number>  calling for 
information from, undertaking inspection of, conducting enquiries and 
investigations including audit of the insurers, intermediaries, insurance 
intermediaries and other organisations connected with the insurance business;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>i</number>  control and 
regulation of the rates, advantages, terms and conditions that may be offered by 
insurers in respect of general insurance business not so controlled and 
regulated by the Tariff Advisory Committee undersection 64U of the Insurance 
Act, 1938 (4 of 1938);
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>j</number>  specifying 
the form and manner in which books of account shall be maintained and statement 
of accounts shall be rendered by insurers and other insurance intermediaries;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>k</number>  regulating 
investment of funds by insurance companies;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>l</number>  regulating 
maintenance of margin of solvency;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>m</number>  adjudication 
of disputes between insurers and intermediaries or insurance intermediaries;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>n</number>  supervising 
the functioning of the Tariff Advisory Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>o</number>  specifying 
the percentage of premium income of the insurer to finance schemes for promoting 
and regulating professional organisations referred to in clause (f);
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>p</number>  specifying 
the percentage of life insurance business and general insurance business to be 
undertaken by the insurer in the rural or social sector; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>q</number>  exercising 
such other powers as may be prescribed.
</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>15</number> Grants by Central 
Government.—The 
Central Government may, after due appropriation made by the Parliament by law in 
this behalf, make to the Authority grants of such sums of money as the 
Government may think fit for being utilised for the purposes of this Act.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>16</number> Constitution of 
Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> There 
shall be constituted a fund to be called “the Insurance Regulatory and 
Development Authority Fund” and there shall be credited thereto—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  all 
Government grants, fees and charges received by the Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  all sums 
received by the Authority from such other source as may be decided upon by the 
Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the 
percentage of prescribed income received from the insurer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Fund shall be 
applied for meeting—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the salaries, 
allowances and other remuneration of the members, officers and other employees 
of the Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the other 
expenses of the Authority in connection with the discharge of its functions and 
for the purposes of this Act.
</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>17</number> Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall maintain proper accounts and other relevant records and 
prepare an annual statement of accounts in such form as may be prescribed by the 
Central Government in consultation with the Comptroller and Auditor-General of 
India.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The accounts of the 
Authority shall be audited by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India at 
such intervals as may be specified by him and any expenditure incurred in 
connection with such audit shall be payable by the Authority to the Comptroller 
and Auditor-General.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Comptroller and 
Auditor-General of India and other person appointed by him in connection with 
the audit of the accounts of the Authority shall have the same rights and 
privileges and authority in connection with such audit as the Comptroller and 
Auditor-General generally has in connection with the audit of the Government 
accounts and, in particular, shall have the right to demand the production of 
books of account, connected vouchers and other documents and papers and to 
inspect any of the offices of the Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The accounts of the 
Authority as certified by the Comptroller and Auditor-General of India or any 
other person appointed by him in this behalf together with the audit report 
thereon shall be forwarded annually to the Central Government and that 
Government shall cause the same to be laid before each House of Parliament.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>18</number> Power of Central 
Government to issue directions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to the foregoing provisions of this Act, the Authority shall, 
in exercise of its powers or the performance of its functions under this Act, be 
bound by such directions on questions of policy, other than those relating to 
technical and administrative matters, as the Central Government may give in 
writing to it from time to time:
 
Provided that the 
Authority shall, as far as practicable, be given an opportunity to express its 
views before any direction is given under this sub-section.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The decision of the 
Central Government, whether a question is one of policy or not, shall be final.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>19</number> Power of Central 
Government to supersede Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If, at any time the Central Government is of the opinion—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  that, on 
account of circumstances beyond the control of the Authority, it is unable to 
discharge the functions or perform the duties imposed on it by or under the 
provisions of this Act; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  that the 
Authority has persistently defaulted in complying with any direction given by 
the Central Government under this Act or in the discharge of the functions or 
performance of the duties imposed on it by or under the provisions of this Act 
and as a result of such default the financial position of the Authority or the 
administration of the Authority has suffered; or
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  that 
circumstances exist which render it necessary in the public interest so to do,
 
the Central Government 
may, by notification and for reasons to be specified therein, supersede the 
Authority for such period, not exceeding six months, as may be specified in the 
notification and appoint a person to be the Controller of Insurance under 
section 2B of the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938), if not already done:
 
Provided that before 
issuing any such notification, the Central Government shall give a reasonable 
opportunity to the Authority to make representations against the proposed 
supersession and shall consider the representations, if any, of the Authority.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon the publication 
of a notification under sub-section (1) superseding the Authority,—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the 
Chairperson and other members shall, as from the date of supersession, vacate 
their offices as such;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  all the 
powers, functions and duties which may, by or under the provisions of this Act, 
be exercised or discharged by or on behalf of the Authority shall, until the 
Authority is reconstituted under sub-section (3), be exercised and discharged by 
the Controller of Insurance; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  all 
properties owned or controlled by the Authority shall, until the Authority is 
reconstituted under sub-section (3), vest in the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On or before the 
expiration of the period of supersession specified in the notification issued 
under sub-section (1), the Central Government shall reconstitute the Authority 
by a fresh appointment of its Chairperson and other members and in such case any 
person who had vacated his office under clause (a) of sub-section (2) shall not 
be deemed disqualified for re-appointment.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Central Government 
shall cause a copy of the notification issued under sub-section (1) and a full 
report of any action taken under this section and the circumstances leading to 
such action to be laid before each House of Parliament at the earliest.


</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>20</number> Furnishing of 
returns, etc., to Central Government.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority shall furnish to the Central Government at such time and in such 
form and manner as may be prescribed, or as the Central Government may direct to 
furnish such returns, statements and other particulars in regard to any proposed 
or existing programme for the promotion and development of the insurance 
industry as the Central Government may, from time to time, require.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to 
the provisions of sub-section (1), the Authority shall, within nine months after 
the close of each financial year, submit to the Central Government a report 
giving a true and full account of its activities including the activities for 
promotion and development of the insurance business during the previous 
financial year.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Copies of the reports 
received under sub-section (2) shall be laid, as soon as may be after they are 
received, before each House of Parliament.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>21</number> Chairperson, members, officers 
and other employees of Authority to be public servants.—The Chairperson, members, 
officers and other employees of the Authority shall be deemed, when acting or 
purporting to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act, to be 
public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 
1860).</article> 

  
 <article><number>22</number> Protection of action taken in 
good faith.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceedings shall lie against the Central 
Government or any officer of the Central Government or any member, officer or 
other employee of the Authority for anything which is in good faith done or 
intended to be done under this Act or the rules or regulations made 
thereunder:
 Provided that nothing in this Act 
shall exempt any person from any suit or other proceedings which might, apart 
from this Act, be brought against him.</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>23</number> Delegation of 
powers.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Authority may, by general or special order in writing, delegate to the 
Chairperson or any other member or officer of the Authority subject to such 
conditions, if any, as may be specified in the order, such of its powers and 
functions under this Act as it may deem necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Authority may, by 
a general or special order in writing, also form Committees of the members and 
delegate to them the powers and functions of the Authority as may be specified 
by the regulations.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>24</number> Power to make 
rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the salary 
and allowances payable to, and other terms and conditions of service of the 
members other than part-time members under sub-section (1) of section 7;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the 
allowances to be paid to the part-time members under sub-section (2) of section 
7;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  such other 
powers that may be exercised by the Authority under clause (q) of sub-section 
(2) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the form of 
annual statement of accounts to be maintained by the Authority under sub-section 
(1) of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  the form and 
the manner in which and the time within which returns and statements and 
particulars are to be furnished to the Central Government under sub-section (1) 
of section 20;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  the matters 
under sub-section (5) of section 25 on which the Insurance Advisory Committee 
shall advise the Authority;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>g</number>  any other 
matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed, or in respect of which 
provision is to be or may be made by rules.
</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>25</number> Establishment of 
Insurance Advisory Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority may, by notification, establish with effect from such date as it 
may specify in such notification, a Committee to be known as the Insurance 
Advisory Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Insurance Advisory 
Committee shall consist of not more than twenty-five members excluding 
ex-officio members to represent the interests of commerce, industry, 
transport, agriculture, consumer fora, surveyors, agents, intermediaries, 
organisations engaged in safety and loss prevention, research bodies and 
employees’ association in the insurance sector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson and 
the members of the Authority shall be the ex-officio Chairperson and 
ex-officio members of the Insurance Advisory Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The objects of the 
Insurance Advisory committee shall be to advise the Authority on matters 
relating to the making of the regulations under section 26.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Without prejudice to 
the provisions of sub-section (4), the Insurance Advisory Committee may advise 
the Authority on such other matters as may be prescribed.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>26</number> Power to make 
regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Authority may, in consultation with the Insurance Advisory Committee, by 
notification, make regulations consistent with this Act and the rules made 
thereunder to carry out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and 
without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may 
provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
        <number>a</number>  the time and 
places of meetings of the Authority and the procedure to be followed at such 
meetings including the quorum necessary for the transaction of business under 
sub-section (1) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>b</number>  the 
transaction of business at its meetings under sub-section (4) of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>c</number>  the terms and 
other conditions of service of officers and other employees of the Authority 
under sub-section (2) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>d</number>  the powers 
and functions which may be delegated to Committees of the members under 
sub-section (2) of section 23; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>e</number>  any other 
matter which is required to be, or may be, specified by regulations or in 
respect of which provision is to be or may be made by regulations.
</subsection></section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>27</number> Rules and 
regulations to be laid before Parliament.—Every 
rule and every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be 
after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a 
total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or 
more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter 
have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>28</number> Application of 
other laws not barred.—The 
provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, the 
provisions of any other law for the time being in force.
</article> 

 

 <article>
<number>29</number> Power to remove 
difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as may appear to be 
necessary for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no order 
shall be made under this section after the expiry of two years from the 
appointed day.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under 
this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each 
House of Parliament.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>30</number> Amendment of Act 4 of 
1938.—The 
Insurance Act, 1938 shall be amended in the manner specified in the First 
Schedule to this Act.</article> 

  
 <article><number>31</number> Amendment of Act 31 of 
1956.—The Life 
Insurance Corporation Act, 1956 shall be amended in the manner specified in the 
Second Schedule to this Act.</article> 

  
 <article><number>32</number> Amendment of Act 57 of 
1972.—The General 
Insurance Business (Nationalisation) Act, 1972 shall be amended in the manner 
specified in the Third Schedule to this Act.
  </article><form>
 

The 
Insurance Regulatory and development  
Authority Act, 1999 
 

 
 

The 
First Schedule
 

(See 
section 30)
 

Amendments 
to The Insurance Act, 1938
 

(4 of 
1938)
 

1. In the Act, except in clause 
(5B) of section 2 and section 2B, for “Controller” wherever it occurs, 
substitute “Authority” and such consequential changes as the rules of grammar 
may require shall also be made;
 

2. In sections 27, 27A, 27B, 31, 
32A, 40A, 48B, 64F, 64G, 64-I, 64J, 64L, 64R, 64UC, 64UM, 113 and 115, for 
“Central Government” wherever they occur, substitute “Authority”;
 

3. Section 2,—
 

(a)  after clause (1) insert 
the following:—
 

                  
‘(lA)“Authority” means the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority 
established under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Insurance Regulatory and 
Development Authority Act, 1999;’,
 

(b)  for clause (5B), 
substitute the following:—
 

                  
“(5B) “Controller of Insurance” means the officer appointed by the Central 
Government under section 2B to exercise all the powers, discharge the functions 
and perform the duties of the Authority under this Act or the Life Insurance 
Corporation Act, 1956 (31 of 1956) or the General Insurance Business 
(Nationalisation) Act, 1972 (57 of 1972) or the Insurance Regulatory and 
Development Authority Act, 1999;’,
 

(c)  after clause (7), insert 
the following:—
 

                  
‘(7A) “Indian insurance company” means any insurer being a company—
 

           
(a)   which is formed and registered under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 
of 1956);
 

           
(b)   in which the aggregate holdings of equity shares by a foreign 
company, either by itself or through its subsidiary companies or its nominees, 
do not exceed twenty-six per cent. paid-up equity capital of such Indian 
insurance company;
 

           
(c)   whose sole purpose is to carry on life insurance business or 
general insurance business or re-insurance business.
 


Explanation.—For the 
purposes of this clause, the expression “foreign company” shall have the meaning 
assigned to it under clause (23A) of section 2 of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 
of 1961);’;
 

           
(d)   in clause (14) for “section 114”, substitute “this 
Act”.
 

4. After section 2, insert the 
following:—
 

            
“2A. Interpretation of certain words and expressions.—Words and 
expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the Life Insurance 
Corporation Act, 1956 (31 of 1956), the General Insurance Business 
(Nationalisation) Act, 1972 (57 of 1972), and the Insurance Regulatory and 
Development Authority Act, 1999 shall have the meanings respectively assigned to 
them in those Acts.”.
 

5. Section 2B, for sub-section (1), 
substitute the following:—
 

            
“(1) If at any time, the Authority is superseded under sub-section (1) of 
section 19 of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999, the 
Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint a 
person to be the Controller of Insurance till such time the Authority is 
reconstituted under sub-section (3) of section 19 of that Act.”;
 

6. Section 2C, in sub-section (1), 
after the second proviso, insert the following:—
 

            
“Provided also that no insurer other than an Indian insurance company shall 
begin to carry on any class of insurance business in India under this Act on or 
after the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority 
Act, 1999.”;
 

7. Section 3,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), after 
the first proviso, insert the following:—
 

                        
“Provided further that a person or insurer, as the case may be, carrying on any 
class of insurance business in India, on or before the commencement of the 
Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999, for which no 
registration certificate was necessary prior to such commencement, may continue 
to do so for a period of three months from such commencement or, if he had made 
an application for such registration within the said period of three months, 
till the disposal of such application:
 

                  
Provided also that any certificate of registration, obtained immediately before 
the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 
1999, shall be deemed to have been obtained from the Authority in accordance 
with the provisions of this Act.”;
 

(b)  in sub-section 
(2)—
 

             
(i)  in the opening portion, for “Every application for registration shall 
be accompanied by—”, substitute the following:—
 

                  
“Every application for registration shall be made in such manner as may be 
determined by the regulations made by the Authority and shall be accompanied 
by—”;
 

            
(ii)  in clause (d) for “working capital”, substitute “paid-up equity 
capital or working capital”;
 

           
(iii)  in clause (f) in the proviso, omit “and” occurring at the 
end;
 

           
(iv)  for clause (g) substitute the following:—
 

         
“(g)   the receipt showing payment of fee as may be determined by 
regulations which shall not exceed fifty thousand rupees for each class of 
business as may be specified by regulations made by the Authority;
 

           
(h)   such other documents as may be specified by the regulations made 
by the Authority;”;
 

(c)  after sub-section (2A), 
insert—
 

                        
“(2AA) The Authority shall give preference to register the applicant and grant 
him a certificate of registration if such applicant agrees, in the form and 
manner as may be specified by the regulations made by the Authority, to carry on 
the life insurance business or general insurance business for providing health 
cover to individuals or group of individuals.”;
 

(d)  in sub-section 
(4),—
 

             
(i)  in clause (f), for “of any rule or order made thereunder, or”, 
substitute the following:—
 

                  
“of any rule or any regulation or order made or, any direction issued 
thereunder, or”;
 

            
(ii)  in clause (h) insert “or” at the end;
 

           
(iii)  after clause (h) insert the following:—
 

          
“(i)   if the insurer makes a default in complying with any direction 
issued or order made, as the case may be, by the Authority under the Insurance 
Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999, or
 

            
(j)   if the insurer makes a default in complying with, or acts in 
contravention of, any requirement of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or the 
Life Insurance Corporation Act, 1956 (31 of 1956) or the General Insurance 
Business (Nationalisation) Act, 1972 (57 of 1972) or the Foreign Exchange 
Regulation Act, 1973 (46 of 1973),”;
 

(e)  in sub-section 
(5C),—
 

             
(i)  for “clause (h)”, substitute “clause (h) or clause (i) or clause 
(j)”;
 

            
(ii)  for “any requirement of this Act or of any rule or order made 
thereunder” substitute the following:—
 

                  
“any requirement of this Act or the Insurance Regulatory and Development 
Authority Act, 1999 or of any rule or any regulation, or any order made 
thereunder or any direction issued under those Acts”;
 

(f)   after sub-section 
(5D), insert the following:—
 

                        
“(5E) The Authority may, by order, suspend or cancel any registration in such 
manner as may be determined by the regulations made by it:
 

                        
Provided that no order under this sub-section shall be made unless the person 
concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.”;
 

(g)  for sub-section (7), 
substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(7) The Authority may, on payment of such fee, not exceeding five thousand 
rupees, as may be determined by the regulations, issue a duplicate certificate 
of registration to replace a certificate lost, destroyed or mutilated, or in any 
other case where the Authority is of opinion that the issue of duplicate 
certificate is necessary.”.
 

8. Section 3A,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“the 31st day of December, 1941,”, substitute the following:—
 

                  
“the 31st day of March, after the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and 
Development Authority Act, 1999.”;
 

(b)  in sub-section 
(2)—
 

             
(i)  for “prescribed fee”, substitute “fee as determined by regulations 
made by the Authority”;
 

            
(ii) for clause (i), substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(i) exceed one-fourth of one per cent. of such premium income or rupees five 
crores, whichever is less,”;
 

           
(iii) for clause (ii), substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(ii) be less, in any case, than fifty thousand rupees for each class of 
insurance business:”;
 

(c)  in sub-section (3) for 
“prescribed fee”, substitute “fee as determined by the regulations made by the 
Authority”;
 

(d)  in sub-section (4) for 
“prescribed fee”, substitute “fee as determined by the regulations made by the 
Authority, and”.
 

9. For section 6, substitute the 
following:—
 


                 
“6. Requirement as to capital.—No insurer carrying on the business of life 
insurance, general insurance, or re-insurance in India on or after the 
commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999, 
shall be registered unless he has,—
 

             
(i)  a paid-up equity capital of rupees one hundred crore, in case of a 
person carrying on the business of life insurance or general insurance; 
or
 

            
(ii)  a paid-up equity capital of rupees two hundred crore, in case of a 
person carrying on exclusively the business as a re-insurer:
 

                        
Provided that in determining the paid-up equity capital specified under clause 
(i) or clause (ii), the deposit to be made under section 7 and any preliminary 
expenses incurred in the formation and registration of the company shall be 
excluded:
 

                        
Provided further that an insurer carrying on business of life insurance, general 
insurance or re-insurance in India before the commencement of the Insurance 
Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 and who is required to be 
registered under this Act, shall have a paid-up equity capital in accordance 
with clause (i) and clause (ii), as the case may be, within six months of the 
commencement of that Act.”.
 

10. Section 6A,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (4), in 
clause (b),—
 

            
(I)  in sub-clause (i), omit “and” occurring at the end;
 

           
(II)  in sub-clause (ii) for “sanction of the Central Government has been 
obtained to the transfer.”, substitute “approval of the Authority has been 
obtained to the transfer,”; 
 

          
(III)  after sub-clause (ii), insert the following:—
 

         
“(iii)   where, the nominal value of the shares intended to be 
transferred by any individual, firm, group, constituents of a group, or body 
corporate under the same management, jointly or severally exceeds one per cent. 
of paid-up equity capital of the insurer, unless the previous approval of the 
Authority has been obtained for the transfer.
 

                        
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this sub-clause, the expressions “group” and “same management”, 
shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Monopolies and 
Restrictive Trade Practices Act, 1969 (54 of 1969).”;
 

(b)  in sub-section 
(11),—
 

             
(i)  for “Explanation 1”, substitute 
“Explanation”;
 

            
(ii)  omit Explanation 2;
 

11. After section 6A, insert the 
following:—
 

            
“6AA. Manner of divesting excess shareholding by promoter in certain 
cases.—(1) No promoter shall at any time hold more than twenty-six per cent. 
or such other percentage as may be prescribed, of the paid-up equity capital in 
an Indian insurance company:
 

            
Provided that in a case where an Indian insurance company begins the business of 
life insurance, general insurance or re-insurance in which the promoters hold 
more than twenty-six per cent. of the paid-up equity capital or such other 
excess percentage as may be prescribed, the promoters shall divest in a phased 
manner the share capital in excess of the twenty-six per cent. of the paid-up 
equity capital or such excess paid-up equity capital as may be prescribed, after 
a period of ten years from the date of the commencement of the said business by 
such Indian insurance company or within such period as may be prescribed by the 
Central Government.
 

            
Explanation.—For 
the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that nothing contained in proviso 
shall apply to the promoters being foreign company, referred to in sub-clause 
(b) of clause (7A) of section 2.
 

            
(2) The manner and procedure for divesting the excess share capital under 
sub-section (1) shall be specified by regulations made by the 
Authority.”.
 

12. Section 7,—
 

(a)  in sub-section 
(1),—
 

             
(i)  omit “not being an insurer specified in sub-clause (c) of clause (9) 
of section 2”;
 

            
(ii)  for clauses (a) and (b), substitute the following:—
 

         
“(a)   in the case of life insurance business, a sum equivalent to one 
per cent. of his total gross premium written in India in any financial year 
commencing after the 31st day of March, 2000, not exceeding rupees ten 
crore;
 

           
(b)   in the case of general insurance business, a sum equivalent to 
three per cent. of his total gross premium written in India, in any financial 
year commencing after the 31st day of March, 2000, not exceeding rupees ten 
crore;
 

           
(c)   in the case of re-insurance business, a sum of rupees twenty 
crore:”;
 

           
(b)  omit sub-sections (1A), (1B), (1C), (1D) and (1E).
 

13. Section 11,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“calendar year”, substitute “financial year”;
 

(b)  after sub-section (1), 
insert the following:—
 

                        
“(1A) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), every insurer, on 
or after the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority 
Act, 1999, in respect of insurance business transacted by him and in respect of 
his shareholders’ funds, shall at the expiration of each financial year prepare 
with reference to that year, a balance-sheet, a profit and loss account, a 
separate account of receipts and payments, a revenue account in accordance with 
the regulations made by the Authority.
 

                        
(1B) Every insurer shall keep separate accounts relating to funds of 
shareholders and policy-holders.”;
 

14. Section 13,—
 

(a)  in sub-section 
(1),—
 

             
(i)  for “once at least in every three years”, substitute “every 
year”;
 

            
(ii)  in the first proviso, for “not later than four years”, substitute 
“not later than two years”;
 

           
(iii)  after the second proviso, insert the following:—
 

                        
“Provided also that for an insurer carrying on life insurance business in India 
immediately before the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development 
Authority Act, 1999, the last date as at which the first investigation after 
such commencement should be caused by an actuary shall be the 31st day of March, 
2001:”;
 

           
(iv)  after third proviso, insert the following:—
 

                
        “Provided also that every insurer, on or 
after the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority 
Act, 1999, shall cause an abstract of the report of the actuary to be made in 
the manner specified by regulations made by the Authority.”;
 

(b)  in sub-section (4), after 
proviso, insert the following:—
 

                        
“Provided further that the statement referred to in sub-section (4) shall be 
appended in the form and in the manner specified by the regulations made by the 
Authority.”;
 

15. After section 27B,— insert the 
following:—
 

            
“27C. Prohibition for investment of funds outside India.—No insurer shall 
directly or indirectly invest outside India, the funds of the 
policy-holders.
 

            
27D. Manner and conditions of investment.—(1) Without prejudice to 
anything contained in sections 27, 27A and 27B, the Authority may, in the 
interests of the policy-holders, specify by the regulations made by it, the 
time, manner and other conditions of investment of assets to be held by an 
insurer for the purposes of this Act.
 

            
(2) The Authority may give specific directions for the time, manner and other 
conditions subject to which the funds of policy-holders shall be invested in the 
infrastructure and social sector as may be specified by regulations made by the 
Authority and such regulations shall apply uniformly to all the insurers 
carrying on the business of life insurance, general insurance, or re-insurance 
in India on or after the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and 
Development Authority Act, 1999.
 

            
(3) The Authority may, after taking into account the nature of business and to 
protect the interests of the policy-holders, issue to an insurer the directions 
relating to the time, manner, and other conditions of investment of assets to be 
held by him:
 

            
Provided that no direction under this sub-section shall be issued unless the 
insurer concerned has been given a reasonable opportunity of being 
heard.”.
 

16. Section 28A, in sub-section 
(1), for “31st day of December”, substitute “31st day of March”.
 

17. Section 28B, in sub-section (1) 
for “31st day of December”, substitute “31st day of March”.
 

18. Section 31B,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“Central Government” at both the places where they occur, substitute 
“Authority”;
 

(b)  in sub-section (2), for 
“a statement in the prescribed form”, substitute “a statement, in the form 
specified by the regulations made by the Authority,”;
 

(c)  after sub-section (3), 
insert the following:—
 

                        
“(4). Every direction under this section shall be issued by an order made by the 
Authority:
 

                        
Provided that no order under this section shall be made unless the person 
concerned has been given an opportunity of being heard.”.
 

19. After section 32A, insert the 
following:—
 

                
                    
“32B. Insurance business in rural or social sector.—Every insurer shall, after the 
commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999, 
undertake such percentages of life insurance business and general insurance 
business in the rural or social sector, as may be specified, in the Official 
Gazette by the Authority, in this behalf.”.
 


      “32C. Obligations of insurer in respect of 
rural or unorganised sector and backward classes.—Every insurer shall, after 
the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 
1999, discharge the obligations specified under section 32B to provide life 
insurance or general insurance policies to the persons residing in the rural 
sector, workers in the unorganised or informal sector or for economically 
vulnerable or backward classes of the society and other categories of persons as 
may specified by regulations made by the Authority and such insurance policies 
shall include insurance for crops.”.
 

20. For section 33, substitute the 
following:—
 

Investigation
 

            
33. Power of investigation and inspection by Authority.—(1) The Authority 
may, at any time, by order in writing, direct any person (hereafter in this 
section referred to as “Investigating Authority”) specified in the order to 
investigate the affairs of any insurer and to report to the Authority on any 
investigation made by such Investigating Authority:
 

            
Provided that the Investigating Authority may, wherever necessary, employ any 
auditor or actuary or both for the purpose of assisting him in any investigation 
under this section.
 

            
(2) Notwithstanding anything to the contrary contained in section 235 of the 
Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), the Investigating Authority may, at any time, 
and shall, on being directed so to do by the Authority, cause an inspection to 
be made by one or more of his officers of any insurer and his books of account; 
and the Investigating Authority shall supply to the insurer a copy of his report 
on such inspection.
 

            
(3) It shall be the duty of every manager, managing director or other officer of 
the insurer to produce before the Investigating Authority directed to make the 
investigation under sub-section (1), or inspection under sub-section (2), all 
such books of account, registers and other documents in his custody or power and 
to furnish him with any statement and information relating to the affairs of the 
insurer as the said Investigating Authority may require of him within such time 
as the said Investigating Authority may specify.
 

            
(4) Any Investigating Authority, directed to make an investigation under 
sub-section (1), or inspection under sub-section (2), may examine on oath, any 
manager, managing director or other officer of the insurer in relation to his 
business and may administer oaths accordingly.
 

            
(5) The Investigating Authority shall, if he has been directed by the Authority 
to cause an inspection to be made, and may, in any other case, report to the 
Authority on any inspection made under this section.
 

            
(6) On receipt of any report under sub-section (1) or sub-section (5), the 
Authority may, after giving such opportunity to the insurer to make a 
representation in connection with the report as, in the opinion of the 
Authority, seems reasonable, by order in writing,—
 

           
(a)   require the insurer, to take such action in respect of any matter 
arising out of the report as the Authority may think fit; or
 

           
(b)   cancel the registration of the insurer; or
 

           
(c)   direct any person to apply to the court for the winding up of the 
insurer, if a company, whether the registration of the insurer has been 
cancelled under clause (b) or not.
 

            
(7) The Authority may, after giving reasonable notice to the insurer, publish 
the report submitted by the Investigating Authority under sub-section (5) or 
such portion thereof as may appear to it to be necessary.
 

            
(8) The Authority may by the regulations made by it specify the minimum 
information to be maintained by insurers in their books, the manner in which 
such information shall be maintained, the checks and other verifications to be 
adopted by insurers in that connection and all other matters incidental thereto 
as are, in its opinion, necessary to enable the Investigating Authority to 
discharge satisfactorily his functions under this section.
 

            
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section, the expression “insurer” shall include in the case 
of an insurer incorporated in India—
 

           
(a)   all its subsidiaries formed for the purpose of carrying on the 
business of insurance exclusively outside India; and
 

           
(b)   all its branches whether situated in India or outside 
India.
 

            
(9) No order made under this section other than an order made under clause (b) 
of sub-section (6) shall be capable of being called in question in any 
court.
 

            
(10) All expenses of, and incidental to, any investigation made under this 
section shall be defrayed by the insurer, shall have priority over that debts 
due from the insurer and shall be recoverable as an arrear of land 
revenue.’.
 

21. Section 33A, omit “Central 
Government or the”.
 

22. Section 34H,—
 

(a)  in sub-section 
(1),—
 

             
(i)  for “Controller”, substitute, “Chairperson of the 
Authority”;
 

            
(ii)  for “an Assistant Controller of Insurance”, substitute “an officer 
authorised by the Authority”;
 

(b)  in sub-sections (5) and 
(7), for “Controller” wherever it occurs, substitute “ Chairperson of the 
Authority”;
 

23. Section 35,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“sanctioned by the Controller”, substitute “approved by the 
Authority”;
 

(b)  in sub-section 
(3),—
 

             
(i)  in the first paragraph, for “to sanction any such scheme”, substitute 
“to approve any such scheme”;
 

            
(ii)  in the second paragraph, for “the amalgamation or transfer if 
sanctioned”, substitute “the amalgamation or transfer if approved”;
 

24. Section 36,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“may sanction the arrangement”, substitute “may approve the 
arrangement”;
 

(b)  in sub-section 
(2),—
 

             
(i)  for “the insurers concerned in the amalgamation, the Controller may 
sanction”, substitute “the insurers concerned in the amalgamation, the Authority 
may approve”;
 

            
(ii)  for “contracts as sanctioned by the Controller”, substitute 
“contracts as approved by the Authority”.
 

25. Section 37, in clause (c), for 
“scheme sanctioned”, substitute “scheme approved”.
 

26. In section 40A, in sub-section 
(3), for the portion beginning with the words “an amount exceeding” and ending 
with the words “ten per cent. of the premium payable on the policy”, substitute 
“an amount not exceeding fifteen per cent. of the premium payable on the policy 
where the policy relates to fire or marine insurance or miscellaneous 
insurance.”.
 

27. Section 42,—
 

(a)  for sub-section (1), 
substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(1) The Authority or an officer authorised by it in this behalf shall, in the 
manner determined by the regulations made by it and on payment of the fee 
determined by the regulations, which shall not be more than two hundred and 
fifty rupees, issue to any person making an application in the manner determined 
by the regulations, a licence to act as an insurance agent for the purpose of 
soliciting or procuring insurance business:
 

                  
Provided that,—
 

            
(i)   in the case of an individual, he does not suffer from any of the 
disqualifications mentioned in sub-section (4); and
 

           
(ii)   in the case of a company or firm, any of its directors or 
partners does not suffer from any of the said disqualifications:
 

            
Provided further that any licence issued immediately before the commencement of 
the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 shall be deemed to 
have been issued in accordance with the regulations which provide for such 
licence.”;
 

(b)  for sub-section (3), 
substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(3) A licence issued under this section, after the date of the commencement of 
the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999, shall remain in 
force for a period of three years only from the date of issue, but shall, if the 
applicant, being an individual does not, or being a company or firm any of its 
directors or partners does not, suffer from any of the disqualifications 
mentioned in clauses (b), (c), (d), (e) and (f) of sub-section (4) and the 
application for renewal of licence reaches the issuing authority at least thirty 
days before the date on which the licence ceases to remain in force, be renewed 
for a period of three years at any one time on payment of the fee determined by 
regulations made by the Authority which shall not be more than rupees two 
hundred and fifty, and additional fee of an amount determined by the regulations 
not exceeding rupees one hundred by way of penalty, if the application for 
renewal of the licence does not reach the issuing authority at least thirty days 
before the date on which the licence ceases to remain in force.”;
 

(c)  in sub-section (3A), for 
the proviso, substitute the following:—
 

                        
“Provided that the Authority may, if satisfied that undue hardship would be 
caused otherwise, accept any application in contravention of this sub-section on 
payment by the applicant of a penalty of seven hundred and fifty 
rupees.”;
 

(d) in sub-section (4), after 
clause (d), insert the following:—
 

                        
“(e) that he does not possess the requisite qualifications and practical 
training for a period not exceeding twelve months, as may be specified by the 
regulations made by the Authority in this behalf;
 

                        
(f) that he has not passed such examination as may be specified by the 
regulations made by the Authority in this behalf:
 

                        
Provided that a person who had been issued a licence under sub-section (1) of 
this section or sub-section (1) of section 64UM shall not be required to possess 
the requisite qualifications, practical training and pass such examination as 
required by clauses (e) and (f);
 

                        
(g) that he violates the code of conduct as may be specified by the regulations 
made by the Authority.”;
 

(e)  for sub-section (6), 
substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(6) The Authority may issue a duplicate licence to replace a licence lost, 
destroyed or mutilated, on payment of such fee not exceeding fifty rupees as may 
be determined by the regulations.”;
 

(f)   in sub-section 
(7),—
 

             
(i)  for “fifty rupees”, substitute “five hundred rupees”;
 

            
(ii)  for “one hundred rupees”, substitute “one thousand 
rupees”;
 

(g)  in sub-section (8), for 
“fifty rupees”, substitute “five thousand rupees”.
 

28. Section 42A, in sub-section 
(1),—
 

(a)  for “Controller or an 
officer authorised by him”, substitute “Authority or an officer authorised by 
it”;
 

(b)  for “an application to 
him”, substitute “an application to it”.
 

29. After section 42C, insert the 
following:—
 

            
“42D. Issue of licence to intermediary or insurance intermediary.—(1) The 
Authority or an officer authorised by it in this behalf shall, in the manner 
determined by regulations made by the Authority and on payment of the fees 
determined by the regulations made by the Authority, issue to any person making 
an application in the manner determined by the regulations, and not suffering 
from any of the disqualifications herein mentioned, a licence to act as an 
intermediary or an insurance intermediary under this Act:
 

            
Provided that—
 

           
(a)   in the case of an individual, he does not suffer from any of the 
disqualifications mentioned in sub-section (4) of section 42, or
 

           
(b)   in the case of a company, or firm, any of its directors or 
partners does not suffer from any of the said disqualifications.
 

            
(2) A licence issued under this section shall entitle the holder thereof to act 
as an intermediary or insurance intermediary.
 

            
(3) A licence issued under this section shall remain in force for a period of 
three years only from the date of issue, but shall, if the applicant, being an 
individual does not, or being a company or firm any of its directors or partners 
does not suffer from any of the disqualifications mentioned in clauses (b), (c), 
(d), (e) and (f) of sub-section (4) of section 42 and the application of or 
renewal of licence reaches the issuing authority at least thirty days before the 
date on which the licence ceases to remain in force, be renewed for a period of 
three years at any one time on payment of the fee, determined by the regulations 
made by the Authority and additional fee for an amount determined by the 
regulations, not exceeding one hundred rupees by way of penalty, if the 
application for renewal of the licence does not reach the issuing authority at 
least thirty days before the date on which the licence ceases to remain in 
force.
 

            
(4) No application for the renewal of a licence under this section shall be 
entertained if the application does not reach the issuing authority before the 
licence ceases to remain in force:
 

            
Provided that the Authority may, if satisfied that undue hardship would be 
caused otherwise, accept any application in contravention of this sub-section on 
payment by the applicant of a penalty of seven hundred and fifty 
rupees.
 

            
(5) The disqualifications above referred to shall be the following:—
 

           
(a)   that the person is a minor;
 

           
(b)   that he is found to be of unsound mind by a court of competent 
jurisdiction;
 

           
(c)   that he has been found guilty of criminal misappropriation or 
criminal breach of trust or cheating or forgery or an abetment of or attempt to 
commit any such offence by a court of competent jurisdiction:
 

                        
Provided that, where at least five years have elapsed since the completion of 
the sentence imposed on any person in respect of any such offence, the Authority 
shall ordinarily declare in respect of such person that his conviction shall 
cease to operate as a disqualification under this clause;
 

           
(d)   that in the course of any judicial proceedings relating to any 
policy of insurance of the winding up of an insurance company or in the course 
of an investigation of the affairs of an insurer it has been found that he has 
been guilty of or has knowingly participated in or connived at any fraud, 
dishonesty or misrepresentation against an insurer or an insured;
 

           
(e)   that he does not possess the requisite qualifications and 
practical training for a period not exceeding twelve months, as may be specified 
by the regulations made by the Authority in this behalf;
 

            
(f)   that he has not passed such examinations as may be specified by 
the regulations made by the Authority in this behalf;
 

           
(g)   that he violates the code of conduct as may be specified by 
regulations made by the Authority.
 

                        
(6) If it be found that an intermediary or an insurance intermediary suffers 
from any of the foregoing disqualifications, without prejudice to any other 
penalty to which he may be liable, the Authority shall, and if the intermediary 
or an insurance intermediary has knowingly contravened any provision of this Act 
may cancel the licence issued to the intermediary or insurance intermediary 
under this section.
 

                        
(7) The Authority may issue a duplicate licence to replace a licence lost, 
destroyed or mutilated, on payment of such fee, as may be determined by 
regulations made by the authority.
 

                        
(8) Any person who acts as an intermediary or an insurance intermediary without 
holding a licence issued under this section to act as such, shall be punishable 
with fine, and any insurer or any person who appoints as an intermediary or an 
insurance intermediary or any person not licensed to act such or transacts any 
insurance business in India through any such person, shall be punishable with 
fine.
 

                        
(9) Where the person contravening sub-section (8) is a company or a firm, then, 
without prejudice to any other proceedings which may be taken against the 
company or firm, every director, manager, secretary or other officer of the 
company, and every partner of the firm who is knowingly a party to such 
contravention shall be punishable with fine.”.
 

30. Section 64UA, in sub-section 
(1), in sub-clause (a), for “Controller of Insurance” substitute “Chairperson of 
the Authority”;
 

31. Section 64UB,—
 

(a)  for sub-section (1), 
substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(l) The Authority may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
regulations to carryout the purposes of this Part.”;
 

(b)  in sub-section (2), for 
“rules”, substitute “regulations”;
 

(c)  in sub-section (3), for 
“Central Government” at both the places where it occur, substitute 
“Authority”;
 

(d)  in sub-section (5), for 
“Controller of Insurance”, substitute “Chairperson of the Authority”.
 

32. Section 64UC, in sub-section 
(1), in the proviso, for “the Controller may, with the previous approval of the 
Central Government”, substitute “the Authority may”;
 

33. Section 64UD, after sub-section 
(1) insert the following:—
 

            
“Provided that the Chairperson of the Authority shall become the Chairman of the 
Advisory Committee with effect from the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory 
and Development Authority Act, 1999 and function as such, and any Chairman of 
the Tariff Committee holding office immediately before such commencement shall 
cease to be the Chairman.”.
 

34. Section 64UJ, in sub-section 
(5), for “Central Government” wherever it occurs, substitute 
“Authority”;
 

35. Section 64UM,—
 

(a)  in sub-section 
(1),—
 

             
(i)  in paragraph (B), after “the Insurance (Amendment) Act, 1968” insert 
“but before the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development 
Authority Act, 1999”;
 

            
(ii)  after paragraph (B), insert the following:—
 

                        
“(BA) Every person who intends to act as a surveyor or loss assessor after the 
expiry of a period of one year from the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory 
and Development Authority Act, 1999, shall make an application to the Authority 
within such time, in such manner and on payment of such fee as may be determined 
by the regulations made by the Authority:
 

                        
Provided that any licence issued immediately before the commencement of the 
Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 shall be deemed to have 
been issued in accordance with the regulations providing for such 
licence.”;
 

           
(iii)  in paragraph (C) for “as may be prescribed”, substitute “as may be 
determined by the regulations”;
 

           
(iv)  in paragraph (D), in clause (i),—
 

           
(A)   for item (a), substitute the following:— 
 

                  
“(a)      has been in practice as a surveyor or loss 
assessor on the date of commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development 
Authority Act, 1999, or”;
 

           
(B)   in item (f), for “prescribed” substitute “specified by the 
regulations made by the Authority”;
 

(b)  after sub-section (1), 
insert—
 

                        
“(1A) Every surveyor and loss assessor shall comply with the code of conduct in 
respect of their duties, responsibilities and other professional requirements as 
may be specified by regulations made by the Authority.”.
 

36. Section 64V,—
 

(a)  in sub-section 
(1),—
 

             
(i)  in clause (i), after sub-clause (g), insert the following:—
 

               
         “(h) such other asset or assets 
as may be specified by regulations made in this behalf;”;
 

            
(ii)  in clause (ii),—
 

                  
(A) in sub-clause (b), in items (i) and (ii), for “40 per cent.”, substitute “50 
per cent.”;
 

                  
(B) after sub-clause (f), insert the following:—
 

                  
“(g) such other liability which may be made in this behalf to be included for 
the purpose of clause (ii).”;
 

(b)  for sub-section (2), 
substitute the following:—
 

                        
“(2) Every insurer shall furnish to the Authority with his returns under section 
15 or section 16, as the case may be, a statement certified by an auditor 
approved by the Authority in respect of general insurance business, or an 
actuary approved by the Authority in respect of life insurance business, as the 
case may be, of his assets and liabilities assessed in the manner required by 
this section as on the 31st day of March of the preceding year.
 

                        
(3) Every insurer shall value his assets and liabilities in the manner required 
by this section and in accordance with the regulations which may be made by the 
Authority in this behalf.”.
 

37. Section 64VA,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“at all times”, substitute “at all times before the commencement of the 
Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999”;
 

(b)  after sub-section (1), 
insert the following:—
 

            
“(1A) Every insurer shall, at all times, on or after the commencement of the 
Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999, maintain an excess of 
the value of his assets over the amount of his liabilities of not less than the 
amount arrived at as follows (hereinafter referred to in this section referred 
to as the “required solvency margin”), namely:—
 

             
(i)  in the case of an insurer carrying on life insurance business, the 
required solvency margin, shall be the higher of the following 
amounts—
 

           
(a)   fifty crores of rupees (one hundred crores of rupees in case of 
re-insurers); or
 

           
(b)   the aggregate sums of the results arrived at in items (I) and 
(II) stated below:—
 

                  
(I)  the aggregate of the results arrived at by applying the calculation 
described in item (A) below (Step I) and the calculation described in item (B) 
below (Step II):
 

                        
(A)  for Step I—
 

                                
(A. 1)  there shall be taken, a sum equal to a percentage determined by the 
regulations not exceeding five per cent. of the mathematical reserves for direct 
business and re-insurance acceptances without any deduction for re-insurance 
cessions;
 

                                
(A. 2)  the amount of mathematical reserves at the end of the preceding 
financial year after the deduction of re-insurance cessions shall be expressed 
as a percentage of the amount of those mathematical reserves before any such 
deduction; and
 

                                
(A. 3)  the sum mentioned in item (A.1) above shall be 
multiplied—
 

                             
(A. 3.1)  where the percentage arrived at under item (A. 2) above is 
greater than eighty-five per cent. (or in the case of a re-insurer carrying on 
exclusive re-insurance business, fifty per cent.), by that greater percentage; 
and
 

                             
(A. 3.2)  in any other case, by eighty-five per cent. (or in the case of a 
re-insurer carrying on exclusive re-insurance business, fifty per 
cent.);
 

                        
(B)  for Step II—
 

                                 
(B.1)  there shall be taken, a sum equal to a percentage determined by the 
regulations made by the Authority not exceeding one per cent. of the sum at risk 
for the policies on which the sum at risk is not a negative figure, 
and
 

                                
(B. 2)  the amount of sum at risk at the end of the preceding financial 
year for policies on which the sum at risk is not a negative figure after the 
deduction of re-insurance cession shall be expressed as a percentage of the 
amount of that sum at risk before any such deduction, and 
 

                                
(B. 3)  the sum arrived at under item (B.1) above shall be 
multiplied—
 

                             
(B. 3.1)  where the percentage arrived at under item (B.2) above is greater 
than fifty per cent., by that greater percentage; and
 

                             
(B. 3.2)  in any other case, by fifty per cent.
 

                  
(II) a percentage determined by the regulations made by the Authority of the 
value of assets determined in accordance with the provisions of section 
64V;
 

           
(ii)   in the case of an insurer carrying on general insurance 
business, the required solvency margin, shall be the highest of the following 
amounts:—
 

                  
(a)  fifty crores of rupees (one hundred crores of rupees in case of 
re-insurer); or
 

                  
(b)  a sum equivalent to twenty per cent. of net premium income; 
or
 

                  
(c)  a sum equivalent to thirty per cent. of net incurred 
claims,
 

subject to credit for re-insurance 
in computing net premiums and net incurred claims being actual but a percentage, 
determined by the regulations, not exceeding fifty per cent.:
 

Provided that if in respect of any 
insurer, the Authority is satisfied that either by reason of an unfavourable 
claim experience or because of sharp increase in the volume of the business, or 
for any other reason, compliance with the provisions of this sub-section would 
cause undue hardship to the insurer, the Authority may direct, for such period 
and subject to such conditions, such solvency margin not being less than the 
lower of the amount mentioned in sub-clause (i) or sub-clause (ii) above, as the 
case may be.
 

Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
sub-section, the expressions—
 

(i)   “mathematical 
reserves” means the provision made by an insurer to cover liabilities (excluding 
liabilities which have fallen due and liabilities arising from deposit back 
arrangement in relation to any policy whereby an amount is deposited by 
re-insurer with the cedant) arising under or in connection with policies or 
contracts for life insurance business. Mathematical reserves also include 
specific provision for adverse deviations of the bases, such as mortality and 
morbidity rates, interest rates, and expense rates, and any explicit provisions 
made, in the valuation of liabilities, in accordance with the regulations made 
by the Authority for this purpose;
 

(ii)  “net incurred claims” 
means the average of the net incurred claims during the specified period of not 
exceeding three preceding financial years;
 

(iii) “sum at risk”, in relation to 
a life insurance policy, means a sum which is—
 

           
(a)  in any case in which an amount is payable in consequence of death 
other than a case falling within sub-clause (b) below, the amount payable on 
death, and
 

           
(b)  in any case in which the benefit under the policy in question consists 
of the making, in consequence of death, of the payments of annuity, payment of a 
sum by instalments or any other kind of periodic payments, the present value of 
that benefit,
 

less in either case the 
mathematical reserve in respect of the relevant policies.”;
 

            
(c)  after sub-section (2), insert the following:—
 

               
         “(2A) If, at any time an insurer 
does not maintain the required solvency margin in accordance with the provisions 
of this section, he shall, in accordance with the directions issued by the 
Authority, submit a financial plan, indicating a plan of action to correct the 
deficiency to the Authority within a specified period not exceeding three 
months.
 

                        
(2B) An insurer who has submitted a plan under sub-section (2A) to the Authority 
shall propose modifications to the plan if the Authority considers it 
inadequate, and shall give effect to any plan accepted by the Authority as 
adequate.
 

                        
(2C) An insurer who does not comply with the provisions of sub-section (2A) 
shall be deemed to be insolvent and may be wound up by the court.”;
 

           
(d)  after sub-section (6), insert the following:—
 

                        
“(7) Every insurer shall furnish to the Authority his returns under section 15 
or section 16, as the case may be, in case of life insurance business a 
statement certified by an actuary approved by the Authority, and in case of 
general insurance business a statement certified by an auditor approved by the 
Authority, of the required solvency margin maintained by the insurer in the 
manner required by sub-section (1A).”.
 

38. Section 70, in sub-section (1), 
for “the Controller a certificate of registration”, substitute “the Authority, 
before the date of commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development 
Authority Act, 1999, a certificate of registration”.
 

39. Section 95, in sub-section (1), 
for “In this Part—”, substitute, “In this Part, before the date of commencement 
of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999,—”.
 

40. Section 101A,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“the Central Government”, substitute “the Authority with the previous approval 
of the Central Government”;
 

(b)  in sub-section (2), for 
“the Central Government”, substitute “the Authority”.
 

41. Section 101B,—
 

(a)  in sub-section (1), for 
“the Central Government”, substitute “the Authority with the previous approval 
of the Central Government.”;
 

(b)  in sub-section (2), for 
“prescribed”; substitute “determined by the regulations made by the 
Authority”.
 

42. For sections 102 to 105, 
substitute the following:—
 

      
“102. Penalty for default in complying with, or act in contravention of, this 
Act.—If any person, who is required under this Act, or rules or regulations 
made thereunder,—
 

           
(a)  to furnish any document, statement, account, return or report to the 
Authority, fails to furnish the same; or
 

           
(b)  to comply with the directions, fails to comply with such 
directions;
 

            
(c)  to maintain solvency margin, fails to maintain such solvency 
margin;
 

           
(d)  to comply with the directions on the insurance treaties, fails to 
comply with such directions on the insurance treaties,
 

      he 
shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding five lakh rupees for each such 
failure and punishable with fine.
 

            
103. Penalty for carrying on insurance business in contravention of sections 
3, 7 and 98.—If a person makes a statement, or furnishes any document, 
statement, account, return or report which is false and which he either knows or 
believes to be false or does not believe to be true,—
 

           
(a)  he shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding five lakh rupees for 
each such failure; and
 

           
(b)  he shall be punishable with imprisonment which may extend to three 
years or with fine for each such failure.
 

            
104. Penalty for false statement in document.—If a person fails to comply 
with the provisions of section 27 or section 27A or section 27B or section 27C 
or section 27D, he shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding five lakh rupees 
for each such failure.
 

            
105. Wrongfully obtaining or withholding property.—If any director, 
managing director, manager or other officer or employees of an insurer 
wrongfully obtains possession of any property or wrongfully applies to any 
purpose of the Act, he shall be liable to a penalty not exceeding two lakh 
rupees for each such failure.
 

            
105A. Offences by companies.—(1) Where any offence under this Act has 
been committed by a company, every person who, at the time the offence was 
committed, was in charge of, and was responsible to, the company for the conduct 
of the business of the company as well as the company shall be deemed to be 
guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished 
accordingly:
 

            
Provided that nothing contained in this sub-section shall render any such person 
liable to any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without 
his knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
commission of such offence.
 

            
(2) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where any offence 
under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the offence 
has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or is attributable to any 
neglect on the part of, any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the 
company, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall be deemed to 
be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
punished accordingly.
 

            
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 

           
(a)   “company” means any body corporate, and includes—
 

                  
(i)   a firm; and
 

                  
(ii)  an association of persons or a body of individuals whether 
incorporated or not; and
 

           
(b)   “director”, in relation to—
 

                  
(i)   a firm, means a partner in the firm;
 

                  
(ii)  an association of persons or a body of individuals, means any member 
controlling the affairs thereof.
 

                        
105B. Penalty for failure to comply with section 32B.—If an insurer fails 
to comply with the provisions of section 32B, he shall be liable to a penalty 
not exceeding five lakh rupees for each such failure and shall be punishable 
with imprisonment which may extend to three years or with fine for each such 
failure.
 

                        
105C. Penalty for failure to comply with section 32C.—If an insurer fails 
to comply with the provisions of section 32C, he shall be liable to a penalty 
not exceeding twenty-five lakh rupees for each such failure and in the case of 
subsequent and continuing failure, the registration granted to such insurer 
under section 3 shall be cancelled by the Authority.”.
 

43. In Sections 110A, 110B and 110C 
for “Controller”, wherever it occurs, substitute “Chairperson of the 
Authority”.
 

44. Section 110G, for “Controller” 
at both the places where it occurs, substitute “Chairperson of the 
Authority”.
 

45. Section 110H, in sub-section 
(1), for “under sections”, substitute “under sections 27D,”.
 

46. Section 114, in sub-section 
(2),—
 

(a)  after clause (a), insert 
the following:—
 

        
“(aa)  such other percentage of paid-up equity capital in excess of 
twenty-six per cent. of the paid-up equity capital and the period within which 
such excess paid-up equity capital shall be divested under sub-section (1) of 
section 6AA.”;
 

(b)  omit clauses (g), and 
(h),
 

47. After section 114, insert the 
following:—
 

            
“114A. Power of Authority to make regulations.—(1) The Authority may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with this Act 
and the rules made thereunder, to carry out the purposes of this Act.
 

            
(2) In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such regulations may provide for all or any of the following matters, 
namely:—
 

           
(a)   the matters including fee relating to the registration of 
insurers under section 3;
 

           
(b)   the manner of suspension or cancellation of registration under 
sub-section (5E) of section 3;
 

           
(c)   such fee, not exceeding five thousand rupees, as may be 
determined by the regulations for issue of a duplicate certificate of 
registration under sub-section (7) of section 3;
 

           
(d)   the matters relating to the renewal of registration and fee 
therefor under section 3A;
 

           
(e)   the manner and procedure for divesting excess share capital 
under sub-section (2) of section 6AA;
 

            
(f)   the preparation of balance-sheet, profit and loss account and a 
separate account of receipts and payments and revenue account under sub-section 
(1A) of section 11;
 

           
(g)   the manner in which an abstract of the report of the actuary to 
be specified under the fourth proviso to sub-section (1) of section 
13;
 

           
(h)   the form and the manner in which the statement referred to in 
sub-section (4) of section 13 shall be appended;
 

            
(i)   the time, manner and the other conditions of investment of 
assets held by an insurer under sub-sections (1), (2) and (3) of section 
27D;
 

            
(j)   the minimum information to be maintained by insurer in their 
books, the manner in which such information should be maintained, the checks and 
other verifications to be adopted by insurers in that connection and all other 
matters incidental thereto under sub-section (8) of section 33;
 

           
(k)   the manner for making an application, the manner and the fee for 
issue of a licence to act as an insurance agent under sub-section (1) of section 
42;
 

            
(l)   the fee and the additional fee to be determined for renewal of 
licence of insurance agent under sub-section (3) of section 42;
 

          
(m)   the requisite qualifications and practical training to act as an 
insurance agent under clause (e) of sub-section (4) of section 42;
 

           
(n)   the passing of examination to act as an insurance agent under 
clause (f) of sub-section (4) of section 42;
 

           
(o)   the code of conduct under clause (g) of sub-section (4) of 
section 42;
 

           
(p)   the fee not exceeding rupees fifty for issue of duplicate 
licence under sub-section (6) of section 42;
 

           
(q)   the manner and the fees for issue of a licence to an 
intermediary or an insurance intermediary under sub-section (1) of section 
42D;
 

           
(r)   the fee and the additional fee to be determined for renewal of 
licence of intermediaries or insurance intermediaries under sub-section (3) of 
section 42D;
 

           
(s)   the requisite qualifications and practical training of 
intermediaries or insurance intermediaries under clause (e) of sub-section (5) 
of section 42D;
 

           
(t)   the examination to be passed to act as an intermediary or 
insurance intermediary under clause (f) of sub-section (5) of section 
42D;
 

           
(u)   the code of conduct under clause (g) of sub-section (5) of 
section 42D;
 

           
(v)   the fee for issue of duplicate licence under sub-section (7) of 
section 42D;
 

          
(w)   such matters as specified under sub-section (2) of section 64UB 
relating to the Tariff Advisory Committee;
 

           
(x)   the matters relating to licensing of surveyors and loss 
assessors, their duties, responsibilities and other professional requirements 
under section 64UM;
 

           
(y)   such other asset or assets as may be specified under clause (h) 
of sub-section (1) of section 64V for the purposes of ascertaining sufficiency 
of assets undersection 64VA;
 

           
(z)   the valuation of assets and liabilities under sub-section (3) of 
section 64V;
 

         
(za)   the matters specified under sub-section (1A) of section 64VA 
relating to sufficiency of assets;
 

         
(zb)   the matters relating to re-insurance under sections 101A and 
101B;
 

         
(zc)   the matters relating to redressal grievances of policy-holders 
to protect their interest and to regulate, promote and ensure orderly growth of 
insurance industry; and
 

         
(zd)   any other matter which is to be, or may be, specified by the 
regulations made by the Authority or in respect of which provisions is to be 
made or may be made by the regulations.
 

            
(3) Every regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the regulation or both Houses agree that the 
regulation should not be made, the regulation shall, thereafter, have effect 
only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, 
that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the 
validity of anything previously done under that regulation.”.
 

38. Section 116A, for “Central 
Government”, at both the places where they occur, substitute “Central 
Government, before the date of commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and 
Development Authority Act, 1999”.</form><form>
 

The 
Insurance Regulatory and development  
Authority Act, 1999 
 

 
 

The 
Second Schedule
 

(See 
section 31)
 

AmendmentS 
to the Life Insurance Corporation Act, 1956
 

(31 of 
1956)
 

1. In the Act, for “Controller” 
wherever it occurs, substitute “Authority”.
 

2. After section 30, insert the 
following:—
 

            
“30A. Exclusive privilege of Corporation to cease.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, the exclusive privilege of carrying on life 
insurance business in India by the Corporation shall cease on and from the 
commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development Authority Act, 1999 and 
the Corporation shall, thereafter, carry on life insurance business in India in 
accordance with the provisions of the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 
1938)”.</form><form>
 




The Insurance Regulatory and development  

Authority Act, 1999 
 



 




The Third Schedule
 


(See section 32)
 




Amendment to the General Insurance Business (nationalisation) Act, 1972
 


(57 of 1972)
 


After section 24, insert 
the following:—
 


            “24A. 
Exclusive privilege of Corporation and acquiring companies to cease.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in this Act, the exclusive privilege of the Corporation and 
the acquiring companies of carrying on general insurance business in India shall 
cease on and from the commencement of the Insurance Regulatory and Development 
Authority Act, 1999 (4 of 1999) and the Corporation and the acquiring companies 
shall, thereafter, carry on general insurance business in India in accordance 
with the provisions of the Insurance Act, 1938 (4 of 1938).”
 



</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>