<act><title>THE CENTRAL ELECTRICITY REGULATORY COMMISSION 
(PROCEDURE, TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR GRANT OF TRADING LICENCE AND OTHER RELATED 
MATTERS) REGULATIONS, 20091</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>-
<section><number>a</number> These regulations may 
be called the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission (Procedure, Terms and 
Conditions for Grant of Trading Licence and other Related Matters) Regulations, 
2009. 
 
 


</section><section><number>b</number> These regulations shall come into force on and from the 
  date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> of their publication in the Official Gazette. </section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> </title><title>Definitions and Interpretation. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> In 
these regulations, unless the context or subject-matter, otherwise requires,- 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> "Act" means the Electricity Act, 2003 (36 of 2003); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> "applicant" means a person who has made an application to the 
  Commission for grant of licence; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> "associate", in relation to an applicant or the licensee, as the case 
  may be, means the person- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> who owns or controls shares carrying not less than twenty-six per 
    cent of the voting rights of the applicant or the licensee, as the case may 
    be; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> in respect of whom the applicant or the licensee, as the case may 
    be, owns or controls shares carrying not less than twenty-six per cent of 
    the voting rights; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> who is under the same management as the applicant or the licensee, 
    as the case may be. </subsubsection>
 Explanation .-For the purpose of this sub-clause, the applicant or 
  the licensee, as the case may be, and the person concerned shall be deemed to 
  be under the same management- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> if the managing director or manager of the applicant or the licensee, 
    as the case may be, is the managing director or manager of such person; or 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> if a majority of the directors of the applicant or the licensee, as 
    the case may be, constitute or any time within six months immediately 
    preceding, constituted a majority of the directors of such person; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> if not less than one-third of the total voting power with respect 
    to any matter relating to the applicant or the licensee, as the case may be, 
    and such person is exercised or controlled by the same individual or body 
    corporate; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iv</number> if any of the directors of the applicant or the licensee, as the 
    case may be, while holding the majority of shares of the applicant or the 
    licensee as the case may be, also hold the majority of shares in such 
    person. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> "Commission" means the Central Electricity Regulatory Commission 
  referred to in section 76 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> "Conduct of Business Regulations" means the Central Electricity 
  Regulatory Commission (Conduct of Business) Regulations, 1999, as amended from 
  time-to-time and includes any statutory re-enactment thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> "current ratio" means ratio between the current assets and current 
  liabilities, where- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> current assets include cash or cash equivalent of money, accounts 
    receivables, inventory, marketable securities, and pre-paid expenses, and 
    
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> current liabilities include sundry creditors, provisions and other 
    liabilities to be discharged within a period of one year; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> "economic offence" means an offence to which the Economic Offences 
  (Inapplicability of Limitation) Act, 1974 (12 of 1974), is applicable for the 
  time being; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> "existing licensees" means the persons holding licence on the date of 
  commencement of these regulations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> "fraud" has the same meaning as is assigned to it under section 17 of 
  the Indian Contract Act, 1872 (9 of 1872); 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> "Grid Code" means the Grid Code specified by the Commission under 
  clause (h) of sub-section (1) of section 79 of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> "inter-State trading" means transfer of electricity from the territory 
  of one State for re-sale to the territory of another State and includes 
  electricity imported from any other country for re-sale in any State of India; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> "licence" means a licence granted to any person by the Commission to 
  undertake inter-State trading in electricity as an electricity trader; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> "licensee" means a person who has been granted licence; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> "liquidity ratio" means the ratio between the liquid assets and current 
  liabilities, where,- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> liquid assets include the current assets less inventory, and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> current liabilities include sundry creditors, provisions and other 
    liabilities to be discharged within a period of one year; </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> "net worth" means aggregate value of the paid up equity capital and 
  free reserves (excluding reserves created out of revaluation) reduced by the 
  aggregate value of accumulated losses, deferred expenditure (including 
  miscellaneous expenses) not written off and loans and advances to the 
  associates; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> "other business" means any business of the licensee other than the 
  business of inter-State trading; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> "promoter" with reference to a company means a person who has promoted 
  and is actively associated with the management of the company or holds not 
  less than twenty-six per cent of the share capital of such company; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> "year" means a period of twelve months from 1st April of a calendar 
  year to 31st March of the following calendar year. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Save as aforesaid and unless repugnant to the context or the 
subject-matter otherwise requires, words and expressions used in these 
regulations and not defined, but defined in the Act, or the Grid Code shall have 
the meanings assigned to them respectively in the Act or the Grid Code. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The provisions of the General Clauses Act, 1897 (10 of 1897) as amended 
from time-to-time shall apply for the interpretation of these regulations as 
they apply for the interpretation of an Act of Parliament. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Disqualifications </title>.-The applicant shall not be qualified 
for grant of licence if- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> the applicant, or any of his associates, or partners, or promoters, or 
  Directors is an undischarged insolvent; or 
 </section><section><number>b</number> the applicant, or any of his associates, or partners, or promoters, or 
  Directors has been convicted of an offence involving moral turpitude, fraud, 
  or any economic offence during the year of making the application or three 
  years immediately preceding that year and a period of six months has not 
  elapsed since his release from imprisonment, if any, consequent to such 
  conviction; or 
 </section><section><number>c</number> an order canceling the licence of the applicant, or any of his 
  associates, or partners, or promoters, or Directors, has been passed by the 
  Commission; or 
 </section><section><number>d</number> the applicant holds a licence for transmission of electricity; or 
 </section><section><number>e</number> the applicant, or any of his associates, or partners, or promoters, or 
  Directors has in the past been- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> refused a licence on the grounds which continue to remain  valid, 
    or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> found guilty in any proceedings for non-compliance of any of the 
    provisions of the Act or the rules or the regulations made thereunder or an 
    order made by the Appropriate Commission, during the year of making the 
    application or five years immediately preceding that year; or 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>f</number>  the applicant is not considered a fit and proper person for the 
  grant of licence for any other reason to be recorded in writing. 
</section>
 Explanation. -For the purpose of determining as to whether the 
applicant is a 'fit and proper person', the Commission may take account of any 
consideration as it deems fit, including but not limited to the following 
namely:- 
 
 <section><number>i</number> financial integrity of the applicant; 
 </section><section><number>ii</number> his competence; 
 </section><section><number>iii</number> his reputation and character; and 
 </section><section><number>iv</number> his efficiency and honesty. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> </title><title>Proceedings before the Commission. </title>-All 
proceedings under these regulations shall be governed by the Conduct of Business 
Regulations. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>6</number> </title><title>Procedure for grant of licence. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Any 
person desirous of undertaking inter-State trading in electricity shall make an 
application to the Commission for grant of licence in the manner specified in 
Form I appended to these regulations and such application shall be accompanied 
by- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> such fee as may be prescribed by the Central Government from 
  time-to-time payable through Bank Draft or Pay Order drawn in favour of 
  Assistant Secretary, Central Electricity Regulatory Commission, New Delhi . 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> copies of the annual reports in case of the persons incorporated under 
  the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) and audited accounts along with the 
  Directors' Report, Auditors' Report, the Schedules and notes on accounts for 
  three years immediately preceding the year in which the application has been 
  made and the special balance sheet as on any date falling within 30 days 
  immediately preceding the date of making the application: </subsection>
 Provided that where the applicant has not been incorporated, registered or 
formed during the period of three years immediately preceding the year in which 
the application is made, the application shall be accompanied by the copies of 
the annual reports and audited accounts for such lesser period for which the 
applicant has been in existence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The application for grant of licence, along with annexures and enclosures 
shall also be submitted to the Commission on compact disc (CD). 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The applicant shall post complete application along with annexures and 
enclosures on his own website so as to facilitate access to the application by 
any person through internet and shall keep them on the website till the disposal 
of his application. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The applicant shall within 7 days after making such application, publish 
a notice of his application, in two daily newspapers having circulation in each 
of the five regions in addition to those published from Delhi, including one 
economic daily newspaper in Form II, with the following particulars, namely:- 

 
 <subsection><number>a</number> Name of the applicant (in bold) at the top clearly bringing out whether 
  the applicant is an individual/sole proprietor, an association or body of 
  individuals, a partnership firm registered under the Indian Partnership Act 
  1932 (9 of 1932), a private limited company or a  public limited company, 
  incorporated under the Companies Act, 1956, (1 of 1956) giving full 
  particulars of its registered office address in case of a company incorporated 
  under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) and address for correspondence; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> A statement that the applicant has made an application for grant of 
  licence for Category I or Category II or Category III, as the case may be, 
  under sub-section (1) of section 15 of the Act, to the Central Electricity 
  Regulatory Commission; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> Share capital </subsection>
 (Rs. in lakh) 
 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> Authorised: 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> Issued: 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> Subscribed: 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> Paid up: </subsection>
 <subsection><number>d</number> Shareholding pattern (List of details of shareholders holding 5% or 
  more shares, number of shares held by each of them and percentage of shares of 
  the total paid-up capital) of the applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> Financial and technical strength of the applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> Volume of electricity intended to be traded per year; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> Management profile of the applicant including details of past 
  experience of the applicant or the persons on its management in same or 
  similar activity; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>h</number> Geographical areas within which the applicant will undertake trading in 
  electricity; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> Net worth, current ratio and liquidity ratio of the applicant as on 
   31st March of three consecutive years immediately preceding the year of 
  making of the application or for such lesser period as may be applicable and 
  on the date of the special balance sheet accompanying the application; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> A statement whether the applicant or any of his associates, or 
  partners, or promoters, or Directors has been "declared insolvent", and if so, 
  the details thereof and whether or not they have been discharged; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>k</number> Details of cases resulting in conviction of an offence involving moral 
  turpitude, fraud or economic offence of the applicant, or any of his 
  associates, or partners, or promoters, or Directors during the year of making 
  the application or three years immediately preceding that year and the date of 
  release of the above person from imprisonment, if any, consequent to such 
  conviction; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>l</number> A statement whether the applicant or any of his associates, or 
  partners, or promoters, or Directors was ever refused licence, and if so, the 
  particulars of the application, date of making the application, date of order 
  refusing licence and reasons for such refusal; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>m</number> A statement whether the applicant is in possession of a licence for 
  transmission of electricity and if so, the details thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>n</number> A statement whether an order canceling the licence of the applicant or 
  any of his associates, or partners, or promoters, or Directors has been made 
  by the Commission and if so the details thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>o</number> A statement whether the applicant or any of his associates, or 
  partners, or promoters, or Directors has been found guilty of non-compliance 
  of any of the provisions of the Act or the rules or the regulations made 
  thereunder or an order made by the Appropriate Commission, and if so the 
  details thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>p</number> A statement to the effect that the application and other documents 
  filed before the Commission, are available with the applicant for inspection 
  by any person; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>q</number> Name and address and other relevant details of the person under the 
  control of the applicant with whom the application and other documents can be 
  inspected by any person; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>r</number> Address of the website where the complete application along with 
  annexures, enclosures, has been posted; </subsection>
 <subsection><number>s</number> A statement that objections or suggestions, if any, be filed before the 
Secretary, Central Electricity Regulatory Commission,....................(Give 
here address where the office of the Commission is situate), New Delhi with a 
copy of the objections or suggestions to the applicant, within 30 days of 
publication of the notice; 
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> The applicant shall within 7 days from the date of publication of the 
notice as aforesaid submit to the Commission on affidavit the details of the 
notice published and shall also file the original complete page of the newspaper 
in which the notice has been published. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> The applicant may file his reply to the objections or suggestions 
received in response to the notice within 45 days of its publication in the 
newspapers. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> The Commission after consideration of the objections or suggestions 
received in response to the notice published by the applicant and his reply may 
propose to grant licence. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> When the Commission proposes to grant licence, it shall publish a notice 
of its proposal in two daily newspapers, as the Commission may consider 
appropriate, stating the name and address of the person to whom it proposes to 
issue the licence, with such other details as the Commission considers 
appropriate, to invite further objections or suggestions to its proposal. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> On consideration of further objections or suggestions received and the 
reply of the applicant thereto, if any, the Commission may grant the licence or 
reject the application, for reasons to be recorded in writing if the application 
does not conform to the provisions of the Act, the rules or the regulations or 
provisions of any other law for the time being in force: 
 Provided that no application shall be rejected, unless the applicant has been 
given an opportunity of being heard. 
 </section><section><number>10</number> As far as practicable the licence shall be granted in accordance with 
format prescribed in Form III appended to these regulations. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>7</number> </title><title>Obligations of the licensee. </title>-The 
licensee shall be subject to the following obligations; namely:- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> The licensee shall comply with the requirements of laws in force and, 
  in particular, the Act, the Rules and the Regulations, Grid Code, orders and 
  directions issued from time-to-time by the Commission and any of the State 
  Electricity Regulatory Commissions in accordance with law. 
 </section><section><number>b</number> The licensee shall not exceed the volume of trading authorized under 
  the licence, but may, in exceptional circumstances, undertake trading in 
  electricity up to the maximum of 120 per cent of the volume of trade 
  authorized under the licence granted to him: 
 Provided that the licensee, on exceeding the volume of trading authorized 
  in a year under he licence granted to him shall pay licence fee applicable to 
  the higher category for that particular year: 
 Provided further that the licensee may with the prior approval of the 
  Commission and on such terms and conditions as the Commission may decide, 
  exceed the specified limit of 120% in a year. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> The licensee shall not charge any amount exceeding the trading margin 
  for the inter-State trading in electricity, fixed by the Commission from 
  time-to-time. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> The licensee shall continue to be governed by the qualifications or 
  disqualifications specified in these regulations for making an application for 
  licence throughout the period of licence. 
 </section><section><number>e</number> The licensee shall establish adequate communication facilities like 
  telephone, fax, computer, internet facilities, before undertaking trading. 

 </section><section><number>f</number> The licensee may coordinate with Regional Power Committees, the Central 
  Transmission Utility, State Transmission Utilities, the Regional Load Despatch 
  Centres, and the State Load Despatch Centres with regard to his trading- 
  related activities, to the extent authorized by the concerned buyer and 
  seller. 
 </section><section><number>g</number> The licensee shall render all assistance to any person authorised by 
  the Commission to carry out his duties relating to the licence. 
 </section><section><number>h</number> The licensee shall carry out trading in accordance with the agreed 
  terms and conditions, and may take such safeguards as he may consider 
  necessary with regard to payment security mechanism from the buyers, but shall 
  always ensure timely payment of dues to the seller for purchase of the agreed 
  quantum of electricity either through a letter of credit or any other 
  appropriate instrument or as may be mutually agreed between the seller and the 
  licensee. 
 </section><section><number>i</number> The licensee shall ensure that appropriate agreement for purchase and 
  sale of electricity are entered into by him with the sellers and the buyers 
  prior to scheduling a transaction, and that the agreement shall specify the 
  following, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the boundaries, that is to say, upper and lower MW limits of 
    electricity to be purchased or sold, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> modalities for scheduling, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> persons authorized to specify the schedule, or to modify it after 
    it has been intimated to the Regional Load Despatch Centre or the State Load 
    Despatch Centre, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> whether the buyer or the seller can unilaterally advise modification 
    of the schedule, or whether the modification can only be advised jointly by 
    the buyer and the seller, 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> the liabilities of the parties (seller, buyer and licensee) in case 
    the scheduled quantum (MW) and time of scheduling differs from the agreed 
    terms, or in case of modification in schedule, and in the latter case, the 
    party that will bear non-refundable part of short-term open access charges. 
    </subsection>
 </section><section><number>j</number> The licensee shall ensure that there is no discrepancy or scope for 
  dispute in the scheduling advised to the Regional Load Despatch Centre and in 
  case of any discrepancy or ambiguity in the scheduling advice, the decision of 
  the Regional Load Despatch Centre on the acceptance or otherwise of such 
  advice shall be binding. 
 </section><section><number>k</number> The licensee shall ensure that the buyer and the seller are, either 
  grid connected entities or represent such entities, with special energy meters 
  on their periphery and that the mechanism for Unscheduled Interchange 
  accounting by the appropriate authority is in place. 
 </section><section><number>l</number> The licensee shall not purchase electricity from the entities and the 
  associates of such entities, defaulting in payment of Unscheduled Interchange 
  charges, transmission charges, reactive energy charges, congestion charge and 
  fee and charges for National Load Despatch Centre or Regional load Despatch 
  Centre or the Unified Load Despatch and Communication Scheme or any other 
  payment levied by the Commission or any of the State Commissions under the 
  provisions of the Act or any regulation made thereunder, when so advised by 
  the Commission. 
 </section><section><number>m</number> The licensee shall regularly pay the licence fee specified by the 
  Commission from time-to-time. 
 </section><section><number>n</number> The licensee shall not omit or neglect to undertake trading activity. 
  
 </section><section><number>o</number> The licensee shall not enter into any agreement for purchase or sale of 
  electricity that may lead to abuse of his dominant position or enter into a 
  combination which causes or is likely to cause an adverse effect on 
  competition in electricity industry. 
 </section><section><number>p</number> The licensee shall maintain up-to-date record of all the trading 
  transactions undertaken by him, separately for bilateral transactions, 
  inter-State as well as intra-State, and those through the power exchange. 
 </section><section><number>q</number> The licensee shall make an appropriate application before the 
  Commission for prior approval of the Commission whenever so required, in 
  accordance with the Conduct of Business Regulations. 
 </section><section><number>r</number> The licensee shall, subject to settlement of commercial terms in 
  accordance with law, not omit sale of electricity to a consumer allowed open 
  access by the concerned State Commission. </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>8</number> </title><title>Accounts of the licensee. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The 
licensee shall- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> keep the accounts of the business covered by the licence separate from 
  any other business, whether licensed or otherwise. 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> maintain the statement of accounts in such form and containing such 
  particulars as may be specified by the Commission and till such time these are 
  specified by the Commission, the accounts shall be maintained in accordance 
  with the Companies Act, 1956, (1 of 1956) as amended from time-to-time; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> prepare on a consistent basis from such records, accounting statements 
  for each year comprising a Profit and Loss Account, a Balance Sheet and a 
  statement of source and application of funds together with notes thereto and 
  showing separately the amounts of any revenue, cost, asset, liability, 
  reserve, or provision which has been either- 
 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> charged from or to any other business together with a description of 
    the basis of that charge; or 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> determined by apportionment or allocation between the various 
    business activities together with a description of the basis of the 
    apportionment or allocation. </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> provide in respect of the accounting statements prepared in accordance 
  with foregoing clauses, a report by the Auditors in respect of each year, 
  stating whether in their opinion the statements have been properly prepared 
  and give a true and fair view of the revenue, costs, assets, and liabilities, 
  reserves reasonably attributable to the business to which the statements 
  relate; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> submit to the Commission copies of the accounting statements and 
  Auditor's report not later than nine months after the close of the year to 
  which they relate and shall keep them posted in its website or any other 
  authorized website for a period of at least two years thereafter. 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any person authorised by the Commission shall be entitled to inspect and 
verify the accounts of the licensee and the licensee shall render all necessary 
assistance to such person. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> </title><title>Submission of information. </title>-The licensee 
shall- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> supply such information, as may be called for by the Commission from 
  time-to-time; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> furnish monthly information in Forms IVA, IVB and IVC appended to these 
  regulations, separately in respect of inter-State trading, intra-State trading 
  and trading through power exchange so as to reach the Commission before 10th 
  of the succeeding month: 
 Provided that the information sent to the Commission shall be posted on the 
  website of the licensee or any other website, and such report shall be 
  available on the website for not less than two years. 
 </section><section><number>c</number> submit to the Commission copies of the Annual Reports including 
  Directors' report, Auditors' report, Balance Sheet and Profit and Loss Account 
  pertaining to inter-State trading segment of the business alongwith all the 
  schedules and notes to the accounts, not later than nine months after the 
  close of the year to which they relate and shall keep them posted in its 
  website or in any authorized website for a period of at least two years 
  thereafter. 
 </section><section><number>d</number> report to the Commission the following events as soon as possible:- 

 
 <subsection><number>i</number> when the licensee or any of his associates, or partners, or 
    promoters, or Directors has been declared insolvent; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> when the licensee, or any of his associates, or partners, or 
    promoters, or Directors has been convicted of an offence involving moral 
    turpitude, fraud, or any economic offence; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> when the licence of any of the associates, partners, promoters, 
    Directors has been cancelled by the Commission; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> when the licensee, or any of his associates, or partners, or 
    promoters, or Directors has been found guilty for non-compliance of any of 
    the provisions of the Act or the rules or the regulations made thereunder or 
    an order made by the Appropriate Commission. </subsection></section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>10</number> </title><title>Standards of performance. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The 
Commission may, after consultation with the licensee specify the standards of 
performance of a licensee or a class of licensees. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Till such time the standards of performance are specified under clause 
(1) the licensee shall furnish to the Commission the performance details for 
each year in the format prescribed in Form V, appended to these regulations by 
30th April immediately following the year ending on 31st March. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>11</number> </title><title>Prudential reporting. </title>-The licensee 
shall, as soon as possible, report to the Commission- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> any significant change in the circumstances which may affect his 
  ability to meet the obligations under the Act, the Rules and the Regulations, 
  directives and orders issued by the Commission, the Grid Code, agreement or 
  the licence; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> any material breach of the provisions of the Act, the Rules and the 
  Regulations, directives and orders issued by the Commission, the Grid Code, 
  agreement or the licence; and 
 </section><section><number>c</number> any major change in its shareholding pattern, ownership or management. 
  </section>

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> </title><title>Amendment of licence. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> The terms 
and conditions of the licence may be modified by the Commission in public 
interest or on an application made by the licensee: 
 Provided that before ordering any substantive alteration or modification in 
the licence, proposed to be made otherwise than on the application of the 
licensee, the Commission shall publish a notice in two such daily newspapers as 
it considers necessary with the following particulars, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> name and address of the licensee; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> alterations and modifications proposed to be made; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> grounds for such alterations and modifications; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> inviting suggestions, if any, on the proposal for consideration of the 
  Commission within the time specified in the notice. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> The procedure specified in regulation 6 shall mutatis mutandis 
be applicable in case the licensee makes an application for any substantive 
alteration of or modification to the terms and conditions of the licence: 
 Provided that where the licensee has made an application under sub- 
 section (1) of section 18 of the Act, proposing any substantive alteration 
and modifications in his licence, he shall publish a notice of such application 
in two daily newspapers having circulation in all the five regions, in addition 
to those published from Delhi, including one economic newspaper, in Form VI, 
with the following particulars, namely:- 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> name of the applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> category of the licence granted to him; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> that an application for alteration and modifications has been made 
  before the Commission; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> details of alteration and modifications proposed in the application, 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> reasons for seeking such alterations and modifications; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> a statement that the application made before the Commission has been 
  posted on the website and can also be inspected in the office of the 
  applicant; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> a statement that any suggestion to the proposal for alteration and 
  modifications made in the application may be submitted to the Secretary of the 
  Commission within 30 days of publication of the notice. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title>13 </title>. <title>Procedure for securing compliance of terms and 
conditions of licence. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Where the Commission, on the basis of 
material in its possession is satisfied that the licensee is contravening, or is 
likely to contravene, the terms and conditions of licence, it shall serve a 
notice to the licensee narrating the terms and conditions of licence contravened 
or likely to be contravened by him to invite his objections or suggestions. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The notice may be served on him by delivering the same at the registered 
office or at the usual or his last known place of residence or business, either 
through registered post or speed post or by hand delivery through a messenger or 
publication in a newspaper where the Commission is satisfied that it is not 
reasonably practicable to serve the notice on the licensee through registered 
post or speed post or by hand delivery or in any other manner as considered 
appropriate by the Commission in the facts and circumstances of the case. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Commission shall publish a notice in two newspapers specifying the 
terms and conditions contravened or likely to be contravened by the licensee to 
bring the matters to the attention of persons affected or likely to be affected 
by such contraventions, to invite suggestions from such persons. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The licensee or the persons affected or likely to be affected by the 
contravention of the terms and conditions of the licence by the licensee may 
file their objections or suggestions within 30 days from the date of receipt of 
notice under clause (1) or publication of notice in the newspapers under clause 
(3), as he case may be. (5) The Commission shall on consideration of the 
objections and suggestions received as aforesaid, pass such order or give such 
directions as may be necessary to secure compliance of the terms and conditions 
of license. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>14</number> </title><title>Revocation of licence. </title>-The Commission 
may revoke the licence, in any of the following circumstances, namely:- 
 
 <section><number>a</number> where the licensee in the opinion of the Commission, makes willful and 
  prolonged default in doing anything required of him by or under the Act, or 
  the Rules or the Regulations; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> where the licensee breaches any of the terms and conditions of his 
  licence, the breach of which is expressly declared by such licence to render 
  it liable to revocation; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> where the licensee fails, within the period fixed in this behalf by his 
  licence, or any longer period which the Commission may allow therefor, to show 
  to the satisfaction of the Commission, that he is in a position fully and 
  efficiently to discharge the duties and obligations imposed on him by his 
  licence; 
 </section><section><number>d</number> where in the opinion of the Commission the financial position of the 
  licensee is such that he is unable to fully and efficiently discharge the 
  duties and obligations imposed on him by his licence; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> where the licensee has neglected to undertake trading in electricity; 
  
 </section><section><number>f</number> where the licensee fails to meet the qualifications specified for 
  making an application or incurs any of the disqualifications under these 
  regulations; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> where the licensee fails to submit the information as required in 
  accordance with the regulations 9, 10 and 11 or knowingly furnishes false and 
  wrong information: </section>
 Provided that the licence shall not be revoked except after an enquiry by the 
adjudicating officer appointed by the Commission under section 143 of the Act in 
the manner prescribed by the Central Government: 
 Provided further that the Commission may, instead of revoking a licence under 
clause 
<section><number>1</number> above, permit the licence to remain in force subject to such further 
terms and conditions as it thinks fit to impose, and any further terms and 
conditions so imposed shall be binding upon and be observed by the licensee and 
shall be of like force and effect as if they were contained in the licence. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When the licensee makes an application for revocation of the licence and 
the Commission is satisfied that such revocation of licence shall not 
prejudicially affect the public interest, the Commission may revoke his licence, 
on such terms and conditions as it thinks fit. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Commission shall serve a notice of revocation upon the licensee and 
fix a date on which the revocation shall take effect. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>16</number> </title><title>Communication. </title>-
<section><number>1</number> Unless otherwise 
specified in these regulations, all communications relating to the licence shall 
be in writing and shall be delivered either in person to the addressee or his 
authorized agent, or sent by registered or speed post at the place of business 
of the addressee. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> All communications shall be regarded to have been given by the sender and 
received by the addressee,- 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> when delivered in person to the addressee or to his authorised agent; 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> on expiry of 15 days from the date of sending by registered or speed 
  post at the address of the addressee. </subsection>

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>17</number> </title><title>Power to relax. </title>-The Commission may in 
appropriate cases and for reasons to be recorded in writing relax any of the 
provisions of these regulations. 

</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>18</number> </title><title>Repeal and saving </title>.-
<section><number>1</number> Save as 
otherwise provided in these regulations, the Central Electricity Regulatory 
Commission (Procedure, Terms and Conditions for Grant of Trading Licence and 
other Related Matters) Regulations, 2004 shall stand repealed from the date of 
commencement of these regulations. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done or purported to have been done 
under the repealed regulations shall be deemed to have been done or purported to 
have been done under these regulations. 

</section></article><form>
 

THE CENTRAL ELECTRICITY REGULATORY COMMISSION 
(PROCEDURE, TERMS AND CONDITIONS FOR GRANT OF TRADING LICENCE AND OTHER RELATED 
 
MATTERS) REGULATIONS, 20091
 

 
 

FORM III 
 

CENTRAL ELECTRICITY REGULATORY COMMISSION 
 

LICENCE FOR INTER-STATE TRADING IN ELECTRICITY 

 

1. The Central Electricity Regulatory Commission (hereinafter referred to as 
"the Commission"), in exercise of the powers conferred under section 14 of the 
Electricity Act, 2003 (hereinafter referred to as "the Act"), hereby grants this 
licence as a Category...................trader to..................., 
(hereinafter referred to as "the licensee") having its registered office 
situated at...................to undertake inter-State trade in electricity as 
an electricity trader in the area...................subject to the terms and 
conditions contained in the Act, (in particular, sections 17 to 22 thereof, both 
inclusive), the Rules made by the Central Government (hereinafter referred to as 
"the Rules") and the Regulations specified by the Commission (hereinafter 
referred to as "the Regulations"), including statutory amendments, alterations, 
modifications, re-enactments thereof, which shall be read as part and parcel of 
this licence. 
 

2. This licence is not transferable, except in accordance with the provisions 
of the Act, the Rules and the Regulations. 
 

3. (1) The licensee shall not without prior approval of the Commission- 
 
 

(a) undertake any transaction to acquire by purchase or take over or 
  otherwise, the utility of any other licensee; or 
 

(b) merge its utility with utility of any other licensee. 
 

(2) The licensee shall not at any time assign its licence, or transfer its 
utility, or any part thereof, by sale, lease, exchange or otherwise without the 
prior approval of the Commission. 
 

(3) Any agreement relating to any transaction referred to in sub-clause (1) 
and sub-clause (2) unless made with the approval of the Commission, shall be 
void. 
 

4. The grant of this licence to the licensee shall not in any way hinder or 
restrict the right of the Commission to grant a licence to any other person 
within the same area for inter-State trading in electricity as an electricity 
trader. The licensee shall not claim any exclusivity. 
 

5. This licence shall commence on the date of its issue and unless revoked 
earlier, shall continue to be in force for a period of 25 (twenty-five) years. 

 

6. The licensee may with prior intimation to the Commission, engage in any 
business for optimum utilisation of its assets: 
 

Provided that the licensee shall not engage in the business of transmission 
of electricity. 
 

7. Unless otherwise specified by the Commission, the licensee shall pay 
annual license fee of Rs. ...................lakh, and license fee for a part of 
the year shall be paid on pro-rata basis rounded off to the nearest hundred 
rupees. 
 

8. The provisions contained in sections 19 to 22, both 
inclusive, of the Act shall apply to the licensee with regard to revocation of 
licence and sale of his utility. 
 

SECRETARY 
 

---------
 

1. Vide Notification No. L-7/143/158/2008/CERC, dated 
16th February, 2009, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. III, Sec. 4, 
No. 28, dated 24th February, 2009. </form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Came into force on 24-2-2009.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>