<act> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
This Act may be called the Depositories Act, 1996.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall be deemed to have come into force 
on the 20th day of September, 1995.
</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  “beneficial owner” means a person whose name is recorded as such with a 
depository;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  “Board” means the Securities and Exchange Board of India established under 
section 3 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>c</number>  “bye-laws” means bye-laws made by a depository under section 26;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>d</number>  “Company Law Board” means the Board of Company Law Administration 
constituted under section 10E of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956);
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>e</number>  “depository” means a company formed and registered under the Companies Act, 
1956 (1 of 1956), and which has been granted a certificate of registration under 
sub-section (1A) of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India 
Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>f</number>  “issuer” means any person making an issue of securities;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>g</number>  “participant” means a person registered as such under sub-section (1A) of 
section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>h</number>  “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number> 
“record” includes the records maintained in the form of books or stored in a 
computer or in such other form as may be determined by regulations;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>j</number> “registered owner” means a depository whose name is entered as such in the 
register of the issuer;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>k</number> 
“regulations” means regulations made by the Board;
 
1[(ka)  
“Securities Appellate Tribunal” means a Securities Appellate Tribunal 
established under sub-section (1) of section 15K of the Securities and Exchange 
Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992);]
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>l</number>  “security” means such security as may be specified by the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>m</number>  “service” means any service connected with recording of allotment of 
securities or transfer of ownership of securities in the record of a depository.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions used herein and not 
defined but defined in the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), or the Securities 
Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956), or the Securities and Exchange 
Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992), shall have the meanings respectively 
assigned to them in those Acts.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> Certificate of commencement of business by 
depositories.—
<section><number>1</number> No depository shall 
act as a depository unless it obtains a certificate of commencement of business 
from the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A certificate granted under sub-section (1) 
shall be in such form as may be specified by the regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board shall not grant a certificate 
under sub-section (1) unless it is satisfied that the depository has adequate 
systems and safeguards to prevent manipulation of records and transactions:
 
Provided that no certificate shall be refused 
under this section unless the depository concerned has been given a reasonable 
opportunity of being heard.


</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Agreement between depository and participant.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A depository shall enter into an agreement with one or more participants as its 
agent.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every agreement under sub-section (1) shall 
be in such form as may be specified by the bye-laws.
</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>5</number> Services of depository.—Any 
person, through a participant, may enter into an agreement, in such form as may 
be specified by the bye-laws, with any depository for availing its services.


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Surrender of certificate of security.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person who has entered into an agreement under section 5 shall surrender the 
certificate of security, for which he seeks to avail the services of a 
depository, to the issuer in such manner as may be specified by the regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The issuer, on receipt of certificate of 
security under sub-section (1), shall cancel the certificate of security and 
substitute in its records the name of the depository as a registered owner in 
respect of that security and inform the depository accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> A depository shall, on receipt of 
information under sub-section (2), enter the name of the person referred to in 
sub-section (1) in its records, as the beneficial owner.
</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Registration of transfer of securities with 
depository.—
<section><number>1</number> Every depository 
shall, on receipt of intimation from a participant, register the transfer of 
security in the name of the transferee.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a beneficial owner or a transferee of any 
security seeks to have custody of such security the depository shall inform the 
issuer accordingly.
</section></article> 
 The Depositories 
Act, 1996
  
 <article><number>8</number> Options to receive security certificate or hold 
securities with depository.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
person subscribing to securities offered by an issuer shall have the option 
either to receive the security certificates or hold securities with a 
depository.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where a person opts to hold a security with a 
depository, the issuer shall intimate such depository the details of allotment 
of the security, and on receipt of such information the depository shall enter 
in its records the name of the allottee as the beneficial owner of that 
security.

</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Securities in depositories to be in fungible 
form.—
<section><number>1</number> All securities held by a 
depository shall be dematerialised and shall be in a fungible form.
 

1[(2) Nothing contained in sections 153, 
153A, 153B, 187B, 187C and 372 of the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956), shall 
apply to a depository in respect of securities held by it on behalf of the 
beneficial owners.]
 
 


</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Rights of depositories and beneficial owner.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, 
a depository shall be deemed to be the registered owner for the purposes of 
effecting transfer of ownership of security on behalf of a beneficial owner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Save as otherwise provided in sub-section 
(1), the depository as a registered owner shall not have any voting rights or 
any other rights in respect of securities held by it.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The beneficial owner shall be entitled to 
all the rights and benefits and be subjected to all the liabilities in respect 
of his securities held by a depository.


</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Register of beneficial owner.—Every 
depository shall maintain a register and an index of beneficial owners in the 
manner provided in section 150, section 151 and section 152 of the Companies 
Act, 1956 (1 of 1956).






















</article> 
 The Depositories 
Act, 1996
  
 <article><number>12</number> Pledge or hypothecation of securities held in a 
depository.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to such 
regulations and bye-laws, as may be made in this behalf, a beneficial owner may 
with the previous approval of the depository create a pledge or hypothecation in 
respect of a security owned by him through a depository.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every beneficial owner shall give intimation of 
such pledge or hypothecation to the depository and such depository shall 
thereupon make entries in its records accordingly.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Any entry in the records of a depository under 
sub-section (2) shall be evidence of a pledge or 
hypothecation.</section></article> 
 The Depositories 
Act, 1996
  
 <article><number>13</number> Furnishing of information and records by 
depository and issuer.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
depository shall furnish to the issuer information about the transfer of 
securities in the name of beneficial owners at such intervals and in such manner 
as may be specified by the bye-laws.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every issuer shall make available to the 
depository copies of the relevant records in respect of securities held by such 
depository.</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Option to opt out in respect of any 
security.—
<section><number>1</number> If a beneficial owner 
seeks to opt out of a depository in respect of any security he shall inform the 
depository accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The depository shall on receipt of 
intimation under sub-section (1) make appropriate entries in its records and 
shall inform the issuer.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every issuer shall, within thirty days of 
the receipt of intimation from the depository and on fulfillment of such 
conditions and on payment of such fees as may be specified by the regulations, 
issue the certificate of securities to the beneficial owner or the transferee, 
as the case may be.


</section></article> 
 The Depositories 
Act, 1996
  
 <article><number>15</number> The Bankers’ Books Evidence Act to apply to 
depositories.—The Bankers’ Books 
Evidence Act, 1891 (18 of 1891), shall apply in relation to a depository as if 
it were a bank as defined in section 2 of that Act.




</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Depositories to indemnify loss in certain 
cases.—
<section><number>1</number> Without prejudice to the 
provisions of any other law for the time being in force, any loss caused to the 
beneficial owner due to the negligence of the depository or the participant, the 
depository shall indemnify such beneficial owner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the loss due to the negligence of the 
participant under sub-section (1) is indemnified by the depository, the 
depository shall have the right to recover the same from such participant.
</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Rights and obligations of depositories, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Subject to the provisions of this Act, the rights and obligations of the 
depositories, participants and the issuers whose securities are dealt with by a 
depository shall be specified by the regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The eligibility criteria for admission of 
securities into the depository shall be specified by the regulations.
</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Power of Board to call for information and 
enquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board, on being 
satisfied that it is necessary in the public interest or in the interest of 
investors so to do, may, by order in writing,—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  call upon any issuer, depository, participant or beneficial owner to 
furnish in writing such information relating to the securities held in a 
depository as it may require; or
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  authorise any person to make an enquiry or inspection in relation to the 
affairs of the issuer, beneficial owner, depository or participant, who shall 
submit a report of such enquiry or inspection to it within such period as may be 
specified in the order.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every director, manager, partner, secretary, 
officer or employee of the depository or issuer or the participant or beneficial 
owner shall on demand produce before the person making the enquiry or inspection 
all information or such records and other documents in his custody having a 
bearing on the subject-matter of such enquiry or inspection.
</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Power of Board to give directions in certain 
cases.—Save as provided in this Act, 
if after making or causing to be made an enquiry or inspection, the Board is 
satisfied that it is necessary—
 <section>        <number>i</number>  
in the interest of investors, or orderly development of securities market; or
 </section><section>        
<number>ii</number>  to prevent the affairs of any depository or participant being conducted in 
the manner detrimental to the interests of investors or securities market,
 it may issue 
such directions,—
 <subsection>
            <number>a</number>  to any depository or participant or any person associated with 
the securities market; or
 </subsection><subsection>
            <number>b</number>  to any issuer,
 
as may be appropriate in the interest of 
investors or the securities market.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19A</number> Penalty for failure to furnish 
information, return, etc.—Any person, 
who is required under this Act or any rules or regulations or bye‑laws made 
thereunder,—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  to furnish any information, document, books, returns or report to the 
Board, fails to furnish the same within the time specified therefor, he shall be 
liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure 
continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less for each such failure;
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  to file any return or furnish any information, books or other documents 
within the time specified therefor in the regulations or the bye‑laws, fails to 
file return or furnish the same within the time specified therefor, he shall be 
liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure 
continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less;
 </section><section>       
<number>c</number>  to maintain books of account or records, fails to maintain the same, he 
shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such 
failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.]
 
 


</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19B</number> Penalty for failure to enter into 
an agreement.—If a depository or 
participant or any issuer or its agent or any person, who is registered as an 
intermediary under the provisions of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange 
Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992),  and is required under this Act or any 
rules or regulations made thereunder, to enter into an agreement, fails to enter 
into such agreement, such depository or participant or issuer or its agent or 
intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during 
which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less for every 
such failure.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19C</number> Penalty for failure to redress 
Investors’ grievances.—If any 
depository or participant or any issuer or its agent or any person, who is 
registered as an intermediary under the provisions of section 12 of the 
Securities and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992), after having been 
called upon by the Board in writing, to redress the grievances of the investors, 
fails to redress such grievances within the time specified by the Board, such 
depository or participant or issuer or its agent or intermediary shall be liable 
to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during which such failure continues 
or one crore rupees, whichever is less.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19D</number> Penalty for delay in 
dematerialisation or issue of certificate of securities.—If 
any issuer or its agent or any person, who is registered as an intermediary 
under the provisions of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange Board of India 
Act, 1992 (15 of 1992), fails to dematerialise or issue the certificate of 
securities on opting out of a depository by the investors, within the time 
specified under this Act or regulations or bye‑laws made thereunder or abets in 
delaying the process of dematerialisation or issue the certificate of securities 
on opting out of a depository of securities, such issuer or its agent or 
intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each day during 
which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19E</number> Penalty for failure to reconcile 
records.—If a depository or 
participant or any issuer or its agent or any person, who is registered as an 
intermediary under the provisions of section 12 of the Securities and Exchange 
Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992), fails to reconcile the records of 
dematerialised securities with all the securities issued by the issuer as 
specified in the regulations, such depository or participant or issuer or its 
agent or intermediary shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh rupees for each 
day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, whichever is less.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19F</number> Penalty for failure to comply with 
directions issued by Board under section 19 of the Act.—If 
any person fails to comply with the directions issued by the Board under section 
19, within the time specified by it, he shall be liable to a penalty of one lakh 
rupees for each day during which such failure continues or one crore rupees, 
whichever is less.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19G</number> Penalty for contravention where no 
separate penalty has been provided.—Whoever 
fails to comply with any provision of this Act, the rules or regulations or 
bye‑laws made or directions issued by the Board thereunder for which no separate 
penalty has been provided, shall be liable to a penalty which may extend to one 
crore rupees.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19H</number> Power to adjudicate.—
<section><number>1</number> 
For the purpose of adjudging under sections 19A, 19B, 19C, 19D, 19E, 19F and 
19G, the Board shall appoint any officer not below the rank of a Division Chief 
of the Securities and Exchange Board of India to be an adjudicating officer for 
holding an inquiry in the prescribed manner after giving any person concerned a 
reasonable opportunity of being heard for the purpose of imposing any penalty.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> While holding an inquiry, the adjudicating 
officer shall have power to summon and enforce the attendance of any person 
acquainted with the facts and circumstances of the case to give evidence or to 
produce any document, which in the opinion of the adjudicating officer, may be 
useful for or relevant to the subject-matter of the inquiry and if, on such 
inquiry, he is satisfied that the person has failed to comply with the 
provisions of any of the sections specified in sub‑section (1), he may impose 
such penalty as he thinks fit in accordance with the provisions of any of those 
sections.]
 
 


</section></article> 
 The Depositories 
Act, 1996
  
 <article>1[<number>19I</number> Factors to be taken into account by 
adjudicating officer.—While adjudging 
the quantum of penalty under section 19H, the adjudicating officer shall have 
due regard to the following factors, namely:—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  the amount of disproportionate gain or unfair advantage, wherever 
quantifiable, made as a result of the default;
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  the amount of loss caused to an investor or group of investors as a 
result of the default;
 </section><section>       
<number>c</number>  the repetitive nature of the default.]
  

</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>19J</number> Crediting sums realised by way of 
penalties to Consolidated Fund of India.—All 
sums realised by way of penalties under this Act shall be credited to the 
Consolidated Fund of India.]
 
 


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>20</number> Offences.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to any award of penalty by the adjudicating officer under this 
Act, if any person contravenes or attempts to contravene or abets the 
contravention of the provisions of this Act or of any rules or regulations or 
bye­-laws made thereunder, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term 
which may extend to ten years, or with fine, which may extend to twenty‑five 
crore rupees, or with both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any person fails to pay the penalty 
imposed by the adjudicating officer or fails to comply with any of his 
directions or orders, he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than one month but which may extend to ten years, or with 
fine, which may extend to twenty‑five crore rupees, or with both.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Offences by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company, every person 
who at the time the offence was committed was in charge of, and was responsible 
to, the company for the conduct of the business of the company, as well as the 
company, shall be deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly:
 
Provided that nothing contained in this 
sub-section shall render any such person liable to any punishment provided in 
this Act, if he proves that the offence was committed without his knowledge or 
that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the commission of such 
offence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
sub-section (1), where an offence under this Act has been committed by a company 
and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the consent or 
connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part of, any director, 
manager, secretary or other officer of the company, such director, manager, 
secretary or other officer shall also be deemed to be guilty of the offence and 
shall be liable to be proceeded against and punished accordingly.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  “company” means any body corporate and includes a firm or other association 
of individuals; and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> 
“director”, in relation to a firm, means a partner in the firm.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22</number> Cognizance of offences by courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No court shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act or any 
rules or any regulations or bye‑laws made thereunder, save on a complaint made 
by the Central Government or State Government or the Securities and Exchange 
Board of India or by any person.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No court inferior to that of a Court of 
Session shall try any offence punishable under this Act.]
 
 





</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22A</number> Composition of certain 
offences.—Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal 
Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), any offence punishable under this Act, not being an 
offence punishable with imprisonment only, or with imprisonment and also with 
fine, may either before or after the institution of any proceeding, be 
compounded by a Securities Appellate Tribunal or a court before which such 
proceedings are pending.]
 
 



</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>22B</number> Power to grant immunity.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, on recommendation by the Board, if the Central 
Government is satisfied, that any person, who is alleged to have violated any of 
the provisions of this Act or the rules or the regulations made thereunder, has 
made a full and true disclosure in respect of alleged violation, grant to such 
person, subject to such conditions as it may think fit to impose, immunity from 
prosecution for any offence under this Act, or the rules or the regulations made 
thereunder or also from the imposition of any penalty under this Act with 
respect to the alleged violation:
 
Provided that no such immunity shall be granted 
by the Central Government in cases where the proceedings for the prosecution for 
any such offence have been instituted before the date of receipt of application 
for grant of such immunity:
 
Provided further that recommendation of the 
Board under this sub‑section shall not be binding upon the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> An immunity granted to a person under 
sub‑section (1) may, at any time, be withdrawn by the Central Government, if it 
is satisfied that such person had, in the course of the proceedings, not 
complied with the condition on which the immunity was granted or had given false 
evidence, and thereupon such person may be tried for the offence with respect to 
which the immunity was granted or for any other offence of which he appears to 
have been guilty in connection with the contravention and shall also become 
liable to the imposition of any penalty under this Act to which such person 
would have been liable, had not such immunity been granted.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Appeals.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any person aggrieved by 

1[an order of the Board made before the 
commencement of the Securities Laws (Second Amendment) Act, 1999] under this 
Act, or the regulations made thereunder may prefer an appeal to the Central 
Government within such time as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal shall be admitted if it is 
preferred after the expiry of the period prescribed therefor:
 
Provided that an appeal may be admitted after 
the expiry of the period prescribed therefor if the appellant satisfies the 
Central Government that he had sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal 
within the prescribed period.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every appeal made under this section shall 
be made in such form and shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed 
against and by such fees as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The procedure for disposing of an appeal 
shall be such as may be prescribed:
 
Provided that before disposing of an appeal, the 
appellant shall be given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>23A</number> Appeal to Securities Appellate 
Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> Save as provided in 
sub-section (2), any person aggrieved by an order of the Board made, on and 
after the commencement of the Securities Laws (Second Amendment) Act, 1999 (32 
of 1999), under this Act, or the regulations made thereunder 

2[or by an order made by an adjudicating 
officer under this Act], may prefer an appeal to a Securities Appellate Tribunal 
having jurisdiction in the matter.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No appeal shall lie to the Securities 
Appellate Tribunal from an order made by the Board with the consent of the 
parties.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every appeal under sub-section (1) shall be 
filed within a period of forty-five days from the date on which a copy of the 
order made by the Board is received by the person referred to in sub-section (1) 
and it shall be in such form and be accompanied by such fee as may be 
prescribed:
 
Provided that the Securities Appellate Tribunal 
may entertain an appeal after the expiry of the said period of forty-five days 
if it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not filing it within that 
period.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of an appeal under sub-section 
(1), the Securities Appellate Tribunal may, after giving the parties to the 
appeal an opportunity of being heard, pass such orders thereon as it thinks fit, 
confirming, modifying or setting aside the order appealed against.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Securities Appellate Tribunal shall send 
a copy of every order made by it to the Board and parties to the appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The appeal filed before the Securities 
Appellate Tribunal under sub-section (1) shall be dealt with by it as 
expeditiously as possible and endeavour shall be made by it to dispose of the 
appeal finally within six months from the date of receipt of the appeal.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>23B</number> Procedure and powers of Securities 
Appellate Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Securities Appellate Tribunal shall not be bound by the procedure laid down by 
the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) but shall be guided by the 
principles of natural justice and, subject to the other provisions of this Act 
and of any rules, the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall have powers to 
regulate their own procedure including the places at which they have their 
sittings.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Securities Appellate Tribunal shall 
have, for the purpose of discharging their functions under this Act, the same 
powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 
of 1908), while trying a suit, in respect of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  summoning and enforcing the attendance of any person and examining him on 
oath;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  requiring the discovery and production of documents;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>c</number>  receiving evidence on affidavits;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>d</number>  issuing commissions for the examination of witnesses or documents;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>e</number>  reviewing its decisions;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>f</number>  dismissing an application for default or deciding it ex parte;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>g</number>  setting aside any order of dismissal of any application for default or any 
order passed by it ex parte; and 
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>h</number>  any other matter which may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every proceeding before the Securities 
Appellate Tribunal shall be deemed to be a judicial proceeding within the 
meaning of sections 193 and 228, and for the purposes of section 196 of the 
Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) and the Securities Appellate Tribunal shall be 
deemed to be a civil court for all the purposes of section 195 and Chapter XXVI 
of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>23C</number> Right to legal representation.—The 
appellant may either appear in person or authorise one or more chartered 
accountants or company secretaries or cost accountants or legal practitioners or 
any of its officers to present his or its case before the Securities Appellate 
Tribunal.
 
Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this section,—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  “chartered accountant” means a chartered accountant as defined in clause 
(b) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Chartered Accountants Act, 1949 (38 
of 1949) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of 
section 6 of that Act;
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  “company secretary” means a company secretary as defined in clause (c) of 
sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Company Secretaries Act, 1980 (56 of 1980) 
and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of section 
6 of that Act;
 </section><section>       
<number>c</number>  “cost accountant” means a cost accountant as defined in clause (b) of 
sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Cost and Works Accountants Act, 1959 (23 of 
1959) and who has obtained a certificate of practice under sub-section (1) of 
section 6 of that Act;
 </section><section>       
<number>d</number>  “legal practitioner” means an advocate, vakil or an attorney of any High 
Court, and includes a pleader in practice.]



</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>23D</number> Limitation.—The 
provisions of the Limitation Act, 1963 (36 of 1963) shall, as far as may be, 
apply to an appeal made to a Securities Appellate Tribunal.]



</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>23E</number> Civil court not to have 
jurisdiction.—No civil court shall 
have jurisdiction to entertain any suit or proceeding in respect of any matter 
which a Securities Appellate Tribunal is empowered by or under this Act to 
determine and no injunction shall be granted by any court or other authority in 
respect of any action taken or to be taken in pursuance of any power conferred 
by or under this Act.]


</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>23F</number> Appeal to Supreme Court.—Any 
person aggrieved by any decision or order of the Securities Appellate Tribunal 
may file an appeal to the Supreme Court within sixty days from the date of 
communication of the decision or order of the Securities Appellate Tribunal to 
him on any question of law arising out of such order:
 
Provided that the Supreme Court may, if it is 
satisfied that the appellant was prevented by sufficient cause from filing the 
appeal within the said period, allow it to be filed within a further period not 
exceeding sixty days.]
 
 





</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>24</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:—
 
        1[(a)  
the manner of inquiry under sub‑section (1) of section 19H;
 <subsection>      <number>aa</number>  
the time within which an appeal may be preferred under sub‑section (1) of 
section 23;]
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  the form in which an appeal may be preferred, under sub-section (3) of 
section 23 and the fees payable in respect of such appeal;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>c</number>  the procedure for disposing of an appeal under sub-section (4) of section 
23;
 
2[(d)  
the form in which an appeal may be filed before the Securities Appellate 
Tribunal under section 23A and the fees payable in respect of such appeal.]
 
 





</subsection></section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>25</number> Power of Board to make regulations.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Without prejudice to the provisions contained in section 30 of the Securities 
and Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992), the Board may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make regulations consistent with the 
provisions of this Act and the rules made thereunder to carry out the purposes 
of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing power, such regulations may provide for—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  the form in which record is to be maintained under clause (i) of 
sub-section (1) of section 2;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  the form in which the certificate of commencement of business shall be 
issued under sub-section (2) of section 3;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number> 
the manner in which the certificate of security shall be surrendered under 
sub-section (1) of section 6;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>d</number>  the manner of creating a pledge or hypothecation in respect of security 
owned by a beneficial owner under sub-section (1) of section 12;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>e</number>  the conditions and the fees payable with respect to the issue of 
certificate of securities under sub-section (3) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>f</number>  the rights and obligations of the depositories, participants and the 
issuers under sub-section (1) of section 17;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>g</number>  the eligibility criteria for admission of securities in the depository 
under sub-section (2) of section 17.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>26</number> Power of depositories to make bye-laws.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A depository shall, with the previous approval of the Board, make bye-laws 
consistent with the provisions of this Act and the regulations.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the 
generality of the foregoing power, such bye-laws shall provide for—
 <subsection>       
<number>a</number>  the eligibility criteria for admission and removal of securities in the 
depository;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>b</number>  the conditions subject to which the securities shall be dealt with;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>c</number>  the eligibility criteria for admission of any person as a participant;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>d</number>  the manner and procedure for dematerialisation of securities;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>e</number>  the procedure for transactions within the depository;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>f</number>  the manner in which securities shall be dealt with or withdrawn from a 
depository;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>g</number>  the procedure for ensuring safeguards to protect the interests of 
participants and beneficial owners;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>h</number>  the conditions of admission into and withdrawal from a participant by a 
beneficial owner;
 </subsection><subsection>        <number>i</number>  
the procedure for conveying information to the participants and beneficial 
owners on dividend declaration, shareholder meetings and other matters of 
interest to the beneficial owners;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>j</number>  the manner of distribution of dividends, interest and monetary benefits 
received from the company among beneficial owners;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>k</number>  the manner of creating pledge or hypothecation in respect of securities 
held with a depository;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>l</number>  inter se rights and obligations among the depository, issuer, 
participants and beneficial owners;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>m</number>  the manner and the periodicity of furnishing information to the Board, 
issuer and other persons;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>n</number>  the procedure for resolving disputes involving depository, issuer, company 
or a beneficial owner;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>o</number>  the procedure for proceeding against the participant committing breach of 
the regulations and provisions for suspension and expulsion of participants from 
the depository and cancellation of agreements entered with the depository;
 </subsection><subsection>       
<number>p</number>  the internal control standards including procedure for auditing, reviewing 
and monitoring.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Board considers it expedient so to 
do, it may, by order in writing, direct a depository to make any bye-laws or to 
amend or revoke any bye-laws already made within such period as it may specify 
in this behalf.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If the depository fails or neglects to 
comply with such order within the specified period, the Board may make the 
bye-laws or amend or revoke the bye-laws made either in the form specified in 
the order or with such modifications thereof as the Board thinks fit.


</section></article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Rules and regulations to be laid before 
Parliament.—Every rule and every 
regulation made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or regulation or both Houses agree that the 
rule or regulation should not be made, the rule or regulation shall thereafter 
have effect, only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; 
so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice 
to the validity of anything previously done under that rule or regulation.
</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Application of other laws not barred.—The 
provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of, any 
other law for the time being in force relating to the holding and transfer of 
securities.
</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Removal of difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make such 
provisions not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act as appear to it to 
be necessary or expedient for removing the difficulty:
 
Provided that no order shall be made under this 
section after the expiry of a period of two years from the commencement of this 
Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order made under this section shall be 
laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of Parliament.
</section></article> 
 The Depositories 
Act, 1996
  
 <article><number>30</number> Amendments to certain enactments.—The enactments specified in the Schedule to this Act 
shall be amended in the manner provided therein.</article> 
 
The 
Depositories Act, 1996
 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Repeal and Saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Depositories (Third) Ordinance, 1996 (Ord. 28 of 1996) is hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done 
or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to have been done 
or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act. 
</section></article><form>
 

The Depositories 
Act, 1996
 

 
 

THE 
SCHEDULE
 

(See 
section 30)
 

AMENDMENTS 
TO CERTAIN ENACTMENTS
 

PART I
 

AMENDMENT 
TO THE INDIAN STAMP ACT, 1899 (2 OF 1899)
 

Amendment
 

After section 8, 
the following section shall be inserted, namely:—
 

            
‘8A. Securities not liable to stamp duty.—Notwithstanding anything 
contained in this Act,—
 

        
(a)  an issuer, by the issue of securities to one or more depositories 
shall, in respect to such issue, be chargeable with duty on the total amount of 
security issued by it and such securities need not be stamped;
 

        
(b)  where an issuer issues certificate of security under sub-section (3) 
of section 14 of the Depositories Act, 1996, on such certificate duty shall be 
payable as is payable on the issue of duplicate certificate under this Act;
 

        
(c)  transfer of registered ownership of shares from a person to a 
depository or from a depository to a beneficial owner shall not be liable to any 
stamp duty;
 

        
(d)  the transfer of beneficial ownership of shares, such shares being 
shares of a company dealt with by a depository shall not be liable to duty under 
article 62 of Schedule I of this Act.
 

            
Explanation.—For the purposes of this section, the expressions “beneficial 
owner”, “depository”, and “issuer” shall have the meanings respectively assigned 
to them in clauses (a), (e) and (f) of sub-section (1) of section 2 of the 
Depositories Act, 1996.’.
 

PART II
 

AMENDMENTS 
TO THE COMPANIES ACT, 1956 (1 OF 1956)
 

Amendments
 

    1.  In 
section 2, after clause (45A), the following clause shall be inserted, 
namely:—
 

            
‘(45B) “Securities and Exchange Board of India” means the Securities and 
Exchange Board of India established under section 3 of the Securities and 
Exchange Board of India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992).’.
 

    2.  
Interpretation of certain words and expressions.—After section 2, the following 
section shall be inserted, namely:—
 

            
“2A. Words and expressions used and not defined in this Act but defined in the 
Depositories Act, 1996, shall have the same meanings respectively assigned to 
them in that Act.’’.
 

    3.  In 
section 41, after sub-section (2), the following sub-section shall be inserted, 
namely:—
 

            
“(3) Every person holding equity share capital of company and whose name is 
entered as beneficial owner in the records of the depository shall be deemed to 
be a member of the concerned company.”.
 

    4.  In 
section 49, in sub-section (5), after clause (b), the following clause shall be 
inserted, namely:—
 

            
“(c) from holding investments in the name of a depository when such investments 
are in the form of securities held by the company as a beneficial owner.”.
 

    5.  In 
section 51, the following proviso shall be inserted, namely:—
 

            
“Provided that where the securities are held in a depository, the records of the 
beneficial ownership may be served by such depository on the company by means of 
electronic mode or by delivery of floppies or discs.”.
 

    6.  
Section 83 shall be omitted.
 

    7.  In 
section 108, after sub-section (2), the following sub-section shall be inserted, 
namely:—
 

            
“(3) Nothing contained in this section shall apply to transfer of security 
effected by the transferor and the transferee both of whom are entered as 
beneficial owners in the records of a depository.”.
 

    8.  In 
section 111, after sub-section (13), the following sub-section shall be 
inserted, namely:—
 

            
‘(14) In this section, “company” means a private company and includes a private 
company which had become a public company by virtue of section 43A of this 
Act.’.
 

    9.  
After section 111, the following section shall be inserted, namely:—
 

            
“111A. Rectification of Register on Transfer.—(1) In this section, unless 
the context otherwise requires, “company” means a company other than a company 
referred to in sub-section (14) of section 111 of this Act.
 

            
(2) Subject to the provisions of this section, the shares or debentures and any 
interest therein of a company shall be freely transferable.
 

            
(3) The Company Law Board may, on an application made by a depository, company, 
participant or investor or the Securities and Exchange Board of India within two 
months from the date of transfer of any shares or debentures held by a 
depository or from the date on which the instrument of transfer or the 
intimation of transmission was delivered to the company, as the case may be, 
after such inquiry as it thinks fit, direct any company or depository to rectify 
register or records if the transfer of the shares or debentures is in 
contravention of any of the provisions of the Securities and Exchange Board of 
India Act, 1992 (15 of 1992), or regulations made thereunder or the Sick 
Industrial Companies (Special Provisions) Act, 1985 (1 of 1986).
 

            
(4) The Company Law Board, while acting under sub-section (3), may at its 
discretion make such interim order as to suspend the voting rights before making 
or completing such enquiry.
 

            
(5) The provisions of this section shall not restrict the right of a holder of 
shares or debentures, or transfer such shares or debentures and any person 
acquiring such shares or debentures shall be entitled to voting rights unless 
the voting rights have been suspended by an order of the Company Law Board.
 

            
(6) Notwithstanding anything contained in this section, any further transfer, 
during the pendency of the application with the Company Law Board, of shares or 
debentures shall entitle the transferee to voting rights unless the voting 
rights in respect of such transferee have also been suspended.
 

            
(7) The provisions of sub-sections (5), (7), (9), (10) and (12) of section 111 
shall, so far as may be, apply to the proceedings before the Company Law Board 
under this section as they apply to the proceedings under that section.’.
 

  10.  
In section 113, after sub-section (3), the following sub-section shall be 
inserted namely:—
 

            
“(4) Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1), where the securities 
are dealt in a depository, the company shall intimate the details of allotment 
of securities to depository immediately on allotment of such securities.”.
 

  11.  
In section 150, in sub-section (1), in clause (b), the words “distinguishing 
each share by its number” shall be omitted.
 

  12.  
In section 152, in sub-section (1), in clause (b), the words “distinguishing 
each debenture by its number” shall be omitted.
 

  13.  
After section 152, the following section shall be inserted, namely:—
 


     “152A. Register and index of beneficial owners to be 
of debenture holder.—The register and index of beneficial owners maintained 
by a depository under section 11 of the Depositories Act, 1996, shall be deemed 
to be an index of members and register and index of debenture holders, as the 
case may be, for the purposes of this Act.”.
 

  14.  
In Schedule II, in Part II, in clause C, after sub-clause 9, the following 
sub-clause shall be inserted, namely:—
 

            
“9A. The details of opinion to subscribe for securities to be dealt with in a 
depository.”.
 

 
 

PART III
 

AMENDMENTS 
TO THE SECURITIES CONTRACTS  
(REGULATION) ACT, 1956 (42 OF 1956)
 

Amendments
 

    1.  In 
section 2, for clause (i), the following clause shall be substituted, 
namely:—
 

        
“(i)  “spot delivery” contract means a contract which provides for,—
 

             
(a) actual delivery of securities and the payment of a price therefor either on 
the same day as the date of the contract or on the next day, the actual periods 
taken for the despatch of the securities or the remittance of money therefor 
through the post being excluded from the computation of the period aforesaid if 
the parties to the contract do not reside in the same town or locality;
 

             
(b) transfer of the securities by the depository from the account of a 
beneficial owner to the account of another beneficial owner when such securities 
are dealt with by a depository.’’.
 

    2.  
Section 22A shall be omitted.
 

PART IV
 

AMENDMENT 
TO THE INCOME-TAX ACT, 1961 (43 OF 1961)
 

Amendment
 

In section 45, 
after sub-section (2), the following sub-section shall be inserted, namely:—
 

            
“(2A) Where any person has had at any time during the previous year any 
beneficial interest in any securities, then, any profits or gains arising from 
transfer made by the depository or participant of such beneficial interest in 
respect of securities shall be chargeable to income-tax as the income of the 
beneficial owner of the previous year in which such transfer took place and 
shall not be regarded as income of the depository who is deemed to be the 
registered owner of securities by virtue of sub-section (1) of section 10 of the 
Depositories Act, 1996, and for the purposes of—
 

         
(i)  section 48; and
 

        
(ii)  proviso to clause (42A) of section 2,
 

         
the cost of acquisition and the period of holding of any securities shall be 
determined on the basis of the first-in-first-out method.
 

            
Explanation.—For the purposes of this sub-section, the expressions 
“beneficial owner”, “depository” and “security” shall have the meanings 
respectively assigned to them in clauses (a), (e) and (l) of sub-section (1) of 
section 2 of the Depositories Act, 1996.”.
 

PART V
 

AMENDMENT 
TO THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS 
(PROHIBITION) ACT, 1988 (45 OF 1988)
 

Amendment
 

In section 3, 
for sub-section (2), the following sub-section shall be substituted, 
namely:—
 

         
“(2) Nothing in sub-section (1) shall apply to—
 

        
(a)  the purchase of property by any person in the name of his wife or 
unmarried daughter and it shall be presumed, unless the contrary is proved, that 
the said property had been purchased for the benefit of the wife or the 
unmarried daughter;
 

        
(b)  the securities held by a—
 

              
(i) depository as a registered owner under sub-section (1) of section 10 of the 
Depositories Act, 1996;
 

             
(ii) participant as an agent of a depository.
 

            
Explanation.— The expressions “depository” and “participant” shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in clauses (e) and (g) of sub-section (1) 
of section 2 of the Depositories Act, 1996.”.
 

PART VI
 

AMENDMENTS 
TO THE SECURITIES AND EXCHANGE 
BOARD OF INDIA ACT, 1992 (15 OF 1992)
 

Amendments
 

    1.  In 
section 2, in sub-section (2), for the words, brackets and figures “the 
Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956)”, the words, brackets 
and figures “the Securities Contracts (Regulation) Act, 1956 (42 of 1956), or 
the Depositories Act, 1996”, shall be substituted.
 

    2.  In 
section 11, in sub section (2), in clause (ba), for the words “depositories, 
custodians”, the words “depositories, participants, custodians” shall be 
substituted.
 

    3.  In 
section 12, in sub-section (1A), for the words “depository, custodian”, at both 
the places where they occur, the words “depository, participant, custodian” 
shall be substituted.
 

    4.  In 
section 16, in sub-section (1), for the words “this Act”, the words and figures 
“this Act or the Depositories Act, 1996” shall be substituted.</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>