<act><title>
THE
NEWSPAPER (PRICE AND PAGE) ACT, 1956</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and duration.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called The Newspaper (Price and Page) Act, 1956.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[***]
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
“daily newspaper” means a newspaper which is published on not less
than six days in a week, and includes any supplement of special edition of such
newspaper;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“newspaper” means any printed periodical work containing public news
or comments on public news appearing at intervals of not more than a week.
   


   


  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>3</number>
Power to regulate prices and pages of newspapers, etc.—
<section><number>1</number>
If the Central Government is of opinion that for the purpose of preventing
unfair competition among newspapers so that newspapers generally and in
particular, newspapers with smaller resources and those published in Indian
languages may have fuller opportunities of freedom of expression, it is
necessary or expedient so to do, the Central Government may, from time to time,
by notification in the Official Gazette, make an order providing for the
regulation of the prices charged for newspapers in relation to their maximum or
minimum number of pages, sizes or areas and for the space to be allotted for
advertising matter in relation to other matters therein. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
An order under this section—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
may be made in relation to newspapers generally or in relation to any
class of newspapers;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
may contain different provisions for daily newspapers and newspapers
appearing at other periodical intervals and for different classes of newspapers,
and may, in particular, make separate provisions for weekly editions of daily
newspapers whether appearing under the same title or not, and also for
supplements or special editions of newspapers issued on special occasions;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>
shall be made relatable to such period of time as the Central Government
may deem reasonable;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number>
may provide for incidental or supplementary matters.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number>
An order under this section shall be made with due regard to the need for
reasonable flexibility with reference to the fall of news, the flow of
advertisements and other matters connected with the normal working of
newspapers.
 </section><section><number>4</number>
Before making any order under this section, the Central Government shall consult
associations of publishers, and such publishers likely to be affected by the
order as it may think fit with respect to the action proposed to be taken.
   



 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>4</number>
Prohibition of publication and sale of newspapers in contravention of order
under section 3.—No newspaper shall
be published or sold in the territories to which this Act extends in
contravention of any of the provisions of an order made under section 3.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>5</number>
Returns to be furnished by newspapers.—For
the purpose of verifying whether an order made under section 3 is being complied
with or not, the Press Registrar appointed under the Press and Registration of
Books Act, 1867, may, from time to time, direct the publisher of any newspaper
to which such an order applies to furnish to him such weekly returns and
statistics with respect to any of the particulars referred to in section 3 as
the Press Registrar may, from time to time, require and the publisher of every
newspaper shall comply with such direction. 
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>6</number>
Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any newspaper is
published or sold in contravention of 
section 4, the publisher of the newspaper shall, on first conviction, be
punishable with fine which may extend to one thousand rupees and on any second
or subsequent conviction, with fine which may extend to two thousand rupees. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
If the publisher of any newspaper—
 <subsection><number>a</number>
refuses or neglects to comply with any direction of the Press Registrar
given under section 5; or
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>
furnishes or causes to be furnished to the Press Registrar may weekly
returns or statistics which he has reason to believe to be false,
 he
shall be punishable with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees.
   

  



 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

   


 <article><number>7</number>
Cognizance of offences.—No court
shall take cognizance of any offence punishable under this Act except upon a
complaint in writing by the Press Registrar appointed under the Press and
Registration of Books Act, 1867, or by any officer authorised by him in writing
in this behalf.
  
 
  


</article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>
Sub-section (3) providing five years’ duration to the Act was omitted
by Act 36 of 1961 (5-9-1961).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>