<act><tid>53524</tid>
<title>THE SALT CESS ACT, <year>1953</year></title>

ACT NO. 49 OF <year>1953</year>
[ 26th December, <year>1953</year>.]

An Act to provide for the levy and collection of a cess on salt for 
the purpose of raising funds to meet the expenses incurred on the salt 
organisation maintained by Government and on the measures taken by 
Government in connection with the manufacture, supply and distribution 
of salt.





<article><tid>1379934</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1058636</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Salt Cess Act, <year>1953</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>712649</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>.

</section>

<section><tid>571021</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on such <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> date as the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1971826</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1193528</tid>
<number>a</number>" manufacture" in relation to salt includes collection, 
removal, preparation, steeping, evaporation, boiling or 
any one or more of these processes, the separation or 
purification of salt obtained in the manufacture of 
saltpetre, the separation of salt from earth or other 
substance so as to produce alimentary salt, and the 
excavation or removal of natural saline deposits or 
efflorescence; and the word manufacturer' shall be 
construed accordingly and shall include not only a 
person who employs hired labour in the production or 
manufacture of a salt but also any person who engages 
in its production or manufacture on his own account if 
the salt is intended for sale.
Explanation.-- In this clause, saltpetre' 
includes rasi sajji, and all other substances 
manufactured from saline earth, and kharinun and 
every form of sulphate or carbonate of soda;


</section>

<section><tid>1083085</tid>
<number>b</number>' salt' includes swamp salt, spontaneous salt, and salt 
or saline solutions made or produced from any saline 
substances or from salt earth;
The Act comes into force in Pondicherry on 1. 10. <year>1963</year> vide Reg. 7 of 
<year>1963</year>, s. 3 and Sch. I.

Extended to and brought into force in Dadra and Nagar Haveli (w. e. f.  
  1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I. and in Goa, Daman and 
Diu (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1969</year>) by notificaation No. So. 2872, Dated 4- 6- <year>1969</year>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>724</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" except the State of Jammu and Kashmir" omitted by Act 
62 of <year>1956</year>, s. 2 and Sch. 
2  2nd January, <year>1954</year>, vide Notification No. S. R. O. 2378, dated the 
29th December, <year>1953</year>, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary. <year>1953</year>, Pt. 
II, Sec. 3, p. 3601.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>1677020</tid>
<number>c</number>" salt factory" includes--

<subsection><tid>1064048</tid>
<number>i</number>a place used or intended to be used in 
the manufacture of salt and all embankments, 
reservoirs, condensing and evaporating pans, 
buildings, and waste places situated within the 
limits of such place, as defined from time to time 
for the purposes of the Central Excises and Salt 
Act, <year>1944</year>; (1 of <year>1944</year>)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1216234</tid>
<number>ii</number>all drying grounds and storage platforms 
and storehouses appurtaining to any such place;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>733690</tid>
<number>iii</number>land on which salt is spontaneously 
produced;
<footcitenum>1</footcitenum>

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1511269</tid>
<number>e</number>" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this 
Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1724307</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Levy and collection of cess on salt. There shall be levied 
and collected in such manner as may be prescribed, a cess in the 
nature of an excise duty at the rate of fourteen naye paise per forty 
kilograms on all salt manufactured in India in any salt factory, 
whether owned by Government or not.]


</article>



<article><tid>678185</tid>
<number> 4</number> Application of proceeds of cess. The proceeds of the duty 
levied under this Act, reduced by the cost of collection as determined 
by the Central Government, shall, if Parliament by appropriation made 
by law in this behalf so provides, be utilised on all or any of the 
following objects, namely:--
<section><tid>1053171</tid>
<number>a</number>meeting the expenditue incurred in connection with the 
salt organisation maintained by the Central Government;

</section>

<section><tid>1182045</tid>
<number>b</number>meeting the cost of measures taken in connection with 
the manufacture, supply and distribution of salt by 
Union agencies and the regulation and control of the 
manufacture, supply and distribution of salt by other 
agencies; and in particular, measures for--

<subsection><tid>1376283</tid>
<number>i</number>the establishment and maintenance of 
research stations and model salt farms;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1056776</tid>
<number>ii</number>the establishment, maintenance and 
expansion of salt factories;
<pagefootnote><pagenum>725</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Certain words omitted by Act 34 of <year>1961</year>, s. 2. 
2 Cl. (d) omitted by s. 2, ibid. 
3 Subs. by s. 3. ibid., for s. 3.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</subsection>

<subsection><tid>27433</tid>
<number>iii</number>fixing the grades of salt;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1207973</tid>
<number>iv</number>promoting and encouraging co- operative 
effort among manufacturers of salt; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>444926</tid>
<number>v</number>promoting the welfare of labour employed 
in the salt industry.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1532109</tid>
<number> 5</number> Validation of charges levied on salt before the commencement 
of this Act. The charge in respect of the manufacture or production of 
salt imposed by the rule made by the Central Government under section 
 37 of the Central Excises and Salt Act, <year>1944</year> (1 of <year>1944</year>) and 
published with the notification of the former Finance Department 
 (Revenue Division) No. 3 dated the 29th March, <year>1947</year>, shall be deemed 
to have been levied under this Act as if this Act was in force on 
the day on which the charge was so imposed and accordingly,--
<section><tid>848162</tid>
<number>a</number>any sum paid or payable by way of such charge shall be 
deemed to heve been paid or payable in accordance with 
the law; and

</section>

<section><tid>252168</tid>
<number>b</number>no claim shall lie in any Court for the refund of any 
such so paid.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>720653</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>961387</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the 
purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>676737</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the 
foregoing power, such rules may provide for--

<subsection><tid>874703</tid>
<number>a</number>the assessment and collection of the cess levied under 
this Act;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1707511</tid>
<number>b</number>the determination of the cost of collection of the cess;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>868562</tid>
<number>c</number>the manner in which accounts relating to the proceeds of 
the cess shall be maintained;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>857507</tid>
<number>d</number>the manner in which the proceeds of the cess may be 
applied on the object specified in section 4;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1581651</tid>
<number>e</number>the exemption from the whole or any part of the cess 
levied under this Act--

<subsubsection><tid>1581018</tid>
<number>i</number>in respect of salt exported from India;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1401003</tid>
<number>ii</number>in respect of salt manufactured by any 
specified categories of small manufacturers; and

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1166261</tid>
<number>iii</number>in respect of salt utilised in the 
manufacture of any other product of industry.

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>983118</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this 
section shall be laid as soon as may be after it is made before each
<pagefootnote><pagenum>726</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 34 of <year>1961</year>, s. 4.


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid] both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be no effect, as 
the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>727</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 4 of <year>1986</year>, s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15. 5. <year>1986</year>.)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>