<act><title>THE BUREAU OF INDIAN STANDARDS RULES, 
19871</title> 
 
The Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 19871
 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Bureau of Indian Standards Rules, 1987.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into force on the date 
of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 





</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>—In these rules, unless the context 
otherwise requires,— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> “Act” means the Bureau of Indian Standards Act, 1986 (63 of 1986); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> “Advisory Committee” means an Advisory Committee constituted by the 
  Bureau under sub-section (1) of section 5; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> “applicant” means a person who has applied to the Bureau for a Licence 
  <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[or Registration]; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[<number>cc</number> “Consultant” means an expert or an organization of 
  experts engaged for a specific task relating to standards formulation to whom 
  a fee is payable by the Bureau;] 
 </section><section><number>d</number> “Committee” means a Technical Committee constituted by the Bureau under 
  sub-section (3) of section 5 and includes a Division Council, Sectional 
  Committee, Sub-committee, Panel or any other committee; 
 </section><section><number>e</number> “Director-General” means Director-General of the Bureau; 
 </section><section><number>f</number> “Form” means a form set out in the Appendix hereto; 
 </section><section><number>g</number> “licensee” means a person to whom a licence has been granted under the 
  Act; 
 </section><section><number>h</number> “President” means the President of the Bureau; 
 </section><section><footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[<number>ha</number> ‘registration' means permission granted under rule 16C to 
  use the words “Self declaration—Conforming to IS…………...” on any article 
  notified under clause (fa) of rule 13;] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>hb</number> ‘Registered User' means a person who is granted 
  registration under rule 16C;] 
 <subsection><number>i</number> “section” means a section of the Act; 
 </subsection></section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>ia</number> ‘Self declaration' for the purpose of Chapter IVA means 
  the declaration made by the Registered User that the article for which 
  registration has been granted conforms to the relevant Indian Standard;] 
 </section><section><number>j</number> “Vice-President” means the Vice-President of the Bureau; 
 </section><section><number>k</number> “year” means the financial year commencing on the first day of April; 
  
 </section><section><number>l</number> words and expressions used in the rules and not defined but defined in 
  the Act, shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act. 
</section>




</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Constitution of the Bureau. </title>— <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> [
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau shall consist of the following members, namely:— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the Minister in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having administrative control of the Bureau who shall be ex-officio  President of the Bureau; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Minister of State or a Deputy Minister, if any, in the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having administrative control of the Bureau who shall be ex-officio  Vice-President of the Bureau, and where there is no such Minister of State or Deputy Minister, such person as may be nominated by the Central Government to be the Vice-President of the Bureau; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> the Secretary to the Government of India in charge of the Ministry or Department of the Central Government having administrative control of the Bureau ex-officio ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> the Director General of the Bureau, ex-officio ; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> two Members of Parliament of whom one shall be from the House of the People and one from the Council of States; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> three persons representing the Ministries and Departments of the Central Government dealing with important subjects of interest to the Bureau; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number> five representatives—one each from five zones of State Governments and the Union Territories on rotation basis who shall be,— 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> the Minister in charge of the Department having administrative control over quality and standards in the case of States and Union Territories having a Council of Ministers; and 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> the Administrator or the Chief Executive Councillor, as the case may be, in the case of Union Territories, not having a Council of Ministers; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>h</number> two persons either representing recognized Consumer Organizations which in the opinion of the Central Government are active and effective in their operations, or are in the opinion of that Government are capable of representing consumer interests; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>i</number> one person, who, in the opinion of the Central Government, is capable of representing farmers' interests, to be nominated from amongst farmers or farmers associations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>j</number> five persons representing the industry and trade and their associations and public sector enterprises to be chosen as follows:— 
 <subsubsection><number>i</number> Presidents of three industry associations or federations of all-India level; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number> Chief Executive of one Central or State Public Sector Enterprise related to subjects of importance to the Bureau; 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>iii</number> Chairman or Managing Director of one industrial organization other than the public sector who is awardee for the Rajiv Gandhi National Quality Award; 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>k</number> three persons representing the scientific and research institutions, technical educational and professional organizations related to subjects of importance to the Bureau.] 
 <subsubsection><footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[<number>IA</number> The term of office of a member shall continue so long as he holds the office by virtue of which he is such a member.] 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> The Bureau may, on the recommendation of the Director-General, <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[associate persons not exceeding fifteen to assist] or advise in the fields of science and technology including environmental control, energy conservation, import substitution, transfer of technology and other areas of emerging technology. 

























</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Terms of office of members. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Members appointed under clause (e) to clause (m) of sub-rule (1) of rule 3 shall hold office for a period of two years and shall be eligible for re-appointment. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> When a member appointed under sub-rule (1) of rule 3 desires to resign from membership of the Bureau, he shall forward his letter of resignation under his own hand to the Central Government and such resignation shall take effect from the date of its acceptance by the Central Government or on the expiry of a period of one month from the date of its receipts by the Central Government, whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> When a vacancy occurs by resignation of a member under sub-rule (2) or otherwise, the Central Government shall take steps to <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> [fill the vacancy within a period of six months from the date of its occurrence by making an appointment] from amongst the category of persons to which the person who vacated the office belonged and the person so appointed shall hold office for the remainder of the term of office of the member in whose place he is appointed. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> A person shall be disqualified for being appointed as a member or shall be removed from membership by the Central Government if he— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> has been convicted and sentenced to imprisonment for an offence, which in the opinion of the Central Government, involves moral turpitude; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> is an undischarged insolvent; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> is of unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> has been removed or dismissed from the service of the Government or a body corporate owned or controlled by the Government; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> has in the opinion of the Central Government such financial or other interest in the Bureau as is likely to affect prejudicially the discharge by him of his functions as a member: 
 Provided that no member shall be removed on the ground that he has become subject of the disqualification mentioned under clause (e) of sub-rule (4) of unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard in the matter. 
  



</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Proceedings of the Bureau. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The President, or in his absence the Vice-President, shall preside at the meetings of the Bureau. In the absence of both the President and the Vice-President, the members present at the meeting shall elect one from amongst themselves to preside over the meeting. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> At least one meeting of the Bureau shall be held every year. The President may at his discretion convene more than one meeting in a year if he considers it necessary.] 
 </section><section><number>3</number> A notice of not less than twenty-one days from the date of issue shall ordinarily be given to every member for each meeting of the Bureau, if it is necessary to convene an emergency meeting, a notice of not less than seven days shall be given to every member. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every notice of meeting of the Bureau shall specify the place and the day and hour of the meeting. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The President shall cause to be prepared and circulated to the members, at least seven days before the meeting, an agenda for the meeting: 
 Provided that where an emergency meeting is convened, an agenda for such meeting may be circulated to the members at the meeting. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> [<number>6</number> Five members shall form the quorum, provided that if any meeting is adjourned for want of quorum, the adjourned meeting may be called on a date not later than seven days from the date of the original meeting to transact the business regardless of the quorum.] 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Each member including the President shall have one vote. In the case of an equality of votes on any question to be decided by the Bureau, the President or the Vice-President or the member presiding over such meeting shall in addition have a casting vote. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> The proceedings of each meeting shall be circulated to each member of the Bureau and these shall be confirmed at the next meeting with or without modifications. 
  






</section></article> 

 <title> </title>
 <title> </title>
 <article><title><number>6</number> Executive Committee. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Executive Committee shall perform, exercise and discharge such of the functions, powers and duties as may be delegated to it by the Bureau. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>9</footcitenum>[<number>2</number> The Executive Committee shall consist of the Director General as ex-officio Chairman and nine other members, representing the following categories, to be appointed by the Bureau of Indian Standards, with the prior approval of the Central Government, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><footcitenum>10</footcitenum>[<number>i</number> Additional Secretary and Financial Advisor and Special Secretary or Additional Secretary or Joint Secretary of the Ministry/Department having administrative control of the Bureau;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> one person representing a Ministry or Departments of Central Government other than at (i) above; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> one person representing recognised consumer organization; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>  one person representing industry, trade and their associations; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> two persons representing scientific and research institutions; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>vi</number> two persons representing public sector enterprises and technical, educational or professional organisations.] 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> The members of the Executive Committee appointed under sub-rule (2) shall hold office for a period of two years and shall be eligible for re-appointment. The term of office of the ex-officio  Chairman shall be on a tenure basis for a period of three years who shall be eligible for re-appointment. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> When a member appointed under sub-rule (2) desires to resign from membership of the Executive Committee, he shall forward his letter of resignation under his own hand to the Director-General and such resignation shall take effect from the date of its acceptance by the Director-General or on the expiry of a period of one month from the date of its receipt by the Director-General whichever is earlier. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>11</footcitenum>[<number>5</number> The vacancy caused on resignation and termination of a member of the Executive Committee shall be filled within a period of three months from the date of occurrence by the Bureau of Indian Standards with the prior approval of the Central Government.] 
 </section><section><number>6</number> A meeting of the Executive Committee shall be held at least once in every three months. 
 </section><section><number>7</number> Each meeting of the Executive Committee shall be called by giving not less than fourteen days from the date of issue, notice in writing to every member: 
 Provided that an emergency meeting may be called by giving not less than three days' notice to every member. 
 </section><section><number>8</number> Every notice of a meeting of the Executive Committee shall specify the place and the day and hour of the meeting. 
 </section><section><number>9</number> The ex-officio  Chairman of the Executive Committee shall cause to be prepared and circulated to the member, at least seven days before the meeting, an agenda for the meeting: 
 Provided that where an emergency meeting is called, an agenda for such meeting may be circulated to the members at the meeting. 
 </section><section><footcitenum>12</footcitenum>[<number>10</number> The quorum for a meeting of the Executive Committee shall be three.] 
 </section><section><number>11</number> The proceedings of each meeting shall be circulated to each member of the Executive Committee and these shall be confirmed at the next meeting with or without modification. <title> </title>







</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>6A</number> Travelling and Daily 
Allowances to Bureau and Executive Committee Members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The members and persons associated with the Bureau and the members of the 
Executive Committee representing the Central Government, State Governments, 
Union Territories, statutory and autonomous bodies (other than those specially 
approved by the Executive Committee), public sector undertakings, trade, 
industry and their associations, 

2[***] shall not be eligible to draw 
any travelling or daily allowance from the funds of the Bureau.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Travelling and daily allowances to 
members and persons associated with the Bureau and members of the Executive 
Committee other than those specified in sub-rule (1), while travelling within 
the country with prior concurrence of the Director-General, may be admissible 
from the Bureau for attending meetings of the Bureau and the Executive 
Committee and discharging any duty as assigned by the Bureau or the Executive 
Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The rates of travelling and daily 
allowances admissible to the members and persons covered by sub-rule (2) shall 
be the same as applicable to non-officials attending the meetings of committees 
set up by the Central Government.]
 

3[(4) If any member is a Member of 
Parliament, he shall not be entitled to any allowance other than compensatory 
allowance, as defined in clause (a) of section 2 of the Parliament (Prevention 
of Disqualification) Act, 1959 (10 of 1959):
 
Provided that such member shall not be 
entitled to any allowance except for meetings held during the intersession 
period.
 
Explanation.—Intersession 
period means the interval between the adjournment of a House of Parliament of 
which he is a Member and the re-assembly of that House.]
 
 






</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>7</number> Establishment, publication and 
promotion of Indian Standards.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Establishment—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  The Bureau shall 
establish Indian Standards in relation to any article or process and shall 
amend, revise or cancel the standards so established as may be necessary, by a 
process of consultation with consumers, manufactures, technologists, scientists 
and officials through duly constituted committees as provided hereafter. The 
procedure employed in establishing the standard shall also be designed such 
that concerned interests, in addition of the members of the Committees of the 
Bureau, have the opportunity to communicate their views:
 
             Provided 
that any Indian Standard established by the Indian Standards Institution at any 
time before the date on which the Act, the Rules and the Regulations come into 
force shall be deemed to have been established under the provisions of the Act, 
the Rules and the Regulations.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  All standards, 
their revisions, amendments and cancellations shall be established by 
notification in the Official Gazette.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Technical Committees—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  For the purpose 
of formulation of Indian Standards in respect of articles or processes, 
technical committees of experts may be constituted. Such committees may include 
Division Councils, Sectional Committees, Sub-committees and Panels.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  Division 
Councils, Sectional Committees and Sub-committees shall be reconstituted once 
every three years. The tenure of Panels shall be as decided by the concerned 
Sectional Committee.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Division Councils—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  Division Councils 
shall be set up by the Bureau in defined areas of industries and technologies 
for formulation of standards. These shall include concerned officers of the 
Bureau and representatives of various interests such as consumers, regulatory 
and other Government bodies, industry, scientists, technologists and testing 
organizations. These may also include consultants*. An officer of the Bureau 
shall be the Member-Secretary.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  Major functions 
of a Division Council would be as follows:—
 <subsubsection>
     <number>i</number>  to advise on the subject areas to 
be taken up for formulation of standards in their respective areas keeping in 
view the national needs and priorities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>ii</number>  to set up Sectional Committees 
within their areas, define their scopes, appoint their Chairman and members and 
co-ordinate their activities;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>iii</number>  to approve proposals for work, 
decide which proposals should be taken up and direct the Sectional Committee(s) 
concerned to undertake the approved work and to determine the priority to be 
assigned to the work;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>iv</number>  to advise on matters relating to 
research and development needed for the establishment of standards or their 
revisions;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>v</number>  to study the work of international 
organizations and their committees in standards formulation as related to the 
area of work of the Division Council and recommend on the extent and manner of 
participation in standardization activities at the international level;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>vi</number>  to advise on 
implementation of established standards;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>vii</number>  to receive and 
deal with activity reports and to make recommendations thereon to the Bureau 
concerning matters in which the decision of the Bureau is necessary;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
   <number>viii</number>  to carry out 
such tasks as may be specifically referred to it by the Bureau/Standards 
Advisory Committee.
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Sectional Committees, Sub-committees and 
Panels—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  Sectional 
Committees shall be appointed by Division Councils or if necessary by the 
Bureau for the preparation of a particular standard or group of standards. 
These shall include concerned officers of the Bureau and representatives of 
various interests such as consumers, regulatory and other Government bodies, 
industry, scientists, technologists and testing organisations and may also 
include consultants, but consumer interests shall, as far as possible, 
predominate. An officer of the Bureau shall be the Member-Secretary.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  A Sectional 
Committee may appoint sub-committees and/or panels.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  Sectional 
Committees, Sub-committees and Panels may co-opt experts to assist them in 
their work.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> Terms and conditions for engaging 
consultants—
 
The terms and conditions for engaging 
consultants in the work of the Division Councils and other Technical Committees 
and in the work relating to establishment of standards shall be as decided by 
the Executive Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Procedure for establishment of Indian 
Standards—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  Any Ministry of 
the Central Government, State Governments, Union Territory Administrations, 
consumer organizations, industrial units, industry-associations, professional 
bodies, members of the Bureau and members of its Technical Committees may 
submit proposals to the Bureau for establishing a standard or for revising, 
amending, or cancelling an established standard by making such request in 
writing.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  The work of 
formulation of standards on any specific subject shall be undertaken when the 
Division Council concerned is satisfied as a result of its own deliberations or 
on investigation and consultation with concerned interests that the necessity 
for standardization has been established.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  When the subject 
has been so investigated as in sub-rule (b) and the need established, the 
Division Council concerned shall assign the task of formulating the standard to 
an appropriate Technical Committee or shall appoint a new Technical Committee 
for the purpose.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  When request for 
establishing a standard for any specific subject has not been accepted after 
its due consideration the proposer shall be informed of the decision.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  A draft standard 
prepared and duly approved by a Committee shall be issued in draft form and 
widely circulated for a period of not less than one month amongst the various 
interests concerned for critical review and suggestions for improvement. The 
wide circulation may be waived if so decided by the Sectional Committee where 
the matter is urgent or non-controversial.
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  The appropriate 
Technical Committee shall thereafter finalize the draft standard giving due 
consideration to the comments that may be received. The draft standard after it 
has been approved by the Sectional Committee or its Chairman shall be submitted 
to the Chairman of the Division Council concerned for adoption on its behalf.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>g</number>  All established 
standards shall be reviewed periodically, at least once in five years, to 
determine the need for revision or withdrawal. Standards which in the opinion 
of the Sectional Committee need no revision or amendment shall be reaffirmed by 
the Sectional Committee.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>h</number>  Proposals for 
revising or amending published standards shall be considered by the Technical 
Committee concerned. The revision or amendment shall then be dealt with in 
accordance with clauses (e) and (f) of sub-rule (6) dealing with the 
establishment of Indian Standards.
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>i</number>  The 
Director-General, however, shall have the power to issue amendments of the 
corrigenda type meant to correct errors and omissions in established Indian 
Standards, without reference to the concerned Technical Committee or the 
Division Council and report to the concerned Technical Committee.
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>j</number>  The 
Director-General shall also have the power to tentatively modify such of the 
provisions of an Indian Standard as in his view are necessary for expeditious 
fulfilment of any of the objectives of the Act:
 
          Provided that 
within six months of such actions, concurrence of the concerned Sectional 
Committee is duly obtained.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>k</number>  Withdrawal of an 
established Indian Standard shall be decided upon by the Chairman of the 
respective Division Council on the recommendation of the Sectional Committee 
concerned.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> Status of Indian Standards—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  The procedure 
employed in establishing Indian Standards is designed to ensure that all 
interested parties have an opportunity to put forward their views, that a 
consensus has been obtained on the contents of the standards and that there is 
substantial support for the standards.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  Indian Standards 
are voluntary and available to the public. Their implementation depends on 
adoption by concerned parties. However, an Indian Standard becomes binding if 
it is stipulated in a contract or referred to in a legislation or made 
mandatory by specific orders of the Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> Publication—
 
The Indian Standards established by the 
Bureau, their revisions and amendments shall be published and copies thereof, 
in any form as may be determined by the Bureau, shall be made available for 
sale.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> Pricing of Indian Standards and other 
publications—
 
The prices of Indian Standards and other 
publications shall be fixed by the Director General according to the policy 
directives of the Executive Committee and may be reviewed periodically.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> Standards promotion—
 
The Bureau may promote standardization and 
adoption of Indian Standards by consumers, commerce, industry, Government and 
other interests, in such manner as may be considered necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> Procedure for establishment of 
Tentative (Provisional) Indian Standards—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  A tentative 
Indian Standard may be prepared when urgently needed but its technical accuracy 
cannot be established on account of technology being new or not having been 
proven commercially.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  The proposal for 
preparation of a Tentative Indian Standard shall be as per clause (a) of 
sub-rule (6) of rule 7. The proposal shall be accompanied by a draft of the 
Tentative Indian Standard.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  The draft of the 
Tentative Indian Standard shall be examined by the Sectional Committee 
concerned for approval and issued as a Tentative Indian Standard without wide 
circulation, after its adoption by Chairman of Division Council concerned on 
its behalf.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  The Foreword of 
the Tentative Indian Standard shall clearly bring out the following:—
 <subsubsection>
     <number>i</number>  Need for preparing the Tentative 
Indian Standard;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
     <number>ii</number>  Scope of its application; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
    <number>iii</number>  Period of its validity.
 
           The Sectional Committee, may 
decide the period of validity but this shall not exceed two years. Period of 
validity may be extended by not more than two years on a review by the 
Sectional Committee.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  The Tentative 
Standard shall not be used for Standard Mark.
 </subsection><subsection>
    <number>f</number>  Before the 
expiry of the validity period, the Tentative Indian Standard shall be 
considered by the Sectional Committee for establishing it as a regular 
standard. If the Sectional Committee is not in favour of its establishment as a 
regular standard, the Tentative Indian Standard shall lapse after its validity 
period.
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>g</number>  Tentative Indian 
Standard shall be gazetted in accordance with clause (b) of sub-rule (1) of 
rule 7.]
 
 






</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>17</footcitenum> [<number>8</number> Recognition of other Standards as Indian Standards. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau may, in relation to an article or process, recognize any standard established by any other institution in India or outside as an Indian Standard with necessary editorial modifications, in accordance with the procedure as provided hereafter: 
 Provided that any standard recognized by the Indian Standards Institution at any time before the date on which the Act, the Rules and the Regulations come into force shall be deemed to have been recognized under provisions of the Act, the Rules and the Regulations. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The proposal for such recognition of the appropriate standard shall be made as laid down in clause (a) of sub-rule (6) of rule 7. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the Director General is satisfied that the proposal should be further processed, he shall— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> refer it to the Chairman of the concerned Sectional Committee for his recommendation regarding the recognition of the other standard as Indian Standard; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> if the subject-matter of the proposed standard does not fall within the scope of work of any of the existing Sectional Committees, refer it to the Chairman of the Division Council scope of which is close to the subject under consideration for his recommendation regarding its recognition; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> if the subject-matter of the proposed standard does not fall within the scope of work of any of the existing Sectional Committees and if there is no Division Council scope of which is close to the subject under consideration, consult an ad hoc experts committee specially constituted by him for this purpose for recommendations regarding its recognition. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Standards so recognized as Indian Standards shall be notified in the Official Gazette in accordance with clause (b) of sub-rule (1) of rule 7. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> Recognized Indian Standards shall also be made available for sale.] 
  


</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Standard Mark.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Standard Mark in relation to each Indian Standard shall be published by the 
Bureau in the Official Gazette:
 
Provided that the Bureau may amend or 
rescind any Standard Mark so published.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Standard Mark already established 
and notified by the Indian Standards Institution shall be deemed to be valid 
unless amended or rescinded by the Bureau.
</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Establishment, maintenance and 
recognition of laboratories.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Laboratories established and maintained by the Bureau shall—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  carry out testing 
of samples in relation to the use of the Standard Mark;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  carry out 
research and development investigations or testing for collecting data for 
evolving and revising Indian Standards and for quality assessment studies;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  provide support 
services to industries for quality improvement on such terms and conditions to 
be laid down by the Bureau from time to time;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  carry out such 
other functions as may be necessary to fulfil the objectives of the Bureau.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (a) The Bureau may recognize any 
laboratory in India or in any other country for carrying out testing of samples 
in relation to use of the Standard Mark and such other functions as may be 
necessary. In case any laboratory after recognition ceases to fulfil any 
conditions laid down at the time of recognition, it shall be liable to be 
de-recognized by the Bureau. The guidelines for recognition and de-recognition 
of laboratories shall be laid down by the Bureau.
 <subsection>
<number>b</number> Register of recognized laboratories—The 
Bureau shall cause to maintain a register of such laboratories as are 
recognized by it for testing samples of articles or processes in relation to 
the relevant Indian Standards.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Appointment of agents.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Bureau may appoint any person or organisation in India or outside India as 
their agents to act on their behalf for discharging any one or more of the 
following functions:—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  to carry out 
inspections of manufacturer’s premises in India 
or outside for allowing use of the Standard Mark;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  to test samples 
of products for their conformity to Indian Standards;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  to inspect 
consignments intended to be covered under the Standard Mark.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The terms and conditions of the 
appointment as agents shall be set out in an agreement between the Bureau and 
the agent so appointed:
 

1[Provided that the appointment of 
agents outside India shall be made with the previous approval of the Central 
Government.]
 
 




</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>12</number> Inspection of article or process when 
Standard Mark or conformity to Indian Standard is required by the Act or under 
any other law.—
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau 
may, in terms of provisions of section 25, carry out inspections, through its 
inspecting officers or agents, of articles or processes where Standard Mark or 
conformity to Indian Standard is required or claimed under this Act or under 
any other law if authorised under that law.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such inspections may be carried out in 
India or outside India at place of manufacture before despatch, or at place of 
its sale or use in India.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Such inspections may include inspection 
of quality control system, or verification of records of testing or testing of 
a sample or any other related matter.
 

1[(4) The Bureau of Indian Standards 
shall be paid fees in advance for such inspection and expenses of travelling 
allowances, daily allowances and the like as may be mutually agreed.]
 
 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>13</number> Other functions of the Bureau. </title>—The Bureau under clause (p) of sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 10 may also— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> formulate, implement and co-ordinate activities relating to quality maintenance and improvement in products and processes; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> promote harmonious development in standardization, quality systems and certification, and matter connected therewith both within the country and at international level; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> provide information, documentation and other services to consumers and recognized consumer organisations on such terms and conditions as may be mutually agreed upon; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> give recognition to quality assurance systems in manufacturing or processing units on such terms and conditions as may be mutually agreed upon; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> bring out handbooks, guides and other special publications; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>f</number> carry out inspections and testing or testing of an article or process for conformity to any other standard if so authorized on such terms and conditions as may be mutually agreed upon; 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>21</footcitenum>[<number>fa</number> formulate, implement and coordinate activities relating to registration for self declaration of conformity to the relevant Indian Standard on voluntary or compulsory basis, of articles as may be considered expedient in public interest and so notified through an order by the Central Government after consulting the Bureau;] 
 </subsection><subsection><number>g</number>  perform such other functions as may be conducive to the interests of the Bureau. 
</subsection>



 
 “(fa) formulate, implement and coordinate activities relating to registration for self declaration of conformity to the relevant Indian Standard on voluntary or compulsory basis, as may be considered expedient in public interest and so notified by the Central Government after consulting the Bureau;”. 

</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Exemption from prohibition to use 
certain names, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bureau may exempt any name, mark or trade mark, referred to in section 12 
from the operation thereof, if such name, mark or trade mark has been 
established by or under any law for the time being in force and application has 
been made to it by any person under sub-rule (2) within a period of six months 
from the date of commencement of these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person claiming an exemption in 
respect of any name, mark or trade mark under sub-rule (1), may make an 
application to the Bureau in Form 1.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Bureau shall cause to maintain a 
register in which shall be entered all names, marks and trade marks exempted by 
the Bureau under sub-rule (1).
</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Licence.—The 
manner of grant, renewal, suspension and cancellation of licence shall be as 
determined by Regulations.
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>16</number> Appeals against decisions of the Bureau. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> An appeal 
under section 16 may be preferred by the aggrieved party to the Central 
Government within ninety days from the date of decision of the Bureau: 
 Provided that an appeal may be admitted after the expiry of the period of 
ninety days if the appellant satisfies the Central Government that he had 
sufficient cause for not preferring the appeal within the ninety days period. 

 </section><section><number>2</number> Every appeal made under sub-rule (1) shall be lodged in duplicate and 
shall be accompanied by a copy of the order appealed against. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every appeal made under sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a fee of 
rupees five hundred in the form of a Demand Draft drawn in favour of the Bureau. 

 </section><section><number>4</number> The Central Government may call for relevant papers from the Bureau and 
may after such inquiry in the matter as it considers necessary and after giving 
an opportunity to parties to be heard pass such orders as it thinks fit and any 
such order by the Central Government shall be final. 

</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>24</footcitenum>[<number>16A</number> Registration. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every manufacturer of the articles notified by the Central Government for compulsory registration under clause (fa) of rule 13 shall apply to the Bureau for grant of registration for self declaration. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Any manufacturer of the articles notified by the Central Government for voluntary registration under clause (fa) of rule 13 may apply to the Bureau for registration for self declaration. ] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>26</footcitenum>[<number>16B</number> Application for registration. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every application for registration shall be made in Form VI and shall be accompanied by— 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> self evaluation cum declaration as specified in Form VII; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> test report of sample of article as specified in sub-rule (3). 
</subsection>
 </section><section><number>2</number> For every manufacturing unit of the articles notified under clause (fa) of rule 13, separate registration shall be required. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The applicant shall get the sample of the article tested from any laboratory in India recognized by the Bureau or any laboratory abroad covered under a mutual recognition agreement with the Bureau: 
 <footcitenum>27</footcitenum>[Provided that the test report so furnished shall not be beyond the period of ninety days as on the date of submission of application with Bureau.] 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every foreign applicant shall set up a liaison office or branch office located in India which shall meet all liabilities and obligations with respect to the Act and the rules and regulations framed thereunder for the purpose of registration: 
 Provided that the requirement to set up an office in India shall not apply if the Bureau enters into a Memorandum of Understanding with the concerned country for implementation of the Act and the rules and regulations framed thereunder, or if the foreign applicant nominates an authorized representative located in India who declares his consent to be responsible for compliance to the provisions of the Act and the rules and regulations framed thereunder on behalf of the foreign applicant.] 




</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>29</footcitenum>[<number>16C</number> Grant of registration. </title>—The Bureau shall scrutinize the application and if the same is in accordance with provisions of rule 16B, registration shall be granted: 
 Provided that the Bureau may reject the application for registration if it is not in accordance with the provisions of rule 16B: 
 Provided further that no application shall be rejected before giving the applicant an opportunity of the being heard and before consideration of the explanation, if any, submitted by him in this regard. ] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>31</footcitenum>[<number>16D</number> Validity of registration. </title>—The registration granted under rule 16C, unless renewed or its renewal is deferred, shall lapse at the end of the period for which it is granted. ] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>33</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16E</number> Certificate of registration. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every Registered User shall be given a certificate of registration in Form VIII. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Where registration is granted, it shall be notified by the Bureau on its website, specifying particulars of the registration and the said particulars shall be entered in a register to be maintained by the Bureau. ] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>35</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16F</number> Conditions of registration. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Every Registered User shall display the words ‘Self declaration—Conforming to IS…….'on the article or packaging, as the case may be, in a manner so as to be easily visible and where the article cannot be packaged, written on the test certificate relating thereto: 
 Provided that no Registered User shall display or make such self declaration unless the article conforms to the relevant Indian Standard. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> No person other than the Registered User who is in possession of a valid registration shall make a public claim, through advertisements, sales promotion leaflets, price-lists or the like, that his article conforms to the Indian Standard or make such a declaration on the article. ] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>37</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16G</number> Collection and testing of samples. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any person authorized by the Central Government or the Bureau may collect samples of articles of a particular registered user from the market or from the manufacturing unit to check their conformity with sub-rules (1) and (2) of rule 16F. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The cost of the samples, whether drawn from the registered user or from the market, and their testing charges shall be borne by the registered user. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The person authorized by the Central Government or the Bureau shall send the sample so collected, to a laboratory recognized by the Bureau or to a laboratory abroad covered under mutual recognition agreement with the Bureau as the case may be, for testing of their conformity to the relevant India Standard. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The laboratory to which the samples are sent for testing shall send the test reports in respect of articles under compulsory registration to the Central Government and those in respect of articles under voluntary registration to the Bureau. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> If the samples do not conform to the relevant Indian Standard, the Bureau may take action as specified under rule 16I. ] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>39</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16H</number> Suspension of registration. </title>—A registration may be suspended by the Bureau on request from the registered user, if the operation in his premises can no longer be carried due to— 
 
 <section><number>a</number> natural calamities such as flood, fire earthquake, etc; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> a lock out; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> closure of operations directed by a competent court or statutory authority. ] 
</section>



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>41</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16I</number> Stoppage of Self declaration. </title>—The Bureau may, on receipt of information from the Central Government about non conformity of the articles under compulsory registration to the relevant Indian Standard as per the test report received under sub-rule (4) of rule 16G or on the basis of the test reports received directly by it under the said rule in relation to articles under voluntary registration, direct the Registered User to stop the use of the words ‘Self declaration—Conforming to IS……' if it is satisfied that such article is not conforming to the relevant Indian Standard. 
 <section><number>2</number> The Bureau may permit resumption of self declaration by the Registered User, if it is satisfied that the Registered User has taken necessary corrective action and sufficient evidence is produced about conformity of the article to the relevant Indian Standard. ] 
  



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>43</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16J</number> Renewal of registration. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau may renew the registration if an application in Form IX is made by the Registered User at least one month before the expiry of the period for which registration has been granted, in case no action is pending against him under rule 16I. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The registration shall be renewed for a further period of two years on every occasion if the Registered User is eligible for the same. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> If any action under rule 16I is pending against the Registered User, renewal of his registration may be deferred for a maximum period of twelve months and after the expiry of the said period, the registration shall be deemed to have been renewed and Bureau shall grant the registration to the Registered User, duly renewed, unless non-renewal of the registration has been due to reasons attributable to the Registered User. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> Before the Bureau decides not to renew any registration, it shall give the Registered User not less than fourteen days notice of its intention to do so. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Registered User may submit his explanation, if any within seven days from the date of receipt of the notice and the same shall be considered by the Bureau and a hearing shall be given to him within fourteen days from the date of receipt of such explanation or before the expiry of the notice period, whichever is later. 
 </section><section><number>6</number> In case of failure of the Registered User to submit his explanation within the prescribed time limit or the explanation submitted by the Registered User is not found satisfactory, the Bureau may, on expiry of the notice period, allow the registration to lapse and an intimation thereof in writing, together with the reasons therefore, shall be sent to the Registered User through registered post.
 </section><section> <number>7</number> The Registered User shall not use the words ‘Self declaration—Conforming to IS….' in case his registration lapses or its renewal is deferred under sub-rule (3). ] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>45</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16K</number> Cancellation of registration. </title>—
<section><number>1</number> Any registration granted by the Bureau may be cancelled by it if on the basis of the test report under sub-rule (4) of rule 16G it is satisfied that— 
 <subsection><number>a</number> the articles on which conformity has been self declared under a registration do not conform to the relevant Indian Standard; or 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> the Registered User has failed to comply with any of the terms and conditions of the registration. 
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Before the Bureau cancels any registration, it shall give the Registered User not less than fourteen days notice of its intention to do so. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Registered User may submit his explanation, if any, within seven days from the date of receipt of the notice and the same shall be considered by the Bureau and a hearing shall be given to him within fourteen days from the date of receipt of such explanation or before expiry of the notice period, whichever is later. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> In case of failure of the Registered User to submit his explanation within the specified time limit or the explanation submitted by the Registered User is not found satisfactory, the Bureau may, on expiry of the notice period, cancel the registration and an intimation thereof in writing, together with the reasons therefor, shall be sent to the Registered User through registered post. ] 



</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>47</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16L</number> Withdrawal of Indian Standards. </title>—When an Indian Standard is withdrawn any registration granted in respect thereof shall be deemed to have been cancelled from the date of withdrawal of such Indian Standard. ] 



</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>49</footcitenum>[<number>16M</number> </title><title><footcitenum>50</footcitenum>[Effect of suspension or cancellation]. </title>—Where a registration has been suspended or cancelled, or the term thereof has not been renewed on the expiry of the period of its validity, the Registered User shall discontinue forthwith the use of the words ‘Self declaration—Conforming to IS…..' on the article, notwithstanding the pendency of any appeal before the Central Government.] 




</article> 

  
 <article><title><footcitenum>52</footcitenum>[</title><title><number>16N</number> Appeal. </title>—An appeal against any order of the Bureau may be made to the Central Government within ninety days from the date of the order of the Bureau.] 



</article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Budget.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bureau shall prepare budget estimates for the next year and the revised 
estimates for the current year and shall forward it to the Central Government 
each year by 15th October or on such date as may be decided by the Central 
Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> These estimates shall be prepared 
separately on revenue and capital accounts.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Budget estimates shall contain the 
following details:—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  budget estimate 
for the current year;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  revised estimates 
for the current year;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  
budget estimates for the next year.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>

1[<number>17A</number> Expenditure not Budgetted for.—The 
expenditure which is of an emergent and essential in character but provision 
for the same has not been made in the budget shall be incurred only after the 
Executive Committee has approved of it.]
 
 




</article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>54</footcitenum>[<number>17B</number> 
Appropriation.—The funds provided 
in the sanctioned budget shall be deemed to be at the disposal of the 
Director-General who shall have full powers to appropriate sums therefrom to 
meet expenditure under different heads of accounts for activities and purposes 
authorised and provided for in the budget:
 
Provided that funds shall not be 
appropriated or reapropriated to meet expenditure which has not been sanctioned 
by an authority competent to sanction it.]



</article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>55</footcitenum>[<number>17C</number> 
Reappropriation.—The 
Director-General shall have powers within the scope of the budgetted activities 
and purposes in reappropriate sums from one head of account to another:
 
Provided that funds shall not be 
reappropriated—
 <section>
    <number>i</number>  to meet the 
expenditure on any new item of work not contemplated in the budget;
 </section><section>
    <number>ii</number>  to meet the 
expenditure on any Project involving construction which has not received 
administrative approval and technical sanction from the competent authorities;
 </section><section>
   <number>iii</number>  to meet the 
expenditure on any Project involving construction, in excess of 10 per cent. of 
the approved estimates;
 </section><section>
   <number>iv</number>  from the 
provision made for any specified new item of expenditure in the budget for any 
other purpose;
 </section><section>
   <number>v</number>  from funds 
provided under Plan heads to the Non-Plan heads of expenditure and from Capital 
to Revenue and vice versa; and
 </section><section>
   <number>vi</number>  from or to head 
of account "Overseas travel" expenditure.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>56</footcitenum>[<number>17D</number> 
Bank Account.—
<section><number>1</number> Bank accounts 
shall be opened in State Bank of India or any of its subsidiaries or any of the 
nationalised banks and operated in such a manner as may be authorised by the 
Director-General.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All moneys belonging to the Fund shall 
be deposited promptly into the Bank.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>57</footcitenum>[<number>17E</number> 
Investment.—Moneys belonging to 
the Fund may, with the approval of the Director-General or any other Officer 
authorised in this behalf, be invested in the form and modes as specified under 
sub-section (5) of section 11 of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (1 of 1961), for 
investment of income derived from property held under trust wholly for 
charitable or religious purposes.]
 
 



</article> 
 the Bureau of Indian Standards Rules, 
1987
  
 <article><footcitenum>58</footcitenum>[<number>17F</number> Contract.—
<section><number>1</number> The Bureau may enter into all such contracts 
as it may consider necessary for giving effect to any of the provisions of the 
Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> 
Every contract made under or for any purpose of the Act shall be made on behalf 
of the Bureau by the Director-General or such other officers as may be 
authorised by him in this behalf.]
  


</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article><footcitenum>59</footcitenum>[<number>17G</number> 
Administration of Provident Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Contributory Provident Fund and General Provident Fund applicable to the 
officers and employees of the Bureau shall be administered by a committee of 
administrators, to be nominated by the Director-General, comprising a Chairman 
and four other persons out of which at least two of them shall be the 
representatives of officers and employees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The functions of the committee of 
administrators shall include management of the provident funds and investment 
of the same in Government securities and other deposits, in the manner laid 
down by the Central Government in this regard. It shall also have the power to 
delegate such of the functions as it may consider necessary to one or more of 
its members.]
 
 



</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Annual Report.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bureau shall prepare its annual report and forward it to the Central 
Government within 9 months of the end of the year for being laid before each 
House of Parliament.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The annual report shall give a full 
account of the activities of the Bureau during the previous year and shall 
include the audited accounts of the year and the report of the Comptroller and 
Auditor General of India thereon. The Bureau shall forward copies of the annual 
report to the Central Government and that Government shall cause the same to be 
laid before the House of Parliament.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The annual report shall be prepared in 
the format given in Form II or as nearer thereto as the circumstances admit.
</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Accounts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bureau shall maintain accounts of its income and expenditure relating to 
each year and maintain records in such a manner as to prepare annual statement 
of accounts consisting of income and expenditure account and the balance sheet.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Annual statement of accounts shall be 
submitted for audit not later than 30th June each year in the following forms 
or as nearer thereto as the circumstances admit:—
 <subsection>
   <number>a</number>  income and 
expenditure account in Form III;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>b</number>  Schedules A to M 
attached to and forming part of the income and expenditure account;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>c</number>  balance-sheet in 
Form IV;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>d</number>  Schedules N to T 
attached to and forming part of the balance-sheet;
 </subsection><subsection>
   <number>e</number>  annual statement 
of accounts shall be signed on behalf of the Bureau by the office incharge of 
accounts and the Director General.
</subsection></section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Inspecting officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Bureau shall designate such of the officers of the Bureau as Inspecting 
Officers under sub-section (1) of section 25, as it may consider necessary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Inspecting Officer shall be 
furnished by the Bureau with a certificate of appointment as an Inspecting 
Officer in Form V. The certificate shall be carried by the Inspecting Officer 
at all times while he is on duty and shall on demand, be produced by him.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every applicant for a licence or every 
licence shall afford to the Inspecting Officer such reasonable facilities as 
the Inspecting Officer may require for carrying out the duties imposed on him 
by or under the Act.
</section></article> 
 
the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Powers of Inspecting Officer.—For 
the purpose of performing the duties imposed on him by or under section 25 and 
section 26 of the Act, an Inspecting Officer may,—
 <section>
   <number>a</number>  at any time 
during the usual business hours enter upon any premises in which any article or 
process in respect of which a licence has been granted under rule 16 is 
manufactured or employed by a licensee with a view to ascertaining that the 
Standard Mark is being used in accordance with the terms and conditions imposed 
by the Bureau and that the scheme of routine inspection and testing specified 
by the Bureau is being correctly followed;
 </section><section>
   <number>b</number>  inspect and take 
samples at such premises of any such article or any material used or intended 
to be used in the manufacture of such article which is marked with a Standard 
Mark;
 </section><section>
   <number>c</number>  inspect any 
process at such premises in respect of which licensee has been given the 
authority to use the Standard Mark;
 </section><section>
   <number>d</number>  examine the 
records kept by the licensee relating to the use of the Standard Mark;
 </section><section>
   <number>e</number>  enter into and 
search such place, premises or conveyance for such article or process 
contravening provisions of section 11 or section 12 of the Act, as provided in 
section 26 and in accordance with the procedure laid down in the Regulations.
 </section><section>
    <number>f</number>  where as a 
result of search made under clause (e) any article or process has been found in 
relation to which contravention of section 11 or section 12 of the Act has 
taken place, seize such articles and any other things as provided in section 26 
and in accordance with the procedure laid down in the Regulations.
 
 
</section></article><form>
 

The Bureau of Indian Standards Rules, 
1987
 

 
 

Appendix
 

FORM 
I
 

(See rule 
14)
 

Application 
for Exemption from Prohibition under section 12 of the Bureau of Indian 
Standards Act, 1986
 

To
 

The Director General,
 

Bureau of Indian 
Standards
 

...............................................
 

1. *I/We carrying on business at 
................................................. (full business address) under 
the style of ................................................................... 
(full name) hereby apply for exemption from prohibition under section 12 of the 
Bureau of Indian Standards Act, 1986, in respect of name/mark/trade mark 
detailed below of which I/We am/are the proprietor(s). Complete information in 
regard to its use is furnished as required.
 

        
(1) Name/mark/trade mark* in respect of which exemption is sought
 

        
(2) Whether registered
 

        
(3) Date of registration and registration number
 

        
(4) Authority with whom registered
 

        
(5) Since when the name/mark/trade mark* has been in actual use by the 
applicant
 

        
(6) The article(s) in relation to which the name/mark/trade mark* is 
used
 

        
(7) Claim for distinctiveness of the name/mark/trade mark*
 

        
(8) Full particulars about the nature of business of the applicant
 

        
(9) Any other remarks
 

2. *I/We declare that the 
information given above is to the best of my/our knowledge true, and in support 
of it *I/We attach the following documentary evidence:—
 

List of documents 
enclosed.
 

Dated 
this................................... day of 
....................................20.......
 

                                                    
Signature 
...................................................................
 

                                                    
Name 
.........................................................................
 

                                                    
Designation 
...............................................................
 

                                                    
for and on behalf of 
...................................................
 

Note.—Separate applications shall 
be made for each name/mark/trade mark.
 

 </form><form>
 


the Bureau of Indian Standards 
Rules, 1987
 


 
 


FORM II
 


(See rule 18)
 


Format of the 
Annual Report
 


DIRECTOR-GENERAL'S REPORT
 


FORMULATION OF STANDARDS
 


CERTIFICATION AND QUALITY ASSURANCE
 


LABORATORIES
 


PROMOTIONAL ACTIVITIES
 


REGIONAL AND BRANCH OFFICES
 


INTERNATIONAL COOPERATION
 


PLAN PROJECTS
 


PERSONAL MANAGEMENT
 


OTHER RELATED ACTIVITIES
 


FIANCES
 


ANNUAL ACCOUNTS AND AUDITED REPORTS
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 
31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 7(E), dated 6th January, 1989.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 
31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 666(E), dated 26th October, 2006, for sub-rule (1) (w.e.f. 26-10-2006). Earlier sub-rule (1) was amended by G.S.R. 48(E), dated 2nd February, 1990 (w.e.f. 2-2-1990) and by G.S.R. 638(E), dated 16th July, 1990 (w.e.f. 16-7-1990). Sub-rule (1), before substitution by G.S.R. 666(E), stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 48(E), dated 2nd February, 1990 (w.e.f. 2-2-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins. by G.S.R. 48(E), dated 2nd February, 1990 (w.e.f. 2-2-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 666(E), dated 26th October, 2006, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 26-10-2006). Sub-rule (2), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 666(E), dated 26th October, 2006, for sub-rule (6) (w.e.f. 26-10-2006). Sub-rule (6), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 666(E), dated 26th October, 2006, for sub-rule (2) (w.e.f. 26-10-2006). Earlier Sub-rule (2) was substituted by G.S.R. 557(E), dated 16th August, 1993 (w.e.f. 17-8-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 297(E), dated 4th April, 2011, for clause (i) (w.e.f. 4-4-2011). Clause (i), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>11</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 666(E), dated 26th October, 2006, for sub-rule (5) (w.e.f. 26-10-2006). Earlier Sub-rule (5) was amended by G.S.R. 48(E), dated 2nd February, 1990 (w.e.f. 2-2-1990) and by G.S.R. 557(E), dated 16th August, 1993 (w.e.f. 17-8-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>12</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 666(E), dated 26th October, 2006, for sub-rule (10) (w.e.f. 26-10-2006).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>13</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 7(E), dated 6th 
January, 1989 (w.e.f. 6-1-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>14</number>  Omitted by G.S.R. 702(E), dated 11th 
November, 1993 (w.e.f. 12-11-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>15</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 702(E), dated 11th 
November, 1993 (w.e.f. 12-11-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>16</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 7(E), dated 6th 
January, 1989 (w.e.f. 6-1-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>17</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 7(E), dated 6th January, 1989 (w.e.f. 6-1-1989).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>18</number>  Added by G.S.R. 48(E), dated 2nd 
February, 1990 (w.e.f. 2-2-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>19</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 557(E), dated 16th 
August, 1993 (w.e.f. 17-8-1993).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>20</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>21</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 887(E), dated 4th November, 2010, for clause (fa) (w.e.f. 8-11-2010). Earlier 
  clause (fa) was inserted by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009). 
  Clause (fa), before substitution, stood as under:</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>22</number>  Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, 
published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 
1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>23</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>24</number>16A ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>25</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>26</number> ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>27</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 887(E), dated 4th November, 2010 (w.e.f. 8-11-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>28</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>29</number>16C ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>30</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>31</number>16D ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>32</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>33</number>16E ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>34</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>35</number>16F ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>36</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>37</number>16G ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>38</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>39</number>16H ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>40</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>41</number>16I ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>42</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>43</number>16-J ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>44</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>45</number>16-K ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>46</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>47</number>16-L ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>48</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>49</number> ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>50</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 887(E), dated 4th November, 2010, for “Effect of suspension” (w.e.f. 8-11-2010).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>51</number> Vide  G.S.R. 361(E), dated 31st March, 1987, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 1st April, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>52</number>16-N ins. by G.S.R. 938(E), dated 31st December, 2009 (w.e.f. 31-12-2009).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>53</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 543(E), dated 1st 
June, 1990 (w.e.f. 5-6-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>54</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 543(E), dated 1st 
June, 1990 (w.e.f. 5-6-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>55</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 543(E), dated 1st 
June, 1990 (w.e.f. 5-6-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>56</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 543(E), dated 1st 
June, 1990 (w.e.f. 5-6-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>57</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 543(E), dated 1st 
June, 1990 (w.e.f. 5-6-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>58</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 543(E), dated 
1st June, 1990 (w.e.f. 5-6-1990).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>59</number>  Ins. by G.S.R. 543(E), dated 1st 
June, 1990 (w.e.f. 5-6-1990).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>