<act><title>


THE PROTECTION OF WOMEN FROM DOMESTIC VIOLENCE Act, 2005</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Protection of Women from Domestic Violence Act, 2005. 
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
It shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> as the Central Government may, by
notification in the Official Gazette, appoint.
  








 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
 “aggrieved
person” means any woman who is, or has been, in a domestic relationship with
the respondent and who alleges to have been subjected to any act of domestic
violence by the respondent;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“child” means any person below the age of eighteen years and includes
any adopted, step or foster child;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“compensation order” means an order granted in terms of section 22;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
“custody order” means an order granted in terms of section 21;
 </section><section><number>e</number>
“domestic incident report” means a report made in the prescribed form
on receipt of a complaint of domestic violence from an aggrieved person;
 </section><section><number>f</number>
“domestic relationship” means a relationship between two persons who
live or have, at any point of time, lived together in a shared household, when
they are related by consanguinity, marriage, or through a relationship in the
nature of marriage, adoption or are family members living together as a joint
family;
 </section><section><number>g</number>
“domestic violence” has the same meaning as assigned to it in
section 3;
 </section><section><number>h</number>
“dowry” shall have the same meaning as assigned to it in section 2 of
the Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961 (28 of 1961);
 </section><section><number>i</number>
“Magistrate” means the Judicial Magistrate of the first class, or as
the case may be, the Metropolitan Magistrate, exercising jurisdiction under the
Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) in the area where the aggrieved
person resides temporarily or otherwise or the respondent resides or the
domestic violence is alleged to have taken place;
 </section><section><number>j</number>
“medical facility” means such facility as may be notified by the
State Government to be a medical facility for the purposes of this Act;
 </section><section><number>k</number>
“monetary relief” means the compensation which the Magistrate may
order the respondent to pay to the aggrieved person, at any stage during the
hearing of an application seeking any relief under this Act, to meet the
expenses incurred and the losses suffered by the aggrieved person as a result of
the domestic violence;
 </section><section><number>l</number>
“notification” means a notification published in the Official Gazette
and the expression “notified” shall be construed accordingly;
 </section><section><number>m</number>
“prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under this Act;
 </section><section><number>n</number>
“Protection Officer” means an officer appointed by the State
Government under sub-section (1) of section 8;
 </section><section><number>o</number>
“protection order” means an order made in terms of section 18;
 </section><section><number>p</number>
“residence order” means an order granted in terms of sub-section (1)
of section 19;
 </section><section><number>q</number>
“respondent” means any adult male person who is, or has been, in a
domestic relationship with the aggrieved person and against whom the aggrieved
person has sought any relief under this Act:
 Provided
that an aggrieved wife or female living in a relationship in the nature of a
marriage may also file a complaint against a relative of the husband or the male
partner.
 </section><section><number>r</number>
“service provider” means an entity registered under sub-section (1)
of section 10;
 </section><section><number>s</number>
“shared household” means a household where the person aggrieved lives
or at any stage has lived in a domestic relationship either singly or along with
the respondent and includes such a household whether owned or tenanted either
jointly by the aggrieved person and the respondent, or owned or tenanted by
either of them in respect of which either the aggrieved person or the respondent
or both jointly or singly have any right, title, interest or equity and includes
such a household which may belong to the joint family of which the respondent is
a member, irrespective of whether the respondent or the aggrieved person has any
right, title or interest in the shared household.
 </section><section><number>t</number>
“shelter home” means any shelter home as may be notified by the State
Government to be a shelter home for the purposes of this Act.
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Definition of domestic violence.—For
the purposes of this Act, any act, omission or commission or conduct of the
respondent shall constitute domestic violence in case it—
 <section><number>a</number>
 harms or injures
or endangers the health, safety, life, limb or well‑being, whether mental
or physical, of the aggrieved person or tends to do so and includes causing
physical abuse, sexual abuse, verbal and emotional abuse and economic abuse; or
 </section><section><number>b</number>
 harasses, harms,
injures or endangers the aggrieved person with a view to coerce her or any other
person related to her to meet any unlawful demand for any dowry or other
property or valuable security; or
 </section><section><number>c</number>
 has the effect of threatening
the aggrieved person or any person related to her by any conduct mentioned in
clause (a) or clause (b); or
 </section><section><number>d</number>
 otherwise injures
or causes harm, whether physical or mental, to the aggrieved person.
 Explanation
I.—For
the purposes of this section,—
 <subsection><number>i</number>
 “physical
abuse” means any act or conduct which is of such a nature as to cause bodily
pain, harm, or danger to life, limb, or health or impair the health or
development of the aggrieved person and includes assault, criminal intimidation
and criminal force;
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>
 “sexual abuse”
includes any conduct of a sexual nature that abuses, humiliates, degrades or
otherwise violates the dignity of woman;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number>
 “verbal and
emotional abuse” includes—
 <subsubsection><number>a</number>
insults, ridicule, humiliation, name calling and insults or ridicule specially
with regard to not having a child or a male child; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number>
repeated threats to cause physical pain to any person in whom the aggrieved
person is interested.
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>iv</number>
“economic abuse” includes­—
 <subsubsection><number>a</number>
deprivation of all or any economic or financial resources to which the
aggrieved person is entitled under any law or custom whether payable under an
order of a court or otherwise or which the aggrieved person requires out of
necessity including, but not limited to, household necessities for the aggrieved
person and her children, if any, stridhan, property, jointly or
separately owned by the aggrieved person, payment of rental related to the
shared household and maintenance;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number>
 disposal of
household effects, any alienation of assets whether movable or immovable,
valuables, shares, securities, bonds and the like or other property in which the
aggrieved person has an interest or is entitled to use by virtue of the domestic
relationship or which may be reasonably required by the aggrieved person or her
children or her stridhan or any other property jointly or separately held
by the aggrieved person; and
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number>
 prohibition or
restriction to continued access to resources or facilities which the aggrieved
person is entitled to use or enjoy by virtue of the domestic relationship
including access to the shared household.
 Explanation
II.—For the purpose of determining whether any act, omission, commission
or conduct of the respondent constitutes “domestic violence” under this
section, the overall facts and circumstances of the case shall be taken
into consideration.
  




 



</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>4</number>
Information to Protection Officer and exclusion of liability of informant.—
<section><number>1</number>
Any person who has reason to believe that an act of domestic violence has been,
or is being, or is likely to be committed, may give information about it to the
concerned Protection Officer.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
No liability, civil or criminal, shall be incurred by any person for giving in
good faith of information for the purpose of sub-section (1).
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>5</number>
Duties of police officers, service providers and Magistrate.—A
police officer, Protection Officer, service provider or Magistrate who has
received a complaint of domestic violence or is otherwise present at the place
of an incident of domestic violence or when the incident of domestic violence is
reported to him, shall inform the
aggrieved person— 
 <section>
 <number>a</number>
 of her right to make an
application for obtaining a relief by way of a protection order, an order for
monetary relief, a custody order, a residence order, a compensation order or
more than one such order under this Act;
 </section><section>
 <number>b</number>
 of the availability of
services of service providers; 
 </section><section><number>c</number>
of the availability of services of the Protection Officers;
 </section><section><number>d</number>
of her right to free legal services under the Legal Services Authorities
Act, 1987 (39 of 1987); 
 </section><section><number>e</number>
of her right to file a complaint under section 498A of the Indian Penal
Code (45 of 1860), wherever relevant: 
 Provided
that nothing in this Act shall be construed in any manner as to relieve a police
officer from his duty to proceed in accordance with law upon receipt of
information as to the commission of a cognizable offence.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Duties of shelter homes.—If an
aggrieved person or on her behalf a Protection Officer or a service provider
requests the person in charge of a shelter home to provide shelter to her, such
person  in
charge of the shelter home shall provide shelter to the aggrieved person in the
shelter home.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Duties of medical facilities.—If 
an aggrieved person or, on her behalf a Protection Officer or a service provider 
requests the person in charge of a medical facility to provide any medical aid 
to her, such person in charge of the medical facility shall provide medical aid 
to the aggrieved person in the medical facility.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Appointment of Protection Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The State Government shall, by notification, appoint such number of Protection 
Officers in each district as it may consider necessary and shall also notify the 
area or areas within which a Protection Officer shall exercise the powers and 
perform the duties conferred on him by or under this Act.

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Protection Officers shall as far as possible be women and shall possess 
such qualifications and experience as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The terms and conditions of service of the Protection Officer and the other 
officers subordinate to him shall be such as may be prescribed.




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Duties and functions of Protection Officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
It shall be the duty of the Protection Officer—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
to assist the Magistrate in the discharge of his functions under this 
Act;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
to make a domestic incident report to the Magistrate, in such form and in 
such manner as may be prescribed, upon receipt of a complaint of domestic 
violence and forward copies thereof to the police officer in charge of the 
police station within the local limits of whose jurisdiction domestic violence 
is alleged to have been committed and to the service providers in that area;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
 to make an application in such 
form and in such manner as may be prescribed to the Magistrate, if the aggrieved 
person so desires, claiming relief for issuance of a protection order;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
 to ensure that the aggrieved 
person is provided legal aid under the Legal Services Authorities Act, 1987 (39 
of 1987) and make available free of cost the prescribed form in which a 
complaint is to be made;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
 to maintain a list of all 
service providers providing legal aid or counselling, shelter homes and medical 
facilities in a local area within the jurisdiction of the Magistrate;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
to make available a safe shelter home, if the aggrieved person so 
requires and forward a copy of his report of having lodged the aggrieved person 
in a shelter home to the police station and the Magistrate having jurisdiction 
in the area where the shelter home is situated;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>
 to get the aggrieved person 
medically examined, if she has sustained bodily injuries and forward a copy of 
the medical report to the police station and the Magistrate having jurisdiction 
in the area where the domestic violence is alleged to have been taken 
place;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>
 to ensure that the order for 
monetary relief under section 20 is complied with and executed, in accordance 
with the procedure prescribed under the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974);
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>
 to perform such other duties 
as may be prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Protection Officer shall be under the control and supervision of the 
Magistrate, and shall perform the duties imposed on him by the Magistrate and 
the Government by, or under, this Act.




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Service providers.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to 
such rules as may be made in this behalf, any voluntary association registered 
under the Societies Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860) or a company registered 
under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956) or any other law for the time being in 
force with the objective of protecting the rights and interests of women by any 
lawful means including providing of legal aid, medical, financial or other 
assistance shall register itself with the State Government as a service provider 
for the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A service provider registered under sub‑section (1) shall have the power to—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
 record the 
domestic incident report in the prescribed form if the aggrieved person so 
desires and forward a copy thereof to the Magistrate and the Protection Officer 
having jurisdiction in the area where the domestic violence took place;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
 get the aggrieved person 
medically examined and forward a copy of the medical report to the Protection 
Officer and the police station within the local limits of which the domestic 
violence took place;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
 ensure that the 
aggrieved person is provided shelter in a shelter home, if she so requires and 
forward a report of the lodging of the aggrieved person in the shelter home to 
the police station within the local limits of which the domestic violence took 
place.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any service 
provider or any member of the service provider who is, or who is deemed to be, 
acting or purporting to act under this Act, for anything which is in good faith 
done or intended to be done in the exercise of powers or discharge of functions 
under this Act towards the prevention of the commission of domestic violence.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Duties of Government.—The 
Central Government and every State Government, shall take all measures to ensure 
that—
 <section>
<number>a</number>
 the provisions of this Act are 
given wide publicity through public media including the television, radio and 
the print media at regular intervals;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
the Central Government and State Government officers including the police 
officers and the members of the judicial services are given periodic 
sensitization and awareness training on the issues addressed by this Act;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
 effective 
co‑ordination between the services provided by concerned Ministries and 
Departments dealing with law, home affairs including law and order, health and 
human resources to address issues of domestic violence is established and 
periodical review of the same is conducted;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
 protocols for the 
various Ministries concerned with the delivery of services to women under this 
Act including the courts are prepared and put in place.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Application to Magistrate.—
<section><number>1</number>
An aggrieved person or a Protection Officer or any other person on behalf of 
the aggrieved person may present an application to the Magistrate seeking one or 
more reliefs under this Act:
 
Provided that before passing any order on such application, the Magistrate shall 
take into consideration any domestic incident report received by him from the 
Protection Officer or the service provider.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The relief sought for under sub-section (1) may include a relief for 
issuance of an order for payment of compensation or damages without prejudice to 
the right of such person to institute a suit for compensation or damages for the 
injuries caused by the acts of domestic violence committed by the respondent:
 
Provided that where a decree for any amount as compensation or damages has been 
passed by any court in favour of the aggrieved person, the amount, if any, paid 
or payable in pursuance of the order made by the Magistrate under this Act shall 
be set off against the amount payable under such decree and the decree shall, 
notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 
1908), or any other law for the time being in force, be executable for the 
balance amount, if any, left after s
 
uch set off.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every application under sub-section (1) shall be in such form and contain 
such particulars as may be prescribed or as nearly as possible thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Magistrate shall fix the first date of hearing, which shall not 
ordinarily be beyond three days from the date of receipt of the application by 
the court.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Magistrate shall endeavour to dispose of every application made under 
sub-section (1) within a period of sixty days from the date of its first 
hearing.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Service of notice.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A notice of the date of hearing fixed under section 12 shall be given by the 
Magistrate to the Protection Officer, who shall get it served by such means as 
may be prescribed on the respondent, and on any other person, as directed by the 
Magistrate within a maximum period of two days or such further reasonable time 
as may be allowed by the Magistrate from the date of its receipt.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A declaration of service of notice made by the Protection Officer in such 
form as may be prescribed shall be the proof that such notice was served 
upon the respondent and on any other person as directed by the Magistrate unless 
the contrary is proved.
  





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Counselling.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Magistrate may, at any stage of the proceedings under this Act, direct the 
respondent or the aggrieved person, either singly or jointly, to undergo 
counselling with any member of a service provider who possess such 
qualifications and experience in counselling as may be prescribed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Magistrate has issued any direction under sub‑section (1), he 
shall fix the next date of hearing of the case within a period not exceeding two 
months.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Assistance of welfare expert.—In 
any proceeding under this Act, the Magistrate may secure the services of such 
person, preferably a woman, whether related to the aggrieved person or not, 
including a person engaged in promoting  family
welfare as he thinks fit, for the purpose of assisting him in discharging 
his functions.




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Proceedings to be held in camera.—If 
the Magistrate considers that the circumstances of the case so warrant, and if 
either party to the proceedings so desires, he may conduct the proceedings under 
this Act in camera.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Right to reside in a shared household.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, 
every woman in a domestic relationship shall have the right to reside in the 
shared household, whether or not she has any right, title or beneficial interest 
in the same.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The aggrieved person shall not be evicted or excluded from the shared 
household or any part of it by the respondent 
save in accordance with the procedure established by law.
  






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Protection orders.—The 
Magistrate may, after giving the aggrieved person and the respondent an 
opportunity of being heard and on being prima facie satisfied that 
domestic violence has taken place or is likely to take place, pass a protection 
order in favour of the aggrieved person and prohibit the respondent from—
 <section>
<number>a</number>
 committing any act 
of domestic violence;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>
 aiding or abetting 
in the commission of acts of domestic violence;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>
 entering the place 
of employment of the aggrieved person or, if the person aggrieved is a child, 
its school or any other place frequented by the aggrieved person;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>
 attempting to 
communicate in any form, whatsoever, with the aggrieved person, including 
personal, oral or written or electronic or telephonic contact;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>
 alienating any 
assets, operating bank lockers or bank accounts used or held or enjoyed by both 
the parties, jointly by the aggrieved person and the respondent or singly by the 
respondent, including her stridhan or any other property held either 
jointly by the parties or separately by them without the leave of the 
Magistrate;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>
causing violence to the dependants, other relatives or any person who 
give the aggrieved person assistance from domestic violence;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>
 committing any 
other act as specified in the protection order.




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Residence orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
While disposing of an application under sub‑section (1) of section 12, the 
Magistrate may, on being satisfied that domestic violence has taken place, pass 
a residence order—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
restraining the respondent from dispossessing or in any other manner 
disturbing the possession of the aggrieved person from the shared household, 
whether or not the respondent has a legal or equitable interest in the shared 
household;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
 directing the 
respondent to remove himself from the shared household;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
 restraining the 
respondent or any of his relatives from entering any portion of the shared 
household in which the aggrieved person resides;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
 restraining the 
respondent from alienating or disposing of the shared household or encumbering 
the same;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>
restraining the respondent from renouncing his rights in the shared 
household except with the leave of the Magistrate; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
directing the respondent to secure same level of alternate accommodation 
for the aggrieved person as enjoyed by her in the shared household or to pay 
rent for the same, if the circumstances so require:
 
Provided that no order under clause (b) shall be passed against any person who 
is a woman.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Magistrate may impose any additional conditions or pass any other 
direction which he may deem reasonably necessary to protect or to provide for 
the safety of the aggrieved person or any child of such aggrieved person.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Magistrate may require from the respondent to execute a bond, with or 
without sureties, for preventing the commission of domestic violence.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> An order under sub-section (3) shall be deemed to be an order under Chapter 
VIII of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) and shall be dealt with 
accordingly.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> While passing an order under sub-section (1), sub-section (2) or sub-section 
(3), the court may also pass an order directing the officer-in-charge of the 
nearest police station to give protection to the aggrieved person or to assist 
her or the person making an application on her behalf in the implementation of 
the order.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> While making an order under sub-section (1), the Magistrate may impose on 
the respondent obligations relating to the discharge of rent and other payments, 
having regard to the financial needs and resources of the parties.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The Magistrate may direct the officer-in-charge of the police station in 
whose jurisdiction the Magistrate has been approached to assist in the 
implementation of the protection order.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The Magistrate may direct the respondent to return to the possession of the 
aggrieved person her stridhan or any other property or valuable security 
to which she is entitled to.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Monetary reliefs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
While disposing of an application under sub-section (1) of section 12, the 
Magistrate may direct the respondent to pay monetary relief to meet the expenses 
incurred and losses suffered by the aggrieved person and any child of the 
aggrieved person as a result of the domestic violence and such relief may 
include but is not limited to—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the loss of earnings;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the medical expenses;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the loss caused due to the destruction, damage or removal of any property 
from the control of the aggrieved person; and
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>
the maintenance for the aggrieved person as well as her children, if any, 
including an order under or in addition to an order of maintenance under section 
125 of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974) or any other law for the 
time being in force.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The monetary relief granted under this section shall be adequate, fair and 
reasonable and consistent with the standard of living to which the aggrieved 
person is accustomed.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Magistrate shall have the power to order an appropriate lump sum payment 
or monthly payments of maintenance, as the nature and circumstances of the case 
may require.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Magistrate shall send a copy of the order for monetary relief made under 
sub-section (1) to the parties to the application and to the in-charge of the 
police station within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the respondent 
resides.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The respondent shall pay the monetary relief granted to the aggrieved person 
within the period specified in the order under sub‑section (1).
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Upon the failure on the part of the respondent to make payment in terms of 
the order under sub‑section (1), the Magistrate may direct the employer or a 
debtor of the respondent, to directly pay to the aggrieved person or to deposit 
with the court a portion of the wages or salaries or debt due to or accrued to 
the credit of the respondent, which amount may be adjusted towards the monetary 
relief payable by the respondent.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Custody orders.—Notwithstanding 
anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the Magistrate 
may, at any stage of hearing of the application for protection order or for any 
other relief under this Act grant temporary custody of any child or children to 
the aggrieved person or the person making an application on her behalf and 
specify, if necessary, the arrangements for visit of such child or children by 
the respondent:
 
Provided that if the Magistrate is of the opinion that any visit of the 
respondent may be harmful to the interests of the child or children, the 
Magistrate shall refuse to allow such visit.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Compensation orders.—In 
addition to other reliefs as may be granted under this Act, the Magistrate may 
on an application being made by the aggrieved person, pass an order directing 
the respondent to pay compensation and damages for the injuries, including 
mental torture and emotional distress, caused by the acts of domestic violence 
committed by that respondent.




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Power to grant interim and ex parte orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In any proceeding before him under this Act, the Magistrate may pass such 
interim order as he deems just and proper.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Magistrate is satisfied that an application prima facie 
discloses that the respondent is committing, or has committed an act of domestic 
violence or that there is a likelihood that the respondent may commit an act of 
domestic violence, he may grant an ex parte order on the basis of the 
affidavit in such form, as may be prescribed, of the aggrieved person under 
section 18, section 19, section 20, section 21 or, as the case may be, section 
22 against the respondent.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Court to give copies of order free of cost.—The 
Magistrate shall, in all cases where he has passed any order under this Act, 
order that a copy of such order, shall be given free of cost, to the parties to 
the application, the police officer-in‑charge of the police station in the 
jurisdiction of which the Magistrate has been approached, and any service 
provider located within the local limits of the jurisdiction of the court and if 
any service provider has registered a domestic incident report, to that service 
provider.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Duration and alteration of orders.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A protection order made under section 18 shall be in force till the aggrieved 
person applies for discharge.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the Magistrate, on receipt of an application from the aggrieved person or 
the respondent, is satisfied that there is a change in the circumstances 
requiring alteration, modification or revocation of any order made under this 
Act, he may, for reasons to be recorded in writing pass such order, as he may 
deem appropriate.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Relief in other suits and legal proceedings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Any relief available under sections 18, 19, 20, 21 and 22 may also be sought in 
any legal proceeding, before a civil court, family court or a criminal court, 
affecting the aggrieved person and the respondent whether such proceeding was 
initiated before or after the commencement of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any relief referred to in sub‑section (1) may be sought for in addition to 
and along with any other relief that the aggrieved person may seek in such suit 
or legal proceeding before a civil or criminal court.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In case any relief has been obtained by the aggrieved person in any 
proceedings other than a proceeding under this Act, she shall be bound to inform 
the Magistrate of the grant of such relief.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The court of Judicial Magistrate of the first class or the Metropolitan 
Magistrate, as the case may be, within the local limits of which—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>
the person aggrieved permanently or temporarily resides or carries on 
business or is employed; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the respondent resides or carries on business or is employed; or
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>
the cause of action has arisen,
 
shall be the competent court to grant a protection order and other orders under 
this Act and to try offences under this Act.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any order made this Act shall be enforceable throughout India.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Procedure.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in this Act, all proceedings under sections 12, 18, 
19, 20, 21, 22 and 23 and offences under section 31 shall be governed by the 
provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Nothing in sub-section (1) shall prevent the court from laying down its own 
procedure for disposal of an application under section 12 or under sub-section 
(2) of section 23.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Appeal.—There 
shall lie an appeal to the Court of Session within thirty days from the date on 
which the order made by the Magistrate is served on the aggrieved person or the 
respondent, as the case may be, whichever is later.
  






 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Protection Officers and members of service providers to be public servants.—The 
Protection Officers and members of service providers, while acting or purporting 
to act in pursuance of any of the provisions of this Act or any rules or orders 
made thereunder shall be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of 
section 21 of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860).
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Penalty for breach of protection order by respondent.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A breach of protection order, or of an interim protection order, by the 
respondent shall be an offence under this Act and shall be punishable with 
imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to one year, or 
with fine which may extend to twenty thousand rupees, or with both.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The offence under sub-section (1) shall as far as practicable be tried by 
the Magistrate who had passed the order, the breach of which has been alleged to 
have been caused by the accused.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> While framing charges under sub-section (1), the Magistrates may also frame 
charges under section 498A of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860) or any other 
provision of that Code or the Dowry Prohibition Act, 1961 (28 of 1961), as the 
case may be, if the facts disclose the commission of an offence under those 
provisions.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number>
Cognizance and proof.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code 
of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), the offence under sub-section (1) of 
section 31 shall be cognizable and non-bailable.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon the sole testimony of the aggrieved person, the court may conclude that 
an offence under sub-section (1) of section 31 has been committed by the 
accused.
  




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Penalty for not discharging duty by Protection Officer.—If 
any Protection Officer fails or refuses to discharges his duties as directed by 
the Magistrate in the protection order without any sufficient cause, he shall be 
punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to 
one year, or with fine which may extend to twenty thousand rupees, or with both.
  





 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Cognizance of offence committed by Protection Officer.—No 
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Protection Officer 
unless a complaint is filed with the previous sanction of the State Government 
or an officer authorised by it in this behalf.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Protection of action taken in good faith.—No 
suit, prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Protection 
Officer for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything which is in 
good faith done or intended to be done under this Act or any rule or order made 
thereunder.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Act not in derogation of any other law.—The 
provisions of this Act shall be in addition to, and not in derogation of the 
provisions of any other law, for the time being in force.
  




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Power of Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification, make rules for carrying out the 
provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing 
power, such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> the qualifications and experience which a Protection Officer shall possess 
under sub-section (2) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>
the terms and conditions of service of the Protection Officers and the 
other officers subordinate to him, under sub‑section (3) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> the form and manner in which a domestic incident report may be made under 
clause (b) of sub‑section (1) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> the form and the manner in which an application for protection order may be 
made to the Magistrate under clause (c) of sub‑section (1) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> the form in which a complaint is to be filed under clause (d) of 
sub­-section (1) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>
the other duties to be performed by the Protection Officer under clause 
of sub‑section (1) of section 9;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number> the rules regulating registration of service providers under sub‑section (1) 
of section 10;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number> the form in which an application under sub‑section (1) of 
section 12 seeking reliefs under this Act may be made and the particulars which 
such application shall contain under sub‑section (3) of that section;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number> the means of serving notices under sub‑section (1) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number> the form of declaration of service of notice to be made by the Protection 
Officer under sub‑section (2) of section 13;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number> the qualifications and experience in counselling which a member of the 
service provider shall possess under sub‑section (1) of section 14;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>
the form in which an affidavit may be filed by the aggrieved person under 
sub‑section (2) of section 23;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number> any other matter which has to be, or may be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made under this Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is 
made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period 
of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in 
making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule.
  




 



</section></article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number>   Came into force on 
26-10-2006, vide S.O. 1776(E), dated 17th October, 2006, published in the 
Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 17th October, 2006.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>