<act><title>

The 
    Employment of Manual Scavengers and Construction of Dry Latrines 
    (Prohibition) Act, 1993</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title, application and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Employment of Manual Scavengers and Construction 
    of Dry Latrines (Prohibi­tion) Act, 1993.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It applies 
    in the first instance to the whole of States of Andhra Pradesh, Goa, 
    Karnataka, Maharashtra, Tripura and West Bengal and to all the Union 
    territories and it shall also apply to such other State which adopts this 
    Act by resolution passed in that behalf under clause (1) of article 252 of 
    the Constitution.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It 
    shall come into force in the States of Andhra Pradesh, Goa, Karnataka, 
    Maharashtra, Tripura and West Bengal and in the Union territories on such 
    date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification, appoint and in any other State 
    which adopts this Act under clause (1) of article 252 of the Constitution, 
    on the date of such adoption.
 
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In this Act, unless 
    the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   “area”, in relation to any provision of 
    this Act, means such area as the State Government may, having regard to the 
    requirements of that provi­sion, specify by notification; 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   “building” means a house, out‑house, 
    stable, latrine, urinal, sheet house, hut, wall (other than a boundary wall) 
    or any other structure whether made of masonry, bricks, wood, mud, metal or 
    other material; 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “dry latrine” means a latrine other than 
    a water‑seal latrine; 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “environment” includes water, air and 
    the land and the inter‑relationship which exists among and between water, 
    air and land and human beings, other living creatures, plants, 
    micro‑organism and property; 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   “environmental pollutant” means any 
    solid, liquid or gaseous substance present in such concentration as may be, 
    or tend to be, injurious to environment; 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   “environmental pollution” means the 
    presence in the environment of any environmental pollutant; 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “Executive Authority” means an Executive 
    Authority appointed under sub‑section (1) of section 5; 
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “HUDCO” means the Housing and Urban 
    Development Corporation Limited, a Government company registered by that 
    name under the Companies Act, 1956 (1 of 1956); 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   “latrine” means a place set apart for 
    defecation together with the structure comprising such place, the receptacle 
    therein for collection of human excreta and the fittings and apparatus, if 
    any, connected therewith; 
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   “manual scavenger” means a person 
    engaged in or employed for manually carrying human excreta and the 
    expression “manual scavenging” shall be construed accordingly; 
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   “notification” means a notification 
    published in the Official Gazette; 
 </section><section>
<number>l</number>   “prescribed” means prescribed by rules 
    made under this Act; 
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>   “State Government”, in relation to a 
    Union territory, means the Admin­istrator thereof appointed under article 
    239 of the Constitution; 
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>   “water‑seal latrine” means a pour‑flush 
    latrine, water flush latrine or a sanitary latrine with a minimum water‑seal 
    of 20 millimetres diameter in which human excreta is pushed in or flushed by 
    water. 
  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Prohibition of employment of manual scavengers, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to sub‑section (2) and the other provisions of this Act, with effect 
    from such date and in such area as the State Government may, by 
    notification, specify in this behalf, no person shall— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   engage in or employ for or permit to be 
    engaged in or employed for any other person for manually carrying human 
    excreta; or 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   construct or maintain a dry latrine. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The State 
    Government shall not issue a notification under sub‑section (1) unless— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   it has, by notification, given not less 
    than ninety days’ notice of its intention to do so; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   adequate facilities for the use of 
    water‑seal latrines in that area exist; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   it is necessary or expedient to do so 
    for the protection and improvement of the environment or public health in 
    that area. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Power to 
    exempt.—The State Government may, 
    by a general or special order published in the Official Gazette, and upon 
    such conditions, if any, as it may think fit to impose, exempt any area, 
    category of buildings or class of persons from any provisions of this Act or 
    from any specified requirement contained in this Act or any rule, order, 
    notification or scheme made thereunder or dispense with the observance of 
    any such requirement in a class or classes of cases, if it is satisfied that 
    compliance with such provisions or such requirement is or ought to be 
    exempted or dispensed with in the circumstances of the case. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Appointment of Executive Authorities and their powers and functions.—­The 
    State Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, appoint a 
    District Magistrate or a Sub‑Divisional Magistrate, as an Executive 
    Authority to exercise jurisdiction within such area as may be specified in 
    the order and confer such powers and impose such duties on him, as may be 
    necessary to ensure that the provisions of this Act are properly carried out 
    and the Executive Authority may specify the officer or officers, subordinate 
    io him, who shall exercise all or any of the powers, and perform all or any 
    of the duties, so conferred or imposed and the local limits within which 
    such powers or duties shall be carried out by the officer or officers so 
    specified. 
 <section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Executive Authority appointed under sub‑section (1) and the officer or 
    officers specified under that sub‑section shall, as far as practicable, try 
    to rehabilitate and promote the welfare of the persons who were engaged in 
    or employed for as manual scavengers in any area in respect of which a 
    notification under sub‑section (1) of section 3 has been issued by securing 
    and protecting their economic interests. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Power of 
    State Government to make schemes.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Govern­ment may, by notification, make one or more schemes for 
    regulating conversion of dry latrines into, or construction and maintenance 
    of, water‑seal latrines, rehabilita­tion of the persons who were engaged in 
    or employed for as manual scavengers in any area in respect of which a 
    notification under sub‑section (1) of section 3 has been issued in gainful 
    employment and administration of such schemes and different schemes may be 
    made in relation to different areas and for different purposes of this Act: 
 
Provided that 
    no such scheme as involving financial assistance from the HUDCO shall be 
    made without consulting it. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such schemes may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   time‑bound phased programme for the 
    conversion of dry latrines into water‑seal latrines; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   provision of technical or financial 
    assistance for new or alternate low cost sanitation to local bodies or other 
    agencies; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   construction and maintenance of 
    community latrines and regulation of their use on pay and use basis; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   construction and maintenance of shared 
    latrines in slum areas or for the benefit of socially and economically 
    backward classes of citizens; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   registration of manual scavengers and 
    their rehabilitation; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   specification and standards of 
    water‑seal latrines; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   procedure for conversion of dry latrines 
    into water‑seal latrines; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   licensing for collection of fees in 
    respect of community latrines or shared latrines. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power of 
    State Government to issue directions.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law but subject to the other provisions of 
    this Act, the State Government may, in the exercise of its powers and 
    performance of its functions under this Act, issue directions in writing to 
    any person, officer or local or other authority and such person, officer or 
    a local or other authority shall be bound to comply with such directions. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Executive 
    Authorities, inspectors, officers and other employees of such authorities to 
    be public servants.—All Executive 
    Authorities, all officers and other employees of such authorities including 
    the officers authorised under sub‑section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 5, all inspectors 
    appointed under sub‑section (1) of section 9 and all officers and other 
    employees authorised to execute a scheme or order made under this Act, when 
    acting or purporting to act in pursuance of any provisions of this Act or 
    the rules or schemes made or orders or directions issued thereunder, shall 
    be deemed to be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the 
    Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Appointment of inspectors and their powers of entry and inspection.—­
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification, appoint such persons as it may 
    think fit to be inspectors for the purposes of this Act, and define the 
    local limits within which they shall exercise their powers under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every 
    inspector within the local limits of jurisdiction of an Executive Authority 
    shall be subordinate to such authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to 
    any rules made in this behalf by the State Government, an inspector may, 
    within the local limits of his jurisdiction, enter, at all reasonable times, 
    with such assistance, as he considers necessary, any place for the purpose 
    of— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   performing any of the functions of the 
    Executive Authority entrusted to him; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   determining whether and if so in what 
    manner, any such functions are to be performed or whether any provisions of 
    this Act or the rules, orders or schemes made thereunder or any notice, 
    order, direction or authorisation served, made, given or granted under this 
    Act is being or has been complied with; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   examining and testing any latrine or for 
    conducting an inspection of any building in which he has reason to believe 
    that an offence under this Act or the rules, orders or schemes made 
    thereunder has been or is being or is about to be committed and to prevent 
    or mitigate environmental pollution. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Power to 
    Executive Authority to prevent environmental pollution in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    On receipt of information with respect to the fact or apprehension of any 
    occurrence of contravention of the provisions of section 3, whether through 
    intimation by some person or on a report of the inspector or otherwise, the 
    Executive Authority shall, as early as practicable, besides taking any other 
    action under this Act, direct the owner or occupier of the premises to take 
    such remedial measures, as may be necessary, within such reasonable time as 
    may be specified therein and in case the owner or occupier, as the case may 
    be, fails to comply with such directions, cause such remedial measures to be 
    taken as are necessary to prevent or mitigate the environmental pollution at 
    the cost of such owner or occupier of the premises. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    expenses, if any, incurred by the Executive Authority with respect to the 
    remedial measures referred to in sub‑section (1), together with interest at 
    such rate as the State Government may specify from the date when a demand 
    for the expenses is made until it is paid, may be recovered by such 
    authority or agency from the person concerned as arrears of land revenue or 
    of public demand. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Duty of 
    HUDCO to extend financial assistance in certain cases.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in its Memorandum of Association or 
    Articles of Association or schemes for the grant of loans for housing and 
    urban development, it shall be the duty of HUDCO to extend, in suitable 
    cases, financial assistance for the implementation of such schemes for the 
    construction of water‑seal latrines as may be made under section 6. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    financial assistance referred to in sub‑section (1) may be extended by HUDCO 
    on such terms and conditions (including on easy and concessional rates of 
    interest) and in such manner as it may think fit in each case or class of 
    cases. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Power to 
    levy fee.—Any order or scheme 
    which the State Government is empowered to make under this Act may, 
    notwithstanding the absence of any express provision to that effect, provide 
    for levy of fees in respect of— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   community latrines constructed under a 
    scheme on pay and use basis; or 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   shared latrines constructed under a 
    scheme; or 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   supply of copies of documents or orders 
    or extracts thereof; or 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   licensing of contractors for 
    construction of water‑seal latrines; or 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   any other purpose or matter involving 
    rendering of service by any officer, committee or authority under this Act 
    or any rule, direction, order or scheme made thereunder: 
 
Provided that 
    the State Government may, if it considers necessary so to do, in the public 
    interest, by general or special order published in the Official Gazette, 
    grant exemption on such grounds as it deems fit from the payment of any such 
    fee either in part or in full. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Constitution of committees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by no­tification, constitute— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   one or more Project Committees for 
    appraising of the schemes for the construction of water‑seal latrines in the 
    country; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   one or more Monitoring Committees to 
    monitor the progress of such schemes; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   such other committees for such purposes 
    of the Act and with such names as the Central Government may deem fit. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    composition of the committees constituted by the Central Government, the 
    powers and functions thereof, the terms and conditions of appointment of the 
    members of such committees and other matters connected therewith shall be 
    such as the Central Government may prescribe. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The members 
    of the committees under sub‑section (1) shall be paid such fees and 
    allowances for attending the meetings as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The State 
    Government may, by notification, constitute— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   one or more State Co‑ordination 
    Committees for co‑ordinating and moni­toring of the programmes for the 
    construction of water‑seal latrines in the State and rehabilitation of the 
    persons who were engaged in or employed for as manual scavengers in any area 
    in respect of which a notification under sub‑section (1) of section 3 has 
    been issued; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   such other committees for such purpose 
    of the Act and with such names as the State Government may deem fit. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The 
    composition of the committees constituted by the State Government the powers 
    and functions thereof, the terms and conditions of the members of such 
    committees and other matters connected therewith shall be such as the State 
    Government may prescribe. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The members 
    of the committees under sub‑section (4) shall be paid such fees and 
    allowances for attending the meetings as may be prescribed. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>14</number> Penalty for contravention of the provisions 
      of the Act and rules, orders, directions and schemes.—Whoever fails to comply with or contravenes any 
      of the provisions of this Act, or the rules or schemes made or orders or 
      directions issued thereunder shall, in respect of each such failure or 
      contravention be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend 
      to one year or with fine, which may extend to two thousand rupees, or with 
      both, and in case the failure or contravention continues, with additional 
      fine which may extend to one hundred rupees for every day during which 
      such failure or contravention continues after the conviction for the first 
      such failure or contravention. 
 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Offences 
    by companies.—
<section><number>1</number> If the person 
    committing an offence under this Act is a company, the company as well as 
    every person in charge of, and responsible to, the company for the conduct 
    of its business at the time of the commission of the offence, shall be 
    deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
    against and punishable accordingly: 
 
Provided that 
    nothing contained in this sub‑section shall render any such person liable to 
    any punishment, if he proves that the offence was committed without his 
    knowledge or that he had exercised all due diligence to prevent the 
    commission of such offence. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in sub‑section (1), where an offence 
    under this Act has been committed by a company and it is proved that the 
    offence has been committed with the consent or connivance of, or that the 
    commission of the offence is attributable to any neglect on the part of any 
    director, manager, managing agent or such other officer of the company, such 
    director, manager, managing agent or such other officer shall also be deemed 
    to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be proceeded against and 
    punished accordingly. 
 
Explanation.—For 
    the purpose of this section,— 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   “company” means any body corporate and 
    includes a firm or other association of individuals; and 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “director”, in relation to a firm, means 
    a partner in the firm. 
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Offences 
    to be cognizable.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), 
    every offence under this Act shall be cognizable. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Provision in relation to jurisdiction.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    No court inferior to that of a Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial 
    Magistrate of the first class shall try any offence under this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    prosecution for any offence under this Act shall be instituted except by or 
    with the previous sanction of the Executive Authority. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No court 
    shall take cognizance of any offence under this Act except upon a complaint 
    made by a person generally or specially authorised in this behalf by the 
    Executive Authority. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> 
    Limitation of prosecution.—No 
    court shall take cognizance of an offence punishable under this Act unless 
    the complaint thereof is made within three months from the date on which the 
    alleged commission of the offence came to the knowledge of the complainant. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Information, reports or returns.—The 
    Central Government may, in relation to its functions under this Act, from 
    time to time, require any person, officer, State Government or other 
    authority to furnish to it, any prescribed authority or officer any reports, 
    returns, statistics, accounts and other information as may be deemed 
    necessary and such person, officer, State Government or other authority, as 
    the case may be, shall be bound to do so. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>20</number> Protection of action taken in good 
      faith.—No suit, prosecution or 
      other legal proceedings shall lie against the Government or any officer or 
      other employee of the Government or any authority constituted under this 
      Act or executing any scheme made under this Act or any member, officer or 
      other employee of such authority or authorities in respect of anything 
      which is done or intended to be done in good faith in pursuance of this 
      Act or the rules or schemes made, or the orders or directions issued, 
      thereunder. 
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>21</number> Effect of other laws and agreements 
      inconsistent with the Act.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Subject to the provisions of sub‑section (2), the provisions of this Act, 
      the rules, schemes or orders made thereunder shall have effect 
      notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith contained in any enactment 
      other than this Act, custom, tradition, contract, agreement or other 
      instrument. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> If any act or omission constitutes an 
      offence punishable under this Act and also under any other Act, then, the 
      offender found guilty of such offence shall be liable to be punished under 
      the other Act and not under this Act. 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Power to 
    Central Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Gov­ernment may, by notification, make rules to carry out the 
    provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide 
    for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the composition of the Project 
    Committees, Monitoring Committees and other committees constituted by the 
    Central Government under sub‑sec­tion (1) of section 13, the powers and 
    functions thereof, the number of members and their terms and conditions of 
    appointment and other matters connected therewith; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the fees and allowances to be paid to 
    the members of the committees constituted under sub‑section (1) of section 
    13. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule 
    made by the Central Government under this Act, shall be laid, as soon as may 
    be after it is made, before each House of Parliament, while it is in 
    session, for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in one 
    session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of 
    the session immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
    aforesaid, both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule 
    shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
    as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment 
    shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under 
    that rule. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Power of 
    State Government to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification, makes rules, not being a matter 
    for which the rules are or required to be made by the Central Government, 
    for carrying out the provisions of this Act. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without 
    prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide 
    for all or any of the following matters, namely:— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the composition of the State 
    Co‑ordination Committees and other com­mittees constituted by the State 
    Government under sub‑section (4) of section 13, the powers and functions 
    thereof, the number of members and their terms and conditions of appointment 
    and other matters connected therewith; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the fees and allowances to be paid to 
    the members of the committees constituted under sub‑section (4) of section 
    13; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   any other matter which is required to 
    be, or may be, prescribed. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule 
    and every scheme made by the State Government under this Act shall be laid, 
    as soon as may be after it is made, before the State Legislature. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Power to 
    remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
    difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order published in the Official Gazette, make 
    such provisions, not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, as may 
    appear to it to be necessary or expedient for the removal of the difficulty: 
 
Provided that 
    no such order shall be made in relation to a State after the expiration of 
    three years from the commencement of this Act in that State. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every order 
    made under this section shall, as soon as may be after it is made, be laid 
    before each House of Parliament. 
 
 
 
 
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>