<act><title>


    The Building and Other Construction 
    Workers’ welfare CesS Rules, 19981</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short 
    title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These 
    rules may be called the Building and Other Construction Workers’ Welfare 
    Cess Rules, 1998.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall 
    come into force on the date of  their publication in the Official Gazette.
 





 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In these rules, 
    unless the context otherwise requires,—
 
 <section>
<number>a</number>    “Act” means the Building and Other 
      Construction Workers’ Welfare Cess Act, 1996 (Act 28 of 1996);
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>    “Main Act” means the Building and 
      Other Construction Workers (Regulation of Employment and  Conditions of 
      Service) Act, 1996 (Act 27 of 1996);
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>    “Form” means the form annexed to 
      these rules;
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>    all other words and expressions used 
      in these rules but not defined and defined in the Act or in the main Act 
      shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in those Acts;
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>    “specified” means specified by a 
      State Government by an order published in the Official Gazette;
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>    “Cess Collector” means an officer 
      appointed by the State Government for collection of cess under the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>    “Assessing Officer” means a gazetted 
      officer of a State Government or an officer of a local authority holding 
      an equivalent post to a gazetted officer of the State Government appointed 
      by such State Government for assessment of Cess under the Act;
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>    “Appellate Authority” means  an 
      officer, senior in rank to the Assessing Officer, appointed by  the State 
      Government for the purposes of section 11 of the Act.
</section>
  
  
  
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Levy of 
    cess.— For the purpose of levy of 
    cess under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 3 of the Act, cost of construction 
    shall include all expenditure incurred by an employer in connection with the 
    building or other construction work but shall not include—
 
 
—cost of land;
 
—any compensation paid or payable to a 
      worker or his kin under the Workmen’s Compensation Act, 1923.

  
  
  
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Time and 
    manner of collection.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    cess levied under sub-section (1) of section 3 of the Act shall be paid by 
    an employer, within thirty days of completion of the construction project or 
    within thirty days of the date on which assessment of cess payable is 
    finalised, whichever is earlier, to the cess collector.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Notwithstanding the provisions of sub-rule (1), where the duration of the 
    project or construction  work exceeds one year, cess shall be paid within 
    thirty days of completion of one year from the date of commencement of work 
    and every year thereafter at the notified rates on the cost of construction 
    incurred during the relevant period. 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Notwithstanding the provisions of sub-rule (1) and sub-rule (2), where the 
    levy of cess pertains to building and other construction work of a 
    Government or of a Public Sector Undertaking, such  Government or the Public 
    Sector Undertaking shall deduct or cause to be deducted the cess payable at 
    the notified rates from the bills paid for such works.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Notwithstanding the provisions of sub-rule (1) and sub-rule (2), where the 
    approval of a construction work by a local authority is required, every 
    application for such approval shall be accompanied by a crossed demand draft 
    in favour of the Board and payable at the station at which the Board is 
    located for an amount of cess payable at the notified  rates on the 
    estimated cost of construction:
 
Provided that 
    if the duration of the project is likely to exceed one year, the demand 
    draft may be for the amount of cess payable on cost of construction 
    estimated to be incurred during one year from the date of commencement and 
    further payments of cess due shall be made as per the provisions of sub-rule 
    (2).
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> An 
    employer may pay in advance an amount of cess calculated on the basis of the 
    estimated cost of construction along with the notice of commencement of work 
    under section 46 of the Main Act by a  crossed demand draft in favour of the 
    Board and payable at the station at which the Board is located:
 
Provided that 
    if the  duration of the project is likely to exceed one year, the demand 
    draft may be for the amount of cess payable on cost of construction 
    estimated to be incurred during one year from the date of such commencement 
    and further payment of cess due shall be made as per the provisions of 
    sub-rule (2).
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Advance 
    cess paid under sub-rules (3), (4) and (5), shall be adjusted in the final 
    assessment made by the Assessing Officer.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Transfer 
    of the proceeds of the cess to the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The proceeds of the cess collected under rule 4 shall be transferred by such 
    Government office, Public Sector Undertakings, local authority, or cess 
    collector, to the Board alongwith the form of challan prescribed (and in the 
    head of account of the Board) under the accounting procedures of the State, 
    by whatever  name they are known.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Such 
    government office of Public Sector Undertaking may deduct from the cess 
    collected, or claim from the Board, as the case may be, actual collection 
    expenses not exceeding one per cent. of the total amount collected.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The amount 
    collected shall be transferred to the Board within thirty days of its 
    collection.
  
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Information to be furnished by the employer.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every employer, within thirty days of commencement of his work of payment of 
    cess, as the case may be, furnish to the Assessing Officer, information in 
    Form I.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any change 
    or modification in the  information furnished under sub-rule (1) shall be 
    communicated to the Assessing Officer immediately but not later than thirty 
    days from the date of affecting the modification or change.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Assessment.—
<section><number>1</number> The Assessing 
    Officer, on receipt of information in Form I from an employer shall make a 
    scrutiny of such information furnished and, if he is satisfied about the 
    correctness of the particulars so furnished, he shall make an order of 
    assessment within a period not exceeding six months from the date of receipt 
    of such information in Form I, indicating the  amount of cess payable by the 
    employer and endorse a copy thereof to the employer, to the Board and to the 
    cess collector and despatch such order within five days of the date on which 
    such order is made.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The order 
    shall inter-alia specify the amount of cess due, cess already paid by 
    the employer or deducted at source and the balance amount payable and the 
    date, consistent with the provision of rule 4, by which the cess shall be 
    paid to the cess collector.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If on 
    scrutiny of information furnished, the Assessing Officer is of the opinion 
    that employer has under-calculated or miscalculated the cost of construction 
    or has  calculated less amount of cess payable, he shall issue notice to the 
    employer for assessment of the cess.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt 
    of such notice the employer shall furnish to the Assessing Officer a reply 
    together with copies of documentary or other  evidence in support of his 
    claim, within fifteen days of the receipt of the notice:
 
Provided that 
    the Assessing Officer may, in the course of assessment, afford an 
    opportunity to the assessee to be heard in person, if he so requests to 
    substantiate his claim.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If the 
    employer fails to furnish the reply within the period specified under 
    sub-rule (4), or where an employer fails to furnish information in Form I, 
    the Assessing Officer shall proceed to make the assessment on the basis of 
    available records, and other  information incidental thereto.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The 
    Assessing Officer may, at anytime while the work is in progress, authorise 
    such officer to make such enquiry at the work site or from documentary 
    evidence or in any other manner as he may think fit for the purpose of 
    estimating the cost of construction as accurately as possible.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Return 
    of overpaid cess.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the 
    Assessing Officer has passed an order of assessment and the employer decides 
    to withdraw from or foreclose the works or modifies the plan of construction 
    thereby reducing the cost of construction undertaken or has been forced by 
    other circumstances to call off the  completion of the work undertaken, he 
    may seek revision of the assessment order by making an information in Form 
    II to the Assessing Officer giving details of such reduction or stoppage of 
    work.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Revision 
    of order of assessment shall  be made by the Assessing Officer, in the same 
    manner as the original order, within thirty days of receipt of such 
    information in Form II.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Following 
    the revision of assessment as per sub-rule (2), the Assessing Officer shall, 
    wherever necessary, endorse a copy of the revised assessment to the Board or 
    cess collector, as the case may be, for making the refund of excess cess as 
    ordered in the revised assessment.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Board 
    shall, within thirty days of receipt of the endorsement from the Assessing 
    Officer under sub-rule (3), refund the amount specified in the order to the  
    employer through a demand draft payable at the station where the 
    establishment is located.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where the 
    Appellate Authority has modified the order of assessment reducing the amount 
    of cess, refund shall be made within such time as may be specified in that 
    order.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Exemption.—
<section><number>1</number> Any employer or 
    class of employers in  a State seeking exemption under section 6 of the Act 
    may  make an  application to the Director General of Labour Welfare, 
    Ministry of Labour, Government of India, stating the details of works 
    undertaken, name  of the Act or corresponding law in force in that State  
    under which he is liable to pay cess  for the welfare of the construction 
    workers and amount of cess actually paid alongwith the date of such payment 
    and proof thereof. A copy of such application shall be endorsed to each of 
    the Assessing Officer and the board concerned. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt 
    of such application the Central Government may, if it feels necessary, seek 
    a report from the State Government concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On 
    examining the grounds, facts and merits of such application the Central 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, issue an order 
    exempting the employer or class of employers, as the case may be, from 
    payment of cess payable under the Act where such cess is already levied and 
    payable under such corresponding law.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Assessment 
    proceedings shall be stopped by the Assessing Officer for a period of thirty 
    days commencing from the date of the receipt of a copy of the application  
    under sub-rule (1) to him, or till the order of the Central Government under 
    sub-rule (3) is conveyed to an employer or class of employers who made the 
    application under sub-rule (1), whichever is earlier.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Powers 
    of Assessing Officer and other officers.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An Assessing Officer, or an officer authorised under sub-rule (6) of rule 7, 
    if empowered by the State Government under section 7 of the Act, may,—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    enter any establishment where 
      building and other construction work is going on;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    make an inventory of materials, 
      machinery or other articles lying at the work place;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    enquire about the number of workers 
      engaged in various activities;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    require the production of any 
      prescribed register or any other documents relevant to the assessment of 
      cost of construction or number of workers employed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    seize or take copies of any such 
      records;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>    make general assessment of the stage 
      of the construction work having been completed;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>    direct the employer or any other 
      person incharge of the place that no material or machinery shall be 
      removed or disturbed for so long as is necessary for the purpose of any 
      examination;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>    take measurement, notes or 
      photographs;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>    exercise such other powers considered 
      absolutely necessary for reasonable assessment of cost of construction.
</subsection>
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Date of 
    payment.—Date of payment of cess 
    shall be the date on which the amount is deposited with the cess collector 
    under sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> of rule 4, or the date of deduction at source under 
    sub-rule (3) of rule 4,  or the date on which the draft has been deposited 
    with the local authority under sub-rule (4) of rule 4, as the case may be.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Penalty 
    for non-payment.—
<section><number>1</number> An Assessing 
    Officer, if it appears to him that an employer has not paid the  cess within 
    the date as specified in the assessment order or has paid less cess, 
    including the cess deducted at source or paid in advance, shall issue a 
    notice to such employer that it shall be deemed to be in arrears and such 
    Assessing Officer may, after such inquiry as it deems fit, impose on such 
    employer, a penalty not exceeding such amount of cess:
 
Provided that 
    before imposing any such penalty, such employer shall be given a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard and if after such hearing the Assessing Officer 
    is satisfied that the default was for any good and sufficient reason, no 
    penalty shall be imposed on such employer.
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Recovery of overdue amount.—For  
    the purpose of recovery of sums due on account of unpaid cess, interest for 
    overdue payment or, penalty under these rules, the assessing officer shall  
    prepare a certificate signed by  him, specifying the amount due and send it 
    to the collector of the district concerned who shall proceed to recover from 
    the said employer the amount specified thereunder as if it were an arrear of 
    land revenue.
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Appeal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    An employer aggrieved by an order of the assessment made under rule 7 or by 
    an order imposing penalty made under rule 12 may appeal against such order, 
    within three months of the receipt of such  order, to the Appellate 
    Authority.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The appeal 
    shall be accompanied with—
 
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>    the order appealed against;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>    a certificate from the cess collector 
      to the effect that the amount of cess or penalty or both, as the case may 
      be, relating to such appeal has been deposited;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>    a fee equivalent to one per cent. of 
      the amount in dispute or penalty or both, as the case may be, under such 
      appeal;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>    a statement of points in dispute;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>    documentary evidence relied upon.
</subsection>
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt 
    of the appeal the Appellate Authority may call from the Assessing Officer a 
    statement on the basis of his assessment order appealed against, as such 
    Appellate Authority may consider necessary for the disposal of such appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The 
    Appellate Authority shall give the appellant an opportunity of being heard 
    in the matter and dispose of the appeal as expeditiously as possible.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On being 
    satisfied on the quantum of cess the Appellate Authority shall confirm the 
    order of the Assessing Officer or if in his opinion the assessment was wrong 
    or on the higher side shall modify the order of assessment or if in his 
    opinion the assessment is on the lower  side or if the basis of assessment 
    is wrong, it shall remand back the assessment order to the Assessing Officer 
    alongwith his observations to rectify the wrong. 
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> An order 
    remanded back under sub-rule (5) shall be disposed of by the Assessing 
    Officer within one month in view of the observation made by the Appellate 
    Authority:
 
Provided that 
    if the amount of cess is  proposed to be enhanced the assessee shall be 
    given an opportunity of being heard.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> No appeal 
    shall lie against the order of the Appellate Authority under this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If the 
    Appellate Authority is of the opinion that the quantum of penalty imposed is 
    on the higher side or not correctly made it shall suitably modify or set 
    aside the order of the Assessing Officer, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The appeal 
    under this rule shall be disposed of by making a speaking order and  a copy 
    of such order shall be sent to each of the appellant, the Assessing Officer 
    and the Board within five days of the date on which such order is made.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> An order 
    in appeal reducing the amount of cess shall also ask the Board to refund the 
    excess cess.
 </section><section>
<number>11</number> An order 
    in appeal reducing, enhancing or confirming the orders of penalty, as the 
    case may be, shall also specify the date by which the amount of penalty 
    should be paid/refunded.
  
  
  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Filing 
    of complaints.—
<section><number>1</number> The  Assessing 
    Officer, or any inspector under the main Act, or a Trade Union, having come 
    to know of violation  of an obligation to furnish return, furnishing of 
    false information, intentionally or wilfully evading or attempting to evade 
    the payment of cess may make  a complaint to the Board. The Board on 
    receiving such complaint shall examine the complaint and if it so decide may 
    refer such complaint to the Central Government for taking legal action 
    against the offender.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Central Government on receiving such reference  may make such inquiry as may 
    be considered  necessary and authorise an inspector of appropriate 
    jurisdiction to file a complaint in the  court of law.
  
  
  

 
  


</section></article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Building and Other Construction  

    Workers’ welfare CesS Rules, 1998
 

 
 

 
 

FORM I 

(See  rule 7)
 
 
 
 


1. Name of Establishment
 
 

Registration No. under 
        Building and Other Construction Workers’ Regulation of Employment and 
        Conditions of Service) Act, 1996. Registering Authority

 
 
 

2. Address
 
 

 

 
 
 

3. Name of 
        Work
 
 

 

 
 
 

4. No.of 
        Workers employed
 
 

 

 
 
 

5. Date of 
        commencement of work
 
 

                         
        Estimated period of work :  Month  Year

 
 
 


 Date  Month
 Year
 
 

 

 
 
 


6. Estimated Cost of Construction
 
 


Details of Payment of Cess

 
 
 
 
 
 

Stage
 
 

Cost

 
 
 

 
 
 

 

 
 
 

1st 
            Year
 
 

 

 
 
 

2nd 
            Year
 
 

 

 
 
 

3rd 
            Year
 
 

 

 
 
 

4th 
            Year
 
 

 

 
 
 

Total
 
 

 



 
 
 
 
 


Amount Challan No. &amp; Date
 
 


Advance - A 

            Deduction of Source - D 

            Final - F




 
 
 

 
 
 

 
 
 

Signature of 
        the Employer 

        Name of Employer 

        Date

 
 
 

TO BE FILLED BY 
        ASSESSING OFFICER

 
 
 
 
 
 

7. Date of Completion
 
 

8. Final Cost

 
 
 

9. Date of Assessment
 
 

10. Amount Assessed

 
 
 

11. Date of Appeal
 
 

12. Date of order in 
            Appeal

 
 
 

13. Amount as per 
            Order in Appeal
 
 

14. Date of transfer 
            of cess to the Board

 
 
 

15. Amount transferred 
            Challan No. and Date
 
 

 




 
 
 

Signature  

        Designation


 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




    The Building and Other Construction  

    Workers’ welfare CesS Rules, 1998
 

 
 


FORM II 

[See  rule 9 (1)]
 



    Notice of Stoppage or Reduction of Work
 

 
 
 
 
 


1. Name of Establishment 
 
 


Registration No. under Building and Other 
          Construction Workers’ (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of 
        Service) Act, 1996

 
 
 


Address
 
 

 

 
 
 


II. Date of commencement of work
 
 


Estimated period of work :  Month
 Year

 
 
 


  Date
 Month  Year
 
 

 

 
 
 


    Estimated Cost of Work 
        (Original)
 
 


Advance Cess / Deduction at source 

        Date of Assessment Order 

        Amount of Cess Assessed

 
 
 


III. Modification  to the original 
        estimates 

        Revised date of completion / date of stoppage 

        Actual cost estimates 

        Actual cost incurred 

        Whether work is being handed over to any other person/ agency for 
        completion. If yes, Name/ Address of such person / agency
 
 


 

        Reason 

 

 

        Yes / No


 
 
 
 

 
 
 

Signature of employer 

            Name of employer 

            Date


 
 
 
 

TO BE USED BY ASSESSING 
        OFFICER

 
 
 


Date of revision of assessment 

 
 

 

 
 
 


Amount of cess after revision
 
 

 

 
 
 


Cess already received
 
 


Cess to be recovered

 
 
 


Cess to be refunded, if any
 
 


Reference to board for refund;

 
 
 

 
 
 


Date / Number

 
 
 

 
 
 


Signature

 
 
 

 
 
 


Designation


 

 
 

 
 

 

 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>