<act><title>


The Disaster Management National Executive Committee (Procedure and Allowances)
Rules, 20061</title> 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Disaster Management National Executive Committee 
(Procedures and Allowances) Rules, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 


</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Disaster Management Act, 2005 (53 of 2005);
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  “Chairperson” 
means the Chairperson of the National Executive Committee under clause (a) of 
sub-section (2) of section 8;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  “member” means 
the member of the National Executive Committee under sub-section (2) of section 
8; 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  “section” 
means a section of the Act; 
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>e</number>  
“sub-committee” means a sub-committee constituted by the National Executive 
Committee under sub-section (1) of section 9.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Words and expressions 
used herein and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act shall have the 
meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>3</number> Procedure to be 
followed by the National Executive Committee.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson of the National Executive Committee may, as and when required, 
in the implementation of the directions of the Central Government, seek guidance 
from the National Authority as to the modalities of such implementation.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson of the 
National Executive Committee shall, in case of emergency, have the power to 
exercise all or any of the powers of the National Executive Committee but 
exercise of such powers shall be subject to ratification by the National 
Executive Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chairperson of the 
National Executive Committee shall preside over the meetings of the National 
Executive Committee:
 
Provided that in the case 
of his inability to preside over any meeting of the National Executive 
Committee, he shall nominate one of members of the National Executive Committee 
to preside over the meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Chairperson of the 
National Executive Committee may nominate one or more officers:—
 <subsection>
       <number>a</number>  to assist him 
in the performance of his functions as the Chairperson of the National Executive 
Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>b</number>  to maintain 
proper records relating to the meetings of the National Executive Committee;
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>c</number>  to take follow 
up action to ensure that the decisions taken in the meetings of the National 
Executive Committee are implemented in time; and
 </subsection><subsection>
       <number>d</number>  to perform 
such other functions as the Chairperson may desire them to perform.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> The Chairperson of the 
National Executive Committee shall decide the day, time and place of a meeting 
of the National Executive Committee.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The National Executive 
Committee shall meet as often as necessary but at least once in three months.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The National Executive 
Committee shall give notice of its meeting and circulate its agenda at least 
three days in advance, unless there is an emergency situation on occurrence of a 
major disaster or a situation of such a threatening disaster, when the National 
Executive Committee shall meet at the earliest to ensure a smooth and efficient 
response.
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The National Authority 
may, invite any member of the National Executive Committee whenever required, to 
assist it in discharge of its functions.
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The National Executive 
Committee shall invite, the Secretary or Additional Secretary, as the case may 
be, of the National Authority, as a special invitee to attend its every meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>10</number> The National 
Executive Committees shall forward the minutes of every meeting to the National 
Authority.
</section></article> 

 

 <article>
<number>4</number> Allowances to be 
paid to a person associated as an expert with a sub-committee of the National 
Executive Committee.—A 
member of the sub-committee constituted under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 9, 
shall be paid traveling and daily allowances as are admissible to non-officials 
attending the meetings of committees set-up by the Central Government, as 
specified in Appendix 2 to Supplementary Rule 190.
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>