<act><title>


the Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925*</title> 

 

 <article>
<number>1</number> 
These rules and orders may be called the Indian Reserve Forces Rules, 1925.



</article> 
 


the Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
 

 <article>
<number>2</number> 
In these rules and orders “Commanding Officer” means the officer in commanding 
of reserve centre or of the corps or portion of a corps to which a reservist is 
attached for training or muster:
 
Provided that in the case 
of a reservist of the Indian Hospital Corps, who is attached for training or 
muster to a unit of his corps, his Commanding Officer will be:—
 <section>
       <number>a</number>  When the 
reservist is not called up for training, or muster, the Officer in charge, 
Indian Hospital Corps Records.
 </section><section>
       <number>b</number>  When the 
reservist is called up for training, or muster, the Commanding Officer of the 
unit to which he is attached for such a training, or muster.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><number>3A</number> The reserve shall consist 
of:—
 <section>       
<number>a</number>  Junior Commissioned officers who have been or may be transferred to 
the reserve either with their own consent or in pursuance of the conditions of 
their Commission. (SRO 291/62).
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  Viceroy’s Commissioned officers commissioned under Rules 4A and 
4B.
 </section><section>       
<number>c</number>  Indian Warrant Officers appointed under Rule 4B.
 </section><section>       
<number>d</number>  Persons enrolled under the Indian Army Act, 1911, and transferred to 
the Reserve either with their own consent or in pursuance of the conditions of 
their enrolment.
 </section><section>       
<number>e</number>  Persons enrolled under the said Act for service in the 
reserve.</section></article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>3B</number> Every reservist other than a 
reservist of the Indian Supplementary Reserve, shall be subject to military law 
until duly discharged or dismissed.</article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>3C</number> A reservist of the Indian 
Supplementary Reserve shall be subject to military law only when called out for 
service or when carrying out the annual trade test.</article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>4A</number> 
<section><number>a</number> Commissions as Risaldars or 
Jamadars in the Reserve of the Indian Army Service Corps may be granted to 
gentlemen of influence who being not more than 30 years of age are pronounced 
medically fit for service.
 </section><section><number>b</number> Such Viceroy’s Commissioned 
officers will ordinarily by retired on attaining 45 years of age.
 </section><section><number>c</number> When called out for army 
service or for training, such Viceroy’s Commissioned officers will, for the 
purposes of pay, allowances and other concessions in cash and kind, be on the 
same footing as Viceroy’s Commissioned officers of corresponding rank serving on 
the active list in A.T. units with the exception that they will not be entitled 
to clothing allowance for the period of training in peace. For the purpose of 
disability and family pensions they will be governed by the same rules as are 
applicable to the corresponding ranks mentioned above.
 </section><section><number>d</number> Viceroy’s Commissioned 
officers of the Reserve will rank among themselves according to the dates of 
their commissions and, when employed on army service, will rank with Viceroy’s 
Commissioned officers of corresponding rank in the Indian army, but as juniors 
of each rank. Viceroy’s Commissioned officers commissioned under clause (a) will 
exercise no military command except over persons belonging or attached to the 
Indian Army Service Corps.
 </section><section><number>e</number> Commissions already granted 
under the provisions of Military Department Notification No. 112, dated the 10th 
February 1905, shall be deemed to have been granted under the provisions of this 
rule.</section></article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>4B</number> 
<section><number>a</number> Gentlemen possessing the 
requisite medical and other disqualifications may be granted commissions as 
Jamadars or higher commissioned rank, or may be appointed as warrant officers, 
in the Indian Medical Department Sub-Assistant Surgeon Reserve.
 </section><section><number>b</number> Such Viceroy’s Commissioned 
officers and warrant officers will serve for a period of five years, which may 
be further extended by periods of two years at a time, until attaining the age 
of 55 years.
 </section><section><number>c</number> When called up for periodical 
training such Viceroy’s Commissioned officers and warrant officers will receive 
pay at the minimum of their rank admissible to regular military sub-assistant 
surgeons, and when called out for army service they will receive pay at the 
minimum of their rank as admissible to regular military sub-assistant surgeons, 
with increments as admissible for each year’s completed army service. Pension 
will be drawn in addition by pensioned military sub-assistant surgeons. For the 
purpose of disability and family pensions they will be under the same rules as 
regular military sub-assistant surgeons. A gratuity at the rate of one month’s 
pay for each year’s army service, based on the rate of pay drawn at the time of 
release, will be admissible on conclusion of army service.
 </section><section><number>d</number> Viceroy’s Commissioned 
officers and warrant officers of the I.M.D. S.A.S. Reserve will rank with 
regular Viceroy’s Commissioned officers and warrant officers of the 
sub-assistant surgeon branch of the I.M.D. as follows:—
 Viceroy’s Commissioned 
Officers—according to the date of joining 
the Reserve as Viceroy’s Commissioned officers, or from the date of promotion to 
Viceroy’s Commissioned officer if promoted on a date subsequent to joining the 
Reserve.
 Warrant Officers—from the date of appointment to 
the Reserve.
 </section><section><number>e</number> Appointments to the I.M.D., 
S.A.S. Reserve already made shall be deemed to have been made under the 
provisions of this rule.</section></article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>5A</number> Every reservist other than a 
reservist of the Indian Medical Department Sub-Assistant Surgeon Reserve shall 
come up for service, training or muster, when required to do so by order of his 
Commanding Officer; or for service when required to do so by order of the 
Commander-in-Chief in Indian or of any authority empowered by him in this 
behalf, and shall for this purpose attend at any place specified in such 
order.</article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>5B</number> Every reservist of the Indian 
Medical Department Sub-Assistant Surgeon Reserve shall come up for training when 
required to do so by order of his commanding officer, or for service when 
required to do so by a notification in the Gazette of India, and shall for this 
purpose attend at any place specified in such order or notifications.
 Note
 A reservist in Civil Government 
employ will, when called for periodical training, receive military pay and 
allowances. He will also receive the excess, if any, of his civil pay over his 
military pay, provided that this concession is specifically sanctioned by the 
Department of the Government of India affected, or its attached and subordinate 
offices, or by the local Government concerned in whose employ the reservist is 
serving in his civil capacity, and provided also that (except where his civil 
pay is also met from the Army Estimates) the extra expenditure involved does not 
constitute a charge against the Army Estimates. A civil sub-assistant surgeon 
belonging to the I.M.D., S.A.S. Reserve will, when called up for periodical 
training, receive civil pay in addition to military pay. Civil pay will not be 
admissible in addition to military pay for periods or mobilized army 
service.
 The periods spent in training and 
on the journey to and from the place of training will be treated as duty for 
purposes of civil leave, pension and increments of civil 
pay.</article> 
 


the Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
Every reservist shall 
inform his commanding officer of his address, and shall, on any change of such 
address, at once inform the said commanding officer of such change.
</article> 
 


the Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
No reservist shall leave India except with the permission of his commanding 
officer, and in the case of Indian Medical Department Sub-Assistant Surgeon 
Reserve, with the permission of the A.G. in India. For the purpose of this Rule, 
Nepal shall, as regards Gurkha reservists, be deemed to be included in the term 
“India” except in the case of Gurkha Reservists of the ambulance and nursing 
sections of the Indian Hospital Corps.
</article> 
 


the Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
A reservist who has, for 
any reason, failed to attend at any place when required to do so in pursuance of 
Rule 5A or 5B may be required by his commanding officer to attend for medical 
examination at the nearest military station to his home, and if so required, 
shall attend at such military station on the date appointed for such 
examination.
</article> 
 


the Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in section 126 of the Indian Army Act, 1911 
it shall not be necessary to assemble a Court of Inquiry under that section 
merely because a reservist has failed to attend when required to do so in 
pursuance of Rule 5A, 5B or 8. Such a Court of inquiry may, however, at the 
discretion of the commanding officer of the reservist, be assembled in such a 
case.
</article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>10</number> A reservist who fails to attend 
at only place on the date on which required to do so in pursuance of Rule 5A, or 
5B shall be liable, at the discretion of his commanding officer, to forfeit all 
or a portion of arrears of pay and allowances due to him. In determining the 
amount of such forfeiture regard shall be had to the length of the reservist’s 
absence and to the cause, whether reasonable or otherwise, to which it is due. 
The absence continues until the reservist is apprehended or satisfies his 
commanding officer by surrender or otherwise that he is available to fulfil his 
obligations as a reservist.</article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>11</number> 
<section><number>a</number> A reservist, who is 
discharged at his own request at any time within three calendar months from the 
date fixed for the next training or muster, shall forfeit all pay and allowances 
due to him with effect from the first day of the third calendar month preceding 
the date of such training or muster, provided that if a reservist is discharged 
on obtaining permanent civil employment under the Central or a Provincial 
Government, he shall be eligible for pay and allowances up to the date of 
discharge.
 </section><section><number>b</number> A reservist who is discharged 
for misconduct shall forfeit pay and allowances due to him with effect from the 
date of misconduct or the first day of the third calendar month preceding the 
date fixed for the next training or muster whichever is 
earlier.</section></article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>12</number> The certificate referred to in 
clause (2) of section 6 of the Indian Reserves Forces Act, 1888 may be signed by 
the commanding officer of the reservist concerned, or, in respect of a reservist 
who fails to attend for medical inspection when required to do so in pursuance 
of Rule 8, by the commanding officer of the military station at which such 
reservist was required to attend.</article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>13</number> When a person subject to the 
Indian Army Act, 1911, is to be transferred to the Reserve, his commanding 
officer shall, previous to such transfer, explain or cause to be explained to 
him the obligations and restrictions imposed by Rules 5A to 8 and the forfeiture 
which may be incurred under Rules 10 and 11. When a person not subject to the 
said Act is enrolled thereunder for service in a reserve establishment, the 
officer enrolling him shall explain the aforesaid obligations, restrictions and 
forfeiture.</article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>14</number> The authority referred to in the 
proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 7 shall be the chief officer in charge of 
the revenue administration of the district (whether known as Collector or by any 
other designation) within the local limits of whose jurisdiction the person 
claiming reinstatement was employed immediately before he was called up for 
training, muster or any service under these rules. (SRO 
400/64).</section></article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>15</number> Where a reference is made by any 
party under the proviso to sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 7 to the authority 
referred to in Rule 14, a copy of such reference shall be served upon the 
opposite party and the said authority shall decide the matter after giving both 
the parties a reasonable opportunity of being heard and after making such 
further inquiry, if any, as it thinks fit.</section></article> 
 the 
Indian Reserve Forces rules, 1925
  
 <article><number>16</number> When any reservist is called up 
for training, muster or Army service under these Ruels—
 <section>       
<number>a</number> he may, at his option, continue to subscribe to any provident or 
superannuation fund or other scheme for the benefit of employees maintained in 
connection with the employment which he relinquished immediately before he was 
called up for training, muster or Army service, at such rates as were applicable 
to him under the rules of such fund or scheme;
 </section><section>       
<number>b</number>  the employer by whom such reservist was employed shall continue to 
credit his account in the fund or scheme with the amount subscribed and the 
interest on the amount in such account in accordance with the rules of the fund 
of scheme;
 </section><section>       
<number>c</number>  such reservist may, if the rule of the fund or scheme so permit and in 
accordance with such rules, withdraw sums from the amount standing at his credit 
in the fund or scheme; and
 </section><section>       
<number>d</number>  for the purpose of calculating the amount of contribution or 
withdrawal admissible, such reservist’s salary be deemed to be the salary which 
he would have received had he not been so called up.
  </section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>