<act><title>THE OFFICIAL LANGUAGES ACT, 1963 </title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be called 
the Official Languages Act, 1963. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Section 3 shall come into force on the 26th day of January, 1965 and the 
remaining provisions of this Act shall come into force on such date<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> 
as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint 
and different dates may be appointed for different provisions of this Act. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> appointed day, in relation to section 3, means the 26th day of 
  January, 1965 and in relation to any other provision of this Act, means the 
  day on which that provision comes into force; 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Hindi means Hindi in Devanagari Script. </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[ <title><number>3</number> Continuance of English language for official 
purposes of the Union and for use in Parliament. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
the expiration of the period of fifteen years from the commencement of the 
Constitution, the English language may, as from the appointed day, continue to 
be used, in addition to Hindi, 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> for all the official purposes of the Union for which it was being used 
  immediately before that day; and 
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> for the transaction of business in Parliament: </subsection>
 Provided that the English language shall be used for purposes of 
communication between the Union and a State which has not adopted Hindi as its 
official language: 
 Provided further that where Hindi is used for purposes of communication 
between one State which has adopted Hindi as its official language and another 
State which has not adopted Hindi as its official language, such communication 
in Hindi shall be accompanied by a translation of the same in the English 
language: 
 Provided also that nothing in this sub-section shall be construed as 
preventing a State which has not adopted Hindi as its official language from 
using Hindi for purposes of communication with the Union or with a State which 
has adopted Hindi as its official language, or by agreement with any other 
State, and in such a case, it shall not be obligatory to use the English 
language for purposes of communication with that State. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) where Hindi or the 
English language is used for purposes of communication 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> between one Ministry or Department or office of the Central Government 
  and another; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> between one Ministry or Department or office of the Central Government 
  and any corporation or company owned or controlled by the Central Government 
  or any office thereof; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> between any corporation or company owned or controlled by the Central 
  Government or any office thereof and another; a translation of such 
  communication in the English language or, as the case may be, in Hindi shall 
  also be provided till such date as the staff of the concerned Ministry, 
  Department, office or corporation or company aforesaid have acquired a working 
  knowledge of Hindi. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub-section (1) both Hindi and the 
English languages shall be used for 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> resolutions, general orders, rules, notifications, administrative or 
  other reports or press communiques issued or made by the Central Government or 
  by a Ministry, Department or office thereof or by a corporation or company 
  owned or controlled by the Central Government or by any office of such 
  corporation or company; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> administrative and other reports and official papers laid before a 
  House or the Houses of Parliament; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> contracts and agreements executed, and licences, permits, notices and 
  forms of tender issued by or on behalf of the Central Government or any 
  Ministry, Department or office thereof or by a corporation or company owned or 
  controlled by the Central Government or by any office of such corporation or 
  company. </subsection>
 </section><section><number>4</number> Without prejudice to the provisions of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) 
or sub-section (3) the Central Government may, by rules made under section 8, 
provide for the language or languages to be used for the official purpose of the 
Union including the working of any Ministry, Department, section or office, and 
in making such rules, due consideration shall be given to the quick and 
efficient disposal of the official business and the interests of the general 
public and in particular, the rules so made shall ensure that persons serving in 
connection with the affairs of the Union and having proficiency either in Hindi 
or in the English language may function effectively and that they are not placed 
at a disadvantage on the ground that they do not have proficiency in both the 
languages. 
 </section><section><number>5</number> The provisions of clause (a) of sub-section (1), and the provisions of 
sub-section (2), sub-section (3) and sub-section (4) shall remain in force until 
resolutions for the discontinuance of the use of the English language for the 
purposes mentioned therein have been passed by the Legislatures of all the 
States which have not adopted Hindi as their official language and until after 
considering the resolutions aforesaid, a resolution for such discontinuance has 
been passed by each House of Parliament.] 




  </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Committee on Official Language. </title>
<section><number>1</number> After the expiration 
of ten years from the date on which section 3 comes into force, there shall be 
constituted a Committee on official language, on a resolution to that effect 
being moved in either House of Parliament with the previous sanction of the 
President and passed by both Houses. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Committee shall consist of thirty members, of whom twenty shall be 
members of the House of the People and ten shall be members of the Council of 
States, to be elected respectively by the members of the House of the People and 
the members of the Council of States in accordance with the system of 
proportional representation by means of the single transferable vote. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> It shall be the duty of the Committee to review the progress made in the 
use of Hindi for the official purposes of the Union and submit a report to the 
President making recommendations thereon and the President shall cause the 
report to be laid before each House of Parliament, and sent to all the State 
Governments. 
 </section><section><number>4</number> The President may, after consideration of the report referred to in 
sub-section (3), and the views, if any, expressed by the State Governments 
thereon, issue directions in accordance with the whole or any part of that 
report: 
 [Provided that the directions so issued shall not be inconsistent 
with the provisions of section 3.] 
1.Added by Act 1 of 1968, sec. 3 (w.e.f. 
8-1-1968). </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Authorised Hindi translation of Central Acts, etc. </title>
<section><number>1</number> A 
translation in Hindi published under the authority of the President in the 
Official Gazette on and after the appointed day 
 
 <subsection><number>a</number> of any Central Act or of any Ordinance promulgated by the President, or 
  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> of any order, rule, regulation or bye-law issued under the Constitution 
  or under any Central Act, </subsection>
 shall be deemed to be the authoritative text thereof in Hindi. (2) As 
from the appointed day, the authoritative text in the English language of all 
Bills to be introduced or amendments thereto to be moved in either House of 
Parliament shall be accompanied by a translation of the same in Hindi authorised 
in such manner as may be prescribed by rules made under this Act. 
  </section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>6</number> Authorised Hindi translation of State Acts in certain cases. 
</title>Where the Legislature of a State has prescribed any language other 
than Hindi for use in Acts passed by the Legislature of the State or in 
Ordinances promulgated by the Governor of the State, a translation of the same 
in Hindi, in addition to a translation thereof in the English language as 
required by clause (3) of article 348 of the Constitution, may be published on 
or after the appointed day under the authority of the Governor of the State in 
the Official Gazette of that State and in such a case, the translation in Hindi 
of any such Act or Ordinance shall be deemed to be the authoritative text 
thereof in the Hindi language. </article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>7</number> Optional use of Hindi or other official language in judgments 
etc., of High Courts. </title>As from the appointed day or any day thereafter 
the Governor of a State may, with the previous consent of the President, 
authorise the use of Hindi or the official language of the State, in addition to 
the English language, for the purposes of any judgment, decree or order passed 
or made by the High Court for that State and where any judgment, decree or order 
is passed or made in any such language (other than the English language), it 
shall be accompanied by a translation of the same in the English language issued 
under the authority of the High Court. 
Merely because under the order of 
the Governor issued with the previous consent of the President optional use of 
Hindi is authorised in addition to English language for the purpose of judgment, 
decree or order passed or made by the High Court and it is provided that in such 
a case the judgment, decree or order shall be accompanied by a translation of 
the same in English language, it cannot be said that section 7 of the 1963 Act 
is inconsistent with the Presidential order in so far as optional use of Hindi 
in the judgments, decrees and orders in the High Court are concerned; 
Narendra Kumar v. Rajasthan High Court, AIR 1991 Raj 33. 
</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>8</number> Power to make rules. </title>
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes 
of this Act. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every rule made under this section shall be laid, as soon as may be after 
it is made, before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session 1 [or two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree 
in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should 
not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified form or 
be of no effect, as the case may be, so however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done 
under that rule. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>9</number> Certain provisions not to apply to Jammu and Kashmir.—</title>The provisions of section 6 and section 7 shall not apply to the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
  
  </article>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Sub-section (1) of section 5 came into force on 10-1-1965, 
vide S.O. 94, dated 4th January, 1965, published in the Gazette of India, Pt. 
II, Sec. 3(ii), dated 9th January, 1965.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Subs. by Act 1 of 1968, sec. 2, for section 3 (w.e.f. 
8-1-1968).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by Act 4 of 1986, sec. 2 and Sch., for certain words 
(w.e.f. 15-5-1986).</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>