<act> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called 
the National Commission for Protection of Child Rights Rules, 2006.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the date on which the Commission for Protection of Child Rights Act, 2005 (4 
of 2006) shall come into force.
  



</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In these rules, unless the 
context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
“Act” means the Commissions for Protection of Child Rights Act, 2005 (4 of 
2006);
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
“Commission” means the National Commission for Protection of Child Rights 
constituted under section 3;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  
“Chairperson” means the Chairperson of the Commission;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  
“Member” means the Member of the Commission;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  
“Member Secretary” means the Member-Secretary of the Commission;
 </section><section>        
<number>f</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  
words and expressions used and not defined in these rules but defined in the Act 
shall have the meanings respectively assigned to them in the 
Act.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>3</number> Eligibility for appointment 
as Chairperson and other Members.—No person having any past 
record of violation of human rights or child rights shall be eligible for 
appointment as Chairperson or other Members of the 
Commission.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>4</number> 
Member-Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> The Member-Secretary 
appointed by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 
11.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Member-Secretary shall 
have a minimum tenure of three years.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>5</number> Powers and duties of the 
Member-Secretary.—
<section><number>1</number> The Member-Secretary 
shall—
 <subsection>        
<number>i</number>  have power to execute all decisions taken by the Commission in order 
to carry out the powers and functions of the Commission as provided in sections 
13 and 14;
 </subsection><subsection>        
<number>ii</number>  exercise and discharge such powers and perform such duties as are 
required for the proper administration of the affairs of the Commission and its 
day to day management as specified in section 11;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iii</number>  
convene the meetings of the Commission in consultation with its Chairperson and 
serve notices of the meetings to all concerned;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>iv</number>  
take steps to ensure that the quorum required for convening a meeting of the 
Commission is secured;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>v</number>  
prepare, in consultation with the Chairperson, the agenda for each meeting of 
the Commission and have notes prepared by the Secretariat and such notes shall, 
as far as possible, be self-contained;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>vi</number>  
make available specific records covering the agenda items to the Commission for 
reference; 
 </subsection><subsection>      <number>vii</number>  ensure 
that the agenda papers are circulated to the Members at least two clear working 
days in advance of the meeting, except in cases when urgent attention is 
required;
 </subsection><subsection>     <number>viii</number>  prepare the 
minutes of the meetings of the Commission and shall execute the decisions of the 
Commission taken in the meeting and shall also ensure placing of the Action 
Taken Note of the decisions of the Commission before the Commission in its 
subsequent meetings;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>ix</number>  
ensure that the procedure of the Commission is followed by it in transaction of 
its business;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>x</number>  take 
up all such matters with the Ministry of Women and Child Development for release 
of grants, creation of posts, revision of scales, procurement of vehicles, 
appointment of staff, laying of annual and audit report in Parliament, 
re-appropriation of funds, residential accommodation, permitting any officer of 
the Commission for deputation abroad and any other matter requiring the approval 
of the Central Government;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>xi</number>  
exercise such financial powers as are delegated to him by the Chairperson on 
behalf of the Commission;
                  
Provided that no expenditure on an item exceeding one lakh rupees shall be 
incurred without the sanction of the Chairperson;
 <subsubsection>      <number>xii</number>  be the 
appointing and disciplinary authority in respect of officers and other employees 
of the Commission.</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>6</number> Term of office of Chairperson 
and other Members.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson shall, 
unless removed from office under section 7, hold office for a period not 
exceeding three years, or till the age of sixty-five years, whichever is 
earlier.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every Member shall, unless 
removed from office under section 7, hold office for a period not exceeding 
three years, or till the age of sixty years, whichever is earlier.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything 
contained in sub-rule (1) or sub-rule (2),—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  a 
person who has held the office of Chairperson shall be eligible for 
re-nomination, and
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  a 
person who has held the office of a Member shall be eligible for re-nomination 
as a member or nomination as a Chairperson:
 Provided that a person who has 
held an office of Chairperson or Member for two terms, in any capacity shall not 
be eligible for re-nomination as Chairperson or, as the case may be, as 
Member.
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> If the Chairperson is unable 
to discharge his functions owing to illness or other incapacity, the Central 
Government shall nominate any other Member to act as Chairperson and the Member 
so nominated shall hold office of Chairperson until the Chairperson resumes 
office or till the remainder of his term.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Chairperson or a Member 
may, by writing under his hand addressed to the Central Government, resign his 
office at any time.
 </section><section><number>6</number> A vacancy caused by death, 
resignation or any other reason shall be filled-up nomination within ninety days 
from the date of occurrence of such vacancy.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>7</number> Salaries and 
allowances.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Save as otherwise provided in section 6, the Chairperson shall be paid salary 
equivalent to the salary of the Cabinet Secretary to the Government of India and 
every other Member shall be paid salary equivalent to that of a Secretary to the 
Government of India:
 Provided that where the 
Chairperson or any other Member is a retired Government servant, Semi-Government 
body, public sector undertaking or recognized research institution, the salary 
payable together with the pension or pensionary value of the terminal benefits, 
or both, received by him shall not exceed to the last pay drawn.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The salary and allowances 
payable to, and the other terms and conditions of service of the 
Member-Secretary and the other officers and other employees appointed for the 
purpose of the Commission shall be such as may be determined by the Central 
Government from time to time.
 </section><section><number>3</number> If the Chairperson or a 
Member is in service of the Central Government or a State Government, his salary 
shall be regulated in accordance with the rules applicable to 
him.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>8</number> Dearness 
allowance.—The 
Chairperson and every other Member shall receive dearness allowance appropriate 
to their pay at the rates admissible to officers of the equivalent level of the 
Central Government.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>9</number> Compensatory (City) 
Allowance.—The 
Chairperson and every other Member shall receive compensatory (city) allowance 
appropriate to their pay at the rates admissible to officers of the Central 
Government of equivalent level.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>10</number> Leave.—The Chairperson and every other 
Member shall be entitled to leave as follows:—
 <section>       <number>a</number>  
Earned leave, half pay leave and commuted leave as admissible to Central 
Government servants in accordance with the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 
1972, as amended from time to time.
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
Extraordinary leave as admissible to the temporary Central Government servants 
under the Central Civil Services (Leave) Rules, 1972, as amended from time to 
time.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>11</number> Leave sanctioning 
authority.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government shall be the authority competent to sanction leave to the 
Chairperson.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson shall be the 
authority to sanction leave to every Member including the 
Member-Secretary.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Member-Secretary shall 
be the authority to sanction leave to any officer or other employee of the 
Commission.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>12</number> Travelling 
allowance.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairperson and every other Member shall be entitled to draw travelling 
allowances and daily allowance at the rates appropriate to their pay admissible 
to equivalent post of the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson and every 
other Member shall be his own controlling officer in respect of his bills 
relating to travelling allowances and daily allowances.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>13</number> Residential 
accommodation.—
<section><number>1</number> The Chairperson and every 
other Member shall be entitled to the use of an official residence as may be 
determined by the Government of India.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If the Chairperson or a 
Member is not provided with or does not avail himself of the accommodation 
provided under sub-rule (1), he shall be paid every month house rent allowance 
at the rates admissible to officers of an equivalent rank in the Central 
Government.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>14</number> Facility for 
conveyance.—The 
Chairperson and every other Member shall be entitled to the facilities of staff 
car for journeys for official and private purpose in accordance with the Staff 
Car Rules of the Government of India, as amended from time to 
time.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>15</number> Facility for medical 
treatment.—The 
Chairperson and every other Member shall be entitled to medical treatment and 
hospital facilities as applicable to Central Government servants of equivalent 
rank as provided in the Central Government Contributory Health Scheme Rules, 
1954 or as may be determined in the Central Government.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>16</number> Residuary 
provisions.—The 
conditions of service of the Chairperson and the other Members for which no 
express provision has been made in these rules shall be such as may be 
determined by the Central Government.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>17</number> Functions of the 
Commission.—The 
Commission shall, in addition to the functions assigned to it under clauses 
<section><number>a</number> 
to (j) of sub-section (1) of section 13, perform the following functions, 
namely:—
 </section><section>       <number>a</number>  
analyze existing law, policy and practice to assess compliance with Convention 
on the Rights of the Child, undertake inquiries and produce reports on any 
aspect of policy or practice affecting children and comment on proposed new 
legislation from a child rights perspective;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number>  
present to the Central Government annually and at such other intervals as the 
Commission may deem fit, reports upon the working of those 
safeguards;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number>  
undertake formal investigations where concern has been expressed either by 
children themselves or by concerned person on their behalf;
 </section><section>       <number>d</number>  
ensure that the work of the Commission is directly informed by the views of 
children in order to reflect their priorities and perspectives;
 </section><section>       <number>e</number>  
promote, respect and serious consideration of the views of children in its work 
and in that of all Government Departments and Organisations dealing with 
child;
 </section><section>        
<number>f</number>  produce and disseminate information about child rights;
 </section><section>       <number>g</number>  
compile and analyze data on children;
 </section><section>       <number>h</number>  
promote the incorporation of child rights into the school curriculum, teachers 
training and training of personnel dealing with 
children.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>18</number> Procedure for transaction of 
business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Commission shall meet regularly at its office at Delhi at such time as the 
Chairperson thinks fit, but three months shall not intervene between its last 
meeting and the next meeting.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Commission shall 
ordinarily hold its meetings in its office located in Delhi but may, in its 
discretion, hold its meetings at any other place in India if it considers it 
necessary or expedient to do so.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Secretariat 
assistance.—The Member-Secretary, along with such officers as the 
Chairperson may direct, shall attend the meetings of the Commission.
 </section><section><number>4</number>(i) The Member-Secretary 
shall, in consultation with the Chairperson, prepare the agenda for each meeting 
of the Commission and shall have notes prepared by the Secretariat and such 
notes shall, as far as possible, be self-contained;
 <subsection><number>ii</number> The records covering the 
agenda items shall be made readily available to the Commission for its 
reference;
 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> The agenda papers shall 
ordinarily be circulated to members at least two clear working days in advance 
of the meeting, except in cases when urgent attention is required.
 </subsection></section><section><number>5</number> Four members including the 
Chairperson shall form the quorum at every meeting of the Commission.
 </section><section><number>6</number> All decisions of the 
Commission at its meetings shall be taken by majority:
 Provided that in the case of 
equality of votes, the Chairperson, or in his absence the person presiding shall 
have and exercise a second or a casting vote.
 </section><section><number>7</number> If, for any reason, the 
Chairperson is unable to attend the meeting of the Commission, any Member chosen 
by the Members present from amongst themselves at the meeting, shall 
preside.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>19</number> Minutes of the 
meeting.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The minutes of each meeting of the Commission shall be recorded during the 
meeting itself or immediately thereafter by the Member-Secretary or by any other 
officer of the Commission as directed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The minutes of meeting of 
the Commission shall be submitted to the Chairperson for approval and, upon 
approval, be circulated to all members of the Commission at the earliest and in 
any case, sufficiently before the commencement of the next meeting.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The conclusions of the 
Commission in every matter undertaken by it shall be recorded in the form of an 
opinion and dissenting opinions, if given, shall also form part of and be kept 
on record. Action shall be taken on the basis of majority opinion where there is 
any difference of opinion.
 </section><section><number>4</number> All orders and decisions of 
the Commission shall be authenticated by the Member-Secretary or any other 
officer of the Commission duly authorized by the Member-Secretary with the prior 
approval of the Chairperson in this behalf.
 </section><section><number>5</number> Unless specifically 
authorized, no action shall be taken by the Secretariat of the Commission on the 
minutes of the meetings until the Chairperson confirms the same.
 </section><section><number>6</number> A master copy of the record 
of all meetings and opinions of the Commission shall be maintained duly 
authenticated by the Member-Secretary.
 </section><section><number>7</number> A copy of the minutes 
pertaining to each item shall be kept in the respective files for appropriate 
action. Opinions shall be kept in respective records and for convenience, copies 
thereof with appropriate indexing shall be kept in guard 
files.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>20</number> Report of Action 
Taken.—Report 
of the follow up action shall be submitted by the Member-Secretary to the 
Commission at every subsequent meeting indicating therein the present stage of 
action taken on each item on which the Commission had taken any decision in any 
of its earlier meetings, excepting the items on which no further action is 
called for.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>21</number> Transaction of business 
outside headquarters.—The Commission or some members 
may transact business at places outside its headquarters as and when previously 
approved by the Chairperson, provided that if parties are to be heard in 
connection with any inquiry under the Act, at least two members shall constitute 
the bench of the Commission for such purpose.</article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>22</number> Panel of 
consultants.—
<section><number>1</number> The Commission may 
constitute a panel of consultants for assisting the Commission in a wide range 
of tasks such as investigation or inquiry; to serve on task forces or Committees 
and for research and analysis.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Commission may draw on 
experts from academic, research, administrative, investigative, legal or civil 
society groups to form the panel.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Commission may devise a 
transparent process for empanelling these consultants so that they are available 
for quick delegation of tasks.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>23</number> Annual 
report.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Commission shall prepare and publish an annual report before the 31st December 
every year for submission to the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Commission shall also 
prepare special reports on specific issues as and when necessary under the 
direction of the Chairperson.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Central Government shall 
cause the annual report and the special reports of the Commission to be laid 
before each House of Parliament.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The annual report shall 
include information on administrative and financial matters; complaints 
investigated/inquired into; action taken on cases; details of research; reviews; 
education and promotion efforts; consultations; details and specific 
recommendations of the Commission on any matter, besides any other matter that 
the Commission may consider warranting inclusion in the report.
 </section><section><number>5</number> In case the Commission 
considers that there could be a time lag for the preparation of the annual 
report, it may prepare and submit a special report to the Central 
Government.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The forms in which the 
budget may be prepared and provided and forwarded to the Central Government 
shall be as provided in Forms I, II, III and IV of Schedule I.
 </section><section><number>7</number> The estimated receipts and 
expenditure shall be accompanied by the revised budget estimates for the 
relevant financial year.
 </section><section><number>8</number> The budget shall, as far as 
may be, based on the account heads specified in Schedule 
II.</section></article> 
 The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
  
 <article><number>24</number> Financial 
powers.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
Commission shall spend the sums of money received by it for the purposes of the 
Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Chairperson shall have 
all powers relating to financial transaction of the Commission, except in cases, 
which require prior approval of the Central Government.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The Chairperson shall obtain 
prior approval of the Central Government in matters of creation of posts, 
revision of pay scales, procurement of vehicles, re-appropriation of funds from 
one head to another, permitting any officer of the Commission to participate in 
Seminars, conferences or training programmes abroad and such other matters 
determined by the Central Government, by order.
 </section><section><number>4</number> The Chairperson shall, 
subject to such conditions and limitations and control and supervision, have 
powers to delegate his financial powers to any Member or the 
Member-Secretary:
 Provided that no such powers 
shall be delegated in respect of incurring an expenditure on an item exceeding 
one lakh rupees without the prior approval of the Chairperson.
 </section><section><number>5</number> The Chairperson shall have 
powers to engage any person or persons as consultant or consultants for a 
specific purpose and for a specific period on the terms and conditions agreed in 
advance relating to honorarium, travelling allowance, dearness 
allowance.
 </section><section><number>6</number> The Member-Secretary shall 
have powers to execute all decisions taken by the Chairperson or any other 
Member on his behalf relating to financial matters.
 </section><section><number>7</number> All financial powers of the 
Commission shall be governed by the General Financial Rules, delegation of 
financial powers rules and economy instructions issued by the Ministry of 
Finance of the Central Government from time to time.</section></article><form>
 

The National Commission for Protection of 
Child Rights Rules, 2006
 

 
 

Schedule 
II
 

BudgeT and Account Heads
 

[See rule 23(8)]
 

Administration
 

Heads of Accounts (Expenditure)
 

1. 
Salaries
 

2. 
Wages
 

3. 
Travel Expenses
 

4. 
Office Expenses
 

        
(a)  Furniture
 

        
(b)  Postage
 

        
(c)  Office machines/equipment
 

        
(d)  Liveries
 

        
(e)  Hot and cold weather charges
 

         
(f)  Telephones
 

        
(g)  Electricity and water charges
 

        
(h)  Stationery
 

         
(i)  Printing
 

         
(j)  Staff car and other vehicles
 

        
(k)  Other items
 

5. 
Fee and honoraria
 

6. 
Payment for professional and special services
 

7. 
Rents, rates and taxes/royalty
 

8. 
Publications
 

9. 
Advertising sales and publicity expenses
 

10. Grant in aid/contributions/subsidies
 

11. Hospitality expenses/sumptuary allowances 
etc.
 

12. Pensions/gratuities
 

13. Write off/losses
 

14. Suspenses
 

15. Other charges (a residuary head, this will also 
include rewards and prizes)
 

Heads of Account (Receipts)
 

1. 
Payments by Central Government
 

2. 
Other receipts
 

 </form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>