<act> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS
(PROHIBITION) ACT, 1988
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title, extent and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> This Act may be 
called the Benami Transactions (Prohibition) Act, 1988.
 </section><section><number>2</number> It extends to the whole of 
India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number> The provisions of sections 
3, 5 and 8 shall come into force at once, and the remaining provisions of this 
Act shall be deemed to have come into force on the 19th day of May, 1988.
  
</section></article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS
(PROHIBITION) ACT, 1988
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>       <number>a</number> “Benami transaction” means any transaction 
in which property is transferred to one person for a consideration paid or 
provided by another person;
 </section><section>       <number>b</number> “prescribed” means prescribed by rules made under 
this Act;
 </section><section>       <number>c</number> “property” means property of any kind, whether 
movable or immovable, tangible or intangible, and includes any right or interest 
in such property.







</section></article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS (PROHIBITION) ACT, 
1988
  
 <article><number>3</number> 
Prohibition of benami transactions.—
<section><number>1</number> No person shall enter into any benami 
transaction.
 1[(2) Nothing in sub-section (1) shall apply to— 

 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the 
purchase of property by any person in the name of his wife or unmarried daughter 
and it shall be presumed, unless the contrary is proved, that the said property 
had been purchased for the benefit of the wife or the unmarried daughter;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the 
securities held by a—
 <subsubsection>             
<number>i</number>  depository as registered owner under sub-section (1) of section 10 of 
the Depositories Act, 1996
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>            
<number>ii</number>  participant as an agent of a depository.
 Explanation.—The expressions “depository” and “Participants shall 
have the meanings respectively assigned to them in clauses (e) and (g) of 
sub-section (1) of section 2 of the Depositories Act, 1996]. 
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>3</number> 
Whoever enters into any benami transaction shall be punishable with 
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years or with fine or with 
both.
 </section><section><number>4</number> 
Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 
1974), an offence under this section shall be non-cognizable and 
bailable.







</section></article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS
(PROHIBITION) ACT, 1988
  
 <article><number>4</number> Prohibition of the right 
to recover property held benami.—
<section><number>1</number> 
No suit, claim or action to enforce any right in respect of any property held 
benami against the person in whose name the property is held or against any 
other person shall lie by or on behalf of a person claiming to be the real owner 
of such property.
 </section><section><number>2</number> No defence based on any 
right in respect of any property held benami, whether against the person 
in whose name the property is held or against any other person, shall be allowed 
in any suit, claim or action by or on behalf of a person claiming to be the real 
owner of such property.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing in this section 
shall apply,—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number> where the person in whose name the property is 
held is a coparcener in a Hindu undivided family and the property is held for 
the benefit of the coparceners in the family; or
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number> where the person in whose name the property is 
held is a trustee or other person standing in a fiduciary capacity, and the 
property is held for the benefit of another person for whom he is a trustee or 
towards whom he stands in such capacity.



















</subsection></section></article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS
(PROHIBITION) ACT, 1988
  
 <article><number>5</number> Property held benami 
liable to acquisition.—
<section><number>1</number> All 
properties held benami shall be subject to acquisition by such authority, 
in such manner and after following such procedure, as may be prescribed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> For the removal of doubts, 
it is hereby declared that no amount shall be payable for the acquisition of any 
property under sub-section (1).



</section></article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS (PROHIBITION) ACT, 
1988
  
 <article><number>6</number> 
Act not to apply in certain cases.—Nothing in this Act shall affect the provisions of 
section 53 of the Transfer of Property Act, 1882 (4 of 1882), or any law 
relating to transfers for an illegal purpose.


</article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS (PROHIBITION) ACT, 
1988
  
 <article><number>7</number> 
Repeal of provisions of certain Acts.—
<section><number>1</number> Sections 81, 82 and 94 of the Indian Trusts Act, 
1882 (2 of 1882), section 66 of the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), 
and section 281A of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961), are hereby 
repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> For 
the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that nothing in sub-section (1) 
shall affect the continued operation of section 281A of the Income-tax Act, 1961 
(43 of 1961), in the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
  </section></article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS
(PROHIBITION) ACT, 1988
  
 <article><number>8</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules 
for carrying out the purposes of this Act.
 </section><section><number>2</number> In particular, and without 
prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for 
all or any of the following matters, namely:—
 <subsection>       <number>a</number>  the authority competent to acquire properties 
under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>b</number>  the manner in which, and the procedure to be 
followed for, the acquisition of properties under section 5;
 </subsection><subsection>       <number>c</number>  any other matter which is required to be, or may 
be, prescribed.
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Every rule made under this 
Act shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of thirty days which may 
be comprised in one session or in two or more successive sessions, and if, 
before the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in 
the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, as the 
case may be; so, however, that any such modification or annulment shall be 
without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done under that rule.
</section></article> 
 THE BENAMI TRANSACTIONS
(PROHIBITION) ACT, 1988
  
 <article><number>9</number> Repeal and saving.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Benami Transactions (Prohibition of the Right to Recover Property) 
Ordinance, 1988 (Ordinance 2 of 1988), is hereby repealed.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, 
anything done or any action taken under the said Ordinance shall be deemed to 
have been done or taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.
  
</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>