<act><tid>590554</tid>
<title>THE TRADING WITH THE ENEMY (CONTINUANCE OF EMERGENCY PROVISIONS) 
ACT, <year>1947</year></title>

ACT NO. 16 OF <year>1947</year>
[ 20th March, <year>1947</year>.]

An Act to provide for the continuance of certain provisions of 
the Defence of India Rules relating to the control of trading with 
States, and persons and firms belonging to States at war with the 
Government of India, and the custody of the property belonging to 
them.

It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>1734453</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.
<section><tid>1999201</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be  
called the Trading with the Enemy (Continuance of Emergency  
  Provisions) Act, <year>1947</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1207425</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>; and it applies 
also to all citizens of India outside India.]

</section>

<section><tid>15947</tid>
<number>3</number>It shall come into force on the 25th day of March, <year>1947</year>.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>539534</tid>
<number> 2</number> Continuance of certain emergency provisions.
<section><tid>1849812</tid>
<number>1</number> 
Notwithstanding the expiry of the Defence of India Act, <year>1939</year> (35 of  
  <year>1939</year>), and the Emergency Provisions (Continuance) Ordinance, <year>1946</year> (20  
  of <year>1946</year>),

<subsection><tid>742188</tid>
<number>a</number>the provisions of the Defence of India Rules mentioned 
in the first column of the Schedule to this Act shall con- 
tinue in force, and shall have effect subject to the modi- 
fications specified in the second column thereof;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>466921</tid>
<number>b</number>any order or other instrument made or deemed to be made 
under or in pursuance of any of the said provisions and in 
force immediately before the commencement of this Act shall 
continue in force so far as consistent with the provisions as 
continued in force by this section and be deemed to be made 
under or In pursuance of the provisions so continued in 
force.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>18</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year>, for the former sub- section. 
2 The words" except Part B States" were rep. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, 
s. 3 and Sch.






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1741976</tid>
<number>2</number>The references in sub- section (1) to the Defence of India 
Rules shall be construed as references to those Rules as modified and 
continued in force by the Emergency Provisions (Continuance) 
Ordinance, <year>1946</year> (20 of <year>1946</year>),



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1321213</tid>
<number>3</number>Effect of rules, etc., inconsistent with other enactments. The 
provisions of the Defence of India Rules as continued in force by 
section 2 and all orders made or deemed to be made under such 
provisions shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent 
therewith contained in any enactment other than this Act or in any 
instrument having effect by virtue of any enactment other than this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1812388</tid>
<number> 4</number> Delegations.
<section><tid>1130216</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may by order direct  
that any power or duty which by or under any of the provisions as 
continued in force by section 2 is conferred or imposed upon the 
Central Government, shall, in such circumstances and under such 
conditions, if any, as may be specified in the direction, be exercised 
or discharged by any officer or authority subordinate to that 
Government or by any other authority.

</section>

<section><tid>1364245</tid>
<number>2</number>All orders delegating any power or duty conferred or imposed by 
any of the provisions continued in force by section 2 made by the 
Central Government before the commencement of this Act and in force 
immediately before such commencement, shall continue in force and be 
deemed to be made by the Central Government under this section.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>465757</tid>
<number> 5</number> Savings as to orders.
<section><tid>1369714</tid>
<number>1</number>No order made or deemed to be  
made in exercise of any power conferred by or under any of the 
provisions continued in force by section 2 shall be called in 
question in any court.

</section>

<section><tid>746434</tid>
<number>2</number>Where an order purports to have been made and signed by any 
authority in exercise of any power conferred by or under any of the 
aforesaid provisions, a court shall, within the meaning of the Indian 
Evidence Act, <year>1872</year>, (1 of <year>1872</year>.) presume that such order was so made 
by that authority.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1076626</tid>
<number> 6</number> Protection of action taken under rules.
<section><tid>1608810</tid>
<number>1</number>No suit,  
prosecution or other legal proceeding shall lie against any person 
for anything which is in good faith done or in- tended to be done in 
pursuance of any of the provisions continued in force by section 2 or 
any order made or deemed to be made thereunder.

</section>

<section><tid>271143</tid>
<number>2</number>No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the 
Government for any damage caused or likely to be caused by anything in 
good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of any of the 
provisions continued in force by section 2 or any order made or deemed 
to be made thereunder.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>19</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>



</section>

</article>



 </act>