<act><title>THE DANGEROUS MACHINES (REGULATION) RULES, 20071</title> 

  
 <article><title><number>1</number> Short title and commencement. </title>
<section><number>1</number> These rules may be called the Dangerous Machines (Regulation) Rules, 2007. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force on such date as the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, specify, and different dates may be specified for different rules. 


</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>2</number> Definitions. </title>In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires, 
 
 <section><number>a</number> Act means the Dangerous Machines (Regulation) Act, 1983 (35 of 1983); 
 </section><section><number>b</number> Form means a form appended to the First Schedule to the rules; 
 </section><section><number>c</number> Schedule means a Schedule appended to these rules. 
</section>


</article> 

  
 <article><title><number>3</number> Form of licence issued under section 9. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every licence issued to a person authorizing him to manufacture, or to commence or to carry on business as the manufacturer of any dangerous machine shall be issued in Form I. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> There shall be issued for each category of dangerous machine, a separate licence and every such licence shall be issued in Form I. 
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every licence to commence or carry on business as a dealer of a dangerous machine shall be issued in Form II. 
(4) Every licence referred to in sub-rule (2) shall be valid for dealing with the types or models of dangerous machines specified in the licence.


</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>4</number> Standards and specifications of power threshers, power operated chaff cutter and sugarcane crushers. </title>Every licence issued under rule 3 shall ensure that the power thresher, power operated chaff cutter and sugarcane crushers manufactured by him/her complies with the standards and specifications laid down in the Second Schedule. 


</article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>5</number> Modifications of existing dangerous machines how to be made. </title>
<section><number>1</number> Every person who has, immediately before the commencement of the Act, in his/her custody or control any power thresher, power operated chaff cutter and sugarcane crusher which does not comply, in all respects, with the provisions of the Act, and the rules and orders made thereunder, shall get it modified so as to ensure that the feeding system conforms to the specifications laid down in the Third Schedule. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> The transmission system of every power thresher, power operated chaff cutter and sugarcane crusher shall be provided with suitable guards as specified in the Third Schedule. 


</section></article><form>
 

THE DANGEROUS MACHINES (REGULATION) RULES, 20071
 

THE SECOND SCHEDULE 
 

[ See rule 4] 
 

1. A power thresher shall comply with the following Indian Standards as may be relevant: 
 

IS 9020:2002 (Power Threshers-Safety Requirements) 
 

2. A power operated chaff cutter shall comply with the requirements of the following Indian Standards: 
 

IS 15542: 2005 (Power Operated Chaff Cutter-Safety requirements) 
 

IS 11459: 1985 (Specification for power operated Chaff Cutter) 
 

3. A power operated sugarcane crusher shall comply with the requirements of the following Indian Standards: 
 

IS 15561: 2005 (Sugarcane Crushers - Safety requirements) 
 

IS 1973: 1999 (Sugarcane Crusher - Specifications (third revision) 
 

----------
 

1. Vide G.S.R. 506(E), dated 24th July, 2007, published in the Gazette of India, Extra., Pt. II, 
Sec. 3(i), dated 25th July, 2007.
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>