<act><title>

The
Places of Worship (Special Provisions) Act, 1991</title> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>1</number>
Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number>
This Act may be called the Places of Worship (Special Provisions) Act, 1991.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
It extends to the whole of India except the State of Jammu and Kashmir.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
The provisions of sections 3, 6 and 8 shall come into force at once and the
remaining provisions of this Act shall be deemed to have came into force on the
11th day of July, 1991.

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>2</number>
Definitions.—In this Act, unless the
context otherwise requires,—
 <section><number>a</number>
“commencement of this Act” means the commencement of this Act on the
11th day of July, 1991;
 </section><section><number>b</number>
“conversion”, with its grammatical variations, includes alteration or
change of whatever nature;
 </section><section><number>c</number>
“place of worship” means a temple, mosque, gurudwara, church,
monastery or any other place of public religious worship of any religious
denomination or any section thereof, by whatever name called.

  


</section></article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>3</number>
Bar of conversion of places of worship.—No
person shall convert any place of worship of any religious denomination or any
section thereof into a place of worship of a different section of the same
religious denomination or of a different religious denomination or any section
thereof.
  



  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>4</number> Declaration as to the religious character of 
      certain places of worship and bar of jurisdiction of courts,
etc.—
<section><number>1</number> It is hereby 
      declared that the religious character of a place of worship existing on 
      the 15th day of August, 1947 shall continue to be the same as it existed 
      on that day.
 </section><section><number>2</number> If, on the commencement of this Act, any 
      suit, appeal or other proceeding with respect to the conversion of the 
      religious character of any place of worship, existing on the 15th day of 
      August, 1947, is pending before any court, tribunal or other authority, 
      the same shall abate, and no suit, appeal or other proceeding with respect 
      to any such matter shall lie on or after such commencement in any court, 
      tribunal or other authority:
 Provided that if any suit, appeal or other 
      proceeding, instituted or filed on the ground that conversion has taken 
      place in the religious character of any such place after the 15th day of 
      August, 1947, is pending on the commencement of this Act, such suit, 
      appeal or other proceeding shall not so abate and every such suit, appeal 
      or other proceeding shall be disposed of in accordance with the provisions 
      of sub-section (1).
 </section><section><number>3</number> Nothing contained in sub-section (1) and 
      sub-section (2) shall apply to,—
 <subsection><number>a</number> any place of worship 
      referred to in the said sub-sections which is an ancient and historical 
      monument or an archaeological site or remains covered by the Ancient 
      Monuments and Archaeological Sites and Remains Act, 1958 (24 of 1958) or 
      any other law for the time being in force;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> any suit, appeal or 
      other proceeding, with respect to any matter referred to in sub-section 
      (2), finally decided, settled or disposed of by a court, tribunal or other 
      authority before the commencement of this Act;
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number> any dispute with 
      respect to any such matter settled by the parties amongst themselves 
      before such commencement;
 </subsection><subsection><number>d</number> any conversion of any 
      such place effected before such commencement by acquiescence;
 </subsection><subsection><number>e</number> any conversion of any 
      such place effected before such commencement which is not liable to be 
      challenged in any court, tribunal or other authority being barred by 
      limitation under any law for the time being in force.
  


  </subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>5</number> Act not to apply to Ram Janma Bhumi-Babri 
      Masjid.—Nothing contained in 
      this Act shall apply to the place or place of worship commonly known as 
      Ram Janma Bhumi-Babri Masjid situated in Ayodhya in the State of Uttar 
      Pradesh and to any suit, appeal or other proceeding relating to the said 
      place or place of worship.
  


  </article> 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>6</number>
Punishment for contravention of section 3.—
<section><number>1</number>
Whoever contravenes the provisions of section 3 shall be punishable with
imprisonment for a term which may extend to three years and shall also be liable
to fine.
 </section><section><number>2</number>
Whoever attempts to commit any offence punishable under sub-section (1) or to
cause such offence to be committed and in such attempt does any act towards the
commission of the offence shall be punishable with the punishment provided for
the offence.
 </section><section><number>3</number>
Whoever abets, or is a party to a criminal conspiracy to commit, an offence
punishable under sub-section (1) shall, whether such offence be or be not
committed in consequence of such abetment or in pursuance of such criminal
conspiracy, and notwithstanding anything contained in section 116 of the Indian
Penal Code, be punishable with the punishment provided for the offence.

  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>7</number> Act to override other 
      enactments.—The provisions of 
      this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything inconsistent therewith 
      contained in any other law for the time being in force or any instrument 
      having effect by virtue of any law other than this Act.
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
  
 <article><number>8</number> Amendment of Act 43 of 1951.—In section 8 of the Representation of the 
      People Act, 1951, in sub-section 
<section><number>1</number>,—
 <subsection><number>a</number> in clause (i), the word 
      “or” shall be inserted at the end;
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number> after clause (i), as so 
      amended, the following clause shall be inserted, namely:—
 “(j) section 6 (offence of conversion of a 
      place of worship) of the Places of Worship (Special Provisions) Act, 
      1991,”
  </subsection></section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>