<act><tid>618694</tid>
<title>THE HIMACHAL PRADESH LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY (CONSTITUTION  
  AND PROCEEDINGS) VALIDATION ACT, <year>1958</year></title>

ACT NO. 56 OF <year>1958</year>
[ 30th December, <year>1958</year>.]

An Act to validate the constitution and proceedings of the Legislative 
Assembly of the New State of Himachal Pradesh formed under the 
Himachal Pradesh and Bilaspur (New State) Act, <year>1954</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Ninth Year of the Republic of 
India as follows:--





<article><tid>1234811</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Himachal Pradesh 
Legislative Assembly (Constitution and Proceedings) Validation Act, 
<year>1958</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1505451</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," new Legislative Assembly" means the 
body of persons deemed under clause (a) of section 3 to have been the 
duly constituted Legislative Assembly of the New State of Himachal 
Pradesh.


</article>



<article><tid>1833446</tid>
<number> 3</number> Validation of the constitution and proceedings of the 
Legislative Assembly of the new State of Himachal Pradesh. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any law or in any judgment, 
decree or order of any court,--
<section><tid>1070707</tid>
<number>a</number>the body of persons summoned to meet from time to time 
as the Himachal Pradesh Legislative Assembly (Himachal  
  Pradesh Vidhan Sabha) during the period commencing on 
the 1st day of July, <year>1954</year>, and ending with the 31st day 
of October, <year>1956</year>, by the Lieutenant- Governor of 
Himachal Pradesh in the exercise or purported exercise 
of the powers conferred on him by section 9 of the 
Government of Part C States Act, <year>1951</year> (49 of <year>1951</year>), 
shall be deemed for all purposes to have been the duly 
constituted Legislative Assembly of the new State of 
Himachal Pradesh formed under section 3 of the Himachal 
Pradesh and Bilaspur (New State) Act, <year>1954</year> (32 of  
  <year>1954</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>766535</tid>
<number>b</number>the persons who sat or voted or otherwise took part in 
the proceedings of the new Legislative Assembly shall 
be deemed to have been entitled so to do as members;

</section>

<section><tid>1696801</tid>
<number>c</number>the persons who functioned as the Speaker and the Deputy 
Speaker of the new Legislative Assembly shall be

<pagefootnote><pagenum>516</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

deemed to have been duly chosen as the Speaker and the 
Deputy Speaker respectively;

and accordingly--


<subsection><tid>354207</tid>
<number>i</number>any Bill passed by the new Legislative Assembly (whether  
the Bill was introduced in the new Legislative Assembly 
or was introduced in the Legislative Assembly of 
Himachal Pradesh functioning immediately before the 1st 
  day of July, <year>1954</year>) and assented to by the President 
shall be deemed to have been validly enacted and to 
have the force of law;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>613598</tid>
<number>ii</number>any grant made, resolution passed or adopted, 
proceeding taken or any other thing done by or before 
the new Legislative Assembly shall be deemed to have 
been made, passed, adopted, taken or done in accordance 
with law.



</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>26334</tid>
<number>4</number>Court not to question validity of proceedings of new 
Legislative Assembly on the ground of defect in constitution, etc. No 
court shall question any Act passed, or any grant, resolution, 
proceeding or thing made, passed, adopted, taken or done, by or before 
the new Legislative Assembly merely on the ground that the new 
Legislative Assembly had not been duly constituted or on the ground 
that a person who was not entitled so to do presided over, sat or 
voted or otherwise took part in the proceedings of the new Legislative 
Assembly.


</article>



<article><tid>1317994</tid>
<number>5</number>[ Repeal.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1960</year> (58 of  
  <year>1960</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I.


</article>



 </act>