<act><title>


    The Wakf Act, 1995</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title, extent and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    This Act may be called the Wakf Act, 1995.  
    
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> It extends to the whole of India except 
    the State of Jammu and Kashmir.  
    
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> It shall come into force in a State 
    on such date1 as 
    the Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    appoint; and different dates may be appointed for different areas within a 
    State and for different provisions of this Act, and any reference in any 
    provision to the commencement of this Act, shall, in relation to any State 
    or area therein be construed as reference to the commencement of that 
    provision in such State or area.
 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Application of the Act.—Save as 
    otherwise expressly provided under this Act, this Act shall apply to all 
    wakfs whether created before or after the commencement of this Act:  
     
 
Provided that nothing in this Act shall apply 
    to Durgah Khawaja Saheb, Ajmer to which the Durgah Khawaja Saheb Act, 1955 
    (36 of 1955), applies.  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Definitions.—In this Act, unless the 
    context otherwise requires,—  
     
 <section>
<number>a</number>   
    “beneficiary” means a person or object for whose benefit a wakf is created 
    and includes religious, pious and charitable objects and any other objects 
    of public utility sanctioned by the Muslim law; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    “benefit” does not include any benefit which a mutawalli is entitled to 
    claim solely by reason of his being such mutawalli; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   “Board” 
    means a Board of Wakf established under sub-section (1), or as the case may 
    be, under sub-section (2) of section 13 and shall include a common Wakf 
    Board established under section 106; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   “Chief 
    Executive Officer” means the Chief Executive Officer appointed under 
    sub-section (1) of section 23; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   
    “Council” means the Central Wakf Council established under section 9; 

 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   
    “Executive Officer” means the Executive Officer appointed by the Board under 
    sub-section (1) of section 38; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>g</number>   “list of 
    wakfs” means the list of wakfs published under sub-section (2) of section 5;
      
 </section><section>
<number>h</number>   “member” 
    means a member of the Board and includes the Chairperson; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>i</number>   
    “mutawalli” means any person appointed, either verbally or under any deed or 
    instrument by which a wakf has been created, or by a competent authority, to 
    be the mutawalli of a wakf and includes any person who is a mutawalli of a 
    wakf by virtue of any custom or who is a naib-mutawalli, khadim, mujawar, 
    sajjadanashin, amin or other person appointed by a mutawalli to perform the 
    duties of a mutawalli and save as otherwise provided in this Act, any 
    person, committee or corporation for the time being managing or 
    administering any wakf or wakf property: 
 
 
Provided that 
    no member of a committee or corporation shall be deemed to be a mutawalli 
    unless such member is an office bearer of such committee or corporation;
      
 </section><section>
<number>j</number>   “net 
    annual income”, in relation to a wakf, means net annual income determined in 
    accordance with the provisions of the Explanations to sub-section (1) 
    of section 72; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>k</number>   “person 
    interested in a wakf” means any person who is entitled to receive any 
    pecuniary or other benefits from the wakf and includes—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   any 
    person who has a right to worship or to perform any religious rite in a 
    mosque, idgah, imambara, dargah, khangah, maqbara, graveyard or any other 
    religious institution connected with the wakf or to participate in any 
    religious or charitable institution under the wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the 
    wakif and any descendant of the wakif and the mutawalli; 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>l</number>   
    “prescribed”, except in Chapter III, means prescribed by rules made by the 
    State Government; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>m</number>   
    “regulations” means the regulations made by the Board under this Act; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>n</number>   “Shia 
    wakf” means a wakf governed by Shia law; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>o</number>   “Sunni 
    wakf” means a wakf governed by Sunni law; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>p</number>   “Survey 
    Commissioner” means the Survey Commissioner of Wakf appointed under 
    sub-section (1) of section 4 and includes any Additional or Assistant Survey 
    Commissioners of Wakfs under sub-section (2) of section 4; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>q</number>   
    “Tribunal”, in relation to any area, means the Tribunal constituted under 
    sub-section (1) of section 83, having jurisdiction in relation to that area;
      
 </section><section>
<number>r</number>   “wakf” 
    means the permanent dedication by a person professing Islam, of any movable 
    or immovable property for any purpose recognised by the Muslim law as pious, 
    religious or charitable and includes—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   a wakf by user but such wakf shall not 
    cease to be a wakf by reason only of the user having ceased irrespective of 
    the period of such cesser;  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   “grants”, including mashrut-ul-khidmat 
    for any purpose recognised by the Muslim law as pious, religious or 
    charitable; and  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   a wakf-alal-aulad to the extent to 
    which the property is dedicated for any purpose recognised by Muslim law as 
    pious, religious or charitable,  
     
 
and “wakif” 
    means any person making such dedication; 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>s</number>   “wakf” 
    deed” means any deed or instrument by which a wakf has been created and 
    includes any valid subsequent deed or instrument by which any of the terms 
    of the original dedication have been varied; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>t</number>   “Wakf 
    Fund” means a wakf fund formed under sub-section (1) ofsection 77. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Preliminary survey of wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, appoint for 
    the State a Survey Commissioner of Wakfs and as many Additional or Assistant 
    Survey Commissioners of Wakfs as may be necessary for the purpose of making 
    a survey of wakfs existing in the State at the date of the commencement of 
    this Act.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All Additional and Assistant Survey 
    Commissioners of Wakfs shall perform their functions under this Act under 
    the general supervision and control of the Survey Commissioner of Wakfs.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Survey Commissioner shall, after 
    making such inquiry as he may consider necessary, submit his report, in 
    respect of wakfs existing at the date of the commencement of this Act in the 
    State or any part thereof, to the State Government containing the following 
    particulars, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the 
    number of wakfs in the State showing the Shia wakfs and Sunni wakfs 
    separately; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
    nature and objects of each wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the 
    gross income of the property comprised in each wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the 
    amount of land revenue, cesses, rates and taxes payable in respect of each 
    wakf;   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the 
    expenses incurred in the realisation of the income and the pay or other 
    remuneration of the mutawalli of each wakf; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   such 
    other particulars relating to each wakf as may be prescribed. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The Survey Commissioner shall, while 
    making any inquiry, have the same powers as are vested in a civil court 
    under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), in respect of the 
    following matters, namely:—  
     
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    summoning and examining any witness; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    requiring the discovery and production of any document; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    requisitioning any public record from any court or office; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   issuing 
    commissions for the examination of any witness or accounts; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   making 
    any local inspection or local investigation; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   such 
    other matters as may be prescribed. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> If, during any such inquiry, any dispute 
    arises as to whether a particular wakf is a Shia wakf or Sunni wakf and 
    there are clear indications in the deed of wakf as to its nature, the 
    dispute shall be decided on the basis of such deed.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The State Government may, by notification 
    in the Official Gazette, direct the Survey Commissioner to make a second or 
    subsequent survey of wakf properties in the State and the provisions of 
    sub-sections (2), (3), (4) and (5) shall apply to such survey as they apply 
    to a survey directed under sub-section (1):  
     
 
Provided that no such second or subsequent 
    survey shall be made until the expiry of a period of twenty years from the 
    date on which the report in relation to the immediately previous survey was 
    submitted under sub-section (3).  
     
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Publication of list of wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> On 
    receipt of a report under sub-section (3) of section 4, the State Government 
    shall forward a copy of the same to the Board. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board shall examine the report 
    forwarded to it under sub-section (1) and publish in the Official Gazette a 
    list of Sunni wakfs or Shia wakfs in the State, whether in existence at the 
    commencement of this Act or coming into existence thereafter, to which the 
    report relates, and containing such other particulars as may be prescribed.  
     
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Disputes regarding wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> If any 
    question arises whether a particular property specified as wakf property in 
    the list of wakfs is wakf property or not or whether a wakf specified in 
    such list is a Shia wakf or Sunni wakf, the Board or the mutawalli of the 
    wakf or any person interested therein may institute a suit in a Tribunal for 
    the decision of the question and the decision of the Tribunal in respect of 
    such matter shall be final:  
     
 
Provided that no such suit shall be 
    entertained by the Tribunal after the expiry of one year from the date of 
    the publication of the list of wakfs.  
     
 
Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
    section and section 7, the expression “any person interested therein”, 
    shall, in relation to any property specified as wakf property in the list of 
    wakfs published after the commencement of this Act, shall include also every 
    person who, though not interested in the wakf concerned, is interested in 
    such property and to whom a reasonable opportunity had been afforded to 
    represent his case by notice served on him in that behalf during the course 
    of the relevant inquiry under section 4.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub-section (1), no proceeding under this Act in respect of any wakf shall 
    be stayed by reason only of the pendency of any such suit or of any appeal 
    or other proceeding arising out of such suit.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Survey Commissioner shall not be made 
    a party to any suit under sub-section (1) and no suit, prosecution or other 
    legal proceeding shall lie against him in respect of anything which is in 
    good faith done or intended to be done in pursuance of this Act or any rules 
    made thereunder.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The list of wakfs shall, unless it is 
    modified in pursuance of a decision or the Tribunal under sub-section (1), 
    be final and conclusive.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On and from the commencement of this Act 
    in a State, no suit or other legal proceeding shall be instituted or 
    commenced in a court in that State in relation to any question referred to 
    in sub-section (1).  
     
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Power of Tribunal to determine disputes 
    regarding wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> If, after the commencement of this Act, any 
    question arises, whether a particular property specified as wakf property in 
    a list of wakfs is wakf property or not, or whether a wakf specified in such 
    list is a Shia wakf or a Sunni wakf, the Board or the mutawalli of the wakf, 
    or any person interested therein, may apply to the Tribunal having 
    jurisdiction in relation to such property, for the decision of the question 
    and the decision of the Tribunal thereon shall be final:  
     
 
Provided that—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the 
    case of the list of wakfs relating to any part of the State and published 
    after the commencement of this Act no such application shall be entertained 
    after the expiry of one year from the date of publication of the list of 
    wakfs; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   in the 
    case of the list of wakfs relating to any part of the State and published at 
    any time within a period of one year immediately preceding the commencement 
    of this Act, such an application may be entertained by Tribunal within the 
    period of one year from such commencement: 
 
 
Provided further that where any such question 
    has been heard and finally decided by a civil court in a suit instituted 
    before such commencement, the Tribunal shall not re-open such question.  
     
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Except where the Tribunal has no 
    jurisdiction by reason of the provisions of sub-section (5), no proceeding 
    under this section in respect of any wakf shall be stayed by any court, 
    tribunal or other authority by reason only of the pendency of any suit, 
    application or appeal or other proceeding arising out of any such suit, 
    application, appeal or other proceeding.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Executive Officer shall not be 
    made a party to any application under sub-section (1).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The list of wakfs and where any such list 
    is modified in pursuance of a decision of the Tribunal under sub-section 
    (1), the list as so modified, shall be final.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Tribunal shall not have jurisdiction 
    to determine any matter which is the subject-matter of any suit or 
    proceeding instituted or commenced in a civil court under sub-section (1) of 
    section 6, before the commencement of this Act or which is the 
    subject-matter of any appeal from the decree passed before such commencement 
    in any such suit or proceeding or of any application for revision or review 
    arising out of such suit, proceeding or appeal, as the case may be.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Recovery of costs of survey.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    total cost of making a survey including the cost of publication of the list 
    or lists of wakfs under this Chapter shall be borne by all the mutawalli of 
    the wakfs the net annual income whereof exceeds five hundred rupees, in 
    proportion to the net annual income accruing in the State to such wakfs, 
    such proportion being assessed by the Survey Commissioner.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    deed or instrument by which the wakf was created, any mutawalli may pay from 
    the income of the wakf any sum due from him under sub-section (1).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any sum due from a mutawalli under 
    sub-section (1) may, on a certificate issued by the State Government, be 
    recovered from the property comprised in the wakf in the same manner as an 
    arrear of land revenue.  
     
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Establishment and constitution of 
    Central Wakf Council.—
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of advising it, on matters 
    concerning the working of Boards and the due administration of wakfs, the 
    Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a 
    Council to be called the Central Wakf Council.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Council shall consist of,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the 
    Union Minister in charge of wakfs—ex officio Chairperson; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
    following members to be appointed by the Central Government from amongst 
    Muslims, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   three persons to represent Muslim 
    organisations having all India character and national importance; 

 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   four persons of national eminence of 
    whom two shall be from amongst persons having administrative and financial 
    expertise;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   three Members of Parliament of whom 
    two shall be from the House of the People and one from the Council of 
    States;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   Chairpersons of three Boards by 
    rotation;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>v</number>   two persons who have been Judges of the 
    Supreme Court or a High Court;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vi</number>   one advocate of national eminence;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>vii</number>   one person to represent the mutawallis 
    of the wakf having a gross annual income of rupees five lakhs and above;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>viii</number>   there persons who are eminent 
    scholars in Muslim Law.  
     
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The term of office of, the procedure to be 
    followed in the discharge of their functions by, and the manner of filling 
    casual vacancies among, members of the Council shall be such as may be 
    prescribed by rules made by the Central Government.  
     
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Finance of Council.—
<section><number>1</number> Every Board 
    shall pay from its Wakf Fund annually to the Council such contribution as is 
    equivalent to one per cent. of the aggregate of the net annual income of the 
    wakfs in respect of which contribution is payable under sub-section (1) of 
    section 72:   
 
Provided that where the Board, in the case of 
    any particular wakf has remitted under sub-section (2) of section 72 the 
    whole of the contribution payable to it under sub-section (1) of that 
    section, then for calculating the contribution payable to the Council under 
    this section the net annual income of the wakf in respect of which such 
    remission has been granted shall not be taken into account.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All monies received by the Council under 
    sub-section (1) and all other monies received by it as donations, 
    benefactions and grants shall form a fund to be called the Central Wakf 
    Fund.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to any rules that may be made by 
    the Central Government in this behalf, the Central Wakf Fund shall be under 
    the control of the Council and may be applied for such purposes as the 
    Council may deem fit.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Accounts and audit.—
<section><number>1</number> The Council 
    shall cause to be maintained such books of account and other books in 
    relation to its accounts in such form and in such manner as may be 
    prescribed by rules made by the Central Government.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The accounts of the Council shall be 
    audited and examined annually by such auditor as may be appointed by the 
    Central Government.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The costs of the audit shall be paid from 
    the Central Wakf Fund.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Power of Central Government to make 
    rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, make rules to carry out the purposes of this Chapter.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to 
    the generality of the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any 
    of the following matters, namely:—  
     
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the term 
    of office of, the procedure to be followed in the discharge of their 
    functions by, and the manner of filling casual vacancies among, the members 
    of the Council; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   control 
    over and application of the Central Wakf Fund; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the form 
    and manner in which accounts of the Council may be maintained. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Every rule made by the Central Government 
    under this Chapter shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before 
    each House of Parliament, while it is in session for a total period of 
    thirty days, which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following, the session or the successive sessions aforesaid, both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Incorporation.—
<section><number>1</number> With effect from 
    such date as the State Government may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, appoint in this behalf, there shall be established a Board of Wakfs 
    under such name as may be specified in the notification.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub-section (1), if the Shia wakfs in any State constitute in number more 
    than fifteen per cent. of all the wakfs in the State or if the income of the 
    properties of the Shia wakfs in the State constitutes more than fifteen per 
    cent. of the total income of properties of all the wakfs in the State, the 
    State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, establish a 
    Board of Wakfs each for Sunni wakfs and for Shia wakfs under such names as 
    may be specified in the notification.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board shall be a body corporate having 
    perpetual succession and a common seal with power to acquire and hold 
    property and to transfer any such property subject to such conditions and 
    restrictions as may be prescribed and shall by the said name sue and be 
    sued.   
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Composition of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board 
    for a State and the Union territory of Delhi* shall consist of—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a 
    Chairperson; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   one and 
    not more than two members, as the State Government may think fit, to be 
    elected from each of the electoral colleges consisting of—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   Muslim Members of Parliament from the 
    State or, as the case may be, the Union territory of Delhi*,  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   Muslim Members of the State 
    Legislature,   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   Muslim Members of the Bar Council of 
    the State, and  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iv</number>   mutawallis of the wakfs having an 
    annual income of rupees one lakh and above;  
     
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   one and 
    not more than two members to be nominated by the State Government 
    representing eminent Muslim organisations; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   one and 
    not more than two members to be nominated by the State Government, each from 
    recognised scholars in Islamic Theology; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   an 
    officer of the State Government not below the rank of Deputy Secretary.
      
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Election of the members specified in 
    clause (b) of sub-section (1) shall be held in accordance with the system of 
    proportional representation by means of a single transferable vote, in such 
    manner as may be prescribed:  
     
 
Provided that where the number of Muslim 
    Members of Parliament, the State Legislature or the State Bar Council, as 
    the case may be, is only one, such Muslim Member shall be declared to have 
    been elected on the Board:  
     
 
Provided further that where there are no 
    Muslim Members in any or the categories mentioned in sub-clauses (i) to 
    (iii) of clause (b) of sub-section (1), the ex-Muslim Members of Parliament, 
    the State Legislature or ex-member of the State Bar Council, as the case may 
    be, shall constitute the electoral college.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this 
    section, where the State Government is satisfied, for reasons to be recorded 
    in writing, that it is not reasonably practicable to constitute an electoral 
    college for any of the categories mentioned in sub-clauses (i) to (iii) of 
    clause (b) of sub-section (1), the State Government may nominate such 
    persons as the members of the Board as it deems fit.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The number of elected members of the Board 
    shall at, all times, be more than the nominated members of the Board except 
    as provided under sub-section (3).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where there are Shia wakfs but no separate 
    Shia Wakfs Board exists, at least one of the members from the categories 
    listed in sub-section (1), shall be a Shia Muslim.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In determining the number of Shia members 
    or Sunni members of the Board, the State Government shall have regard to the 
    number and value of Shia wakfs and Sunni wakfs to be administered by the 
    Board and appointment of the members shall be made, so far as may be, in 
    accordance with such determination.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In the case of the Union territory other 
    than Delhi, the Board shall consist of not less than three and not more than 
    five members to be appointed by the Central Government from amongst the 
    categories of persons specified in sub-section (1):  
     
 
Provided that there shall be one mutawalli as 
    the member of the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> Whenever the Board is constituted or 
    re-constituted, the members of the Board present at a meeting convened for 
    the purpose shall elect one from amongst themselves as the Chairperson of 
    the Board.   
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> The members of the Board shall be 
    appointed by the State Government by notification in the Official Gazette.
    
 
 
 
 




 



</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Term of office.—The members of the 
    Board shall hold office for a term of five years.  
     
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Disqualification for being appointed, 
    or for continuing as, a member of the Board.—A person shall be 
    disqualified for being appointed, or for continuing as, a member of the 
    Board if—   
 <section>
<number>a</number>   he is 
    not a Muslim and is less than twenty-one years of age; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   he is 
    found to be a person of unsound mind; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   he is an 
    undischarged insolvent; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   he has 
    been convicted of an offence involving moral turpitude and such conviction 
    has not been reversed or he has not been granted full pardon in respect of 
    such offence;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   he has 
    been on a previous occasion—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   removed from his office as a member or 
    as a mutawalli, or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   removed by an order of a competent 
    court or tribunal from any position of trust either for mismanagement or for 
    corruption.  
  



 



</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Meetings of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Board shall meet for the transaction of business at such time and places as 
    may be provided by regulations.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairperson, or in his absence, any 
    member chosen by the members from amongst themselves shall preside at a 
    meeting of the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to the provisions of this Act, all 
    questions which come before any meeting of the Board shall be decided by a 
    majority of votes of the members present, and in the case of equality of 
    votes, the Chairperson or, in his absence any other person presiding shall 
    have a second or casting vote.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Committees of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Board may, whenever it considers necessary, establish either generally or 
    for a particular purpose or for any specified area or areas committees for 
    the supervision of wakfs.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The constitution, functions and duties and 
    the term of office of such committees shall be determined from time to time 
    by the Board:  
 
Provided that it shall not be necessary for 
    the members of such committees to be members of the Board.  
</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Resignation of Chairperson and members.—The 
    Chairperson or any other member may resign his office by writing under his 
    hand addressed to the State Government:  
 
Provided that the Chairperson or the member 
    shall continue in office until the appointment of his successor is notified 
    in the Official Gazette.  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Removal of Chairperson and member.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, remove 
    the Chairperson of the Board or any member thereof if he—  
     
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   is or 
    becomes subject to any disqualifications specified in section 16; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   refuses 
    to act or is incapable of acting or acts in a manner which the State 
    Government, after hearing any explanation that he may offer, considers to be 
    prejudicial to the interests of the wakfs; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   fails in 
    the opinion of the Board, to attend three consecutive meetings of the Board, 
    without sufficient excuse. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Chairperson of the Board is 
    removed under sub-section (1), he shall also cease to be a member of the 
    Board.  

 
  


</section></article> 

  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Filling of a vacancy.—When the seat 
    of a member becomes vacant by his removal, resignation, death or otherwise, 
    a new member shall be appointed in his place and such member shall hold 
    office so long as the member whose place he fills would have been entitled 
    to hold office, if such vacancy had not occurred.  
</article> 

  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Vacancies, etc., not to invalidate 
    proceedings of the Board.—No act or proceeding of the Board shall be 
    invalid by reason only of the existence of any vacancy amongst its members 
    or any defect in the constitution thereof.  
</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Appointment of Chief Executive Officer 
    and his term of office and other conditions of service.—
<section><number>1</number> There shall 
    be a Chief Executive Officer of the Board who shall be a Muslim and shall be 
    appointed by the State Government, in consultation with the Board, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The term of office and other conditions of 
    service of the Chief Executive Officer shall be such as may be prescribed.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Executive Officer shall be ex 
    officio Secretary of the Board and shall be under the administrative 
    control of the Board.  
     
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Officers and other employees of the 
    Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board shall have the assistance of such number of 
    officers and other employees as may be necessary for the efficient 
    performance of its functions under this Act, details thereof shall be 
    determined by the Board in consultation with the State Government.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The appointment of officers and other 
    employees, their term of office and conditions of service shall be such as 
    may be provided by regulations.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Duties and powers of Chief Executive 
    Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of this Act and of the rules made 
    thereunder and the directions of the Board, functions of the Chief Executive 
    Officer shall include—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    investigating the nature and extent of wakfs and wakf properties and calling 
    whenever necessary, an inventory of wakf properties and calling, from time 
    to time, for accounts, returns and information from mutawallis; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    inspecting or causing inspection of wakf properties and account, records, 
    deeds or documents relating thereto; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   doing 
    generally of such acts as may be necessary for the control, maintenance and 
    superintendence of wakfs. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In exercising the powers of giving 
    directions under sub-section (1) in respect of any wakf, the Board shall act 
    in conformity with the directions by the wakf in the deed of the wakf, the 
    purpose of wakf and such usage and customs of the wakf as are sanctioned by 
    the school of Muslim law to which the wakf belongs.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Save as otherwise expressly provided in 
    this Act, the Chief Executive Officer shall exercise such powers and perform 
    such duties as may be assigned to him or delegated to him under this Act.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Powers of Chief Executive Officer in 
    respect of orders or resolutions of Board.—Where the Chief Executive 
    Officer considers that an order or resolution passed by the Board—  
     
 <section>
<number>a</number>   has not 
    been passed in accordance with the law; or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   is in 
    excess of or is an abuse of the powers conferred on the Board by or under 
    this Act or by any other law; or 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   if 
    implemented, is likely to— 
 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   cause financial loss to the Board or to 
    the concerned wakf or to the wakfs generally; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   lead to a riot or breach of peace; or  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   cause danger to human life, health or 
    safety; or   
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>d</number>   is not 
    beneficial to the Board or to any wakf or to wakfs generally, 
 
 
he may, before implementing such order or 
    resolution place the matter before the Board for its reconsideration and, if 
    such order or resolution is not confirmed by a majority of vote of the 
    members present and voting after such reconsideration, refer the matter to 
    the State Government along with his objections to the order or resolution, 
    and the decision of the State Government thereon shall be final.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Delegation of powers by the Board.—The 
    Board may, by a general or special order in writing, delegate to the 
    Chairperson, any other member, the secretary or any other officer or servant 
    of the Board or any area committee, subject to such conditions and 
    limitations as may be specified in the said order, such of its powers and 
    duties under this Act, as it may deem necessary.
  
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Chief Executive Officer to exercise 
    powers through Collectors, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the provisions of this 
    Act and of the rules made thereunder, the Chief Executive Officer may 
    exercise all or any of the powers conferred on him by or under this Act with 
    the previous approval of the Board through the Commissioner of the division 
    or the Collector of the district in which the concerned wakf property is 
    situated or through any other Gazetted Officer whom he may appoint for such 
    purpose and may, from time to time, delegate any of his powers to any such 
    Commissioner of the division or Collector or any other Gazetted Officer and 
    may, at any time, revoke the delegations so made by him.
 

 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any delegation of powers is made by 
    the Chief Executive Officer under sub-section (1), the person to whom such 
    delegation is made may exercise those powers in the same manner and to the 
    same extent as if they have been conferred on him directly by this Act and 
    not by way of delegation.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>29</number> Powers of Chief Executive Officer to 
    inspect records, registers, etc.— The Chief Executive Officer or 
    any officer of the Board duly authorised by him in this behalf shall, 
    subject to such conditions and restrictions as may be prescribed and subject 
    to the payment of such fees as may be leviable under any law for the time 
    being in force, be entitled at all reasonable time to inspect, in any public 
    office, any records, registers or other documents relating to a wakf or 
    movable or immovable properties which are wakf properties or are claimed to 
    be wakf properties.  
     

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Inspection of records.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Board may allow inspection of its proceedings or other records in its 
    custody and issue copies of the same on payment of such fees and subject to 
    such conditions as may be prescribed.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All copies issued under this section shall 
    be certified by the Chief Executive Officer of the Board in the manner 
    provided in section 76 of the Indian Evidence Act, 1872 (1 of 1872).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The powers conferred on the Chief 
    Executive Officer by sub-section (2) may be exercised by such other officer 
    or officers of the Board as may either generally or specially be authorised 
    in this behalf by the Board.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
(43 of 1995) 
 
[22nd November, 1995]
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Prevention of disqualification for 
    membership of Parliament.—It is hereby declared that the offices of the 
    Chairperson or members of a Board shall not be disqualified and shall be 
    deemed never to have been disqualified for being chosen as, or for being, a 
    Member of Parliament.  
     

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Powers and functions of the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to any rules that may be made under this Act, the general 
    superintendence of all wakfs in a State shall vest in the Board established 
    or the State; and it shall be the duty of the Board so to exercise its 
    powers under this Act as to ensure that the wakfs under its superintendence 
    are properly maintained, controlled and administered and the income thereof 
    is duly applied to the objects and for the purposes for which such wakfs 
    were created or intended:  
 
Provided that in exercising its powers under 
    this Act in respect of any wakf, the Board shall act in conformity with the 
    directions of the wakif, the purposes of the wakf and any usage or custom of 
    the wakf sanctioned by the school of Muslim law to which the wakf belongs.  
     
 
Explanation.—For the removal of doubts, 
    it is hereby declared that in this sub-section, “wakf” includes a wakf in 
    relation to which any scheme has been made by any court of law, whether 
    before or after the commencement of this Act.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Without prejudice to the generality of the 
    foregoing power, the functions of the Board shall be—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   to 
    maintain a record containing information relating to the origin, income, 
    object and beneficiaries of every wakf; 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   to 
    ensure that the income and other property of wakfs are applied to the 
    objects and for the purposes for which such wakfs were intended or created;
      
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   to give 
    directions for the administration of wakfs; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   to 
    settle schemes of management for a wakf:  
 
       
    Provided that no such settlement shall be made without giving the parties 
    affected an opportunity of being heard; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   to 
    direct—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   the utilisation of the surplus income of 
    a wakf consistent with the objects of a wakf;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   in what manner the income of a wakf, 
    the objects of which are not evident from any written instrument, shall be 
    utilized;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>iii</number>   in any case where any object of wakf 
    has ceased to exist or has become incapable of achievement, that so much of 
    the income of the wakf as was previously applied to that object shall be 
    applied to any other object, which shall be similar, or nearly similar or to 
    the original object or for the benefit of the poor or for the purpose of 
    promotion of knowledge and learning in the Muslim community:  
 
Provided that 
    no direction shall be given under this clause without giving the parties 
    affected an opportunity of being heard. 
 
 

    Explanation—For the purposes of 
    this clause, the powers of the Board shall be exercised—  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   in the case of a Sunni wakf, by the 
    Sunni members of the Board only; and  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   in the case of a Shia wakf, by the Shia 
    members of the Board only: 
 
Provided that 
    where having regard to the number of the Sunni or Shia members in the Board 
    and other circumstances, it appears to the Board that the power should not 
    be exercised by such members only, it may co-opt such other Muslims being 
    Sunnis or Shias, as the case may be, as it thinks fit, to be temporary 
    members of the Board for exercising its powers under this clause; 
 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   to 
    scrutinise and approve the budgets submitted by mutawallis and to arrange 
    for the auditing of account of wakfs; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   to 
    appoint and remove mutawallis in accordance with the provisions of this Act;
      
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   to take 
    measures for the recovery of lost properties of any wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   to 
    institute and defend suits and proceedings relating to wakfs; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   to 
    sanction any transfer of immovable property of a wakf by way of sale, gift, 
    mortgage, exchange or lease, in accordance with the provisions of this Act:  
 
     Provided 
    that no such sanction shall be given unless at least two thirds of the 
    members of the Board vote in favour of such transaction; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   to 
    administer the Wakf Fund; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   to call 
    for such returns, statistics, accounts and other information from the 
    mutawallis with respect to the wakf property as the Board may, from time to 
    time, require; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>m</number>   to 
    inspect, or cause inspection of, wakf properties, accounts, records or deeds 
    and documents relating thereto; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>n</number>   to 
    investigate and determine the nature and extent of wakf and wakf property, 
    and to cause, whenever necessary, a survey of such wakf property; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>o</number>   
    generally do all such acts as may be necessary for the control, maintenance 
    and administration of wakfs. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Board has settled any scheme of 
    management under clause (d) or given any direction under clause (e) of 
    sub-section (2), any person interested in the wakf or affected by such 
    settlement or direction may institute a suit in a Tribunal for setting aside 
    such settlement or directions and the decision of the Tribunal thereon shall 
    be final.   
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the Board is satisfied that any wakf 
    land, which is a wakf property, offers a feasible potential for development 
    as a shopping centre, market, housing flats and the like, it may serve upon 
    the mutawalli of the concerned wakf a notice requiring him within such time, 
    but not less than sixty days, as may be specified in the notice, to convey 
    its decision whether he is willing to execute the development works 
    specified in the notice.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On consideration of the reply, if any, 
    received to the notice issued under sub-section (4), the Board, if it is 
    satisfied that the mutawalli is not willing or is not capable of executing 
    the works required to be executed in terms of the notice, it may, with the 
    prior approval of the Government, take over the property, clear it of any 
    building or structure thereon, which, in the opinion of the Board is 
    necessary for execution of the works and execute such works from wakf funds 
    or from the finances which may be raised on the security of the properties 
    of the wakf concerned, and control and manage the properties till such time 
    as all expenses incurred by the Board under this section, together with 
    interest thereon, the expenditure on maintenance of such works and other 
    legitimate changes incurred on the property are recovered from the income 
    derived from the property:  
 
Provided that the Board shall compensate 
    annually the mutawalli of the concerned wakf to the extent of the average 
    annual net income derived from the property during the three years 
    immediately preceding the taking over of the property by the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> After all the expenses as enumerated in 
    sub-section (5) have been recouped from the income of the developed 
    properties, the developed properties shall be handed over to mutawalli of 
    the concerned wakf.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>33</number> Powers of inspection by Chief Executive 
    Officer or persons authorised by him.—
<section><number>1</number> With a view to examining 
    whether, by reason of any failure or negligence on the part of a mutawalli 
    in the performance of his executive or administrative duties, any loss or 
    damage has been caused to any wakf or wakf property, the Chief Executive 
    Officer with the prior approval of the Board, either himself or any other 
    person authorised by him in writing in this behalf, may inspect all movable 
    and immovable properties, which are wakf properties, and all records, 
    correspondences, plans, accounts and other documents relating thereto.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever any such inspection as referred 
    to in sub-section (1) is made, the concerned mutawalli and all officers and 
    other employees working under him and every person connected with the 
    administration of the wakf shall extend to the person making such 
    inspection, all such assistance and facilities as may be necessary and 
    reasonably required by him to carry out such inspection, and shall also 
    produce for inspection any movable property or documents relating to the 
    wakf as may be called for by the person making the inspection and furnish to 
    him such information relating to the wakf as may be required by him.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where, after any such inspection, it 
    appears that the concerned mutawalli or any officer or other employee who is 
    or was working under him had misappropriated, misapplied or fraudulently 
    retained, any money or other wakf property, or had incurred irregular, 
    unauthorised or improper expenditure from the funds of the wakf, the Chief 
    Executive Officer may, after giving the mutawalli or the person concerned a 
    reasonable opportunity of showing cause why an order for the recovery of the 
    amount or property, should not be passed against him and after considering 
    such explanation, if any, as such person may furnish, determine the amount 
    or the property, which has been misappropriated, misapplied or fraudulently 
    retained, or the amount of the irregular, unauthorised or improper 
    expenditure incurred by such person, and make an order directing such person 
    to make payment of the amount so determined and to restore the said property 
    to the wakf, within such time as may be specified in the order.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A mutawalli or other person aggrieved by 
    such order may, within thirty days of the receipt by him of the order, 
    appeal to the Tribunal:  
 
Provided that no such appeal shall be 
    entertained by the Tribunal unless the appellant first deposits with the 
    Chief Executive Officer the amount which has been determined under 
    sub-section (3) as being payable by the appellant and the Tribunal shall 
    have no power to make any order staying pending the disposal of the appeal, 
    the operation of the order made by the Chief Executive Officer under 
    sub-section (3).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Tribunal may, after taking such 
    evidence as it may think fit, confirm, reverse or modify the order made by 
    the Chief Executive Officer under sub-section (3) or may remit, either in 
    whole or in part, the amount specified in such order and may make such 
    orders as to costs as it may think appropriate in the circumstances of the 
    case.   
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The order made by the Tribunal under 
    sub-section (5) shall be final.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>34</number> Recovery of the amount determined under 
    section 33.—Where any mutawalli or other person who has been ordered, 
    whether under sub-section (3) or sub-section (5) of section 33, to make any payment or to restore the possession 
    of any property, omits or fails to make such payment or restoration within 
    the time specified in such order, the Chief Executive Officer, with the 
    prior approval of the Board shall, take such steps as he may think fit for 
    the recovery of possession of the property aforesaid and shall also send a 
    certificate to the Collector of the district in which the property of such 
    mutawalli or other person in situate, stating therein the amount that has 
    been determined by him or by the Tribunal, as the case may be, under section 
    33, as being payable by such mutawalli or other person, and, thereupon, the 
    Collector shall recover the amount specified in such certificate as if it 
    were an arrear of land revenue and on the recovery of such amount, pay the 
    same to the Chief Executive Officer, who shall, on receipt thereof, credit 
    the amount to the funds of the concerned wakf. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>35</number> Conditional attachment by Tribunal.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where the Chief Executive Officer is satisfied that the mutawalli or any 
    other person who has been ordered under sub-section (3) or sub-section (5) 
    of section 33 to make any payment, with intent to defeat or delay the 
    execution of the said order,—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   is about 
    to dispose of the whole or any part of his property; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   is about 
    to remove the whole or any part of his property from the jurisdiction of the 
    Chief Executive Officer, 
 
 
he may, with the prior approval of the Board, 
    apply to the Tribunal for the conditional attachment of the said property or 
    such part thereof, as he may think necessary. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chief Executive Officer shall, unless 
    the Tribunal otherwise directs, specify in the application the property 
    required to be attached and the estimated value thereof.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Tribunal may direct the mutawalli or 
    the person concerned, as the case may be, within a time to be fixed by it, 
    either to furnish security, in such sum as may be specified in the order, to 
    produce and place at the disposal of the Tribunal when required, the said 
    property or the value of the same or such portion thereof as may be 
    sufficient to satisfy the amount specified in the certificate referred to in 
    section 34, or to appear and show cause why he should not furnish such 
    security.   
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Tribunal may also in the order direct 
    the conditional attachment of the whole or any portion of the property so 
    specified.   
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every attachment made under this section 
    shall be made in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), as if it were an order for attachment made 
    under the provision of the said Code.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>36</number> Registration.—
<section><number>1</number> Every wakf, 
    whether created before or after the commencement of this Act, shall be 
    registered at the office of the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Application for registration shall be made 
    by the mutawalli:  
     
 
Provided that such applications may be made by 
    the wakf or his descendants or a beneficiary of the wakf or any Muslim 
    belonging to the sect to which the wakf belongs.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An application for registration shall be 
    made in such form and manner and at such place as the Board may by 
    regulation provide and shall contain following particulars:—  
     
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a 
    description of the wakf properties sufficient for the identification 
    thereof; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
    gross annual income from such properties; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the 
    amount of land revenue, cesses, rates and taxes annually payable in respect 
    of the wakf properties; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   an 
    estimate of the expenses annually incurred in the realisation of the income 
    of the wakf properties; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the 
    amount set apart under the wakf for— 
 
 <subsubsection>


    <number>i</number>   the salary of the mutawalli and allowances to the individuals; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>


    <number>ii</number>   purely religious purposes; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>


    <number>iii</number>   charitable purposes; and 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>


    <number>iv</number>   any other purposes; 
 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   any 
    other particulars provided by the Board by regulations. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Every such application shall be 
    accompanied by a copy of the wakf deed or if no such deed has been executed 
    or a copy thereof cannot be obtained, shall contain full particulars, as far 
    as they are known to the applicant, of the origin, nature and objects of the 
    wakf.   
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every application made under sub-section 
    (2) shall be signed and verified by the applicant in the manner provided in 
    the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) for the signing and 
    verification of pleadings.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Board may require the applicant to 
    supply any further particulars or information that it may consider 
    necessary.   
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> On receipt of an application for 
    registration, the Board may, before the registration of the wakf make such 
    inquiries as it thinks fit in respect of the genuineness and validity of the 
    application and correctness of any particulars therein and when the 
    application is made by any person other than the person administering the 
    wakf property, the Board shall, before registering the wakf, give notice of 
    the application to the person administering the wakf property and shall hear 
    him if he desires to be heard.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> In the case of wakfs created before the 
    commencement of this Act, every application for registration shall be made, 
    within three months from such commencement and in the case of wakfs created 
    after such commencement, within three months from the date of the creation 
    of the wakf:   
 
Provided that where there is no
    board at the time of creation 
    of a wakf, such application will be made within three months from the date 
    of establishment of the Board.  
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>37</number> Register of wakfs.—The Board shall 
    maintain a register of wakfs which shall contain in respect of each wakf 
    copies of the wakf deeds, when available and the following particulars, 
    namely:—   
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the 
    class of the wakf; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   the name 
    of the mutawalli; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the rule 
    of succession to the office of mutawalli under the wakf deed or by custom or 
    by usage; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   
    particulars of all wakf properties and all title deeds and documents 
    relating thereto; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   
    particulars of the scheme of administration and the scheme of expenditure at 
    the time of registration; 
 
 </section><section>
<number>f</number>   such 
    other particulars as may be provided by regulations.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>38</number> Powers of Board to appoint Executive 
    Officer.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, the Board 
    may, if it is of the opinion that it is necessary so to do in the interests 
    of the wakf, appoint on whole-time or part-time basis or in an honorary 
    capacity, subject to such conditions as may be provided by regulations, an 
    Executive Officer with such supporting staff as it considers necessary for 
    any wakf having a gross annual income of not less than five lakhs rupees:  
 
Provided that the person chosen for 
    appointment should be a person professing Islam.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every Executive Officer appointed under 
    sub-section (1) shall exercise such powers and discharge such duties as 
    pertain only to the administration of the property of the wakf for which he 
    has been appointed and shall exercise those powers and discharge those 
    duties under the direction, control and supervision of the Board:  
 
Provided that the Executive Officer who is 
    appointed for a wakf having a gross annual income of not less than five lakh 
    rupees shall ensure that the budget of the wakf is submitted, the accounts 
    of the wakf are regularly maintained, and the yearly statement of accounts 
    are submitted within such time as the Board may specify.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> While exercising his powers and 
    discharging his functions under sub-section (2), the Executive Officer shall 
    not interfere with any religious duties or any usage or custom of the wakf 
    sanctioned by the Muslim law.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The salaries and allowances of the 
    Executive Officer and his staff shall be fixed by the Board and in fixing 
    the quantum of such salary the Board shall have due regard to the income of 
    the wakf, the extent and nature of the duties of the Executive Officer and 
    shall also ensure that the amounts of such salaries and allowances are not 
    disproportionate to the income of the wakf and do not operate as an 
    unnecessary financial burden on it.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The salaries and allowances of the 
    Executive Officer and his staff shall be paid by the Board from the Wakf 
    Fund and, if the wakf generates any additional income as a result of 
    appointment of the Executive Officer, the Board may claim reimbursement of 
    amounts spent on the salaries and allowances from the fund of the wakf 
    concerned.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The Board may, for sufficient reasons, and 
    after giving to the Executive Officer or a member of his staff, a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard, suspend, remove or dismiss the Executive Officer 
    or a member of his staff from his post.  
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any Executive Officer or a member of his 
    staff who is aggrieved by any order of removal or dismissal made under 
    sub-section (6) may, within thirty days from the date of communication of 
    the order, prefer an appeal against the order to the Tribunal and the 
    Tribunal may, after considering such representation as the Board may make in 
    the matter, and after giving a reasonable opportunity to the Executive 
    Officer or a member of his staff of being heard, confirm, modify or reverse 
    the order.   

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>39</number> Powers of Board in relation to wakfs 
    which have ceased to exist.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board shall, if it is satisfied that 
    the objects or any part thereof, of a wakf have ceased to exist, whether 
    such cesser took place before or after the commencement of this Act, cause 
    an inquiry to be held by the Chief Executive Officer, in the prescribed 
    manner, to ascertain the properties and funds pertaining to such wakf.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On the receipt of the report of inquiry of 
    the Chief Executive Officer, the Board shall pass an order—  
     
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    specifying the property and funds of such wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    directing that any property or funds pertaining to such wakf which have been 
    recovered shall be applied or utilised for the renovation of any wakf 
    property and where there is no need for making any such renovation or where 
    utilisation of the funds for such renovation is not possible, be 
    appropriated, to any of the purposes specific in sub-clause (iii) ofclause 
    (e) of sub-section (2) of section 32. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board may, if it has reason to believe 
    that any building or other place which was being used for religious purpose 
    or instruction or for charity has, whether before or after the commencement 
    of this Act, ceased to be used for that purpose, make an application to the 
    Tribunal for an order directing the recovery of possession of such building 
    or other place.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Tribunal may, if it is satisfied, 
    after making such inquiry as it may think fit, that such building or other 
    place—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   is wakf property; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   has not been acquired under any law for the time being 
    in force relating to acquisition of land or is not under any process of 
    acquisition under any such law, or has not vested in the State Government 
    under any law for the time being in force relating to land reforms; and  
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   is not in the occupation of any person who has been authorised by or under any law for the time being in force to occupy such 
    building or other place, make an order—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   directing the 
    recovery of such building or place from any person who may be in 
    unauthorised possession thereof, and  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   directing that 
    such property, building or place be used for religious purpose or 
    instruction as before, or if such use is not possible, be utilised for any 
    purpose specified in sub-clause (iii) of clause (e) of sub-section (2) of 
    section 32.   

 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>40</number> Decision if a property is wakf 
    property.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board may itself collect information regarding any 
    property which it has reason to believe to be wakf property and if any 
    question arises whether a particular property is wakf property or not or 
    whether a wakf is a Sunni wakf or a Shia wakf it may, after making such 
    inquiry as it may deem fit, decide the question.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The decision of the Board on a question 
    under sub-section (1) shall, unless revoked or modified by the Tribunal, be 
    final.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the Board has any reason to believe 
    that any property of any trust or society registered in pursuance of the 
    Indian Trusts Act, 1882 (2 of 1882) or under the Societies Registration Act, 
    1860 (21 of 1860) or under any other Act, is wakf property, the Board may 
    notwithstanding anything contained in such Act, hold an inquiry in regard to 
    such property and if after such inquiry the Board is satisfied that such 
    property is wakf property, call upon the trust or society, as the case may 
    be, either to register such property under this Act as wakf property or show 
    cause why such property should not be so registered:  
     
 
Provided that in all such cases, notice of the 
    action proposed to be taken under this sub-section shall be given to the 
    authority by whom the trust or society had been registered.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Board shall, after duly considering 
    such cause as may be shown in pursuance of notice issued under sub-section 
    (3), pass such orders as it may think fit and the order so made by the 
    Board, shall be final, unless it is revoked or modified by a Tribunal.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>41</number> Power to cause registration of wakf and 
    to amend register.—The Board may direct a mutawalli to apply for the 
    registration of a wakf, or to supply any information regarding a wakf or may 
    itself cause the wakf to be registered or may at any time amend the register 
    of wakfs.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>42</number> Change in the management of wakfs to be 
    notified.—
<section><number>1</number> In the case of any change in the management of a 
    registered wakf due to the death or retirement or removal of the mutawalli, 
    the incoming mutawalli shall forthwith, and any other person may notify the 
    change to the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In the case of any other change in any of 
    the particulars mentioned in section 36, the mutawalli shall, within three 
    months from the occurrence of the change, notify such change to the Board.  
     
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>43</number> Wakfs registered before the 
    commencement of this Act deemed to be registered.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Chapter, where any wakf has been registered 
    before the commencement of this Act, under any law for the time being in 
    force, it shall not be necessary to register the wakf under the provisions 
    of this Act and any such registration made before such commencement shall be 
    deemed to be a registration made under this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>44</number> Budget.—
<section><number>1</number> Every mutawalli of a 
    wakf shall, in every year prepare, in such form and at such time as may be 
    prescribed, a budget in respect of the financial year next ensuing showing 
    the estimated receipts and expenditure during that financial year.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such budget shall be submitted by 
    the mutawalli at least ninety days before the beginning of the financial 
    year to the Board and shall make adequate provision for the following:—  
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   for carrying out the objects of the wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   for the maintenance and preservation of the wakf 
    property; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   for the discharge of all liabilities and subsisting commitments 
    binding on the wakf under this Act or any other law for the time being in 
    force.   
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board may give such directions for 
    making alterations, omissions or additions in the budget as it may deem fit, 
    consistent with the objects of the wakf and the provisions of this Act.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If in the course of the financial year the 
    mutawalli finds it necessary to modify the provisions made in the budget in 
    regard to the receipt or to the distribution of the amounts to be expended 
    under the different heads, he may submit to the Board a supplementary or a 
    revised budget and the provisions of sub-section (3) shall, as far as may 
    be, apply to such supplementary or revised budget.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>45</number> Preparation of budget of wakfs under 
    direct management of the board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Chief Executive Officer shall prepare, in such form and at such time as 
    may be prescribed, a budget in respect of the financial year next ensuing 
    showing the estimated receipts and expenditure for each of the wakfs under 
    the direct management of the Board, showing therein the estimated receipts 
    and expenditure and submit it to the Board for its approval.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> While submitting the budget under 
    sub-section (1), the Chief Executive Officer shall also prepare statement 
    giving details of the increase, if any, in the income of each wakf under the 
    direct management of the Board and the steps which have been taken for its 
    better management and the results accruing therefrom during the year.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Chief Executive Officer shall keep 
    regular accounts and be responsible for the proper management of every wakf 
    under the direct management of the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every budget submitted by the Chief 
    Executive Officer under sub-section (1) shall comply with the requirements 
    of section 46 and, for this purpose, references therein to the mutawalli of 
    the wakf shall be construed as references to the Chief Executive Officer.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The audit of accounts of every wakf under 
    the direct management of the Board shall be undertaken by the State Examiner 
    of Local Funds or any other officer appointed by the State Government for 
    this purpose, irrespective of the income of the wakf.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The provisions of sub-sections (2) and (3) 
    of section 47 and the provisions of sections 48 and 49 shall, in so far as 
    they are not inconsistent with the provisions of this section, apply to the 
    audit of accounts referred to in this section.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where any wakf is under the direct 
    management of the Board, such administrative charges as may be specified by 
    the Chief Executive Officer shall be payable by the wakf to the Board:  
     
 
Provided that the Chief Executive Officer 
    shall not collect more than ten per cent. of the gross annual income of the 
    wakf under the direct management of the Board as administrative charges.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>46</number> Submission of accounts of wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Every mutawalli shall keep regular accounts.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Before the 1st day of May next, following 
    the date on which the application referred to in section 36 has been made 
    and thereafter before the 1st day of May in every year, every mutawalli of a 
    wakf shall prepare and furnish to the Board a full and true statement of 
    accounts, in such form and containing such particulars as may be provided by 
    regulations by the Board, of all moneys received or expended by the 
    mutawalli on behalf of the wakf during the period of twelve months ending on 
    the 31st day of March, or, as the case may be, during that portion of the 
    said period during which the provisions of this Act, have been applicable to 
    the wakf:   
 
Provided that the date on which the annual 
    accounts are to be closed may be varied at the discretion of the Board.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>47</number> Audit of accounts of wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    accounts of wakfs submitted to the Board under section 46 shall be audited 
    and examined in the following manner, namely:—  
     
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   in the case of a wakf having no income or a net annual 
    income not exceeding ten thousand rupees, the submission of a statement of 
    accounts shall be a sufficient compliance with the provisions of section 46 
    and the accounts of two per cent. of such wakfs shall be audited annually by 
    an auditor appointed by the Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   the accounts of the wakf having net annual income 
    exceeding ten thousand rupees shall be audited annually, or at such other 
    intervals as may be prescribed, by an auditor appointed by the Board from 
    out of the panel of auditors prepared by the State Government and while 
    drawing up such panel of auditors, the State Government shall specify the 
    scale of remuneration of auditors; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   the State Government may, at any time cause the 
    account of any wakf audited by the State Examiner of Local Funds or by any 
    other officer designated for that purpose by that State Government; 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The auditor shall submit his report to the 
    Board and the report of the auditor shall among other things, specify all 
    cases of irregular, illegal or improper expenditure or of failure to recover 
    money or other property caused by neglect or misconduct and any other matter 
    which the auditor considers it necessary to report; and the report shall 
    also contain the name of any person who, in the opinion of the auditor, is 
    responsible for such expenditure or failure and the auditor shall in every 
    such case certify the amount of such expenditure or loss as due from such 
    person.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The cost of the audit of the accounts of a 
    wakf shall be met from the funds of that wakf:  
     
 
Provided that the remuneration of the auditors 
    appointed from out of the panel drawn by the State Government in relation to 
    wakfs having a net annual income of more than ten thousand rupees but less 
    than fifteen thousand rupees shall be paid in accordance with the scale of 
    remuneration specified by the State Government under clause (c) of 
    sub-section (1):  
 
Provided further that where the audit of the 
    accounts of any wakf is made by the State Examiner of Local Funds or any 
    other officer designated by the State Government in this behalf, the cost of 
    such audit shall not exceed one and a half per cent. of the net annual 
    income of such wakf and such costs shall be met from the funds of the wakfs 
    concerned.   

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>48</number> Board to pass orders on auditor’s 
    report.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board shall examine the auditor’s report, and may call 
    for the explanation of any person in regard to any matter mentioned therein, 
    and shall pass such orders as it thinks fit including orders for the 
    recovery of the amount certified by the auditor under sub-section (2) of 
    section 47.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The mutawalli or any other person 
    aggrieved by any order made by the Board may, within thirty days of the 
    receipt by him of the order, apply to the Tribunal to modify or set aside 
    the order and the Tribunal may, after taking such evidence as it may think 
    necessary, confirm or modify the order or remit the amount so certified, 
    either in whole or in part, and may also make such order as to costs as it 
    may think appropriate in the circumstances of the case.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No application made under sub-section (2) 
    shall be entertained by the Tribunal unless the amount certified by the 
    auditor under sub-section (2) of section 47 has first been deposited in the 
    Tribunal and the Tribunal shall not have any power to stay the operation of 
    the order made by the Board under sub-section (1).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The order made by the Tribunal under 
    sub-section (2) shall be final.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every amount for the recovery of which any 
    order has been made under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall, where 
    such amount remains unpaid, be recoverable in the manner specified in 
    section 34 or section 35 as if the said order were an order for the recovery 
    of any amount determined under sub-section (3) of section 35.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>48</number> Board to pass orders on auditor’s 
    report.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board shall examine the auditor’s report, and may call 
    for the explanation of any person in regard to any matter mentioned therein, 
    and shall pass such orders as it thinks fit including orders for the 
    recovery of the amount certified by the auditor under sub-section (2) of 
    section 47.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The mutawalli or any other person 
    aggrieved by any order made by the Board may, within thirty days of the 
    receipt by him of the order, apply to the Tribunal to modify or set aside 
    the order and the Tribunal may, after taking such evidence as it may think 
    necessary, confirm or modify the order or remit the amount so certified, 
    either in whole or in part, and may also make such order as to costs as it 
    may think appropriate in the circumstances of the case.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No application made under sub-section (2) 
    shall be entertained by the Tribunal unless the amount certified by the 
    auditor under sub-section (2) of section 47 has first been deposited in the 
    Tribunal and the Tribunal shall not have any power to stay the operation of 
    the order made by the Board under sub-section (1).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The order made by the Tribunal under 
    sub-section (2) shall be final.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every amount for the recovery of which any 
    order has been made under sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) shall, where 
    such amount remains unpaid, be recoverable in the manner specified in 
    section 34 or section 35 as if the said order were an order for the recovery 
    of any amount determined under sub-section (3) of section 35.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>49</number> Sums certified to be due recoverable as 
    arrears of land revenue.—
<section><number>1</number> Every sum certified to be due from any 
    person by an auditor in his report under section 47 unless such certificate 
    is modified or cancelled by an order of the Board or of the Tribunal made 
    under section 48, and every sum due on a modified certificate shall be paid 
    by such person within sixty days after the service of a demand for the same 
    issued by the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If such payment is not made in accordance 
    with the provisions of sub-section (1), the sum payable may, on a certificate issued by the Board after 
    giving the person concerned an opportunity of being heard, be recovered in 
    the same manner as an arrear of land revenue.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>50</number> Duties of mutawalli.—It shall be 
    the duty of every mutawalli—  
     
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   to carry out the directions of the Board in accordance 
    with the provisions of this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder;
      
 </section><section>

    <number>b</number>   to furnish such returns and supply such information or 
    particulars as may from time to time be required by the Board in accordance 
    with the provisions of this Act or of any rule or order made thereunder;
      
 </section><section>

    <number>c</number>   to allow inspection of wakf properties, accounts or 
    records or deeds and documents relating thereto; 
 
 </section><section>

    <number>d</number>   to discharge all public dues; and 
 
 </section><section>

    <number>e</number>   to do any other act which he is lawfully required to 
    do by or under this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>51</number> Alienation of wakf property without 
    sanction of Board to be void.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    the wakf deed, any gift, sale, exchange or mortgage of any immovable 
    property which is wakf property, shall be void unless such gift, sale, 
    exchange or mortgage is effected with the prior sanction of the Board:  
 
Provided that no mosque, dargah or khangah 
    shall be gifted, sold, exchanged or mortgaged except in accordance with any 
    law for the time being in force.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board may, after publishing in the 
    Official Gazette, the particulars relating to the transaction referred to in 
    sub-section (1) and inviting any objections and suggestions with respect 
    thereto and considering all objections and suggestions, if any, that may be 
    received by it from the concerned mutawalli or any other person interested 
    in the wakf, accord sanction to such transaction if it is of opinion that 
    such transaction is—  
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   necessary or beneficial to the wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   consistent with the objects of the wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the consideration thereof is reasonable and adequate:  
 
Provided that the sale of the property 
    sanctioned by the Board shall be effected by public auction and shall be 
    subject to confirmation by the Board within such time as may be prescribed:  
 
Provided further that the Tribunal may, on the 
    application of the aggrieved mutawalli or other person, for reasons to be 
    recorded by it in writing, permit such sale to be made otherwise than by 
    public auction, if it is of opinion that it is necessary so to do in the 
    interest of the wakf.  
     
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The utilisation or investment of the 
    amount realised by the sale or exchange mortgage of any property shall be 
    made by the mutawalli subject to the approval of the Board, and where any 
    amount has been raised by mortgage of any such property, the mutawalli or 
    other person shall make repayment of the mortgage-debt and obtain a 
    discharge of the mortgage-debt from the mortgage within such reasonable time 
    as the Board may specify.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every approval given by the Board under 
    sub-section (3) shall be communicated to the mutawalli and shall also be 
    published in the manner prescribed.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The mutawalli or any other person having 
    an interest in the wakf who is aggrieved by the decision given under 
    sub-section (3), may, within ninety days from the date of communication to 
    him of such decision or the publication of the decision, as the case may be, 
    prefer an appeal to the Tribunal against such decision, and, thereupon, the 
    Tribunal may, after giving the appellant and the Board, a reasonable 
    opportunity of being heard, confirm, modify or set aside such decision.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

 
(43 of 1995) 
 
[22nd November, 1995]
  
 <article>
<number>52</number> Recovery of wakf property transferred 
    in contravention of section 51.—
<section><number>1</number> If the Board is satisfied, after 
    making any inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed, that any immovable 
    property of a wakf entered as such in the register of wakf maintained under 
    section 36, has been transferred without the previous sanction of the Board 
    in contravention of the provisions of section 51, it may send a requisition 
    to the Collector within whose jurisdiction the property is situate to obtain 
    and deliver possession of the property to it.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of a requisition under 
    sub-section (1), the Collector shall pass an order directing the person in 
    possession of the property to deliver the property to the Board within a 
    period of thirty days from the date of the service of the order.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every order passed under sub-section (2) 
    shall be served—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   by giving or tendering the order, or by sending it by 
    post to the person for whom it is intended; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   if such person cannot be found, by affixing the order 
    on some conspicuous part of his last known place of abode or business, or by 
    giving or tendering the order to some adult male member or servant of his 
    family or by causing it to be affixed on some conspicuous part of the 
    property to which it relates:  
 
Provided that where the person on whom the 
    order is to be served is a minor, service upon his guardian or upon any 
    adult male member or servant of his family shall be deemed to be the service 
    upon the minor.  
     
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Any person aggrieved by the order of the 
    Collector under sub-section (2) may, within a period of thirty days from the 
    date of the service of the order, prefer an appeal to the Tribunal within 
    whose jurisdiction the property is situate and the decision of the Tribunal 
    on such appeal shall be final.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where an order passed under sub-section 
    (2) has not been complied with and the time for appealing against such order 
    has expired without an appeal having been preferred or the appeal, if any, 
    preferred within that time has been dismissed, the Collector shall obtain 
    possession of the property in respect of which the order has been made, 
    using such force, if any, as may be necessary for the purpose and deliver it 
    to the Board.   
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In exercising his functions under this 
    section the Collector shall be guided by such rules as may be provided by 
    regulations.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>53</number> Restriction on purchase of property on 
    behalf of wakf.—Notwithstanding anything contained in a wakf deed, no 
    immovable property shall be purchased for or on behalf of any wakf from the 
    funds of any wakf except with the prior sanction of the Board, and the Board 
    shall not accord such sanction unless it considers that the acquisition of 
    such property is necessary or beneficial to the wakf and that the price 
    proposed to be paid therefor is adequate and reasonable:  
 
Provided that before such sanction is 
    accorded, the particulars relating to the proposed transaction shall be 
    published in the Official Gazette inviting objections and suggestions with 
    respect thereto and, the Board shall, after considering the objections and 
    suggestions that may be received by it from mutawallis or other persons 
    interested in the wakf, make such orders as it may think fit.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>54</number> Removal of encroachment from wakf 
    property.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever the Chief Executive Officer considers whether on 
    receiving any complaint or on his own motion that there has been an 
    encroachment on any land, building, space or other property which is wakf 
    property and, which has been registered as such under this Act, he shall 
    cause to be served upon the encroacher a notice specifying the particulars 
    of the encroachment and calling upon him to show cause before a date to be 
    specified in such notice, as to why an order requiring him to remove the 
    encroachment before the date so specified should not be made and shall also 
    send a copy of such notice to the concerned mutawalli.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice referred to in sub-section (1) 
    shall be served in such manner as may be prescribed.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, after considering the objections, 
    received during the period specified in the notice, and after conducting an 
    inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed, the Chief Executive Officer is 
    satisfied that the property in question is wakf property and that there has 
    been an encroachment on any such wakf property, he may, by an order, require 
    the encroacher to remove such encroachment and deliver possession of the 
    land, building, space or other property encroached upon to the mutawalli of 
    the wakf.   
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Nothing contained in sub-section (3) shall 
    prevent any person aggrieved by the order made by the Chief Executive 
    Officer under that sub-section from instituting a suit in a Tribunal to 
    establish that he has right, title or interest in the land, building, space 
    or other property:  
 
Provided that no such suit shall be instituted 
    by a person who has been let into possession of the land, building, space or 
    other property as a lessee, licensee or mortgagee by the mutawalli of the 
    wakf or by any other person authorised by him in this behalf.  
     
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>55</number> Enforcement of orders made under 
    section 54.—Where the person, ordered under sub-section (3) of section 
    54 to remove any encroachment, omits or fails to remove such encroachment, 
    within the time specified in the order or, as the case may be, fails to 
    vacate the land, building, space or other property to which the order 
    relates, within the time aforesaid, the Chief Executive Officer may apply to 
    the Sub-divisional Magistrate within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
    the land, building, space or other property is situate for evicting the 
    encroacher, and, thereupon, such Magistrate shall make an order directing 
    the encroacher to remove the encroachment, or, as the case may be, vacate 
    the land, building, space or other property and to deliver possession 
    thereof to the concerned mutawalli and in default of compliance with the 
    order, remove the encroachment or, as the case may be, evict the encroacher 
    from the land, building, space or other property and may, for the purpose, 
    take such police assistance as may be necessary.  
     

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>56</number> Restriction on power to grant lease of 
    wakf property.—
<section><number>1</number> A lease or sub-lease for any period exceeding three 
    years of any immovable property which is wakf property shall, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in the deed or instrument of wakf or in 
    any other law for the time being in force, be void and of no effect.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A lease or sub-lease for a period 
    exceeding one year and not exceeding three years of any immovable property 
    which is wakf property shall, notwithstanding anything contained in the deed 
    or instrument of wakf or in any other law for the time being in force, be 
    void and of no effect unless it is made with the previous sanction of the 
    Board.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Board shall, in granting sanction for 
    lease or sub-lease or renewal thereof under this section review the terms 
    and conditions on which the lease or sub-lease is proposed to be granted or 
    renewed and make its approval subject to the revision of such terms and 
    conditions in such manner as it may direct.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>57</number> Mutawalli entitled to pay certain costs 
    from income of wakf property.—Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    wakf deed, every mutawalli may pay from the income of the wakf property any 
    expenses properly incurred by him for the purpose of enabling him to furnish 
    any particulars, documents or copies under section 36 or any accounts under 
    section 46 or any information or documents required by the Board or for the 
    purpose of enabling him to carry out the directions of the Board. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>58</number> Power of Board to pay dues in case of 
    default by mutawalli.—
<section><number>1</number> Where a mutawalli refuses to pay or fails to 
    pay any revenue, cess, rates or taxes due to the Government or any local 
    authority, the Board may discharge dues from the Wakf Fund and may recover 
    the amount so paid from the wakf property and may also recover damages not 
    exceeding twelve and a half per cent. of the amount so paid.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any sum of money due under sub-section (1) 
    may, on a certificate issued by the Board after giving the mutawalli 
    concerned an opportunity of being heard, be recovered in the same manner as 
    an arrear of land revenue.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>59</number> Creation of reserve fund.—For the 
    purpose of making provisions for the payment of rent and of revenue, cess, 
    rates and taxes due to the Government or any local authority, for the 
    discharge of the expenses of the repair of the wakf property and for the 
    preservation of the wakf property, the Board may direct the creation and 
    maintenance, in such manner as it may think fit, of a reserve fund from the 
    income of a wakf.
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>60</number> Extension of time.—The Board may, 
    if it is satisfied that it is necessary so to do, extend the time within 
    which any act is required to be done by the mutawalli under this Act.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>61</number> Penalties.—
<section><number>1</number> If a mutawalli fails 
    to—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   apply for the registration of a wakfs; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   furnish statements of particulars or accounts or 
    returns as required under this Act; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   supply information or particulars as required by the 
    Board;   
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>d</number>   allow inspection of wakf properties, accounts, records 
    or deeds and documents relating thereto; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>e</number>   deliver possession of any wakf property, if ordered 
    by the Board or Tribunal; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>f</number>   carry out the directions of the Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>g</number>   discharge any public dues; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>h</number>   do any other act which he is lawfully required to do 
    by or under this Act.  
 
he shall, unless he satisfies the court or the 
    Tribunal that there was reasonable cause for his failure, be punishable with 
    fine which may extend to eight thousand rupees. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub-section (1) if—  
     
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   a mutawalli omits or fails, with a view to concealing 
    the existence of a wakf, to apply for its registration under this Act,—
      
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   in the case of 
    a wakf created before the commencement of this Act, within the period 
    specified therefor in sub-section (8) of section 36;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   in the case of 
    any wakf created after such commencement, within three months from the date 
    of the creation of the wakf; or  
     
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   a mutawalli furnishes any statement, return or 
    information to the Board, which he knows or has reason to believe to be 
    false, misleading, untrue or incorrect in any material particular, 
 
 
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to six months and also with fine which may extend to 
    fifteen thousand rupees. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> No court shall take cognizance of an 
    offence punishable under this Act save upon complaint made by the Board or 
    an officer duly authorised by the Board in this behalf.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> No court inferior to that of a 
    Metropolitan Magistrate or a Judicial Magistrate of the first class shall 
    try any offence punishable under this Act.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    Code of Criminal Procedure, 1973 (2 of 1974), the fine imposed under 
    sub-section (1), when realised, shall be credited to the Wakf Fund.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> In every case where offender is convicted 
    after the commencement of this Act, of an offence punishable under 
    sub-section (1) and sentenced to a fine, the court shall also impose such 
    term of imprisonment in default of payment of fine as is authorised by law 
    for such default.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>62</number> Mutawalli not to spend any money 
    belonging to wakf for self-defence.—No mutawalli shall spend any money 
    out of the funds of the wakf, of which he is the mutawalli, for meeting any 
    costs, charges, or expenses which are or may be, incurred by him, in 
    relation to any suit, appeal or any other proceeding for, or incidental to, 
    his removal from office or for taking any disciplinary action against 
    himself.   
 




 



</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>63</number> Power to appoint mutawallis in certain 
    cases.—When there is a vacancy in the office of the mutawalli of a wakf 
    and there is no one to be appointed under the terms of the deed of the wakf, 
    or where the right of any person to act as mutawalli is disputed the Board 
    may appoint any person to act as mutawalli for such period and on such 
    conditions as it may think fit.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>64</number> Removal of mutawalli.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Notwithstanding anything contained in any other law or the deed of wakf, the 
    Board may remove a mutawalli from his office if such mutawalli—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   has been convicted more than once of an offence 
    punishable under section 61; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   has been convicted of any offence of criminal breach 
    of trust or any other offence involving moral turpitude, and such conviction 
    has not been reversed and he has not been granted full pardon with respect 
    to such offence; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   is of unsound mind or is suffering from other mental 
    or physical defect or infirmity which would render him unfit to perform the 
    functions and discharge the duties of a mutawalli; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>d</number>   is an undischarged insolvent; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>e</number>   is proved to be addicted to drinking liquor or other 
    spirituous preparations, or is addicted to the taking of any narcotic drugs; 
    or   
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>f</number>   is employed as a paid legal practitioner on behalf 
    of, or against, the wakf; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>g</number>   has failed, without reasonable excuse, to maintain 
    regular accounts for two consecutive years or has failed to submit, in two 
    consecutive years, the yearly statement of accounts, as required by 
    sub-section (2) of section 46; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>h</number>   is interested, directly or indirectly, in a subsisting 
    lease in respect of any wakf property, or in any contract made with, or any 
    work being done for, the wakf or is in arrears in respect of any sum due by 
    him to such wakf; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>i</number>   continuously neglects his duties or commits any 
    misfeasance, malfeasance, misapplication of funds or breach of trust in 
    relation to the wakf or in respect of any money or other wakf property; or
      
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>j</number>   wilfully and persistently disobeys the lawful orders 
    made by the Central Government, State Government, Board under any provision 
    of this Act or rule or order made thereunder; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>k</number>   misappropriates or fraudulently deals with the 
    property of the wakf. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The removal of a person from the office of 
    the mutawalli shall not affect his personal rights, if any, in respect of 
    the wakf property either as a beneficiary or in any other capacity or his 
    right, if any, as a sajjadanashin. 
 
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> No action shall be taken by the Board 
    under sub-section (1), unless it has held an inquiry into the matter in a 
    prescribed manner and the decision has been taken by a majority of not less 
    than two-thirds of the members of the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A mutawalli who is aggrieved by an order 
    passed under any of the clauses (c) to (i) of sub-section (1), may, within 
    one month from the date of the receipt by him of the order, appeal against 
    the order to the Tribunal and the decision of the Tribunal on such appeal 
    shall be final.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where any inquiry under sub-section (3) is 
    proposed, or commenced, against any mutawalli, the Board may, if it is of 
    opinion that it is necessary so to do in the interest of the wakf, by an 
    order suspend such mutawalli until the conclusion of the inquiry:  
 
Provided that no suspension for a period 
    exceeding ten days shall be made except after giving the mutawalli a 
    reasonable opportunity of being heard against the proposed action.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where any appeal is filed by the mutawalli 
    to the Tribunal under sub-section (4), the Board may make an application to the Tribunal for the 
    appointment of a receiver to manage the wakf pending the decision of the 
    appeal, and where such an application is made, the Tribunal shall, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 
    of 1908), appoint a suitable person as receiver to manage the wakf and 
    direct the receiver so appointed to ensure that the customary or religious 
    rights of the mutawalli and of the wakf are safeguarded. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Where a mutawalli has been removed from 
    his office under sub-section (1), the Board may, by order, direct the 
    mutawalli to deliver possession of the wakf property to the Board or any 
    officer duly authorised in this behalf or to any person or committee 
    appointed to act as the mutawalli of the wakf property.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> A mutawalli of a wakf removed from his 
    office under this section shall not be eligible for re-appointment as a 
    mutawalli of that wakf for a period of five years from the date of such 
    removal.   
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>65</number> Assumption of direct management of 
    certain wakfs by the Board.—
<section><number>1</number> Where no suitable person is available 
    for appointment as a mutawalli of a wakf, or where the Board is satisfied, 
    for reasons to be recorded by it in writing, that the filling up of the 
    vacancy in the office of a mutawalli is prejudicial to the interests of the 
    wakf, the Board may, by notification in the Official Gazette, assume direct 
    management of the wakf for such period or periods, not exceeding five years 
    in the aggregate, as may be specified in the notification.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The State Government, may, on its own 
    motion or on the application of any person interested in the wakf, call for 
    the records of any case for the purpose of satisfying itself as to the 
    correctness, legality or propriety of the notification issued by the Board 
    under sub-section (1) and pass such orders as it may think fit and the 
    orders so made by the State Government shall be final and shall be published 
    in the manner specified in sub-section (1).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> As soon as possible after the close of 
    every financial year, the Board shall send to the State Government a 
    detailed report in regard to every wakf under its direct management, giving 
    therein—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   the details of the income of the wakf for the year 
    immediately preceding the year under report; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   the steps taken to improve the management and income 
    of the wakf; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   the period during which the wakf has been under the 
    direct management of the Board and explaining the reasons as to why it has 
    not been possible to entrust the management of the wakf to the mutawalli or 
    any committee of management during the year; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>d</number>   such other matters as may be prescribed. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The State Government shall examine the 
    report submitted to it under sub-section (3), and after such examination 
    issue such directions or instructions to the Board as it may think fit and 
    the Board shall comply with such directions or instructions on receipt 
    thereof.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>66</number> Powers of appointment and removal of 
    mutawalli when to be exercised by the State Government.—Whenever a deed 
    of wakf or any decree or order of a court of any scheme of management of any 
    wakf provides that a court or any authority other than a Board may appoint 
    or remove a mutawalli or settle or modify such scheme of management or 
    otherwise exercise superintendence over the wakf, then notwithstanding 
    anything contained in such deed of wakf, decree, order or scheme, such 
    powers aforesaid shall be exercisable by the State Government:  
 
Provided that where a Board has been 
    established, the State Government shall consult the Board before exercising 
    such powers.   

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>67</number> Supervision and supersession of 
    committee of management.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever the supervision or management of a 
    wakf is vested in any committee appointed by the wakf, then, notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act, such committee shall continue to function 
    until it is superseded by the Board or until the expiry of its term as may 
    be specified by the wakf, whichever is earlier:  
 
Provided that such committee shall function 
    under the direction, control and supervision of the Board and abide by such 
    directions as the Board may issue from time to time:  
 
Provided further that if the Board is 
    satisfied that any scheme for the management of a wakf by a committee is 
    inconsistent with any provision of this Act or of any rule made thereunder 
    or with the directions of the wakf, it may, at any time, modify the scheme 
    in such manner as may be necessary to bring it in conformity with the 
    directions of the wakf or of the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
    thereunder.   
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in this 
    Act and in the deed of the wakf, the Board may, if it is satisfied, for 
    reasons to be recorded in writing, that a committee, referred to in 
    sub-section (1) is not functioning properly and satisfactorily, or that the 
    wakf is being mismanaged and that in the interest of its proper management, 
    it is necessary so to do, by an order, supersede such committee, and, on 
    such supersession, any direction of the wakf, in so far as it relates to the 
    constitution of the committee, shall cease to have any force:  
 
Provided that the Board shall, before making 
    any order superseding any committee, issue a notice setting forth therein 
    the reasons for the proposed action and calling upon the Committee to show 
    cause within such time, not being less than one month, as may be specified 
    in the notice, as to why such action shall not be taken.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every order made by the Board under 
    sub-section (2) shall be published in the prescribed manner and on such 
    publication shall be binding on the mutawalli and all persons having any 
    interest in the wakf.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any order made by the Board under 
    sub-section (2) shall be final:  
     
 
Provided that any person aggrieved by the 
    order made under sub-section (2) may, within sixty days from the date of the 
    order, appeal to the Tribunal:  
     
 
Provided further that the Tribunal shall have 
    no power to suspend the operation of the order made by the Board pending 
    such appeal.   
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Board shall, whenever it supersedes 
    any committee under sub-section (2), constitute a new committee of 
    management simultaneously with the order made by it under sub-section (2).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    foregoing sub-sections, the Board may, instead of superseding any committee 
    under sub-section (2), remove any member thereof if it is satisfied that 
    such member has abused his position as such member or had knowingly acted in 
    a manner prejudicial to the interests of the wakf, and every such order for 
    the removal of any member shall be served upon him by registered post:  
 
Provided that no order for the removal of the 
    member shall be made unless he has been given a reasonable opportunity of 
    showing cause against the proposed action:  
     
 
Provided further that any member aggrieved by 
    any order for his removal from the membership of the committee may, within a 
    period of thirty days from the date of service of the order on him, prefer 
    an appeal against such order to the Tribunal and the Tribunal may, after 
    giving a reasonable opportunity to the appellant and the Board of being 
    heard, confirm, modify or reverse the order made by the Board and the order 
    made by the Tribunal in such appeal shall be final.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>68</number> Duty of mutawalli or committee to 
    deliver possession of records, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> Where any mutawalli or committee 
    of management has been removed by the Board in accordance with the 
    provisions of this Act, or of any scheme made by the Board, the mutawalli or 
    the committee so removed from the office (hereinafter in this section 
    referred to as the removed mutawalli or committee) shall hand over charge 
    and deliver possession of the records, accounts and all properties of the 
    wakf (including cash) to the successor mutawalli or the successor committee, 
    within one month from the date specified in the order.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any removed mutawalli or committee 
    fails to deliver charge or deliver possession of the records, accounts and 
    properties (including cash) to the successor mutawalli or committee within 
    the time specified in sub-section (1), or prevents or obstructs such 
    mutawalli or committee, from obtaining possession thereof after the expiry 
    of the period aforesaid, the successor mutawalli or any member of the 
    successor committee may make an application, accompanied by a certified copy 
    of the order appointing such successor mutawalli or committee, to any 
    Magistrate of the first class within the local limits of whose jurisdiction 
    any part of the wakf property is situated and, thereupon, such Magistrate 
    may, after giving notice to the removed mutawalli or members of the removed 
    committee, make an order directing the delivery of charge and possession of 
    such records, accounts and properties (including cash) of the wakf to the 
    successor mutawalli or the committee, as the case may be, within such time 
    as may be specified in the order.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the removed mutawalli or any member 
    of the removed committee, omits or fails to deliver charge and possession of 
    the records, accounts and properties (including cash) within the time 
    specified by the Magistrate under sub-section (2), the removed mutawalli or 
    every member of the removed committee, as the case may be, shall be 
    punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or 
    with fine which may extend to eight thousand rupees, or with both.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Whenever any removed mutawalli or any 
    member of the removed committee omits or fails to comply with the orders 
    made by the Magistrate under sub-section (2), the Magistrate may authorise 
    the successor mutawalli or committee to take charge and possession of such 
    records, accounts, properties (including cash) and may authorise such person 
    to take such police assistance as may be necessary for the purpose.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> No order of appointment of the successor 
    mutawalli or committee, shall be called in question in the proceedings 
    before the Magistrate under this section.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Nothing contained in this section shall 
    bar the institution of any suit in a competent civil court by any person 
    aggrieved by any order made under this section, to establish that he has 
    right, title and interest in the properties specified in the order made by 
    the Magistrate under sub-section (2).  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>69</number> Power of Board to frame scheme for 
    administration of wakf.—
<section><number>1</number> Whenever the Board is satisfied, whether on 
    its own motion or on the application of not less than five persons 
    interested in any wakf, that it is necessary or desirable to frame a scheme 
    for the proper administration of the wakf, it may by an order frame such 
    scheme for the administration of the wakf, after consultation with the 
    mutawalli or the applicant in the prescribed manner.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A scheme framed under sub-section (1) may 
    provide for the removal of the mutawalli of the wakf holding office as such 
    immediately before the date on which the scheme comes into force:  
     
 
Provided that where any such scheme provides 
    for the removal of any hereditary mutawalli, the scheme shall also provide 
    for the appointment of the person next in hereditary succession of the 
    mutawalli so removed, as one of the members of the committee appointed for 
    the proper administration of the wakf.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every order made under sub-section (2) 
    shall be published in the prescribed manner, and, on such publication shall 
    be final and binding on the mutawalli and all persons interested in the 
    wakf:  
 
Provided that any person aggrieved by an order 
    made under this section may, within sixty days from the date of the order, 
    prefer an appeal to the Tribunal and after hearing such appeal, the Tribunal 
    may confirm, reverse or modify the order:  
 
Provided further that the Tribunal shall have 
    no power to stay the operation of the order made under this section.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Board may, at any time by an order, 
    whether made before or after the scheme has come into force, cancel or 
    modify the scheme.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Pending the framing of the scheme for the 
    proper administration of the wakf, the Board may appoint a suitable person 
    to perform all or any of the functions of the mutawalli thereof and to 
    exercise the powers, and perform the duties, of such mutawalli.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>70</number> Inquiry relating to administration of 
    wakf.—Any person interested in a wakf may make an application to the 
    Board supported by an affidavit to institute an inquiry relating to the 
    administration of the wakf and if the Board is satisfied that there are 
    reasonable grounds for believing that the affairs of the wakf are being 
    mismanaged, it shall take such action thereon as it thinks fit.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>71</number> Manner of holding inquiry.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Board may, either on an application received under section 73 or on its own 
    motion,— 
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   hold an inquiry in such manner as may be prescribed; 
    or 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   authorise any person in this behalf to hold an inquiry 
    into any matter relating to a wakf and take such action as it thinks fit.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purposes of an inquiry under this 
    section, the Board or any person authorised by it in this behalf, shall have 
    the same powers as are vested in a civil court under the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908) for enforcing the attendance of witnesses and 
    production of documents.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>72</number> Annual contribution payable to Board.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The mutawalli of every wakf, the net annual income of which is not less than 
    five thousand rupees, shall pay annually, out of the net annual income 
    derived by the wakf, such contributions, not exceeding seven per cent. of 
    such annual income, as may be prescribed, to the Board for the services 
    rendered by such Board to the wakf.  
     
 
Explanation I.—For the purposes of this 
    Act, “net annual income” shall mean the gross income of the wakf from all 
    sources, including nazars and offerings which do not amount to 
    contributions to the corpus of the wakfs, in a year after deducting 
    therefrom the following, namely:—  
     
 <subsection>

    <number>i</number>   the land revenue paid by it to the Government; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>ii</number>   the rates, cesses, taxes and licence fees, paid by it 
    to the Government or any local authority; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   expenditure incurred for all or any of the following purposes, 
    namely:— 
 
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   maintenance of, 
    or repairs to, irrigation works, which shall not include the capital cost of 
    irrigation;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   seeds or 
    seedlings;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number>   manure;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>d</number>   purchase and 
    maintenance of agricultural implements;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>e</number>   purchase and 
    maintenance of cattle for cultivation;  
     
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>f</number>   wages for ploughing, watering, sowing, transplanting, harvesting, threshing and other 
    agricultural operations;  
     
 

    Provided that the total deduction in respect of 
    an expenditure incurred under this clause shall not exceed ten per cent. of 
    the income derived from lands belonging to the wakf; 
 
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   expenditure on sundry repairs to rented buildings, not exceeding five 
    per cent. of the annual rent derived therefrom, or the actual expenditure, 
    whichever is less; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>v</number>   sale proceeds of immovable properties or rights 
    relating to, or arising out of immovable properties, if such proceeds are 
    re-invested to earn income for the wakf:
 
Provided that the following items of receipts 
    shall not be deemed to be income for the purposes of this section, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>

    <number>a</number>   advances and deposits recovered and loans taken or 
    recovered; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>b</number>   deposits made as security by employees, lessees or 
    contractors and other deposits, if any; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>c</number>   withdrawals from banks or of investments; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>d</number>   amounts recovered towards costs awarded by courts;
      
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>e</number>   sale proceeds of religious books and publications 
    where such sales are undertaken as an un-remunerative enterprise with a view 
    to propagating religion; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>f</number>   donations in cash or kind or offerings made by the 
    donors as contribution to the corpus of the wakf; 
 
 

    Provided that the interest on income, if any, 
    accruing from such donations or offerings shall be taken into account in 
    calculating the gross annual income; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>g</number>   voluntary contributions received in cash or kind for a 
    specific service to be performed by the wakf and expended on such service;
      
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>

    <number>h</number>   audit recoveries. 
 
 
Explanation II.—In determining, the net 
    annual income for the purposes of this section, only the net profit derived 
    by any wakf from its remunerative undertakings, if any, shall be taken as 
    income, and in respect of its non-remunerative undertakings, such as, 
    schools, colleges, hospitals, poor homes, orphanages or any other similar 
    institutions, the grants given by the Government or any local authority or 
    donations received from the public or fees collected from the pupils of 
    educational institutions shall not be taken as income.  
     
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board may in the case of any mosque or 
    orphanage or any particular wakf reduce or remit such contribution for such 
    time as it thinks fit.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The mutawalli of the wakf may realise the 
    contributions payable by him under sub-section (1) from the various persons 
    entitled to receive any pecuniary or other material benefit from the wakf, 
    but the sum realisable from any one of such persons shall not exceed such 
    amount as shall bear to the total contribution payable the same proportion, 
    as the value of the benefits receivable by such person bears to the entire 
    net annual income of the wakf:  
 
Provided that if there is any income of the 
    wakf available in excess of the amount payable as dues under this Act, other 
    than as the contribution under sub-section (1), and in excess of the amount 
    payable under the wakf deed, the contribution shall be paid out of such 
    income.   
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The contribution payable under sub-section 
    (1) in respect of a wakf shall, subject to the prior payment of any dues to 
    the Government or any local authority or of any other statutory first charge 
    on the wakf property or the income thereof, be a first charge on the income 
    of the wakf and shall be recoverable, on a certificate issued by the Board 
    after giving the mutawalli concerned an opportunity of being heard, as an 
    arrear of land revenue.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> If a mutawalli realises the income of the 
    wakf and refuses to pay or does not pay such contribution, he shall also be 
    personally liable for such contribution which may be realised from his 
    person or property in the manner aforesaid.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Where, after the commencement of this Act, 
    the mutawalli of a wakf fails to submit a return of the net annual income of 
    the wakf within the time specified therefor or submits a return which, in 
    the opinion of the Chief Executive Officer is incorrect or false in any 
    material particular, or which does not comply with the provisions of this 
    Act or any rule or order made thereunder, the Chief Executive Officer may 
    assess the net annual income of the wakf to the best of his judgment or 
    revise the net annual income as shown in the return submitted by the 
    mutawalli and the net annual income as so assessed or revised shall be 
    deemed to be the net annual income of the wakf for the purposes of this 
    section:   
 
Provided that no assessment of the net annual 
    income or revision of return submitted by mutawalli shall be made except 
    after giving a notice to the mutawalli calling upon him to show cause, 
    within the time specified in the notice, as to why such assessment or 
    revision of the return shall not be made and every such assessment or 
    revision shall be made after considering the reply if any, given by the 
    mutawalli.   
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Any mutawalli who is aggrieved by the 
    assessment or revision made by the Chief Executive Officer, under 
    sub-section (6) may prefer an appeal to the Board within thirty days from 
    the date of the receipt of the assessment or revision of return and the 
    Board may, after giving the appellant a reasonable opportunity of being 
    heard, confirm, reverse or modify the assessment or revision or the return 
    and the decision of the Board thereon shall be final.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> If, for any reason, the contribution or 
    any portion thereof leviable under this section has escaped assessment in 
    any year, whether before or after the commencement of this Act, the Chief 
    Executive Officer may, within five years from the last date of the year to 
    which such escaped assessment relates serve upon the mutawalli a notice 
    assessing him with the contribution or portion thereof which had escaped 
    assessment, and demanding payment thereof within thirty days from the date 
    of service of such notice, and the provisions of this Act and the rules made 
    thereunder, shall, as far as may be, apply as if the assessments were made 
    under this Act, in the first instance.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>73</number> Power of Chief Executive Officer to 
    direct banks or other person to make payments.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any other law for the time being in force, the Chief 
    Executive Officer, if he is satisfied that it is necessary and expedient so 
    to do, make an order directing any bank in which, or any person with whom 
    any money belonging to a wakf is deposited, to pay the contribution, 
    leviable under section 72, out of such money, as may be standing to the 
    credit of the wakf in such bank or may be deposited with such person, or out 
    of the moneys which may, from time to time, be received by bank or other 
    person for or on behalf of the wakf by way of deposit, and on receipt of 
    such orders, the bank or the other person, as the case may be, shall, when 
    no appeal has been preferred under sub-section (3), comply with such orders, 
    or where an appeal has been preferred under sub-section (3), shall comply 
    with the orders made by the Tribunal on such appeal.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every payment made by a bank or other 
    person in pursuance of any order made under sub-section (1), shall operate 
    as a full discharge of the liability of such bank or other person in 
    relation to the sum so paid.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any bank or other person who is ordered 
    under sub-section (1) to make any payment may, within thirty days from the 
    date of the order, prefer an appeal against such order to the Tribunal and 
    the decision of the Tribunal on such appeal shall be final.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every officer of the bank or other person 
    who fails, without any reasonable excuse, to comply with the order made 
    under sub-section (1) or, as the case may be, under sub-section (3), shall 
    be punishable with imprisonment for a term which may extend to six months or 
    with fine which may extend to eight thousand rupees, or with both.
 


 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>74</number> Deduction of contribution from 
    perpetual annuity payable to the wakf.—
<section><number>1</number> Every authority empowered to 
    disburse any perpetual annuity payable to a wakf under any law relating to 
    the abolition of zamindaries or jagirs, or laying down land ceilings, shall, 
    or receipt of a certificate from the Chief Executive Officer, specifying the 
    amount of contribution payable by the wakf under section 72 which remains 
    unpaid, deduct before making payment of the perpetual annuity to the wakf, 
    the amount specified in such certificate and remit the amount so deducted to 
    the Chief Executive Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every amount remitted under sub-section 
    (1) to the Chief Executive Officer shall be deemed to be a payment made by 
    the wakf and shall, to the extent of the amount so remitted, operate as a 
    full discharge of the liability of such authority with regard to the payment 
    of the perpetual annuity.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>75</number> Power of Board to borrow.—
<section><number>1</number> For 
    the purpose of giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the Board may, 
    with the previous sanction of the State Government, borrow such sum of money 
    and on such terms and conditions as the State Government may determine.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board shall repay the money borrowed, 
    together with any interest or costs due in respect thereof, according to the 
    terms and conditions of the loan. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>76</number> Mutawalli not to lend or borrow moneys 
    without sanction.—
<section><number>1</number> No mutawalli, Executive Officer or other person in 
    charge of the administration of a wakf shall lend any money belonging to the 
    wakf or any wakf property or borrow any money for the purposes of the wakf 
    except with the previous sanction of the Board:  
     
 
Provided that no such sanction is necessary if 
    there is an express provision in the deed of wakf for such borrowing or 
    lending, as the case may be.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Board may, while according sanction, 
    specify any terms and conditions subject to which the person referred to in 
    sub-section (1) is authorised by him to lend or borrow any money or lend any 
    other wakf property.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any money is lent or borrowed, or 
    other wakf property is lent in contravention of the provisions of this 
    section, it shall be lawful for the Chief Executive Officer,—  
     
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   to recover an amount equal to the amount which has 
    been so lent or borrowed, together with interest due thereon, from the 
    personal funds of the person by whom such amount was lent or borrowed;
      
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   to recover the possession of the wakf property lent in 
    contravention of the provisions of this Act, from the person to whom it was 
    lent, or from persons who claim title to such property through the person to 
    whom such property was lent.  

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>77</number> Wakf Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> All moneys received 
    or realised by the Board under this Act and all other moneys received as 
    donations, benefactions or grants by the Board shall form a fund to be 
    called the Wakf Fund.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All moneys received by the Board, as 
    donations, benefactions and grants shall be deposited and accounted for 
    under a separate sub-head.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Subject to any rules that may be made by 
    the State Government in this behalf, the Wakf Fund shall be under the 
    control of the Board, so, however, that the Wakf Fund under the control of 
    common Wakf Board shall be subject to rules, if any, made in this behalf by 
    the Central Government.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> The Wakf Fund shall be applied to—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   repayment of any loan incurred under section 75 and 
    payment of interest thereon; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   payment of the cost of audit of the Wakf Fund and the 
    accounts of wakfs; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   payment of the salary and allowances to the officers 
    and staff of the Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>d</number>   payment of travelling allowances to the Chairperson, 
    members, of the Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>e</number>   payment of all expenses incurred by the Board in the 
    performance of the duties imposed, and the exercise of the powers conferred, 
    by or under this Act; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>f</number>   payment of all expenses incurred by the Board for the 
    discharge of any obligation imposed on it by or under any law for the time 
    being in force. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>5</number> If any balance remains after meeting the 
    expenditure referred to in sub- 
    section (4), the Board may use any portion of such balance for the 
    preservation and protection of wakf properties or for such other purposes as 
    it may deem fit.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>78</number> Budget of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board 
    shall in every year prepare, in such form and at such time as may be 
    prescribed, a budget for the next financial year showing the estimated 
    receipts and expenditure during that financial year and forward a copy of 
    the same to the State Government. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of the budget forwarded to it 
    under sub-section (1), the State Government shall examine the same and 
    suggest such alterations, corrections, or modifications to be made therein 
    as it may think fit and forward such suggestions to the Board for its 
    consideration.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of the suggestions from the 
    State Government the Board may make written representations to that 
    Government with regard to the alterations, corrections or modifications 
    suggested by that Government and the State Government shall, after 
    considering such representations, communicate, within a period of three 
    weeks from the date of receipt thereof, to the Board its final decision in 
    relation to the matter and the decision of the State Government shall be 
    final.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the decision of the State 
    Government under sub-section (3), the Board shall incorporate in its budget 
    all the alternations, corrections, modifications finally suggested by the 
    State Government and the budget as so altered, corrected or modified, shall 
    be the budget which shall be passed by the Board.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>79</number> Accounts of Board.—The Board shall 
    cause to be maintained such books of account and other books in relation to 
    its accounts in such form and in such manner as may be provided by 
    regulations.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>80</number> Audit of accounts of Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    accounts of the Board shall be audited and examined annually by such auditor 
    as may be appointed by the State Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The auditor shall submit his report to the 
    State Government and the report of the auditor shall, among other things, 
    specify whether the accounts of every wakf under the direct management of 
    the Board have been kept separately and whether such accounts have been 
    audited annually by the State Examiner of Local Funds and shall also specify 
    all cases of irregular, illegal or improper expenditure or of failure to 
    recover money or other property caused by neglect or misconduct and any 
    other matter which the auditor considers it necessary to report; and the 
    report shall also contain the name of any person who, in the opinion of the 
    auditor is responsible for such expenditure or failure and the auditor shall 
    in every such case certify the amount of such expenditure or loss as due 
    from such person.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The cost of the audit shall be paid from 
    the Wakf Fund. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>81</number> State Government to pass orders on 
    auditor’s report.—The State Government shall examine the auditor’s 
    report and may call for the explanation of any person in regard to any 
    matter mentioned therein, and shall pass such orders on the report as it 
    thinks fit. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>81</number> State Government to pass orders on 
    auditor’s report.—The State Government shall examine the auditor’s 
    report and may call for the explanation of any person in regard to any 
    matter mentioned therein, and shall pass such orders on the report as it 
    thinks fit. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>82</number> Dues of Board to be recovered as 
    arrears of land revenue.—
<section><number>1</number> Every sum certified to be due from any 
    person by an auditor in his report under section 80, be paid by such person 
    within sixty days after the service of a demand notice by the Board.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If such payment is not made in accordance 
    with the provisions of sub-section (1), the sum payable may, on a 
    certificate issued by the Board, after giving the person concerned an 
    opportunity of being heard, be recovered as an arrear of land revenue. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>83</number> Constitution of Tribunals, etc.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The State Government shall, by notification in the Official Gazette, 
    constitute as many Tribunals as it may think fit, for the determination of 
    any dispute, question or other matter relating to a wakf or wakf property 
    under this Act and define the local limits and jurisdiction under this Act 
    of each of such Tribunals.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any mutawalli person interested in a wakf 
    or any other person aggrieved by an order made under this Act, or rules made 
    thereunder, may make an application within the time specified in this Act or 
    where no such time has been specified, within such time as may be 
    prescribed, to the Tribunal for the determination of any dispute, question 
    or other matter relating to the wakf.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where any application made under 
    sub-section (1) relates to any wakf property which falls within the 
    territorial limits of the jurisdiction of two or more Tribunals, such 
    application may be made to the Tribunal within the local limits of whose 
    jurisdiction the mutawalli or any one of the mutawallis of the wakf actually 
    and voluntarily resides, carries on business or personally works for gain, 
    and, where any such application is made to the Tribunal aforesaid, the other 
    Tribunal or Tribunals having jurisdiction shall not entertain any 
    application for the determination of such dispute, question or other matter:
      
 
Provided that the State Government may, if it 
    is of opinion that it is expedient in the interest of the wakf or any other 
    person interested in the wakf or the wakf property to transfer such 
    application to any other Tribunal having jurisdiction for the determination 
    of the dispute, question or other matter relating to such wakf or wakf 
    property, transfer such application to any other Tribunal having 
    jurisdiction, and, on such transfer, the Tribunal to which the application 
    is so transferred shall deal with the application from the stage which was 
    reached before the Tribunal from which the application has been so 
    transferred, except where the Tribunal is of opinion that it is necessary in 
    the interests of justice to deal with the application afresh.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Every Tribunal shall consist of one 
    person, who shall be a member of the State Judicial Service holding a rank, 
    not below that of a District, Sessions or Civil Judge, Class I, and the 
    appointment of every such person may be made either by name or by 
    designation.   
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The Tribunal shall be deemed to be a civil 
    court and shall have the same powers as may be exercised by a civil court 
    under the Code of Civil Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), while trying a suit, or 
    executing a decree or order.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in the 
    Code of Civil Procedure, 1908
    (5 of 1908), the Tribunal shall follow such procedure as may be prescribed. 
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The decision of the Tribunal shall be 
    final and binding upon the parties to the application and it shall have the 
    force of a decree made by a civil court.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>8</number> The execution of any decision of the 
    Tribunal shall be made by the civil court to which such decision is sent for 
    execution in accordance with the provisions of the Code of Civil Procedure, 
    1908 (5 of 1908).  
     
 </section><section>
<number>9</number> No appeal shall lie against any decision 
    or order whether interim or otherwise, given or made by the Tribunal:  
     
 
Provided that a High Court may, on its own 
    motion or on the application of the Board or any person aggrieved, call for 
    and examine the records relating to any dispute, question or other matter 
    which has been determined by the Tribunal for the purpose of satisfying 
    itself as to the correctness, legality or propriety of such determination 
    and may confirm, reverse or modify such determination or pass such other 
    order as it may think fit.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>84</number> Tribunal to hold proceedings 
    expeditiously and to furnish to the parties copies of its decision.—Whenever 
    an application is made to a Tribunal for the determination of any dispute, 
    question or other matter relating to a wakf or wakf property it shall hold 
    its proceedings as expeditiously as possible and shall as soon as 
    practicable, on the conclusion of the hearing of such matter give its 
    decision in writing and furnish a copy of such decision to each of the 
    parties to the dispute.
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>85</number> Bar of jurisdiction of civil courts.—No 
    suit or other legal proceeding shall lie in any civil court in respect of 
    any dispute, question or other matter relating to any wakf, wakf property or 
    other matter which is required by or under this Act to be determined by a 
    Tribunal.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>86</number> Appointment of a receiver in certain 
    cases.—Notwithstanding anything contained in the Code of Civil 
    Procedure, 1908 (5 of 1908), or in any other law for the time being in 
    force, where any suit or other legal proceeding is instituted or commenced— 
 <section>

    <number>a</number>   by or on behalf of a Board—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   to set aside 
    the sale of any immovable property, which is wakf property, in execution of 
    a decree or order of a civil court;  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   to set aside 
    the transfer of any immovable property, which is wakf property, made by the 
    mutawalli thereof, whether for valuable consideration or not, without or 
    otherwise than in accordance with, the sanction of the Board;  
     
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   to recover 
    possession of the property referred to in clause (a) or
    clause (b) or to restore possession of such property to the mutawalli of the 
    concerned wakf; or 
 </subsection></section><section>

    <number>b</number>   by a mutawalli to recover possession of immovable 
    property, which is wakf property, which has been transferred by a previous 
    mutawalli, whether for valuable consideration or not, without otherwise than 
    in accordance with the sanction of the Board, and which is in the possession 
    of the defendant, 
 
 
the court may, on the application of the 
    plaintiff, appoint a receiver of such property and direct such receiver to 
    pay from time to time to the plaintiff, out of the income of the property, 
    such amount as the court may consider to be necessary for further 
    prosecution of the suit.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>87</number> Bar to the enforcement of right on 
    behalf of unregistered wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    any other law for the time being in force, no suit, appeal or other legal 
    proceeding for the enforcement of any right on behalf of any wakf which has 
    not been registered in accordance with the provisions of this Act, shall be 
    instituted or commenced or heard, tried or decided by any court after the 
    commencement of this Act, or where any such suit, appeal or other legal 
    proceeding had been instituted or commenced before such commencement, no 
    such suit, appeal or other legal proceeding shall be continued, heard, tried 
    or decided by any court after such commencement unless such wakf has been 
    registered, in accordance with the provisions of this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The provisions of sub-section (1) shall 
    apply as far as may be, to the claim for set-off or any other claim made on 
    behalf of any wakf which has not been registered in accordance with the 
    provisions of this Act. 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>88</number> Bar to challenge the validity of any 
    notification, etc.—Save as otherwise expressly provided in this Act, no 
    notification or order or decision made, proceeding or action taken, by the 
    Central Government or the State Government under this Act or any rule made 
    thereunder shall be questioned in any civil court. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>89</number> Notice of suits by parties against 
    Board.—No suit shall be instituted against the Board in respect of any 
    act purporting to be done by it in pursuance of this Act or of any rules 
    made thereunder, until the expiration of two months next after notice in 
    writing has been delivered to, or left at, the office of the Board, stating 
    the cause of action, the name, description and place of residence of the 
    plaintiff and the relief which he claims; and the plaint shall contain a 
    statement that such notice has been so delivered or left. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>90</number> Notice of suits, etc., by courts.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    In every suit or proceeding relating to a title to or possession of a wakf 
    property or the right of a mutawalli or beneficiary, the court or Tribunal 
    shall issue notice to the Board at the cost of the party instituting such 
    suit or proceeding.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Whenever any wakf property is notified for 
    sale in execution of a decree of a civil court or for the recovery of any 
    revenue, cess, rates or taxes due to the Government or any local authority, 
    notice shall be given to the Board by the court, Collector or other person 
    under whose order the sale is notified.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> In the absence of a notice under 
    sub-section (1), any decree or order passed in the suit or proceeding shall 
    be declared void, if the Board, within one month of its coming to know of 
    such suit or proceeding, applies to the court in this behalf.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In the absence of a notice under 
    sub-section (2), the sale shall be declared void, if the Board, within one 
    month of its coming to know of the sale, applies in this behalf to the court 
    or other authority under whose order the sale was held.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>91</number> Proceedings under Act 1 of 1894.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If, in the course of proceedings under the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 or 
    under any law for the time being in force relating to the acquisition of 
    land or other property, it appears to the Collector before an award is made 
    that any property under acquisition is wakf property, a notice of such 
    acquisition shall be served by Collector on the Board and further 
    proceedings shall be stayed to enable the Board to appear and plead as a 
    party to the proceeding at any time within three months from the date of the 
    receipt of such notice. 
 
Explanation.—The reference to the 
    Collector in the foregoing provisions of this sub-section shall, in relation 
    to any other law referred to therein, be construed, if the Collector is not 
    the competent authority under such other law to make an award of the 
    compensation or other amount payable for acquisition of land or other 
    property thereunder, as a reference to the authority under such other law 
    competent to make such award. 
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Board has reason to believe that 
    any property under acquisition is wakf property, it may at any time before 
    the award is made appear and plead as a party to the proceeding.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> When the Board has appeared under the 
    provisions of sub-section (1) or sub-section (2) no order shall be passed 
    under section 31 or section 32 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 or under 
    the corresponding provisions of the other law referred to in sub-section (1) 
    without giving an opportunity to the Board to be heard.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Any order passed under section 31 or 
    section 32 of the Land Acquisition Act, 1894 or under the corresponding 
    provisions of the other law referred to in sub-section (1) without giving an 
    opportunity to the Board to be heard, shall be declared void if the Board, 
    within one month of its coming to know of the order, applies in this behalf 
    to the authority which made the order.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>92</number> Board to be party to suit or 
    proceeding.—In any suit or proceeding in respect of a wakf or any wakf 
    property the Board may appear and plead as a party to the suit or 
    proceeding.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>93</number> Bar to compromise of suits by or 
    against mutawallis.—No suit or proceeding in any court by or against the 
    mutawalli of a wakf relating to title to wakf property or the rights of the 
    mutawalli shall be compromised without the sanction of the Board. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>94</number> Power to make application to the 
    tribunal in case of failure of mutawalli to discharge his duties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where a mutawalli is under an obligation to perform any act which is 
    recognised by Muslim law as pious, religious or charitable and the mutawalli 
    fails to perform such act, the Board may apply to the Tribunal for an order 
    directing the mutawalli to pay to the Board or to any person authorised by 
    the Board in this behalf the amount necessary for the performance of such 
    act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where a mutawalli is under an obligation 
    to discharge any other duties imposed on him under the wakf and the 
    mutawalli wilfully fails to discharge such duties, the Board or any person 
    interested in the wakf may make an application to the Tribunal and the 
    Tribunal may pass such order thereon as it thinks fit.  
 




 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>95</number> Power of appellate authority to 
    entertain appeal after expiry of specified period.—Where under this Act 
    any period has been specified for the filing of an appeal, the appellate 
    authority may, if it is satisfied that the appellant was prevented by 
    sufficient cause from preferring the appeal within the period so specified, 
    entertain the appeal after the expiry of the said period. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>96</number> Power of Central Government to regulate 
    secular activities of wakfs.—
<section><number>1</number> For the purpose of regulating the 
    secular activities of wakfs, the Central Government shall have the following 
    powers and functions, namely:—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   to lay down general principles, and policies of wakf 
    administration in so far as they relate to the secular activities of the 
    wakfs;   
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   to co-ordinate the functions of the Central Wakf 
    Council and the Board, in so far as they relate to their secular functions;
      
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   to review administration of the secular activities of wakfs generally and to suggest improvements, if any. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> In exercising its powers and functions 
    under sub-section (1), the Central Government may call for any periodic or 
    other reports from any Board and may issue to the Board such directions as 
    it may think fit and the Board shall comply with such directions.  
     
 
Explanation.—For the purposes of this 
    section “secular activities” shall include social, economic, educational and 
    other welfare activities.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>97</number> Directions by State Government.—Subject 
    to any directions issued by the Central Government under section 96, the 
    State Government may, from time to time give to the Board such general or 
    special directions as the State Government thinks fit and in the performance 
    of its functions, the Board shall comply with such directions. 
 


 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>98</number> Annual report by State Government.—As 
    soon as may be after the close of a financial year, the State Government 
    shall cause a general annual report on the working and administration of the 
    State Wakf Board and the Administration of wakfs in the State during that 
    year to be prepared and laid before each House of the State Legislature 
    where it consists of two Houses, or where such Legislature consists of one 
    House, before that House, and every such report shall be in such form and 
    shall contain such matters as may be provided by regulations.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>99</number> Power to supersede Board.—
<section><number>1</number> If 
    the State Government is of opinion that the Board is unable to perform or 
    has persistently made default in the performance of, the duty imposed on it 
    by or under this Act or has exceeded or abused its powers, or has wilfully 
    and without sufficient cause failed to comply with any direction issued by 
    the Central Government under section 96 or the State Government under 
    section 97, or if the State Government is satisfied on consideration of any 
    report submitted after annual inspection, that the Board’s continuance is 
    likely to be injurious to the interests of the wakfs in the State, the State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, supersede the Board 
    for a period not exceeding six months:
 
Provided that before issuing a notification 
    under this sub-section, the State Government shall give a reasonable time to 
    the Board to show cause why it should not be superseded and shall consider 
    the explanations and objections, if any, of the Board.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Upon the publication of a notification 
    under sub-section (1) superseding the Board,—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   all the members of the Board shall, as from the date 
    of supersession, vacate their offices as such members; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   all the powers and duties which may, by or under the 
    provisions of this Act, be exercised or performed by or on behalf of the 
    Board shall, during the period of supersession, be exercised and performed 
    by such person or persons as the State Government may direct; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   all property vested in the Board shall, during the 
    period of supersession vest in the State Government. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> On the expiration of the period of 
    supersession specified in the notification issued under sub-section (1), the 
    State Government may—  
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   extend the period of supersession for such further 
    period as it may consider necessary; or 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   reconstitute the Board in the manner provided in 
    section 14. 
 

 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>100</number> Protection of action taken in good 
    faith.—No suit or other legal proceeding shall lie against the Board or 
    Chief Executive Officer or Survey Commissioner or any other person duly 
    appointed under this Act in respect of anything which is in good faith done 
    or intended to be done under this Act. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>101</number> Survey Commissioner, members and 
    officers of the Board deemed to be public servants.—
<section><number>1</number> The Survey 
    Commissioner, members of the Board, every officer, every auditor of the 
    Board and every other person duly appointed to discharge any duties imposed 
    on him by this Act or any rule or order made thereunder, shall be deemed to 
    be public servants within the meaning of section 21 of the Indian Penal Code 
    (45 of 1860).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every mutawalli of a wakf, every member of 
    managing committee, whether constituted by the Board or under any deed of 
    wakf, every Executive Officer and every person holding any office in a wakf 
    shall also be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning of section 21 
    of the Indian Penal Code (45 of 1860). 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>102</number> Special provision for reorganisation 
    of certain Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> Where on account of the reorganisation of States 
    under any law providing reorganisation of States, the whole or any part of a 
    State in respect of which a Board was, immediately before the day of such 
    reorganisation, functioning has been transferred on that day to another 
    State and by reason of such transfer, it appears to the Government of a 
    State in any part of which the Board is functioning that the Board should be 
    dissolved or that it should be reconstituted as an Intra-State Board for the 
    whole or any part of the State, the State Government may frame a scheme or 
    such dissolution or such reconstitution, including proposals regarding the 
    transfer of all assets, rights and liabilities of the Board to any other 
    Board or State Government and the transfer or re-employment of employees of 
    the Board and forward the scheme to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On receipt of a scheme forwarded to it 
    under sub-section (1), the Central Government may, after consulting the 
    State Governments concerned, approve the scheme with or without 
    modifications and give effect to the scheme so approved by making such order 
    as it thinks fit.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An order under sub-section (2) may provide 
    for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
     
 <subsection>

    <number>a</number>   the dissolution of the Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>b</number>   the reconstitution in any manner whatsoever of the 
    Board including the establishment, where necessary, of a new Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>c</number>   the area in respect of which the reconstituted Board 
    or new Board shall function and operate; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>d</number>   the transfer, in whole or in part, of the assets, 
    rights and liabilities of the Board (including the rights and liabilities 
    under any contract made by it) to any other Board or State Government and 
    the terms and conditions of such transfer; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>e</number>   the substitution of any such transferee for the 
    Board, or the addition of any such transferee, as a party to any legal 
    proceeding to which the Board is a party; and the transfer of any proceeding 
    pending before the Board to any such transferee; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>f</number>   the transfer or re-employment of any employee of the 
    Board to or by, any such transferee and subject to the provisions of law 
    providing for the reorganisation of the concerned State, the terms and 
    conditions of service applicable to such employees after such transfer or 
    re-employment; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>

    <number>g</number>   such incidental, consequential and supplemental 
    matters as may be necessary to give effect to the approved scheme. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where an order is made under this section 
    transferring the assets, rights and liabilities of any Board, then, by 
    virtue of that order, such assets, rights and liabilities of the Board shall 
    vest in and be the assets, rights and liabilities of, the transferee.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every order made under this section shall 
    be published in the Official Gazette.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> Every order made under this section shall 
    be laid before each House of Parliament, as soon as may be, after it is 
    made.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>103</number> Special provision for establishment of 
    Board for part of a state.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where on account of the territorial changes brought about by any law 
    providing for the reorganisation of any State, this Act is as from the date 
    on which that law comes into force applicable only to any part or parts of a 
    State but has not been brought into force in the remaining part thereof, 
    then notwithstanding anything contained in this Act, it shall be lawful for 
    the Government of the State to establish one or more Boards for such part or 
    parts in which this Act is in force and in such a case any reference in this 
    Act to the word ‘State’ in relation of a Board shall be construed as a 
    reference to that part of the State for which the Board is established.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where any such Board has been established 
    and it appears to the Government of the State that a Board should be 
    established for the whole of the State, the State Government may, by order 
    notified in the Official Gazette dissolve the Board established for the part 
    of the State or reconstitute and reorganise such Board or establish a new 
    Board for the whole of the State and thereupon, the assets, rights and 
    liabilities of the Board for the part of the State shall vest in and be the 
    assets, rights and liabilities of the reconstituted Board or the new Board, 
    as the case may be.  
     
  



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>104</number> Application of Act to properties given 
    or donated by persons not professing Islam for support of certain wakf.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in this Act where any movable or immovable property has 
    been given or donated by any person not professing Islam for the support of 
    a wakf being—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   a 
    mosque, idgah, imambara, dargah, khangah or a maqbara;
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   a Muslim 
    graveyard;
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   a 
    choultry or musafirkhana,
 
then such property shall be deemed to be 
    comprised in that wakf and be dealt in the same manner as the wakf in which 
    it is so comprised.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>105</number> Power of Board and Chief Executive 
    Officer to require copies of documents, etc., to be furnished.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in any law for the time being in force, it shall be 
    lawful for the Board or the Chief Executive Officer to require any person 
    having the custody of any record, register, report or other document 
    relating to a wakf or any immovable property, which is wakf property, to 
    furnish subject to the payment of necessary costs, copies of, or extracts 
    from, any such record, register, report or document and every person to whom 
    such a requisition is made, shall furnish, as soon as may be practicable, to 
    the Board or Chief Executive Officer copies or extracts from the required 
    record, register, report or other document. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>106</number> Powers of Central Government to 
    constitute common Boards.—
<section><number>1</number> Where the Central Government is satisfied 
    that by reasons of— 
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the 
    smallness of the Muslim population in two or more States, 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the 
    slender resources of the wakfs in such States, and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the 
    disproportion between the number and income of the wakfs and the Muslim 
    population in such States, 
 
 
it is expedient in the interests of the wakfs 
    in the States and the Muslim population of such States, to have, instead of 
    separate Boards for each of such States, a common Board, it may, after 
    consultation with the Government of each of the concerned States, establish, 
    by notification in the Official Gazette, a common Board for such States as 
    it may deem fit, and may, by the same or any subsequent notification specify 
    the place at which the principal office of such common Board shall be 
    located. 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Every common Board established under 
    sub-section (1) shall, as far as practicable, consist of the persons 
    specified in sub-section (1) or, as the case may be, sub-section (7) of 
    section 14.   
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Whenever any common Board is established 
    under sub-section (1),—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   all 
    powers vested in the State Government under any deed of wakf or any 
    provision of law for the time being in force relating to wakfs, shall stand 
    transferred to, and vested in, the Central Government and, thereupon, 
    references in such deed of wakf or law to the State Governments shall be 
    construed as references to the Central Government:  
 
       
    Provided that while establishing a common Board for two or more States, the 
    Central Government shall ensure that at least one representative of each of 
    the concerned States is included as a member of the Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   
    references in this Act to a State shall be construed as references to each 
    of the States for which the common Board has been established; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the 
    Central Government may, without prejudice to any rule applicable to a Board 
    in a State, make, by notification in the Official Gazette, rules regulating 
    the conduct of business by, and affairs of, the common Board. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The common Board shall be a body 
    corporate, with objects not confined to one State, having perpetual 
    succession and a common seal with power to acquire and hold property and to 
    transfer any such property, subject to such conditions and restrictions as 
    may be specified by the Central Government, and shall by the said name sue 
    or be sued.   

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>107</number> Act 36 of 1963 not to apply for 
    recovery of wakf properties.—Nothing contained in the Limitation Act, 
    1963 shall apply to any suit for possession of immovable property comprised 
    in any wakf or for possession of any interest in such property. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>108</number> Special provision as to evacuee wakf 
    properties.—The provisions of this Act shall apply, and shall be deemed 
    always to have applied, in relation to any evacuee property within the 
    meaning of clause (f) of section 2 of the Administration of Evacuee Property 
    Act, 1950 (31 of 1950), which immediately before it became such evacuee 
    property within the said meaning was property comprised in any wakf and, in 
    particular any instrument (whether by transfer of any documents or in any 
    other manner and whether generally or for specified purpose) of any such 
    property to a Board made before the commencement of this Act in pursuance of 
    the instructions of the Custodian under the Administration of Evacuee 
    Property Act, 1950 shall have, and shall be deemed always to have had, 
    notwithstanding anything contained in any other provision of this Act, 
    effect as if such entrustment had operated to— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   vest 
    such property in such Board in the same manner and with the same effect as 
    in a trustee of such property for the purposes of sub-section (1) of section 
    11 of the Administration of Evacuee Property Act, 1950 
    (31 of 1950) with effect from the date of such entrustment, and 

 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   
    authorise such Board to assume direct management of the wakf concerned for 
    so long as it might deem necessary. 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>109</number> Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> The State 
    Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to carry 
    out the purposes of this Act, other than those of Chapter III.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to 
    the generality of the foregoing powers, such rules may provide for all or 
    any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   other 
    particulars which the report of the Survey Commissioner may contain, under 
    clause (f) of sub-section (3) of section (4); 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   any 
    other matter under clause (f) of sub-section (4) of section 4; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   the 
    particulars which a list of wakfs published under sub-section (2) of section 
    5, may contain; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the 
    manner of election of members of the Board by means of a single transferable 
    vote, under sub-section (2) of section 14; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   the 
    terms and conditions of service of the Chief Executive Officer under 
    sub-section (2) of section 23; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   the 
    conditions and restrictions subject to which the Chief Executive Officer or 
    any other officer may inspect any public office, records or registers under 
    section 29; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   the 
    conditions subject to which an Executive Officer and supporting staff may be 
    appointed under sub-section (1) of section 38; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>   the 
    manner in which an inquiry may be held by the Chief Executive Officer under 
    sub-section (1) of section 39; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ix</number>   the 
    form in which, and the time within which, a separate budget for wakfs under 
    the direct management of the Board shall be prepared under sub-section (1) 
    of section 45; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>x</number>   the 
    interval at which accounts of wakfs may be audited in pursuance of the 
    provisions of sub-section (1) of section 47; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>xi</number>   the 
    time within which, the sale of any property is to be informed under the 
    first proviso to sub-section (2) of section 51 and the manner in which the 
    approval given under sub-section (3) of that section shall be published;
      
 <subsubsection>
<number>xii</number>   the 
    guidance subject to which the Collector shall recover the property 
    transferred in contravention of the provisions of this Act, under section 
    52;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xiii</number>   the 
    manner of service of notice issued under sub-section (1) of 
    section 54 and the manner in which any inquiry is to be made under 
    sub-section (3) of that section; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xiv</number>   the 
    manner in which any inquiry may be held under section 64 or section 71;
      
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xv</number>   the 
    other matters which may be specified in the report submitted under 
    sub-section (3) of section 65; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xvi</number>   the 
    manner of publication of order made under sub-section (2) of 
    section 67; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xvii</number>   the 
    manner in which consultation may be made with mutawalli under sub-section 
    (1) of section 69; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xviii</number>   the 
    manner of publication of order made under sub-section (3) of 
    section 69; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xix</number>   the 
    rate at which contribution is to be made by a mutawalli under section 72;
      
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xx</number>   the 
    payment of moneys into the Wakf Fund, the investment, the custody and 
    disbursement of such moneys under section 77; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxi</number>   the 
    form in which, and the time within which, the budget of the Board may be 
    prepared and submitted under section 78; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxii</number>   the 
    time within which application is to be made to the Tribunal under 
    sub-section (2) of section 83; 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxiii</number>   the 
    procedure which the Tribunal shall follow under sub-section (6) of section 
    83;   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxiv</number>   the 
    form in which the annual report is to be submitted and the matters which 
    such report shall contain under section 98; and 
 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>xxv</number>   any 
    other matter which is required to be, or may be, prescribed. 
 

 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>110</number> Powers to make regulations by the 
    Board.—
<section><number>1</number> The Board may, with the previous sanction of the State 
    Government, make regulations not inconsistent with this Act or the rules 
    made thereunder, for carrying out its functions under this Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In particular, and without prejudice to 
    the generality of the foregoing powers, such regulations may provide for all 
    or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the time 
    and places of the meetings of the Board under sub-section (1) of section 17;
      
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the 
    procedure and conduct of business at the meetings of the Board; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the 
    constitution and functions of the committees and the Board and the procedure 
    for transaction of business at the meetings of such committees; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the 
    allowances or fees to be paid to the Chairperson or members of the Board or 
    members of committees: 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the 
    terms and conditions of service of the officers and other employees of the 
    Board under sub-section (2) of section 24; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the 
    forms of application for registration of wakfs further particulars to be 
    contained therein and the manner and place of registration of wakfs under 
    sub-section (3) of section 36; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   further 
    particulars to be contained in the register of wakfs under section 37;
    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   the form 
    in which, and the time within which, the budgets of wakfs may be prepared 
    and submitted by the mutawalli and approved by the Board under sub-section 
    (1) of section 44; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   the 
    books of accounts and other books to be maintained by the Board under 
    section 79; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   fees 
    payable for inspection of proceedings and records of the Board or for issue 
    of copies of the same; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   persons 
    by whom any order or decision of the Board may be authenticated; and 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>l</number>   any 
    other matter which has to be, or may be provided by regulations. 
 
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> All regulations made under this section 
    shall be published in the Official Gazette and shall have effect from the 
    date of such publication.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>111</number> Laying of rules and regulations before 
    State Legislature.—Every rule made under section 109 and every 
    regulation made under section 110 shall be laid, as soon as may be after it 
    is made, before the State Legislature.

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>112</number> Repeal and savings.—
<section><number>1</number> The Wakf 
    Act, 1954 (29 of 1954) and the Wakf (Amendment) Act, 1984 (69 of 1984) are 
    hereby repealed.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Notwithstanding such repeal, anything done 
    or any action taken under the said Acts shall be deemed to have been done or 
    taken under the corresponding provisions of this Act.  
     
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If, immediately before the commencement of 
    this Act, in any State, there is in force in that State, any law which 
    corresponds to this Act that corresponding law shall stand repealed:  
     
 
Provided that such repeal shall not affect the 
    previous operation of that corresponding law, and subject thereto, anything 
    done or any action taken in the exercise of any power conferred by or under 
    the corresponding law shall be deemed to have been done or taken in the 
    exercise of the powers conferred by or under this Act as if this Act was in 
    force on the day on which such things were done or action was taken.  
     

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
 <article>
<number>113</number> Power to remove difficulties.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, the 
    Central Government may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of 
    this Act, remove the difficulty: 
 
Provided that no such order shall be made 
    after the expiry of the period of two years from the commencement of this 
    Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> However, order made under this section 
    shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House of 
    Parliament.  
 
  


</section></article>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>