<act><tid>631834</tid>
<title>THE MAINTENANCE ORDERS ENFORCEMENT ACT, <year>1921</year></title>

ACT NO. 18 OF <footcitenum>1921</footcitenum>
[ 5th October, <year>1921</year>.]

An Act to facilitate the enforcement in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] of Maintenance 
Orders made <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> reciprocating territories]], <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and vice 
versa. 
[ 5th October, <year>1921</year>.]

WHEREAS it is expedient to facilitate the enforcement in 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] of Maintenance Orders made <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> reciprocating 
territories]], <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> and vice versa; It is hereby enacted as follows:-





<article><tid>578192</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1342346</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Maintenance Orders Enforcement Act, <year>1921</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1926978</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum> It extends to the whole of India <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> except the State of 
Jammu and kashmir].]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>705498</tid>
<number>2</number>Definitions. In this Act, unless there is anything repugnant 
in the subject or context,-
" Court of summary jurisdiction" means the Court of a Chief 
Presidency Magistrate or of a District Magistrate;

" dependants" means such persons as a person against whom a 
maintenance order is made is liable to maintain according to the law 
in force in <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> the reciprocating territory] in which the maintenance 
order is made;

<footcitenum>9</footcitenum> India" means the territory of India excluding the State of 
Jammu and Kashmir;]

" maintenance order" means a decree or order, other than an order 
of affiliation, made by a Court in the exercise of civil or criminal 
jurisdiction for the periodical payment of sums of money towards


<pagefootnote><pagenum>550</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" Part A States and 
Part C States". 
2 Subs. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> for" in other parts of". 
3 The words" in Part B States or" omitted by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 
and Sch. 
4 Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1952</year>, s. 2, for" His Majesty' s Dominions and 
Protectorates". 
5 The words" Acceding States and other Indian States" omitted by 
the A. O. <year>1950</year>. 
6 Subs., ibid., for the former sub- section (2). 
7 Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" except Part B 
States". 
8 Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3, for" the part of His Majesty' s 
Dominions". 
9 Ins. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch.

This Act has been extended to and brought into force in Dadra 
and Nagar Haveli (w. e. f. 1- 7- <year>1965</year>) by Reg. 6 of <year>1963</year>, s. 2 and 
Sch. I.

This Act has been extended to the Union territory of Pondicherry 
by Act 26 of <year>1968</year>, s. 3 and Schedule.




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

the maintenance of the wife or other dependants of the person against 
whom the order is made;

" prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

" proper authority" means the authority appointed by, or under the 
law of, a reciprocating territory to receive and transmit documents to 
which this Act applies; and

<footcitenum>1</footcitenum> reciprocating territory" means any country or territory 
outside India in respect of which this Act for the time being applies 
by virtue of a declaration under section 3.]

<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>



</article>



<article><tid>1891982</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Declaration of reciprocal arrangements. If the Central 
Government is satisfied that legal provision exists in any country or 
territory outside India for the enforcement within that country or 
territory of maintenance orders made by Courts in India, the Central 
Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, declare that 
this Act applies in respect of that country or territory and thereupon 
it shall apply accordingly.]


</article>



<article><tid>1327653</tid>
<number> 4</number> Registration in India of maintenance orders made in the 
reciprocating territories.
<section><tid>1664663</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a maintenance order has, whether  
before or after the passing of this Act, been made against any person 
by any Court in any reciprocating territory, and a certified copy of 
the order has been transmitted by the proper authority of that 
territory to the Central Government, the Central Government shall send 
a copy of the order to the prescribed officer of a Court in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India] 
for registration, and, on receipt thereof, the order shall be 
registered in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>736173</tid>
<number>2</number>The Court in which an order is to be so registered as 
aforesaid shall, if the Court by which the order was made was, in the 
opinion of the Central Government, a Court of superior jurisdiction, 
be a High Court, and, if the Court was not, in its opinion, a Court of 
superior jurisdiction, be a Court of summary jurisdiction.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1597125</tid>
<number>5</number>Transmission of maintenance orders made in India. Where a 
Court in <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> India] has, whether before or after the commencement of 
this Act, made a maintenance order against any person, and it is 
proved to that Court that the person against whom the order was made 
is resident in a reciprocating territory, the Court shall send to the 
Central Government, for transmission to the proper authority of that 
territory, a certified copy of the order.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>551</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1952</year>, s. 3, for the former definition. 
2 Definition of" States" ins. by the A. O. <year>1950</year> was omitted by Act 
3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch. 
3 Subs. by Act 47 of <year>1952</year>, s. 4, for the former s. 3. 
4 Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>664722</tid>
<number> 6</number> Power of summary Courts to make provisional maintenance orders 
against persons resident in reciprocating territories.
<section><tid>485074</tid>
<number>1</number>Where  
application is made to a Court of summary jurisdiction in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] 
for a maintenance order against any person, and it is proved that 
person is resident in a reciprocating territory, the Court may, in the 
absence of that person, if after hearing the evidence it is satisfied 
of the justice of the application, make any such order as it might 
have made if that person had wilfully neglected to attend the Court; 
but in such case the order shall be provisional only and shall have no 
effect unless and until confirmed by a competent Court in such 
territory.

</section>

<section><tid>1057104</tid>
<number>2</number>The evidence of every witness who is examined on any such 
application shall be reduced to writing, and such deposition shall be 
read over to, and signed by, him.

</section>

<section><tid>1205768</tid>
<number>3</number>Where such an order is made, the Court shall send to the 
Central Government, for transmission to the proper authority of the 
reciprocating territory in which the person against whom the order is 
made is alleged to reside, the depositions so taken and a certified 
copy of the order together with a statement of the grounds on which 
the making of the order might have been opposed if the person against 
whom the order is made had been duly served with a summons and had 
appeared at the hearing and such information as the Court possesses 
for facilitating the identification of that person and ascertaining 
his whereabouts.

</section>

<section><tid>1387805</tid>
<number>4</number>Where any such provisional order has come before a Court in a 
reciprocating territory for confirmation, and the order has by that 
Court been remitted to the Court of summary jurisdiction which made 
the order for the purpose of taking further evidence, that Court 
shall, after giving the prescribed notice, proceed to take the 
evidence in like manner and subject to the like conditions as the 
evidence in support of the original application.

</section>

<section><tid>1450410</tid>
<number>5</number>If it appears to the Court hearing such evidence that the 
order ought not to have been made, the Court may rescind the order, 
but in any other case the depositions shall be sent to the Central 
Government and dealt with in like manner as the original depositions.

</section>

<section><tid>1137359</tid>
<number>6</number>The confirmation of an order made under this section shall 
not affect any power of a Court of summary jurisdiction to vary or 
rescind that order:
Provided that, on the making of a varying or rescinding order, 
the Court shall send a certified copy thereof to the Central 
Government for transmission to the proper authority of the 
reciprocating territory in which the original order was confirmed, or 
to which it was sent for confirmation and that, in the case of an 
order varying the

<pagefootnote><pagenum>552</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


original order, the order shall not have any effect unless and until 
confirmed in like manner as the original order.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>101778</tid>
<number> 7</number> Power of Court of summary jurisdiction to confirm maintenance 
order made out of India.
<section><tid>1212022</tid>
<number>1</number>Where a maintenance order has been made  
by a Court in a reciprocating territory and the order is provisional 
only, and has no effect unless and until confirmed by a Court of 
summary jurisdiction in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], and a certified copy of the order, 
together with the depositions of the witnesses and a statement of the 
grounds on which the order might have been opposed, has been 
transmitted to the Central Government, and it appears to the Central 
Government that the person against whom the order has been made is 
resident in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], the Central Government may send the said 
documents to the prescribed officer of a Court of summary 
jurisdiction, with a requisition that a summons be issued calling upon 
the person to show cause why that order should not be confirmed, and, 
upon recipt of such documents and requisition, the Court shall issue 
such a summons and cause it to be served upon such person.

</section>

<section><tid>942780</tid>
<number>2</number>A summons issued under sub- section (1) shall for all purposes 
be deemed to be a summons issued by the Court in the exercise of its 
original criminal jurisdiction.

</section>

<section><tid>958885</tid>
<number>3</number>At the hearing it shall be open to the person to whom the 
summons was issued to raise any defence which he might have raised in 
the original proceedings had he been a party thereto, but no other 
defence, and the certificate from the Court which made the provisional 
order stating the grounds on which the making of the order might have 
been opposed if the person against whom the order was made had been a 
party to the proceedings shall be conclusive evidence that those 
grounds are grounds on which objection may be taken.

</section>

<section><tid>1854013</tid>
<number>4</number>If at the hearing the person served with the summons does not 
appear or, on appearing, fails to satisfy the Court that the order 
ought not to be confirmed, the Court may, notwithstanding any 
pecuniary limit imposed on its power by any law for the time being in 
force in <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India], confirm the order either without modification or 
with such modifications as to the Court after hearing the evidence may 
seem just:
Provided that no sum shall be awarded as maintenance under this 
section, or shall be recoverable as such, at a rate exceeding that 
proposed in the provisional order.


</section>

<section><tid>521481</tid>
<number>5</number>If the person to whom the summons was issued appears at the 
hearing and satisfies the Court that for the purpose of any defence
<pagefootnote><pagenum>553</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


it is necessary to remit the case to the Court which made the 
provisional order for the taking of any further evidence, the Court 
may for that purpose send a certified copy of the record to the 
Central Government for transmission to that Court through the proper 
authority of the reciprocating territory, and may adjourn the 
proceedings.


</section>

<section><tid>1071826</tid>
<number>6</number>Where a provisional order has been confirmed under this 
section, it may be varied or rescinded in like manner as if it had 
originally been made by the confirming Court, and where on an 
application for rescission or variation the Court is satisfied that it 
is necessary to remit the case to the Court which made the provisional 
order for the purpose of taking any further evidence, the Court may 
for that purpose send a certified copy of the record to the Central 
Government for transmission to that Court through the proper authority 
of the reciprocating territory, and may adjourn the proceedings.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>588423</tid>
<number> 8</number> Enforcement of maintenance orders.
<section><tid>1795405</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of this Act, where an order has been registered under this 
Act in a High Court, the order shall, from the date of such 
registration, be of the same force and effect, and all proceedings may 
be taken thereon as if it had been an order originally obtained in the 
High Court in the exercise of its civil jurisdiction, or in such Civil 
Court subordinate to that High Court as may be named by the High Court 
in this behalf, and that Court shall have power to enforce the order 
accordingly.

</section>

<section><tid>1804780</tid>
<number>2</number>A Court of summary jurisdiction in which an order has been 
registered under this Act or by which an order has been confirmed 
under this Act, and the officers of such Court, shall have such powers 
and perform such duties, for the purpose of enforcing the order, as 
may be prescribed.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1687062</tid>
<number>9</number>Payment of charges for transmission of sums awarded as 
maintenance and other costs and charges. A Court in registering or 
confirming an order for maintenance in accordance with the provisions 
of this Act shall direct that the charges for the transmission to the 
Court, from which the order has been received or in which the 
provisional order has been made, as the case may be, of the sum 
awarded as maintenance shall be borne by the person against whom the 
order has been so made or confirmed, and shall be recovered from him 
in addition to the sum awarded as maintenance and in addition to, and 
in the same manner as, such other costs and charges as may be awarded 
or levied by the Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1106843</tid>
<number>10</number>Proof of documents signed by officers of Court. For the 
purposes of this Act, any document purporting to be signed by a judge 
or officer of a Court outside <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> India] shall, until the contrary is 
proved, be deemed to have been so signed without
<pagefootnote><pagenum>554</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 3 of <year>1951</year>, s. 3 and Sch., for" the States".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


proof of the signature of judicial or official character of the person 
appearing to have signed it, and the officer of a Court by whom a 
document is signed shall, until the contrary is provided, be deemed to 
have been the proper officer of the Court to sign the document.



</article>



<article><tid>1326864</tid>
<number>11</number>Depositions to be evidence. Depositions taken in a Court in 
any reciprocating territory may, for the purposes of this Act, be 
received in evidence in proceedings before Courts of summary 
jurisdiction under this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>1367164</tid>
<number> 12</number> Rule- making power. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[
<section><tid>374827</tid>
<number>1</number>] The Central Government <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> may,  
by notification in the Official Gazette, make rules] for the purpose 
of carrying into effect the purposes of this Act, and in particular 
may make rules for the levy of the costs or charges for anything done 
under this Act and for all matters which are directed or permitted to 
be prescribed.

</section>

<section><tid>1277447</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Every rule made by the Central Government under this Act 
shall be laid, as soon as may be after it is made, before each House 
of Parliament, while it is in session, for a total period of thirty 
days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree in making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.]
<pagefootnote><pagenum>555</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 12 renumbered as sub- section (1) thereof by Act 20 of <year>1983</year>, 
s. 2 and Sch. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>). 
2 Subs. by s. 2 and Sch., ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>). 
3 Ins. by s. 2 and Sch., ibid. (w. e. f. 15- 3- <year>1984</year>).

</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>