<act><title>


The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) 
Central Rules, 19711</title> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Central 
Rules, 1971.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date2 of 
their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the subject or context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  “Act” means 
the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  “Appellate 
Officer” means the Appellate Officer appointed by the Central Government under 
sub-section (1) of section 15;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  “Board” 
means the Central Advisory Contract Labour Board constituted under section 3;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  “Chairman” 
means the Chairman of the Board;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  “Committee” 
means a Committee constituted under sub-section (1) of section 5;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  “Form” means 
a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>
         <number>g</number>  “Section” 
means a section of the Act.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
The Board shall consist of 
the following Members.—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  a Chairman 
to be appointed by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  the Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central)—ex-officio;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  

1[three] persons 
representing the Central Government, to be appointed by that Government from 
amongst its officials;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number> 

2[two] persons 
representing the Railways, to be appointed by Central Government after 
consultation with the Railway Board;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  

3[five] persons, 
one representing the employers in coal mines, 

1[two] representing 
the employers in other mines and two representing contractors to whom the Act 
applies, to be appointed by the Central Government after consultation with such 
organisations, if any, of the employers and the contractors as may be recognised 
by the Central Government;
 </section><section>
         <number>f</number>  

4[seven] persons,


5[two] representing 
the employees in the Railways, one representing the employees in coal mines,


4[two] representing 
the employees in other mines and two representing the employees of contractors 
to whom the Act applies, to be appointed by the Central Government after 
consultation with such organisations, if any, of employees representing the 
respective interest as may be recognised by the Central Government.
 
 







</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>4</number> Terms of Office.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Chairman of the Board shall hold office as such for a period of three years 
from the date on which his appointment is first notified in the Official 
Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each of the members of 
the Board, referred to in clauses (c) and (d) of rule 3, shall hold office as 
such during the pleasure of the President.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Each of the members 
referred to in clauses (e) and (f) of rule 3 shall hold office as such for a 
period of three years commencing from the date on which his appointment is first 
notified in the Official Gazette:
 
Provided that where the 
successor of any such member has not been notified in the Official Gazette on or 
before the expiry of the said period of three years, such member shall, 
notwithstanding the expiry of the period of his office, continue to hold such 
office until the appointment of his successor has been notified in the Official 
Gazette.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If a member is unable 
to attend a meeting of the Board, the Central Government or the body which 
appointed or nominated him may, by notice in writing signed on its behalf and by 
such member and addressed to the Chairman of the said Board, nominate a 
substitute in his place to attend the meeting and such a substitute member shall 
have all rights of a member in respect of that meeting and any decision taken at 
the meeting shall be binding on the said body.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>5</number> Resignation.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A member of the Board, not being an ex-officio member, may resign his 
office by a letter in writing addressed to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The office of such a 
member shall fall vacant from the date on which his resignation is accepted by 
the Central Government, or on the expiry of thirty days from the date of receipt 
of the letter of resignation by that Government whichever is earlier.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>6</number> Cessation of 
membership.—If 
any member of the Board, not being an ex-officio member, fails to attend 
three consecutive meetings of the Board, without obtaining the leave of the 
Chairman for such absence, he shall cease to be a member of the Board:
 
Provided that the Central 
Government may, if it is satisfied that such member was prevented by sufficient 
cause from attending three consecutive meetings of the Board, direct that such 
cessation shall not take place and on such direction being made, such member 
shall continue to be a member of the Board.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>7</number> Disqualification for 
membership.—
<section><number>1</number> 
A person shall be disqualified for being re-appointed, and for being a member of 
the Board,—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  if he is of 
unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  if he is an 
undischarged insolvent; or
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  if he has 
been or is convicted of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, involves moral turpitude.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If a question arises 
as to whether a disqualification has been incurred under sub-rule (1), the 
Central Government shall decide the same.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>8</number> Removal from 
membership.—The 
Central Government may remove from office any member of the Board, if in its 
opinion such a member has ceased to represent the interest which he purports to 
represent on the Board:
 
Provided that no such 
member shall be removed unless a reasonable opportunity is given to him of 
making any representation against the proposed action.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>9</number> Vacancy.—When 
a vacancy occurs or is likely to occur in the membership of the Board the 
Chairman shall submit a report to the Central Government and on receipt of such 
report the Central Government shall take steps to fill the vacancy by making an 
appointment from amongst the category of persons to which the person vacating 
membership belonged and the person so appointed shall hold office for the 
remainder of the term of office of the member in whose place he is appointed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>10</number> Staff.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) The Central Government may appoint one of its officials as Secretary to the 
Board and appoint such other staff as it may think necessary to enable the Board 
to carry out its functions.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The salaries and 
allowances payable to the staff and the other conditions of service of such 
staff shall be such as may be decided by the Central Government.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Secretary—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  shall 
assist the Chairman in convening meetings of the Board;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  may attend 
the meetings but shall not be entitled to vote at such meetings;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>iii</number>  shall keep 
a record of the minutes of such meetings; and
 </subsection><subsection>
        <number>iv</number>  shall take 
necessary measures to carry out the decisions taken at the meetings of the 
Board.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>11</number> Allowances of 
members.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The travelling allowance of an official member shall be governed by the rules 
applicable to him for journey performed by him on official duties and shall be 
paid by the authority paying his salary.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The non-official 
members of the Board shall be paid travelling allowance for attending the 
meeting of the Board at such rates as are admissible to Grade I Officers of the 
Central Government and daily allowances shall be calculated at the maximum rate 
admissible to Grade I officers of the Central Government in their respective 
places.
</section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>12</number> Disposal of business </title>.—Every question which the Board is required to take into consideration shall be considered at a meeting, or, if the Chairman so directs, by sending the necessary papers to every member for opinion, and the question shall be disposed of in accordance with the decision of the majority: 
 Provided that in the case of equality of votes, the Chairman shall have a second or a casting vote. 
 Explanation .—“Chairman” for the purposes of this Rule shall include the Chairman nominated under rule 13 to preside over a meeting. 
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>13</number> Meetings.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Board shall meet at such places and times as may be specified by the 
Chairman.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Chairman shall 
preside over every meeting of the Board at which he is present and in his 
absence nominate a member of the Board to preside over such meeting.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>14</number> Notice of meeting 
and list of business.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Ordinarily seven days’ notice shall be given to the members of a proposed 
meeting.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> No business which is 
not on the list of business for a meeting shall be considered at that meeting 
without the permission of the Chairman.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>15</number> Quorum.—No 
business shall be transacted at any meeting unless at least five members are 
present:
 
Provided that if at any 
meeting less than five members are present, the Chairman may adjourn the meeting 
to another date informing members present and given notice to the other members 
that he proposes to dispose of the business at the adjourned meeting whether 
there is prescribed quorum or not, and it shall thereupon be lawful for him to 
dispose of the business at the adjourned meeting irrespective of the number of 
members attending.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>16</number> Committees of the 
Board.—
<section><number>1</number> (i) 
The Board may constitute such committees and for such purpose or purposes as it 
may think fit.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> While constituting 
the Committee the Board may nominate one of its members to be the Chairman of 
the Committee.
 

1[(2) (i) The 
Committee shall meet at such times and places as the Chairman of the said 
Committee may decide.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number> The provisions of 
rules 12, 13(2), 14 and 15 shall apply to the Committee for transaction of 
business at its meetings as they apply to the Board, subject to the Modification 
that the quorum specified in rule 15 shall be one-third of the members instead 
of ‘five members’.]
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The provisions of rule 
11 shall apply to the members of the Committee for attending the meetings of the 
Committee as they apply to the members of the Board.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>17</number> Manner of making 
application for registration of establishments.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The application referred to in sub-section (1) of section 7 shall be made in 
triplicate in Form I to the registering officer of the area in which the 
establishment sought to be registered is located.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be accompanied by a 

1[demand draft] 
showing payment of the fees for the registration of the establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every application 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall be either personally delivered to the 
registering officer or sent to him by registered post.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the 
application referred to in sub-rule (1), the registration officer shall, after 
noting thereon the date of receipt by him of the application, grant an 
acknowledgement to the applicant.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>18</number> Grant of 
certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The certificate of registration granted under sub-section (2) of section 7 shall 
be in Form II.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every certificate of 
registration granted under sub-section (2) of section 7 shall contain the 
following particulars, namely:—
 <subsection>
         <number>a</number>  the name and 
address of the establishment;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  the maximum 
number of workmen to be employed as contract labour in the establishment;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  the type of 
business, trade, industry, manufacture or occupation which is carried on in the 
establishment;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  such other 
particulars as may be relevant to the employment of contract labour in the 
establishment.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The registering 
officer shall maintain a register in Form III showing the particulars of 
establishment in relation to which certificates of registration have been issued 
by him.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> If, in relation to an 
establishment, there is any change, in the particulars specified in the 
certificate of registration, the principal employer of the establishment shall 
intimate to the registering officer, within thirty days from the date when such 
change takes place, the particulars of, and the reasons for, such change.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>19</number> Circumstances in 
which application for registration may be rejected.—
<section><number>1</number> 
If any application for registration is not complete in all respects, the 
registering officer shall require the principal employer to amend the 
application so as to make it complete in all respects.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the principal 
employer, on being required by the registering officer to amend his application 
for registration, omits or fails to do so, the registering officer shall reject 
the application for registration.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>20</number> Amendment of 
certificate of registration.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where, on receipt of the intimation under sub-rule (4) of rule 18, the 
registering officer is satisfied that an amount higher than the amount which has 
been paid by the principal employer as fees for the registration of the 
establishment is payable, he shall require such principal employer to 

1[pay] a sum which, 
together with the amount already paid by such principal employer, would be equal 
to such higher amount of fees payable for the registration of the establishment 
and to produce the 

1[demand draft] 
showing such deposit.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where, on receipt of 
the intimation referred to in sub-rule (4) of rule 18, the registering officer 
is satisfied that there has occurred a change in the particulars of the 
establishment, as entered in the register in Form III, he shall amend the said 
register and record therein the change which has occurred:
 
Provided that no such 
amendment shall affect anything done or any action taken or any right, 
obligation or liability acquired or incurred before such amendment:
 
Provided further that the 
registering officer shall not carry out any amendment in the register in Form 
III unless the appropriate fees have been deposited by the principal employer.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>21</number> Application for a 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every application by a contractor for the grant of a licence shall be made in 
triplicate in Form IV, to the licensing officer of the area in which the 
establishment, in relation to which he is the contractor, is located.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every application for 
the grant of a licence shall be accompanied by a certificate by the principal 
employer in Form V to the effect that the applicant has been employed by him as 
a contractor in relation to his establishment and that he undertakes to be bound 
by all the provisions of the Act and the rules made thereunder in so far as the 
provisions are applicable to him as principal employer in respect of the 
employment of contract labour by the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every such application 
shall be either personally delivered to the licensing officer or sent to him by 
registered post.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> On receipt of the 
application referred to in sub-rule (1), the licensing officer shall, after 
noting thereon the date of receipt of the application, grant an acknowledgment 
to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Every application 
referred to in sub-rule (1) shall also be accompanied by a 

1[demand draft] 
showing—
 <subsection>
          <number>i</number>  the deposit 
of the security at the rates specified in rule 24, and
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>ii</number>  the payment 
of the fees at the rates specified in rule 26.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>22</number> Matters to be taken 
into account in granting or refusing a licence.—In 
granting or refusing to grant a licence, the licensing officer shall take the 
following matter into account, namely:—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  whether the 
applicant—
 <subsection>
               <number>i</number>  is a 
minor, or
 </subsection><subsection>
              <number>ii</number>  is of 
unsound mind and stands so declared by a competent court; or
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iii</number>  is an 
undischarged insolvent, or
 </subsection><subsection>
             <number>iv</number>  has 
been convicted (at any time during a period of five years immediately preceding 
the date of application) of an offence which, in the opinion of the Central 
Government, involves moral turpitude;
 </subsection></section><section>
         <number>b</number>  whether 
there is an order of the appropriate Government or an award or settlement for 
the abolition of contract labour in respect of the particular type of work in 
the establishment for which the applicant is a contractor;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  whether any 
order has been made in respect of the applicant under sub-section (1) of section 
14, and, if so, whether a period of three years has elapsed from the date of 
that order;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  whether the 
fees for the application have been deposited at the rate specified in rule 26; 
and
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  whether 
security has been deposited by the applicant at the rates specified in rule 24.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>23</number> Refusal to grant 
licence.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
On receipt of the application from the contractor, and as soon as possible 
thereafter, the licensing officer shall investigate or cause investigation to be 
made to satisfy himself about the correctness of the facts and particulars 
furnished in such application and the eligibility of the applicant for a licence.]
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) Where the 
licensing officer is of opinion that the licence should not be granted, he 
shall, after affording reasonable opportunity to the applicant to be heard, make 
an order rejecting the application.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The order shall 
record the reasons for the refusal and shall be communicated to the applicant.
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

  
 <article><title><number>24</number> Security </title>.—
<section><number>1</number> Before a licence is issued, an amount 
calculated at the rate of Rs. <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[90] for each of the workman to be 
employed as contract labour, in respect of which the application for licence has 
been made, shall be deposited by the contractor for due performance of the 
conditions of the licence and compliance with the provisions of the Act or the 
rules made thereunder: 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>[Provided that where the contractor is a co-operative society, 
the amount deposited as security shall be at the rate of <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>[Rs. 15] 
for each other of the workmen to be employed as a contract labour.] 
 </section><section><footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[<number>1A</number> Where the applicant for the licence was holding a licence 
in regard to another work and that licences had expired, the licensing officer, 
if he is of the view that any amount out of the security deposited in respect of 
that licence is to be directed to be refunded to the applicant under rule 31, 
may, on an application made for that purpose in Form VA by the applicant adjust 
the amount so to be refunded towards the security required to be deposited in 
respect of the application for the new licence and the applicant need deposit, 
in such a case, only the balance amount, if any, after making such adjustment.] 

 </section><section><number>2</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>[The amount of security, or the balance amount, required to 
be deposited under sub-rule (1) or, as the case may be, under sub-rule (1A)] 
shall be paid in the local treasury under the Head of Account “Section 
T—Deposits &amp; Advances—Part II Deposits bearing interest—(c) Other Deposit 
Accounts—Departmental and Judicial Deposits—Civil Deposits—Deposits, under 
Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 (Central).” 




</section></article> 

  
  
 <article><title><number>25</number> Forms and terms and conditions of licence </title>.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
licence granted under sub-section (1) of section 12 shall be in Form VI. 
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every licence granted under sub-rule (1) or renewed under rule 29 shall 
be subject to the following conditions, namely:— 
 
 <subsection><number>i</number> the licence shall be non-transferable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number> the number of workmen employed as contract labour in the establishment 
  shall not, on any day, exceed the maximum number specified in the licence; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>iii</number> save as provided in these rules, the fees paid for the grant, or as 
  the case may be, for renewal of the licence shall be non-refundable; 
 </subsection><subsection><number>iv</number> the rates of wages payable to the workmen by the contractor shall not 
  be less than the rates prescribed under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 
  1948), for such employment where applicable and where the rates have been 
  fixed by agreement, settlement or award, not less than the rates so fixed; 

 </subsection><subsection><number>v</number> (a) in cases where the workman employed by the contractor perform the 
  same or similar kind of work as the workmen directly employed by the principal 
  employer of the establishment, the wage rates, holidays, hours of work and 
  other conditions of service of the workmen of the contractor shall be the same 
  as applicable to the workmen directly employed by the principal employer of 
  the establishment on the same or similar kind of work: </subsection>
 Provided that in the case of any disagreement with regard to the type of work 
the same shall be decided by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[the Deputy Chief Labour Commissioner 
(Central)] <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>[***]; 
 
 
 <subsection><number>b</number> in other cases the wage rates, holidays, hours of work and conditions 
    of service of the workmen of the contractor shall be such as may be 
    specified in this behalf by <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[the Deputy Chief Labour 
    Commissioner (Central)]; </subsection>
 Explanation .—While determining the wage rates, holidays, hours of 
work and other conditions of services under (b) above, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum>[the Deputy 
Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) shall have due regard to the wage rates, 
holidays, hours of work and other conditions of service obtaining in similar 
employments; 
 
 <subsection><number>vi</number> (a) in every establishment where twenty or more women are ordinarily 
  employed as contract labour, there shall be provided two rooms of reasonable 
  dimensions for the use of their children under the age of six years, 
 
 <subsubsection><number>b</number> one of such rooms shall be used as a play room for the children and 
    the other as bed room for the children, 
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>c</number> the contractor shall supply adequate number of toys and games in the 
    play room and sufficient number of cots and beddings in the sleeping room, 
    (d) the standard of construction and maintenance of the creches shall be 
    such as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief Labour Commissioner 
    (Central); </subsubsection>
 </subsection><subsection><number>vii</number> the licensee shall notify any change in the number of workmen or the 
  conditions of work to the licensing officer; </subsection>
 <subsection><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>[<number>viii</number> the licensee shall, within fifteen days of the 
commencement and completion of each contract work submit a return to the 
Inspector, appointed under section 28 of the Act intimating the actual date of 
the commencement or, as the case may be, completion of such contract work in 
Form VIA;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>7</footcitenum>[<number>ix</number> a copy of the licence shall be displayed prominently at the 
premises where the contract work is being carried on;] 
 </subsection><subsection><footcitenum>8</footcitenum>[<number>x</number> no female contract labour shall be employed by any 
contractor before 6.00 a.m. or after 7.00 p.m.: 
 Provided that this clause shall not apply to the employment of women in 
pithead baths, creches and canteens and so to midwives and nurses in hospitals 
and dispensaries.] 






</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>26</number> Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The fees to be paid for the grant of a certificate of registration under section 
7 shall be as specified below:—
 
If the number of workmen 
proposed to be employed on contract on any day:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> is 
20                                                                                     
Rs. 60
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> exceeds 20 but does 
not exceed 50                                            Rs. 150
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> exceeds 50 but does 
not exceed 100                                          Rs. 300
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> exceeds 100 but does 
not exceed 200                                        Rs. 600
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> exceeds 200 but does 
not exceed 400                                        Rs. 1200
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> exceeds 
400                                                                           Rs. 
1500
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The fees to be paid 
for the grant of a licence under section 12 shall be as specified below:
 
If the number of workmen 
employed by the contractor on any day—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number> is 20 
                                                                                    
Rs. 15
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> exceeds 20 but does 
not exceed 50                                            Rs. 37.50
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> exceeds 50 but does 
not exceed 100                                          Rs. 75 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> exceeds 100 but does 
not exceed 200                                         Rs. 150
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number> exceeds 200 but does 
not exceed 400                                         Rs. 300 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number> 
 
exceeds 400                                                                            Rs. 375.]
 
 



</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>27</number> Validity of the 
licence.—Every 
licence granted under rule 25 or renewed under rule 29 shall remain in force for 
twelve months from the date it is granted or renewed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>28</number> Amendment of the 
licence.—
<section><number>1</number> A 
licence issued under rule 25 or renewed under rule 29 may, for good and 
sufficient reasons, be amended by the Licensing Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The contractor who 
desires to have the licence amended shall submit to the licensing officer an 
application stating the nature of the amendment and reasons therefor.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) If the licensing 
officer allows the application he shall require the applicant to furnish a


1[demand draft] for 
the amount, if any, by which the fees that would have been payable if the 
licence had been originally issued in the amended form exceeds the fees 
originally paid for the licence.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> On the applicant 
furnishing the requisite 

1[demand draft] the 
licence shall be amended according to the orders of the licensing officer.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Where the application 
for amendment is refused, the licensing officer shall record the reasons for 
such refusal and communicate the same to the applicant.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>29</number> Renewal of licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Every contractor shall apply to the licensing officer for renewal of the licence.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every such application 
shall be in Form VII in triplicate and shall be made not less than thirty days 
before the date on which the licence expires, and if the application is so made, 
the licence shall be deemed to have been renewed until such date when the 
renewed licence is issued.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The fees chargeable 
for renewal of the licence shall be the same as for the grant thereof:
 
Provided that if the 
application for renewal is not received within the time specified in sub-rule 
(2), a fee of 25 per cent. in excess of the fee ordinarily payable for the 
licence shall be payable for such renewal:
 
Provided further that in 
case where the licensing officer is satisfied that the delay in submission of 
the application is due to unavoidable circumstances beyond the control of the 
contractor, he may reduce or remit as he thinks fit the payment of such excess 
fee.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>30</number> Issue of duplicate 
certificate of registration or licence.—Where 
a certificate of registration or a licence granted or renewed under the 
preceding rules has been lost, defaced or accidentally destroyed, a duplicate 
may be granted on payment of fees of rupees five.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>31</number> Refund of security.—
<section><number>1</number> 
(i) On expiry of the period of licence the contractor may, if he does not intend 
to have his licence renewed, make an application to the licensing officer for 
the refund of the security deposited by him under rule 24.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> If the Licensing 
Officer is satisfied that there is no breach of the conditions of licence or 
there is no order under section 14 for the forfeiture of security or any portion 
thereof, he shall direct the refund of the security to the applicant.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> If there is any order 
directing the forfeiture of any portion of the security, the amount to be 
forfeited shall be deducted from the security deposit, and balance, if any, 
refunded to the applicant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Any application for 
refund shall, as far as possible, be disposed of within 60 days of the receipt 
of the application.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>32</number> Grant of temporary 
certificate of registration and licence.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where conditions arise in an establishment requiring the employment of contract 
labour immediately and such employment is estimated to last for not more than 
fifteen days, the Principal Employer of the establishment or the contractor, as 
the case may be, may apply for a temporary certificate of registration or 
licence to the Registering Officer or the Licensing Officer, as the case may be, 
having jurisdiction over the area in which the establishment is situated.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The application for 
such temporary certificate of registration or licence shall be made in 
triplicate in Forms VIII and X respectively and shall be accompanied by a 

1[demand draft 
drawn in favour of the Pay and Accounts Officer, Office of the Chief Labour 
Commissioner (Central) New Delhi] showing payment of appropriate fees and in the 
case of licence the appropriate amount of security also.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> On receipt of the 
application, complete in all respects, and on being satisfied either on 
affidavit by the applicant or otherwise that the work in respect of which the 
application has been made would be finished in a period of fifteen days and was 
of a nature which could not but be carried out immediately, the Registering 
Officer or the Licensing Officer, as the case may be, shall forthwith grant a 
certificate of registration in Form IX or a Licence in Form XI, as the case may 
be, for a period of not more than fifteen days.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Where a certificate of 
registration or licence is not granted, the reasons therefor shall be recorded 
by the Registering Officer or the Licensing Officer, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> On the expiry of the 
validity of the registration certificate the establishment shall cease to employ 
in the establishment contract labour in respect of which the certificate was 
given.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The fees to be paid 
for the grant of the certificate of registration under sub-rule (3) shall be as 
specified below:
 
If the number of workmen 
proposed to be employed on contract on any day—
 <subsection>

                                                                                         
<number>Rs</number>
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number> exceeds 20 but does 
not exceed 50                                 

2[30.00]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number> exceeds 50 but does 
not exceed 200                               

2[60.00]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number> exceeds 200 
                                                               

2[90.00]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>7</number> The fees to be paid 
for the grant of a licence under sub-rule (3) shall be specified below:
 
If the number of workmen 
to be employed by the contractor on any day—
 <subsection>

                                                                                         
<number>Rs</number>
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number> exceeds 20 but does 
not exceed 50                                 

2[15.00]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number> exceeds 50 but does 
not exceed 200                               

2[60.00]
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number> exceeds 200 
                                                               

2[90.00]
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>8</number> The provision of rule 
23 and rule 24 shall apply to the refusal to grant licence or to grant licence 
under sub-rule (4) and sub-rule (3) respectively.
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>33</number> 

<section><number>1</number> (i) Every appeal under sub-section (1) of section 15 shall be preferred in 
the form of a memorandum signed by the appellant or his authorised agent and 
presented to the Appellate Officer in person or sent to him by registered post.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The memorandum shall 
be accompanied by a certified copy of the order appealed from and a 

1[demand draft] for 
rupees 10.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The memorandum shall 
set forth concisely and under distinct heads the grounds of appeal to the order 
appealed from.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>34</number> 

<section><number>1</number> Where the memorandum of appeal does not comply with the provisions of 
sub-rule (2) of rule 33 it may be rejected or returned to appellant for the 
purpose of being amended within a time to be fixed by the Appellate Officer.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where the Appellate 
Officer rejects the memorandum under sub-rule (1) he shall record the reason for 
such rejection, and communicate the order to the appellant.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Where the memorandum 
of appeal is in order the Appellate Officer shall admit the appeal, endorse 
thereon the date of presentation and shall register the appeal in a book to be 
kept for the purpose called the Register of Appeals.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> (i) When the appeal 
has been admitted, the Appellate Officer shall send the notice of the appeal to 
the Registering Officer or the Licensing Officer as the case may be, from whose 
order the appeal has been preferred and the Registering Officer or the Licensing 
Officer shall send the record of the case to the Appellate Officer.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> On receipt of the 
record, the Appellate Officer shall send a notice to the appellant to appear 
before him at such date and time as may be specified in the notice for the 
hearing of the appeal.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>35</number> 
If on the date fixed for hearing, the appellant does not appear, the Appellate 
Officer may dismiss the appeal for default of appearance of the appellant.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>36</number> 

<section><number>i</number> Where an appeal has been dismissed under rule 35 the appellant may apply to 
the Appellate Officer for the re-admission of the appeal, and where it is proved 
that he was prevented by any sufficient cause from appearing when the appeal was 
called on for hearing, the Appellate Officer shall restore the appeal on its 
original number.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> Such an application 
shall, unless the Appellate Officer extends the time for sufficient reason, be 
made within 30 days of the date of dismissal.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>37</number> 

<section><number>1</number> If the appellant is present when the appeal is called on for the hearing, 
the Appellate Officer shall proceed to hear the appellant or his authorised 
agent and any other person summoned by him for this purpose, and pronounce 
judgment on the appeal, either confirming, reversing or varying the order 
appealed from.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The judgment of the 
Appellate Officer shall state the points for determination, the decisions 
thereon and the reasons for the decisions.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The order shall be 
communicated to the appellant and copy thereof shall be sent to the Registering 
Officer of the Licensing Officer from whose order the appeal has been preferred.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>

1[<number>38</number> Payment of 
Fees.—
<section><number>1</number> All amounts of money payable on account of security deposit, 
registration fees, licence fee, appeal, supply of duplicate copies of 
registration certificates and in terms of any other provisions of the Act and 
rules shall be paid through a crossed demand draft drawn in favour of the 
officers as shown in Annexure ‘A’ and made payable at branch of the Union Bank 
of India at the headquarters of the officers specified in column (3) of the said 
Annexure. All such demand drafts shall be accompanied by a challan in form No. 
TR-6 (in triplicate) indicating the details of payments, etc.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The Licensing Officer, 
the Registering Officer or the Appellate Authority, as the case may be on 
receipt of the demand draft from the party shall arrange to deposit the amount 
in the appropriate account in the Bank with which he, in his capacity as 
Regional Labour Commissioner/Assistant Labour Commissioner (Central) as Drawing 
and Disbursing Officer is in account. The Assistant Labour Commissioner 
(Central), Delhi shall deposit the demand draft in the Union Bank of India, 
Extension Counter, Shram Shakti Bhawan, Rafi Marg, New Delhi in the Account of 
‘Pay and Accounts Officer’ Chief Labour Commissioner, New Delhi.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The payments received 
by the officers specified in the said Annexure by way of demand drafts shall be 
deposited in the relevant heads of accounts as shown below:—
 
              Registration 
fees—“087—Labour and Employment—Fees under Contract Labour (Regulation and 
Abolition) Central Rules, 1971 (adjustable in the books of the Pay and Accounts 
Officer, (Chief Labour Commissioner), Ministry of Labour, New Delhi”.
 
              Licensing 
fees—“087—Labour Employment—Fees under the Contract Labour (Regulation and 
Abolition) Central Rules, 1971 (adjustable in the books of the Pay and Accounts 
Officer, (Chief Labour Commissioner), Ministry of Labour, New Delhi”;
 
              Security 
deposits—Deposits and Advance(—) deposits not bearing interest 843—Civil 
Deposits under Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 (adjustable 
in the books of the Pay and Accounts Officer Chief Labour Commissioner) Ministry 
of Labour, New Delhi”.
 
              Duplicate 
copy of the Registration Certificates.—“087—Labour and Employment Fee under 
Contract Labour Appeals (Regulation and Abolition) Central Rules, 1971”].
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>39</number> Copies.—Copy 
of the order of the Registering Officer, Licensing Officer or the Appellate 
Officer may be obtained on payment of fees of rupees two for each order on 
application specifying the date and other particulars of the order, made to the 
officer concerned.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>40</number> 

<section><number>1</number> The facilities required to be provided under sections 18 and 19 of the Act, 
namely sufficient supply of wholesome drinking water, a sufficient number of 
latrines and urinals, washing facilities and first-aid facilities shall be 
provided by the contractor in the case of the existing establishments within 
seven days of the commencement of these rules and in the case of new 
establishments within seven days of the commencement of the employment of 
contract labour therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If any of the facility 
mentioned in sub-rule (1) is not provided by the contractor within the period 
prescribed the same shall be provided by the principal employer within seven 
days of the expiry of the period laid down in the said sub-rule.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>41</number> Rest Rooms.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every place wherein contract labour is required to halt at night in 
connection with the working of the establishment to which the Act applies and in 
which employment of contract labour is likely to continue for 3 months or more, 
the contractor shall provide and maintain rest rooms or other suitable 
alternative accommodation within fifteen days of the coming into force of the 
rules in the case of existing establishments, and within fifteen days of the 
commencement of the employment of contract labour in new establishments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the amenity 
referred to in sub-rule (1) is not provided by the contractor within the period 
prescribed the principal employer shall provide the same within a period of 
fifteen days of the expiry of the period laid down in the said sub-rule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Separate rooms shall 
be provided for women employees.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Effective and suitable 
provision shall be made in every room for securing and maintaining adequate 
ventilation by the circulation of fresh air and there shall also be provided and 
maintained sufficient and suitable natural or artificial lighting.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> The rest-room or rooms 
or other suitable alternative accommodation shall be of such dimensions so as to 
provide at least a floor area 1.1 sq. metre for each person making use of the 
rest room.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The rest-room or rooms 
or other suitable alternative accommodation shall be so constructed as to afford 
adequate protection against heat, wind, rain and shall have smooth, hard and 
impervious floor surface.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> The rest-room or other 
suitable alternative accommodation shall be at a convenient distance from the 
establishment and shall have adequate supply of wholesome drinking water.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>42</number> Canteens.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every establishment to which the Act applies and wherein work regarding the 
employment of contract labour is likely to continue for six months and wherein 
contract labour numbering one hundred or more are ordinarily employed an 
adequate canteen shall be provided by the contractor for the use of such 
contract labour within sixty days of the date of coming into force of the rules 
in the case of the existing establishments and within 60 days of the 
commencement of the employment of contract labour in the case of new 
establishments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the contractor 
fails to provide the canteen within the time laid down the same shall be 
provided by the principal employer within sixty days of the expiry of the time 
allowed to the contractor.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The canteen shall be 
maintained by the contractor or principal employer, as the case may be, in an 
efficient manner.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>43</number> 

<section><number>1</number> The canteen shall consist of at least a dining hall, kitchen, store room, 
pantry and washing places separately for workers and for utensils.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) The canteen shall 
be sufficiently lighted at all times when any person has access to it.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The floor shall be 
made of smooth and impervious material and inside walls shall be lime washed or 
colour-washed at least once in each year:
 
Provided that the inside 
walls of the kitchen shall be lime-washed every four months.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) The precincts of 
the canteen shall be maintained and in a clean and sanitary condition.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Waste water shall be 
carried away in suitable covered drains and shall not be allowed to accumulate 
so as to cause a nuisance.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> Suitable 
arrangements shall be made for the collection and disposal of garbage.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>44</number> 

<section><number>1</number> The dining hall shall accommodate at a time at least 30 per cent. of the 
contract labour working at a time.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The floor area of the 
dining hall, excluding the area occupied by the service counter and any 
furniture except tables and chairs shall be not less than one square metre per 
diner to be accommodated as prescribed in sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> (i) A portion of the 
dining hall and service counter shall be partitioned off and reserved for women 
workers, in proportion to their number.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Washing places for 
women shall be separate and screened to secure privacy.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> Sufficient tables, 
stools, chairs or benches shall be available for the number of diners to be 
accommodated as prescribed in sub-rule (1).
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>45</number> 

<section><number>1</number> (i) There shall be provided and maintained sufficient utensils, crockery, 
cutlery, furniture and any other equipment necessary for the efficient running 
of the canteen.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The furniture, 
utensils and other equipment shall be maintained in a clean and hygienic 
condition.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) Suitable clean 
clothes for the employees serving in the canteen shall also be provided and 
maintained.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> A service counter, if 
provided, shall have top of smooth and impervious material.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number> Suitable facilities 
including an adequate supply of hot water shall be provided for the cleaning of 
utensils and equipment.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>46</number> 
The foodstuffs and other items to be served in the canteen shall be in 
conformity with the normal habits of the contract labour.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>47</number> 
The charges for foodstuffs, beverages and any other items served in the canteen 
shall be based on ‘no-profit, no loss’ and shall be conspicuously displayed in 
the canteen.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>48</number> 
In arriving at the prices of foodstuffs and other articles served in the canteen 
the following items shall not be taken into consideration as expenditure 
namely:—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  the rent for 
the land and building;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  the 
depreciation and maintenance charges for the building and equipment provided for 
in the canteen;
 </section><section>
         <number>c</number>  the cost of 
purchase, repairs and replacement of equipments including furniture, crockery, 
cutlery and utensils;
 </section><section>
         <number>d</number>  the water 
charges and other charges incurred for lighting and ventilation;
 </section><section>
         <number>e</number>  the interest 
on the amounts spent on the provision and maintenance of furniture and equipment 
provided for in the canteen.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>49</number> 
The books of accounts and registers and other documents used in connection with 
the running of the canteen shall be produced on demand to an Inspector.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>50</number> 
The accounts pertaining to the canteen shall be audited once every 12 months by 
registered accountants and auditors:
 
Provided that the Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central) may approve of any other person to audit the 
accounts, if he is satisfied that it is not feasible to appoint a registered 
accountant and auditor in view of the site or the location of the canteen.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>51</number> Latrines and 
Urinals.—Latrines 
shall be provided in every establishment coming within the scope of the Act on 
the following scale, namely:—
 <section>
         <number>a</number>  where 
females are employed, there shall be at least one latrine for every 25 females;
 </section><section>
         <number>b</number>  where males 
are employed, there shall be at least one latrine for every 25 males;
 
Provided that where the 
number of males or females exceeds 100, it shall be sufficient if there is one 
latrine for every 25 males or females, as the case may be, upto the first 100, 
and one for every 50 thereafter.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>52</number> 
Every latrine shall be under cover and so partitioned off as to secure privacy, 
and shall have a proper door and fastenings.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>53</number> 

<section><number>1</number> Where workers of both sexes are employed there shall be displayed outside 
each block of latrine and urinal a notice in the language understood by the 
majority of the workers “For Men only” or “For Women only” as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The notice shall also 
bear the figure of a man or of a woman, as the case may be.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>54</number> 
There shall be at least one urinal for male workers upto 50 and one for female 
workers upto fifty employed at a time:
 
Provided that where the 
number of male or female workmen, as the case may be, exceeds 500 it shall be 
sufficient if there is one urinal for every 50 males or females upto the first 
500 and one for every 100 or part thereof thereafter.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>55</number> 

<section><number>1</number> The latrines and urinals shall be conveniently situated and accessible to 
workers at all times at the establishment.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> (i) The latrines and 
urinals shall be adequately lighted and shall be maintained in a clean and 
sanitary condition at all times.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> Latrines and urinals 
other than those connected with a flush sewage system shall comply with the 
requirements of the public health authorities.
</subsection></section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>56</number> 
Water shall be provided by the means of tap or otherwise so as to be 
conveniently accessible in or near the latrine and urinals.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>57</number> Washing Facilities.—
<section><number>1</number> 
In every establishment coming within the scope of the Act adequate and suitable 
facilities for washing shall be provided and maintained for the use of contract 
labour employed therein.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Separate and adequate 
screening facilities shall be provided for the use of male and female workers.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Such facilities shall 
be conveniently accessible and shall be kept in clean and hygienic condition.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>58</number> First-Aid 
Facilities.—In 
every establishment coming within the scope of the Act there shall be provided 
and maintained so, as to be readily accessible during all working hours 
first-aid boxes at the rate of not less than one box for 150 contract labour or 
part thereof ordinarily employed.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>59</number> 

<section><number>1</number> The first-aid box shall be distinctively marked with a red cross on a white 
ground and shall contain the following equipment, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>A</number> For establishments in 
which the number of contract labour employed does not exceed fifty—
 
Each first-aid box shall 
contain the following equipment:—
 <subsubsection>
          <number>i</number>  6 small 
sterilized dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>ii</number>  3 medium 
size sterilized dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>iii</number>  3 large 
size sterilized dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>iv</number>  3 large 
sterilized burn dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>v</number>  1 (30 ml.) 
bottle containing a two per cent. alcohol solution of iodine.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>vi</number>  1 (30 ml.) 
bottle containing salvolatile having the dose and mode of administration 
indicated on the label.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>vii</number>  1 
snake-bite lancet.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>viii</number>  1 (30 gms.) 
bottle of potassium permanganate crystals.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ix</number>  1 pair 
scissors.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>x</number>  1 copy of 
the first-aid leaflet issued by the Director General, Factory Advice Service and 
Labour Institutes, Government of India.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>xi</number>  A bottle 
containing 100 tablets (each of 5 grains) of aspirin.
 <subsubsubsection>
        <number>xii</number>  Ointment 
for burns.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>xiii</number>  A bottle of 
suitable surgical anti-septic solution.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>B</number> For establishments in 
which the number of contract labour exceed fifty—
 
Each first-aid box shall 
contain the following equipment:—
 <subsubsection>
          <number>i</number>  12 small 
sterilized dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>ii</number>  6 medium 
size sterilized dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>iii</number>  6 large 
size sterilized dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>iv</number>  6 large size 
sterilized burn dressings.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>v</number>  6 (15 gms.) 
packets sterilized cotton wool.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>vi</number>  1 (60 ml.) 
bottle containing a two per cent alcohol solution of iodine.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>vii</number>  1 (60 ml.) 
bottle containing salvolatile having the dose and mode of administration 
indicated on the label.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
       <number>viii</number>  1 roll of 
adhesive plaster.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>ix</number>  A snake-bite 
lancet.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>x</number>  1 (30 gms.) 
bottle of potassium permanganate crystals.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
        <number>xi</number>  1 pair 
scissors.
 <subsubsubsection>
        <number>xii</number>  1 copy of 
the first-aid leaflet issued by the Director General, Factory Advice Service and 
Labour Institutes, Government of India.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>xiii</number>  A bottle 
containing 100 tablets (each of 5 grains) of aspirin.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>xiv</number>  Ointment for 
burns.
 </subsubsubsection><subsubsubsection>
       <number>xv</number>  A bottle of a 
suitable surgical anti-septic solution.
 </subsubsubsection></subsubsection></subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Adequate arrangement 
shall be made for immediate recoupment of the equipment when necessary.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>60</number> 
Nothing except the prescribed contents shall be kept in the First-Aid Box.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>61</number> 
The First-Aid Box shall be kept in charge of a responsible person who shall 
always be readily available during the working hours of the establishment.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>62</number> 
A person incharge of the First-Aid Box shall be a person trained in First-Aid 
treatment, in establishment where the number of contract labour employed is 150 
or more.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>63</number> 
The contractor shall fix wage periods in respect of which wages shall be 
payable.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>64</number> 
No wage period shall exceed one month.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>65</number> 
The wages of every person employed as contract labour in an establishment or by 
a contractor where less than one thousand such persons are employed shall be 
paid before the expiry of the seventh day and in other cases before the expiry 
of tenth day after the last day of the wage period in respect of which the wages 
are payable.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>66</number> 
Where the employment of any worker is terminated by or on behalf of the 
contractor the wages earned by him shall be paid before the expiry of the second 
working day from the day on which his employment is terminated.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>67</number> 
All payments of wages shall be made on a working day at the work premises and 
during the working time and on a date notified in advance and in case the work 
is completed before the expiry of the wage period, final payment shall be made 
within 48 hours of the last working day.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>68</number> 
Wages due to every worker shall be paid to him or to other person authorised by 
him in this behalf.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>69</number> 
All wages shall be paid in current coin or currency or in both.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>70</number> 
Wages shall be paid without any deductions of any kind except those specified by 
the Central Government by general or special order in this behalf or permissible 
under the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>71</number> 
A notice showing the wage period and the place and time of disbursement of wages 
shall be displayed at the place of work and a copy sent by the contractor to the 
principal employer under acknowledgement.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>72</number> 
The principal employer shall ensure the presence of his authorised 
representative at the place and time of disbursement of wages by the contractor 
to workmen and it shall be the duty of the contractor to ensure the disbursement 
of wages in the presence of such authorised representative.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>73</number> 
The authorised representative of the principal employer shall record under his 
signature a certificate at the end of the entries in the Register of Wages or 
the 

1[Register of 
Wages-cum-Muster Roll] as the case may be, in the following form:
 
              “Certified 
that the amount shown in column No. ... has been paid to the workman concerned 
in my presence on ..... at .....”
 
 



</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>74</number> Register of 
contractors.—Every 
principal employer shall maintain in respect of each registered establishment a 
register of contractors in Form XII.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>75</number> Register of persons 
employed.—Every 
contractor shall maintain in respect of each registered establishment where he 
employs contract labour a register in Form XIII.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>76</number> Employment Card.—
<section><number>i</number> 
Every contractor shall issue an employment card in Form XIV to each worker 
within three days of the employment of the worker.
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number> The card shall be 
maintained upto date and any change in the particulars shall be entered therein.
</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>77</number> Service 
Certificate.—On 
termination of employment for any reason whatsoever the contractor shall issue 
to the workman whose services have been terminated a Service Certificate in Form 
XV.
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>78</number> Muster Roll, Wages 
Registers, Deduction Register and Overtime Register.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 

<subsection><number>a</number> Every contractor shall in respect of each work on which he engages contract 
labour,—
 <subsubsection>
          <number>i</number>  maintain a 
Muster Roll and a Register of Wages in Form XVI and Form XVII respectively:
 
                 Provided 
that a combined Register of Wage-cum-Muster Roll in Form XVIII shall be 
maintained by the contractor where the wage period is a Fortnight or less;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>ii</number>  maintain a 
Register of Deduction for damage or loss, Register of Fines and Register of 
Advances in Form XX, Form XXI and Form XXII respectively;
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
         <number>iii</number>  maintain a 
Register of Overtime in Form XXIII recording therein the number of hours of, and 
wages paid for, overtime work, if any;
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number> Every contractor 
shall, where the wage period is one week or more, issue wage slips in Form XIX, 
to the workmen at least a day prior to the disbursement of wages;
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number> Every contractor shall 
obtain the signature or thumb impression of the worker concerned against the 
entries relating to him on the Register of Wages or Muster Roll-cum-Wages 
Register, as the case may be, and the entries shall be authenticated by the 
initials of the contractor or his authorised representative and shall also be 
duly certified by the authorised representative of the principal employer in the 
manner provided in rule 73.
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number> In respect of 
establishments which are governed by the Payment of Wages Act, 1936 (4 of 1936) 
and the rules made thereunder, or Minimum Wages Act, 1948 (11 of 1948) or the 
rules made thereunder, the following registers and records required to be 
maintained by a contractor as employer under those Acts and the rules made 
thereunder shall be deemed to be register and records to be maintained by the 
contractor under these rules, namely:—
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>a</number>  Muster Roll;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>b</number>  Register of 
Wages;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>c</number>  Register of 
Deductions;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>d</number>  Register of 
Overtime;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>e</number>  Register of 
Fines;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>f</number>  Register of 
Advances;
 </subsection><subsection>
         <number>g</number>  Wage slip;
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> Notwithstanding 
anything contained in these rules, where a combined or alternative form is 
sought to be used by the contractor to avoid duplication of work for compliance 
with the provisions of any other Act or the rules framed thereunder for any 
other laws or regulation or in cases where mechanised pay rolls are introduced 
for better administration, alternative suitable form or forms in lieu of any of 
the forms prescribed under these rules, may be used with the previous approval 
of the 

2[Regional Labour 
Commissioner (Central)].
 
 




</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>79</number> 
Every contractor shall display an abstract of the Act and rules in English and 
Hindi and in the language spoken by the majority of workers in such form as may 
be approved by the Chief Labour Commissioner (Central).
</article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>80</number> 

<section><number>1</number> All registers and other records required to be maintained under the Act and 
rules, shall be maintained complete and up-to-date, and, unless otherwise 
provided for, shall be kept at an officer or the nearest convenient building 
within the precincts of the workplace or at a place within a radius of three 
kilometres.
 

1[(2) Such 
registers shall be maintained legibly in English and Hindi or in the language 
understood by the majority of the persons employed in the establishment.]
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> All the registers and 
other records shall be preserved in original for a period of three calendar 
years from the date of last entry therein.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> All the registers, 
records and notices maintained under the Act or rules shall be produced on 
demand before the Inspector or any other authority under the Act or any person 
authorised in that behalf by the Central Government.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Where no deduction or 
fine has been imposed or no overtime has been worked during any wage period, a 
‘nil’ entry shall be made across the body of the register at the end of the wage 
period indicating also in precise terms the wage period to which the ‘nil’ entry 
relates, in the respective registers maintained in Forms XX, XXI, and XXIII 
respectively.
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>81</number> 

<section><number>1</number> (i) Notices showing the rates of wages, hours of work, wage period, dates of 
payment of wages, names and addresses of the Inspectors having jurisdiction, and 
date of payment of unpaid wages, shall be displayed in English and in Hindi and 
in the local language understood by the majority of the workman in conspicuous 
places at the establishment and the work-site by the principal employer or the 
contractor, as the case may be.
 <subsection>
<number>ii</number> The notices shall be 
correctly maintained in a clean and legible condition.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A copy of the notice 
shall be sent to the Inspector and whenever any changes occur the same shall be 
communicated to him forthwith.
 

1[(3) Every 
principal employer shall, within fifteen days of the commencement or completion 
of each contract work under each contractor, submit a return to the Inspector, 
appointed under section 28 of the Act, intimating the actual dates of the 
commencement or, as the case may be, completion of such contract work, in Form 
VI B.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>82</number> 

<section><number>1</number> Every contractor shall send half yearly return in Form XXIV (in duplicate) 
so as to reach the Licensing Officer concerned not later than 30 days from the 
close of the half year.
 
Note.—Half 
year for the purpose of this rule means “a period of 6 months commencing from 
1st January and 1st July of every year”.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Every principal 
employer of a registered establishment shall send annually a return in Form XXV 
(in duplicate) so as to reach the Registering Officer concerned not later than 
the 15th February following the end of the year to which it relates.
 

1[(3) The returns 
to be submitted under this rule by contractor/principal employer shall be 
correct, complete and up-to-date in all respects.]
 
 



</section></article> 

 
 
 <article>
<number>83</number> 

<section><number>1</number> The Board, Committee, 
Chief Labour Commissioner (Central) or the Inspector or any other authority 
under the Act shall have powers to call for any information or statistics in 
relation to contract labour from any contractor or principal employer at any 
time by an order in writing.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Any person called upon 
to furnish the information under sub-rule (1) shall be legally bound to do so.
 
 
</section></article><form>
 

THE CONTRACT LABOUR (REGULATION AND ABOLITION) 
RULES, 19711
 

FORM I 
 

[ SEE RULE 17(1)] 
 

APPLICATION FOR REGISTRATION OF ESTABLISHMENTS 
 
EMPLOYING CONTRACT LABOUR 
 

1. Name and location of the establishment 
 

2. Postal address of the establishment. 
 

3. Full name and address of the Principal Employer (furnish father's name in 
the case of individuals). 
 

4. Full name and address of the Manager or person responsible for the 
supervision and control of the establishment. 
 

5. Nature of work carried on in the establishment. 
 

6. Particulars of contractors and contract labour: 
 

(a) Names and Addresses of Contractors. 
 

(b) Nature of work in which contract labour is employed or is to be employed. 

 

(c) Maximum number of contract labour to be employed on any day through each 
contractor. 
 

2[(cc) Estimated date of commencement of each contract work under 
each contractor.] 
 

(d) Estimated date of termination of employment of contract labour under each 
contractor. 
 

3[7. Particular of demand draft enclosed (Name of the Union Bank, 
amount, demand draft No. and date).] 
 

I hereby declare that the particulars given above are true to the best of my 
knowledge and belief. 
 

Principal employer 
 

Seal and Stamp 
 

Office of the Registering 
 

Officer 
 

Date of receipt of 
 

application 
 

---------
 

1. V ide G.S.R. 191, published in the Gazette of India, 
Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 10th February, 1971.
 

2. Ins. by G.S.R. 199, dated 25th January, 1977.
 

3. Ins. by G.S.R. 657, dated 11th August, 1987. 
</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form X
 


[See 
rule 32(2)]
 




Application for Temporary Licence
 


     1.  Name and address 
of the contractor (including his father’s name in case of 
individuals).......................................... 
....................................................................................................................................................................................
 


     2.  Date of birth and 
age (in case of individuals).
 


     3.  Particulars of 
establishment where Contract Labour is to be employed:—
 


        (a)  Name and 
address of the establishment:
 


        (b)  Type of 
business, trade, industry, manufacture or occupation, which is carried on in the 
establishment:
 


        (c)  Name and 
address of the Principal Employer:
 


     4.  Particulars of 
contract labour:—
 


        (a)  Nature of work 
in which contract labour is to be employed in the establishment:
 


        (b)  Duration of 
the proposed contract work (give particulars of proposed date of commencing and 
ending):
 


        (c)  Name and 
address of the Agent or Manager of Contractor at the work-site:
 


        (d)  Maximum No. of 
contract labour proposed to be employed in the establishment on any day:
 


     5.  Whether the 
contractor was convicted of any offence within the preceding five years. If so, 
give details.
 


     6.  Whether there was 
any order against the contractor revoking or suspending licence or forfeiting 
security deposits in respect of an earlier contract. If so, the date of such 
order.
 


     7.  Whether the 
contractor has worked in any other establishment within the past five years. If 
so, give details of the Principal Employer, Establishment and nature of work.
 



1[8. Amount of 
licence fee paid—name of the Union Bank, demand draft No. and date.]
 



1[9. Amount of 
security deposit—name of the Union Bank, demand draft No. and date. Date of the 
receipt of the application with demand draft for fees/security deposits.]
 


I hereby declare that the 
particulars given above are true to the best of my knowledge and belief.
 


      Signature of the 
Applicant
 



Place....................                                                                                                                                               
(Contractor)
 


Date.....................
 


 


 
 


(To 
be filled in the office of the Licensing Officer)
 


Date of receipt of the 
application with challan for fees/Security Deposit.
 


Signature of the Licensing 
Office
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Subs. by G.S.R. 657, 
dated 11th August, 1987.
</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form XI
 


[See 
rule 32(3)]
 



Government of India
 




Office of the Licensing Officer
 


Licence No. ........... 
                                                          
Date ..............                                         
Fee paid Rs. ............
 


Signature of the Licensing 
Officer
 


Temporary Licence                                                                                           
Expires on ..............
 


Licence is hereby granted 
to ........... under section 12(2) of the Contract Labour (Regulation and 
Abolition) Act, 1970, subject to the conditions specified in Annexure.
 


The Licence shall remain in 
force till...................
 


Signature and Seal of the 
Licensing Officer
 


Date...................
 


 
 



ANNEXURE
 


The licence is subject to 
the following conditions:—
 


     1.  The licence shall 
be non-transferable.
 


     2.  The number of 
workmen employed as contract labour in the establishment shall not, on any day, 
exceed .............
 


     3.  Except as provided 
in the rules the fees paid for the grant, of the licence shall be 
non-refundable.
 


     4.  The rates of wages 
payable to the workmen by the contractor shall not be less than the rates 
prescribed for the Schedule of employment under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, 
where applicable, and where the rate have been fixed by agreement, settlement or 
award, not less than the rates fixed.
 


     5.  In case where the 
workmen employed by the contractor perform the same or similar kind or work as 
the workmen directly employed by the principal employer of the establishment, 
the wage rates, holidays, hours of work and other conditions of service of the 
workmen of the contractor shall be the same as applicable to the workmen 
directly employed by the principal employer of the establishment on the same or 
similar kind of work: Provided that in the case of any disagreement with regard 
to the type of work the same shall be decided by the 

1[Deputy Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central)] whose decision shall be final.
 


     6.  In other cases the 
wage rates, holidays, hours of work and conditions of service of the workmen of 
the contractor shall be such as may be specified in this behalf by the Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central).
 


 

2[7.  A copy of the 
licence shall be displayed prominently at the premises where the contract work 
is being carried on].
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
574(E), dated 30th June, 2000 (w.e.f. 30-6-2000).
 


   2. Ins. by G.S.R. 948, 
dated 12th July, 1978.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form XIV
 


(See 
rule 76)
 




Employment Card
 


Name and address of 
Contractor..................                                               Name and address of 
Establishment 
 



                                                                                                                     in/under which contract is 
carried
 



                                                                                                                     on........
 


Nature of work and location 
of work                                                             Name and address of Principal 
 
 


                                                                                                                      Employer 
............................................
 


1.  Name of the 
workman                                                                               
..............................................................
 


2.  S.No. in the register 
of workmen employed                                               ..............................................................
 


3.  Nature of 
employment/Designation                                                           
..............................................................
 


4.  Wage rate (with 
particulars of unit in case                                                
..............................................................
 


     of piece 
work,)                                                            
 


5.  Wage 
period                                                                                              ..............................................................
 


6.  Tenure of 
employment                                                                               .............................................................
 


7.  
Remarks                                                                                                     ..............................................................
 


Signature of Contractor
 


 
 



</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form XIX
 



1[See 
rule 78(1)(b)]
 




Wage Slip
 


Name and address of 
Contractor......................                                                                 
Name and Father’s/Husband’s
 



                                                                                                                                          
name of the workman..............
 


Name and location of work 
.............................                                                                  
For the Week/Fortnight/
 



                                                                                                                                          
Month ending...........................
 


1. No. of days 
worked                                                                                                       
………………………………………
 


2. No. of units worked in 
case of                                 
 


    piece rate 
workers                                                                                                        
………………………………………
 


3. Rate of daily 
wages/piece 
rate                                                                                      
………………………………………
 


4. Amount of overtime 
wages                                                                                            
………………………………………
 


5. Gross wages 
payable                                                                                                    
………………………………………
 


6. Deductions, if 
any                                                                                                          
………………………………………
 


7. Net amount of wages 
paid                                                                                            
………………………………………
 


 
 


Initials of the Contractor 
or his 
 


representative
 


 
 


—————
 


     1.   Subs. by G.S.R. 
948, dated 12th July, 1978.
 



 



</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form II
 


[See 
rule 18(1)]
 




Certificate of Registration
 



                                                                   
Date.......................
 



Government of India
 



Office of the Registering Officer
 


A Certificate of 
Registration containing the following particulars is hereby granted under 
sub-section (2) of section 7 of the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) 
Act, 1970, and the rules made thereunder, to 
......................................
 



.............................................................................................................................................................................................
 



.............................................................................................................................................................................................
 


     1.  Nature of work 
carried on in the establishment.
 


     2.  Names and 
Addresses of Contractors.
 


     3.  Nature of work in 
which contract labour is employed or is to be employed.
 


     4.  Maximum number of 
contract labour to be employed on any day through each contractor.
 


     5.  Other particulars 
relevant to the employment of contract labour.
 


 
 


Signature of Registering

 


Officer with Seal.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form XXIV
 


[See 
rule 82(1)]
 




Return to be sent by the Contractor to  

the Licensing Officer
 


      Half year ending 
....................................
 


1.   Name and address of 
Contractor 
 


2.   Name and address of 
Establishment 
 


3.   Name and address of 
Principal Employer
 


4.   Duration of contract: 
From ........ to...........
 


5.   No. of days during the 
half year on which—
 


(a) the establishment of 
the principal emp-      

loyer had worked
 


(b) the contractors’ 
establishment had wor-     

ked .......................
 


6.   Maximum number of 
contract labour employed            
 


      on any day during the 
half year:
 


      Men Women Children 
Total
 


7.   (i) Daily hours of 
work and spread over—-
 


      (ii) (a) Whether 
weekly holidays observed
 


       and on what day—-
 


       (b) If so, whether 
it was paid for—
 


      (iii) Number of man 
hours of overtime worked—
 


8.   Number of mandays 
worked by—
 


      Men Women Children 
Total
 


9.   Amount of wages paid
 


      Men Women Children 
Total
 


10. Amount of deductions 
from wages, if any:—
 


      Men Women Children 
Total
 


11. Whether the following 
have been provided—
 


(i)   Canteen
 


(ii)  Rest Rooms
 


(iii) Drinking water
 


(iv) Creches
 


(v)  First Aid
 


(If 
the answer is ‘yes’ state briefly standards provided)
 


 
 


Signature of Contractor
 


Place....................
 


Date.....................
 

 
</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form IV
 


[See 
rule 21(1)]
 




Application for Licence
 


     1.  Name and address 
of the contractor (including his father’s name in case of individuals).
 


     2.  Date of birth and 
age (in case of individuals).
 


     3.  Particulars of 
Establishment where contract labour is to be employed:—
 


        (a)  Name and 
address of the establishment;
 


        (b)  Type of 
business, trade, industry, manufacture or occupation, which is carried on in the 
establishment;
 


        (c)  Number and 
date of Certificate of Registration of the Establishment under the Act;
 


        (d)  Name and 
address of the Principal Employer.
 


     4.  Particulars of 
contract labour:—
 


        (a)  Nature of work 
in which contract labour is employed or is to be employed in the establishment:
 


        (b)  Duration of 
the proposed contract work (give particulars of proposed date of commencing and 
ending):
 


        (c)  Name and 
address of the Agent or Manager of Contractor at the worksite:
 


        (d)  Maximum No. of 
contract labour proposed to be employed in the establishment on any date:
 


     5.  Whether the 
contractor was convicted of any offence within the preceding five years. If so, 
give details.
 


     6.  Whether there was 
any order against the contractor revoking or suspending licence or forfeiting 
security deposits in respect of an earlier contract. If so, the date of such 
order.
 


     7.  Whether the 
contractor has worked in any other establishment within the past five years. If 
so, give details of the Principal Employer, Establishment and nature of work.
 


     8.  Whether a 
certificate by the Principal Employer in Form V is enclosed.
 



      1[9.  Amount 
of licence fee, name of the Union Bank, demand draft No. and date.]
 


   10.  Amount of security 
deposit, name of the Union Bank, demand draft No. and date.
 


Note.—The 
application shall be accompanied by demand draft and the challan for the 
appropriate amount and a certificate in Form V from the principal employer 
...... dated of the receipt of the application with ‘demand draft’ and the 
challan for fees/security deposit].
 


Declaration.—I 
hereby declare that the details given above are correct to the best of my 
knowledge and belief.
 



Place...............                                                                                                   Signature of the applicant (Contractor)
 


Date...............
 


 


Note.—The 
  application should be accompanied by a Treasury Receipt for the appropriate 
  amount and a certificate in Form V from the Principal Employer.
 


(To be filled in the office 
of the Licensing Officer)
 


Date of receipt of the 
application with challan for fees/Security Deposit.
 


Signature of the Licensing 
Officer
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 657, 
dated 11th August, 1987.
 


 
</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form V
 


[See 
rule 21(2)]
 




Form of Certificate by Principal Employer
 


Certified that I have 
engaged the applicant (name of the contractor) as a contractor in my 
establishment. I undertake to be bound by all the provisions of the Contract 
Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970 and the Contract Labour (Regulation 
and Abolition) Central Rules, 1971, in so far as the provisions are applicable 
to me in respect of the employment of contract labour by the applicant in my 
establishment 
 


Signature of Principal 
Employer
 


Name and address of 
Establishment
 


Place....................
 


Date.....................
 


 
 

 
</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form VI
 


[See 
rule 25(1)]
 



Government of India
 



Office of Licensing Officer
 



LICENCE
 


Licence No. 
Dated                                                                                                                           
Fee paid Rs..............
 


1. Licence is hereby 
granted to 
........................................................................................ 
under section 12(1) of the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) Act, 1970, 
subject to the conditions specified in Annexure.
 



1[2. This licence is 
for doing the work of (nature of work to be indicated) in the establishment 
of.................(name of principal employer to be indicated) 
of........................ (place of work to be indicated).
 


3. The licence shall remain 
in force till..........................(date to be indicated)].
 



Date............................
 


Signature and Seal of the 
Licensing Officer
 


 
 



RENEWAL 
 



[Rule 29]
 


 


Date of Renewal 
                                                    
  Fee paid for renewal                                              
  Date of Expiry
 


1.
 


2.
 


3.
 



Date.......................                                                                                             
Signature and Seal of the Licensing Officer
 


 
 



ANNEXURE
 


The licence is subject to 
the following conditions:
 


     1.  The licence shall 
be non-transferable.
 


     2.  The number of 
workmen employed as contract labour in the establishment shall not, on any day, 
exceed .............
 


     3.  Except as provided 
in the rules the fees paid for the grant, or as the case may be, for renewal of 
the licence shall be non-refundable.
 


     4.  The rates of wages 
payable to the workmen by the contractor shall not be less than the rates 
prescribed for the Schedule of employment under the Minimum Wages Act, 1948, 
where applicable, and where the rates have been fixed by agreement, settlement 
or award, not less than the rates fixed.
 


     5.  In case where the 
workmen employed by the contractor perform the same or similar kind of work as 
the workmen directly employed by the principal employer of the establishment, 
the wage rates, holidays, hours of work and other conditions of service of the 
workmen of the contractor shall be the same as applicable to the workmen 
directly employed by the principal employer of the establishment on the same or 
similar kind of work: Provided that in the case of any disagreement with regard 
to the type of work the same shall be decided by the 

2[Deputy Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central)] whose decision shall be final.
 


     6.  In other cases the 
wage rates, holidays, hours of work and conditions of service of the workmen of 
the contractor shall be such as may be specified in this behalf by the 

2[Deputy Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central)].
 


     7.  In every 
establishment where 20 or more women are ordinarily employed as contract labour 
there shall be provided 2 rooms of reasonable dimension for the use of their 
children under the age of six years. One of such rooms would be used as a play 
room for the children and the other as bed room for the children. For this 
purpose the contractor shall supply adequate number of toys and games in the 
play room and sufficient number of cots and beddings in the sleeping room. The 
standard of construction and maintenance of the creches may be such as may be 
specified in this behalf by the 

2[Deputy Chief 
Labour Commissioner (Central)].
 


     8.  The licensee shall 
notify any change in the number of workmen or the conditions of work to the 
Licensing Officer.
 



      3[9.  A copy 
of the licence shall be displayed prominently at the premises where the contract 
work is being carried on].
 



  4[10.  The license 
shall, within fifteen days of the commencement and completion of each contract 
work submit a return to the Inspector appointed under section 28 of the Act 
intimating the actual date of the commencement or, as the case may be, 
completion of such contract work in Form VI-A.]
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Ins. by G.S.R. 948, 
dated 12th July, 1978.
 


   2.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
574(E), dated 30th June, 2000 (w.e.f. 30-6-2000).
 


   3.  Ins. by G.S.R. 948, 
dated 12th July, 1978.
 


   4.  Ins. by G.S.R. 657, 
dated 11th August, 1987.
 


 
</form><form>
 

THE CONTRACT LABOUR (REGULATION AND ABOLITION) 
RULES, 19711
 

2[FORM VI-A 
 

[ SEE RULE 25(2) (VIII)] 
 

NOTICE OF COMMENCEMENT/COMPLETION OF CONTRACT WORK 

 

I/We, Shri M/s. ......................................................... 
(Name and address of the contractor) hereby intimate that the contract 
work.......................................................... 
............................................................... 
 

(Name of work)....................... in the establishment of 
the....................... (Name and address of principal employer) for which 
licence No...... dated................... has been issued to me/us by the 
licencing officer (name of the headquarter), has been commenced/completed with 
effect from/date/on (date). 
 

Signature of the Contractor(s) 
 

To 
 

The Inspector 
 

...................................... 
 

......................................] 
 

---------
 

1. V ide G.S.R. 191, published in the Gazette of India, 
Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 10th February, 1971.
 

2. Ins. by G.S.R. 199, dated 25th January, 
1977.</form><form>
 

THE CONTRACT LABOUR (REGULATION AND ABOLITION) 
RULES, 19711
 

2[FORM VI-B 
 

[ SEE RULE 81(3)] 
 

NOTICE OF COMMENCEMENT/COMPLETION OF CONTRACT WORK 

 

1. Name of the principal..................... 
 

Employer and address..................... 
 

2. No. and date of..................... 
 

Certificate of registration................. 
 

3. I/We hereby intimate that the contract work (Name of work) given to (Name 
and address of the contractor) having licence No. ......... 
dated................. has been commenced/completed with effect from (date)/on 
(date). 
 

Signature of the Principal Employer 
 

To 
 

The Inspector 
 

...................................... 
 

.......................................] 
 

---------
 

1. V ide G.S.R. 191, published in the Gazette of India, 
Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 10th February, 1971.
 

2. Ins. by G.S.R. 199, dated 25th January, 
1977.</form><form>
 

The 
Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  
Central Rules, 
1971
 

 
 

1[Form 
VIB
 

[See 
rule 81(3)]
 

Notice 
of commencement/completion of contract work
 

     1.  
Name of the principal..................... 
 

          
Employer and address.....................
 

     2.  
No. and date of..................... 
 

          
Certificate of registration.................
 

     3.  
I/We hereby intimate that the contract work (Name of work) given to (Name and 
address of the contractor) having licence No. ......... dated................. 
has been commenced/completed with effect from (date)/on (date).
 

Signature of the 
Principal Employer
 

To
 

The Inspector
 

......................................
 

.......................................]
 

 
 

—————
 

   1.  Ins. by 
G.S.R. 199, dated 25th January, 1977.
 

 </form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form VII
 


[See 
rule 29(2)]
 




Application for Renewal of Licences
 


     1.  Name and address 
of the contractor
 


     2.  Number and date of 
the licence
 


     3.  Date of expiry of 
the previous licence
 


     4.  Whether the 
licence of the contractor was suspended or revoked.
 



      1[5.  Name of 
the Bank number and date for the demand draft enclosed. Date of receipt of the 
application with “demand draft number and date”.]
 


 
 


Place....................
 



Date.....................                                                                                                                      Signature of the Applicant
 


(To 
be filled in office of the Licensing Officer)
 


Date of receipt of the 
application
 


with Treasury Receipt No. 
and date.                                                                                  
Signature of the Licensing Officer
 


 
 


—————
 


   1. Added by G.S.R. 657, 
dated 11th August, 1987.
 


 
 


 
</form><form>
 

THE CONTRACT LABOUR (REGULATION AND ABOLITION) 
RULES, 19711
 

 
 

FORM VIII 
 

[ SEE RULE 32(2)] 
 

APPLICATION FOR TEMPORARY REGISTRATION OF ESTABLISHMENTS 
EMPLOYING CONTRACT LABOUR 
 

1. Name and location of the establishment. 
 

2. Postal address of the establishment. 
 

3. Full name and address of the Principal Employer (furnish father's name in 
the case of individuals). 
 

4. Full name and address of the Manager or person responsible for the 
supervision and control of the establishment. 
 

5. Nature of work carried on in the establishment. 
 

6. Particulars of contract labour: 
 

A. Nature of work in which contract labour is to be employed and reasons for 
urgency. 
 

B. Maximum number of contract labour to be employed on any day. 
 

C. Estimated date of termination of employment of contract labour. 
 

2[7. Particulars of demand draft enclosed (Name of the Union Bank, 
demand draft No. and date).] 
 

I hereby declare that the particulars given above are true to the best of my 
knowledge and belief. 
 

Principal Employer Seal and Stamp 
 

 
 

Time and date of receipt of application 
 

With Treasury Receipt 3[***]. 
 

Office of the Registering Officer. 
 

---------
 

1. V ide G.S.R. 191, published in the Gazette of India, 
Extra., Pt. II, Sec. 3(i), dated 10th February, 1971.
 

2. Added by G.S.R. 657, dated 11th August, 1987.
 

3. Omitted by G.S.R. 870, dated 26th July, 
1974.</form><form>
 




The Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition)  

Central Rules, 1971
 





 




Form IX
 


[See 
rule 32(3)]
 


Date 
of Expiry ........
 




Temporary Certificate of Registration
 



No.........                                                                                                                                                  
Date................
 



Government of India
 



Office of the 

1[Registering] 
Officer
 


A Temporary Certificate of 
Registration containing the following particulars is hereby granted under 
sub-section (2) of section 7 of the Contract Labour (Regulation and Abolition) 
Act, 1970, and the rules made thereunder, to 
.............................................................................................................................................................................................. 
..................................................................valid from 
................................................................. 
to.....................................
 


     1.  Nature of work 
carried on in the establishment.
 


     2.  Nature of work in 
which contract labour is to be employed.
 


     3.  Maximum number of 
contract labour to be employed on any day.
 


     4.  Other particulars 
relevant to the employment of contract labour.
 


Signature of Registering 
Officer
 



                                                                                         
                                                                   
with Seal
 


 
 


—————
 


   1.  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1649, dated 16th December, 1972.
 


 
</form>
<pagefootnote>
<pagenote><number>1</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 1215(E), dated 28th December, 1988.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>2</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 200, dated 13th February, 1973.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>3</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 948, dated 12th July, 1978.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>4</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 41(E), dated 21st January, 1999 (w.e.f. 
21-1-1999).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>5</number> Omitted by G.S.R. 871(E), dated 26th November, 1985.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>6</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 199, dated 25th January, 1977 (w.e.f. 
12-2-1977).</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>7</number> Ins. by G.S.R. 657, dated 11th August, 1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>8</number> Renumbered and ins. by G.S.R. 657, dated 11th August, 
1987.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>9</number>  Subs. by G.S.R. 
1215(E), dated 28th December, 1988.</pagenote>

<pagenote><number>10</number> Subs. by G.S.R. 48, 
dated 31st December, 1987.</pagenote>
</pagefootnote>
</act>