<act><tid>648854</tid>
<title>THE LEGISLATIVE ASSEMBLY OF NAGALAND (CHANGE IN REPRESENTATION) ACT, <year>1968</year></title>

ACT NO. 61 OF <year>1968</year>
[ 31st December, <year>1968</year>.]

An Act to provide for a change in representation in the Legis- 
lative Assembly of Nagaland and for that purpose to make consequential 
amendments in the State of Nagaland Act, <year>1962</year> and the Representation 
of the People Act, <year>1950</year>.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Nineteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Short title.



<article><tid>1374275</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Legislative Assembly of 
Nagaland (Change in Representation) Act, <year>1968</year>.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>2</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Change in representation in the Legislative Assembly of Nagaland.

</article>



<article><tid>865282</tid>
<number> 2</number> Change in representation in the Legislative Assembly of 
Nagaland. For the period referred to in clause (2) of article 371A of 
the Constitution, the total number of seats allotted to the 
Legislative Assembly of Nagaland shall be increased from forty- six to 
fifty- two, of which-
<section><tid>191092</tid>
<number>a</number>the seats allocated to the Tuensang district shall be 
increased from six to twelve and shall be filled by persons 
chosen by the members of the regional council, referred to in 
that article, from amongst themselves in such manner as the 
Governor of Nagaland, after consulting that council may, by 
notification in the Official Gazette, specify, and

</section>

<section><tid>1066469</tid>
<number>b</number>the remaining forty seats shall be filled by persons 
chosen by direct election from assembly constituencies in the 
rest of the State of Nagaland.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>3</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Amendment of Act 27 of <year>1962</year>.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>16346</tid>
<number> 3</number> Amendment of Act 27 of <year>1962</year>. In the proviso to sub- section
<section><tid>1598136</tid>
<number>1</number> 
of section 11 of the State of Nagaland Act, <year>1962</year>,-

<subsection><tid>1836616</tid>
<number>i</number>for the figures" 46", the figures" 52" shall be 
substituted;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1016025</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" six seats", the words" twelve seats" 
shall be substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>4</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>.


</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1740456</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of Act 43 of <year>1950</year>. In the Representation of the 
People Act, <year>1950</year>,-
<section><tid>1930675</tid>
<number>a</number>in the proviso to sub- section (1) of section 7,-

<subsection><tid>1489027</tid>
<number>i</number>for the word" forty- six", the word" fifty- two" 
shall be substituted;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>170</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1701821</tid>
<number>ii</number>for the words" six seats", the words" twelve 
seats" shall be substituted;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1104952</tid>
<number>b</number>in the Second Schedule, in the entries relating to" 11. 
Nagaland", in column 5, for the figures" 46", the figures 
" 52" shall be substituted.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>5</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

Saving as to present Legislative Assembly.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>202043</tid>
<number>5</number>Saving as to present Legislative Assembly. Nothing in this Act 
shall affect any representation in the present Legislative Assembly of 
Nagaland until its dissolution,

</article>



 </act>