<act> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 20001
  
 <article><number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Foreign Exchange (Compounding Proceedings) Rules, 
2000.
 </section><section><number>2</number> They shall come into force 
on the 1st day of June, 2000.
  


</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>         <number>a</number>  “Act” means the Foreign Exchange Management 
Act, 1999 (42 of 1999);
 </section><section>         <number>b</number> “authorised officer” means an officer 
authorised under sub-rule (1) of rule 3;
 </section><section>         <number>c</number>  “applicant” means a person who makes an 
application under section 15(1) of the Act to the compounding authority;
 </section><section>         <number>d</number>  “Compounding Order” means an order issued 
under sub-section (1) of section 15 of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>e</number>  “Form” means a form appended to these rules;
 </section><section>          <number>f</number>  “section” means a section of the Act;
 </section><section>         <number>g</number>  all other words and expressions used in these 
rules and not defined but defined in the Act, shall have the meaning 
respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>3</number> 
<section><number>1</number> “Compounding Authority” means the persons 
authorised by the Central Government under sub-section (1) of section 15 of the 
Act, namely:—
 <subsection>         <number>a</number>  an 
officer of the Enforcement Directorate not below the rank of Deputy Director or 
Deputy Legal Adviser (DLA).
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  An 
officer of the Reserve Bank of India not below the rank of the Assistant General 
Manager.</subsection></section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>4</number> Power of Reserve Bank to 
compound contravention.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
If any person contravenes any provisions of the Foreign Exchange Management Act, 
1999 (42 of 1999), except clause 
<subsection><number>a</number> of section 3 of that Act]—
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>a</number>  in case where the sum involved in such 
contravention is five lakhs rupees or below, by the Assistant General Manager of 
the Reserve Bank of India;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  in case where the sum involved in such 
contravention is more than rupees five lakhs but less than rupees twenty lakhs, 
by the Deputy General Manager of Reserve Bank of India;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number>  in case where the sum involved in the 
contravention is rupees twenty lakhs or more but less than rupees fifty lakhs by 
the General Manager of Reserve Bank of India;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>d</number>  in case the sum involved in such contravention 
is rupees fifty lakhs or more, by the Chief General Manager of the Reserve Bank 
of India:
 Provided further that no 
contravention shall be compounded unless the amount involved in such 
contravention is quantifiable.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
sub-section (1) shall apply to a contravention committed by any person within a 
period of three years from the date on which a similar contravention committed 
by him was compounded under these rules.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, any second or subsequent contravention committed 
after the expiry of a period of three years from the date on which the 
contravention was previously compounded shall be deemed to be a first 
contravention.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every officer specified 
under sub-rule (1) of rule 4 of the Reserve Bank of India shall exercise the 
powers to compound any contravention subject to the direction, control and 
supervision of the Governor of the Reserve Bank of India.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every application for 
compounding any contravention under this rule shall be made in Form to the 
Reserve Bank of India, Exchange Control Department, Central Office, Mumbai along 
with a fee of Rs. 5000/- by Demand Draft in favour of compounding authority.
  


</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>5</number> The Power of Enforcement 
Directorate to compound contraventions.—1[
<section><number>1</number> 
If any person contravenes provisions of section 3
<subsection><number>a</number> of the Foreign Exchange 
Management Act]—
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>a</number>  in case where the sum involved in such 
contravention is five lakh rupees or below, by the Deputy Director of the 
Directorate of Enforcement;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>b</number>  in case where the sum involved in such 
contravention is more than rupees five lakhs but less than rupees ten lakhs, by 
the Additional Director of the Directorate of Enforcement;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>c</number>  in case where the sum involved in the 
contravention is rupees ten lakhs or more but less than fifty lakh rupees by the 
Special Director of the Directorate of Enforcement;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>d</number>  in case where the sum involved in the 
contravention is rupees fifty lakhs or more but less than one crore rupees by 
Special Director with Deputy Legal Adviser of the Directorate of Enforcement;
 </subsection><subsection>         <number>e</number>  in case the sum involved in such contravention 
is one crore rupees or more, by the Director of Enforcement with Special 
Director of the Enforcement Directorate:
 Provided further that no 
contravention shall be compounded unless the amount involved in such 
contravention is quantifiable.
 </subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Nothing contained in 
sub-section (1) shall apply to a contravention committed by any person within a 
period of three years from the date on which a similar contravention committed 
by him was compounded under these rules.
 Explanation.—For 
the purposes of this rule, any second or subsequent contravention committed 
after the expiry of a period of three years from the date on which the 
contravention was previously compounded shall be deemed to be a first 
contravention.
 </section><section><number>3</number> Every officer of the 
Directorate of Enforcement specified under sub-rule (1) of this rule shall 
exercise the powers to compound any contravention subject to the direction, 
control and supervision of the Director of Enforcement.
 </section><section><number>4</number> Every application for 
compounding any contravention under this rule shall be made in Form to the 
Director, Directorate of Enforcement, New Delhi, along with a fee of Rs. 5000/- 
by DD in favour of the Compounding Authority.
  


</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>6</number> Where any contravention is compounded before the 
adjudication of any contravention under section 16, no inquiry shall be held for 
adjudication of such contravention in relation to such contravention against the 
person in relation to whom the contravention is so 
compounded.</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>7</number> Where the compounding of any contravention is made 
after making of a complaint under sub-section (3) of section 16, such 
compounding shall be brought by the authority specified in rule 4 or rule 5 in 
writing, to the notice of the Adjudicating Authority and on such notice of the 
compounding of the contravention being given, the person in relation to whom the 
contravention is so compounded shall be discharged.</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>8</number> Procedure for compounding.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The Compounding Authority may call for any information, record or any other 
documents relevant to the compounding proceedings.
 </section><section><number>2</number> The Compounding Authority 
shall pass an order of compounding after affording an opportunity of being heard 
to all the concerned as expeditiously as possible and not later than 180 days 
from the date of application.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article>

1[<number>9</number> Payment of amount compounded.—The 
sum for which the contravention is compounded as specified in the order of 
compounding under sub-rule (2) of rule 8, shall be paid by demand draft in 
favour of the Compounding Authority within fifteen days from the date of the 
order of compounding of such contravention.]
  


</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>10</number> In case a person fails to pay the sum compounded in 
accordance with rule 9 within the time specified in that rule, he shall be 
deemed to have never made an application for compounding of any contravention 
under these rules and the provisions of the Act for contravention shall apply to 
him.</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>11</number> No contravention shall be compounded if an appeal has 
been filed under section 17 or section 19 of the Act.</article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>12</number> Contents of the order of 
the Compounding Authority.—
<section><number>1</number> Every 
order shall specify the provisions of the Act or of the rules, directions, 
requisitions or orders made thereunder in respect of which contravention has 
taken place alongwith details of the alleged contravention.
 </section><section><number>2</number> Every such order shall be 
dated and signed by the Compounding Authority under his seal.
</section></article> 
 The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
  
 <article><number>13</number> Copy of the order.—One 
copy of the order made under rule 8 (2) shall be supplied to the applicant and 
the Adjudicating Authority as the case may be.
</article><form>
 

The Foreign Exchange (Compounding 
Proceedings) Rules, 2000
 

 
 

Form
 

(See rule 4 or 5)
 

(To be filled in duplicate and shall be accompanied by 
certified copy  
of the Memorandum issued)
 

   1.  Name 
of the 
applicant                                       
:
 

        
(in block letters)
 

   2.  Full 
address of the 
applicant                               
:
 

   3.  
Whether the applicant is resident in India 
           : 
or resident 
outside India:
 

        
[Please refer to section 2(v) of the 
Act]             
:
 

   4.  Name 
of the Adjudicating Authority before whom    
the case is 
pending                                            
:
 

   5.  Nature of the contravention according to 
 
sub-section (1) of section 
13                            
:
 

   6.  Brief 
facts of the 
case                                        
:
 

   7.  
Details of fee for application of compounding      
:
 

   8.  Any 
other information relevant to the 
case         :
 

I/we declare that the particulars given above are true and 
correct to the best of my/our knowledge and belief and that I/We am/are willing 
to accept any direction/order of the Compounding Authority in connection with 
compounding of my/our case.
 

 
 

Dated.........................                                                          
..........................................
 

                                                                                                   
(Signature of applicant)</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>