<act><tid>65076</tid>
<title>THE SALARIES AND ALLOWANCES OF MINISTER ACT, <year>1952</year></title>

ACT NO, 58 OF <year>1952</year>
 12th August, <year>1952</year>.

An Act to provide for the salaries and allowances of Ministers.

Be it enacted by Parliament as follows:-





<article><tid>1803448</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Salaries and 
Allowances of Short title. Ministers Act, <year>1952</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>1688219</tid>
<number>2</number>Definition. In this Act," Minister" means a member of the 
Council of Ministers, by whatever name called, and includes a Deputy 
Minister.


</article>



<article><tid>1129711</tid>
<number> 3</number> 
<section><tid>1657029</tid>
<number>1</number>Salaries, and daily and constituency allowances. Each  
Minister shall be entitled to receive a salary per mensem, and 
allowance for each day during the whole of his term as such Minister 
at the same rates as are specified in section 3 of the Salaries, 
Allowances and Pension of Members of Parliament Act, <year>1954</year> with respect 
to members of Parliament,

</section>

<section><tid>1169541</tid>
<number>2</number>Each Minister shall be entitled to receive a constituency 
allowance at the same rate as is specified under section 8 of the said 
Act with respect to members of Parliament.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1184568</tid>
<number> 4</number> 
<section><tid>1836442</tid>
<number>1</number>Residence of Ministers. Each Minister shall be  
entitled without payment of rent to the use of a furnished residence 
throughout his term of office and for period of <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> one month] 
immediately thereafter, and no charge shall fall on the Minister 
personally in respect of the maintenance of such residence.

</section>

<section><tid>850799</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> In the event of the death of the Minister, his family shall 
be entitled to the use of the furnished residence occupied by the 
Minister-

<subsection><tid>174799</tid>
<number>a</number>for a period of one month immediately after his death, 
without payment of rent and no charge shall fall on the 
family of the Minister in respect of the maintenance of such 
residence, and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>414114</tid>
<number>b</number>for a further period of one month, on payment of rent 
at such rates as may be prescribed by rules made in this 
behalf by the Central Government and also charges in respect 
of electricity and water consumed in that residence during 
such further period.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>24</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>S. 4 re- numbered as sub- section (1) of that section by Act 47 
of <year>1969</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1966</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 2, ibid., for" fifteen days" (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1966</year>),

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by s. 2, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 11- <year>1966</year>).'

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 76 of <year>1985</year>, s. 2 (w. e. f. 26. 12. <year>1985</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," residence" in- 
cludes the staff quarters and other buildings appurtenant thereto, and 
the garden thereof, and" maintenance" in relation to a residence 
includes the payment of local rates and taxes and the provision of 
electricity and water.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1220083</tid>
<number> 5</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Sumptuary allowance to Ministers. There shall be paid a 
sumptuary
<section><tid>192546</tid>
<number>a</number>the Prime Minister Rupees one thousand 
five hundred per 
mensem;

</section>

<section><tid>1602969</tid>
<number>b</number>every other Minister Rupees one thousand 
who is a member of per mensem; 
the Cabinet

</section>

<section><tid>1281981</tid>
<number>c</number>a Minister of State Rupees five hundred 
per mensem;

</section>

<section><tid>1628471</tid>
<number>d</number>a Deputy Minister Rupees three hundred 
per mensem.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>645159</tid>
<number> 6</number> 
<section><tid>1457805</tid>
<number>1</number>Travelling and daily allownaces to Ministers. Subject to  
any rules made in this behalf by the Central Government, a Minister 
shall be entitled to-

<subsection><tid>954912</tid>
<number>a</number>travelling allowances for himself and the members of 
his family and for the transport of his and his family' s 
effects-

<subsubsection><tid>194435</tid>
<number>i</number>in respect of the journey to Delhi from his usual 
place of residence outside Delhi for assuming office, 
and (ii) in respect of the journey from Delhi to his 
usual place of residence outside Delhi on relinquishing 
office; and

</subsubsection>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>281879</tid>
<number>b</number>travelling and daily allowances in respect of tours 
undertaken by him in the discharge of his official duties, 
whether by sea, land or air.
<footcitenum>2</footcitenum>


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>982536</tid>
<number>2</number>Any travelling allowance under this section may be paid in cash 
or free official transport provided in lieu thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1862984</tid>
<number>7</number>Medical treatment, etc., to Ministers. Subject to any rules 
made in this behalf by the Central Government, a Minister and the 
members of his family shall be entitled free of charge to 
accommodation in hospitals maintained by the Government and also to 
medical treatment.


</article>



<article><tid>1140682</tid>
<number>8</number>Advances to Ministers for purchase of motorcars. There may be 
paid to any Minister by way of a repayable advance such sum of money 
as may be determined by rules made in this behalf for the purchase of 
a motor- car in order that he may be able to discharge conveniently and 
efficiently the duties of his office.


</article>



<article><tid>1576595</tid>
<number>9</number>Ministers not to draw salary or allowances as Members of 
Parliament. No person in receipt of a salary or allowance under this 
Act shall be entitled to receive any sum out of funds provided by 
Parlia-

<pagefootnote><pagenum>25</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 76 of <year>1985</year>, s. 3 (w. e. f. 26. 12. <year>1985</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Ins. by s. 4, ibid. (w. e. f. 26. 12. <year>1985</year>)


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

ment by way of salary or allowance in respect of his membership of Or 
either House of Parliament.



</article>



<article><tid>970977</tid>
<number>10</number>Notification respecting appointment, etc., of Ministers to be 
conclusive evidence there of. The date on which any person became or 
ceased to be a Minister shall be published in the Official Gazette, 
and any such notification shall be conclusive evidence of the fact 
that he became, or ceased to be, a Minister on that date for all the 
purposes of this Act.








</article>



<article><tid>743961</tid>
<number>12</number>Regularisation of certain payments. All salaries paid or 
payable for the period commencing on the 14th day of May, <year>1952</year>, and 
ending with the commencement of this Act to Ministers described as 
Ministers of Cabinet rank (but not Members of the Cabinet), all 
charges incurred before the commencement of this Act in respect of the 
accommodation provided in any hospital maintained by the Central 
Government for or on the medical treatment of any Minister or any 
member of his family and all payments made before such commencement by 
way of travelling or daily allowances to any Deputy Minister, shall be 
deemed to have been properly paid, payable or incurred or made.


</article>



<article><tid>1061705</tid>
<number>13</number>[ Repeal of Act 53 of <year>1947</year>.] Rep. by the Repealing and Amend- 
ing Act, <year>1957</year> (36 of <year>1957</year>), s. 2 and Sch, 1,
<pagefootnote><pagenum>26</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 37 of <year>1977</year>, s 2, for s. 11.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>For such rules, see Gazette of India, Extraordinary, Pt. 11, 
Sec. 3, <year>1952</year>, pp. 803, 835, 837, 849, ibid. <year>1953</year>, pp. 101, 528, 2269, 
3467.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 76 of <year>1985</year>, s. 5 (w. e. f. 26. 12. <year>1985</year>)



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>