<act><title>


the Employees’ State Insurance Corporation 
    (General Provident Fund) Rules, 19951</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    These rules may be called the Employees’ State Insurance Corporation 
    (General Provident Fund) Rules, 1995.
 

1[(2) 
    They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official 
    Gazette.] 



 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—
<section><number>1</number> In these rules 
    unless the context otherwise requires—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   
    “Accounts Officer” means the Financial Commissioner of the Employees’ State 
    Insurance Corporation or such other officer as may be specified in this 
    behalf;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   “Act” 
    means the Employees’ State Insurance Act, 1948 (43 of 1948);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   
    “Corporation” means Employees’ State Insurance Corporation.   
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   
    “emoluments” means pay, leave salary or subsistence grant if admissible and 
    any remuneration of the nature of pay received in respect of deputation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   
    “employee” means a person appointed to or borne on the cadre of staff of the 
    Corporation, other than persons on deputation;    
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   “Family” 
    means—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   In the case of a male-subscriber the 
    wife or wives, parents, children, minor brothers, unmarried sisters, 
    deceased son’s widow and children and where no parent of the subscriber is 
    alive, a paternal grandparent:  
 
Provided that if a subscriber proves that his 
    wife has been judicially separated from him or has ceased under the 
    customary law of the community to which she belongs to be entitled to 
    maintenance, she shall henceforth be deemed to be  no longer a member of the 
    subscriber’s family in matters to which these rules relate, unless the 
    subscriber subsequently intimates in writing to the Accounts Officer that he 
    shall continue to be so regarded;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   In the case of a female subscriber, the 
    husband, parents, children, minor brothers, unmarried sisters, deceased 
    son’s widow and children and where no parent of the subscriber is alive, a 
    paternal grandparent:  
 
Provided that if a subscriber by notice in 
    writing to the Accounts Officer expresses her desire to exclude her husband 
    from her family, the husband shall henceforth be deemed to be no longer a 
    member of the subscriber’s family in matters to which these rules relate 
    unless the subscriber subsequently cancels such notice in writing.  
 
Explanation.—In this clause, child 
    means legitimate child and includes an adopted child, where adoption is 
    recognised by the personal law governing the subscriber;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   “Fund” 
    means the Employees’ State Insurance Corporation General Provident Fund;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   “Leave” 
    means any kind of leave recognised by the Employees’ State Insurance 
    Corporation (Staff and Conditions of Service) Regulations, 1959;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   
    “Service” means service under the Corporation;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   “Year” 
    means a financial year.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Any other expression used in these rules 
    which is defined either in the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925) or 
    Employees’ State Insurance Act, 1948 (34 of 1948) or in the Fundamental 
    Rules, is used in the sense thereon defined but not defined herein shall 
    have the meaning respectively assigned to them in the Provident Funds Act, 
    1925 (19 of 1925), the Employees’ State Insurance Corporation (Central) 
    Rules, 1950, Employees’ State Insurance Corporation (Staff and Conditions of 
    Service) Regulations, 1959 or the Fundamental Rules, as the case may be.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Nothing in these rules shall be deemed to 
    have the effect of terminating the existence of the General Provident Funds 
    as heretofore existing or of constituting any new fund. 
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> Constitution of the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Fund shall be maintained in Rupees.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> All sums paid into the Fund under these 
    rules shall be credited to a Fund called “The Employees’ State Insurance 
    Corporation General Provident Fund”. Sums of which payment has not been 
    taken within six months after they become payable under these rules shall be 
    transferred to the Deposit Account at the end of the year and treated under 
    the ordinary rules relating to deposits.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> Operation of Fund by the Accounts 
    Officer.—The Fund shall be operated upon by the Accounts Officer who is 
    hereby authorised to arrange for all payments required to be made under 
    these rules. 
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> Investments.—All monies 
    belonging to the Fund shall be invested in the manner specified in the 
    Employees’ State Insurance (Central) Rules, 1950, for investment of monies 
    belonging to the Employees’ State Insurance Fund.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> Conditions of eligibility.—All 
    temporary employees after a continuous service of one year, all re-employed 
    pensioners (other than those eligible for admission to CPF) and all 
    permanent employees shall subscribe to the Fund:
 
Provided that no such employee as has been 
    required or permitted to subscribe to a Contributory Provident Fund shall be 
    eligible to join or continue as a subscriber to the Fund while he retains 
    his right to subscribe to such a Fund:
 
Provided further that such of the temporary 
    employees who have completed continuous service of one year before the 31st 
    March, 1960 shall not subscribe to the Fund from a date earlier than the 1st 
    April, 1960.
 
Explanation.—A temporary employee who 
    completes one year of continuous service on any day of a month shall 
    subscribe to the fund with effect from the subsequent month.
 
Note 1.—Apprentices and Probationers 
    shall be treated as temporary employees for the purpose of this rule.
 
Note 2.—A temporary employee who 
    completes one year of continuous service during the middle of a month shall 
    subscribe to the Fund from the subsequent month.
 
Note 3.—Temporary employee (including 
    Apprentices and Probationers) who have been appointed against regular 
    vacancies and are likely to continue for more than a year may subscribe to 
    the General Provident Fund any time before completion of one year’s service.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> Nominations.—
<section><number>1</number> A subscriber shall, 
    at the time of joining the Fund, send to the Accounts Officer a nomination 
    conferring on one or more persons the right to receive the amount that may 
    stand to his credit in the Fund in the event of his death before that amount 
    has become payable or having become payable has not been paid:
 
Provided that where a subscriber is a minor he 
    shall be required to make the nomination only on his attaining the age of 
    majority:
 
Provided further that a subscriber who has a 
    family at the time of making the nomination shall make nomination only in 
    favour of a member or members of his family:
 
Provided also that the nomination made by the 
    subscriber in respect of any other provident fund to which he was 
    subscribing before joining the Fund shall if the amount to his credit in 
    such other fund has been transferred to his credit in the Fund, be deemed to 
    be a nomination in accordance with this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If a subscriber nominates more than one 
    person under sub-rule (1)  he shall specify in the nomination the amount or 
    share payable to each of the nominees, in such manner as to cover the whole 
    of the amount that may stand to his credit in the Fund at any time.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Every nomination shall be made in the 
    Forms set forth in the Schedule I appended to these rules.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> A subscriber may at any time cancel a 
    nomination made by him by sending a notice in writing to the Accounts 
    Officer. The subscriber shall, along with such notice or separately, send a 
    fresh nomination made in accordance with the provision of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> A subscriber may provide in a nomination—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   That in 
    the event of his predeceasing the subscriber, the right conferred upon the 
    specified nominee shall pass to such other person or persons as may be 
    specified in the nominations:  
 
Provided that 
    such other person or persons shall, if the subscriber has any other member 
    in his family, be such member or members of the family:  
 
Provided 
    further that where the subscriber confers the right under this clause on 
    more than one person, he shall specify the amount or share payable to each 
    of such persons in such a manner as to cover the whole of the amount payable 
    to the nominee.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   That the 
    nomination shall become invalid in the event of the happening of a 
    contingency specified therein:  
 
Provided that 
    if at the time of making the nomination the subscriber has only one member 
    of his family he shall provide in the nomination that the right conferred 
    upon the alternate nominee under clause (a) shall become invalid in the 
    event of his subsequently acquiring other member or members in his family.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>6</number> Immediately on the death of a nominee in 
    respect of whom no special provision has been made in the nomination under 
    clause (a) of sub-rule (5) or on the occurrence of any event by reason of 
    which the nomination becomes invalid in pursuance of clause (b) of sub-rule 
    (5) or the proviso thereto the subscriber send a notice in writing to the 
    Accounts Officer cancelling the nomination, together with the fresh 
    nomination made in accordance with the provisions of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> Every nomination made, and every notice of 
    cancellation given by a subscriber shall, to the extent that it is valid, 
    take effect on the date on which it is received by the Accounts Officer.
 
Note:—In this rule, unless the context 
    otherwise requires, ‘person’ or ‘persons’ shall include a company or 
    association or body of individuals, whether incorporated or not. It shall 
    also include a Fund such as the Prime Minister’s National Relief Fund or any 
    Charitable or other Trust of Fund, to which nomination may be made through 
    the Secretary or other executive of the said Funds or Trust authorised to 
    receive payments.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Subscriber’s Account.—An account 
    shall be opened in the name of each subscriber to show—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   his 
    subscriptions;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   
    interest, as provided in rule 13 on subscriptions;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   
    advances and withdrawals from the fund.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> Subscriber’s Account.—An account 
    shall be opened in the name of each subscriber to show—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   his 
    subscriptions;  
 </section><section>
<number>ii</number>   
    interest, as provided in rule 13 on subscriptions;  
 </section><section>
<number>iii</number>   
    advances and withdrawals from the fund.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> Conditions and rates of subscriptions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A subscriber shall subscribe to the Fund every month except during the 
    period when he is under suspension:
 
Provided that a subscriber on reinstatement 
    after a period of suspension shall be allowed the option of paying in one 
    lump sum or in instalments any sum not exceeding the maximum amount of 
    arrear of subscription payable in respect of the said period:
 
Provided further that a subscriber may, at his 
    option not subscribe during any period of leave which either does not carry 
    any leave salary or carries leave salary equal to or less than half pay or 
    half average pay.
 
Note 1.—The holder of a seasonal post 
    in an establishment need not subscribe to Fund, during the period of his 
    employment.
 
Note 2.—A subscriber need not subscribe 
    during a period treated as dies non.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The subscriber shall intimate his option 
    not to subscribe during leave referred to in the second proviso to sub-rule 
    (1) in the following manner:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   If he is 
    an officer who draws his own pay bills, by making no deduction on account of 
    subscription in his first pay bill drawn after proceeding on leave.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   If he is 
    not an officer who draws his own pay bills, by written communication to the 
    Head of Office before he proceeds on leave. On failure to make due and 
    timely intimation shall be deemed to constitute an option to subscribe.  
 
Note.—The option of a subscriber once 
    intimated under this sub-rule shall be final.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> A subscriber who has under rule 17 
    withdrawn the amount standing to his credit in the Fund shall not subscribe 
    to the Fund after such withdrawal unless he returns to duty.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Notwithstanding anything contained in 
    sub-rule (1) a subscriber shall not subscribe to the Fund for the month in 
    which he quits service unless, before the commencement of the said month, he 
    communicates to the Head of Office in writing his option to subscribe for 
    the said month.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> Rates of subscription.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    amount of subscription shall be fixed by the subscriber himself, subject to 
    the following conditions, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   It shall 
    be expressed in whole rupees.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   It may 
    be any sum, so expressed which shall not be less than 6 per cent. of his 
    emoluments and not more than his total emoluments:  
 
Provided that 
    in the case of a subscriber who has previously been subscribing to the 
    Employees’ State Insurance Corporation Contributory Provident Fund at the 
    higher rate of 8-1/3%, it may be any sum so expressed which shall not be 
    less than 8-1/3% of his total emoluments and not more than his total 
    emoluments.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   When an 
    employee opts to subscribe at the minimum rate of 6%, or 8-1/3% per cent., 
    as the case may be, the subscription shall be rounded to the nearest whole 
    rupee and for this purpose, 50 paise and more shall be rounded to the next 
    higher rupee.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> For the purpose of sub-rule (1) the 
    emoluments of a subscriber shall be—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   in the 
    case of subscriber who was in service on the 31st March of the preceding 
    year, the emoluments to which he was entitled on that date:  
 
Provided that—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   if the subscriber was on half day leave 
    on the said date and opted not to subscribe during such leave or was under 
    suspension on the said date, his emoluments shall be emoluments to which he 
    was entitled on the first day after his return to duty;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   if the subscriber was on deputation out 
    of India on the said date or was on half pay leave on the said date and 
    continues to be on leave and has opted to subscribe during such leave, his 
    emoluments to which he would have been entitled had he been on duty abroad 
    or on duty in India as the case may be;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   In the 
    case of a subscriber who was not in service on the 31st March of the 
    preceding year, the emoluments to which he was entitled on the day he joins 
    the Fund.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> The subscriber shall intimate the fixation 
    of the amount of his monthly subscription in each year in the following 
    manner, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if he 
    was on the 31st March of the preceding year, by the deduction which he 
    causes to be made in this behalf from his pay bill for that month;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if he 
    was on leave on the 31st March of the preceding year and opted not to 
    subscribe during such half pay leave or was under suspension on that date, 
    by the deduction which he makes in this behalf from his first pay bill after 
    his return to duty;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   if he 
    was on leave on the 31st March of the preceding year, and continues to be on 
    half pay leave and has opted to subscribe during such leave by the deduction 
    which he makes or causes to be made in this behalf from his salary for the 
    month;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   if he 
    has entered into service for the first time during the year, by the 
    deduction which he makes or causes to be made in this behalf, from the 
    salary bill for that month during which he joins the Fund;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   if he 
    was on deputation on the 31st March of the preceding year by the amount 
    credited by him in the Fund of the Corporation on account of subscription 
    for the month of April in the current year.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>4</number> The amount of subscription so fixed may 
    be—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   reduced 
    once at any time during the course of the year;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   enhanced 
    twice during the course of the year; or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   reduced 
    and enhanced as aforesaid:  
 
Provided that 
    when the amount of subscription is so reduced it shall not be less than the 
    minimum prescribed in sub-rule (1):  
 
Provided 
    further that if a subscriber is on leave without pay or leave on half pay or 
    half average pay for part of a calendar month and he has opted not to 
    subscribe during such leave, the amount of subscription payable shall be 
    proportionate to the number of days spent on duty including leave, if any, 
    other than those referred to above.  
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> Transfer on deputation to a post under 
    the Government or any other organisation or deputation out of India.—When 
    subscriber is transferred or sent on deputation out of India, he shall 
    remain subject to these rules in the same manner as if he were not so 
    transferred or sent on deputation.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> Realisation of subscriptions.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    When the emoluments are drawn from the Fund, recovery of subscriptions and 
    the principle and interest of advances, if any, granted from the Fund shall 
    be made direct from the emoluments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> When emoluments are drawn from any other 
    source, the subscriber shall forward his dues monthly to the Accounts 
    Officer:
 
Provided that in the case of a subscriber on 
    deputation to a body corporate owned or controlled by Government the 
    subscription shall be recovered and forwarded to the Accounts Officer by 
    such body.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If a subscriber fails to subscribe with 
    effect from the date on which he is required to join the Fund or is on 
    default in any month or months during the course of a year otherwise than as 
    provided in rule 9, the total amount due to the Fund on account of arrears 
    or subscription shall, with interest thereon at the rate provided in rule 
    13, forthwith be paid by the subscriber to the Fund or in default be ordered 
    by the Accounts Officer to be recovered by deduction from the emoluments of 
    the subscriber by instalments or otherwise, as may be directed by the 
    authority competent to sanction an advance for the grant of which special 
    reasons are required under sub-rule (2) of rule 14:
 
Provided that the subscribers whose deposits 
    in the Fund carry no interest shall not be required to pay any interest.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> Interest.—
<section><number>1</number> Subject to the 
    provisions of sub-rule (5), the Corporation shall pay to the credit of the 
    account of a subscriber interest at such rate as may be determined for each 
    year by the Central Government in respect of the General Provident Fund for 
    the Central Government Employees:
 
Provided that if the rate of interest 
    determined for a year is less than 4 per cent., all subscribers to the Fund 
    in the year preceding that for which the rate has for the first time been 
    fixed at less than 4 per cent., shall be allowed interest at the rate of 4 
    per cent.:
 
Provided further that a subscriber who was 
    previously subscribing to any other Provident Fund of the Central Government 
    and whose subscriptions, together with interest thereon, have been 
    transferred to his credit in his Fund under rule 26 shall also be allowed 
    interest at the rate of 4 per cent., if he had been receiving that rate of 
    interest under the rules of such other Fund under a provision similar to 
    that of the first proviso to this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Interest shall be credited with effect 
    from the last day in each year in the following manner:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   on the 
    amount to the credit of a subscriber on the last day of the preceding year, 
    less sums, if any, withdrawn during the current year, interest for twelve 
    months;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   on sums 
    withdrawn during the current year interest from the beginning of the current 
    year up to the last day of the month preceding the month of withdrawal;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   on all 
    sums credited to the subscriber’s account after the last day of the 
    preceding year interest from the current year;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   the 
    total amount of interest shall be rounded to the nearest whole rupee (fifty 
    paise and more counting as the next higher rupee):  
 
Provided that 
    when the amount standing to the credit of a subscriber has become payable, 
    interest shall thereupon be credited under this rule in respect only of the 
    period from the beginning of the current year or from the date of deposit, 
    as the case may be, upto the date on which the amount standing to the credit 
    of the subscriber becomes payable.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> In this rule, the date of deposit shall, 
    in the case of recovery from emoluments, be deemed to be the first day of 
    the month in which it is recovered, and in the case of an amount forwarded 
    by the subscriber, shall be deemed to be the first day of the month of 
    receipt, if it is received by the Accounts Officer before the fifth day of 
    that month, but if it is received on or after the fifth day of that month, 
    the first day of the next succeeding month:
 
Provided that where there has been a delay in 
    the drawal of pay or leave salary and allowances of a subscriber and 
    consequently the recovery of his subscription towards the Fund, the interest 
    on such subscriptions shall be payable from the month in which the pay or 
    leave salary of the subscriber was due under the rules, irrespective of the 
    month in which it was actually drawn:
 
Provided further that in the case of an amount 
    forwarded in accordance with the proviso to sub-rule (2) of rule 12, the 
    date of deposit shall be deemed to be the first day of the month if it is 
    received by the Accounts Officer before the fifteenth day of that month:
 
Provided also that where the emoluments for a 
    month are drawn and disbursed on the last working day of the same month the 
    date of deposit shall, in the case of recovery of his subscriptions, be 
    deemed to be the first day of the succeeding month.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> In addition to any amount to be paid under 
    rules 20, 21 or 22 interest thereon upto the end of the month preceding that 
    in which the payment is made or upto the end of the six months after the 
    month in which such amount becomes payable whichever of these periods be 
    less, shall be payable to the person to whom such amount is to be paid:
 
Provided that where the Accounts Officer has 
    intimated to that person (or his agent) a date on which he is prepared to 
    make payment in cash or has posted a cheque in payment to that person, 
    interest shall be payable only up to the end of the month preceding the date 
    so intimated or the date of posting the cheque, as the case may be:
 
Provided further that where a subscriber on 
    deputation to a body corporate, owned or controlled by the Government of an 
    autonomous organisation registered under the Societies Registration Act, 
    1860 (21 of 1860) is subsequently absorbed in such body corporate or 
    organisation with effect from a retrospective date, for the purpose of 
    calculating the interest due on the Fund accumulations of the subscriber the 
    date of issue of the orders regarding absorption shall be deemed to be the 
    date on which the amount or the credit of the subscriber became payable 
    subject to the condition that the amount recovered as subscription during 
    the period commencing from the date of absorption and ending with the date 
    of issue of orders of absorption shall be deemed to be subscription to the 
    Fund only for the purpose of awarding interest under this sub-rule.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> Interest shall not be credited to the 
    account of a subscriber if he informs the Accounts Officer that he does not 
    wish to receive it; but if he subsequently asks for interest, it shall be 
    credited with effect from the first day of the year in which he asks for it.
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> The interest on amount which under 
    sub-rule (3) of rule 12, rule 20 or rule 21 are replaced to the credit of 
    the subscriber in the Fund, shall be calculated at such rates as may be 
    successively prescribed under sub-rule (1) of this rule and so far as may be 
    in the manner prescribed in this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>7</number> In case a subscriber is found to have 
    drawn from the Fund an amount in excess of the amount standing to his credit 
    on the date of the drawal, the overdrawn amount, irrespective of whether the 
    overdrawal occurred in the course of an advance or a withdrawal or the final 
    payment from the Fund, shall be repaid by him with interest thereon in one 
    lump sum, or in default be ordered to be recovered by deduction one lump 
    sum, from the emoluments of the subscriber. If the total amount to be 
    recovered is more than half of the subscriber’s emoluments, recoveries shall 
    be made in monthly instalments of moieties of his emoluments till the entire 
    amount together with interest, is recovered. For this sub-rule the rate of 
    interest, to be charged on overdrawn amount would be 2.5 per cent. over and 
    above the normal rate on Provident Fund balance under sub-rule (1). The 
    interest realised on the overdrawn amount shall be credited to Corporation 
    account under a distinct sub-head ‘Interest on Overdrawals from Provident 
    Fund’ under the head “049-interest Receipts-C other Interest Receipts of 
    Corporation—other Receipts”.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> Advance from the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> The 
    Director General or any other officer authorised by him in this behalf, may 
    sanction the payment to any subscriber in the prescribed Form as specified 
    in Schedule II of an advance consisting of a sum of whole rupees and not 
    exceeding in amount three months’ pay or half the amount standing to his 
    credit in the Fund, whichever is less, for one or more of the following 
    purposes, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   to pay 
    expenses in connection with the illness, confinement or a disability 
    including where necessary, the travelling expenses of the subscriber and 
    members of his family or any person actually dependent on him.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   to meet 
    the cost of higher education including where necessary, the travelling 
    expenses of the subscriber and member of his family or any person actually 
    dependent on him; in the following cases, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   for the education outside India in 
    respect of an academic, a technical, a professional or vocational course 
    beyond the High School stage; and   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   for any medical, engineering or other 
    technical or specialised course in India beyond the High School stage, 
    provided that the course of study is of not less than three years’ duration;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   to pay 
    obligatory expenses on a scale appropriate to the subscribers’ status which, 
    by customary usage the subscribers have to incur in connection with 
    betrothal or marriages, funerals or other ceremonies;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   to meet 
    cost of legal proceedings instituted by or against the subscriber or any 
    person actually dependent upon him. The advance in this case being available 
    in addition to any advance admissible for the same purpose from any other 
    Government source;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   to meet 
    the cost of his defence where the subscriber engages a legal practitioner to 
    defend himself in an enquiry in respect of any alleged official misconduct 
    on his part;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   to meet 
    the cost of plot or construction of a house or flat for his residence or to 
    make any payment towards the allotment of a plot or flat by the Delhi 
    Development Authority or a State Housing Board or a House Building 
    Cooperative Society.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> The Director General may, in special 
    circumstances, sanction the payment to any subscriber of an advance if he is 
    satisfied that the subscriber concerned requires the advance for reasons 
    other than those mentioned in sub-rule (1).
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> An advance shall not, except for special 
    reasons to be recorded in writing, he granted to any subscriber in excess of 
    the limit laid down in sub-rule (1) or until repayment of the last 
    instalment of any previous advance.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> When an advance is sanctioned under 
    sub-rule (3) before repayment of last instalment of any previous advance is 
    completed, the balance of any previous advance not recovered shall be added 
    to the advance so sanctioned and the instalments for recovery shall be fixed 
    with reference to the consolidated amount.
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> After sanctioning the advance, the amount 
    shall be drawn on an authorisation from the Accounts Officer in cases where 
    the application for final payment had been forwarded to the Accounts Officer 
    under clause (ii) of sub-rule (3) of rule 25.
 
Note 1.—For the purpose of this rule 
    pay includes dearness pay, where admissible.
 
Note 2.—A subscriber shall be permitted 
    to take an advance once in every six months under clause (b) of sub-rule (1) 
    of rule 14.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> Recovery of advance.—
<section><number>1</number> An advance 
    shall be recovered from the subscriber in such number of equal monthly 
    instalments as the sanctioning authority may direct; but such number shall 
    not be less than twelve unless the subscriber so opt and in any case not 
    more than twenty four. In special cases where amount of advance exceeds 
    three months’ pay of the subscriber under sub-rule (2) of rule 14, the 
    sanctioning authority may fix such number of instalments exceeding twenty 
    four but not exceeding thirty six, a subscriber may, at his option, repay 
    more than one instalment in a month. Each instalment shall be fixed in whole 
    rupees, the amount of the advance being raised or reduced if necessary, to 
    admit the fixation of such instalments.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Recovery of advances shall be made in the 
    manner specified in rule 12 for the realisation of subscription, and shall 
    commence with the issue of pay for the month following the one in which the 
    advance was drawn.  Recovery shall not be made, except with the subscriber’s 
    consent while he is in receipt of subsistence grant or is on leave for ten 
    days or more in a calendar month which either does not carry any leave 
    salary or carries leave salary equal to or less than half pay or half 
    average pay, as the case may be. The recovery may on the subscriber’s 
    written request, be postponed by the sanctioning authority during the 
    recovery of an advance of pay granted to the subscriber.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> If an advance has been granted to a 
    subscriber and drawn by him and the advance is subsequently disallowed 
    before repayment is completed, the whole or balance of amount withdrawn 
    shall be forthwith repaid by the subscriber to the Fund. Or in default, be 
    ordered by the Accounts Officer to be recovered by deduction from the 
    emoluments of the subscriber in a lump sum or in monthly installments not 
    exceeding twelve as may be directed by the Accounts Officer:
 
Provided that before such advance is 
    disallowed, the subscriber shall be given reasonable opportunity to explain 
    to the sanctioning authority in writing within 15 days of the receipt of the 
    communication, why the repayment shall not be enforced and if an explanation 
    is submitted by the subscriber within the said period of 15 days, it shall 
    be referred to the Director General for decision and if no explanation 
    within the said period is submitted by him, the repayment of the advance 
    shall be enforced in the manner presented in the sub-rule.
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> Recoveries made under this rule shall be 
    credited to the subscriber’s account in the Fund.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> Wrongful use of advance.—Notwithstanding 
    anything contained in these rules, if the sanctioning authority has reason 
    to doubt that money drawn as an advance from the Fund under rule 14 has been 
    utilised for a purpose other than that for which sanction was given to the 
    drawal of the money, he shall communicate to the subscriber the reasons for 
    his doubt and require him to explain in writing and within 15 days of the 
    receipt of such communication whether the advance has been utilised for the 
    purpose for which sanction was given to the drawal of the money. If the 
    sanctioning authority is not satisfied with the explanation furnished by the 
    subscriber within the said period of 15 days, the sanctioning authority 
    shall direct the subscriber to repay the amount in question to the Fund 
    forthwith or, in default, order the amount to be recovered by deduction in 
    one sum from the emoluments of the subscriber even if he be on leave. If, 
    however, the total amount to be repaid be more than half the subscriber’s 
    emoluments, recoveries shall be made in monthly instalments of moieties of 
    his emoluments till the entire amount is repaid by him.
 
Note.—The term “emoluments” in this 
    rule shall not include subsistence grant.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> Withdrawal from the Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Subject to the conditions specified therein, withdrawals may be sanctioned 
    to the subscriber in the prescribed Form as specified in Schedule II by the 
    authorities competent to sanction an advance for special reasons under 
    sub-rule (2) of rule 14, at any time, after the completion of twenty years 
    of service (including broken period of service, if any) of a subscriber or 
    within ten years before the date of his retirement on superannuation, 
    whichever is earlier, from the amount standing to his credit in the Fund, 
    for one or more of the following purposes, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   meeting 
    the cost of higher education, including where necessary the travelling 
    expenses of the subscriber or any child of the subscriber in the following 
    cases, namely:—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   for the education outside India for 
    academic, technical, professional or a vocational course beyond the High 
    School stage; and   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   for any medical, engineering or other 
    technical or specialized course in India beyond the High School stage;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   meeting 
    the expenditure in connection with the betrothal/marriage of the subscriber 
    or his sons or daughters and of any other family relation actually dependent 
    on him;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   meeting 
    the expenses in connection with illness, including where necessary, the 
    travelling expenses, of the subscriber and members of his family or any 
    person actually dependent on him.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> After the completion of ten years of 
    service (including broken periods of service, if any) of a subscriber or 
    within ten years before the date of his retirement or superannuation, 
    whichever is earlier, a subscriber will be allowed withdrawals from the 
    amount standing to his credit in the Fund for one or more of the following 
    purposes, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   building 
    or acquiring a suitable house or ready built flat or his residence including 
    the cost of the site;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   
    repaying an outstanding amount on account of loan expressly taken for 
    building or acquiring a suitable house or ready built flat for his 
    residence;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   
    purchasing a house-site for building a house thereon for his residence or 
    repaying any outstanding amount on account of loan expressly taken for this 
    purpose;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   
    reconstructing or making additions or alterations to a house or a flat 
    already owned or acquired by a subscriber;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   
    renovating, additions or alterations or upkeep of an ancestral house at a 
    place other than the place of duty or to a house built  with the assistance 
    of loan from Government at a place other than the place of duty;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vi</number>   
    constructing a house on a site purchased under clause (iii);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>vii</number>   within 
    six months before the date of the subscriber’s retirement for the amount 
    standing to his credit in the Fund for the purpose of acquiring a farm land 
    or business premises or both;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>viii</number>   once 
    during the course of a financial year, an amount equivalent to one year’s 
    subscription paid for by the subscriber towards the Group Insurance Scheme 
    for the Corporation employees on self-financing and contributory basis.  
 
Note 1.—A subscriber who has availed 
    himself of an advance under the scheme of the Ministry of Urban Development 
    for the grant of advance for house building purpose, or has been allowed any 
    assistance in this regard from any other Government source shall be eligible 
    for the grant of final withdrawal under clauses (i), (iii), (iv), (vi) or 
    sub-rule (2) for the purpose specified therein and also for the purpose of 
    repayment of any loan taken under the aforesaid scheme subject to the limit 
    specified in the proviso to sub-rule (1) of rule 18.
 
If a subscriber has an ancestral house or 
    built a house at a place other than the place of his duty with the 
    assistance of loan taken from the Government he shall be eligible for the 
    grant of a final withdrawal under clauses (i) (iii), and (vi) of sub-rule 
    (2) for purchase of a house-site or for construction of another house or for 
    acquiring a ready-built flat at the place of his duty.
 
Note 2.—Withdrawal under clause (i), 
    (iv) or (vi) of sub-rule (2) shall be sanctioned only after a subscriber has 
    submitted a plan of the house to be constructed or of the additions or 
    alterations to be made, duly approved by the local municipal body of the 
    area where the site or house is situated and only in cases where the plan is 
    actually got to be approved.
 
Note 3.—The amount of withdrawal 
    sanctioned under clause (ii) of sub-rule (2) shall not exceed 3/4th of the 
    balance on date of application together with the amount of previous 
    withdrawal under clause (i) reduced by the amount of previous withdrawal. 
    The formula to be followed is 3/4th of the balance (as on date plus amount 
    of previous withdrawal(s) for the house in question) minus the amount of the 
    previous withdrawal(s).
 
Note 4.—Withdrawal under clause (i) or 
    (iv) of sub-rule (2) shall also be allowed where the house-site or house is 
    in the name of wife or husband provided she or he is the first nominee to 
    receive Provident Fund money in the nomination made by the subscriber.
 
Note 5.—Only one withdrawal shall be 
    allowed for the same purpose under this rule. But marriage or education of 
    different children or illness on different occasions or a further addition 
    or alteration to a house or flats covered by a fresh plan duly approved by 
    the local municipal body of the area where the house or flat is situated 
    shall not be treated as the same purpose. Second or subsequent withdrawal 
    under clause (i) or (vi) of sub-rule (2) for completion of the same house 
    shall be allowed up to the limit laid down under Note 3.
 
Note 6.—A withdrawal under this rule 
    shall not be sanctioned if an advance under rule 14 is being sanctioned for 
    the same purpose and at the same time.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> After sanctioning the withdrawal the 
    amount shall be drawn on an authorisation from the Accounts Officer in cases 
    where the application for final payment had been forwarded to the Accounts 
    Officer under clause (ii) of sub-rule (3) of rule 25.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>18</number> Conditions for withdrawal.—
<section><number>1</number> Any 
    sum withdrawn by a subscriber at any one time for one or more of the 
    purposes, specified in rule 17 from the amount standing to his credit in the 
    Fund shall not ordinarily exceed one-half of such amount or six months’ pay, 
    whichever is less. The sanctioning authority may, however, sanction the 
    withdrawal of an amount in excess of this limit up to 3/4th of the balance 
    at his credit in the Fund having regard to (i) the object for which the 
    withdrawal is being made, (ii) the status of the subscriber, and (iii) the 
    amount to this credit in the Fund:
 
Provided that in no case the maximum amount of 
    withdrawal for purposes specified in sub-rule (2) of rule 17 shall exceed 
    the maximum limit prescribed from time to time under rule 2(a) and rule 3(b) 
    of the scheme of the Ministry of Urban Development for the grant of advances 
    for house building purposes:
 
Provided further that in the case of a 
    subscriber who has availed himself of an advance under the scheme of the 
    Ministry of Urban Development for the grant of advances for house building 
    purposes, or has been allowed any assistance in this regard from any other 
    Government sources, the sum withdrawn under this sub-rule together with the 
    amount of advance taken under the aforesaid scheme or the assistance taken 
    from any other Government source shall not exceed the maximum limit 
    prescribed from time to time under rules 2(a) and 3(b) of the aforesaid 
    scheme.
 
Note 1.—A withdrawal sanctioned to a 
    subscriber under clause (i) of sub-rule (2) of rule 17 may be drawn in 
    instalments, the number of which shall not exceed four in a period of twelve 
    calendar months counted from the date of sanction.
 
Note 2.—In cases where a subscriber has 
    to pay in instalments for a site or a house or flat purchased, or a house or 
    flat constructed through the Delhi Development Authority or a State Housing 
    Board or a House Building Cooperative Society he shall be permitted to make 
    a withdrawal as and when he is called upon to make  a payment in any 
    instalment. Every such payment shall be treated as a payment for a separate 
    purpose for rule 16.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> A subscriber who has been permitted to 
    withdraw money from Fund under rule 17 shall satisfy the sanctioning 
    authority within such reasonable period as may be specified by that 
    authority that the money has been utilised for the purpose for which it was 
    withdrawn, and if he fails to do so, the whole of the sum so withdrawn, or 
    so much thereof as has not been applied for the purpose for which it was 
    withdrawn shall forthwith be repaid in one lump sum by the subscriber to the 
    Fund and in default of such payment, it shall be ordered by the sanctioning 
    authority to be recovered from his emoluments either in lump sum or in such 
    number of monthly instalments, as may be determined by the Director-General:
 
Provided that before repayment of a withdrawal 
    is enforced under this sub-rule, the subscriber shall be given a reasonable 
    opportunity to explain in writing and within 15 days of the receipt of the 
    communication why the repayment shall not be enforced and if the sanctioning 
    authority is not satisfied with the explanation or no explanation is 
    submitted by the subscriber within the said period of 15 days the 
    sanctioning authority shall enforce the repayment in the manner prescribed 
    in this sub-rule.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number>(a) A subscriber who has been permitted 
    under clause (i), (ii) or (iii) of sub-rule (2) of rule 17 to withdraw money 
    from the amount standing to his credit in the Fund, shall not part with the 
    possession of the house, built or acquired, or house-site purchased with the 
    money so withdrawn, whether by way of sale, mortgage (other than mortgage to 
    the Director-General), gift, exchange or otherwise, without the previous 
    permission of the Director-General:
 
Provided that such permission shall not be 
    necessary for—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the 
    house or house-site being leased for any term not exceeding three years, or  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   its 
    being mortgaged in favour of a Housing Board, Nationalised Banks, the Life 
    Insurance Corporation or any other Corporation owned or controlled by the 
    Central Government which advances loans for the construction of a new house 
    or for making additions or alteration to an existing house.  
 <subsubsection>
<number>b</number> The subscriber shall submit a declaration 
    not later than the 31st day of December of every year as to whether the 
    house or the house-site as the case may be, continues to be in his 
    possession or has been mortgaged, otherwise transferred or let out as 
    aforesaid and shall, if so required, produce before the sanctioning 
    authority on or before the date specified by that authority in that behalf, 
    the original sale, mortgage or lease deed and also the documents on which 
    his title to the property is based.
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>c</number> If at any time before his retirement, the 
    subscriber parts with the possession of the house or house-site without 
    obtaining the previous permission of the Director-General, he shall 
    forthwith repay the sum so withdrawn by him in default of such repayment, 
    the sanctioning authority shall, after giving the subscriber a reasonable 
    opportunity for making a representation in the matter cause the said sum to 
    be recovered from the emoluments of the subscriber either in lump sum or in 
    such number of monthly instalments, as may be determined by it.
 
Note.—A subscriber who has taken loan 
    from ESI Corporation in lieu thereof mortgaged the house or house-site to 
    the Corporation shall be required to furnish the declaration to the 
    following effect, namely:—
 

Declaration 
 
“I do hereby certify that the 
    house or house-site for the construction of which or for the acquisition of 
    which I have taken a final withdrawal from the Provident Fund continues to 
    be in my possession but stands mortgaged to Corporation”.
 
  


</subsubsection></subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> Conversion of an advance into a 
    withdrawal.—A subscriber who has already drawn or may draw in future an 
    advance under rule 14 for any of the purposes specified therein may convert, 
    at his discretion by written request addressed to the Accounts Officer 
    through the sanctioning authority, the balance outstanding against it into a 
    final withdrawal on his satisfying the conditions laid down in rules 17 and 
    18.
 
Note 1.—The Head of office in case of 
    non-gazetted subscribers and the Treasury Officer concerned in the case of 
    gazetted subscribers may be asked by the administrative authority to stop 
    recoveries from the pay bills. When the application for such conversion is 
    forwarded to the Accounts Officer that authority shall endorse a copy of the 
    letter forwarding the subscriber’s intimation to the Treasury Officer from 
    where he draws his pay in order to permit stoppage of further recoveries.
 
Note 2.—For the purpose of sub-rule 
<section><number>1</number> 
    of rule 18, the amount of subscription with interest thereon standing to the 
    credit of the subscriber in the account at the time of conversion plus the 
    outstanding amount of advance shall be taken as the balance. Each withdrawal 
    shall be treated as a separate one and the same principle shall apply in the 
    event of more than one conversion.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> Final withdrawal of accumulation in the 
    Fund.—When a subscriber quits the service of the Corporation the amount 
    standing to his credit in the Fund shall become payable to him:
 
Provided that a subscriber, who has been 
    dismissed from the service and is subsequently reinstated in the service, 
    shall if required to do so by the Director-General, repay any amount paid to 
    him from the fund in pursuance of this rule, with interest thereon at the 
    rate provided in rule 13 in the manner prescribed in the proviso to rule 21. 
    The amount so repaid shall be credited to his account in the Fund.
 
Explanation 1.—A subscriber, other than 
    one who is appointed on contract or one who has retired from service and is 
    subsequently re-employed, with or without a break in service shall not be 
    deemed to quit the service, when he is transferred without any break in 
    service to a new post under a State Government or in another department of 
    the Central Government (in which he is governed by another set of provident 
    fund rules) and without retaining any connection with his former post, in 
    such case, his subscriptions together with interest thereon shall be 
    transferred—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   to his 
    account in the other Fund in accordance with the rules of that Fund, if the 
    new post is in another department of the Central Government, or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   to a new 
    account under the State Government concerned if the new post is under a 
    State Government and the State Government consents, by general or special 
    order, to such transfer of his subscriptions and interest.  
 
Note.—Transfers shall include cases of 
    resignation from the service in order to take up appointment in another 
    department of the Central Government or under the State Government without 
    any break and with proper permission of the Central Government. In cases 
    where there has been a break in service it shall be limited to the joining 
    time allowed on transfer to a different station.
 
The same shall hold good in cases of 
    retrenchments followed by immediate employment whether under the same or 
    different Government.
 
Explanation II.—When a subscriber, 
    other than one who is appointed on contract or one who has retired from 
    service and is subsequently re-employed or is transferred, without any 
    break, to the service under a body corporate owned or controlled by 
    Government, or an autonomous organisation, registered under the Societies 
    Registration Act, 1860 (21 of 1860), the amount of subscriptions together 
    with interest thereon, shall not be paid to him but shall be transferred 
    with the consent of that body to his new Provident Fund Account under that 
    body.
 
Transfers shall include cases of registration 
    from service in order to take up appointment under a body corporate owned or 
    controlled by Government or an autonomous organisation, registered under the 
    Societies Registration Act, 1860, without any break and with proper 
    permission of the Central Government. The time taken to join the new post 
    shall not be treated as a break in service if it does not exceed the joining 
    time admissible to a Government servant on transfer from one post to 
    another:
 
Provided that the amount of subscription 
    together with interest thereon, of a subscriber opting for service under a 
    public enterprise may, if he so desires, be transferred to his new Provident 
    Fund Account under the enterprise if the concerned Enterprise also agreed to 
    such a transfer. If, however, the subscriber does not desire the transfer or 
    the concerned Enterprise does not operate a Provident Fund, the amount 
    aforesaid shall be refunded to the subscriber.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> Retirement of Subscriber.—When a 
    subscriber—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   has 
    proceeded on leave preparatory to retirement or if he is employed in a 
    vacation department on leave preparatory to retirement combined with 
    vacation, or    
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   while on 
    leave, has been permitted to retire or been declared by a competent medical 
    authority to be unfit for further service the amount standing to his credit 
    in the Fund shall, upon application made by him in that behalf to the 
    Accounts Officer, become payable to the subscriber:  
 
Provided that the subscriber, if he returns to 
    duty, shall if required to do so by the Director-General, repay the fund, 
    for credit to his account, the amount paid to him from the fund in pursuance 
    of this rule with interest thereon at the rate provided in rule 13 in cash 
    or securities by instalments or otherwise, by recovery from his emoluments 
    or otherwise, as may be directed by the authority competent to sanction an 
    advance for the grant of which special reasons are required under sub-rule 
    (2) or rule 14.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>22</number> Procedure on death of subscriber.—On 
    the death of a subscriber before the amount standing to his credit has 
    become payable, or where the amount has become payable before payment has 
    been made—
 <section>
<number>i</number>   When the 
    subscriber leaves a family—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   if a nomination made by the subscriber 
    in accordance with the provisions of rule 7 or of the corresponding rule 
    heretofore in force in favour of a member or members of his family subsists, 
    the amount standing to his credit in the Fund or the part thereof to which 
    the nomination relates shall become payable to his nominee or nominees in 
    the proportion specified in the nomination;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   if no such nomination in favour of a 
    member or members of the family of the subscriber subsists, or if such 
    nomination relates only to a part of the amount standing to his credit in 
    the Fund, the whole amount or the part thereof to which the nomination does 
    not relate, as the case may be, shall, notwithstanding any nomination 
    purporting to be in favour of any person or persons other than a member or 
    members of his family becomes payable to the members of his family in equal 
    shares:  
 
Provided that no share shall be payable to—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>1</number>   sons who have attained majority;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>2</number>   sons of a deceased son who have attained 
    majority;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>3</number>   married daughters whose husbands are 
    alive;  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>4</number>   married daughters of a deceased son 
    whose husbands are alive;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   if there is any member of the family 
    other than those specified in clauses (1), (2), (3) and (4):  
 
Provided further that the widow or widows and 
    the child or children of a deceased son shall receive between them in equal 
    parts only the share which that son would have received if he had survived 
    the subscriber and had been exempted from the provisions of clause (1) to 
    the first proviso:  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>ii</number>   when 
    the subscriber leaves no family, if a nomination made by him in accordance 
    with the provisions of rule 7 or of the corresponding rule heretofore in 
    favour of any person or persons subsist, the amount standing to his credit 
    in the Fund or the part thereof to which the nomination relates, shall 
    become payable to his nominee or nominees in the proportion specified in the 
    nomination.  
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> Deposit-Linked Insurance Scheme.—On 
    the death of a subscriber on or before 30th September, 1991 and to whom rule 
    24 does not apply, the person entitled to receive the amount standing to the 
    credit of the subscriber shall be paid by the Accounts Officer an additional 
    amount equal to the average balance in the account during the 3 years 
    immediately preceding the death of such subscriber subject to the condition 
    that—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the 
    balance at the credit of such subscriber shall not at any time during the 
    three years preceding the month of death have fallen below the limits of—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Rs. 4000 in the case of a subscriber who 
    has held for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a post 
    the maximum of the pay scale of which is Rs. 1,300 or more in the 
    pre-revised scale;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Rs. 2500 in the case of a subscriber 
    who has held, for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a 
    post of the maximum of the pay scale of which is Rs. 900 or more but less 
    than Rs. 1300 in the pre-revised scale;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Rs. 1500 in the case of a subscriber 
    who has held, for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a 
    post the maximum of the pay scale of which is Rs. 291 or more but less than 
    Rs. 900 in the pre-revised scale;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   Rs. 1000 in the case of a subscriber 
    who has held, for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a 
    post the maximum of the pay scale of which is less than Rs. 291 in the 
    pre-revised scale.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>   the 
    additional amount payable under this rule shall not exceed Rs. 10,000;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the 
    subscriber has put in at least five years’ service at the time of his death.  
 
Note 1.—The average balance shall be 
    worked out on the basis of the balance at the credit of the subscriber at 
    the end of each of the 36 months preceding the month in which the death 
    occurs. For this purpose, as also for checking the minimum balances 
    prescribed above—
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>   the 
    balance at the end of March shall include the annual interest credited in 
    terms of rule 13;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if the 
    last of the aforesaid 36 months is not March, the balance at the end of the 
    said last month shall include interest in respect of the period from the 
    beginning of the financial year in which death occurs, to the end of the 
    said last month.  
 
Note 2.—Payments under this scheme 
    should be  in whole rupee. If an amount due includes a fraction of a rupee 
    it should be rounded to the nearest rupee (50 paise counting as the next 
    higher rupee).
 
Note 3.—Any sum payable under this 
    scheme is in the nature of insurance money and, therefore, the statutory 
    protection given by section 3 of the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925), 
    does not apply to sums payable under this scheme.
 
Note 4.—This scheme also applies to 
    those subscribers to the Fund who are transferred to an autonomous 
    organisation consequent upon conversion of a Government Department into such 
    a body and who, on such transfer, opt, in terms of option given to them, to 
    subscriber to this Fund in accordance with these rules.
 
Note 5.—(a) In case of a Government 
    servant who has been admitted to the benefit of the Fund under rule 26 or 
    27, but dies before completion of three years service, or as the case may 
    be, five years service from the date of his admission to the fund, that 
    period of his service under the previous employer in respect whereof the 
    amount of his subscriptions and the employer’s contribution, if any, 
    together with interest have been received, shall count for purposes of 
    clause (a) and clause (c) of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> In case of persons appointed on tenure 
    basis and in the case of re-employed pensioners, service rendered from the 
    date of such appointment of re-employment, as the case may be, only will 
    count for purpose of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> This scheme does not apply to persons 
    appointed on contract basis.
 
Note 6.—The budget estimates of 
    expenditure in respect of this scheme will be prepared by the Accounts 
    Officer responsible for maintenance of the accounts of the Fund having 
    regard to the trend of expenditure, in the same manner as estimates are 
    prepared for other retirement benefits.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> Deposit-Linked Insurance Revised 
    Scheme.—On the death of a subscriber, the person entitled to receive the 
    amount standing to the credit of the subscriber shall be paid by the 
    Accounts Officer an additional amount equal to the average balance in the 
    account during the 3 years immediately preceding the death of such 
    subscriber, subject to the condition that—
 <section>
<number>a</number>   the 
    balance at the credit of such subscriber shall not at any time during the 3 
    years preceding the month of death have fallen below the limits of—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   Rs. 12,000 in the case of subscriber who 
    has held, for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a 
    post of maximum of the pay scale of which is Rs. 4000 or more.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   Rs. 7500 in the case of a subscriber 
    who has held for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a 
    post of the maximum of the pay scale of which is Rs. 2900 or more but less 
    than Rs. 4000.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   Rs. 4500 in the case of a subscriber 
    who has held for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a 
    post of the maximum of the pay scale of which is Rs. 1151 or more but less 
    than Rs. 2900.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   Rs. 3000 in the case of a subscriber 
    who has held for the greater part of the aforesaid period of three years, a 
    post of the maximum of the pay scale of which is less than Rs. 1151.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>b</number>   the 
    additional amount payable under this rule shall not exceed Rs. 30,000.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the 
    subscriber has put in at least 5 years’ service at the time of his/her 
    death.  
 
Note 1.—The average balance shall be 
    worked out on the basis of the balance at the end of each of the 36 months, 
    preceding the month in which the death occurs. For this purpose, as also for 
    checking the maximum balance prescribed above—
 </section><section>
<number>a</number>   the 
    balance at the end of March shall include the annual interest credited in 
    terms of rule 13;  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   if the 
    last of the aforesaid 36 months is not March, the balance at the end of said 
    last month shall include interest in respect of the period from the 
    beginning of the financial year in which death occurs to the end of the said 
    last month.  
 
Note 2.—Payment under this scheme will 
    be in whole rupee. If an amount due includes a fraction of a rupee it should 
    be rounded to the nearest rupee (50 paise counting as the higher rupee).
 
Note 3.—Any sum payable under this 
    scheme is in the nature of insurance money and therefore, the statutory 
    protection given by section 3 of the Provident Funds Act, 1925 (19 of 1925) 
    does not apply to sums payable under this scheme.
 
Note 4.—The scheme also applies to 
    those subscribers to the funds who are transferred to an autonomous 
    organisation consequent upon conversion of a Government Department into such 
    a body and who, on such transfer, opt in terms of option given to them to 
    subscribe to the Fund in accordance with these rules.
 
Note 5.—(a) In case of a Government 
    servant who has been admitted to the benefits of the fund under Rule 26 or 
    27 but died before completion of three years of service or as the case may 
    be, five years of service from the date of his admission to the Fund, the 
    period of his service under the previous employer in respect whereof the 
    amount of his subscription and the employer’s contribution, if any, together 
    with interest have been recovered, shall count for the purpose of clause (a) 
    and clause (c) of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> In case of persons appointed on tenure 
    basis and in the case of re-employed pensioners, service rendered from the 
    date of such appointment on re-employment, as the case may be, only will 
    count for the purposes of this rule.
 </section><section>
<number>c</number> The scheme does not apply to persons 
    appointed on contract basis.
 
Note 6.—The Budget Estimates of 
    expenditure in respect of this scheme will be prepared by the Accounts 
    Officer responsible for maintenance of the account of the Fund having regard 
    to the trend of expenditure, in the same manner as estimates are prepared 
    for other retirement benefits.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> Manner of payment of amount in the 
    Fund.—
<section><number>1</number> When the amount standing to the credit of a subscriber in the 
    Funds become payable, it shall be the duty of the Accounts Officer to make 
    payment on receipt of a written application in this behalf as provided in 
    sub-rule (3).
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> If the person whom, under these rules, any 
    amount of policy is to be paid, assigned or reassigned or delivered; is a 
    lunatic for whose estate a manager has been appointed in this behalf under 
    the Lunacy Act, 1912 (4 of 1912), the payment or reassignment or delivery 
    shall be made to such manager and not to the lunatic:
 
Provided that where no manager has been 
    appointed and the person to whom the sum is payable is certified by a 
    magistrate to be lunatic, the payment shall under the orders of the 
    Collector be made in terms of sub-section (1) section 93 of the Lunacy Act, 
    1912 (4 of 1912), to the person having charge of such lunatic and the 
    Accounts Officer shall pay only the amount which he thinks fit to the person 
    having charge of the lunatic and the surplus, if any, or such part thereof, 
    as he thinks fit shall be paid for the maintenance of such members of the 
    lunatic’s family as are dependent on him for maintenance.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Payment of the amount to be withdrawn 
    shall be made in India only. The persons to whom the amounts are payable 
    shall make their own arrangements to receive payment in India. The following 
    procedure shall be adopted for claiming payment by a subscriber, namely:—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   to 
    enable a subscriber to submit an application for withdrawal of the amount in 
    the Fund, the Head of Office shall send to every subscriber necessary Forms 
    either one year in advance of the date on which the subscriber attains the 
    age of superannuation, or before the date of his anticipated retirement, if 
    earlier, with instructions that they should he returned to him duly 
    completed within a period of one month from the date of receipt of the forms 
    by the subscriber. The subscriber shall submit the application to the 
    Accounts Officer through the Head of Office or Department for payment of the 
    amount in the Fund. The application shall be made—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>a</number>   for the amount standing to his credit in 
    the Fund as indicated in the Accounts Statements for the year ending one 
    year prior to the date of his superannuation, or his anticipated date of 
    retirement, or   
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>b</number>   for the amount indicated in his ledger 
    account in case of the Accounts Statement has not been received by the 
    subscriber.  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the 
    Head of Office or Department shall forward the application to the Accounts 
    Officer indicating the recoveries effected against the advances which are 
    still current and the number of instalments yet to be recovered and also 
    indicate the withdrawals, if any, taken by the subscriber after the period 
    covered by the last statement or the subscriber’s accounts sent by the 
    Accounts Officer.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   The 
    Accounts Officer shall, after verification with the ledger account, issue an 
    authority for the amount indicated in the application at least a month 
    before the date of superannuation but payable on the date of superannuation.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iv</number>   The 
    authority mentioned in clause (iii) will constitute the first instalment of 
    payment. A second authority for payment will be issued as soon as possible 
    after superannuation. This will relate to the contribution made by the 
    subscriber subsequent to the amount mentioned in the application submitted 
    under clause (i) plus the refund of instalments against advances which were 
    current at the time of the first application.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>v</number>   after 
    forwarding the application for final payment to the Accounts Officer, 
    advance/withdrawal may be sanctioned but the amount of advance/withdrawal 
    shall be drawn on an authorisation from the Accounts Officer concerned who 
    shall arrange this as soon as formal sanction of sanctioning authority is 
    received by him.  
 
Note.—When the amount standing to the 
    credit of a subscriber has become payable under rules 20, 21 and 22 the 
    Accounts Officer shall authorise prompt payment of the amount in the manner 
    indicated in sub-rule (3).
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> Procedure on transfer of a Government 
    servant from one Department to another.—
<section><number>a</number> If a Government servant who 
    is a subscriber to any other non-contributory Provident Fund of the Central 
    Government or of a State Government is permanently transferred to 
    pensionable service in a Department of the Central Government in which he is 
    governed by these rules, the amount of subscriptions, together with interest 
    thereon, standing to his credit to such other Fund on the date of transfer 
    shall be transferred to his credit in the Fund:
 
Provided that where a subscriber was 
    subscribing to a non-contributory Provident Fund of a State Government the 
    consent of that Government shall be obtained.
 </section><section>
<number>b</number> If a Government servant who is a 
    subscriber to the State Railways Provident Fund or any other Contributory 
    Provident Fund of the Central Government or a State Contributory Provident 
    Fund is permanently transferred to pensionable service in a Department of 
    Central Government in which he is governed by these rules and unless such a 
    subscriber elects to continue to be governed by the rules of such Fund, when 
    the rules option is given—
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the 
    amount of subscriptions with interest thereon, standing to his credit in 
    such Contributory Provident Fund on the date of transfer shall with the 
    consent of the other Government, if any, be transferred to his credit in the 
    Fund;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the 
    amount of Government contributions, with interest thereon, standing to his 
    credit in such Contributory Provident Fund shall, with the consent of the 
    other Government, if any, be credited to the Central Revenue (Civil);  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   he 
    shall thereupon be entitled to count towards pension, service rendered prior 
    to the date of permanent transfer, to the extent permissible under the 
    relevant pension rules.  
 
Note 1.—The provisions of this rule 
    does not apply to a subscriber who has retired from service, or to a 
    subscriber who was holding the former appointment on contract.
 
Note 2.—The provisions of this rule 
    shall, however apply to persons, who are appointed without break whether 
    temporarily or permanently to a post carrying the benefits of these rules 
    after resignation or retirement from service under another Department of 
    Central Government or under the State Government.
 
  


</subsection></section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>27</number> Procedure on transfer.—On transfer 
    to Government service of a person from the service under a body corporate 
    owned or controlled by Government or an autonomous organisation, registered 
    under the Societies Registration Act, 1860. If a Government servant admitted 
    to the benefit of the Fund was subscriber to any Provident Fund of a body 
    corporate owned or controlled by Government or an autonomous organisation, 
    registered under the Societies Registration Act, 1860, the amount of his 
    subscriptions and the employer’s contribution, if any, together with the 
    interest thereon shall be transferred to his credit in the Fund with the 
    consent of that body.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> Transfer of amount to the Contributory 
    Provident Fund (India).—If a subscriber to the Fund is subsequently 
    admitted to the benefits of the Contributory Provident Fund (India) the 
    amount of his subscriptions, together with interest therein, shall be 
    transferred to the credit of his account in the Contributory Provident Fund 
    (India).
 
Note.—The provisions of this rule do 
    not apply to a subscriber who is appointed on contract or who has retired 
    from service and is subsequently re-employed with or without a break in 
    service in another post carrying Contributory Provident Fund benefits.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number> Relaxation of the 
      provisions of the rules in individual cases.—When the Standing 
      Committee is satisfied that the operation of any of these rules causes or 
      is likely to cause undue hardship to a subscriber, it may, notwithstanding 
      anything contained in these rules after recording its reasons for so doing 
      deal with the case of such subscriber in such manner as may appear to it 
      to be just and equitable.
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> Number of account to be quoted at the 
    time of the payment of subscription.—When paying a subscription in 
    India, either by deduction from emoluments or in cash, a subscriber shall 
    quote the number of his account in the Fund which shall be communicated to 
    him by the Accounts Officer. Any change in the number shall similarly be 
    communicated to the subscriber by the Accounts Officer.
 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>31</number> Annual Statement of account to be 
    supplied to the subscriber.—
<section><number>1</number> As soon as possible after the close of 
    each year, the Accounts Officer shall send to each subscriber a statement of 
    his account in the Fund showing the opening balance as on the 1st April of 
    the year, the total amount credited or debited during the year, the total 
    amount of interest credited as on the 31st March of the year and closing 
    balance on that date. The Accounts Officer shall attach to the statement of 
    accounts an enquiry whether the subscriber—
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   desires 
    to make any alteration in any nomination made under rule 7; or under the 
    corresponding rule heretofore in force.  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   has 
    acquired a family, in cases where the subscriber has made no nomination in 
    favour of a member of his family under the proviso to sub-rule (1) of rule 
    7.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> Subscribers should satisfy themselves as 
    to the correctness of the annual statement, and errors should be brought to 
    the notice of the Accounts Officer within three months from the date of 
    receipt of the Statement.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The Accounts Officer shall, if required by 
    a subscriber, once but not more than once in a year inform the subscriber of 
    the total amount standing to his credit in the Fund at the end of the last 
    month for which his account has been written up.
 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>32</number> Interpretation.—If any question 
    arises relating to interpretation of these rules, it shall be referred to 
    the Central Government, the Ministry of Labour shall decide the same.
 
 
  
  
 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the Employees’ State Insurance Corporation 
    (General Provident Fund) Rules, 1995
 

 
 

 
 



    Schedule I
 


[See rule 7(3)]
 



    Form of Nomination
 


Account No. ....................
 

 
 


I, 
    ............................................., hereby nominate the person(s) 
    mentioned below who is/are member(s) of my family as defined in rule 2 to 
    receive the amount that may stand to my credit in the Fund as indicated 
    below, in the event of my death before that amount has become payable or 
    having become payable has not been paid.
 


1. Name and full address of the nominee(s).
 


2. Relationship with the subscriber.
 


3. Age of the nominee(s).
 


4. Share payable to each nominee.
 


5. Contingencies on the happening of which the 
    nomination will become invalid.
 


6. Name, address &amp; relationship of the 
    person(s) if any to whom the right of nominee shall pass in the event of 
    his/her predeceasing the subscriber.
 


7. If the nominee is not a member of the 
    family as defined indicate the reasons.
 

 
 


Dated this .............................. day 
    of ....................20........... at.............................
 


Signature of 
    subscriber.............................
 


Name in block 
    letters................................
 


 
 


Two witnesses to 
    signature                                        Signature
 


1.  
    Signature..........................................                        
    1...................................
 


     
    Name and Address.............................                         
    2...................................
 


2.  
    Signature..........................................
 


     
    Name and Address............................
 


Reverse of the Form
 


Space 
    for use by the head of office/pay  

    and accounts office
 


Nomination by Shri/Smt/Kumari..................................... 
    Designation ............................ Date of receipt of 
    nomination................................................
 


Signature of Head of Office/Accounts Officer          
    
 



    Designation.....................................................
 



    Date..............................................................
 



    Instructions for the Subscriber
 


(a) Your name may be filled in.
 


(b) Name of the Fund may be completed 
    suitably.
 


(c) Definition of term “family” as given in 
    the General Provident Funds (CS) Rules, 1960 is reproduced below:
 


Family means—
 


(i)   in the case of a male subscriber, the 
    wife or wives, parents, children, minor brothers, unmarried sisters, 
    deceased son’s widow and children and where no parent of the subscriber is 
    alive, a paternal grandparent:
 


Provided that if a subscriber proves that his 
    wife has been judicially separated from him or has ceased under the 
    customary law of the community to which she belongs to be entitled to 
    maintenance she shall henceforth be deemed to be no longer a member of the 
    subscriber’s family in matters to which these rules relate unless the 
    subscriber subsequently intimates in writing to the Accounts Officer that 
    she shall continue to be so regarded.
 


(ii)   In the case of a female subscriber, the 
    husband, parents, children, minor brothers, unmarried sisters, deceased 
    son’s widow and children and where no parent of the subscriber is alive, a 
    paternal grandparent:
 


Provided that if a subscriber by notice in 
    writing to the Accounts Officer expresses her desire to exclude her husband 
    from her family, the husband shall henceforth be deemed to be no longer a 
    member of the subscriber’s family in matter to which these rules relate 
    unless the subscriber subsequently cancelled such notice in writing.
 


Note.—Child means legitimate child and 
    includes an adopted child where adoption is recognised by the personal law 
    governing the subscriber.
 


(d) Column 4 if only one person is nominated 
    the words “in full” should be written against the nominee. If more than one 
    person is nominated, the share payable to each nominee over the whole amount 
    of the Provident Fund shall be specified.
 


(e) Column 5 death of nominee(s) should not be 
    mentioned as contingency in this column. 
 


(f) Column 6 do not mention your name.
 


(g) Draw a line across the blank space below 
    last entry to prevent insertion of any name after you have signed.
 


 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 




the Employees’ State Insurance Corporation 
    (General Provident Fund) Rules, 1995
 

 
 

 
 



    Schedule II
 


[See rule 14(3) and 17(1)]
 



    Application for Advance/Withdrawal from General Provident Fund
 

 
 


1. Name of the 
    subscriber.......................................................
 


2. Account Number 
    ................................................................
 


3. Designation 
    .........................................................................
 


4.   (1)   Pay 
    Rs..............................................................................
 


      (2)   Monthly 
    subscription Rs................................................
 


5. In case of withdrawal
 


(i)   Date of 
    Birth..............................................................
 


(ii)   Date of 
    appointment...............................................
 


(iii)   Date of 
    superannuation.........................................
 


Balance at credit of the subscriber on the 
    date of application as below:
 


(i)   Closing balance as per statement for the 
    year 20........ Rs......
 


(ii)   Credit from.......... to........... on 
    account of monthly subscription Rs. ................
 


(iii)   Refund Rs. ..........................
 


(iv)   Withdrawals during the period from 
    .............. to .................. Rs. .................
 


(v)   Net balance at credit Rs. 
    .......................
 


6. Amount of advance outstanding, if any, and 
    the purpose for which advance was taken by them:—
 


    Amount of advance taken Rs. 
    ..............................................
 


    Balance outstanding as on 
    date Rs. .....................................
 


7. Amount of advance required Rs. 
    ....................................
 


8.   (a) Purpose for which the advance is 
    required ..............
 


      (b) Rules under 
    which the request is covered ...................
 


      (c) If advance 
    is sought for House Building, etc., following information may be given:—
 


(1)   Location and measurement of the plot 
    ......................
 


(2)   Whether plot is freehold or on lease 
    ..........................
 


(3)   Plan for construction 
    ....................................................
 


(4)   If the flat or plot being purchased is 
    from a H.B. Society, the name of the Society, the location and measurements, 
    etc....................
 


(5)   Cost of construction 
    .....................................................
 


(6)   If the purchase of flat from DDA or any 
    Housing Board, etc. the location, dimension, etc. may be 
    given......................
 


       (d)   If 
    advance is required for education of children, following details may be 
    given:—
 


(1)   Name of the son/daughter 
    ............................
 


(2)   Class and Institution/College where 
    studying..........................
 


(3)   Whether a day-scholar or a hosteller 
    ............................
 


       (e)   If 
    advance is required for treatment of ailing family members, following 
    details may be given:—
 


(1)   Name of the patient and relationship 
    ............................
 


(2)   Name of the Hospital/Dispensary/Doctor 
    where the patient is undergoing treatment ............................
 


(3)   Whether outdoor/indoor patient 
    ............................
 


(4)   Whether reimbursement available or not 
    ............................
 


Note.—In case of advance under 8(c) to 
    8(e), no certificate or documentary evidence would be required.
 


9. Amount of the consolidated advance (Items 6 
    and 7) and number of monthly instalments in which the consolidated advance 
    is proposed to be repaid Rs. ........... in instalments.
 


10. Full particulars of the pecuniary 
    circumstances of the subscriber, justifying the application for the advance.
 

 
 


I, certify that the particulars given above 
    are correct and complete to the best of my knowledge and belief and that 
    nothing has been concealed by me.
 


 
 


Signature of Applicant                        
    
 


Name 
    ............................................
 


Designation 
    ....................................
 


Section/Branch ...............................
 


Dated............................
 


Recommendation/Remarks of the Competent 
    Authority.
 


 
 



    Signature............................................
 



    Designation.........................................
 


Dated...............................
 


 
 



 


 
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>