<act><title>


The Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators 
(Receipt, Management and Disposal of Forfeited Property) Rules, 20061</title> 

 


 <article>
<number>1</number> Short title and 
commencement.—
<section><number>1</number> 
These rules may be called the Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators 
(Receipt, Management and Disposal of Forfeited Property) Rules, 2006.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> They shall come into 
force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette.
 
 



</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>2</number> Definitions.—In 
these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,—
 <section>
       
<number>a</number>  “Act” means the Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators 
(Forfeiture of Property) Act, 1976 (13 of 1976);
 </section><section>
       
<number>b</number>  “competent authority” means an officer of the Central Government 
authorised by it under sub-section (1) of section 5;
 </section><section>
       
<number>c</number>  “Form” means form annexed to these rules;
 </section><section>
       
<number>d</number>  “godown” means godown for storage of property forfeited under section 
7 of the Act;
 </section><section>
       
<number>e</number>  “public auction” means the auction as described in the manner as laid 
down in Second Schedule of the Income-tax Act, 1961 (43 of 1961);
 </section><section>
        
<number>f</number>  “sealed tender” means the tenders covered with envelopes stamped with 
seal;
 </section><section>
       
<number>g</number>  the words and expressions used but not defined in these rules shall 
have the same meanings respectively assigned to them in the Act.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>3</number> Assistance to the 
competent authority.—The 
Central Government may provide from time to time such members of staff and other 
persons as it thinks fit to assist the competent authority in performing the 
functions under these rules.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>4</number> Designation of 
godowns.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The competent authority shall designate as many godowns as may be necessary for 
the storage of property mentioned in the orders made under section 7 of the Act.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The competent 
authority shall select godowns referred to in sub-rule (1), keeping in view the 
security of the premises, storage capacity, nature of property and other 
relevant factors.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> Each designated godown 
shall have a godown keeper and a godown-in-charge to assist the competent 
authority.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>5</number> Proper accounting of 
properties.—The 
competent authority shall, at the time of receiving properties, ensure proper 
identification of such property with reference to its particulars mentioned in 
the order made under section 7 of the Act.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>6</number> Godown register.—The 
competent authority shall cause a register in Form I for recording entries in 
respect of property other than the properties referred to in rule 7, to be 
maintained.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>7</number> Godown register for 
valuables.—The 
competent authority shall cause a register in Form II for recording entries in 
respect of property, namely, gold and gold jewellery, diamonds, precious and 
semi-precious stones (hereinafter called “valuables”) to be maintained.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>8</number> Storage of property.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The competent authority shall ensure that the packages containing valuables are 
kept in the godown in an iron safe and vault, under double lock system, one key 
remaining with the godown-keeper and the other to be retained by the godown-in-charge.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Where, for any valid 
reasons, it is found that the packages containing valuables may not be kept in 
godown, such packages shall be kept in lockers obtaining exclusively for this 
purpose, either with any branch of the Reserve Bank of India or of any 
nationalised bank.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The packages referred 
to in sub-rules (1) and (2) shall be stored systematically case-wise, 
serial-wise, year-wise and with proper identification marks to facilitate 
re-check and inspection.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>9</number> Management of land 
and building.—The 
competent authority may authorise any officer referred to in section 17 of the 
Act to take possession of land or building in respect of which an order under 
section 7 has been passed or where the person affected has failed to pay the 
fine under sub-section 
<section><number>1</number> of section 9 within the time allowed under that 
section.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>10</number> Record of land or 
building.—The 
competent authority shall maintain a record of land or building in Form III.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>11</number> Storage of property 
other than valuables.—
<section><number>1</number> 
The movable property other than valuables shall be stored in almirahs and racks.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> Each almirah and rack 
shall have a stock-card indicating the case number and full description of the 
property.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>12</number> Placement of 
stock-cards.—The 
godown-in-charge shall ensure that the racks or almirahs or any other thing used 
for storage of property, display stock-cards indicating the case number and full 
description of the property stored.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>13</number> Opening and 
re-sealing of the packages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Where any package is to be opened for any reason, the same shall be opened in 
the presence of the owner and the concerned godown-in-charge after obtaining the 
order of the competent authority in this respect.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The packages shall be 
re-sealed immediately after the purpose for which such packages were opened is 
fulfilled, in the presence of the owner and the concerned godown-in-charge.
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> At the time of 
re-sealing, the owner and the concerned godown-in-charge shall affix their 
seals.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>14</number> Maintenance of 
forfeited conveyances.—Conveyances, 
such as aircraft, vessel, motor vehicle and any other mode of conveyance shall 
be properly maintained by the godown-in-charge till its disposal.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>15</number> Disposal of 
livestocks, perishable etc.—Subject 
to the sale proceeds being credited into the account of the Central Government, 
the competent authority shall dispose of the livestocks and property which is 
perishable in nature or prone to decay in the manner deemed fit.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>16</number> Disposal of 
valuables.—Subject 
to the sale proceeds being credited into the account of the Central Government, 
the competent authority shall dispose of the valuables mentioned below in the 
following manner, namely:—
 <section>
       
<number>1</number>  Gold, Gold Jewellery, Silver and Silver Jewellery—The 
valuables, namely, gold, gold jewellery, silver and silver jewellery shall be 
deposited in the Government of India mints which shall credit the value of such 
property to the Central Government.
 </section><section>
       
<number>2</number>  Diamonds and precious and semi-precious stones shall be sold by public 
auction failing which by tender after valuation by Government approved valuer.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>17</number> Deposit of 
currency.—
<section><number>1</number> 
Indian and foreign currency shall be deposited with the Reserve Bank of India or 
any nationalised bank.
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The amount so 
deposited shall be credited into the account of the Central Government.
</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>18</number> Disposal of 
conveyance.—Subject 
to the sale proceeds being credited into the account of the Central Government, 
conveyances, such as aircrafts, vessels, vehicles and other modes of conveyance 
shall be sold by public auction failing which by tender.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>19</number> Disposal of land or 
building.—Subject 
to the relevant provisions of any law relating to the acquisition or disposal of 
immovable property and also subject to the sale proceeds being credited into the 
account of the Central Government, land or building shall be disposed of in the 
following manner, namely:—
 <section>
       
<number>1</number>  The disposal of land or building shall be done simultaneously through 
open tender, public auction and e-auction. Bids shall be invited through 
advertisements in local newspapers and through the website of the department. 
After the sealed tenders are received, the property shall be put to public 
auction. Simultaneously, the department shall advertise through internet 
inviting bids through e-auction.* The property shall be sold to the highest 
bidder in all the three methods namely, sealed tender, public auction and 
e-auction, provided the price obtained is not less than the reserve price fixed 
at by the department.
 </section><section>
       
<number>2</number>  In case the property is not disposed of in the manner prescribed under 
sub-rule (1) of rule 19 in two attempts, the same shall be disposed of by 
inviting sealed tenders:
 <subsection>
            
<number>a</number>  the property shall be advertised in the local newspapers indicating 
the reserve price and inviting tenders. The highest bidder (subject to the 
reserve price) shall be entitled to buy the property.
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>b</number>  if the property cannot be sold in the first attempt as provided in 
clause (a), the sale of the property through sealed tender shall be advertised 
again with a proviso that the competent authority reserves the right to sell the 
property to the highest bidder who offers to buy the property for a price which 
is up to fifteen per cent. less than the reserve price.
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>c</number>  if the property remains unsold even after the attempts as provided in 
clause (a) and clause (b), the sale of the property shall be advertised again 
with a proviso that the competent authority reserves the right to sell the 
property to the highest bidder who offers to buy the property for a price which 
is up to thirty per cent. less than the reserve price.
 </subsection></section><section>
       
<number>3</number>  If the property remains unsold even after attempts as provided in 
sub-rule (1) and sub-rule (2), it shall be disposed of through a negotiated sale 
upto fifty per cent. below the reserve price to any of the following entities, 
namely:—
 <subsection>
            
<number>a</number>  Central and State Government Departments.
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>b</number>  Public Sector Undertakings.
 </subsection><subsection>
            
<number>c</number>  Local bodies.
 </subsection></section><section>
       
<number>4</number>  If the property is not sold by any of the above methods, it may be 
disposed of by the Central Government in the manner as deemed fit.
 
 


</section></article> 

 


 <article>
<number>20</number> Disposal of other 
property.—Subject 
to the sale proceeds being credited into the account of the Central Government, 
property other than those mentioned in rules 15 to 19 shall be disposed of by 
public auction failing which by tender.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>21</number> Periodical reports.—The 
godown-in-charge shall submit, every month, a report to the competent authority 
of the property received or disposed of during that period.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>22</number> Periodical 
inspection.—The 
competent authority with a view to ensuring safety, security, proper accounting 
and management of all properties in the godowns, conduct physical inspection and 
verification with the help of such officers as deemed fit.
</article> 

 


 <article>
<number>23</number> Record of receipt 
and disposal.—The 
competent authority shall maintain a record of receipt and disposal of all 
properties received and disposed of under these rules. He shall also maintain an 
account of all income received and expenditure incurred on receipt, management 
and disposal of such property.
</article><form>
 




The Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators  

(Receipt, Management and Disposal of Forfeited Property) Rules, 2006
 




 




Form I
 


(See rule 6)
 




Godown register
 


         
1.  Godown entry Sl. No.
 


         
2.  Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators Act (SAFEMA) File No.
 


         
3.  Description of property in the sealed packages/containers.
 


         
4.  Number of packages/containers.
 


         
5.  Quantity (packages/container-wise).
 


         
6.  Name(s) and address(es) of accused.
 


         
7.  Name with official designation and address of forfeiting officer.
 


         
8.  Facsimile of the seal put on the packages/containers by the forfeiting 
officer.
 


         
9.  Date and time of deposit.
 


       
10.  Particulars of exit and re-entry for exhibiting to Competent 
Authority/Tribunal.
 


       
11.  Date and time of removal for disposal.
 


       
12.  Disposal particulars.
 


      
13.  Certificate of disposal including price payment particulars and credit 
into the account of the Central Government.
 


       
14.  Remarks of the Inspecting Officer(s).
</form><form>
 




The Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators  

(Receipt, Management and Disposal of Forfeited Property) Rules, 2006
 




 




Form II
 


(See rule 7)
 




Godown Register for Valuables
 


         
1.  Godown entry Sl. No.
 


         
2.  Smugglers and Foreign Exchange Manipulators Act (SAFEMA) File No.
 


         
3.  Description of valuables in the sealed packages/containers.
 


         
4.  Number of packages/containers (item-wise).
 


         
5.  Condition of seal at the time of entry.
 


         
6.  Quantity (packages/container-wise).
 


         
7.  Name(s) and address(es) of accused.
 


         
8.  Name with official designation and address of forfeiting officer.
 


         
9.  Facsimile of the seal put on the packages/containers by the forfeiting 
officer.
 


       
10.  Date and time of deposit.
 


       
11.  Particulars of exit and re-entry for exhibiting to Competent 
Authority/Tribunal.
 


       
12.  Date and time of removal for disposal.
 


       
13.  Disposal particulars.
 


      
14.  Certificate of disposal including price payment particulars and credit 
into the Account of the Central Government.
 


       
15.  Remarks of the Inspecting Officer(s).
 

 
</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>