<act><tid>659709</tid>
<title>THE ANDHRA PRADESH AND MYSORE (TRANSFER OF TERRITORY) ACT, <year>1968</year></title>

ACT NO. 36 OF <year>1968</year>
[ 22nd August, <year>1968</year>.]

An Act to provide for the transfer of certain territory from the 
State of Mysore to the State of Andhra Pradesh and for matters 
connected therewith.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Nineteenth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:--





<article><tid>71104</tid>
<number>1</number>Short title. This Act may be called the Andhra Pradesh and 
Mysore (Transfer of Territory) Act, <year>1968</year>.


</article>



<article><tid>73758</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,--
<section><tid>1739477</tid>
<number>a</number>" appointed day" means the 1st day of October, <year>1968</year>;

</section>

<section><tid>404773</tid>
<number>b</number>" assembly constituency"," council constituency" and 
" parliamentary constituency" have the same meanings as 
in the Representation of the People Act, <year>1950</year> (43 of  
  <year>1950</year>);

</section>

<section><tid>294751</tid>
<number>c</number>" sitting member", in relation to either House of 
Parliament or of the Legislature of a State, means a 
person who, immediately before the appointed day, is a 
member of that House;

</section>

<section><tid>480615</tid>
<number>d</number>" transferred territory" means the territory specified in 
the Schedule and transferred from the State of Mysore 
to the State of Andhra Pradesh by section 3.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>357673</tid>
<number> 3</number> Transfer of territory from Mysore to Andhra Pradesh.
<section><tid>196975</tid>
<number>1</number>As  
from the appointed day, there shall be added to the State of Andhra 
Pradesh the territory specified in the Schedule which shall thereupon 
cease to form part of the State of Mysore.

</section>

<section><tid>1068352</tid>
<number>2</number>The transferred territory shall be included in, and form part 
of the Hindupur taluk of Anantapur district in the State of Andhra 
Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>1677732</tid>
<number>3</number>Nothing in sub- section (2) shall be deemed to affect the 
power of the State Government to alter, after the appointed day, the 
name, extent or boundaries of any district or taluk in the State of 
Andhra Pradesh.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>908</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1140678</tid>
<number> 4</number> Amendment of First Schedule to the Constitution. As from the 
appointed day, in the First Schedule to the Constitution, under the 
heading" I. THE STATES",--
<section><tid>1877793</tid>
<number>a</number>for the entry against" I. Andhra Pradesh", the following 
shall be substituted, namely:--
" The territories specified in sub- section (1) of 
section 3 of the Andhra State Act, <year>1953</year>, sub- section 
 (1) of section 3 of the States Reorganisation Act, 
<year>1956</year>, the First Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and 
Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, <year>1959</year>, and the 
Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and Mysore (Transfer of  
  Territory) Act, <year>1968</year>, but excluding the territories 
specified in the Second Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh 
and Madras (Alteration of Boundaries) Act, <year>1959</year>."; and


</section>

<section><tid>1705573</tid>
<number>b</number>in the entry against" 9. Mysore", after the words and 
figures" States Reorganisation Act, <year>1956</year>", the words, 
brackets and figures" but excluding the territory 
specified in the Schedule to the Andhra Pradesh and 
Mysore (Transfer of Territory) Act, <year>1968</year>" shall be 
inserted.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>738419</tid>
<number>5</number>Extent of parliamentary and assembly constituencies. As from 
the appointed day, the transferred territory shall cease to be part of 
Madhugiri parliamentary constituency and Bagepalli assembly 
constituency in the State of Mysore as delimited in Order No. 11 of 
the Delimitation Commission made under section 10 of the Delimitation 
Commission Act, <year>1962</year> (61 of <year>1962</year>), and shall form part of Hindupur 
parliamentary constituency and Hindupur assembly constituency in the 
State of Andhra Pradesh as delimited in Order No. 3 of the 
Delimitation Commission made under the said section.


</article>



<article><tid>1659431</tid>
<number> 6</number> Provision as to sitting members of Parliament and 
Legislative Assemblies.
<section><tid>1630857</tid>
<number>1</number>The sitting members of the House of the  
People representing Hindupur parliamentary constituency in the State 
of Andhra Pradesh and Madhugiri parliamentary constituency in the 
State of Mysore shall, notwithstanding the alteration in the extent of 
those constituencies by virtue of the provisions of this Act, continue 
to be members of the House of the People.

</section>

<section><tid>1916305</tid>
<number>2</number>The sitting members of the Legislative Assemblies of Andhra 
Pradesh and Mysore representing Hindupur assembly constituency and 
Bagepalli assembly constituency respectively shall, notwithstanding 
the alteration in the extent of those constituencies by virtue of the 
provisions of this Act, continue to be members of the said Assemblies.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>909</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>235631</tid>
<number> 7</number> Extent of Council constituencies.
<section><tid>249760</tid>
<number>1</number>Any reference in the  
Delimitation of Council Constituencies (Andhra Pradesh) Order, <year>1957</year>, 
to Anantapur district shall be construed as including the territory 
transferred to that district from the State of Mysore.

</section>

<section><tid>386759</tid>
<number>2</number>Any reference in the Delimitation of Council Constituencies 
 (Mysore) Order, <year>1951</year>, to Kolar district shall be construed as 
excluding the territory transferred from that district to the State of 
Andhra Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>128288</tid>
<number>8</number>Sitting members of Legislative Councils. Every sitting member 
of the Legislative Council of Andhra Pradesh or of Mysore representing 
a council constituency the extent of which is altered by virtue of 
section 7 shall, as from the appointed day, be deemed to have been 
elected to the said Council by that constituency as so altered.


</article>



<article><tid>23869</tid>
<number> 9</number> Extension of jurisdiction of Andhra Pradesh High Court.
<section><tid>618076</tid>
<number>1</number>As  
from the appointed day,--

<subsection><tid>1961320</tid>
<number>a</number>the jurisdiction of the High Court of Andhra Pradesh 
shall extend to the transferred territory; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>562735</tid>
<number>b</number>the High Court of Mysore shall have no jurisdiction in 
respect of the said territory.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1007354</tid>
<number>2</number>If, immediately before the appointed day, there is any 
proceeding relatable to the transferred territory pending in the High 
Court of Mysore, then, notwithstanding anything contained in sub- 
section (1), such proceeding shall be heard and disposed of by that 
High Court.

</section>

<section><tid>1229587</tid>
<number>3</number>Any order made by the High Court of Mysore in any proceeding 
with respect to which that High Court exercises jurisdiction by virtue 
of sub- section (2) shall, for all purposes, have effect, not only as 
an order of the High Court of Mysore but also as an order made by the 
High Court of Andhra Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>592753</tid>
<number>4</number>For the purposes of this section,--

<subsection><tid>142772</tid>
<number>a</number>proceedings shall be deemed to be pending in the High 
Court of Mysore until that Court has disposed of all 
issues between the parties, including any issues with 
respect to the taxation of the costs of the proceedings 
and shall include appeals, applications for leave to 
appeal to the Supreme Court, applications for review, 
petitions for revision and petitions for writs;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1155297</tid>
<number>b</number>references to a High Court shall be construed as 
including references to a Judge or division court 
thereof, and references

<pagefootnote><pagenum>910</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

to an order made by a court or a Judge shall be 
construed as including references to a sentence, 
judgment or decree passed or made by that court or 
Judge.




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>696235</tid>
<number>10</number>Appropriation of moneys for expenditure in transferred 
territory under existing Appropriation Acts. As from the appointed 
day, any Act passed by the Legislature of Andhra Pradesh before that 
day for the appropriation of any money out of the Consolidated Fund of 
the State to meet any expenditure in respect of any part of the 
financial year <year>1968</year>- 69 shall have effect also in relation to the 
transferred territory, and it shall be lawful for the State Government 
to spend any amount for that territory out of the amount authorised by 
such Act to be expended for any services in that State.


</article>



<article><tid>982603</tid>
<number> 11</number> Assets and liabilities.
<section><tid>1141008</tid>
<number>1</number>All land and all stores, articles  
and other goods in the transferred territory belonging to the State of 
Mysore shall, as from the appointed day, pass to the State of Andhra 
Pradesh.
Explanation.-- In this sub- section, the expression" land" includes 
immovable property of every kind and any rights in or over such 
property and the expression" goods" does not include coins, bank notes 
and currency notes.


</section>

<section><tid>839071</tid>
<number>2</number>All rights, liabilities and obligations, whether arising out 
of a contract or otherwise, of the State of Mysore in relation to the 
transferred territory shall, as from the appointed day, be the rights, 
liabilities and obligations, respectively, of the State of Andhra 
Pradesh.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>802986</tid>
<number> 12</number> State Financial Corporations and State Electricity Boards. As 
from the appointed day,--
<section><tid>604614</tid>
<number>a</number>the Financial Corporations constituted under the State 
Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year> (63 of <year>1951</year>), for the 
States of Mysore and Andhra Pradesh, and

</section>

<section><tid>1075285</tid>
<number>b</number>the State Electricity Boards constituted under the 
Electricity (Supply) Act, <year>1948</year> (54 of <year>1948</year>) for the 
said States.
shall be deemed to have been constituted for those States with their 
areas as altered by the provisions of section 3.




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>262738</tid>
<number>13</number>Extension of laws. All laws which, immediately before the 
appointed day, extend to, or are in force in, the Hindupur taluk of 
Anantapur district in the State of Andhra Pradesh but do not extend 
to, or are not in force in, the transferred territory, shall, as from 
that day, extend to, or as the case may be, come into force in, the 
transferred territory; and all laws which,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>911</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>

immediately before the appointed day, are in force in the transferred 
territory but not in the Hindupur taluk of Anantapur district in the 
State of Andhra Pradesh shall, on that day, cease to be in force in 
the transferred territory, except as respects things done or omitted 
to be done before that day.

Explanation.-- In this section," law" includes any enactment, 
ordinance, regulation, order, bye- law, rule, scheme, notification or 
other instrument having the force of law in the whole or in any part 
of the State of Andhra Pradesh or Mysore.



</article>



<article><tid>1862913</tid>
<number>14</number>Power to construe laws. Any court, tribunal or authority 
required or empowered to enforce any law extended to the transferred 
territory by section 13 may, for the purpose of facilitating its 
application in relation to the transferred territory, construe the law 
in such manner, without affecting the substance, as may be necessary 
or proper in regard to the matter before the court, tribunal or 
authority.


</article>



<article><tid>386310</tid>
<number>15</number>Legal proceedings. Where, immediately before the appointed 
day, the State of Mysore is a party to any legal proceedings with 
respect to any property, rights or liabilities transferred to the 
State of Andhra Pradesh under this Act, the State of Andhra Pradesh 
shall be deemed to be substituted for the State of Mysore as a party 
to those proceedings, or added as a party thereto, as the case may be, 
and the proceedings may continue accordingly.


</article>



<article><tid>84913</tid>
<number> 16</number> Transfer of pending proceedings.
<section><tid>1461710</tid>
<number>1</number>Every proceeding pending  
immediately before the appointed day before any court (other than a  
  High Court), tribunal, authority or officer in any area which on that 
day falls within the State of Mysore shall, if it is a proceeding 
relating exclusively to any part of the transferred territory, stand 
transferred to the corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer 
in the State of Andhra Pradesh.

</section>

<section><tid>1252247</tid>
<number>2</number>If any question arises as to whether any proceeding should 
stand transferred under sub- section (1), it shall be referred to the 
High Court of Mysore and the decision of that High Court shall be 
final.

</section>

<section><tid>1325186</tid>
<number>3</number>In this section,--

<subsection><tid>7871</tid>
<number>a</number>" proceeding" includes any suit, case or appeal, and

<pagefootnote><pagenum>912</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>876306</tid>
<number>b</number>" corresponding court, tribunal, authority or officer" in 
the State of Andhra Pradesh means--

<subsubsection><tid>1306434</tid>
<number>i</number>the court, tribunal, authority or officer in 
which, or before whom, the proceeding would have lain 
if the proceeding had been instituted after the 
appointed day, or

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>1099862</tid>
<number>ii</number>in case of doubt, such court, tribunal, 
authority or officer in that State as may be determined 
after the appointed day by the Government of Andhra 
Pradesh, or before the appointed day by the Government 
of Mysore, to be the corresponding court, tribunal, 
authority or officer.



</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1946539</tid>
<number>17</number>Effect of provisions inconsistent with other laws. The 
provisions of this Act shall have effect notwithstanding anything 
inconsistent therewith contained in any other law.


</article>



<article><tid>1310465</tid>
<number>18</number>Power to remove difficulties. If any difficulty arises in 
giving effect to the provisions of this Act (including any difficulty  
in relation to the transition under section 13 from one law to another 
  law), the President may by order do anything not inconsistent with any 
such provision which appears to him to be necessary for the purpose of 
removing the difficulty.


</article>



<article><tid>177786</tid>
<number> 19</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>983097</tid>
<number>1</number>The Central Government may, by  
notification in the Official Gazette, make rules to give effect to the 
provisions of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1998847</tid>
<number>2</number>Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as 
may be after it is made before each House of Parliament while it is in 
session for a total period of thirty days which may be comprised in 
one session or <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> in two or more successive sessions, and if, before 
the expiry of the session immediately following the session or the 
successive sessions aforesaid], both Houses agree in making any 
modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the rule should not 
be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such modified 
form or be of no effect, as the case may be, so however that any such 
modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity 
of anything previously done under that rule.


</section>

</article>



 </act>