<act><title>


    THE FOREIGN MARRIAGE ACT, 1969</title> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>1</number> 
    Short title.—This 
    Act may be called the Foreign Marriage Act, 1969. 

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>2</number> 
    Definitions.—In 
    this Act, unless the context otherwise requires,— 
 <section>
<number>a</number>   "degrees of prohibited 
    relationship" shall have the same meanings as in the Special Marriage Act, 
    1954 (43 of 1954);  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   "district", in relation to a 
    Marriage Officer, means the area within which the duties of his offer are to 
    be discharged;  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   "foreign country" means a country 
    or place outside India, and includes a ship which is for the time being in 
    the territorial waters of such a country or place;  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   "Marriage Officer" means a person 
    appointed under section 3 to be a Marriage Officer;  
 </section><section>
<number>e</number>   "official house", in relation to a 
    Marriage Officer, means—  
 <subsection>
<number>i</number>   the official house of residence of 
    the officer;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>ii</number>   the office in which the business 
    of the officer is transacted;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>iii</number>   a prescribed place; and  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>f</number>   "prescribed" means prescribed by 
    rules made under this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>3</number> 
    Marriage Officers.—For 
    the purposes of this Act, the Central Government may, by notification in the 
    Official Gazette, appoint such of its diplomatic or consular officers as it 
    may think fit to be Marriage Officers for any foreign country.  
 

    Explanation.—In 
    this section, "diplomatic officer" means an ambassador, envoy, minister, 
    high commissioner, commissioner, charge d' affairs or other 
    diplomatic representative or a counsellor or secretary of an embassy, 
    legation or high commission.  
  
  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>4</number> 
    Conditions relating to solemnization of foreign marriages.—A 
    marriage between parties one of whom at least is a citizen of India may be 
    solemnized under this Act by or before a Marriage Officer in a foreign 
    country, if, at the time of the marriage, the following conditions are 
    fulfilled, namely:—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   neither party has a spouse living,  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   neither party is an idiot or a 
    lunatic,  
 </section><section>
<number>c</number>   the bridegroom has completed the 
    age of twenty one years and the bride the age of eighteen years at the time 
    of the marriage, and  
 </section><section>
<number>d</number>   the parties are not within the 
    degrees of prohibited relationship:  
 
Provided 
    that where the personal law or a custom governing at least one of the 
    parties permits of a marriage between them, such marriage may be solemnized, 
    notwithstanding that they are within the degree of prohibited relationship.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>5</number> 
    Notice of intended marriage.—When 
    a marriage is intended to be solemnized under this Act, the parties to the 
    marriage shall give notice thereof in writing in the form specified in the 
    First Schedule to the Marriage Officer of the district in which at least one 
    of the parties to the marriage has resided for a period of not less than 
    thirty days immediately preceding the date on which such notice is given, 
    and the notice shall state that the party has so resided.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>6</number> 
    Marriage Notice Book.—The 
    Marriage Officer shall keep all notices given under section 5 with the 
    records of his office and shall also forthwith enter a true copy of every 
    such notice in a book prescribed for that purpose, to be called the 
    "Marriage Notice Book", and such book shall be open for inspection at all 
    reasonable times, without fee, by any person desirous of inspecting the 
    same.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>7</number> 
    Publication of notice.—Where 
    a notice under section 5 is given to the Marriage Officer, he shall cause it 
    to be published—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   in his own office, by affixing a 
    copy thereof to a conspicuous place, and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   in India and in the country or 
    countries in which the parties are ordinarily resident, in the prescribed 
    manner.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>8</number> 
    Objection to marriage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person may, before the expiration of thirty days from the date of 
    publication of the notice under section 7, object to the marriage on the 
    ground that it would contravene one or more of the conditions specified in 
    section 4.  
 

    Explanation.—Where 
    the publication of the notice by affixation under clause (a) of section 7 
    and in the prescribed manner under clause (b) of that section is on 
    different dates, the period of thirty days shall, for the purposes of this 
    sub-section, be computed from the later date.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every such objection shall be in writing signed by the person making it or 
    by any person duly authorised to sign on his behalf, and shall state the 
    ground of objections; and the Marriage Officer shall record the nature of 
    the objection in his Marriage Notice Book.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>9</number> 
    Solemnization of marriage where no objection made.—If 
    no objection is made within the period specified in section 8 to an intended 
    marriage, then, on the expiry of that period, the marriage may be 
    solemnized.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>10</number> 
    Procedure on receipt of objection.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    If an objection is made under section 8 to an intended marriage, the 
    Marriage Officer shall not solemnize the marriage until he has inquired into 
    the matter of the objection in such manner as he thinks fit and is satisfied 
    that it ought not to prevent the solemnization of the Marriage or the 
    objection is withdrawn by the person making it.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Where a Marriage Officer after making any such inquiry entertains a doubt in 
    respect of any objection, he shall transmit the record with such statement 
    respecting the matter as he thinks fit to the Central Government; and the 
    Central Government, after making such further inquiry into the matter and 
    after obtaining such advice as it thinks fit, shall give its decision 
    thereon in writing to the Marriage Officer, who shall act in conformity with 
    the decision of the Central Government.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>11</number> 
    Marriage not to be in contravention of local laws.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Marriage Officer may, for reason to be recorded in writing refuse to 
    solemnize a marriage under this Act if the intended marriage is prohibited 
    by any law in force in the foreign country where it is to be solemnized.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    Marriage Officer may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, refuse to 
    solemnize a marriage under this Act on the ground that in his opinion, the 
    solemnization of the marriage would be inconsistent with international law 
    or the comity of nations.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Where a Marriage Officer refuses to solemnize a marriage under this section, 
    any party to the intended marriage may appeal to the Central Government in 
    the prescribed manner within a period of thirty days from the date of such 
    refusal; and the Marriage Officer shall act in conformity with the decision 
    of the Central Government on such appeal.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>12</number> 
    Declaration by parties and witnesses.—Before 
    the marriage is solemnized, the parties and three witnesses shall, in 
    presence of the Marriage Officer, sign a declaration in the form specified 
    in the Second Schedule, and the declaration shall be countersigned by the 
    Marriage Officer.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>13</number> 
    Place and form of solemnization.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    A marriage by or before a Marriage Officer under this Act shall be 
    solemnized at the official house of the Marriage Officer with open doors 
    between the prescribed hours in the presence of at least three witnesses.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    marriage may be solemnized in any form which the parties may choose to 
    adopt:  
 
Provided 
    that it shall not be complete and binding on the parties unless each party 
    declares to the other in the presence of the Marriage Officer and the three 
    witnesses and in any language understood by the parties,— "I, (A) 
    take the (B), to be my lawful wife (or husband)":  
 
Provided 
    further that where the declaration referred to in the preceding proviso is 
    made in any language which is not understood by the Marriage Officer or by 
    any of the witnesses, either of the parties shall interpret or cause to be 
    interpreted the declaration in a language which the Marriage Officer, or, as 
    the case may be, such witness understands.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>14</number> 
    Certificate of marriage.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Whenever a marriage is solemnized under this Act, the Marriage Officer shall 
    enter a certificate thereof in the form specified in the Third Schedule in a 
    book to be kept by him for that purpose and to be called the Marriage 
    Certificate Book, and such certificate shall be signed by the parties to the 
    marriage and the three witnesses.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> On a 
    certificate being entered in the Marriage Certificate Book by the Marriage 
    Officer, the certificate shall be deemed to be conclusive evidence of the 
    fact that a marriage under this Act has been solemnized, and that all 
    formalities respecting the residence of the party concerned previous to the 
    marriage and the signatures of witnesses have been complied with.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>15</number> 
    Validity of foreign marriages in India.—Subject 
    to the other provisions contained in this Act, a marriage solemnized in the 
    manner provided in this Act shall be good and valid in law.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>16</number> 
    New notice when marriage not solemnized within six months.—Whenever 
    a marriage is not solemnized within six months from the date on which notice 
    thereof has been given to the Marriage Officer as required under section 5 
    or where the record of a case has been transmitted to the Central Government 
    under section 10, or where an appeal has been preferred to the Central 
    Government under section 11, within three months from the date of decision 
    of the Central Government in such case or appeal, as the case may be, the 
    notice and all other proceedings arising therefrom shall be deemed to have 
    lapsed, and no Marriage Officer shall solemnize the marriage until new 
    notice has been given in the manner laid down in this Act.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>17</number> 
    Registration of foreign marriages.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a Marriage Officer is satisfied 
    that a marriage has been duly solemnized in a foreign country in accordance 
    with the law of that country between parties of whom one atleast was a 
    citizen of India; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a party to the marriage informs 
    the Marriage Officer in writing that he or she desires the marriage to be 
    registered under the section,  
 
the Marriage Officer may, upon payment of the 
    prescribed fee, register the marriage.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> No 
    marriage shall be registered under this section unless at the time of 
    registration it satisfies the conditions mentioned in section 4.  
 </section><section>
<number>3</number> The 
    Marriage Officer may, for reasons to be recorded in writing, refuse to 
    register a marriage under this section on the ground that in his opinion the 
    marriage is inconsistent with international law or the comity of nations.  
 </section><section>
<number>4</number> 
    Where a Marriage Officer refuses to register a marriage under this section 
    the party applying for registration may appeal to the Central Government in 
    the prescribed manner within a period of thirty days from the date of such 
    refusal; and the Marriage Officer shall act in conformity with the decision 
    of the Central Government on such appeal.  
 </section><section>
<number>5</number> 
    Registration of a marriage under this section shall be effected by the 
    Marriage Officer by entering a certificate of the marriage in the prescribed 
    form and in the prescribed manner in the Marriage Certificate Book, and such 
    certificate shall be signed by the parties to the marriage and by three 
    witnesses.  
 </section><section>
<number>6</number> A 
    marriage registered under this section shall, as from the date of 
    registration, be deemed to have been solemnized under this Act.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>18</number> Matrimonial reliefs to be under Special Marriage Act, 
      1954.—
<section><number>1</number> 
      Subject to the other provisions contained in this section, the provisions 
      of Chapters IV, V, VI and VII of the Special Marriage Act, 1954 (43 of 
      1954) shall apply in relation to marriages solemnized under this Act and 
      to any other marriage solemnized in a foreign country between parties of 
      whom one at least is a citizen of India as they apply in relation to 
      marriages solemnized under that Act.  
 Explanation.—In its application to the marriages 
      referred to in this sub-section, section 24 of the Special Marriage Act, 
      1954 (43 of 1954) shall be subject to the following modifications, 
      namely:—  
 <subsection><number>i</number>   the 
      reference in sub-section (1) thereof to clauses (a), (b), (c) and (d) of 
      section 4 of that Act shall be construed as a reference to clauses (a), 
      (b), (c) and (d) respectively of section 4 of this Act, and  
 </subsection><subsection><number>ii</number>   nothing 
      contained in section 24 aforesaid shall apply to any marriage—  
 <subsubsection><number>a</number>   which is not 
      solemnized under this Act; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>b</number>   which is 
      deemed to be solemnized under this Act by reason of the provisions 
      contained in section 17:  
 Provided that the registration of any such marriage as is referred 
      to in sub-clause (b) may be declared to be of no effect if the 
      registration was in contravention of sub-section (2) of section 
      17.  
 </subsubsection></subsection></section><section><number>2</number> Every petition for relief under Chapter V or Chapter VI of the 
      Special Marriage Act, 1954 (43 of 1954) as made applicable to the 
      marriages referred to in sub-section (1), shall be presented to the 
      district court within the local limits of whose ordinary civil 
      jurisdiction—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>   the 
      respondent is residing at the time of the presentation of the petition; 
      or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   the husband 
      and wife last resided together; or  
 </subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   the 
      petitioner is residing at the time of the presentation of the petition, 
      provided that the respondent is at that time residing outside 
India.  
 Explanation.—In this section, "district court" 
      has the same meaning as in the Special Marriage Act, 1954 (43 of 
      1954)  
 </subsection></section><section><number>3</number> Nothing contained in this section shall authorise any 
      court—  
 <subsection><number>a</number>   to make any 
      decree of dissolution of marriage, except where—  
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>   the parties 
      to the marriage are domiciled in India at the time of the presentation of 
      the petition; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>   the 
      petitioner, being the wife, was domiciled in India immediately before the 
      marriage and has been residing in India for a period of not less than 
      three years immediately preceding the presentation of the petition;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>b</number>   to make any 
      decree annulling a voidable marriage, except where—  
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>   the parties 
      to the marriage are domiciled in India at the time of the presentation of 
      the petition; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>   the 
      marriage was solemnized under this Act and the petitioner being the wife, 
      has been ordinarily resident in India for a period of three years 
      immediately preceding the presentation of the petition;  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>c</number>   to make any 
      decree of nullity of marriage in respect of a void marriage, except 
      where—  
 <subsubsection><number>i</number>   either of 
      the parties to the marriage is domiciled in India at the time of the 
      presentation of the petition; or  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection><number>ii</number>   the 
      marriage was solemnized under this Act and the petitioner is residing in 
      India at the time of the presentation of the petition.  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection><number>d</number>   to grant any 
      other relief under Chapter V or Chapter VI of the Special Marriage Act, 
      1954 (43 of 1954) except where the petitioner is residing in India at the 
      time of the presentation of the petition.  
 </subsection></section><section><number>4</number> Nothing contained in sub-section (1) shall authorise any court 
      to grant any relief under this Act in relation to any marriage in a 
      foreign country not solemnized under it, if the grant of relief in respect 
      of such marriage (whether on any of the grounds specified in the Special 
      Marriage Act, 1954 (43 of 1954) or otherwise is provided for under any 
      other law for the time being in force.  
 
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>19</number> 
    Punishment for bigamy.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any person whose marriage is solemnized or deemed to have been solemnized 
    under this Act and who, during the subsistence of his marriage, contracts 
    any other marriage in India shall be subject to the penalties provided in 
    section 494 and section 495 of the Indian Penal Code, 1860 (45 of 1860) and 
    the marriage so contracted shall be void.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> The 
    provisions of sub-section (1) apply also to any such offence committed by 
    any citizen of India without and beyond India.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>20</number> 
    Punishment for contravention of certain other conditions for marriage.—Any 
    citizen of India who procures a marriage of himself or herself be solemnized 
    under this Act in contravention of the condition specified in clause (c) or 
    clause (d) of section 4 shall be punishable—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   in the case of a contravention of 
    the condition specified in clause (c) of section 4, with simple imprisonment 
    which may extend to fifteen days or with the fine which may extend to one 
    thousand rupees, or with both; and  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   in the case of a contravention of 
    the condition specified in clause (d) of section 4, with simple imprisonment 
    which may extend to fifteen days or with fine which may extend to one 
    thousand rupees, or with both.  
 
 
 
 

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>21</number> 
    Punishment for false declaration.—If 
    any citizen of India for the purpose of procuring a marriage, intentionally—  
 <section>
<number>a</number>   where a declaration is required by 
    this Act, makes a false declaration; or  
 </section><section>
<number>b</number>   where a notice or certificate is 
    required by this Act, signs a false notice or certificate,  
 
he shall be punishable with imprisonment for a 
    term which may extend to three years and shall also be liable to fine.

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>22</number> Punishment for wrongful action of Marriage 
      Officer.—Any Marriage Officer who knowingly and wilfully solemnizes a 
      marriage under this Act in contravention of any of the provisions of this 
      Act shall be punishable with simple imprisonment which may extend to one 
      year, or with fine which may extend to five hundred rupees, or with 
      both.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>23</number> 
    Recognition of marriages solemnized under law of other countries.—If 
    the Central Government is satisfied that the law in force in any foreign 
    country for the solemnization of marriages contains provisions similar to 
    those contained in this Act, it may, by notification in the Official 
    Gazette, declare that marriages solemnized under the law in force in such 
    foreign country shall be recognized by courts in India as valid.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>24</number> 
    Certification of documents of marriages solemnized in accordance with local 
    law in a foreign country.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Where—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   a marriage is solemnized in any 
    foreign country specified in this behalf by the Central Government, by 
    notification in the Official Gazette, in accordance with the law of that 
    country between parties of whom one at least is a citizen of India; and  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   a party to the marriage who is 
    such citizen produces to a Marriage Officer in the country in which the 
    marriage was solemnized—  
 <subsubsection>
<number>i</number>   a copy of the entry in respect of 
    the marriage in the marriage register of that country certified by the 
    appropriate authority in that country to be a true copy of that entry; and  
 </subsubsection><subsubsection>
<number>ii</number>   if the copy of that entry is not 
    in the English language, a translation into the prescribed language of that 
    copy; and  
 </subsubsection></subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the Marriage Officer is satisfied 
    that the copy of the entry in the marriage register is a true copy and that 
    the translation, if any, is a true translation,  
 
the Marriage Officer, upon the payment of the 
    prescribed fee, shall certify upon the copy that he is satisfied that the 
    copy is a true copy of the entry in the marriage register and upon the 
    translation that he is satisfied that the translation is a true translation 
    of the copy and shall issue the copy and the translation to the said party.
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>2</number> A 
    document relating to a marriage in a foreign country issued under 
    sub-section (1) shall be admitted in evidence in any proceedings as if it 
    were a certificate duly issued by the appropriate authority of that country.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>25</number> 
    Certified copy of entries to be evidences.—Every 
    certified copy purporting to be signed by the Marriage Officer of an entry 
    of a marriage in the Marriage Certificate Book shall be received in evidence 
    without production or proof of the original.  

 
  


</article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>26</number> 
    Correction of errors.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    Any Marriage Officer who discovers any error in the form or substance of any 
    entry in the Marriage Certificate Book may, within one month next after the 
    discovery of such error, in the presence of the persons, married or, in case 
    of their death or absence, in the presence of two other witnesses, correct 
    the error by entry in the margin without any alteration of the original 
    entry and add thereto the date of such correction.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> 
    Every correction made under this section shall be attested by the witnesses 
    in whose presence it was made.  

 
  


</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>27</number> Act not to affect validity of marriages outside 
      it.—Nothing 
      in this Act shall in any way affect the validity of a marriage solemnized 
      in a foreign country otherwise than under this Act.  
 
  </article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>28</number> 
    Power to make rules.—
<section><number>1</number> 
    The Central Government may, by notification in the Official Gazette, make 
    rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.  
 </section><section>
<number>2</number> In 
    particular, and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power, 
    such rules may provide for all or any of the following matters, namely:—  
 <subsection>
<number>a</number>   the duties and powers of Marriage 
    Officers and their districts;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>b</number>   the manner in which a Marriage 
    Officer may hold any inquiry under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>c</number>   the manner in which notices of 
    marriage shall be published;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>d</number>   the places in which and the hours 
    between which marriages under this Act may be solemnized; 
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>e</number>   the form and the manner in which 
    any books required by or under this Act to be kept shall be maintained;
    
 
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>f</number>   the form and manner in which 
    certificates of marriages may be entered under sub-section (5) of section 
    17;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>g</number>   the fees that may be levied for 
    the performance of any duty imposed upon a Marriage Officer under this Act;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>h</number>   the authorities to which, the form 
    in which and the intervals within which copies of entries in the Marriage 
    Certificate Book shall be sent, and, when corrections are made in the 
    Marriage Certificate Book, the manner in which Certificates of such 
    corrections shall be sent to the authorities;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>i</number>   the inspection of any books 
    required to be kept under this Act and the furnishing of certified copies of 
    entries therein;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>j</number>   the manner in which and the 
    conditions subject to which any marriage may be recognised under section 23;  
 </subsection><subsection>
<number>k</number>   any other matter which may be, or 
    requires to be, prescribed.  
 </subsection></section><section>
<number>3</number> 
    Every rule made under this section shall be laid as soon as may be after it 
    is made before each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total 
    period of thirty days which may be comprised in one session or 


    1[in two or more 
    successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session immediately 
    following the session or the successive sessions aforesaid] both Houses 
    agree in making any modification in the rule or both Houses agree that the 
    rule should not be made, the rule shall thereafter have effect only in such 
    modified form or be of no effect, as the case may be; so, however, that any 
    such modification or annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of 
    anything previously done under that rule.  
 
 






 



</section></article> 
 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article><number>29</number> Amendment of Act 43 of 1954.—In the Special Marriage Act, 
      1954—  
 <section><number>a</number>   in section 
      1, in sub-section (2) for the words "outside the said territories", the 
      words "in the State of Jammu and Kashmir" shall be substituted;  
 </section><section><number>b</number>   in section 
      2, clauses (a) and (c) shall be omitted;  
 </section><section><number>c</number>   in section 
      3, for sub-section (2), the following sub-section shall be substituted, 
      namely:—  
 "(2) For the purposes of 
      this Act, in its application to citizens of India domiciled in the 
      territories to which this Act extends who are in the State of Jammu and 
      Kashmir, the Central Government may, by notification in the Official 
      Gazette, specify such officers of the Central Government as it may think 
      fit to be the Marriage Officers for the State or any part 
thereof.";  
 </section><section><number>d</number>   in section 
      4, for clause (e), the following clause shall be substituted, 
      namely:—  
 "(e)   where the 
      marriage is solemnized in the State of Jammu and Kashmir, both parties are 
      citizens of India domiciled in the territories to which this Act 
      extends.";  
 </section><section><number>e</number>   in section 
      10, for the words "outside the territories to which this Act extends in 
      respect of an intended marriage outside and said territories", the words 
      "in the State of Jammu and Kashmir in respect of an intended marriage in 
      the State" shall be substituted;  
 </section><section><number>f</number>   in section 
      50, in sub-section (1), the words "diplomatic and consular officers and 
      other" shall be omitted.  
 
  </section></article> 
 
 
 
  
 

  
  
 <article>
<number>30</number> 
    Repeal.—The 
    Indian Foreign Marriage Act, 1903 (14 of 1903) is hereby repealed.    
 

 

 


 
  


</article><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE FOREIGN MARRIAGE ACT, 1969
 

 
 


THE FIRST SCHEDULE
 


(See section 5)
 


FORM OF NOTICE OF INTENDED MARRIAGE
 


To
 


The Marriage Officer,
 


for…………………..
 


We hereby give you notice that a marriage 
    under the Foreign Marriage Act, 1969 is intended to be solemnized between us 
    within three months from the date hereof.
 
 
 
 Name and 
        Father's Name
 Condition
 Occupation
 Date of Birth
 Dwelling 
        Place
 Permanent 
        Dwelling Place and Present Dwelling Place if not permanent
 Length of 
        residence in the present dwelling place

 
  

 
  
 A.B.
 Unmarried 

        Widowed 

        Divorcee
  
  
  
  

 
  
 C.D.
 Unmarried 

        Widowed 

        Divorcee
  
  
  
  

 
  


 




    Witness our hands, this………...............…. Day of……………....………20…… tc 
    "Witness 
    our hands, this………...............…. Day of……………....………20……" 
 




    Sd. A.B.
 




    Sd. C.D.
 

 
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE FOREIGN MARRIAGE ACT, 1969
 

 
 


THE SECOND SCHEDULE
 


(See section 12)
 


DECLARATION TO BE MADE BY THE BRIDEGROOM
 

 
 


I. A.B., hereby declare as follows:—
 


             1.  I am at the present time 
    unmarried (or a widower or a divorcee, as the case may be).
 


             2.  I have completed…………………… 
    years of age.
 


             3.  I am not related to C.D. 
    (the bride) within the degrees of prohibited relationship.
 


             4.  I am a citizen of………………..
 


             5.  I am aware that, if any 
    statement in this declaration is false, I am liable to imprisonment and also 
    to fine.
 


Sd. A.B. (the bridegroom)
 




    tc "" 
 



    Declaration to be made by the bride
 


I, C.D. hereby declare as follows:—
 


             1.  I am at the present time 
    unmarried (or a widow, or a divorcee, as the case may be).
 


             2.  I have completed…………………… 
    years of age.
 


             3.  I am not related to A.B. 
    (the bridegroom) within the degrees of prohibited relationship.
 


             4.  I am a citizen 
    of……................…………..
 


             5.  I am aware that, if any 
    statement in this declaration is false, I am liable to imprisonment and also 
    to fine.
 


Sd. C.D. (the bride)
 


Signed in our presence by the above named 
    A.B. and C.D. So far as we are aware, there is no lawful 
    impediment to the marriage.
 




    Sd.   G.H.
 




    Sd.   I.J.                           (Three witnesses.)
 




    Sd.   K.L.
 




    (Countersigned) E.F.
 




    Marriage Officer
 



    Dated....................the………................……..day 
    of……........………..20…….
 

 
 
 

 


</form><form>
 
 
 
 

 
 
 



    THE FOREIGN MARRIAGE ACT, 1969
 

 
 


THE THIRD SCHEDULE
 


(See section 14)
 


FORM OF CERTIFICATE OF MARRIAGE
 

 
 


I, E.F., hereby certify that on 
    the…………………..day of……………………19………. A.B. and C.D……………….†appeared before 
    me and that the declaration required by section…… ‡of the Foreign Marriage 
    Act, 1969, was duly made, and that a marriage under that Act was solemnized 
    between them in my presence and in the presence of three witnesses who have 
    signed hereunder.
 


Sd.   E.F.
 


                Marriage Officer.
 


Sd.   A.B. (bridegroom).
 


Sd.   C.D. (bride).
 


Sd.   G.H.
 


Sd.   I.J.                           
    (Three witnesses).
 


Sd.   K.L.
 

 
 


Date the …………………….day of……………………..20……
 


 
 


 
 




    ------------------------
 


      †   Herein give 
    particulars of the parties.
 


      ‡   To be entered.
 




    ------------------------
 
 

 


</form>
<pagefootnote></pagefootnote>
</act>