<act><tid>663398</tid>
<title>THE CALCUTTA PILOTS ACT, <year>1859</year></title>

ACT NO. 12 OF <year>1859</year> 
[ 4th May, <year>1859</year>.]
An Act to make better provision for the trial of pilots at the 
Presidency of Fort William in Bengal <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> for breach of duty.

Preamble.-- WHEREAS it is expedient to amend the law for the trial 
of person employed in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Hooghly Pilot Service of the 
Commissioners for the Port of Calcutta], when accused of breach of 
duty, and to extend the same to persons licensed to act as pilots at 
the said Presidency <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>; It is enacted as follows:




<article><tid>571547</tid>
<number>1</number>[ Repeal of Acts 24, of <year>1845</year> and 1 of <year>1851</year>.] Rep. by the 
Repealing Act, <year>1870</year> (14 of <year>1870</year>), s. 1 and Sch., Pt. II.


</article>



<article><tid>225194</tid>
<number>2</number>Trial of pilots accused of breach of duty.-- When any person 
employed in <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Hooghly Pilot Service of the Commissioners for 
the Port of Calcutta], or licensed to act as a pilot at the said 
Presidency <footcitenum>2</footcitenum>, shall be accused of having committed any breach of 
duty while engaged in such service or acting under such license, and 
it shall appear to the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Port Officer], or to the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Central 
Government] that such person ought to be brought to trial for such 
breach of duty, such person shall be brought to trial upon a charge or 
charges framed by the said <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Port Officer] or such other person as 
the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Central Government] shall direct, before a Court constituted 
under the provisions of this Act.


</article>



<article><tid>525163</tid>
<number>3</number>Appointment of Judge.-- The <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Central Government] shall 
appoint a fit person to be Judge of the said Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1670181</tid>
<number>4</number>Appointment of prosecutor.-- The <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> Central Government] 
shall appoint such person as <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> it] may think proper to conduct the 
proceedings before the Court as prosecutor on the part of Government.


</article>



<article><tid>190160</tid>
<number>5</number>Trial to be held before Judge and jury.-- Every trial under 
this Act shall be held before the said Judge and a jury composed of 
two merchants of Calcutta, a master of a merchantship lying in the 
Port of Calcutta, and a pilot of not less than twenty years' service.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>67</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Short title given by the Repealing and Amending Act, <year>1903</year> (1 of  
  <year>1903</year>), s. 2 and Sch. I Pt. II.

This Act applies to all persons employed in the pilot 
Service of Government at the Presidency of (i. e., at Calcutta) 
and borne on the rolls of the Government establishment and to all 
persons licencsed to act as pilots at the Presidency (i. e., at  
  Calcutta)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>i. e., at Calcutta,

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1948</year>, s. 11 for" the Pilot Service of 
Government at the Presidency of Fort William in Bengal" (w. e. f.  
  16- 5- <year>1948</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1903</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II Pt. II, for 
" Superintendment of Marine".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" G. G. in C" which had been subs. by 
Act 11 of <year>1929</year>, s. 2 for" said Lieutenant- Governor of Bengal".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs, ibid for" G. G. in C" which had been subs. by Act 11 of 
<year>1929</year>, s. 2 for" said Lieutenant- Governor".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. ibid for" G. G. in C" which had been subs. by Act 11 of 11 
<year>1929</year>, s. 2 as amended by Act 8 of <year>1930</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I for 
" Lieutenant- Governor".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Subs., ibid for" he".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1661158</tid>
<number>6</number>Lists of merchants and pilots liable to serve on jury.-- The 
Judge shall cause to be prepared and shall keep two separate lists, 
one containing the names of merchants, the other containing the names 
of pilots, liable to serve on such jury.
The names in each list shall be arranged in alphabetical order, 
and the place of abode and quality or business of each person named 
shall be stated.



</article>



<article><tid>226267</tid>
<number>7</number>Notice to prosecutor and accused of time and place for 
appointing jury.-- When the Judge shall be about to hold a trial under 
this Act, he shall give notice to the prosecutor and to the party 
accused of a time and place to be fixed by the Judge for appointing a 
jury to serve at such trial.


</article>



<article><tid>1433667</tid>
<number>8</number>Appointment of jury.-- At the time and place mentioned in the 
notice, the Judge in the presence of the prosecutor and the person 
accused shall read over the names which first occur in each of the 
said lists of those merchants and pilots who he has reason to believe 
are present in Calcutta and capable of attending as jurors at the 
trial; and shall also propose the name of a master of a merchantship 
lying in the Port of Calcutta, whom he deems qualified to serve on 
such Jury.
If no objection be made and allowed, the persons so nominated 
shall be the jury to serve at the trial.

If the prosecutor or the party accused shall object to any of the 
persons named as jurors, he shall assign the grounds of his objection, 
and such objection shall forthwith be decided by the Judge.

If the objection be allowed, the Judge shall read from the said 
lists or propose (as the case may be) another name in the place of the 
one objected to, and the person so nominated shall serve on the jury 
provided no objection to such person be made and allowed as aforesaid.



</article>



<article><tid>1369862</tid>
<number>9</number>Day of trial to be fixed and summons to issue to jurors.-- When 
a jury has been appointed under the last preceding section, the Judge 
shall fix a day for the trial and shall summon by writing under his 
hand the persons so appointed to sit as a jury.
Penalty for non- attendance.-- If any such person when duly 
summoned shall, without such excuse as the Judge shall allow to be 
sufficient, neglect or refuse to attend at the time appointed or to 
remain in attendance until the trial shall be completed, it shall be 
lawful for the said Judge to impose upon any such person a fine not 
exceeding two hundred rupees for every such default; and such fine, if 
not paid, shall be levied by distress and sale of the goods and 
chattels of the defaulter under a warrant to be issued for that 
purpose by the Judge.

Such warrant may be transmitted by the Judge to any 1 
[ Presidency Magistrate] for the town of Calcutta, and thereupon such 
Magistrate shall endorse the same and shall cause it to be executed in 
the same manner as if the warrant had been issued by such Magistrate.



</article>



<article><tid>576303</tid>
<number>10</number>Trial how to proceed if any juror does not attend.-- If for 
any cause any of the persons summoned to attend as jurors shall not be 
in attendance at the time fixed for the commencement of the trial, the 
trial may with the consent of the prosecutor and the party accused be 
held before the Judge and such jurors as shall be in attendance.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>68</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 11 of <year>1929</year>, s. 2, for" Magistrate or Police".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


If such consent be not given, the place of the absent juror shall 
be supplied by some other person selected by the Judge from the same 
profession or calling as the person originally summoned and who shall 
consent to serve, provided no objection to such person be made and 
allowed in manner aforesaid.

If the parties or either of them do not consent that the trial 
shall be held before the Judge and such jurors as may be in attendance 
and the place of the absent juror cannot be supplied by a person 
consenting to serve, the trial shall be postponed to another day and 
the Judge shall either re- summon the same jury or appoint and summon 
another jury in the manner hereinbefore provided.



</article>



<article><tid>1324263</tid>
<number>11</number>Register of jurors who have served.-- The Judge shall register 
in a book the names of all jurors mentioned in either of the said two 
lists who have attended and served on a trial held under this Act.
A juror who has served shall not be required again to serve and 
his name shall be excluded in reading over the jury lists until all 
the persons named in the said lists who are present in Calcutta and 
capable of attending as jurors shall have served.


</article>



<article><tid>820504</tid>
<number>12</number>[ Jurors to be sworn.] Rep. by the Indian Oaths Act, <year>1873</year> (10  
  of <year>1873</year>), s. 2 and Sch., Pt. II.


</article>



<article><tid>819210</tid>
<number>13</number>Judge may summon witnesses to attend at certain time and 
place. Examination of witnesses about to leave Calcutta.-- It shall be 
lawful for the Judge of the said Court, at the instance of the 
prosecutor, or of the party accused, or of his own motion, by writing 
under his hand, to summon any person to attend as a witness at a time 
and place to be specified in the summons, for the purpose of being 
examined at any trial before the said Court; or if such person shall 
be about to depart from Calcutta, so as to be unable to attend at such 
trial without serious inconvenience, then to be examined before the 
Judge of the said Court before the day fixed for the trial:
Provided always that due notice of the time and place of such 
examination shall be given to the accused party; provided also that 
such witness may nevertheless be examined at the trial if he shall be 
able to attend thereat in which case his previous examination may also 
be read at the trial.



</article>



<article><tid>1590916</tid>
<number>14</number>Penalty for witnesses not attending or refusing to give 
evidence.-- If any person who shall have been duly summoned to attend 
as a witness shall, without sufficient excuse, neglect or refuse to 
attend, or attending shall refuse to give evidence or to answer any 
question which may be lawfully put to him, such person shall forfeit 
and pay such fine, not exceeding five hundred rupees, as the Judge of 
the said Court shall order; and such fine, if not paid, shall be 
levied by distress and sale of the goods and chattels of the person 
ordered to pay the same in the manner prescribed in section 9 of this 
Act.


</article>



<article><tid>559198</tid>
<number> 15</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Arrest.--
<section><tid>1905219</tid>
<number>1</number>Whenever the Judge of the said Court  
thinks it necessary for obtaining evidence that any person should be 
arrested, he may issue a warrant for his arrest, and may, for the 
purpose of effecting the arrest, authorize any officer (subject,  
nevertheless, to any general or special instructions from the 2 
 [ Central Government]) to enter any vessel.
<pagefootnote><pagenum>69</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Ins. by Act 6 of <year>1883</year>, s. 1 (w. e. f. 1- 1- <year>1984</year>). The original s. 15, 
relating to examination of witnesses on oath, affirmation or 
otherwise, was rep. by Act 10 of <year>1873</year>, s. 2 and Sch., Pt. II.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" G. G. in C" which had been by Act 11 
of <year>1929</year>, s. 2 for" L. G."


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>



</section>

<section><tid>49247</tid>
<number>2</number>Any officer so authorized may, for the purpose of enforcing 
the entry, call to his aid any officers of Police or Customs, or any 
other persons, and may seize and detain the vessel for such time as is 
reasonably necessary to effect the arrest; and every such officer or 
other person shall be deemed to be a public servant within the meaning 
of the Indian Penal Code (45 of <year>1860</year>), section 186.

</section>

<section><tid>110111</tid>
<number>3</number>No person shall be detained under this section for more than 
forty- eight hours.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1203608</tid>
<number>16</number>Verdict of jurors.-- Upon the completion of the trial, the 
jurors shall give their verdict upon the charge, or, if there be more 
than one, upon each separate charge.
The verdict shall be according to the opinion of the majority of 
jurors. If the jurors are equally divided, the Judge shall declare his 
opinion, and the verdict shall be according to the opinion of the 
Judge and the jurors with whom he concurs.



</article>



<article><tid>40255</tid>
<number>17</number>Sentence if accused found guilty.-- If by such verdict the 
accused person is found guilty of the charge or of any one or more of 
the charges preferred against him, the Judge of the Court shall 
sentence him to be dismissed from the said pilot service, or to have 
his licence withdrawn, or shall award such other punishment, by loss 
of rank <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>, or by change of a licence from a higher to a lower 
grade, or suspension from employment for a specified period, as to the 
Judge shall appear fit.
Preparation of schedule of offences and punishments.-- The 2 
[ Central Government], <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> may prepare a schedule of offences and 
punishments (such punishments being of the same nature as those  
  hereinbefore mentioned) for the guidance of the said Court; and if 
such schedule be prepared, <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> and the charge proved before the said 
Court is an offence specified in such schedule, the Judge of the said 
Court shall award such punishment as is prescribed for such offence in 
the said schedule, and no other.

If by such verdict as aforesaid the accused person is found not 
guilty of the charge or charges preferred against him, the Judge shall 
declare him acquitted of the same.



</article>



<article><tid>534237</tid>
<number>18</number>No sentence final till approved by Government.-- The 
proceedings of the Court shall be sent by the Judge to the <footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Port 
Officer] for submission to the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government]; and no 
sentence of punishment pronounced by the Judge of the said Court shall 
be final until it has been approved of by the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Central 
Government].
Government may remit sentence or mitigate punishment.-- The 6 
[ Central Government may remit the whole or any part of such 
sentence, or may direct the substitution of any mitigated punishment 
in lieu of the punishment awarded by the said Court as it shall think 
fit.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>70</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>The words" or pay" omitted by Ben. Act 4 of <year>1920</year>, s. 2.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C" which had been subs. byv 
Act 11 of <year>1929</year>, s. 2 for" Lieutenant- Governor of Bengal".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>The words" with the sanction of the G. G. in C." omitted by ACt 4 
of <year>1914</year>, s. 2 and Sch. Pt. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>The words" and sanctioned" omitted by s. 2 and Sch., Pt. I, ibdi.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by Act 1 of <year>1903</year>, s. 3 and Sch. II, pt. II, for 
" Superintendent of Marine".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year> for" G. G. in C." which had been subs. by 
Act 11 of <year>1929</year>, s. 2, for" said Lieutenant- Governnor".


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</article>



<article><tid>1738353</tid>
<number>19</number>If verdict of jurors be manifestly contrary to evidence, or 
trial otherwise insufficient.-- If it shall appear to the Judge of the 
said Court that the verdict of the jurors is manifestly contrary to 
the evidence, or that the trial is otherwise insufficient, the Judge, 
instead of passing sentence on the accused person or declaring him 
acquitted, as the case may be, may certify the same to the 1 
[ Central Government], and the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Central Government] may either 
order a new trial before another jury or acquit the accused person, as 
it shall think fit.


</article>



<article><tid>143556</tid>
<number>20</number>Power to make rules.-- It shall be lawful for the 1 
[ Central Government] to make such rules as it shall think proper, 
not inconsistent with the provisions of this Act, for conducting the 
proceedings and regulating the practice of the said Court.


</article>



<article><tid>1822501</tid>
<number>21</number>Marine authorities or Government may pass orders upon charge 
of breach of duty where trial unnecessary.-- Nothing contained in this 
Act shall be held to restrict <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> the Commissioners for the Port of 
Calcutta] from passing such orders as may be deemed proper upon any 
charge of breach of duty preferred against any person employed in the 
said pilot service, when it shall not be deemed necessary that such 
person should be brought to trial for such breach of duty under the 
provisions of this Act; <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> provided that no order for suspension, 
reduction or deprivation of appointment shall be made without the 
previous sanction of the Central Government].


</article>



<article><tid>553115</tid>
<number>22</number>Withdrawal of licence from licensed pilot.-- If any person 
licensed to act as a pilot when duly charged with breach of duty as 
aforesaid, shall refuse to submit himself to trial under the 
provisions of this Act, the license of such person shall be withdrawn, 
and he shall be incapable of being again licensed to act as a pilot at 
the said Presidency. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>


</article>



<article><tid>1151522</tid>
<number>23</number>Act applicable to persons in pilot service and to licensed 
pilots.-- The provisions of this Act shall extend to <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> all persons 
employed in the Hooghly Pilot Service and borne on the rolls of the 
Commissioners for the Port of Calcutta], whether such persons receive 
fixed salaries, or are remunerated by a portion of the pilotage 
charged on the vessels piloted by them, or in any other manner, and to 
all persons licensed to act as pilots at the said Presidency. <footcitenum>5</footcitenum>
<pagefootnote><pagenum>71</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by the A. O. <year>1937</year>, for" G. G. in C." which had been subs. by 
Act 11 of <year>1929</year>, s. 2 for" Lieutenant Governor of Bengal".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. ibid., for" G. G. in C." which had been subs. by Act 11 of 
<year>1929</year>, s. 2, for" said Lieutenant Governor".

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1948</year>, s. 11, for" the marine authorities of 
the Government" (w. e. f. 16- 5- <year>1948</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Added by s. 11 ibid. (w. e. f. 16- 5- <year>1948</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>i. e. at Calcutta.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by Act 33 of <year>1948</year>, s. 11, for" all persons employed in the 
Pilot Service at the said Presidency and borne on the rolls of 
the Government establishment" (w. e. f. 16- 5- <year>1948</year>).


</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

</article>



 </act>