<act><tid>6749</tid>
<title>THE INTEREST- TAX ACT, <year>1974</year></title>

ACT NO. 45 OF <year>1974</year>
[ 23rd September. <year>1974</year>]

An Act to impose a special tax on interest in certain cases.

BE it enacted by Parliament in the Twenty- fifth Year of the 
Republic of India as follows:-





<article><tid>106737</tid>
<number> 1</number> Short title and extent.
<section><tid>1577968</tid>
<number>1</number>This Act may be called the  
Interest- tax Act, <year>1974</year>.

</section>

<section><tid>1935784</tid>
<number>2</number>It extends to the whole of India.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>802607</tid>
<number> 2</number> Definitions. In this Act, unless the context otherwise 
requires,-
<section><tid>1070009</tid>
<number>1</number>" assessee" means a person by whom interest- tax or any other 
sum of money is payable under this Act and includes-

<subsection><tid>1775934</tid>
<number>a</number>every person in respect of whom any proceeding under 
this Act has been taken for the assessment of his chargeable 
interest or of the amount of refund due to him or of the 
chargeable interest of any other person in respect of which 
he is assessable or of the amount of refund due to such other 
person;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1403310</tid>
<number>b</number>every person who is deemed to be an assessee in default 
under any provision of this Act;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1497578</tid>
<number>2</number>" assessment" includes reassessment;

</section>

<section><tid>432896</tid>
<number>3</number>" assessment year" means the period of twelve months 
commencing on the 1st day of April, every year;

<pagefootnote><pagenum>598</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</section>

<section><tid>345811</tid>
<number>4</number>Board" means the Central Board of Direct Taxes constituted 
under the Central Boards of Revenue Act, <year>1963</year>; (54 of <year>1963</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>1395033</tid>
<number>5</number>" chargeable interest" means the total amount of interest 
referred to in section 5, computed in the manner laid down in section 
6;

</section>

<section><tid>842643</tid>
<number>5A</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" credit institution" means,-

<subsection><tid>503226</tid>
<number>i</number>a banking company to which the Banking Regulation Act, 
<year>1949</year>, applies (including any bank or banking institution  
  referred to in section 51 of at Act <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>)

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1733306</tid>
<number>ii</number>a public financial institution as defined in section of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>383633</tid>
<number>iii</number>a State financial corporation established under section 
 3 or section 3A or an institution notified under section 46 
of the State Financial Corporations Act, <year>1951</year>; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1046303</tid>
<number>iv</number>any other financial company;

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1736118</tid>
<number>5B</number>" financial company" means a company, other than a company 
referred to in sub- clause (i), (ii) or (iii) of clause (5A), being-

<subsection><tid>834418</tid>
<number>i</number>a hire- purchase finance company, that is to say, a 
company which carries on, as its principal business, hire- 
purchase transactions or the financing of such 
transactions;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>172460</tid>
<number>ii</number>an investment company, that is to say, a company which 
carries on, as its principal business, the acquisition of 
shares, stock, bonds, debentures, debenture stock or 
securities issued by the Government or a local authority, or 
other marketable securities of a like nature;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>445688</tid>
<number>iii</number>a housing finance company, that is to say, a company 
which carries on, as its principal business, the business of 
financing of acquisition or construction of houses, including 
acquisition or development of land in connection therewith;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>508056</tid>
<number>iv</number>a loan company, that is to say, a company[ not being a 
company referred to in sub- clauses (i) to (iii)] which 
carries on, as its principal business, the business of 
providing finance, whether by making loans or advances or 
otherwise;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1021509</tid>
<number>v</number>a mutual benefit finance company, that is to say, a 
company which carries on, as its principal business, the 
business of acceptance of deposits from its members and which 
is declared by the Central Government under section 620A of 
the Companies Act, <year>1956</year>, to be a Nidhi or Mutual Benefit 
Society; <footcitenum>8</footcitenum>

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1656494</tid>
<number>vi</number>a miscellaneous finance company, that is to say, a 
company which carries on exclusively, or almost exclusively, 
two or more classes of business referred to in the preceding 
sub- clauses;]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>927994</tid>
<number>6</number>" Income- tax Act" means the Income- tax Act, <year>1961</year>; (43 of <year>1961</year>.)

</section>

<section><tid>242393</tid>
<number>7</number><footcitenum>6</footcitenum>" interest" means interest on loans and advances made in 
India and includes-

<subsection><tid>704971</tid>
<number>a</number>commitment charges on unutilised portion of any credit 
sanctioned for being availed of in India; and

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1977354</tid>
<number>b</number>discount on promissory notes and bills of exchange drawn 
or made in, India,
but does not include-


<subsubsection><tid>514638</tid>
<number>i</number>interest referred to in sub- section (1B) of the Reserve 
Bank of India Act, <year>1934</year>;

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>849079</tid>
<number>ii</number>discount on treasury bills;]

</subsubsection>

<subsubsection><tid>227582</tid>
<number>va</number><footcitenum>8</footcitenum> a residuary non- banking company[ other than a financial 
company referred to in sub- clause (i), (ii), (iii), (iv), or (v)] 
that is to say, a company which receives any deposit under any scheme 
or arrangement, by whatever name called, in one lumpsum or in 
instalments by way of contributions or subscriptions or by sale of 
units or certificates or other instruments or in any other manner; or]
--- Subject to the provisions of this Act, the chargeable interest 
any previous year of a credit institution shall be the total amount of 
interest (other than interest on loans and advances made to other  
  credit institutions) <footcitenum>8</footcitenum> or to any cooperative society engaged in 
carrying on the business of banking]

Provided that any interest in relation to categories of had or 
doubtful debts referred to in section 43D of the Income- tax Act 
shall be deemed to accrue or arise to the credit institution in the 
previous year in which it is credited by the credit institution to its 
profit and loss account for that year or, as the case may be, in which 
it is actually received by the credit institution, whichever is 
earlier.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>6xxx</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


</subsubsection>

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>190861</tid>
<number>8</number>" Prescribed" means prescribed by rules made under this Act;

</section>

<section><tid>1013754</tid>
<number>10</number>all other words and expressions used herein but not defined 
and defined in the Income- tax Act shall have the meanings respec- 
tively assigned to them in that Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1645650</tid>
<number> 3</number> Tax authorities. <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1816402</tid>
<number>1</number>The income- tax authorities specified  
in section 116 of the income- tax Act shall be the interest- tax 
authorities for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1237754</tid>
<number>1A</number>Every such authority shall exercise the powers and perform 
the functions of an interest- tax authority under this Act in respect 
of any person within his jurisdiction.

</section>

<section><tid>947005</tid>
<number>1B</number>The jurisdiction of an interest- tax authority under this Act 
shall be the same as he has under the Income- tax Act by virtue of 
orders or directions issued under section 120 of that Act (including  
  orders or directions assigning the concurrent jurisdiction) or under 
any other provision of that Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1979038</tid>
<number>1C</number>The interest- tax authority having jurisdiction in relation 
to a credit institution which has no income assessable to income- tax 
under the Income- tax Act shall be the interest- tax authority having 
jurisdiction in respect of the area in which that institution carries 
on its business or has its principal place of business.

</section>

<section><tid>1952907</tid>
<number>1D</number>Section 118 of the Income- tax Act and any notification 
issued thereunder shall apply- in relation to the control of interest- 
tax authorities as they apply in relation to the control of the cor- 
responding income- tax authorities, except to the extent to which the 
Board may, by notification in the Official Gazette, otherwise direct 
in respect of any interest- tax authority-:]

</section>

<section><tid>1385019</tid>
<number>2</number>All officers and persons employed in the execution of this- 
Act shall observe and follow the orders, instructions and directions 
of the Board:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>599</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted and Ins. by Act 66 of <year>1976</year>, s. 30 (w. e. f. 1- 4- <year>1977</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V. (w. e. f. 10- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, s. 43 (retrospectively).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. and Ins. ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 9- <year>1980</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Ins. by Act 14 of <year>1982</year>, s. 40 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1983</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Ins., subs., and omitted by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 91 (w. e. f. 1- 10-  
  <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by s. 92, ibid (w. e. f. 1. 10. <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Omitted and ins. by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, s. 103 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1993</year>)









</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided that no such orders, instructions or directions shall be 
issued-


<subsection><tid>1589539</tid>
<number>a</number>so as to require any tax authority to make a Particular 
assessment or to dispose of a particular case in a particular 
manner; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>51327</tid>
<number>b</number>so as to interfere with the discretion of the 
[ Commissioner (Appeals)] in the exercise of his appellate 
functions.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1643399</tid>
<number>3</number>Every Income- tax Officer[ or Assistant Commissioner] 9 
employed in the execution of this Act shall observe and follow the 
orders, instructions and directions issued for his guidance by the 
[ Director] 9 or by the Commissioner or by the[ Additional Commissioner 
of Income- tax or the Deputy Commissioner] 9 within whose 
jurisdiction he performs his functions.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1350984</tid>
<number> 4</number> Charge of tax.[
<section><tid>1494924</tid>
<number>1</number>] Subject to the provisions of this Act,  
there shall be charged on every scheduled bank for every assessment 
year commencing on or after the 1st day of April, <year>1975</year>, a tax (in this  
  Act referred to as interest- tax) in respect of its chargeable interest 
of the previous year at the rate of seven per cent. of such chargeable 
interest:

</section>

<section><tid>842881</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1) but 
subject to the other provisions of this Act, there shall be charged 
on every credit institution for every assessment year commencing on 
and from 1st day of April, <year>1992</year>, interest- tax in respect of its 
chargeable interest of the previous year at the rate of three per 
cent of such chargeable interest.]
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Provided that the rate at which interest- tax shall be charged 
in respect of any chargeable interest accruing or arising after the 
 31st day of March, <year>1983</year>, shall be three and a half per cent. of such 
chargeable interest.]




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1262851</tid>
<number> 6</number> Computation of chargeable interest.
<section><tid>394806</tid>
<number>1</number>Subject to the  
provisions of sub- section (2), in computing the chargeable interest of 
a previous year, there shall be allowed from the total amount of 
interest (other than interest on loans and advances made to <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> credit  
  institutions]) accruing or arising to the assessee in the previous 
year, a deduction in respect of the amount of interest which is 
established to have become a bad debt during the previous year:
Provided that such interest has been taken into, account in 
computing the chargeable interest of the assessee of an earlier 
previous year and the amount has been written off as irrecoverable in 
the accounts of the assessee for the previous year during which it is 
established to have become a bad debt.

Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that in computing the chargeable interest of a previous year, no 
deduction, other than the deduction specified in this sub- section, 
shall be allowed from the total amount of interest accruing or arising 
to the assesses.


</section>

<section><tid>305464</tid>
<number>2</number>In computing the chargeable interest of a previous year, the 
amount of interest which accrues or arises to the assessee <footcitenum>7</footcitenum>' during 
the period commencing on the 1st day of April, <year>1985</year> and ending with 
the 30th day of September, <year>1991</year>"]. <footcitenum>7</footcitenum> before the 1st day of 
August, <year>1974</year> or during the period commencing on the 1st day of March, 
 <year>1978</year> and ending with the 30th day of June, <year>1980</year>.] shall not be 
taken into account.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>600</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>999999</number> Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 10. 7. <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 19 of <year>1978</year>, s. 33 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1979</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 44 of <year>1980</year>, s. 43 (w. e. f. 1. 9. <year>1980</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. by Act 11 of <year>1983</year>, s. 43 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1980</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Ins. by Act 32 of <year>1985</year>, s. 41 (w. e. f. 1. 4. <year>1985</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Remembered and ins. by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 93 (w. e. f.  
  1. 10. <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. by s. 94, ibid., (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>7</number>Subs. by s. 95, ibid. (w. e. f. 1. 10. <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>8</number>Ins. by Act 18 of <year>1992</year>, s. 104 (w. e. f. 1. 10. <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>9</number>Ins. and subs. by Act 32 of <year>1994</year>, s. 56 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1994</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1605266</tid>
<number> 7</number> Return of chargeable interest.[" <footcitenum>1</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1093764</tid>
<number>1</number>In the case of every  
credit institution, its principal officer, or where in the case of a 
non- resident credit institution any person has been treated as its 
agent under section 163 of the Income- tax Act, such person, shall 
furnish a return of the chargeable interest of the credit institution 
of the previous year in the prescribed form and verified in the 
prescribed manner and setting forth such other particulars as may be 
prescribed, before the 31st day of December of the assessment year.

</section>

<section><tid>1358513</tid>
<number>2</number>Without prejudice to the provisions of sub- section (1), the 
Assessing Officer may, before the end of the relevant assessment year, 
serve a notice upon the principal officer of any credit institution, 
or where in the case of a non- resident credit institution any person 
has been treated as its agent under section 163 of the Income- tax Act, 
upon such person, requiring him to furnish within thirty days from the 
date of service of the notice a return of the chargeable interest of 
the credit institution of the previous year in the prescribed form and 
verified in the prescribed manner and setting forth such other 
particulars as may be prescribed.]

</section>

<section><tid>71520</tid>
<number>3</number>Any assessee who has not furnished a return within the time 
allowed under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2), or having furnished 
a return under sub- section (1) or sub- section (2) discovers any 
omission or wrong statement therein, may furnish a return or a revised 
return, as the case may be, at any time <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> before the expiry of one 
year from the end of the relevant assessment year or before the 
completion of the assessment, whichever is earlier]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1754687</tid>
<number> 8</number> Assessment.
<section><tid>1087381</tid>
<number>1</number>For the purposes of making an assessment  
under this Act, the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing officer] may serve on any person who 
has furnished a return under section 7 or upon whom a notice has been 
served under sub- section (2) of section 7 (whether a return has been  
  furnished or not) a notice requiring him on a date therein to be 
specified, to produce or cause to be produced such accounts or 
documents or evidence as the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing officer] <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing officer] 
may require for the purposes of this Act and may, from time to time, 
serve further notices requiring the production of such further 
accounts or documents or other evidence as he may require.

</section>

<section><tid>799188</tid>
<number>2</number>The <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing officer], after considering such accounts, 
documents or evidence, if any, as he has obtained under sub- section 
 (1) and after taking into account any relevant material which he has 
gathered, shall, by an order in writing assess the chargeable interest 
and the amount of the interest- tax payable on the basis of such 
assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>1598838</tid>
<number>3</number><footcitenum>2</footcitenum> If any person-

<subsection><tid>304483</tid>
<number>a</number>fails to make a return as required under sub- section 
 (1) of section 7 and has not made a return or a revised 
return under sub- section (3) of that section, or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>989298</tid>
<number>b</number>falls to comply with all the terms of notice under sub- 
section (2) of that section,
the Assessing Officer shall, after taking into account all the 
relevant material which he has gathered and after giving the assessee 
an opportunity of being heard, make the assessment of the total 
chargeable interest to the best of his judgment and determine the sum 
payable by the assessee on the basis of such assessment:

Provided that such opportunity shall be given by the Assessing 
Officer by serving a notice calling upon the assessee to show cause, 
on a date and time to be specified in the notice, why the assessment 
should not be completed to the best of his judgment:

Provided further that it shall not be necessary to give such 
opportunity in a case where a notice under sub- section (1) has been 
issued prior to the making of an assessment under this section.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>601</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 96 (w. e. f. 1. 10. <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. and ins. by S. 97, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>





</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1667530</tid>
<number> 9</number> <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Self- assessment.
<section><tid>1789619</tid>
<number>1</number>Where interest- tax is payable on the  
basis of any return required to be furnished under section 7 or 
section 10, after taking into account the amount of interest- tax, if 
any, already paid under any provision of this Act, the assessee shall 
be liable to pay such interest- tax, together with interest payable 
under any provision of this Act for any delay in furnishing the return 
or any default or delay in payment of advance interest- tax, before 
furnishing the return and the return shall be accompanied by proof of 
payment of such interest- tax and interest.
Explanation.- Where the amount paid by the assessee under' this 
sub- section falls short of the aggregate of the interest- tax and 
interest as aforesaid, the amount so paid shall first be adjusted 
towards the interest payable as aforesaid and the balance, it any, 
shall be adjusted towards the interest- tax payable.


</section>

<section><tid>1448149</tid>
<number>2</number>After the assessment under section 8 has been made, any 
amount paid under sub- section (1) shall be deemed to have been paid 
towards such assessment.

</section>

<section><tid>999084</tid>
<number>3</number>If any assessee fails to pay the whole or any part of 
interest- tax or interest or both in accordance with the provisions of 
subsection (1), he shall, without- prejudice to any other consequences 
which he may incur, be deemed to be an assessee in default in respect 
of the interest- tax or interest or both remaining unpaid, and all the 
provisions of this Act shall apply accordingly.]



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>552413</tid>
<number> 10</number> Interest escaping assessment. If-
<section><tid>177473</tid>
<number>a</number>the[ Assessing officer] 2 has reason to believe that by 
reason of the omission or failure on the part of the assessee 
to make a return under section 7 for any assessment year or 
to disclose fully and truly all material facts necessary for 
his assessment for any assessment year, chargeable interest 
for that year has escaped assessment or has been under- 
assessed or has been made the subject of. excessive relief 
under this Act, or

</section>

<section><tid>91972</tid>
<number>b</number>notwithstanding that there has been no omission or 
failure as mentioned in clause (a) on the part of the 
assessee, the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing officer] has, in consequence of 
information in his possession, reason to believe that 
chargeable interest assessable for any assessment year has 
escaped assessment or has been under- assessed or has been the 
subject of excessive relief under this Act,
he may, in cases falling under clause (a), at any time, and in cases 
falling under clause (b), at any time within four years of the end of 
that assessment year, serve on the assessee a notice containing all or 
any of the requirements which may be included in a notice under 
section 7, and may proceed to assess or reassess the amount chargeable 
to interest- tax, and the provisions of this Act shall, so far as may 
be, apply, as if the notice were a notice issued under that section.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>96387</tid>
<number> 10A</number> <footcitenum>3</footcitenum> Time limit for completion of assessments and 
reassessments.
<section><tid>376129</tid>
<number>1</number>No order of assessment shall be made under section  
 8 any time after the expiry of two years from the end of the 
assessment year in which the interest was first assessable.

</section>

<section><tid>1888290</tid>
<number>2</number>No order of assessment or reassessment shall be made under 
section 10 after the expiry of two years from the end of the 
financial year in which the notice under that section was served.

</section>

<section><tid>1285553</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- sections (1) and 
 (2), an order of fresh assessment in pursuance of an order passed 
under section 15, section 16, section 19 or section 20, setting aside 
or cancelling an' assessment, may be made at any time before the 
expiry of two' years from the end of the financial year in which the 
order under section 15 or section 16 is received by the Commissioner 
or, as the case may be, the order under section 19 or section 20 is 
passed by the Commissioner.

</section>

<section><tid>1178927</tid>
<number>4</number>The provisions of sub- sections (1) and (2) shall not apply 
to the assessment or reassessment made in consequence of, or to give 
effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order under 
section 15 or section 16 or section 19 or section 20 of this Act or 
section 256 or section 260 of the Income- tax Act as applicable to this 
Act by virtue of section 21 of this Act or in an order of any court in 
it proceeding otherwise than by way of appeal or reference under this 
Act and such assessment or reassessment may, subject to the provisions 
of sub- section (3), be completed at any time.
Explanation 1- In computing the period of limitation for the 
purposes of this section-


<subsection><tid>1733867</tid>
<number>i</number>the time taken in reopening the whole or any part of 
the proceeding; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1042560</tid>
<number>ii</number>the period during which the assessment proceeding is 
stayed by an order or injunction of any court,
shall be excluded.

Explanation 2.--- Where, by an order referred to in sub- section 
 (4), any interest is excluded from the chargeable interest for an 
assessment year in respect of an assessee, then, an assessment of such 
interest for another assessment year shall, for the purposes of 
section 10 and this section, be deemed to be one made in consequence 
of, or to give effect to, any finding or direction contained in the 
said order.]




</subsection>

</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1098197</tid>
<number> 11</number> Advance payment of interest- tax.
<section><tid>1209350</tid>
<number>1</number>Interest- tax shall  
be payable in advance during the-- year in respect of the 
chargeable interest for the assessment year immediately following that 
financial year in accordance---- the provision of this section.

</section>

<section><tid>962866</tid>
<number>2</number>Interest- tax shall be payable in advance in three 
instalments during each financial year, the due date of, and the 
amount payable in, each such instalment being as specified in the 
following Table:
TABLE

Due date of instalment Amount payable

On or before the 15th September Not less than twenty per cent. 
of such interest- tax payable 
in advance.

On or before the 15th December Not less than fifty per cent. 
of such interest- tax payable 
in advance, as reduced by 
the amount, if any, paid in 
the earlier instalment.

On or before the 15th March The whole amount of such interest- 
tax payable in advance as reduced 
by the amount or amount, if any, 
paid in the earlier instalment 
or instalments


<pagefootnote><pagenum>602</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 98 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by s. 99, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 100, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 101, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>748613</tid>
<number>14</number>Opportunity of being heard. No order imposing a penalty 
under section 12 or section 13 shall be made unless the assessee has 
been heard, or has been given a reasonable opportunity of being heard.


</article>



<article><tid>887099</tid>
<number> 15</number> Appeals to the Commissioner Appeals.
<section><tid>1692588</tid>
<number>1</number>Any person  
objecting to the amount of interest- tax for which he is assessed by 
the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing Officer] or denying his liability to be assessed 
under this Act, or objecting to any penalty or fine imposed by the 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing Officer], or to the amount allowed by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing 
Officer] refusal by the <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> Assessing Officer] to grant relief or to an 
order of rectification having the effect of enhancing the assessment 
or reducing the refund, or to an order refusing to allow the claim 
made by the assessed for a rectification under section 17, may appeal 
to the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)].

</section>

<section><tid>177251</tid>
<number>2</number>Every appeal shall be in the prescribed form and shall be 
verified in the prescribed manner.

</section>

<section><tid>1480602</tid>
<number>3</number>An appeal shall be presented within thirty days of the 
following date, that is to say,-

<subsection><tid>1895868</tid>
<number>a</number>where the appeal relates to assessment or penalty or 
fine, the date of service of the notice of demand relating to 
the assessment or penalty or fine or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>733817</tid>
<number>b</number>in any other case, the date on which the intimation of 
the order sought to be appealed against is served:

<pagefootnote><pagenum>604</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 10- 7- <year>1987</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 102 (w. e. f. 10- 7- <year>1987</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided that the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] may admit an appeal after 
the expiration of the said period if he is satisfied that the 
appellant had sufficient cause for not presenting it within that 
period.


</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>812957</tid>
<number>4</number>The <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] shall hear and determine the 
appeal and, subject to the provisions of this Act, pass such orders as 
he thinks fit and such orders may include an order enhancing the 
assessment or penalty:
Provided that an order enhancing the assessment or penalty shall 
not be made unless the person affected thereby has been given a 
reasonable opportunity of showing cause against such enhancement.


</section>

<section><tid>1838691</tid>
<number>5</number>The procedure to be adopted in the hearing and determination 
of the appeals shall, with any necessary modification, be in 
accordance with the procedure applicable in relation to income- tax.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>211156</tid>
<number> 16</number> Appeals to Appellate Tribunal.
<section><tid>1008578</tid>
<number>1</number>Any assessee aggrieved by  
an order passed by a Commission under section 19, or an order passed 
by <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> a Commissioner (Appeals)] under any provision of this Act, may 
appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against such order.

</section>

<section><tid>1943854</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner may, if he objects to any order passed by 
the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] under any provision of this Act, direct 
the[ Assessing Officer] 4 to appeal to the Appellate Tribunal against 
the order.

</section>

<section><tid>1253339</tid>
<number>3</number>Every appeal under subsection (1) or sub- section (2) shall 
be filed within sixty days of the date on which the order sought to be 
appealed against is communicated to the assessee or to the 
Commissioner, as the case may be.

</section>

<section><tid>622015</tid>
<number>4</number>The[ Assessing Officer] or the assessee, as the case may be, 
on receipt of notice that an appeal against the order of the 
 <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] has been preferred under sub- section (1) or 
sub- section (2) by the other party may, notwithstanding that he may 
not have appealed against such order or any part thereof, within 
thirty days of the receipt of the notice, file a memorandum of cross- 
objections, verified in the prescribed manner, against any part of the 
order of the <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> Commissioner (Appeals)] and such memorandum shall be 
disposed of by the Appellate Tribunal as if it were an appeal 
presented within the time specified in sub- section (3).

</section>

<section><tid>1951168</tid>
<number>5</number>The Appellate Tribunal may admit an appeal or permit the 
filing of a memorandum of cross- objections after the expiry of the 
relevant period referred to in sub- section (3) or sub- section (4), if 
it is satisfied that there was sufficient cause for not presenting it 
within that period.

</section>

<section><tid>852649</tid>
<number>6</number>An appeal to the Appellate Tribunal shall be in the 
prescribed form and shall be verified in the prescribed manner and, 
shall, except in the case of an appeal referred to in sub- section (2) 
or a memorandum of cross- objections referred to in sub- section (4), be 
accompanied by a fee of one hundred and twenty five[ two hundred 
rupees] 2

</section>

<section><tid>823460</tid>
<number>7</number>Subject to the provisions of this Act, in hearing and making 
an order on any appeal under this section, the Appellate Tribunal 
shall exercise the same powers and follow the same procedure as it 
exercises and follows in hearing and making an order on any appeal 
under the Income- tax Act.

<pagefootnote><pagenum>605</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. and ins. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 10- 7-  
  <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 16 of <year>1981</year>, s. 44 (w. e. f. 1- 6- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Omitted by Act 49 or <year>1991</year>, s. 103 (w. e. f. 1. 10. <year>1981</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by s. 104, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).




</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>917744</tid>
<number> 17</number> Rectification of mistakes.
<section><tid>1936962</tid>
<number>1</number>With a view to rectifying any  
mistake apparent from the record, the Commissioner, the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Assessing 
Officer] the[ Commissioner (Appeals)] and the Appellate Tribunal may, 
of his, or its, own motion or on an application by the assessee in 
this behalf, amend any order passed by him or it in any proceeding 
under this Act <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> within four years from the end of the financial year 
in which such order was passed]

</section>

<section><tid>1099819</tid>
<number>2</number>An amendment which has the effect of enhancing the 
assessment or reducing a refund or otherwise increasing the liability 
of the assessee shall not be made under this section unless the 
authority concerned has given notice to the assessee of its intention 
so to do and has allowed the assessee a reasonable opportunity of 
being heard.

</section>

<section><tid>517158</tid>
<number>3</number>Where an amendment is made under this section, the order 
shall be passed in writing by the authority concerned.

</section>

<section><tid>1899180</tid>
<number>4</number>Subject to the other provisions of this Act, where any such 
amendment has the effect of reducing the assessment, the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Assessing 
Officer] shall make any refund which may be due to such assessee.

</section>

<section><tid>535106</tid>
<number>5</number>Where any such amendment has the effect of enhancing the 
assessment or reducing the refund already made, the <footcitenum>4</footcitenum> Assessing 
Officer] shall serve on the assessee a notice of demand in the 
prescribed form specifying the sum payable.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1386306</tid>
<number>18</number><footcitenum>5</footcitenum> Interest- tax deductible in computing total income under 
the Income- tax Act. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- 
tax Act, in computing the income of a credit institution chargeable to 
income- tax under the head" Profits and gains of business or 
profession" or under the head" Income from other sources", the 
interest- tax payable by the credit institution for any assessment year 
shall be deductible from the income, under the respective heads, of 
the credit institution assessable for that assessment year.]


</article>



<article><tid>835950</tid>
<number> 19</number> Revision of order prejudicial to revenue.
<section><tid>1901006</tid>
<number>1</number>The  
Commissioner may call for and examine the record of any proceeding 
under this Act, and if he considers that any order passed therein by 
the <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Assessing Officer] is erroneous in so far as it is prejudicial 
to the interests of the revenue, he may, after giving the assessee an 
opportunity of being heard and after making or causing to be made such 
enquiry as he deems necessary, pass such order thereon as the 
circumstances of the case justify, including an order enhancing or 
modifying the assessment, or cancelling the assessment and directing a 
fresh assessment.
<footcitenum>6</footcitenum> Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that, for the purposes of this sub- section,-


<subsection><tid>258288</tid>
<number>a</number>" record" shall include and shall be deemed always to 
have included all records relating to any proceeding under 
this Act available at the time of examination by the 
Commissioner;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>863219</tid>
<number>b</number>where any order referred to in this sub- section is the 
subject matter of any appeal, the power of the Commissioner 
under this subsection shall extend to all such matters as had 
not been considered and decided in such appeal.]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1014894</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> No order shall be made under sub- section (1) after the 
expiry of two years from the end of the financial year in which the 
order sought to be revised was passed."]

</section>

<section><tid>775428</tid>
<number>3</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (2), an 
order in revision under this section may be passed at any time in the 
case of an order which has been passed in consequence of, or to give 
effect to, any finding or direction contained in an order of the 
Appellate Tribunal, the High Court or the Supreme Court.
Explanation.- In computing the period of limitation for the 
purposes of sub- section (2) <footcitenum>6</footcitenum> the time taken in giving an opportunity 
to the assessee to be re- heard under the priviso to section 129 of the 
Income- tax Act, as applicable to this Act by virtue of section 21 of 
this Act, and"] any period during which any proceeding under this 
section is stayed by an order or injunction of any court shall be 
excluded,


<pagefootnote><pagenum>606</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f. 10. 7. <year>1978</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 67 of <year>1984</year>, s. 82 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Ins. and Subs. by S. 83, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1984</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>4</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 105 (w. e. f. 1. 10. <year>1991</year>)

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>5</number>Subs. by S. 106, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>6</number>Subs. and ins. by S. 107, ibid (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).







</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1159003</tid>
<number> 20</number> Revision of Order by Commissioner.
<section><tid>1425951</tid>
<number>1</number>The Commissioner may,  
either of his own motion or on an application by the assessee for 
revision, call for the record of any proceeding under this Act which 
has been taken by an Income- tax Officer <footcitenum>1</footcitenum> subordinate to him and 
may, make such enquiry or cause such enquiry to be made and, subject 
to the provisions of this Act, may pass such order thereon, not being 
an order prejudicial to the assessee, as he thinks fit.

</section>

<section><tid>947855</tid>
<number>2</number>The Commissioner shall not of his own motion revise any. 
order under this section if the order has been made more than one year 
previously.

</section>

<section><tid>837606</tid>
<number>3</number>In the case of an application for revision under this 
' section by the assessee, the application shall be made within one 
year from the date on which the order in question was communicated to 
him or the date on which he otherwise came to know of it, whichever is 
earlier:
Provided that the Commissioner may, if he is satisfied that the 
assessee was prevented by sufficient cause from making the application 
within that period, admit an application made after the expiry, of 
that period.


</section>

<section><tid>81686</tid>
<number>4</number>The Commissioner shall not revise any order under this 
section in the following cases-

<subsection><tid>1831452</tid>
<number>a</number><footcitenum>1</footcitenum> where an appeal against the order lies[ to the 
Commissioner (Appeals) or to the Appellate Tribunal] but has 
not been made and the time within which such appeal may be 
made has not expired, or the assessee has not waived his 
right of appeal; or

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>69914</tid>
<number>b</number>where the order has been made the subject of an appeal 
 <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> to the Commissioner (Appeals) or to the Appellate Tribunal]

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1779423</tid>
<number>5</number>Every application by an assessee for revision under this 
section shall be accompanied by a fee of twenty- five rupees.
Explanation 1.- An order by the Commissioner declining to 
interfere shall, for the purposes of this section, be deemed not to be 
an order prejudicial to the assessee.


<pagefootnote><pagenum>1xxxx</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>




</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1243590</tid>
<number>21</number>Application of provisions of Income- tax Act. The provisions 
of the following sections and Schedule of the Income- tax Act and the 
Income- tax (Certificate Proceedings) Rules, <year>1962</year> as in force from time 
to time, shall apply with necessary modifications as if the said 
provisions and the rules referred to interest- tax instead of to 
income- tax;--
<footcitenum>3</footcitenum> 2 (44), 129, 131, 132, 132A, 132B, 133 to 136 (both  
  inclusive), 138, 140, 145, 156, 160, 161, 162, 163, 166, 167, 
170, 173, 175 176, 178, 179, 220 to 227 (both inclusive), 
228A, 229, 232, 237 to 245 (both inclusive), 254 to 262 (both  
  inclusive), 265, 266, 268, 269, 281, 281B, 282, 284, 287, 
288, 288A, 288B, 289 to 293 (both inclusive), the Second 
Schedule and the Third Schedule.]


<pagefootnote><pagenum>607</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Omitted and Subs. by Act 29 of <year>1977</year>, s. 39 and Sch. V (w. e. f.  
  10- 7- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 108 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1978</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Subs. by s. 109, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).






</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>

Provided that references in the said provisions and the rules 
to the" assessee" shall be construed as references to an, 
assessee as defined in this Act.



</article>



<article><tid>759086</tid>
<number> 22</number> Income- tax papers to be available for the purposes of this 
Act.
<section><tid>1395315</tid>
<number>1</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in the Income- tax Act, all  
information contained in any statement or return made or furnished 
under the provisions of that Act or obtained or collected for the 
purposes of that Act may be used for the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>1864373</tid>
<number>2</number>All information contained in any statement or return made or 
furnished under the provisions of this Act or obtained or collected 
for the purposes of this Act may be used for the purposes of the 
Income- tax Act.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>750774</tid>
<number>23</number>Failure comply with notices. If any person fails, 
without reasonable cause, to produce or cause to be produced, any 
accounts or documents required to be produced tinder section 8, he 
shall pay by way of penalty, a sum which shall not be less than one 
thousand rupees, but which may extend to twenty- five thousand rupees, 
for each such failure,


</article>



<article><tid>679592</tid>
<number>24</number>False statements. If a person makes a statement in any 
verification under this Act or any rule made thereunder, or delivers 
an account or statement which is false, and which he either knows or 
believes to be false or does not believe to be true, he shall be 
punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which shall not be 
less than three months but which may extend Lo sever. years and with 
fine.


</article>



<article><tid>1845238</tid>
<number> 25</number> Wilful attempt to evade tax, etc. If a person wilfully 
attempts in any manner whatsoever to evade any interest- tax, penalty 
or interest chargeable or impassable, under this Act, he shall, 
without prejudice to any penalty that may be impassable on him under 
any other provision of this Act, be punishable with' rigorous 
imprisonment for a term which shall not be less than three months but 
which may extend to seven years and with fine.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section, a wilful attempt 
to evade any' interest- tax, penalty or interest chargeable or 
impassable under this Act or the payment thereof shall include a case 
where any person-

<section><tid>1030449</tid>
<number>i</number>has in his possession or control any books of account 
or other documents (being books of account or other documents  
  relevant to any proceeding under this Act) containing a false 
entry or statement; or

</section>

<section><tid>1647195</tid>
<number>ii</number>makes or causes to be made any false entry or statement 
in such books of account or other documents; or

</section>

<section><tid>1818541</tid>
<number>iii</number>wilfully omits or causes to be omitted any relevant 
entry or statement in such books of account or other 
documents; or

</section>

<section><tid>310753</tid>
<number>iv</number>causes any other circumstances to exist which will have 
the effect of enabling such per- son to evade any interest- 
tax, penalty or interest chargeable or impassable under this 
Act or the payment thereof.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1285046</tid>
<number>26</number>Abetment of false returns, etc. If a person abets or 
induces in any manner another person to make and deliver any account 
or a statement or declaration relating to any chargeable interest 
which is false and which he either knows or believes to be false or 
does not believe to be true or to commit an offence under section 25, 
he shall be punishable with rigorous imprisonment for a term which 
shall not be less than three months but which may extend to seven 
years and with fine.
</article>



<article><tid>381475</tid>
<number> 26A</number> Offences by credit institutions.
<section><tid>479007</tid>
<number>1</number>Where an offence under  
this Act has been committed by a credit institution, every person who, 
at the time the offence was committed, was in charge of, and was 
responsible to, the credit institution or the conduct of the business 
of the credit institution as well as the credit institution shall be 
deemed to be guilty of the offence and shall be liable to be proceeded 
against and punished accordingly:
Provided that nothing contained in this sub- section shall render 
any such person liable to any punishment if he proves that the offence 
was committed without his knowledge or that he had exercised all due 
diligence to prevent the commission of such offence.


</section>

<section><tid>334661</tid>
<number>2</number>Notwithstanding anything contained in sub- section (1), 
------ an offence under this Act has been committed by a credit insti- 
tution and it is proved that the offence has been committed with the 
------ or connivance of, or is attributable to any neglect on the part 
---- any director, manager, secretary or other officer of the credit 
institution, such director, manager, secretary or other officer shall 
also be deemed to be guilty of that offence and shall be liable to be 
proceeded against and punished accordingly.
Explanation.- For the purposes of this section," director", in 
relation to a co- operative society, means any member controlling the 
affairs thereof.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>144822</tid>
<number> 26B</number> Institution of proceedings and composition of offences.
<section><tid>721356</tid>
<number>1</number> 
A person shall not be proceeded against for any offence under section 
 24 or section 25 or section 26 or for any offence under the Indian 
Penal Code, except with the previous sanction of the Commissioner or 
Commissioner (Appeals):
Provided that the Chief Commissioner or, as the case may be, 
Director General may issue such instructions or directions to the 
aforesaid interest- tax authorities as he may deem fit for institution 
of proceedings under this sub- section.


</section>

<section><tid>1983204</tid>
<number>2</number>Any offence under the sections referred to in sub- section 
 (1) may, either before or after the institution of proceedings, be 
compounded by the Chief Commissioner or Director General.
Explanation.- For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared 
that the power of the Board to issue orders, instructions or direc- 
tions under this Act shall include the power to issue instructions or 
directions (including instructions or directions to obtain the pre-  
  vious approval of the Board) to other interest- tax authorities for the 
proper composition of offences under this section.


</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1661498</tid>
<number>26C</number>Power of credit institutions to vary certain agreements. 
Notwithstanding anything contained in any agreement under which any 
term loan has been sanctioned by the credit institution before the 1st 
day of October, <year>1991</year>, it shall be lawful for the credit institution to 
vary the agreement, so as to increase the rate of interest stipulated 
therein to the extent to which such institution is liable to pay the 
interest- tax under this Act in relation to the amount of interest on 
the term loan which is due to the credit institution.
Explanation- For the purposes of this section," term loan" means 
a loan which is not repayable on demand-]



</article>



<article><tid>1349684</tid>
<number> 27</number> Power to make rules.
<section><tid>922788</tid>
<number>1</number>The Board my, subject to the  
control of the Central Government, by notification in the official 
Gazette, make rules for carrying out the purposes of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>187409</tid>
<number>2</number>In particular, and without prejudice to the generality of 
the foregoing power, such rules may provide for all or any of the 
following matters, namely:-

<subsection><tid>536468</tid>
<number>a</number>the form in which returns under section 7 may be 
furnished and the manner in which they may be Verified;

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1813770</tid>
<number>b</number>the form in which appeals under section 15 or section 
 16 may be filed and the manner in which they may be verified

</subsection>

<subsection><tid>303394</tid>
<number>c</number>the procedure to be followed on applications for 
rectification of mistakes and applications for refunds-,

<pagefootnote><pagenum>608</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Subs. by Act 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 110 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).





</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</subsection>

<subsection><tid>1080383</tid>
<number>d</number>any other matter which by this Act is to be, or may be, 
prescribed.

</subsection>

</section>

<section><tid>1756708</tid>
<number>3</number>The power to make rules conferred by this section shall on 
the first occasion of the exercise thereof include the power to give 
retrospective effect to the rules or any of them from a date not 
earlier than the date of commencement of this Act.

</section>

<section><tid>705838</tid>
<number>4</number>The Central Government shall cause every rule made under 
this section to be laid, as soon as may be, after it is made before 
each House of Parliament while it is in session for a total period of 
thirty days which may be comprised in one session or in two or more 
successive sessions, and if, before the expiry of the session 
immediately following the session or the successive sessions 
aforesaid, both Houses agree In making any modification in the rule or 
both Houses agree that the rule should not be made, the rule shall 
thereafter have effect only in such modified form or be of no effect, 
as the case may be; so, however, that any such modification or 
annulment shall be without prejudice to the validity of anything 
previously done under that rule.



</section>

</article>



<article><tid>1014738</tid>
<number>28</number>Power to exempt. Where the Central Government is of the 
opinion that it is necessary or expedient so to do either in the 
public interest or having regard to the peculiar circumstances of the 
case, it may, by notification, and subject to conditions, if any, as 
may be specified in the notification, exempt <footcitenum>2</footcitenum> any credit institution 
or any class of credit institutions or any interest on any category of 
loans advances] levy of interest- tax:
Provided that no such exemption shall be made except on the 
recommendation of the Reserve Bank of India.



</article>



<article><tid>1962780</tid>
<number> 29</number> Power to remove difficulty. <footcitenum>3</footcitenum>
<section><tid>1672683</tid>
<number>1</number>] If any difficulty  
arises in giving effect to the provisions of this Act, Central 
Government may, by order, not inconsistent with the provisions of this 
Act, remove the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry of a 
period of two years from the commencement of this Act.


</section>

<section><tid>765409</tid>
<number>2</number><footcitenum>3</footcitenum> If any difficulty arises in giving effect to the 
provisions of this Act, as amended by the Finance (No. 2) Act, <year>1991</year>, 
the Central Government may, by order, do anything not inconsistent 
with such provisions for the purpose of removing the difficulty:
Provided that no such order shall be made after the expiry Of two 
years from the 1st day of October, <year>1991</year>.


</section>

<section><tid>105124</tid>
<number>3</number>Every order made under sub- section (2) shall be laid before 
each House of Parliament.]

<pagefootnote><pagenum>1xxx</pagenum>
</pagefootnote>


<pagefootnote><pagenum>999999</pagenum>
<pagenote><number>1</number>Repealed by Act 38 of <year>1978</year>, s. 2 and Sch. I.

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>2</number>Subs. by ACt 49 of <year>1991</year>, s. 111 (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).

</pagenote> 

<pagenote><number>3</number>Remembered and ins. by s. 112, ibid. (w. e. f. 1- 10- <year>1991</year>).



</pagenote> 
</pagefootnote>


</section>

</article>



 </act>